<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">Beyond the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital
               Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Roopika <dhq:family>Risam</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Salem State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rrisam@salemstate.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Roopika Risam is an assistant professor of English and Secondary English
                     Education at Salem State University. She researches intersections between
                     postcolonial, African American, and US ethnic studies and the role of digital
                     humanities in mediating between them. Her work has recently appeared in <title
                        rend="italic">First Monday</title> and is forthcoming in <title
                        rend="italic">Left History</title>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000208</idno>
            <idno type="volume">009</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2015-09-02">2 September 2015</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>digital humanities</item>
                  <item>intersectionality</item>
                  <item>feminism</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="EH" when="2015-04-23">Encoded article</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article examines the relationship between intersectionality and the digital
               humanities. Intersectionality offers a critical approach to debates between theory
               and method in the field, transcending simplistic hack vs. yack binaries. This article
               situates debates over difference in the digital humanities within the context of the
               culture wars within the U.S. academy during the 1980s and 1990s, locating the stakes
               for diversity in the digital humanities. It surveys digital humanities projects,
               outlining the need for alternate histories of the digital humanities told through
               intersectional lenses. Finally, the article proposes ways of looking forward towards
               the deeper intersectional analysis needed to expand intellectual diversity in the
               field and move difference beyond the margins of the digital humanities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Digital humanities scholarship and intersectionality</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>While digital humanities has grown, so too has the number of voices making the case
               for attention to race, class, gender, sexuality, ability, nationality, and other
               categories of identity in the field. Increasing numbers of panels at the annual
               meetings of Digital Humanities; Modern Language Association; American Studies
               Association; American Historical Association; National Women’s Studies Association;
               and Humanities, Arts, Science, and Technology Alliance and Collaboratory (HASTAC)
               examine the role of difference in digital humanities scholarship. In today’s
                  <soCalled>digital humanities moment</soCalled>
               <ptr target="#gold2013"/>, the field often re-encounters the growing pains of the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013">eternal September of the digital
                     humanities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nowviskie2013"/>
               </cit>. As a result, recurring questions insist on the need for cultural critique in
               the field: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2013">Where is cultural criticism in the digital
                     humanities?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#liu2013"/>
               </cit>, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wernimont2013">Can we describe digital archives as
                     feminist?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wernimont2013"/>
               </cit>, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#mcpherson2013">Why are the digital humanities so
                     white?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#mcpherson2013"/>
               </cit>, and <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#earhart2013">Can information be unfettered?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#earhart2013"/>
               </cit>. The persistence of these questions demonstrates the need for more answers to
               the pressing matter of inclusion and exclusion within the field.</p>
            <p>A recent special issue of the journal <title rend="italic">differences</title>,
                  <title rend="quotes">In the Shadow of the Digital Humanities,</title> considers
               the fraught relationship between digital humanities and diversity. The call for
               papers for the Canadian Society for Digital Humanities and Association for Computers
               and the Humanities joint conference encourages proposals from <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#saklofske2014">women, people of color, LGBTQ, or
                     other under-represented groups</quote>
                  <ptr target="#saklofske2014"/>
               </cit>. The 2015 Digital Diversity conference in Edmonton celebrates the 20<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of <title rend="italic">The Orlando
                  Project</title> and asks, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#digitaldiversity2015">Have decades of digital
                     studies enhanced, altered, or muted the project to recover and represent more
                     diverse histories of writers, thinkers, and artists positioned differently by
                     gender, race, ethnicity, sexualities, social class, and/or global
                     location?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#digitaldiversity2015"/>
               </cit>. Such calls suggest that scholars within digital humanities have begun
               recognizing the need for inclusive representation and a critical approach that
               foregrounds intellectual diversity within the field. </p>
            <p>Resistance to the utility of cultural criticism abounds. Notably, Matthew
               Kirschenbaum argues many critics target a construct of <soCalled>digital
                  humanities</soCalled> rather than the varied range of projects that comprise the
               field <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2014"/>. In distinguishing between a discursive
               subject of criticism and material praxis, he echoes debates over the <soCalled>hack
                  vs. yack</soCalled> binary – doing vs. theorizing – that have taken place in the
               field <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>; <ptr target="#cecire2011"/>; <ptr
                  target="#schmidt2011"/>; <ptr target="#jones2013"/>. Invoking a division between
               the two has been something of a stock move, used in equal measure to call digital
               humanists untheoretical <ptr target="#bauer2011"/> and to distance digital humanities
               from the messy realities of race, gender, sexuality, class, and other forms of
               difference <ptr target="#smith2007"/>. As Bethany Nowviskie notes, the binary has
               become a strawman for a false claim of a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2014">fundamental opposition in thinking
                     between humanities theorists and deliberately anti-theoretical DH
                        <soCalled>builders</soCalled></quote>
                  <ptr target="#nowviskie2014"/>
               </cit>. The division between <soCalled>hack</soCalled> and <soCalled>yack</soCalled>
               has been complicated by the idea of tacit knowledge <ptr target="#turkel2010"/> that
               emerges from <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2012">journeyman learning
                     experiences</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nowviskie2012"/>
               </cit> and by the intimate link between building and knowing within the field <ptr
                  target="#rockwell2011"/>; <ptr target="#scheinfeldt2010a"/>. Yet, the binary
               persists, both in questionable arguments that cultural criticism targets a discursive
               construction of the field alone and invalid claims that an emphasis on building makes
               digital humanities untheoretical.</p>
            <p>The relationship between theory and praxis is integral to the digital humanities.
               Connections between the two appear in the archives built, corpora analyzed, oral
               histories recorded, and geographies mapped. As Alan Liu has suggested, the practices
               of digital humanities make engagement with cultural critique online possible <ptr
                  target="#liu2013"/>. In turn, theory contributes to the development of the field’s
               metadiscourse and enables a critical look at material practices, including their
               omissions. Those of us who work with issues of difference often perceive the ways
               that many digital humanities projects fail to engage with race, gender, disability,
               class, sexuality, or a combination thereof. Some of the most developed digital
               humanities work – The Rossetti Archive, The Walt Whitman Archive, The William Blake
               Archive – preserve the writing of dead white men, specifically individuals unlikely
               to be forgotten in Anglophone literary history even if these projects did not exist.
               There are practical explanations for such subjects. For example, the body of pre-1923
               public domain material digitized and ready for study privileges canonical writers and
               texts. As Earhart argues, fewer scholars are working with digital textual recovery
               and diversifying the available texts <ptr target="#earhart2013"/>. Yet, as Skye
               Bianco has argued, the consolidation of digital humanities as a recognizable field
               for institutions and grantors has led to exposure for <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bianco2013">disciplinarily legible projects</quote> that rely on
               canonicity for justification, yielding a field that trades on <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bianco2013">its kinship to much older modes of
                     humanistic study</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>
               </cit>. Bianco describes this trend as a form of <soCalled>retro-humanism</soCalled>
               that does not account for recent developments in the humanities, like cultural
               studies, feminism, postcolonial studies, critical race studies, or queer studies <ptr
                  target="#bianco2013"/>. Earhart proposes that digital humanities might intervene
               by reviving digital textual recovery work and identifying the omissions of the canon: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#earhart2013">crucial work by women, people of color,
                     and the GLBTQ community</quote>
                  <ptr target="#earhart2013"/>
               </cit>. The stakes here are high; as digital humanities becomes the public face of
               the humanities through organizations like 4Humanities and HASTAC, retro-humanism
               cannot be the order of the day. Without attention to the omissions that exist within
               digital humanities scholarship, the field risks replicating the exclusions of a
               dominant culture that already relegates difference to its margins.</p>
            <p>To avoid this pitfall, we need critical approaches that transcend false binaries
               between <soCalled>hack</soCalled> and <soCalled>yack.</soCalled> Intersectionality is
               one such frame that offers a way of examining the history of digital humanities to
               identify strategies for greater intellectual diversity in the field.
               Intersectionality originates in the work of Kimberlé Crenshaw, a legal scholar who
               sought a model for understanding the relationship between race, gender, and violence
               against women of color. The concept articulates Crenshaw’s perception that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#crenshaw1991">the experiences of women of color are
                     frequently the product of intersecting patterns of racism and sexism</quote>
                  <ptr target="#crenshaw1991" loc="1243"/>
               </cit>. Through her research with women living in shelters, Crenshaw saw the ways the
               women encountered <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#crenshaw1991">burdens, largely the consequence of
                     gender and class oppression...compounded by the racially discriminatory
                     employment and housing practices women of color often face, as well as by the
                     disproportionately high unemployment among people of color</quote>
                  <ptr target="#crenshaw1991" loc="1245–1246"/>
               </cit>. Crenshaw proposes that <quote rend="inline" source="#crenshaw1991"
                  >multilayered and routinized forms of domination...often converge</quote> to shape
               the experiences and limit the opportunities of women of color – black women in
               particular – whose concerns are not adequately represented by either anti-racist or
               feminist discourse alone <ptr target="#crenshaw1991" loc="1245"/>. From Crenshaw’s
               grounded analysis in the 1980s to now, intersectionality has come to signify the ways
               that oppression manifests through multiple facets of identity that confer or withhold
               privilege, unearned advantages that accrue to individuals on the basis of their
               identities <ptr target="#mcintosh1990"/>. In its more expansive definition,
               intersectionality is generally understood to look beyond the race-class-gender triad
               described by Crenshaw to additional axes of difference including sexuality and
               ability. As a lens for scholarship in the digital humanities, intersectionality
               resists binary logic, encourages complex analysis, and foregrounds difference.</p>
            <p>This article proposes that intersectionality is a viable approach to cultural
               criticism in the digital humanities, enabling us to write alternate histories of the
               field that transcend simplistic <soCalled>hack</soCalled> vs.
                  <soCalled>yack</soCalled> binaries. I begin by situating debates over difference
               in the digital humanities within the larger context of the culture wars within the US
               academy in the 1980s and 1990s to locate the stakes of diversity within the field.
               Then, I suggest what an intersectional approach to digital humanities might look like
               and offer a survey of projects through an intersectional lens. Finally, I suggest
               ways the field might look forward towards deeper intersectional analysis needed to
               develop a transformed, inclusive digital humanities. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Lessons of Theory</head>
            <p>In 2009, William Pannapacker called digital humanities <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#pannapacker2009">the next big thing,</quote> a move that recalls the
               rise of critical theory, the <emph>last</emph> big thing to shape the humanities <ptr
                  target="#pannapacker2009"/>. Responses to digital humanities from cultural critics
               in the mainstream press often echo the culture wars of the late 1980s and early
               1990s, the struggle within the US academy over the fraught relationship between
               literature and theory. As the story goes, with the advent of theory, Shakespeare was
               going to be jettisoned for Saussure, Defoe for Derrida. Cultural critic Roger Kimball
               argued that <quote rend="inline" source="#kimball1990">ideological posturing, pop
                  culture, and hermetic word games</quote> were supplanting humanities education
                  <ptr target="#kimball1990" loc="11"/>. Critics of the digital humanities have made
               analogous charges. For example, Adam Kirsch suggests, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kirsch2014">...the very idea of language as the
                     basis of humane education – even of human identity – seems to give way to a
                     post- or pre-verbal discourse of pictures and objects. Digital humanities
                     becomes another name for the obsequies of humanism</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kirsch2014"/>
               </cit>. Digital humanities reduces literature to <soCalled>data.</soCalled> Distant
               reading is destroying close reading.</p>
            <p>History repeats itself in other ways too. The backlash against theory for its elision
               of difference resonates with arguments for cultural critique within digital
               humanities. Along with theory came criticism of its rise from black, ethnic, and
               women’s studies. Many scholars in these fields were conscious of their hard-won gains
               during the 1960s and 1970s – establishing academic departments and journals and
               having their work recognized as scholarship – and worried their position within the
               academy would be jeopardized by the arrival of theory in the 1980s. They did not see
               theoretical models based on the work of Karl Marx, Michel Foucault, and Jacques
               Derrida as schools of thought that promoted their goals. Rather, they viewed the rise
               of theory in opposition to their work, which was located not in continental
               philosophy but in lived experiences of difference in the U.S. </p>
            <p>In her essay <title rend="quotes">The Race for Theory,</title> Barbara Christian
               writes about the growing importance of theory in the academy in the late 1980s,
               articulating concerns about inclusion and exclusion that are strikingly relevant to
               the digital humanities. She begins, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#christian1987">The New Philosophers, eager to
                     understand a world that is today fast escaping their political control, have
                     redefined literature so that the distinctions implied by the term…have been
                     blurred. They have changed literary critical language to suit their own
                     purposes as philosophers, and they have reinvented the meaning of
                     theory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#christian1987" loc="51"/>
               </cit>. Just as theory’s <soCalled>New Philosophers</soCalled> have begun
               transforming literary studies through theory, so too are digital humanists opening up
               new possibilities for scholarship. Christian’s <quote rend="inline" source="#christian1987"
                  >literary critical language</quote> is digital humanities’
                  <soCalled>methodologies.</soCalled> She anticipates a shift in the landscape of
               the academy, wondering what will happen to radical critics if theory becomes a
               defining part of literary scholarship and a commodity for appointment, tenure, and
               promotion. Christian sees the possibility of radical critique being domesticated as
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#christian1987">black, women, [and] third world</quote> scholars
               invested in intersectional approaches to literature are coerced into adopting the
               language of theory and <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#christian1987">speaking a language and defining
                     their discussion in terms alien to and opposed to our needs and
                     orientations</quote>
                  <ptr target="#christian1987" loc="52"/>
               </cit>. Likewise, scholars in the digital humanities advocating for cultural critique
               recognize that engaging with difference is not only a question of representation but
               also one of method.</p>
            <p>Digital humanities scholars who work with difference fear for its viability, much
               like Christian and her colleagues worried about their relationship to theory in the
               1980s. Will black, ethnic, and women’s studies be legible within digital humanities?
               Will other forms of difference – gender, sexuality, ability – have a place in the
               field as well? Scholars who take up these issues focus on the ways digital humanities
               intersects with how we engage difference in our work. These approaches are grounded
               in core questions of difference above, articulated by Alan Liu, Jacqueline Wernimont,
               Tara McPherson, and Amy Earhart, among others. Newer groups within digital humanities
               have been inspired by their concerns. For example, #transformDH is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#transformdh2012">an academic guerilla movement
                     seeking to (re)define capital-letter Digital Humanities as a force for
                     transformative scholarship by collecting, sharing, and highlighting projects
                     that push at its boundaries and work for social justice, accessibility, and
                     inclusion</quote>
                  <ptr target="#transformdh2012"/>
               </cit>. The roots of #transformDH lie in <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#conghuyen2013">intersectional critical cultural
                     studies” such as “critical race and ethnic studies; feminist, gender, queer
                     studies; postcolonial, transnational, diaspora; disability studies; DIY (Add
                     your own!)</quote>
                  <ptr target="#conghuyen2013"/>
               </cit>. As a result, #transformDH operates under the assertion that <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#conghuyen2013">gender, sexuality, race, nationality, and ability are
                  all central to how we encounter and participate in digital humanities</quote> and
               that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#conghuyen2013">we must work collectively towards
                     transformative, social justice oriented engagements</quote>
                  <ptr target="#conghuyen2013"/>
               </cit>. Similarly, Postcolonial Digital Humanities, or #dhpoco, has sought to build a
               community of scholars working at the intersections of postcolonial studies and the
               digital humanities, to promote <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#risam2013">global explorations of race, class,
                     gender, sexuality, and disability within cultures of technology</quote>
                  <ptr target="#risam2013"/>
               </cit>. Another initiative, Global Outlook::Digital Humanities (GO::DH), a special
               interest group of the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), fosters
               communication and collaboration around the world, navigating not only geographic but
               also economic difference and the practical challenges of embracing multilingualism
               within ADHO. The organization has supported the development of regional and
               linguistic tracks like South Asian Digital Humanities, Red Humanidades Digitales, and
               Associação das Humanidades Digitais; a whisper campaign to facilitate on-the-fly
               translations at the Digital Humanities 2014 meeting; and Alex Gil’s <title
                  rend="italic">Around DH in 80 Days</title> website that showcases the
               international scope of projects. Groups like #transformDH, Postcolonial Digital
               Humanities, and GO::DH situate their missions at the intersections of multiple axes
               of difference, recognizing the need for attention to the complex power relations that
               serve as barriers to achieving inclusivity within the digital humanities. </p>
            <p>The recent popularity of digital humanities obscures a longer history of which these
               initiatives are part. Just as Christian pushes back against the newness of theory and
               argues, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#christian1987">people of color have always
                     theorized</quote>
                  <ptr target="#christian1987" loc="52"/>
               </cit>, there are earlier, oft-unrecognized instances of digital humanities work that
               engages with difference. Since the 1990s, Afrofuturist scholars have been framing
               technoculture through intersectional lenses. Afrofuturism is an African American
               literary and artistic movement that foregrounds speculative approaches to
               displacement, belonging, and home for the African diaspora. Its literary dimensions
               encompass science and speculative fiction by writers like Nalo Hopkinson, Octavia
               Butler, and Samuel R. Delaney, while its critical angle has considered the ways that
               blackness, gender, class, and sexuality intersect in technoculture. Alondra Nelson
               created the Afrofuturism listserv in the 1990s to examine futurist themes in African
               diasporic cultural production, blackness in science fiction, and the possibilities of
               black technoculture. Her 2001 edited volume <title rend="italic">Technicolor: Race,
                  Technology, and Everyday Life</title> (with Thuy Linh Tu) was one of the first
               collections to consider the influence of racial politics on technoculture, and she
               also edited a 2002 issue of <title rend="italic">Social Text</title> on Afrofuturism,
               with an emphasis on how new media, culture, and technology influence the African
               Diaspora. Kali Tal, who developed the Afrofuturism website, is perhaps best known for
               her article <title rend="quotes">Life Behind the Screen,</title> which considers
               omissions in cyberculture scholarship in the mid-1990s <ptr target="#tal1996"/>.
               Scholars like W.E.B. Du Bois, she argues, have been theorizing identity in ways
               useful for but largely ignored by cyberculture studies. This body of work, which
               situates the African diaspora within the digital milieu, exists alongside early
               efforts at textual recovery for African American studies during the 1990s. As Earhart
               has suggested, projects like <title rend="italic">The Charles Chesnutt
                  Archive</title> and <title rend="italic">Race and Place: An African-American
                  Community in the Jim Crow South</title> embraced the affordances of emerging
               Internet technologies to resist canon bias among early digital projects <ptr
                  target="#earhart2013"/>. To recognize this work within digital humanities is to
               embrace the possibilities of digital cultural recovery for the African diaspora.
               Earhart herself has begun archiving and recovering early work through her project
                  <title rend="italic">The Diverse History of Digital Humanities</title>. </p>
            <p>Another area of scholarship that inspires digital humanities scholars invested in
               intersectionality is new media studies, which has been asking difficult questions
               about difference and the Internet since the 2000s. Lisa Nakamura’s work interrogates
               the ways that online experiences shape perceptions of race, ethnicity, and identity,
               drawing on critical race theory as she identifies a relationship between operations
               of stereotypes online and offline <ptr target="#nakamura2002"/>; <ptr
                  target="#nakamura2012"/>. She further suggests that the Internet is a space of
               re-embodiment along the lines of race and gender, as biotechnologies and other forces
               shape the online body <ptr target="#nakamura2007"/>. Similarly, Wendy Chun has
               examined how superficial views of difference have led to troubling beliefs that
               online spaces are disembodied and therefore insulated from the realities of social
               inequalities <ptr target="#chun2001"/>; <ptr target="#chun2005"/>. Anna Everett also
               takes up related issues, ranging from race in the digital public sphere <ptr
                  target="#everett2002"/> to black public life and black women’s experiences online
                  <ptr target="#everett2009"/> and the influence of intersectional forms of
               difference in video games <ptr target="#everett2014"/>. Bringing a postcolonial lens
               to these debates, Pramod Nayar argues that technologized bodies are <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#nayar2010">raced, gendered, and classed, and situated in
                  particular social, and economic, and cultural contexts</quote> and emphasizes the
               importance of acknowledging subalternity in cyberspace <ptr target="#nayar2010"
                  loc="66"/>. Drawing on theories of globalization as well as postcolonial studies,
               Radhika Gajjala examines the nature of South Asian technospaces, the effects of
               microfinance and peer-to-peer lending on women’s craft communities, and the ways
               silence and voice are shaped online, insisting on the relationship between the local,
               global, and digital <ptr target="#gajjala2008"/>; <ptr target="#gajjala2012"/>.
               Attending to questions of media and migration, Isabelle Rigoni argues that
               intersectionality is an important tool for analyzing ethnic minority media. She
               suggests that while representation is increasingly happening in digital media, little
               attention has been paid to how race, gender, and postcolonial migration together <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#rigoni2012">produce and maintain the unequal
                     distribution of power in the mediascape</quote>
                  <ptr target="#rigoni2012" loc="834"/>
               </cit>. Her work situates the affordances of intersectionality for analysis of
               digital media, arguing that it <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#rigoni2012">provide[s] an important analytical and
                     conceptual tool for enabling us to understand gender, race, and class, as
                     dimensions of social identities in transition, especially as reflected in the
                     media</quote>
                  <ptr target="#rigoni2012" loc="835"/>
               </cit>. Ben Aslinger and Nina Huntemann also identify a relationship between new
               media studies and intersectionality, suggesting that new media studies may be a safe
               space for intersectional analysis and a challenge to the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aslinger2013">often described conflation/caricature
                     of the new media scholar as an apolitical white heterosexual male
                     academic</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aslinger2013" loc="11"/>
               </cit>. Together, these developments in new media speak to the strides that feminist,
               queer, and critical race theory scholars have made in interrogating the relationship
               between digital media and multiple categories of identity, changing the ways we
               understand the relationship between networks, digital media, and subjectivity. </p>
            <p>Recent calls for intersectional analysis in digital humanities are further indebted
               to Sandra Harding’s ground-breaking work in feminist and postcolonial science and
               technology studies, which considers the relationship between feminist ways of knowing
               in scientific paradigms, the role of multiculturalism in science studies, and the
               imperialist foundations of European and American science <ptr target="#harding1998"
               />; <ptr target="#harding2008"/>. This scholarship speaks to the relationship between
               difference and technology in a range of intersectional forms. Implications for
               digital humanities include the emphasis on technoscience, which enables critical
               analysis of the materiality of digital and computational technologies in relation to
               power, embodiment, and difference. Emphasizing that technologies themselves are
               implicated in intersectionality, Claire Potter has suggested, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#potter2013">New digital technologies have their own
                     history, one that is recent to be sure, but that nevertheless resonates to
                     historical questions of race, class, gender, nationalism, and sexuality that
                     are at the heart of a feminist intellectual enterprise</quote>
                  <ptr target="#potter2013" loc="358"/>
               </cit>. Together, these scholarly contributions to difference in technoculture have
               places in the alternate histories we must write about the digital humanities. They
               offer models that foreshadow the role of intersectional analysis in the field by
               making the case that engagement with computational technologies is inextricably
               linked to questions of history, culture, identity, and difference. They hint at
               methods that advocate inclusion and critical analysis but are situated in the
               materiality of technologies – the very methods central to an intersectional approach
               to digital humanities. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Towards an Intersectional Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>These concerns are vital to the analytical work of digital humanities, the
               computational technologies developed or used to produce scholarship, and the ways
               projects are designed. Like any scholarly field, digital humanities veers towards the
               monolithic, constructing centers and peripheries. Every definition is necessarily
               exclusionary but the task of defining is an inevitable part of academic practice.
               Yet, acts of exclusion often come at the expense of those who inhabit the margins and
               whose identities are shaped by intersecting axes of difference. This phenomenon
               manifests in multiple ways, from the presumptive white maleness of digital humanities
                  <ptr target="#bailey2011"/> to the canon bias within the field <ptr
                  target="#earhart2013"/>; <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>. That is to say, this is not
               only a matter of the diversity of individuals within digital humanities but also of
               intellectual diversity. Therefore, it is incumbent on those at the center of the
               digital humanities to understand the position of those whose work dwells in the
               peripheries, to understand the historical legacies that link knowledge production
               with the denigration – even the destruction – of that which is other.</p>
            <p>What I offer here is the beginning of a genealogy that identifies the influences of
               intersectionality on digital humanities, in its approach to theory and practice. I
               chart the ways intersectionality has been part of conversations in the digital
               humanities and survey projects in which we might find hints of intersectionality.
               These are the traces on which we might build to properly situate intersectionality as
               critical approach to the field. Broad in range, hallmarks of intersectionality in
               digital humanities include common sense advice for cultivating a diverse community,
               theoretical models for understanding the ways difference shapes digital practices,
               applied theoretical models that position intersectionality as an already existing but
               oft-overlooked part of computation, and practical tweaks like acknowledging
               inclusions and exclusions in data or developing search functions that enable
               intersectional engagement. Projects that are explicitly intersectional in their
               design and development are more rare but nonetheless essential. </p>
            <p>Among early voices advocating for a theoretically intersectional approach to digital
               humanities is Martha Nell Smith, who proposes that the rigor of the field depends on
               it. She suggests, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2007">Our pliant and accommodating standards
                     need also to be more interdisciplinary and take into account the
                        <soCalled>messy</soCalled> facts of authorship, production, and reception:
                     race, class, gender, and sexuality</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith2007" loc="2"/>
               </cit>. Undertaking such a task of <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2007">embracing messy
                  humanity in all its diversities</quote> is, according to Smith, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2007">no longer a luxury for our community, it
                     is a necessity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith2007" loc="2"/>
               </cit>. More recently, Smith has issued a call to integrate feminist, critical race,
               sexuality, and class-based analysis into digital humanities, particularly in digital
               archival practice. Such an approach would address questions like <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2014">How have these items of knowledge and the
                     organizations and working groups who made them come into being? Who has stakes
                     in their presentation? What is visible in these new media archives and what
                     might not be? Can what is invisible but relevant be known to users of new
                     digital archives?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith2014" loc="409"/>
               </cit>. To thaw the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2014">frozen social relations</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith2014" loc="404"/>
               </cit> that she identifies within digital humanities scholarship, Smith suggests, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2014">Producers should make every effort to
                     make clear what has been occluded by remediation, by principles and practices
                     of selection, and to unfreeze old binaries of authority and involve users in
                     knowledge production</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith2014" loc="409"/>
               </cit>. That is to say, digital humanities scholarship must be self-reflexive,
               interrogating its own positionality within the broader landscape of knowledge
               production, along axes of difference. </p>
            <p>Another consideration is the tensions evoked by engagement with difference in the
               digital humanities. The field is beleaguered by its own creation myths and investment
               in <soCalled>niceness,</soCalled>
               <soCalled>collegiality,</soCalled> and <soCalled>openness.</soCalled> Tom Scheinfeldt
               attributes this niceness to the field’s investment in method, suggesting that
               methodological debates are easier to resolve than theoretical ones <ptr
                  target="#scheinfeldt2010b"/>. Conversely, Bianco has proposed that depictions of
               digital humanities as the <soCalled>cool kids’ table</soCalled> from outside the
               field and the emphasis on niceness within mean digital humanities is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bianco2013">constructing itself through the
                     competing narratives of privileged, middle-class, white high-school politics in
                     tension with privileged, middle-class, white people who work
                        <soCalled>nicely</soCalled> together</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>
               </cit>. These issues – niceness, method, difference, theory – came to the fore in
               responses to Miriam Posner’s essay about coding. While not opposed to code, Posner
               identifies the way that knowledge of coding plays out along gendered, classed, and
               racialized lines, noting that <quote rend="inline" source="#posner2012">men –
                  middle-class white men</quote> are more likely to have been encouraged to engage
               with computational technology at a young age <ptr target="#posner2012"/>. Identifying
               the intersectional structural biases influencing trends in who is most likely to know
               how to code, Posner suggests, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#posner2012">If you [digital humanists] want women
                     and people of color in your community, if it is important to you to have a
                     diverse discipline, you need to do something besides exhort us to code</quote>
                  <ptr target="#posner2012"/>
               </cit>. Responses to Posner’s post, which included dissent, revealed how
               misunderstood the connection between theory and method can be. She responded by
               linking method – coding – to theory – arguing, <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#posner2012">Let’s make inequities of power something else we decide to
                  abandon</quote> and proposing guidelines for intersectional engagement in the
               digital humanities community: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#posner2012">1. Let’s think about ways to build
                     communities of underrepresented people...2. Let’s acknowledge that we all do
                     racist and sexist stuff sometimes...3. Let’s talk about when our niceness could
                     be shutting down important conversations...4. Let’s believe people when they
                     tell us they feel uncomfortable</quote>
                  <ptr target="#posner2012"/>
               </cit>. Here, Posner identifies the influence of difference, arguably a theoretical
               concern, on method. These guidelines are a precondition to an intersectional response
               to difference in digital humanities that embraces the relationship between theory and
               method. </p>
            <p>Approaching difference by blending Smith’s recommendations for intersectional
               analysis and Posner’s community guidelines reveals the ways the field is already
               informed by intersectionality. As Bianco has suggested, computational scholarship
               already is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bianco2013">a radically heterogeneous and a
                     multimodally layered – read, not visible – set of practices, constraints and
                     codifications that operate below the level of user interaction</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>
               </cit>. In that layer, operations of intersectionality may be visible if we look for
               them. Accordingly, Bianco notes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bianco2013">Our ethics, methods and theory are
                        <emph>not transparent</emph> in our tools, unless you have the serious
                     know-how to critically make them or hack them</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>
               </cit>. While digital humanists themselves may have access to that layer by virtue of
               technical skill, users engaging with digital humanities scholarship may not.
               Similarly, Smith argues, <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2014">Tools cannot be
                  separated from the knowledge systems in which they have been imagined and
                  made</quote> but proposes we might frame intersectional practices as tools
               themselves <ptr target="#smith2014" loc="408"/>. To do so would ensure that digital
               humanities scholarship unsettles essentialist categories, rather than reifying
               existing assumptions about race, gender, class, ability, sexuality, or other
               categories of difference. Therefore, it is incumbent on us to make the critical
               layers visible to users in the apparatus developed around our work. </p>
            <p>By approaching intersectionality in the digital humanities at the juncture of
               disciplinary knowledge and technical specification, we blend theory and method and
               avoid what Moya Bailey calls <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bailey2011">the add and stir model of diversity, a
                     practice of sprinkling in more women, people of color, disabled folks and
                     assuming that is enough to change current paradigms</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bailey2011"/>
               </cit>. Bailey frames this issue in intersectional terms, proposing, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bailey2011">This identity based mixing does little
                     to address the structural parameters that are set up when a homogeneous group
                     has been at the center and don’t automatically engender understanding across
                     forms of difference</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bailey2011"/>
               </cit>. Axes of difference are fluid and converge in multiple ways. For example, the
               considerations necessary for a project on black lesbian activism would necessarily be
               different from one on oral histories of Latina transwomen; these might range from
               technical specifications to design principles to issues of safety that a public
               project might raise. As a result, there is not simply one way of doing intersectional
               digital humanities. Rather, it is a provisional lens that suggests practitioners
               begin their work with an understanding of the particularities necessary to design
               projects that account for influences of difference on knowledge-production. To date,
               we have few alternatives that enable such an approach. For example, Kara Keeling’s
                  <title rend="quotes">Queer OS</title> or <q>queer operating system</q> suggests
               that a queer perspective, broadly construed, would change how we view technology.
               Queer OS <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#keeling2014">would take historical, sociocultural,
                     conceptual phenomena that currently shape our realities in deep and profound
                     ways, such as race, gender, class citizenship, and ability … to be mutually
                     constitutive with sexuality and with media and information technologies,
                     thereby making it impossible to think of any of them in isolation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#keeling2014" loc="153"/>
               </cit>. By viewing <q>queer</q> as an operating system, Keeling proposes to decenter
               social norms in favor of their alternatives. Moreover, she frames Queer OS in
               intersectional terms, emphasizing the relationship between sexuality and other
               categories like race, ability, and nationality. Offering another alternative, Fobazi
               M. Ettarh interrogates the relationship between Boolean search terms and
               intersectional identity. Describing her experiences in library school, she notes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#ettarh2013">I am proof that these [race, gender, and
                     sexuality] are not separate issues. I am not Black one day and Queer the next.
                     Instead, I am Black AND Queer. In Principles of Searching we learn how
                     important and, or, and nor are in Boolean searching. Too long the environment
                     has been Black OR Queer</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ettarh2013"/>
               </cit>. As such, she identifies a conceptual fit between intersectionality and
               structures of information. These issues are further explored by Alexis Lothian and
               Amanda Phillips who ask, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lothian2013">Can digital humanities mean
                     transformative critique?</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
               </cit>. They argue that if scholars in fields like ethnic studies, gender studies,
               cultural studies, disability studies, or queer studies are engaging with technology
               in their scholarship, they should <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lothian2013">lay claim to our place within digital
                     humanities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
               </cit>. Through such an intersectional bent Lothian and Phillips look forward to
               transformative digital humanities <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lothian2013">where neither the digital nor the
                     humanities will be terms taken for granted</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
               </cit>. These theoretical perspectives offer models of how intersectionality operates
               in relationship to the digital humanities, from the nature of computation itself to
               the way we constitute relationships between the humanistic inquiry and the digital. </p>
            <p>In additional to theoretical precursors, we have projects that, in their own ways,
               provide models for how to approach digital humanities through an intersectional lens.
               An acknowledgment of the inclusions and exclusions within a data set or the source
               material is an important start. Allison Booth’s <title rend="italic">Collective
                  Biographies of Women</title>
               <ptr target="#cbw"/>, for example, focuses on prosopography, or collective biography,
               a genre of text comprised of short biographies. Using print volumes and digital
               resources like Project Gutenberg or Google Books, <title rend="italic">CBW</title>
               compiles biographical narratives and develops tools for prosopography. The project’s
                  <title rend="quotes">About</title> page offers an important model of how projects
               can be positioned in intersectional terms: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#cbw">Prosopography must be selective, but it can
                     claim a share of attention for marginal identities. Most women have gone
                     missing in history and have no printed memorial. The Anglo-American catalogues
                     in CBW tended to exclude all but the rare working woman, woman of color, or
                     woman who did not belong to the Christian middle class of English descent.
                     Religious nonconformists and various minorities nevertheless began to use this
                     tool of recognition. The collections camouflage or accept some examples of
                     diverse sexuality and same-sex relationships and many examples of single or old
                     women. It is high-ranking women who pursue heterosexual affairs who get
                     censured in these books — but not always or not with conviction. Some books
                     celebrate opposites of the <soCalled>good woman</soCalled> type. The
                     limitations of the lists – and any canons or lists – notwithstanding, a search
                     through this bibliography and the books it registers helps to correct some
                     distorted generalizations about the lack of records of women in the
                     past.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cbw"/>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>The project’s <title rend="quotes">Pop Chart</title> or index of most frequently
               recurring subjects indicates a bias towards white European or American women, with
               Pocahontas and Cleopatra being notable exceptions. However, the <title rend="italic"
                  >CBW</title>’s proactive foregrounding of questions of race, class, gender, and
               sexuality in the fashioning of the project is a fitting model of how to engage with
               intersectional digital humanities. Key here is making the intersecting phenomena that
               shape a project visible even though they may not be readily understood. <title
                  rend="italic">The Orlando Project</title> does this as well. <title rend="italic"
                  >Orlando</title> examines women’s literary history but its focus on women’s
               writing may obscure its intersectional underpinnings upon first glance. However, the
               scholarly introduction to the project notes that while gender is <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#orlando">an indispensable tool for historical analysis,</quote> the project
               creators <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#orlando">see gender as one among other constituents
                     of identity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#orlando"/>
               </cit>. Therefore, the project includes documents that examine race, class, sexuality
               or other categories of difference to illuminate the “cultural formation” of writers.
               Identifying such a frame, the project makes clear that its engagement with gender is
               situated in the flexible and provisional spirit of intersectionality. </p>
            <p>A project might also structure its search mechanism to optimize intersectional
               analysis. Brad Pasanek’s <title rend="italic">The Mind is a Metaphor</title>
               database, for example, makes clear that its scope and textual sources only cover
                  18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century British metaphors <ptr target="#pasanek"
               />. Yet, the metaphors themselves are tagged to enable intersectional searches. A
               user can sort by not only literary period, metaphor category, and genre but also
               gender, race, and nationality. Among the latter, <soCalled>African or
                  Afro-British</soCalled> is one such category, which when selected with
                  <soCalled>female</soCalled> produces a list of metaphors by Phillis Wheatley.
               Despite the predictable underrepresentation of black women in a database of 18<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> century British writing, the ability to navigate the
               database in such a way acknowledges the importance of intersectionality. The <title
                  rend="italic">Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title> (EWWRP) similarly
               foregrounds an intersectional approach through the way it structures project data.
               Among the collections through which the site is organized are <title rend="quotes"
                  >Native American,</title>
               <title rend="quotes">Abolition, Freedom, and Rights,</title> and <title rend="quotes"
                  >Women’s Advocacy,</title> but the collections are fluid, with texts fitting
               multiple categories appearing in more than one collection <ptr target="#ewwrp"/>.
                  <title rend="italic">A Celebration of Women Writers</title>, a site that preserves
               public domain women’s texts compiled by Mary Mark Ockerbloom, also enables ethnicity
               as one method of browsing the archive <ptr target="#ockerbloom2012"/>.</p>
            <p>User integration is another way digital humanities projects can make intersectional
               interventions possible. <title rend="italic">NINES: Nineteenth-century Scholarship
                  Online</title> material is beginning to grow more diverse. Visible tags on the
               project website, including <q>women,</q>
               <q>Chinese,</q>
               <q>African,</q> and <q>diaspora,</q> suggest an effort to foreground a range of
               objects from 125 federated websites. The Collex interface offers possibilities for
               creating exhibits, which allows users to interact with the material through curation;
               even users without specialized training could arrange the material to explore a range
               of topics through available objects. Moreover, Collex offers the possibility of
               expanding the archive of affiliated websites via RDF, allowing creators of
               substantial projects to seek peer review and inclusion in NINES. NINES demonstrates
               openness towards greater representation and offers tools to make that possible.
                  <title rend="italic">The Women Writers Project</title>, which undertakes
               electronic text encoding for pre-Victorian women’s writing, includes a publication
               series called <title rend="italic">Women Writers in Context,</title> which features
               exhibits <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wwp">designed to engage readers in the exploration
                     and discovery of topics related to early modern women’s writing</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wwp"/>
               </cit>. One such exhibit on women and race allowed creator Kim Hall to explore the
               role of intersectional analysis and engagement with <title rend="italic">The Women
                  Writers Project</title>. Accordingly, she notes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hall1999">Rather than isolating race as a focus, the
                     best research sees race in relation to concerns of gender, class, religion, and
                     sexuality. To say that race is connected to these other social divisions is not
                     to say that race is analogous to these other categories, nor is it to say that
                     all marginalized people are oppressed or made marginal in the same ways</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hall1999"/>
               </cit>. Though the scope of <title rend="italic">The Women Writers Project,</title>
               namely the periods of literary history it examines, privileges the writing of white
               women, the <title rend="italic">Women Writers in Context</title> series signifies how
               scholars might find interpretive paths through the material. Through user engagement,
               these projects make intersectional analysis more legible in the archive.</p>
            <p>Beyond projects that address intersectionality indirectly, we can look to the
               examples of those that foreground it in project design. An example of an
               intersectional digital archive, Amy Earhart’s project <title rend="italic">The 19<hi
                     rend="superscript">th</hi> Century Concord Digital Archive</title> examines the
               relationship between Concord, Massachusetts and American literature and history. The
               archive <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cda">invites the scholar to utilize a broad set of
                     digital documents to reconsider how the town and its writers are situated
                     within broader scholarly conversations</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cda"/>
               </cit>. Addressing scope, the project statement notes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cda">These [Concord] authors interacted with groups
                     less frequently recorded in textual documents of the time period: free
                     African-Americans, Irish immigrants, the poor, and criminal class</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cda"/>
               </cit>. The archive offers insight on these engagements across lines of gender,
               nationality, class, and more: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cda">By digitizing a broad range of materials that
                     represent the diverse people associated with literary production the archive
                     allows scholars to rethink the way we conceptualize individual work associated
                     with Concord, to redefine our assumptions about literary and historical
                     representation, and to reconsider the very foundation of our disciplinary
                     studies</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cda"/>
               </cit>. The archive reflects Earhart’s observation that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#earhart2013">scholars invested in early work on race
                     in digital humanities insisted on building editions and digital texts as
                     activist intervention in the closed canon</quote>
                  <ptr target="#earhart2013"/>
               </cit>. Indeed, Earhart’s own project is an example of what intersectional activism
               in the canon looks like. </p>
            <p>A further dimension to consider is how intersectional analysis can be engaged through
               text mining. In their work on the Black Drama database, Shlomo Argamon, Charles
               Cooney, Russell Horton, Mark Olsen, Sterling Stein, and Robert Voyer made space for
               intersectional structures within the database as they considered <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#argamon2009">the degree to which machine learning
                     can isolate stylistic or content characteristics of authors and/or characters
                     having particular attributes – gender, race, and nationality</quote>
                  <ptr target="#argamon2009"/>
               </cit>. The database contains 963 texts written by 128 men and 243 by fifty-three
               women; 831 titles are by US authors while 375 are by authors from Caribbean or
               African countries. There are further variations in the number of speeches by women
               and male characters and black and white characters, with a small number of speeches
               by characters of other ethnic backgrounds. Metadata for the project contains 30
               fields to describe characters and authors from the black stage, including <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#argamon2009">Race, age, gender, nationality,
                     ethnicity, occupation, sexual orientation, performers, if a real person and
                     type</quote>
                  <ptr target="#argamon2009"/>
               </cit>. They use the ARTFL search system PhiloLogic, which <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#argamon2009">allows joining of object attribute
                     searches, forming a matrix of author/title/character searching</quote>
                  <ptr target="#argamon2009"/>
               </cit>. Argamon et al. demonstrate the range of intersectional analysis made possible
               by choice of platform, noting that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#argamon2009">one can search for words in speeches by
                     female, black American characters depicted by male, non-American authors in
                     comedies first published during the first half of the 20<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> century</quote>
                  <ptr target="#argamon2009"/>
               </cit>. Argamon et al.’s work suggests how data mining can provide new understandings
               of language use and its relationship to representation. For example, they note that
               analysis of racial epithets reveals variations of language use based on gender and
               nation and propose that such test cases <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#argamon2009">hint at larger discursive and
                     representation issues</quote>
                  <ptr target="#argamon2009"/>
               </cit>. As Argamon et al.’s work with the Black Drama database begins looking at how
               to represent attributes like gender, race or nation as textual characteristics
               through computation, we might ask, <q>Can the database
                  be intersectional?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Conversation within the 2014 Critical Code Studies Working Group indicates the
               importance of intersectionality to our understanding of code as well. The CCSWG 2014
               featured a week on <title rend="quotes">Feminist Programming,</title> led by Arielle
               Schlesinger and featuring Jacqueline Wernimont and Ben Wiedermann as discussants.
               Schlesinger began by asking the group, <q>What is feminist code? What is feminist coding?</q> in relation to code
               snippets by Mez Breeze and micha cárdenas. Among the conversations generated were the
               relationship between executable code and cárdenas’s work code poems, an issue raised
               by Mark Marino. cárdenas explained, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">I am more committed to the visionary
                     and speculative possibilities of these code snippets than their literal
                     executable possibilities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lasmana2014"/>
               </cit>. Wernimont raised the issue of absence, evoking a generative possibility in <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">allowing the absent-presence of
                     feminist executable code to operate as an irritant</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lasmana2014"/>
               </cit>. She described this in feminist terms as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">an occasion to continue to question the
                     structures that have not permitted such a thing to exist</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lasmana2014"/>
               </cit>. cárdenas further complicated the notion of <soCalled>feminist</soCalled> by
               noting that <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">feminist without
                  qualification can easily be equated to white, cis-gender, first world
                  feminism,</quote> asking <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">What is
                  gained and lost by the formulation of this code as feminist, as opposed to say,
                  decolonial, in the sense of rejecting western systems of epistemology</quote> and
               raising the question of the role of intersectionality in code <ptr
                  target="#lasmana2014"/>. Viola Lasmana responded by invoking Trinh T. Minh-ha:
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lasmana2014">Shake syntax, smash the myths, and if
                  you lose, unearth some new linguistic paths</quote> (qtd. in <ptr
                  target="#lasmana2014"/>. She suggests that such processes occur in the code poems
               written by cárdenas and Breeze. The question of executable code raises the issue of
               whether executability may be a limit to both intersectional praxis and digital
               humanities methodology. Given the reliance of digital humanities methodologies on
               executable code, is engaged intersectional work limited by it? By examining this
               question, we may consider the limits of code as not only sets of operations but also
               a language that may enable or foreclose intersectional conversations. </p>
            <p>Finally, practicing digital humanities through social media, Jessica M. Johnson’s
                  <title rend="italic">The Codex,</title> is an example of intersectional engagement
               in digital humanities. <title rend="italic">The Codex</title> is <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#johnson2015">a social media triptych</quote> composed of three sites:
                  <title rend="italic">African Diaspora, PhD</title>, <title rend="italic">Diaspora
                  Hypertext</title>, and <title rend="italic">Seeing Dark Matter</title>
               <ptr target="#johnson2015"/>. Guiding the development of these sites is Johnson’s
               intersectional praxis, which by her own description, is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johnson2015">anti-oppression, feminist and social
                     justice oriented</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johnson2015"/>
               </cit>. <title rend="italic">African Diaspora, PhD</title> showcases developments in
               African diaspora history, from an intersectional lens. A survey of recent posts shows
               attention to scholarship on a range of subjects like images of <soCalled>faithful
                  slaves</soCalled> in Confederate discourse, including mammies and kinship, and
               race and gender in Atlantic New Orleans. Johnson’s site is an important resource for
               African diaspora scholarship, which she frames in intersectional terms: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johnson2015">The field is also interdisciplinary,
                     supporting and supported by research emerging from the fields of African,
                     Africana/African-American, and Latin American studies; women, gender, and
                     sexuality studies; and feminist, post-colonial, and race theory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johnson2015"/>
               </cit>. <title rend="italic">Diaspora Hypertext</title> showcases Johnson’s work as a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johnson2015">black feminist/radical woman of color
                     digital humanist and media maker</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johnson2015"/>
               </cit>. Organized into <q>writing,</q>
               <q>research,</q> and <q>teaching</q> tracks, the site provides a range of resources
               on African Atlantic Diaspora history. Complementing these sites is <title
                  rend="italic">Seeing Dark Matter</title>, a Tumblr-driven digital archive devoted
               to black diasporic visual culture and to <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johnson2015">processing Atlantic slavery through
                     application, code, and screen</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johnson2015"/>
               </cit>. In its multiple modes, Johnson’s work demonstrates how engaging a range of
               tools enables more full exploration of intersectionality within an interdisciplinary
               field. </p>
            <p>The theoretical approaches and projects I have described here are intentionally
               diverse in subject, providing a survey of intersectional traces in the digital
               humanities. Some projects, like Earhart’s, Argamon et al.’s and Johnson’s work,
               consciously integrate intersectionality into their design. Others, like <title
                  rend="italic">Orlando</title>, <title rend="italic">CBW,</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">NINES</title>, suggest how intersectional engagement possible, even
               if not a primary goal. This cursory look for hints of intersectionality is intended
               as an opening salvo for new histories of the digital humanities that locate
               intersectionality at their center and intervene at the locus of theory and method.
               What I have offered here is the work of survey, a pre-cursor to the deep analysis
               necessary for further developing an intersectional history of digital humanities.
               Yet, I have only examined the relatively painless ways that intersectional
               perspectives can be integrated into scholarship: acknowledging the inclusions or
               exclusions of data, defining terms in inclusive ways, or adding another tag. This is
               the surface-level work of representation that is unlikely to destabilize the moorings
               of digital humanities. The pursuit of a more inclusive field only will begin by
               looking at these practices as ways of being thoughtful, intentional, and
               intersectional about digital humanities. Yet, painful work must be done too. This
               includes looking more closely at digital humanities projects, opening the black boxes
               to examine the imprints of intersectionality on archive, code, metadata, database,
               and more. In the writing and rewriting of these histories, digital humanities
               practitioners must situate them in the histories of Afrofuturism, digital textual
               recovery, new media studies, and science and technology studies, being careful not to
               erase or write over the contributions that scholars of race, class, gender,
               sexuality, disability, or other forms of difference are making to the digital
               humanities – or risk reaffirming the power of Western academic hegemony. Moreover, we
               must develop intersectional practices for the digital humanities that account for
               difference from the ground up, integrating theory and method. At the juncture of the
               two, we must attend to discourses and histories of race and racialization,
               complexities of gender, complications of class, the operations of sexuality, and
               their intersections. In doing so, we can create projects that engage, rather than
               rebuff, difference. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The affordances of the digital humanities are often thought to reside in its ethos of
               building and hacking, in the pursuit of knowledge that emerge from the act of making.
               As this survey of theoretical and project-based traces of intersectionality within
               digital humanities proposes, cultural critique is perhaps misunderstood by its
               detractors in the field as an attempt to force a theoretical rubric onto digital
               humanities or to rehearse a <q>hack</q> vs. <q>yack</q> binary. Rather, theoretical
               moves are implicit within digital humanities projects and excavating them is
               necessary to ensuring intellectual diversity. We have the opportunity to build a more
               inclusive field, new methodologies, and new forms of analysis. </p>
            <p>Why an intersectional approach? As Kathy Davis suggests, intersectionality is not a
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#davis2008">normative straitjacket</quote> or
               predetermined method of feminist analysis <ptr target="#davis2008" loc="79"/>.
               Drawing on Patricia Hill Collins’s observation that intersectionality is often taken
               as pre-defined and ignores convergence and contradiction within intersectional
               scholarship, Anna Carastathis argues that intersectionality must be viewed as a
               provisional concept that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#carastathis2014">anticipates, rather than arrives
                     at, the normative or theoretical goals often imputed to it</quote>
                  <ptr target="#carastathis2014" loc="60"/>
               </cit>. The axes of difference within intersectionality are dynamic and do not
               operate in predictable ways; rather, they are fluid and constructed, the power
               valances in each in flux. Intersectionality is not a prescriptive method because
               there isn’t one particular way of <q>doing</q> intersectionality. Rather,
               intersectional digital humanities asks us to begin with the specificities of a data
               set, identify the layers of difference that intersect within it, and use that
               knowledge as a basis for project design. </p>
            <p>The fluidity of intersectionality is a natural fit for the flexibility that digital
               humanities connotes. In its recent popularity, Patrik Svensson suggests, digital
               humanities has seen <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2009">a higher degree of heterogeneity and
                     inclusion of other epistemic traditions</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2009"/>
               </cit>. He positions such growth in broad ways, suggesting we might view information
               technology as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2010">a tool, an object of study, an
                     exploratory laboratory, an expressive medium, and an activist venue</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>
               </cit>. Svensson proposes that a <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2013"
                  >big-tent digital humanities</quote> would encompass this proliferation of modes
                  <ptr target="#svensson2013"/>. As an alternative to the tent, however, Svensson
               proposes a model of digital humanities that is a <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#svensson2013">meeting place, innovation hub, and trading zone</quote>
               to emphasize <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2013">commitment to interdisciplinary work
                     and deep collaboration</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2013"/>
               </cit>. The affordance of such a model is a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2013">fractioned (not homogeneous)
                     collaborative (not coerced) trading zone and a meeting space that supports
                     deeply collaborative work, individual expression, unexpected connections, and
                     synergetic power</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2013"/>
               </cit>. To appreciate such benefits, Svensson argues, the digital humanities <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2013">needs to support and allow multiple
                     modes of engagement between the humanities and the digital...[to] maximize
                     points of interaction, tackle large research and methodology challenges, and
                     facilitate deep integration between thinking and making</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2013"/>
               </cit>. These are the spaces where complex negotiations between theory and method are
               made possible. They require <soCalled>difficult thinking,</soCalled> which Mark
               Sample defines as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#sample2014">imagining the world from multiple
                     perspectives and wrestling with conflicting evidence about the world</quote>
                  <ptr target="#sample2014"/>
               </cit>. As Sample proposes, difficult thinking does not seek easy reconcilement for
               conflicting ideas but <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#sample2014">faces these ambiguities head-on and even
                     preserves them</quote>
                  <ptr target="#sample2014"/>
               </cit>. Intersectionality, in its emphasis on anti-essentialism and possibilities of
               accounting for competing axes of difference in multiple permutations, makes difficult
               thinking possible and perhaps even brings Svensson’s vision of digital humanities to
               fruition. </p>
            <p>Working at the intersections of digital humanities and intersectionality, we can
               intervene in the false dichotomy between digital humanities and cultural critique.
               For, as Bianco reminds, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bianco2013">We are not required to choose between
                     the philosophical, critical, cultural, and computational; we <emph>are</emph>
                     required to integrate and to experiment</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bianco2013"/>
               </cit>. Existing digital humanities projects provide examples of how, in small and
               large ways, theory and method can be combined to address recurring questions of the
               role of race, class, gender, ability, sexuality, nationality, and other categories of
               difference within the field. These phenomena subtend the development and production
               of digital humanities projects but they may not be evident. Therefore, it is
               incumbent on us, as digital humanities practitioners, to make them legible, to move
               them beyond the margins. To suggest we embrace intersectionality as a critical
               approach for the digital humanities is not to impose a static, single model of
               analysis. Rather, it opens space to engage with the variety of ways difference
               informs our work. There is no single way of being <soCalled>intersectional</soCalled>
               – instead, intersectionality privileges exploration and innovation in feminist
               praxis. And aren’t exploration and innovation at the very heart of digital
               humanities?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>I gratefully acknowledge the advice of Jacqueline Wernimont and three anonymous
                  <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> reviewers whose extensive, generous comments were
               indispensable to this article. I am also grateful for the valuable feedback on parts
               of this article presented at the Harriet Tubman Institute at York University and the
               Kelly Writers House at the University of Pennsylvania. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Argamon 2009" xml:id="argamon2009"> Argamon, S., Cooney, C., Horton, R.,
               Olsen, M., Stein, S., Voyer, R. <title rend="quotes">Gender, Race, and Nationality in
                  Black Drama, 1950-2006: Mining Differences in Language Use in Authors and Their
                  Characters,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 3.2 (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Aslinger 2013" xml:id="aslinger2013"> Aslinger, B. and Huntemann, N. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Media Studies Futures,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Media Culture, &amp; Society</title> 35.1 (2013): 9-12.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bailey 2011" xml:id="bailey2011"> Bailey, M. <title rend="quotes">All the
                  Digital Humanists Are White, All the Nerds Are Men, But Some of Us Are
                  Brave,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Bauer 2011" xml:id="bauer2011">Bauer, J. <title rend="quotes">Who You
                  Calling Untheoretical,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Bianco 2013" xml:id="bianco2013"> Bianco, J.S. <title rend="quotes">This
                  Digital Humanities Which Is Not One.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities,</title> University of Minnesota
               Press, Minneapolis (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Carastathis 2014" xml:id="carastathis2014"> Carastathis, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Reinvigorating Intersectionality as Provisional Concept.</title> In
               N. Goswami, M. M. O’Donovan, and L. Yount (eds), <title rend="italic">Why Race and
                  Gender Still Matter: An Intersectional Approach,</title> Pickering &amp; Chatto
               Publishers, London (2014), pp. 59-70.</bibl>
            <bibl label="CBW" xml:id="cbw"> Collective Biographies of Women. <title rend="quotes"
                  >About.</title>
               <ref target="http://womensbios.lib.virginia.edu/about"
                  >http://womensbios.lib.virginia.edu/about</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="CDA" xml:id="cda"> The 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-Century Concord
               Digital Archive. <title rend="quotes">Project Overview.</title>
               <ref target="http://digitalconcord.tamu.edu/content/project-overview"
                  >http://digitalconcord.tamu.edu/content/project-overview</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cecire 2011" xml:id="cecire2011">Cecire, Natalia. <title rend="quotes">When
                  Digital Humanities Was in Vogue,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011)</bibl>
            <bibl label="Christian 1987" xml:id="christian1987"> Christian, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Race for Theory,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cultural Critique</title> 6 (1987): 51-63.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Chun 2001" xml:id="chun2001"> Chun, W. <title rend="quotes">Scenes of
                  Empowerment: Virtual Racial Diversity and Digital Divides,</title>
               <title rend="italic">New Formations</title> 45 (2001): 169-188.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Chun 2005" xml:id="chun2005">Chun, W. <title rend="italic">Control and
                  Freedom: Power and Paranoia in the Age of Fiber Optics</title>, MIT Press,
               Cambridge, MA (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cong-Huyen 2013" xml:id="conghuyen2013"> Cong-Huyen, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Thinking Through Race (Gender, Class, &amp; Nation) in the Digital
                  Humanities: The #transformDH Example.</title>
               <ref
                  target="https://prezi.com/ysz-t5mc7hyu/thinking-of-race-gender-class-nation-in-dh/"
                  >https://prezi.com/ysz-t5mc7hyu/thinking-of-race-gender-class-nation-in-dh/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Crenshaw 1991" xml:id="crenshaw1991"> Crenshaw, K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence Against
                  Women of Color,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Stanford Law Review</title> 43 (1991): 1241-1299. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Crenshaw 2014" xml:id="crenshaw2014"> Crenshaw, K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Justice Rising: Moving Intersectionally in the Age of Post-Everything.</title>
               London School of Economics. <ref
                  target="http://www.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/videoAndAudio/channels/publicLecturesAndEvents/player.aspx?id=2360"
                  >http://www.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/videoAndAudio/channels/publicLecturesAndEvents/player.aspx?id=2360</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Davis 2008" xml:id="davis2008"> Davis, K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Intersectionality as Buzzword,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Feminist Theory</title> 9.1 (2008): 67-85.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Digital Diversity 2015" xml:id="digitaldiversity2015"> Digital Diversity
               2015. <title rend="quotes">CFP.</title>
               <ref target="http://digitaldiversity2015.org/cfp/"
                  >http://digitaldiversity2015.org/cfp/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Earhart 2013" xml:id="earhart2013"> Earhart, A. <title rend="quotes">Can
                  Information Be Unfettered? Race and the New Digital Humanities Canon.</title> In
               M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>,
               University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ettarh 2013" xml:id="ettarh2013"> Ettarh, F. M. <title rend="quotes">Black
                  OR Queer? Life at the Intersection.</title> Hack Library School. <ref
                  target="https://hacklibschool.wordpress.com/2013/11/19/black-or-queer-life-at-the-intersection/#more-8032"
                  >https://hacklibschool.wordpress.com/2013/11/19/black-or-queer-life-at-the-intersection/#more-8032</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="EWWRP" xml:id="ewwrp"> Emory Women Writers Resource Project. <title
                  rend="quotes">About.</title>
               <ref target="http://womenwriters.library.emory.edu/about.php"
                  >http://womenwriters.library.emory.edu/about.php</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Everett 2002" xml:id="everett2002"> Everett, A. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Revolution Will Be Digitized: Afrocentricity and the Digital Public
                  Sphere,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Social Text</title> 20.2 (2002): 125-146.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Everett 2009" xml:id="everett2009"> Everett, A. <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital Diaspora: A Race for Cyberspace.</title> SUNY Press, Albany (2009). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Everett 2014" xml:id="everett2014"> Everett, A. Champlin, A. and
               Vanderhoef, J. <title rend="quotes">Race, Space, and Digital Games: An Interview with
                  Anna Everett.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Media Fields Journal</title> 8 (2014). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Gajjala 2008" xml:id="gajjala2008">Gajjala, R., Blair, K. and Tulley, C.
               (eds.). <title rend="italic">Webbing Cyberfeminist Practice: Communities, Pedagogies,
                  and Social Action.</title> Hampton Press, New York (2008). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Gajjala 2012" xml:id="gajjala2012">Gajjala, R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Cyberculture and the Subaltern</title>. Lexington Books, Lanham, MD
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gold 2013" xml:id="gold2013"> Gold, M. K. <title rend="quotes">The Digital
                  Humanities Moment.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                  Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Harding 1998" xml:id="harding1998">Harding, S. <title rend="italic">Is
                  Science Multicultural?: Postcolonialisms, Feminisms, and Epistemologies</title>.
               Indiana University Press, Bloomington, IN (1998).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Harding 2008" xml:id="harding2008">Harding, S. <title rend="italic">Science
                  from Below: Feminisms, Postcolonialisms, and Modernities</title>. Duke University
               Press, Durham, NC (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hall 1999" xml:id="hall1999"> Hall, K. <title rend="quotes">Women and
                  Race.</title> The Women Writers Project. <ref
                  target="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/context/#rEss.race.xml"
                  >http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/context/#rEss.race.xml</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Johnson 2015" xml:id="johnson2015"> Johnson, J. M. Diaspora Hypertext, the
               Blog. <ref target="http://diasporahypertext.com/"
               >http://diasporahypertext.com/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Jones 2013" xml:id="jones2013">Jones, S. <title rend="italic">The Emergence
                  of the Digital Humanities</title>. Routledge, New York (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Keeling 2014" xml:id="keeling2014"> Keeling, K. <title rend="quotes">Queer
                  OS,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> 53.2 (2014): 152-7.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kimball 1990" xml:id="kimball1990"> Kimball, R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Tenured Radicals: How Politics Has Corrupted our Higher Education</title>. Ivan
               R. Dee, Chicago (1990).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirsch 2014" xml:id="kirsch2014"> Kirsch, A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Technology is Taking Over English Departments: The False Promise of the Digital
                  Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The New Republic</title>, 2 May 2014. <ref
                  target="http://www.newrepublic.com/article/117428/limits-digital-humanities-adam-kirsch"
                  >http://www.newrepublic.com/article/117428/limits-digital-humanities-adam-kirsch</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2014" xml:id="kirschenbaum2014">Kirschenbaum, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">What is <soCalled>Digital Humanities,</soCalled> and Why Are They
                  Saying Such Terrible Things About It?</title>
               <title rend="italic">differences</title> 25.1 (2014): 46-63.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lasmana 2014" xml:id="lasmana2014"> Lasmana, V. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Critical Code Studies Working Group 2014: Week 2 Highlights.</title> Critical
               Code Studies Working Group 2014. <ref target="http://haccslab.com/?p=85"
                  >http://haccslab.com/?p=85</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lothian 2013" xml:id="lothian2013"> Lothian, A. and Phillips, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities Mean Transformative Critique?</title>
               <title rend="italic">e-Media Studies</title> 3.1 (2013). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Liu 2013" xml:id="liu2013"> Liu, A. <title rend="quotes">Where Is Cultural
                  Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota
               Press, Minneapolis (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="McIntosh 1990" xml:id="mcintosh1990"> McIntosh, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Independent School</title> (1990): 31-36. </bibl>
            <bibl label="McPherson 2013" xml:id="mcpherson2013"> McPherson, T. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? or Thinking the Histories of Race and
                  Computation.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                  Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nakamura 2002" xml:id="nakamura2002"> Nakamura, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet</title>. Routledge, New
               York (2002). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Nakamura 2007" xml:id="nakamura2007"> Nakamura, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Digitizing Race: Visual Cultures of the Internet</title>. University of Minnesota
               Press, Minneapolis (2007). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Nakamura 2012" xml:id="nakamura2012">Nakamura, L and Chow-White, P. (eds).
                  <title rend="italic">Race After the Internet.</title> Routledge, New York
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nayar 2010" xml:id="nayar2010"> Nayar, P. <title rend="italic">An
                  Introduction to New Media and Cybercultures</title>. John C. Wiley and Sons,
               Malden, MA (2010).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nelson 2001" xml:id="nelson2001"> Nelson, A. and Tu, T. L. N. <title
                  rend="italic">Technicolor: Race, Technology, and Everday Life</title>. NYU Press,
               New York (2001). </bibl>
            <bibl label="NINES" xml:id="nines"> NINES: Nineteenth-century Scholarship Online. <title
                  rend="quotes">Collex.</title>
               <ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/software/collex/"
                  >http://www.nines.org/about/software/collex/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie 2012" xml:id="nowviskie2012"> Nowviskie, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Don’t Circle the Wagons.</title> Bethany Nowviskie. <ref
                  target="http://nowviskie.org/2012/dont-circle-the-wagons/"
                  >http://nowviskie.org/2012/dont-circle-the-wagons/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie 2013" xml:id="nowviskie2013"> Nowviskie, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Eternal September of the Digital Humanities.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota
               Press, Minneapolis (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie 2014" xml:id="nowviskie2014">Nowviskie, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >On the Origins of <soCalled>Hack</soCalled> and
                  <soCalled>Yack,</soCalled></title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 3.2 (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ockerbloom 2012" xml:id="ockerbloom2012"> Ockerbloom, M. M. A Celebration
               of Women Writers. <ref target="http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/"
                  >http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Orlando" xml:id="orlando"> The Orlando Project. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Literary History–With a Difference.</title>
               <ref
                  target="http://orlando.cambridge.org/public/svDocumentation?formname=t&amp;d_id=LITERARYHISTORYWITHADIFFERENCE"
                  >http://orlando.cambridge.org/public/svDocumentation?formname=t&amp;d_id=LITERARYHISTORYWITHADIFFERENCE</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Pasanek" xml:id="pasanek"> Pasanek, B. <title rend="quotes">About.</title>
               The Mind Is a Metaphor. <ref target="http://metaphors.iath.virginia.edu/about"
                  >http://metaphors.iath.virginia.edu/about</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Pannapacker 2009" xml:id="pannapacker2009"> Pannapacker, W. <title
                  rend="quotes">The MLA and the Digital Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 28 December 2009.
                  <ref target="http://chronicle.com/blogPost/The-MLAthe-Digital/19468/"
                  >http://chronicle.com/blogPost/The-MLAthe-Digital/19468/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Potter 2010" xml:id="potter2013"> Potter, C. B. <title rend="quotes">Thou
                  Shalt Commit: The Internet, New Media, and the Future of Women’s History,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Women’s History</title> 25.4 (2013): 350-362.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Posner 2012" xml:id="posner2012"> Posner, M. K. <title rend="quotes">Some
                  Things to Think About Before You Exhort Everyone to Code.</title> Miriam Posner’s
               Blog. <ref
                  target="http://miriamposner.com/blog/some-things-to-think-about-before-you-exhort-everyone-to-code/"
                  >http://miriamposner.com/blog/some-things-to-think-about-before-you-exhort-everyone-to-code/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2011" xml:id="ramsay2011">Ramsay, S. <title rend="quotes">Who’s In
                  and Who’s Out.</title> Stephen Ramsay. <ref
                  target="http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out/"
                  >http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Rigoni 2012" xml:id="rigoni2012"> Rigoni, I. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Intersectionality and Mediated Cultural Production in a Globalized Post-Colonial
                  World,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title> 35.5 (2012): p.
               834-849.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Risam 2013" xml:id="risam2013"> Risam, R. and Koh, A. Postcolonial Digital
               Humanities. <ref target="http://dhpoco.org">http://dhpoco.org</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Rockwell 2011" xml:id="rockwell2011"> Rockwell, G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Inclusion in the Digital Humanities.</title> philosophi.ca. <ref
                  target="http://www.philosophi.ca/pmwiki.php/Main/InclusionInTheDigitalHumanities"
                  >http://www.philosophi.ca/pmwiki.php/Main/InclusionInTheDigitalHumanities</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Saklofske 2014" xml:id="saklofske2014"> Saklofske, J., Levesque, S., Bath,
               J., Brown, S., Clement, T., Posner, M., Porter, D., Sinatra, M., and Sinclair, S.
                  <title rend="quotes">Joint ACH and Canadian DH Conference 2015.</title> The
               Association for Computers and the Humanities. <ref
                  target="http://ach.org/2014/10/20/joint-ach-canadian-dh-conference-2015/"
                  >http://ach.org/2014/10/20/joint-ach-canadian-dh-conference-2015/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sample 2014" xml:id="sample2014"> Sample, M. <title rend="quotes">Difficult
                  Thinking About the Digital Humanities.</title> Sample Reality. <ref
                  target="http://www.samplereality.com/2014/05/12/difficult-thinking-about-the-digital-humanities/"
                  >http://www.samplereality.com/2014/05/12/difficult-thinking-about-the-digital-humanities/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Scheinfeldt 2010a" xml:id="scheinfeldt2010a"> Scheinfeldt, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Where’s the Beef?</title> Found History. <ref
                  target="http://foundhistory.org/digital-humanities/wheres-the-beef-does-digital-humanities-have-to-answer-questions/"
                  >http://foundhistory.org/digital-humanities/wheres-the-beef-does-digital-humanities-have-to-answer-questions/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Scheinfeldt 2010b" xml:id="scheinfeldt2010b">Scheinfeldt, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Why Digital Humanities Is <soCalled>Nice.</soCalled></title> Found
               History. <ref
                  target="http://foundhistory.org/2010/05/why-digital-humanities-is-nice/"
                  >http://foundhistory.org/2010/05/why-digital-humanities-is-nice/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Schmidt 2011" xml:id="schmidt2011">Schmidt, B. <title rend="quotes">Theory
                  First,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Smith 2007" xml:id="smith2007"> Smith, M. N. <title rend="quotes">The Human
                  Touch Software of the Highest Order: Revisiting Editing as Interpretation,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Textual Cultures</title> 2.1 (2007): 1-15.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Smith 2014" xml:id="smith2014"> Smith, M. N. <title rend="quotes">Frozen
                  Social Relations and Time for a Thaw: Visibility, Exclusions, and Considerations
                  for Postcolonial Digital Archives,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</title> 19.3 (2014):
               403-410.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Spiro 2013" xml:id="spiro2013"> Spiro, L. <title rend="quotes">This Is Why
                  We Fight: Defining the Values of the Digital Humanities.</title> In M. K. Gold
               (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of
               Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Svensson 2009" xml:id="svensson2009"> Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Humanities Computing as Digital Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 3.3 (2009). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Svensson 2010" xml:id="svensson2010"> Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Landscape of Digital Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 4.1 (2010). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Svensson 2013" xml:id="svensson2013"> Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Beyond the Big Tent.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in
                  the Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Svensson 2012" xml:id="svensson2012"> Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Envisioning the Digital Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 6.1 (2012). </bibl>
            <bibl label="Tal 1996" xml:id="tal1996"> Tal, K. <title rend="quotes">Life Behind the
                  Screen,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 4.10 (1996): 134, 136.</bibl>
            <bibl label="transformDH 2012" xml:id="transformdh2012"> #transformDH. <title
                  rend="quotes">About #transformDH.</title>
               <ref target="http://originaltransformdh.tumblr.com/about"
                  >http://originaltransformdh.tumblr.com/about</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Turkel 2010" xml:id="turkel2010"> Turkel, W. J. and Elliott, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Making and Playing With Models: Using Rapid Prototyping to Explore
                  the History and Technology of Stage Magic.</title> Playing With History. <ref
                  target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/d/dh/12544152.0001.001/1:6/--pastplay-teaching-and-learning-history-with-technology?g=dculture;rgn=div1;view=fulltext;xc=1"
                  >http://quod.lib.umich.edu/d/dh/12544152.0001.001/1:6/--pastplay-teaching-and-learning-history-with-technology?g=dculture;rgn=div1;view=fulltext;xc=1</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wernimont 2013" xml:id="wernimont2013"> Wernimont, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary
                  Archives,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7.1 (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="WWP" xml:id="wwp"> The Women Writers Project. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Exhibits.</title>
               <ref target="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/research/publications/exhibits/"
                  >http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/research/publications/exhibits/</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
