<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization
               and Narrative Form in Video Games</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Cody <dhq:family>Mejeur</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University at
                  Buffalo, SUNY</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cmejeur@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cody Mejeur is Visiting Assistant Professor of Game Studies at University at
                     Buffalo, SUNY. Their work uses games to theorize narrative as an embodied and
                     playful process that constructs how we understand ourselves and our realities.
                     They have published on games pedagogy, gender and queerness in games, and the
                     narrative construction of reality. They currently work with the LGBTQ Video
                     Game Archive on preserving and visualizing LGBTQ representation. They are
                     editor at One Shot: A Journal of Critical Games &amp; Play, and serve as
                     Diversity Officer for the Digital Games Research Association. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000486</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-07-24" who="jmurel">Finished encoding</change>
         <change when="2020-07-23" who="jmurel">Created file and began encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Studies of video game narrative have long acknowledged that narrative in games is
               defined by interactivity — the player’s ability to make different choices and produce
               various story endings. Recent ludonarrative scholarship on games and interactive
               storytelling has started to account for what this interactivity means for narrative
               form, yet it remains difficult to assess how variable narrative is in different
               games, or how different players’ experiences with the same game can be. This article
               uses ImagePlot, software for visualizing large collections of images, to visualize
               playthroughs of a game and compare them. In doing so, it proposes a new method for
               analyzing narrative in games and digital media, and argues that games reveal how
               narrative form is shifting, emergent, and playful. By focusing on where and how
               narrative difference emerges, we can better understand how narrative constructs our
               current realities, and how it might contribute to different ones in the future. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Explores the use of ImagePlot for analyzing video game narratives</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction<note>This article refers to a collection of visualizations of video
                  game playthroughs. In addition to the images included in the article and <ref
                     target="#appendix01">Table of Figure</ref>s, you can view and download the full
                  collection here: <ref target="http://bit.ly/PwPImages"
                     >http://bit.ly/PwPImages</ref></note></head>
            <p>It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games
               media had widely publicized in the past couple months.<note>
                  <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> stands for Playable Teaser. It was supposed to
                  be the teaser for the next game in the Silent Hill series, <title rend="italic"
                     >Silent Hills</title>, but was scrapped by Konami in 2015. The game was created
                  by Kojima Productions under the pseudonym 7780s Studio, and published by
                  Konami.</note> I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision —
               and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around
               at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio,
               and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.
               I reached the end of the hallway eventually and opened the door there to find myself
               in the exact same hallway. This happened each time I opened that door, and each time
               I encountered copies of the hallway with changes ranging from the small (an object in
               a different place) to the major (suddenly the entire hallway was red with flashing
               and spinning lights). Finally, I got stuck: I seemed to be encountering the same
               version of the hallway over and over, and nothing seemed to change. I looked up
               guides and walkthroughs for the game to figure out what I was missing and learned
               that I needed to do <emph>something</emph> to get the in-game phone to ring, though
               no one seemed to know what that something was. So I started trying everything I
               could: interacting with every item, walking down the hallway backwards, and turning
               the radio on and off countless times. I even tried whispering into the PlayStation 4
               microphone, per a Reddit suggestion, but still the phone didn’t ring. I’m still not
               sure what I did to trigger the phone-ringing event––perhaps the game just pitied me
               for taking so long to figure it out.</p>
            <p> This brief narration of my experience with <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> is an
               illustration of a larger point, namely that players have different experiences and
               thus different stories in the games they play. On the one hand, my story is unique.
               No one else has had my exact experience of playing <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>
               in my apartment, navigating <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>’s hallway, encountering
               the game’s events (some randomly generated), or getting stuck where I did. On the
               other hand, my story is quite common in that all players of <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> have their own versions of it. While we all encountered different
               parts of the game at different times and in different ways, there are still many
               images, objects, events, and feelings that we all experienced sooner or later. This
               shared-but-varied phenomenon in game narrative is the result of player interaction
               with the game, and is both afforded and limited by what the game system (hardware,
               software, interfaces, etc.) and the players themselves make possible. Games achieve a
               sense of individuality through interaction by accommodating (intentionally or
               otherwise) a wide variety of play styles and allowing players to make different
               decisions in order to keep the game interesting <ptr target="#atkins2007" loc="5"/>.
               Matthew Miller, one of the creators of the MMORPG <title rend="italic">City of
                  Heroes</title>, describes this dilemma: <quote rend="inline">We wanted players to
                  have unique experiences as they played through the game, so that when a group of
                  players got together, they could talk about [their exploits], and it wouldn’t be
                  identical to everyone else in the room</quote>
               <ptr target="#miller2009" loc="125"/>. Play demands the freedom and potential for
               difference, and as players navigate games they create their own unique (and yet
               similar) narratives.</p>
            <p> Of course game studies scholars have long noted that the player’s ability to affect
               a narrative through gameplay is the defining characteristic of game narratives.<note>
                  See especially Marie-Laure Ryan’s work with game narrative <ptr target="#ryan2014"
                  />. See also Eric Zimmerman’s commentary on the concepts in <ref
                     target="#zimmerman2006" loc="154">Zimmerman (2006), 154</ref>. For the most
                  prominent discussions of player interactivity and narrative, see <ref
                     target="#murray2017">Murray (2017)</ref> and <ref target="#aarseth1997">Aarseth
                     (1997)</ref>.</note> In this framework, game developers and theorists such as
               Chris Crawford have often discussed interactivity as something of a problem for game
               narrative and experience, even going so far as to say that there is an <quote
                  rend="inline">apparent incompatibility between plot and interactivity</quote>
               <ptr target="#crawford2013" loc="51"/>. The issue that Crawford and others have
               identified is that narratives need to have structure and coherence on some level,
               whereas interactivity and play are more about the flowing emergence of possibilities
               that often buck against the limitations of narrative’s structure. This tension, while
               not insurmountable, is why we seem to be less likely or willing to call a sequence of
               representations a narrative the more variable that sequence is. Thus when players
               discussing the same game relate drastically different experiences with the same
               content, such as puzzles and bosses solved or beaten differently; different paths
               taken or choices made; or even entirely different characters and plots, we’re less
               likely to call that content narrative. The reality of shifting and unstable content
               poses a difficulty for games scholars of all sorts (players are always doing
               unexpected things), but is particularly challenging for those attempting to locate
               central themes, meanings, and stories in a given game and play experience. How does
               one begin to account for all of these possibilities for variation? Or, to put it
               another way, how does one stabilize a game’s narrative enough to begin to make claims
               about it, without ignoring the emergent qualities of that narrative?</p>
            <p> In response to these difficulties and questions, a number of scholars have proposed
               ludonarrative as a concept that unites storytelling with the emergent qualities of
               play. As Tison Pugh explains, ludonarrative is a <quote rend="inline">hybrid
                  hermeneutic</quote> that looks at the shared structures of games and narratives,
               including the intersections between them in video games and other media <ptr
                  target="#pugh2019" loc="1"/>. The experience of narrative in video games is one
               where <quote rend="inline">you, the player (or reader, one could say), are suddenly
                  thrown into someone else’s story and are expected to continue the tale,</quote>
               and this experience reveals <quote rend="inline">the notion of the text as being
                  informed by the process of play and as being characterised by multiplicity</quote>
               <ptr target="#mukherjee2015" loc="1, 9"/>. In other words, video games demonstrate
               how narrative can be playful, variable, and divergent, and this can be true of other
               narrative texts such as novels, films, or comics that invite their readers or viewers
               to form their own interpretations and experiences. Within video games, ludonarrative
               approaches seek to understand the <quote rend="inline">whole</quote> of a game by
               viewing gameplay, story, and the player in their many relationships with each other,
               rather than viewing narrative and play as inherently opposed, conflicting elements as
               previous scholarship often did <ptr target="#toh2017" loc="2"/>. </p>
            <p>While ludonarrative provides a framework for understanding the interrelated natures
               of narrative and play, there remain many questions about what forms ludonarrative can
               (or could) take and how players use them. Most scholars working with game narrative,
               including ludonarrative ones, have generalized the issue of divergent player
               experience by pointing to the possibilities for it, and perhaps exploring a few of
               those major possibilities in a given genre or game. At best, some scholars have
               utilized social scientific methods for player interviews, forums research, and
               community studies to understand how different players engage with and interpret a
                  game.<note>The list of such scholars is extensive, and spans disciplines including
                  Anthropology and Communications. Examples include Bonnie Nardi, Tom Boellstorff,
                  and Adrienne Shaw, to name only a prominent few.</note> These studies are
               extremely valuable in how they account for the player’s role in game narrative and
               experience, but they are also limited by sample sizes and what players remember or
               are consciously aware of in their gameplay. Such issues are largely unavoidable, and
               are not a significant detriment to the studies. However we have yet to develop a
               method that allows for the assessment of moment-to-moment experiences of a game and
               its story, including both what is common to different player’s playthroughs and what
               is different. In other words, while ludonarrative helps account for how narrative is
               interactive and variable in games and other media, we have only begun to assess the
               types and amounts of variance that are possible in particular game genres and
               individual games. One way to start doing this is to examine recordings of different
               players’ playthroughs of the same games, such as Let’s Play videos on YouTube and
               other streaming services. As Roth et al. note, these videos are <quote rend="inline"
                  >qualitative samples for the evaluation of the interactive narrative user
                  experience</quote> that have hereto been ignored in game narrative scholarship
                  <ptr target="#roth2018" loc="12"/>.</p>

            <p> This article provides a new method for using video recordings of gameplay to study
               similarity, difference, and variation in narrative caused by player interaction. It
               does so utilizing emerging digital humanities tools for distance visualization of
               visual media, such as the ImagePlot macro for ImageJ. ImagePlot is software that
               takes a collection of images and plots those images on a basic graph where the x and
               y axes correspond to different, quantifiable characteristics of the images. I will
               explain this process and its affordances and limitations in more depth shortly, but
               for now note that ImagePlot allows for the analysis of many types of visual media,
               including paintings, photographs, film, and of course video games. For the purpose of
               visualizing narrative variation in games, ImagePlot allows one to take a video
               recording of gameplay, extract the images from it, and plot those on a graph so an
               entire playthrough of a game is visible in one image (Figure 1). This distance
               visualization allows for storing, representing, and analyzing player experiences on a
               scale previously impossible: one can view a player’s entire playthrough of a game in
               one image, and then compare that playthrough with tens or hundreds of other
               playthroughs at a time. Further, rather than relying on player experience abstracted
               from actual play or reported from memory afterward, this distance visualization
               relies on video recording of play as it happened. By plotting the images extracted
               from the playthroughs of games by different players, one can begin to trace how
               variable a given game’s play experiences can be. A comparison of playthrough
               imageplots reveals the exact what and when of similarities or differences between a
               large number of player experiences with the same game. The imageplots also connect
               with exact measures of time and image qualities (such as brightness, hue, or even
               objects in the images), allowing the assessment of the magnitude of difference in a
               game, and providing some answers as to just how variable the variability of a game’s
               ludonarrative is. This article will focus specifically on variance in time (at what
               point players encounter something, and how long it takes them to play) and sign (what
               players encounter, the content of the images in the imageplot).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>PT1, an imageplot of one playthrough of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> Red
                  boxes added to highlight particular sections of the playthrough.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p> Developing these methods and answering the question of how variable a game’s
               ludonarrative is presents an opportunity to reconsider narrative form. Despite
               attempts to expand narrative in recent decades, such as the theories that space
               itself is narrative or that human perception of reality is dependent on narrative,
               the concept of narrative has remained limited to being a linear or at best
               multilinear form.<note>For recent work on the narrative construction of space, see
                     <ref target="#ryan2016">Ryan (2016)</ref>. The most prominent work on the
                  narrative construction of reality comes from <ref target="#bruner1991">Bruner
                     (1991)</ref>. </note> Even scholars of cognitive narrative processes such as
               David Herman and Marie-Laure Ryan, whose theories of narrative emphasize how it
               generates <quote rend="inline">possible worlds</quote> with many potential outcomes
               (similar to the multiplicities of ludonarrative), have yet to account for how much
               difference and variation is possible in narrative experience, interpretation, and
               construction <ptr target="#herman2004"/>. It has remained difficult to assess just
               how much is possible in making possible worlds, or how far a narrative can change or
               stretch before it becomes either another narrative entirely or something
               unrecognizable as narrative. Yet if we can build on these theories of interactivity
               and possible difference by focusing more on specific lived experiences and instances
               of variation, we can arrive at an understanding of narrative form that is less
               focused on linear or multilinear outcomes and more attentive to the procedural and
               emergent construction of narrative similarities and differences. Such a ludonarrative
               understanding of narrative would emphasize the relationality of signs and open up
               room for their change and motion, rather than seeking to fix them in set times,
               places, and interpretations.<note>I’m referring to signs here in terms of the visual
                  semiotics theorized by film and comics scholars, such as <ref target="#metz1991"
                     >Metz (1991)</ref> and <ref target="#cohn2013">Cohn (2013)</ref>.</note> Shira
               Chess points toward this potential in her theorization of video game narratives as
               queer narratives that forego normative teleological structures of climax; instead
               games present narratives that are non-reproductive and continuous <ptr
                  target="#chess2016" loc="84"/>. Imageplots further the conception of narrative as
               an ongoing, shifting, and possibly queer process by visualizing narrative as it
               unfolds and providing a means of assessing difference and continuity throughout the
               playing of a game. </p>
            <p> In pushing us to consider narrative as an active and changeable form that requires
               play and emergence, the imageplots and the distance visualization they provide
               contribute a method to the renewed discourse on forms, perhaps best captured in
               Caroline Levine’s <title rend="italic">Forms</title>. Levine defines form as <quote
                  rend="inline">all shapes and configurations, all ordering principles, all patterns
                  of repetition and difference,</quote> and goes on to say that narrative is the
               form that best captures how different forms <quote rend="inline">collide</quote>:
                  <quote rend="inline">the strange encounter between two or more forms that
                  sometimes reroutes intention and ideology</quote>
               <ptr target="#levine2015" loc="3, 20"/>. The collisions in forms that Levine
               identifies are observable in the play of similarities and differences in player
               experiences that are captured in imageplots. As players encounter content in a game,
               their actions affect the form of that content — its duration, its arrangement, and
               its relation to other forms in the game. Imageplots capture the effects of this
               interactivity in the form of visual signs and suggest that narrative in games is best
               understood as a particular sequence or arrangement of moving and colliding signs. The
               signs that are common to all playthroughs of a game can be taken together as the
               primary or central narrative of the game: they are the core experience that causes
               the game to cohere as one game, one system of rules and possibilities for players to
               play with. The signs that are different from playthrough to playthrough indicate the
               places and parts of the game where the player can deviate from the central narrative
               and create their own unique experience of it. Taken together, the differences reveal
               how variable that narrative is, or how much play there is to it: more differences
               mean greater opportunity for play and variation, and fewer differences mean less.</p>
            <p> The overarching goal of the distance analysis method proposed here is to locate
               patterns in the visual signs between playthroughs, and to thereby identify both the
               common and different meanings, experiences, and possibilities in a game. In terms of
               ludonarrative, this means being able to establish a central narrative to a game that
               is not limited to the game’s scripted elements, but can also accommodate player input
               and individual experience. This method can provide new insights on how players
               influence game narrative, and what degree of emergence comes with that influence.
               Furthermore, such a study of game narrative can contribute to moving game studies and
               narrative theory beyond accounting for interactivity and variation in abstraction,
               and gain a more solid grasp of narrative as a form that is flexible, emergent, and
               yet limited, always in a playful relationship with its audience. By doing so, we can
               better perceive the possibilities for difference that exist in current games, and how
               we might play within games and other visual media in order to produce new and
               transformative narratives. If we can see narrative forms in a given text, then we can
               better understand how those forms operate, how we can change them, and what we can
               imagine through them.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Imageplots as Visual Archives</head>
            <p> This opportunity to rethink visual narrative form is made possible by ImagePlot, a
               macro for the software ImageJ, which is usually used for the analysis of large
               quantities of images (such as brain scans) in medical science. ImageJ is developed
               and updated by the National Institutes of Health, and the software allows for a
               variety of plugins and macros for different types of image analysis. ImagePlot is one
               such macro, and was created by a team led by Lev Manovich as part of the Software
               Studies Initiative.<note>The Software Studies Initiative is a research lab with
                  locations at The Graduate Center at CUNY and UCSD. According to their website they
                  work on the analysis of <q>big cultural datasets,</q> including data
                  visualization. For more information, see <ref
                     target="http://lab.softwarestudies.com">http://lab.softwarestudies.com</ref>.
               </note> ImagePlot takes a collection of images and plots it on a graph according to
               preset data points. For example, the imageplots included here are plotted with a
               x-axis of time, and a randomly generated y-axis (Figure 2).<note>The randomly
                  generated y-axis ensures that the images do not stack up on top of each other in
                  one line at the bottom of the graph, making it easier to see all of the images
                  from a particular moment in a video.</note> In effect, this means that the
               imageplots represent the temporal progression of images in the collection, or in
               other words they present the images in the order that they appear in the video. The
               progression from the left to the right side of the graph mirrors the progression of
               the video, with the left side of the imageplot being the beginning of the video and
               the right side its end, and each column on the graph contains images from the same
               moment in the video. This mapping of images onto a graph provides a distance
               visualization of a video, allowing one to change the scale of the data and see all of
               the video at once, instead of only seeing individual parts at a time. In this sense,
               ImagePlot is similar to many other digital humanities tools (such as those used for
               network analysis, topic modeling, etc.) that help us zoom out from a particular
               moment in a text or corpus and see larger trends across many moments and texts.
               ImagePlot allows us to do the same for visual media, and this method is only one of
               its many potential applications in the analysis of photos, paintings, film, and video
               games.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>PT2, an imageplot of another playthrough of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>
                  by a different player. Red boxes added to highlight game sections common to all
                  playthroughs.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p> This project uses ImagePlot to visualize entire playthroughs of video games, such as
                  <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>, the game I narrated earlier. The process does
               not require any coding knowledge, but rather involves using a series of files in
               conjunction with ImageJ. In order to run the ImagePlot macro, one first needs a
               collection of images and an associated file or spreadsheet with the filenames of the
               images and any other necessary data, such as a value for hue or saturation in the
               images. To generate these, a number of video files were downloaded from YouTube,
               where each video was a complete playthrough of a game recorded and posted online.
               Next, images were extracted from each of the videos, and organized in separate
               folders. A data spreadsheet for each video was populated with its corresponding image
               filenames, and each image was assigned a random y-value. Finally, ImagePlot was used
               in ImageJ with the collections of images and spreadsheets to plot the images on
               graphs. In sum, one could describe the process as downloading the videos, extracting
               the images, organizing the images, and then plotting the images.<note> For more
                  detail about this process, you can access a modified guide to it here: <ref
                     target="https://bit.ly/PwPGuide">https://bit.ly/PwPGuide</ref>. You can also
                  consult the ImagePlot documentation here: <ref
                     target="https://bit.ly/ImagePlotDocumentation"
                     >https://bit.ly/ImagePlotDocumentation</ref>.</note> This entire process is in
               every way mediated by software, and the end result is a particular form of data and
               knowledge quite different from simply watching a video of a playthrough on YouTube.
               ImagePlot and ImageJ thus fit into a larger technological trend that Manovich
               identifies as software creating new media, which he defines as <quote rend="inline">a
                  combination of particular techniques for generation, editing and accessing
                  content</quote>
               <ptr target="#manovich2013" loc="335"/>. Imageplots are a new way of viewing and
               accessing existing media through distance visualization, and in this regard they are
               a form of new media. Yet they are also their own new form of content, making
               ImagePlot and ImageJ (the software that creates them) new media as well.</p>
            <p> The imageplots included primarily come from one game — <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> — in the survival horror genre, which tasks players with playing and
               surviving while being frightened by horror graphics and settings. I have limited my
               analysis to one game and one genre in order to isolate narrative variation coming
               from player interaction and experience, rather than coming from the differences
               between different games or game genres. While any game genre could work for this
               analysis, I selected the survival horror genre for its tendency to limit player
               actions in order to create a sense of fear. Survival horror games often take place in
               constrained spaces and supply few options for players in order to keep them on set
               paths and force confrontation — after all, monsters are not as scary if one can
               completely avoid them <ptr target="#chien2007" loc="64"/>. As such, survival horror
               games have hypothetically fewer variations between playthroughs, making those
               variations more consistent and noticeable. I selected <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> in particular because it is a uniquely excellent case study for
               narrative variation due to its content and cultural context. <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> is an abbreviation of Playable Teaser, and was originally intended,
               as its name suggests, as a teaser for a new <title rend="italic">Silent Hill</title>
               game being directed by Hideo Kojima (perhaps most famous for the <title rend="italic"
                  >Metal Gear</title> franchise). The game is relatively short, containing only
               about an hour’s worth of play time, and consists of repeatedly exploring the same
               hallway in a dark house with different encounters on each repeat. Thus repetition and
               variation are inherent to the game’s structure and narrative, and the game provides
               an exemplary space for using those concepts to measure player interactivity and
               differences between playthroughs. </p>
            <p> The playthroughs of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> visualized in these imageplots
               are taken from various YouTube videos and Twitch streams and include playthroughs by
               popular streamers and regular players.<note> Twitch is an online platform for live
                  streaming video games and other activities. Streams can also be recorded and
                  played on demand.</note> There are a large number of them available, mostly due to
                  <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>’s notoriety–after Konami cancelled the upcoming
                  <title rend="italic">Silent Hill</title> game and removed access to <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> in April 2015, the game became an instant cult classic.
               Each playthrough plotted is a complete playing of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>,
               in some cases accompanied by visuals associated with the YouTube channel at the
               beginning or end of the video. I have specifically excluded playthroughs that are
               heavily edited, as the additional visual elements added to those playthroughs
               introduce a bias toward similarity in the images. Heavy editing or removal of parts
               of the play experience also defeats the purpose of capturing and visualizing actual
               play, and instead creates its own entertainment media further removed from the game
               itself. Three of the playthroughs contain images of the player superimposed on the
               gameplay (as with many Twitch streams), but in the resulting imageplots the images
               from the player cameras are small enough to be unnoticeable without zooming in.</p>
            <p> There are several limitations to this process worth mentioning before diving into
               analyzing the imageplots. The ability to produce imageplots of game playthroughs is
               limited by having (or not having) access to video recordings of the game in question.
               This means that because less popular games have fewer recorded playthroughs available
               on YouTube or Twitch, it is harder to produce many imageplots of them to compare.
               Even if one sets out to produce their own recordings, there are still constraints of
               time and hard drive space that make it difficult to create many playthroughs to use.
               An additional challenge is finding complete playthroughs of a game that are not cut
               into smaller sections on YouTube, though one can get around this by splicing the
               smaller videos together into complete playthroughs for plotting. The length of a game
               is also potentially a limiting factor, as complete playthroughs of many games are
               significantly longer than the average playthrough of <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title>, and take more time and computing resources to plot.</p>
            <p> In order for the use and comparison of imageplots to be meaningful, careful
               attention to the type and source of the playthroughs that generate them is required.
               On the most basic level this means identifying exactly what the plotting of images is
               revealing regarding the relationship between data points. To put it another way,
               ImagePlot is capable of generating very interesting imageplots that contain very
               little meaning and insight for the analysis of the object they are plotting. An
               imageplot of the brightness and hue of a game reveals very little about that game’s
               narrative structure, and likewise an imageplot of time yields only the most basic
               observations of color usage in a game. Thus one must ensure that what one plots with
               ImagePlot matches the questions they are asking. This project focuses on questions of
               narrative variation in games, so the imageplots included here all deal with time,
               signs, and narrative structure. I have chosen not to plot the games according to
               qualities like hue, saturation, or brightness because all of the playthroughs being
               plotted are of the same games, so plotting those qualities would yield similar (if
               not identical) results.</p>
            <p> The imageplots that result from this process are distance visualizations of players’
               playthroughs of a particular game, and as such they effectively provide an archive of
               player experiences in that game. When looking at an imageplot of a playthrough, one
               can see everything that a player did in that game from start to finish. This means
               one can see both the player’s choices and actions, and the game system and
               environments in which they took place. Imageplots are thus excellent examples of
               archives as Foucault defines them: as <quote rend="inline">the general system of the
                  formation and transformation of statements</quote> and <quote rend="inline">the
                  system that governs the appearance of statements as unique events</quote>
               <ptr target="#foucault2010" loc="129–30"/>. The archive as <quote rend="inline"
                  >system</quote> is key to Foucault’s understanding here; it is the system that
               actually produces the objects it contains. In terms of the <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> imageplots of this project, the archive is the system of the game
               and the player: together they fashion the player’s experiences, encounters, and
               interactions (their <q>statements</q>) with images while playing. Plotting these
               images creates distance visualizations that are objects of the archive: they are
               produced by the game system, and also record that system’s possibilities.</p>
            <p> Conceptualizing the imageplots of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> playthroughs as
               archival objects helps clarify their relationship to the game and their significance
               for analysis, but it does not explain how they function. In order to understand how
               imageplots operate and capture play, one can consider them as diagrams, drawing on
               the idea of the diagram as explained by Deleuze in his reading of Foucault. Deleuze
               quotes Foucault in saying that a diagram is more than an image, it is <quote
                  rend="inline">a functioning, abstracted from any obstacle,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">a map, a cartography,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">a machine that is almost blind and mute,</quote> and <quote
                  rend="inline">a spatio-temporal multiplicity</quote>
               <ptr target="#deleuze2012" loc="34"/>. In essence, to Deleuze and Foucault a diagram
               is a frozen image that still contains motion and possibility in their purest, most
               ideal (and thus stillest) forms. Imageplots of game playthroughs are static images,
               yet they are images of play — they are snapshots of a system in operation, and
               evidence of that system’s potential. As such, they constitute diagrams of play. Each
               imageplot maps out a play experience with all of its movement and variation, yet the
               recording and plotting of images arrests and captures these same forces. The overall
               diagram of a given game is constantly changing according to the player, and yet the
               archive of the game imposes limits on this variation as well. Within this conceptual
               framework, this project is a construction of an archive of diagrams that contain the
               multiplicity of play possibilities, and that thus enable a tracing of the limits of
               interactivity and emergence in a game’s narrative and play.</p>
            <p> ImagePlot provides a new methodology for assessing play experiences on a scale
               previously impossible. The imageplots of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>
               demonstrate how this method works, and what we can learn from it about narrative
               form. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Variance in Time</head>
            <p> While there are many types of variance between the playthroughs that emerge in the
               imageplots, the observable differences in narrative form between playthroughs fall
               into two broad categories. The first type of variability is variance in time,
               measured in both the duration of particular content in a game and in points in time
               when an individual player reaches a specific part of the game. The different times of
               the playthroughs reveal how their respective players engage with <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title>, including how factors like skill, experience, and intent
               specifically affect the playing of the game and the experience of the game’s
               narrative. Measuring time in a playthrough using Imageplot also reveals how variable
               the durations of particular game events are and establishes how long a portion of the
               narrative is for an average player.</p>
            <p> In order to measure variation, however, one first needs something to measure from.
               The points of similarity and sameness between imageplots are therefore a crucial
               place to start, and thankfully they are also some of the most immediately apparent
               aspects of them. All of the playthrough imageplots are plotted to be the same size,
               regardless of the amount of overall time each one visualizes. In effect this means
               that an imageplot of a shorter playthrough, such as PT3 (00:29:44), is visually
               similar to a longer playthrough such as PT5 (00:51:11). While this effaces the
               visualization of exact time, it is helpful for the comparison of time relative to
               different overall playtimes. In other words, one can see that events happen at
               relatively the same place in the playthroughs of PT3 and PT5, even if they happen at
               different time markers because the two players took different amounts of time to
               finish the overall game. Establishing that relative sameness between playthroughs
               then enables the observation and analysis of the variance created by player
               interactivity. Furthermore, one can interpret the similarities between imageplots as
               the visualization of the game’s basic structure and narrative–the common foundation
               that the game provides and all players experience.</p>
            <p> The most obvious example of variation in time in the playthroughs is the fact that
               every playthrough has a different overall playtime. Of the ten playthroughs plotted
               here, the longest one (PT10) has a playtime of 1:24:50, and the shortest one (PT9) is
               0:20:00 long.<note>For the purpose of clarity, I refer to all times in hh:mm:ss
                  format.</note> At first glance there appears to be a wide discrepancy between the
               two that would indicate the possibility for almost infinite variation, but taken
               together with the other playthroughs some clear trends emerge. For example, the
               average time of all the playthroughs is 0:39:22, with a standard deviation of
               00:18:12. This means that 67% of the playthroughs in this dataset fall between
               00:21:10 and 00:57:34 in playtime, and that that range of time accounts for the
               majority of play experiences with <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> Of course there
               is still the possibility for outliers of longer or shorter playtime (including PT9
               and PT10 already mentioned), and the addition of more data would inevitably alter
               these numbers. Yet these playthroughs seem fairly representative of extent available
               playthroughs on YouTube and Twitch, and perhaps even of player experiences not
               present through those platforms. As such, data collected from these playthroughs
               reveals a measure of how player interactivity shapes playtime on average, which
               affects narrative time and experience in <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> A player
               who spends more time in an area will have a fuller experience of that area, and
               likely uncover parts of the game narrative that a player who spends less time there
               might miss. In this way variance in time is intricately linked with variance in sign
               covered in the next section.</p>
            <p> Beyond measuring the overall length of a playthrough, imageplots also indicate the
               specific times when players encounter different parts of a game. In <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> the most prominent example of this is an iteration of
               the hallway that is tinted red and is common to every playthrough and corresponding
               imageplot (Figure 3). Even without measuring the exact time the player reaches this
               version of the hallway, the imageplots show that there is a general variance in the
               time different players do so. Most of the players reached this point at roughly
               halfway through their playthroughs, but imageplots PT2, PT6, and PT7 enter the red
               hallway closer to the end of the game. PT6 is especially noteworthy in this regard,
               and the brevity of the playthrough after the red hallway is surprising when compared
               to the overall playtime, which was actually longer than average (00:40:00). It may be
               that the player in PT6 was more familiar with the later parts of the game and was
               able to complete them quickly. In any case, PT2, PT6, and PT7 reveal that time in the
               later stages of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> is especially variable in ways that
               it is not in the first half of the game. This variance in playtime is actually
               significant in the narrative as well. The versions of the hallway found in the first
               half of the game are relatively stable in terms of time and space–there are no tints
               to the lighting, the player moves at normal speed, and overall experience is more
               realistic (to the extent that that is possible in a world with strange monsters and
               supernatural occurrences). Yet all of this changes as <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> progresses, and the game’s space and time begin to break down in the
               sections where playtime becomes most variable. The imageplots thus reveal that the
               narrative themes of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> are present even on the levels
               of game structure and playtime. This supports the ludonarrative position that
               narrative and play are not readily separable in games, but rather that they are
               constantly interwoven in the experience of a game.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>PT6, including <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>’s red hallway segment,
                  highlighted in red.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p> Potential explanations for the time differences between the playthroughs are found
               in the individual player’s level of experience with the game, their playstyle, and
               their intentions for recording their play experience. While it is difficult to
               account for all of these factors of player experience with a game without contacting
               them, the way the player describes their playthrough can provide some answers. Four
               of the <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> playthroughs included here (PT1, PT3, PT4,
               PT6) have been labeled “Walkthroughs” by their players, indicating that they show
               viewers the correct way to play and complete the game. As a result, one can assume
               that these players have played the game before and know each part of it well enough
               to conduct the walkthrough. In contrast, the other six playthroughs are variations of
               the “Let’s Play” format on YouTube and Twitch, which usually has players playing a
               game for the first time for an audience (sometimes with commentary). The lack of
               player experience in Let’s Plays relative to Walkthroughs means that playtimes in the
               former are on average longer, though not drastically so: the average playtime for the
               six Let’s Plays was 0:41:45, and the average for Walkthroughs was 0:35:47, with a
               difference between them of 0:05:58. These numbers indicate that while experience and
               intention do have an effect on variation in playtime, they alone do not fully explain
               it. The relatively small difference between Walkthroughs and Let’s Plays also may
               suggest that there is a central narrative and experience to a game that averages can
               help trace.</p>
            <p> Experience and intention are by no means the only possible explanations of time
               variation, but unfortunately imageplots do not (and cannot) account for all factors.
               For example, players in different playthroughs may have been distracted by other
               things happening in their personal environments while playing, thus delaying their
               progress. Some players also may have more experience with different games that are
               similar to <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>, making them more familiar with the
               game’s conventions and better able to navigate them. Finally, players also may have
               played with different hardware setups that could subtly lengthen or shorten their
               playtime (this is especially common with older games like <title rend="italic">Silent
                  Hill 2</title>). These and other possibilities do not appear directly in the
               imageplots, and because of this it is impossible to account for them without
               additional information. Future work with ImagePlot and playthroughs could remedy this
               with more direct contact with players, or by adding methods for analyzing the images
               from player cameras found in some playthroughs. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>SHD1, an imageplot of a playthrough of <title rend="italic">Silent Hill:
                     Downpour</title>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p> Imageplots of another game in the Silent Hill franchise, <title rend="italic">Silent
                  Hill: Downpour</title> (Vatra Games, 2012), provide useful comparisons, both to
               other games in the series and to games with more room for exploration than <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.. Silent Hill: Downpour</title> was advertised as containing
               discoverable and variable content, largely to promote its replayability. The
               imageplots of <title rend="italic">Downpour</title> are of very different
               playthroughs: SHD1 is a regular playthrough of the game with a playtime of 4:59:19,
               and SHD2 is a speedrun (where players attempt the shortest playtime possible) with a
               playtime of 2:52:20 (Figure 4). Interestingly, the two imageplots reveal fewer points
               of relative comparison between the playthroughs than with <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title>, indicating that there is much more time variance in more open games
               like <hi rend="italic">Downpour</hi>. Presumably this is due to the presence of more
               content, meaning differences in playstyle will accumulate greater time differences by
               the end of the game. More importantly, this demonstrates how it is more difficult to
               locate a central narrative and player experience in longer games with more choices
               and player interactivity. It is not that a central narrative is not present, but
               rather that that central narrative is spread out and potentially obfuscated by the
               multiplicity of optional content interwoven with it. As seen in the imageplots, the
               narrative diffuses across the variability created by player interactivity, and the
               measures of variance in playtime (average, standard deviation, etc.) become looser as
               a result.</p>
            <p> The durations and times captured by the imageplots are the results of thousands of
               moments of gameplay, and each moment presents the possibility for at least slightly
               different choices and actions on the part of the player. In this sense, the
               temporality of the imageplots is directly related to the multiplicity of emergent
               possibilities that are present in gameplay, and now captured in distance
               visualization. This suggests that the temporality of game narrative and play is
               inextricable from its emergent capabilities, similar to the temporality of
               cybernetics and neural nets described by Orit Halpern. Halpern writes, “the
               temporality of the net is preemptive, it always operates in the future perfect tense,
               but without necessarily defined endpoints or contexts. Nets are about T+1” [Halpern
               2014, loc 3114]. Time in systems like nets or games operates on sets of uncertain
               future conditions, meaning that each moment in a game opens on new possibilities for
               emergence and alteration. The accumulation of these moments as seen in the imageplots
               accounts for measurable differences in time between playthroughs. They also involve
               the second category of difference: variance in content, or sign. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Variance in Sign</head>
            <p> Beyond encountering objects at different times or in different places, players can
               also simply encounter different objects. There are several prominent examples of this
               in the <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> playthroughs, including encounters that are
               similar (like the red hallway already mentioned), those that are similar and
               different (every player encounters a crash screen, but there are different crash
               screens), and those that are entirely different (such as a jump scare only some
               players encounter). The presence or absence of these events in a playthrough alters a
               player’s experience of the game, including their perception of the game’s narrative.
               I refer to these differing experiences of content as variance in sign because they
               involve the presence, absence, or rearranging of visual, auditory, and haptic signs
               that affect the game’s narrative.</p>
            <p> While the red hallway, the crash screen, and the jump scare could each be fruitful
               moments for close analysis, I will only cover them briefly here for their
               significance to narrative structure and variance in games.<note>This points to
                  another basic use of imageplots, however–they can be used to identify important
                  moments of similarity and difference for the purpose of close analysis.</note> The
               red hallway is perhaps the most immediately apparent similarity between all of the
                  <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> playthroughs, and the imageplots reveal that it
               varies more in its location in time than it does in its form. This does not mean that
               its form is not significant––if anything it means quite the opposite. The form and
               meaning of the red hallway are crucial to the progression of the story, as evidenced
               in the fact that every player must encounter it. The red hallway is where the reality
               of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>’s game world begins to bend and break, evident
               in how time speeds up in that version of the hallway and many of the normal objects
               are replaced with abstract and nightmarish versions of themselves. For example, all
               of the paintings and family pictures in the red hallway are replaced with images of
               flashing and revolving lights. This warping of the game’s reality is crucial to the
               central narrative of the game and its conclusion: as the player discovers more and
               more about a series of grisly murders, their first-person experience of the game’s
               environments becomes increasingly unstable, representing a growing psychosis. The red
               hallway is a breaking point in this process, and every player must encounter it in
               much the same way.</p>
            <p> The imageplots demonstrate how the game seems to return to normal after the red
               hallway by presenting players a brightly lit version of the hallway. However the
               player quickly notices that the screen seems to break and glitch as they move around,
               and eventually the game seems to crash. Every player encounters the crash screen,
               indicating its significance as a moment of complete breakage in the game’s reality.
               Yet the type, color, and message of the crash screen varies, including red, yellow,
               white, and black versions of the screen seen in PT9, PT7, and PT2 (Figure 5. The
               black version in PT9 can be hard to distinguish from the other dark images of the
               imageplots without zooming in). The variance in the crash screen’s form introduces
               the possibility for different meaning and interpretation depending on the version the
               player encounters. Examples of the message on the screen include <quote rend="inline"
                  >I’m heading there [to hell] now,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">Development halted due to inexplicable bug,</quote> and <quote
                  rend="inline">I’ll call later.</quote> Which screen the player sees alters the
               meaning of the central narrative, creating a story of paranormal horror, a
               metafiction about game development, an unresolved mystery caller, or other potential
               interpretations.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>PT7, with the yellow crash screen visible.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p> Finally, some occurrences are limited to individual experiences, and are different
               on every playthrough of a game. For example, the player in <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title> is haunted throughout the game by Lisa, the ghost of a murdered wife
               from the radio reports that the player hears. However the encounters with Lisa are
               randomly generated, and there is a jump scare where Lisa attacks the player character
               and breaks their neck that only some players experience (occurring roughly half way
               through PT6). If this happens to a player, that player must start the entire cycle of
               looping hallways over again. The addition of these signs serves the same function as
               most jump scares: to frighten the player with sudden action. Yet they also alter the
               game’s narrative by changing the individual experience of the player, introducing
               elements of failure and becoming trapped in the seemingly endless hallway. Rather
               than being entirely secondary or separate, the variance of even a small number of
               optional and random signs can significantly affect a game’s central narrative. </p>
            <p> The differences in signs between the playthroughs and imageplots of <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> reveal the especially performative and playful nature
               of signs in games, which contributes to the overall mutability of narrative form in
               the medium. Each image or object in a game is a sign that the player interacts
               with–receiving it, interpreting it, deploying it, altering it, etc. This
               understanding is not new; C.S. Pierce recognized a similar interactivity with signs
               in identifying what he calls the <quote rend="inline">interpretant</quote> of a sign,
               a mirror sign created in the mind of an individual encountering a sign <ptr
                  target="#pierce2011" loc="99"/>. Yet visual signs such as those found in games
               function somewhat differently from linguistic signs, and they operate by what Johanna
               Drucker calls distinct <quote rend="inline">basic codes of visual form</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker2014" loc="42"/>. Drucker describes these basic codes as forms
               such as lines, shapes, and movement, and all of these are certainly present in games
                  <ptr target="#drucker2014" loc="43"/>. Games are their own visual form, however,
               and their visual signs have media-specific codes as well. For example, objects in
               games are often marked by specific game symbols or highlighting to notify the player
               that the object is interactive. Similarly, the layout of space and objects can give
               players visual cues for where to go and what to do there, or in other words how to
               play. These visual signs are basic codes particular to games and are essential to how
               players navigate and play with game narrative. ImagePlot is capable of capturing the
               various outcomes or traces of these codes and players’ interactions with them, and in
               this sense an imageplot is itself an indexical sign of player activity in game. The
               relationship between an imageplot and player activity is indicative of how visual
               signs in games are often directly linked to functional purposes, and interacting with
               them during gameplay is a performance of meaning with variable and emergent
                  outcomes.<note>In terms of semiotics, this is the idea that the relationship
                  between signifier and signified with a visual sign is not arbitrary, as it often
                  is with linguistic signs. See Saussure.</note>
            </p>
            <p> The visual and playful signs present in an imageplot become further legible with the
               help of film semiotics. Film scholars such as Jean Mitry have theorized the
               relationship between visual and linguistic signs since the 1980s and have noted that
               different types of signs can have similar structures while functioning differently:
                  <quote rend="inline">any likeness exists in the structures not in the
                  forms</quote>
               <ptr target="#mitry2000" loc="24"/>. Just as there are important differences between
               signs in film and language, there are also differences between signs in film and
               signs in games. One such difference is the fact that the player takes on an active
               role in the construction of signs in games. With <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>,
               for example, it is up to the player to interpret the signs in the game and interact
               with them in the correct ways and sequences in order to progress. Because different
               players perform this role differently, there is variance in time and sign between
               imageplots of the same game when there isn’t for imageplots of the same film.
               Christian Metz’s concept of the <quote rend="inline">imaginary signifier</quote>
               further explains the player’s role and presence in the imageplots. In short, in film
               the imaginary signifier is the transparent or absent signifier that nonetheless
               represents the viewer in the film, acting as their <quote rend="inline">prosthesis
                  for [their] primally dislocated limbs</quote>
               <ptr target="#metz1982" loc="4"/>. A similar phenomenon takes place with player
               characters in games, particularly first person games like <title rend="italic"
                  >P.T.</title>, where the camera mimics the player’s first person experience of
               reality and the player character is not shown on screen. The physical embodiment of
               the player is nowhere represented in an imageplot, yet their presence in the form of
               their choices, actions, and encounters are ever-present. In this sense, the imaginary
               signifier of the player is the first person perspective, and it is found in every
               image plotted in the imageplots.</p>
            <p> Perhaps the greatest insight film semiotics can lend to games and imageplot analysis
               is how signs and narratives are fundamentally fragmented, even as they give the
               illusion of being unified and complete. Film semiotics suggests that visual signs are
               fragmentary in the sense that they are always temporary and incomplete, lacking an
               actual referent and becoming distributed across images and time. Peter Wollen notes
               this in describing film as the <quote rend="inline">fragments of raw reality,
                  multiple and equivocal in themselves</quote>
               <ptr target="#wollen1969" loc="132"/>. The meaning of this fragmentation has profound
               implications for game narrative in that perfectly unitary narrative becomes elusive
               if not impossible. Imageplots reveal how signs in games are always fragmented and
               distributed across the overall experience of the game depending on player
               interactivity; players encounter, interpret, and sequence signs differently. As they
               do so, they generate similar but different realities, and in every moment of play
               there is the potential for difference to emerge. Importantly, the variability of
               signs and narratives in games does not render them ineffectual or secondary to play,
               but rather demonstrates how they are omnipresent and necessary to the construction of
               meaning in games. Metz emphasizes the crucial function of signs when he writes,
                  <quote rend="inline">Nevertheless, it is in [the symbolic’s] wake that we can find
                  hope for a little more knowledge, it is one of its avatars that introduces
                     <q>understanding</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#metz1982" loc="4"/>. ImagePlot helps us visualize how fragmentary signs
               come together in different configurations in play to create unique narrative
               realities, and film semiotics provides a framework for theorizing this process and
               its possibilities. </p>
            <p> The play of game signs evident in imageplots reveals a crucial aspect of visual
               signs that they share with all other signs–as much as they are identifiable and
               understandable, they are never fully stable. As a visual sign enters into the virtual
               world and thus into play with other game signs of all sorts, it will continue to
               change and evolve in a way similar to the change over time Saussure describes in
               diachronic linguistics <ptr target="#saussure2011" loc="81"/>. One type of evolution
               in a game sign is formal, as a particular sign evolves according to player
               interaction and progress. An excellent example of this is the paper bag in the
               opening room of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>, which over the course of the game
               goes from being a simple bag to being a narrator of sorts with a mouth. With each of
               its evolutions the form of the sign will change somewhat, and consequently the way
               the sign will be interpreted by the player and others will change as well. However
               such signs also change informally, in that their relationships to the player and to
               other game signs will constantly be in flux. There are limits to these changes; after
               all each game sign remains beholden to the other signs in its system, especially
               those that make up the central narrative and experience. Still, variance in sign
               means that narrative form in games is never static or fully stable.</p>
            <p> Taken together, the signs in a game create the narrative of a player’s playthrough,
               and the presence or absence of particular signs can fundamentally alter that
               narrative. Variances in encountered signs constitute measurable differences in game
               narrative between playthroughs. Paying close attention to these points of semiotic
               difference allows one to trace the effects and magnitude of player interactivity in a
               given game.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Visualizing and Playing with Narrative Form</head>
            <p> The archive of player experience created by imageplots allows for measures of
               variance in both time and sign in game analysis. There remain a number of limitations
               to this archive––for example, the imageplots cannot fully account for individual
               players’ embodied reactions to a game or exactly how they interpret game elements,
               though a future analysis of player actions and facial expressions caught on camera
               for Twitch streams (such as those found in PT8) may be able to move towards that
               capability. In sum, the strengths and weaknesses of this approach are:</p>
            <table>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell>Strengths</cell>
                  <cell>Weaknesses</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>View entire playthrough in one image, can zoom in to see particular moments </cell>
                  <cell>Limited by available recorded playthroughs, or time and hardware in
                     recording new ones </cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Compare many players’ experiences for similarities and differences </cell>
                  <cell>Does not capture players’ physical reactions or play environments </cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Identify patterns and trends, such as the overall narrative structure </cell>
                  <cell>Can be difficult to find patterns in longer games with much variation
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>See play as it happened, rather than what players remembered afterward </cell>
                  <cell>Impossible to know definitively why players did what they did without
                     contacting them </cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Account for ludonarrative, the narrative and gameplay elements interwoven </cell>
                  <cell>Accounts only for what is present and recorded in the game, requires
                     investigation of social and cultural contexts </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Many of these weaknesses could be addressed through studies that recruit players to
               play a given game (or games) and record new playthroughs, controlling for play
               environment, player experience and intent, and other factors. Yet the advantage of
               the method as-is is that it captures a limited picture of how players are already
               playing on their own and experiencing ludonarrative.</p>
            <p> What the imageplots already account for is a sense of the central narrative
               experience for each game, making it clearer which parts of a game are common to every
               player’s experience and which ones are specific to individual playthroughs. The
               central narrative of a game consists of these common parts, or in other words what
               the developers coded as the essential and necessary elements of the game’s
               characters, events, and overall world. In <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>, the
               imageplots reveal that the central narrative is found in the red hallway, the crash
               screen, and many copies of the hallway that are seemingly identical. Zooming in, one
               can see that the central narrative is told through documents and objects that all
               players interact with, and it is the scripted narrative of a man murdering his family
               and killing himself. It is not that the other parts of the game that are randomly
               generated or optional do not matter, or that they are not meaningful. Such parts are
               often still significant for altering or enhancing a game’s narrative, and they are
               crucial for building space for play and individual experience. Yet being able to
               distinguish between a game’s narrative core and its variable content allows for
               analyses that account for both the central narrative and for interactivity and
               specific differences in player experiences. It provides a way to record and trace the
               limits of player interactivity, and thus to assess where and how that interactivity
               leads to different interpretations and meanings for the game. These types of analysis
               are valuable to the study of games, ludonarrative, and other visual media for
               multiple reasons: they hone our focus on the types and effects of interactivity in
               games; they help us get more specific about similarity and difference between
               players’ experiences of a game and aid in the analysis of individual games as texts;
               they highlight new understandings of narrative; and they point to possibilities for
               playing and designing for difference in video game worlds.</p>
            <p> The greater attention to variation and similarity in player experiences in
               imageplots furthers our understanding of interactivity in games by helping us see
               exactly where and how different games are interactive. While interactivity in games
               usually refers to the interaction between player and game, such as choosing what to
               do, what to use and interface with, and where to go in the virtual world, there are
               other types of interactivity present in games that become apparent in imageplots <ptr
                  target="#walsh2011" loc="84"/>. For example, Daniel Punday argues that games are
               really a form of multimedia in that they are a point of interaction between many
               media, including music, film, and text <ptr target="#punday2011" loc="31–1"/>. In
               this sense, media interact with each other as well as with people, particularly in
               automated ways enabled by software and digital networks. Narrative scholars such as
               Marie-Laure Ryan have identified similar forms of interactivity between different
               categories and aspects of games, such as the interaction of a game’s <quote
                  rend="inline">semiotic substance,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">technical dimension,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">cultural
                  dimension</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2014" loc="25, 29"/>. Players interact with game systems, other
               players, and even other media, and all of this takes place on various levels of
               physical or abstract interaction as forms collide, combine, and emerge. All of these
               processes are in different ways interactive, as Ryan argues: <quote rend="inline"
                  >digital texts are like an onion made of different layers of skin, and that
                  interactivity can affect different levels</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2011" loc="37"/>. Ludonarrative in games is dependent on these many
               forms of interactivity, including the interaction of different narratives, such as
               those laid out by developers, created by players, or that emerge in collective
               discourse inside or outside of a game <ptr target="#mejeur2019"/>. All of these types
               of narrative and interactivity are present in some way in imageplots: the narratives
               scripted into game content by developers (in <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>, the
               story of a man murdering his family) are seen in the objects in the images, the
               narratives players create themselves are observable in the sequence and duration of
               content they choose in their playthrough, and even some of the collective narratives
               that emerge from players interacting are discernible in the player’s webcam as they
               stream for an audience. Imageplots thus allow us to isolate how particular
               interactive and variable forms contribute to player experiences and meaning in
               specific moments throughout a game. They do so by providing observable measures of
               these effects — one can identify and examine how the player in PT1 played differently
               from the player in PT2, and how those differences change the reality of the game.</p>
            <p>Imageplots make it possible to identify and get specific about variations in
               different players’ experiences with a game, such as my experience with <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> that I narrated at the beginning of this article.
                  <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> ends with the phone in its hallway ringing and
               the player answering it, which shortly thereafter triggers a final cutscene that is a
               trailer for the cancelled <title rend="italic">Silent Hill</title> game. I struggled
               to get the phone-ringing event to trigger, and as a result I spent a great deal of
               time in the final version of the hallway desperately trying possible solutions while
               hoping to avoid the randomly generated Lisa jump scare death event. The <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> imageplots reveal that my experience, while shared with
               several other players (PT4, PT5, PT10), was not universal, and even seems to be in
               the minority of players’ experiences with the game. This difference in our
               playthroughs significantly alters the meaning and affect of the game’s ending. For
               most players, the ending is a short exploration of a familiar version of the hallway
               that constitutes an escape from the chaos of the preceding parts of the game. For me
               and other players who were trapped in the final hallway for greater amounts of time,
               the ending was a frantic, stressful scramble to find a way out before possibly dying
               and having to start over. Despite both experiences ending in the same place, the
               variance in time and sign profoundly affects the narrative pacing and structure,
               potentially even leading to divergent interpretations of the game’s messages and
               meanings.</p>
            <p> Imageplots thus aid in the analysis of individual texts by allowing us to see the
               structure of an entire visual text at once, and to assess how that structure
               contributes to the text’s meanings. In other words, ImagePlot allows us to see the
               shape of a text, much the same way that sentiment analysis allowed Matthew Jockers to
               see the shape of plots in novels, that topic modeling allowed Ben Schmidt to identify
               fundamental plot arcs in popular TV shows, or comparing different plots across media
               allowed Chess to identify the queer potentials for narrative in the play spaces of
                  games.<note>See <ref target="#jockers2014">Jockers (2014)</ref>. Also <ref
                     target="#schmidt2015">Schmidt (2015)</ref>. Finally, Chess’s work with queer
                  narrative and play spaces in games is found in <ref target="#chess2016">Chess
                     (2016)</ref>.</note> Using imageplots of playthroughs, one clearly sees how
               long or short a segment of a game is, the colors and aesthetics used in different
               portions of a game, and what trends or cycles exist in the course of a game. For
               example, the imageplots of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> included here reveal the
               structure of the game’s narrative that contributes to its overall meanings and
               determines what all players will experience and what different players will
               experience differently. In particular, the imageplots demonstrate that every player
               will spend roughly the first half of the game exploring more or less similar versions
               of <title rend="italic">P.T.</title>’s hallway, evidenced in the lighting and
               coloring of the images that remains the same throughout those sections of the game.
               However around halfway through their playthrough (more or less, depending on the
               player), the player will encounter a red version of the hallway that radically
               changes the player experience and sets off a descent into instability and incoherence
               in content that dominates much of the rest of the game (see imageplots). While the
               red hallway starts this for each player, the descent looks different for each player
               as well: they encounter different versions of the crash screen after the red hallway
               and randomly generated events from that point on. This structure is essential to the
               narrative of the game — the narrative of a man who wakes up with no memory of his
               surroundings, gradually discovers that a man murdered his family in the house, and
               confronts the growing terror that he might be that man. What is at first a casual, if
               cautious, exploration of a strange house gives way to the desperate attempt to escape
               an increasingly random, broken, nightmarish reality, and this narrative progression
               is visible in the game’s structure. Distance visualization allows us to see a game’s
               overall layout and plotting, and this perspective lends new evidence to game analysis
               that links close analysis of specific scenes to larger forms, structures, and
               patterns. </p>
            <p>Beyond the analysis of individual texts, imageplots and distance visualization
               contribute to a ludonarrative understanding of narrative form that is nonlinear,
               emergent, and playful. Imageplots of games demonstrate the constant connection
               between narrative and play in that they show how the traditionally narrative elements
               are interwoven with segments of play. In other words, the <quote rend="inline"
                  >cutscenes and backstories</quote> that game studies scholars such as Markku
               Eskelinen identify as the only narrative parts of a game still need play in order to
               connect them together into a narrative, and cannot be isolated or abstracted away
               from the player pushing them forward <ptr target="#eskelinen2012" loc="224"/>. Even
               moments in <title rend="italic">P.T.</title> where the player is simply moving down
               the hallway or looking at objects —the mundane actions that make up the majority of
               the <title rend="italic">P.T</title>. playthroughs and imageplots —are progressing
               toward the ultimate fulfillment of the narrative, and it seems arbitrary to
               completely divorce those moments from their narrative function. Instead of
               considering narrative as a linear or multilinear progression of events separate from
               gameplay, what if we considered narrative as a system of signs that coheres into a
               core experience, with variations in sign and time emerging and impacting that center?
               The crucial difference here is that narrative becomes less of a static and stable
               form, and more of an active, evolving, and mutable one. Hanna-Riika Roine argues for
               a similar definition of narrative by pointing out how narrative forms are affected by
                  <quote rend="inline">the participatory nature of digital media:</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">they now appear to us as phenomena to be cut, pasted,
                  reassembled, and distributed</quote>
               <ptr target="#roine2015" loc="83"/>. Imageplots visualize these changing and
               colliding forms in games and other visual media, and help capture what narrative
               looks like as players and viewers experience it differently.</p>
            <p> Exploring the collisions of many forms, structures, and semiotics in visualizations
               like imageplots can yield new insights on how ludonarrative texts operate and create
               multiplicities of meaning. This is not completely new work, and there have been calls
               for the use of semiotics in game studies, such as Paolo Ruffino’s work with semiotics
               and the social contexts of games, or Brian Upton’s work with the procedural
               generation of meaning in games.<note>See <ref target="#ruffino2012">Ruffino
                     (2012)</ref>. For Upton’s work with semiotics, narrative, and players’
                  meaning-making processes, see <ref target="#upton2015">Upton (2015)</ref>. </note>
               However we have yet to fully account for the immense multiplicity of forms and
               possibilities for variation in games, and there is still no consensus in game studies
               (particularly the emerging study of ludonarrative) as to a methodology for game
               analysis. ImagePlot makes it increasingly clear that ludonarrative in games relies on
               the complex interactivity of language and play to create both similarity and
               difference between player experiences. Yet how exactly game signs are formed, laden
               with meaning, and interpreted by players and developers in different contexts remain
               rich topics for further research, and ImagePlot is one method for conducting this
               research on a much greater scale than individual analyses of single playthroughs.
               Identifying the central narrative and using differences in time and sign to measure
               player interactivity is a starting point. It provides a few of the analytical tools
               needed for the theory and praxis of a critical, playful interpretation of games that
               can also account for player interaction and difference. But the ability to visualize
               a game’s forms, signs, and central narrative with ImagePlot also has many profoundly
               interdisciplinary implications and potential uses that are unexplored: imageplots
               could help assess where and how players spend time in games, which game mechanics and
               designs are helpful or harmful to player experiences, or how players learn and adapt
               through the course of a game, among many other questions. For example, the <title
                  rend="italic">P.T.</title> imageplots provide an archive of player experiences in
               a popular survival horror game, and they can help answer questions of how and why
               players engage in settings that create unease, fear, and even terror. In this sense,
               ludonarrative, semiotics, and the study of game forms can contribute to work in the
               other disciplines of game studies, even as it pursues its own projects. </p>
            <p> By better understanding how forms operate in games through distance visualization
               and analysis, we can ultimately find ways to use them in the creation of new story
               worlds and even new realities. For example, Ryan argues that critical attention to
               interactivity can reveal how media form new spaces and experiences for players of
               games <ptr target="#ryan2011" loc="40–1"/>. Alice Bell capitalizes on this
               observation and other parts of Ryan’s work to suggest that hypertext and interactive
               fictions (including games) constantly generate <quote rend="inline">Possible
                  Worlds</quote> that are <quote rend="inline">ontological domains,</quote> and thus
               different spaces and conditions of being <ptr target="#bell2011" loc="79"/>. Players
               repeatedly choose, explore, or foreclose upon these possible worlds, and they do so
               by interacting with the changeable forms that comprise a game’s system and can be
               captured in imageplots. </p>
            <p> Of course there are limits to which possible worlds can emerge that are largely tied
               to the limitations of our current systems. As Ryan writes, <quote rend="inline">we do
                  not really have a story-generating system sufficiently sophisticated to produce a
                  wide variety of interesting stories out of data internal to the system</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2011" loc="48"/>. A story system capable of adapting to any user
               input has long been the goal of game designers such as Chris Crawford, but even after
               decades of attempts such systems are only capable of generating basic procedural
               narratives. It might be that the creation of a fully interactive system can only
               happen once we have reassessed our understanding of forms ranging from signs to
               narratives and beyond, and developed computing, programming languages, game engines,
               and other assets for better utilizing variable and emergent forms like ludonarrative.
               ImagePlot and other digital humanities tools for visualization can help get us there
               by visualizing forms, and making it possible to compare how they collide, flow, and
               shift. In games, they reveal what emerges as the common core of a game’s possible
               worlds and establish what most possible worlds for a game will look like. In effect,
               they show us a game’s pieces, and how those pieces can relate to each other and to
               us. With that knowledge, we can envision how our interactions with a game — along
               with all of the variations they generate — could be different or better. Now let’s
               play. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix01">
            <head>Table of Figures</head>
            <table>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell>Figure Name</cell>
                  <cell>Playthrough Type</cell>
                  <cell>Play Time</cell>
                  <cell>Red Hallway Arrival</cell>
                  <cell>Red Hallway Duration</cell>
                  <cell>Crash Screen Color</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT1</cell>
                  <cell>Walkthrough</cell>
                  <cell>0:31:28</cell>
                  <cell>14:20</cell>
                  <cell>5:17</cell>
                  <cell>Red</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT2</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>0:37:06</cell>
                  <cell>19:35</cell>
                  <cell>5:03</cell>
                  <cell>Grey</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT3</cell>
                  <cell>Walkthrough</cell>
                  <cell>0:29:44</cell>
                  <cell>13:00</cell>
                  <cell>4:30</cell>
                  <cell>Black</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT4</cell>
                  <cell>Walkthrough</cell>
                  <cell>0:41:56</cell>
                  <cell>17:30</cell>
                  <cell>5:37</cell>
                  <cell>Black</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT5</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>0:51:11</cell>
                  <cell>13:25</cell>
                  <cell>12:43</cell>
                  <cell>Grey</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT6</cell>
                  <cell>Walkthrough</cell>
                  <cell>0:40:00</cell>
                  <cell>22:02</cell>
                  <cell>8:49</cell>
                  <cell>Yellow</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT7</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>0:27:07</cell>
                  <cell>13:09</cell>
                  <cell>6:18</cell>
                  <cell>Yellow</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT8</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>0:30:15</cell>
                  <cell>12:48</cell>
                  <cell>5:37</cell>
                  <cell>Black</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT9</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>0:20:00</cell>
                  <cell>8:00</cell>
                  <cell>4:16</cell>
                  <cell>Red</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PT10</cell>
                  <cell>Let’s Play</cell>
                  <cell>1:24:50</cell>
                  <cell>26:59</cell>
                  <cell>19:34</cell>
                  <cell>Red</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>SHD1</cell>
                  <cell>Walkthrough</cell>
                  <cell>4:59:19</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>SHD2</cell>
                  <cell>Speedrun</cell>
                  <cell>2:52:20</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth1997" label="Aarseth 1997">Aarseth, E. <title rend="italic"
                  >Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
               University Press, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="atkins2007" label="Atkins and Krzywinska 2007">Atkins, B. and Krzywinska,
               T. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: videogame, player, text</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Videogame, player, text</title>. Edited by B. Atkins and T.
               Krzywinska, New York: Manchester University Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bell2011" label="Bell 2011">Bell, A. <title rend="quotes">Ontological
                  boundaries and conceptual leaps: the significance of possible worlds for hypertext
                  fiction (and beyond)</title>. <title rend="italic">New Narratives: Stories and
                  Storytelling in the Digital Age</title>. Edited by R. Page and B. Thomas, Lincoln:
               University of Nebraska Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bruner1991" label="Bruner 1991">Bruner, J. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Narrative Construction of Reality</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical
                  Inquiry</title> 18 (1): 1–21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chess2016" label="Chess 2016">Chess, S. <title rend="quotes">The Queer
                  Case of Video Games: Orgasms, Heteronormativity, and Video Game Narrative</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Critical Studies in Media Communication</title> 33 (3):
               84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chien2007" label="Chien 2007">Chien, I. <title rend="quotes">Playing
                  Undead</title>. <title rend="italic">Film Quarterly</title> 61 (2): 64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohn2013" label="Cohn 2013">Cohn, N. <title rend="italic">The Visual
                  Language of Comics: Introduction to the Structure and Cognition of Sequential
                  Images</title>. New York: Bloomsbury Academic, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crawford2013" label="Crawford 2013">Crawford, C. <title rend="italic"
                  >Chris Crawford on Interactive Storytelling</title>. Berkeley: New Riders,
               2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deleuze2012" label="Deleuze 2012">Deleuze, G. <title rend="italic"
                  >Foucault</title>. Translated by S. Hand, Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
               Press, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2014" label="Drucker 2014">Drucker, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production</title>. Cambridge: Harvard
               University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eskelinen2012" label="Eskelinen 2012">Eskelinen, M. <title rend="italic"
                  >Cybertext Poetics: The Critical Landscape of New Media Literary Theory</title>.
               New York: Continuum, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foucault2010" label="Foucault 2010">Foucault, M. <title rend="italic">The
                  Archaeology of Knowledge</title>. Translated by A.M. Sheridan Smith, New York:
               Vintage Books, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="halpern2014" label="Halpern 2014">Halpern, O. <title rend="italic"
                  >Beautiful Data: A History of Vision and Reason since 1945</title>. Durham: Duke
               University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="herman2004" label="Herman 2004">Herman, D. <title rend="italic">Story
                  Logic: Problems and Possibilities of Narrative</title>. Lincoln: University of
               Nebraska Press, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jockers2014" label="Jockers 2014">Jockers, M. <title rend="quotes">A Novel
                  Method for Detecting Plot</title>. <title rend="italic">Matthew L. Jockers</title>
               (blog), June 5, 2014, <ref
                  target="http://www.matthewjockers.net/2014/06/05/a-novel-method-for-detecting-plot/"
                  >http://www.matthewjockers.net/2014/06/05/a-novel-method-for-detecting-plot/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="levine2015" label="Levine 2015">Levine, C. <title rend="italic">Forms:
                  whole, rhythm, hierarchy, network</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press,
               2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich2013" label="Manovich 2013">Manovich, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Software Takes Command: Extending the Language of New Media</title>. New York:
               Bloomsbury, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mejeur2019" label="Mejeur 2019">Mejeur, C. <title rend="quotes"
                  >PokéStories: On Narrative and the Construction of Augmented Reality</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Not Just Play: Essays on Motivations and Impacts of Pokémon
                  Go</title>. Edited by J. Henthorn, A. Kulak, K. Purzycki, and S. Vie, New York:
               McFarland, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="metz1982" label="Metz 1982">Metz, C. <title rend="italic">The Imaginary
                  Signifier: Psychoanalysis and the Cinema</title>. Translated by C. Britton, A.
               Williams, B. Brewster, and A. Guzzetti, Bloomington: Indiana University Press,
               1982.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="metz1991" label="Metz 1991">Metz, C. <title rend="italic">Film language: a
                  semiotics of the cinema</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
               1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="miller2009" label="Miller 2009">Miller, M.P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Storytelling in a Multiplayer Environment</title>. <title rend="italic">Third
                  Person: Authoring and Exploring Vast Narratives</title>. Edited by P. Harrigan and
               N. Wardrip-Fruin, Cambridge: MIT Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitry2000" label="Mitry 2000">Mitry, J. <title rend="italic">Semiotics and
                  the Analysis of Film</title>. Translated by C. King, Bloomington: Indiana
               University Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mukherjee2015" label="Mukherjee 2015">Mukherjee, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Video Games and Storytelling: Reading Games and Playing Books</title>. Palgrave
               Macmillan, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murray2017" label="Murray 2017">Murray, J. <title rend="italic">Hamlet on
                  the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in Cyberspace</title>. Cambridge: The MIT
               Press, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pierce2011" label="Pierce 2011">Pierce, C. S. <title rend="quotes">Logic
                  as Semiotic: The Theory of Signs</title>. <title rend="italic">Philosophical
                  Writings of Pierce</title>. Edited by J. Buchler, New York: Dover Publications,
               Inc., 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pugh2019" label="Pugh 2019">Pugh, T. <title rend="italic">Chaucer’s
                  losers, Nintendo’s children, and other forays in queer ludonarratology</title>.
               Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="punday2011" label="Punday 2011">Punday, D. <title rend="quotes">From
                  Synesthesia to Multimedia: How to Talk about New Media Narrative</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">New Narratives: Stories and Storytelling in the Digital Age</title>.
               Edited by R. Page and B. Thomas, Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmidt2015" label="Schmidt 2015">Schmidt, B.M. <title rend="quotes">Plot
                  Arceology: A Vector-Space Model of Narrative Structure</title>. IEEE, 2015,
               1667–72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roine2015" label="Roine 2015">Roine, H. <title rend="quotes">How You
                  Emerge from This Game Is Up to You: Agency, Positioning, and Narrativity in the
                  Mass Effect Trilogy</title>. <title rend="italic">Narrative Theory, Literature,
                  and New Media: Narrative Minds and Virtual Worlds</title>. Edited by M. Hatavara,
               M. Hyvärinen, M. Mäkelä, and F. Mäyrä, New York: Routledge, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roth2018" label="Roth et al. 2018">Roth, C., T. van Nuenen, and H.
               Koenitz. <title rend="quotes">Ludonarrative Hermeneutics: A Way Out and the Narrative
                  Paradox</title>. <title rend="italic">Interactive Storytelling</title>. Edited by
               R. Rouse, H. Koenitz, and M. Haahr, Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2018,
               11318:93–106. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-04028-4_7"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-04028-4_7</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ruffino2012" label="Ruffino 2012">Ruffino, P. <title rend="quotes">A
                  Theory of Non-Existent Video Games: Semiotic and Video Game Theory</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Computer Games and New Media Cultures</title>. Edited by J. Fromme
               and A. Unger, New York: Springer, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2011" label="Ryan 2011">Ryan, M. <title rend="quotes">The Interactive
                  Onion: Layers of User Participation in Digital Narrative Texts</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">New Narratives: Stories and Storytelling in the Digital Age</title>.
               Edited by R. Page and B. Thomas, Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2014" label="Ryan 2014">Ryan, M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Story/Worlds/Media: Tuning the Instruments of a Media-Conscious
                  Narratology</title>. <title rend="italic">Storyworlds across Media: Toward a
                  Media-Conscious Narratology</title>. Edited by J. Thon and M. Ryan, Lincoln:
               University of Nebraska Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2016" label="Ryan et al. 2016">Ryan, M, K. E. Foote, and M. Azaryahu.
                  <title rend="italic">Narrating Space/Spatializing Narrative: Where Narrative
                  Theory and Geography Meet</title>. Columbus: The Ohio State University Press,
               2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="saussure2011" label="Saussure 2011">Saussure, F. <title rend="italic"
                  >Course in General Linguistics</title>. Translated by W. Baskin, edited by P.
               Meisel and H. Saussy, New York: Columbia University Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="toh2017" label="Toh 2017">Toh, W. <title rend="italic">A Multimodal
                  Approach to Video Games and the Player Experience</title>. New York: Routledge,
               2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="upton2015" label="Upton 2015">Upton, B. <title rend="italic">The Aesthetic
                  of Play</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="walsh2011" label="Walsh 2011">Walsh, R. <title rend="quotes">Emergent
                  Narrative in Interactive Media</title>. <title rend="italic">Narrative</title> 19
               (1): 84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wollen1969" label="Wollen 1969">Wollen, P. <title rend="italic">Signs and
                  Meaning in the Cinema.</title> London: Secker &amp; Warburg, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zimmerman2006" label="Zimmerman 2006">Zimmerman, E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Narrative, Interactivity, Play, and Games: Four Naughty Concepts in Need of
                  Discipline</title>. <title rend="italic">First Person: New Media as Story,
                  Performance, and Game</title>. Edited by N. Wardrip-Fruin and P. Harrigan,
               Cambridge: The MIT Press, 2006.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
