<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">J. M. Coetzee's Work in Stylostatistics</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Peter <dhq:family>Johnston</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Royal Holloway, University of London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>petejohnston1979@me.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Peter Johnston completed his Ph.D. on J.M. Coetzee and mathematics in
                            2013, at Royal Holloway, University of London. With wider interests in
                            the intersection between literature, mathematical philosophy, and
                            digital humanities, he is currently working on a stylometric analysis of
                            the works of David Foster Wallace.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000188</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2014-10-09">9 October 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Though better known for the novels that eventually led to his being awarded the
                    Nobel Prize for Literature in 2003, there is a strong but less widely recognised
                    case for claiming J. M. Coetzee as a significant figure in the early development
                    of digital humanities. In light of the recent renaissance of computer-assisted
                    statistical approaches to literary analysis, the present article charts in
                    detail a formative period (1969-1973) during which this most important of
                    novelists first adopted, then deconstructed, and eventually rejected one of the
                    discipline’s earliest incarnations.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Coetzee's influence on digital humanities</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1 Introduction</head>
                <p>Thanks in no small part to his first two works of <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1997">fictionalised autobiography</quote>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1997"/>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee2002"/> and J. C. Kannemeyer’s recent authorised biography
                        <ptr target="#kannemeyer2012"/> the basic plot-points of J.M. Coetzee's
                    early years are now widely known. Born in Cape Town in 1940, he spent much of
                    his childhood in the more rural Cape Province town of Worcester. After
                    graduating from the University of Cape Town (UCT) with honours degrees in both
                    English literature and mathematics, he travelled to England, where he put his
                    mathematical skills to work as a computer programmer; his literary ambitions
                    manifested themselves at this time in a master's dissertation on Ford Madox
                    Ford, and the search within himself for an authentic poetic voice. Notably,
                    Coetzee's fictionalised account of his younger self reveals in some detail the
                    mathematical inclinations of the adolescent who, to adapt Wordsworth’s dictum,
                    would be father to the novelist: he is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">studying mathematics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>; he <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">assists with first-year tutorials in the mathematics
                            department</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>; he sees himself as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">a mathematician to be</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>; he desires <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">to study pure mathematics to the exclusion of
                            everything else</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="22"/>
                    </cit>, believing that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">pure mathematics appears to be the closest approach the
                            academy affords to the realm of the forms</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="22"/>
                    </cit>; he is convinced that literature is not <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">as noble as mathematics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="53"/>
                    </cit> and wonders whether he will <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">become like those scientists whose brains solve
                            problems while they sleep</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="144"/>
                    </cit>. Later, as a genuine self-awareness finally begins to dawn upon him, he
                    begins to worry that the Atlas computer that is by now his most frequent
                    companion, as well as his partner in the production of poetry, might <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">burn <emph>either-or </emph>paths in the brain of its
                            users and thus lock them irreversibly into its binary logic</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="160"/>
                    </cit>. This prospect, combined with his desire to find <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">the moment in history when <emph>either-or </emph>is
                            chosen and <emph>and/or </emph>is discarded</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="160"/>
                    </cit> contributes to an epiphany of anti-rationalism that would be voiced in
                    one form or another throughout his body of fiction: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee2002">Death to reason, death to talk! All that matters is
                            doing the right thing, whether for the right reason or the wrong reason
                            or for no reason at all</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee2002" loc="164"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>While the evidence provided by Coetzee's fictionalised autobiographies is of
                    course rather compromised by its pointed generic instability, it remains
                    somewhat surprising how little detailed attention the critical discourse
                    surrounding his work has paid to his clear and profound inheritance from his
                    engagement with mathematics and, moreover, computer science. Even so, though
                    some of the more widely cited long-form critical works on Coetzee's writing make
                    no reference to these subjects at all (see, for instance, <ptr target="#kossew1996"/> and <ptr target="#attridge2004"/>, the discourse has
                    not been entirely silent regarding its place in his intellectual development. As
                    each year passes, a growing majority of critics and interviewers have begun to
                    recognise the value of mentioning Coetzee's undergraduate studies at Cape Town,
                    often if only as part of a brief biographical summary that may or may not also
                    reference his short-lived career as a computer programmer and his postgraduate
                    work in America: these include <ptr target="#vanzantengallagher1991" loc="10"/>;
                        <ptr target="#begam1992" loc="419"/>; <ptr target="#canepari-labib2005" loc="24"/>; <ptr target="#head1997" loc="1"/>; <ptr target="#silvani2012" loc="26"/>; <ptr target="#fromm2000" loc="337"/>; and <ptr target="#phillips1998" loc="61"/>. Moreover, and while certainly still in
                    the minority, there exist some critical responses that treat mathematics and
                    computing not just as mere biographical happenstance, but rather in some sense
                    as responsible for certain aspects of Coetzee's literary work: the most valuable
                    of these are <ptr target="#scott1997" loc="82–102"/>; <ptr target="#mulhall2009" loc="39–41"/>; <ptr target="#lamb2010" loc="177–183"/>; <ptr target="#jahn2007" loc="43, 64–66"/>; <ptr target="#attwell1993" loc="128"/>; and <ptr target="#egerer1999" loc="96–101"/>. Given both Coetzee’s
                    contribution to the early development of digital humanities and his pre-eminence
                    as novelist, the lack of a detailed outline of his history within the discipline
                    — either within the digital humanities community or in the wider field of
                    literary studies — is an oversight that clearly requires rectifying.</p>
                <p>One reason for the lack of focused attention on Coetzee's engagement with these
                    subjects in his fiction might well be the fact that his work in this area now
                    seems rather dated, a relic of the structuralist fervour of the late 1960s
                    against which he had himself quite violently revolted by the time he came to
                    publish his first novel, <title rend="italic">Dusklands</title>, in 1974. Hemmed
                    in by the technological limitations of the age, Coetzee’s initial methodology —
                    as well as his later critique of that very methodology — almost inevitably
                    concentrates on the stylostatistical analysis of lexical features, as was
                    characteristic of the period, rather than the more complex linguistic and
                    paralinguistic phenomena that constitute the data available to critics today. As
                    such, the particular methodologies he discusses seem relatively superficial in
                    retrospect, leaving open the question as to how far his specific criticisms
                    might apply to more recent, more sophisticated approaches. Indeed, as Hoover
                    (2008) neatly summarises, and largely as a consequence of the subsequent
                    explosion in accessibility to digitised texts since Coetzee’s time in the field,
                    much has changed for the better; so, while critics such as John Burrows and Hugh
                    Craig might broadly represent a continuation of the discipline as Coetzee
                    conceived of it, their contributions to the field of computational authorial
                    attribution have produced consistently convincing results and reliable,
                    widely-used standard statistical measures such as Burrows’ <title rend="quotes">Delta</title>
                    <ptr target="#burrows2002"/>. Moreover, recent developments have moved away from
                    the simple word-frequency analysis with which Coetzee’s work principally
                    engages, tending to focus instead on multivariate approaches such as principal
                    components analysis <ptr target="#holmes2001"/>, cluster analysis <ptr target="#stewart2003"/>, discriminant analysis <ptr target="#forsyth1999"/>,
                    and correspondence analysis <ptr target="#paling2009"/>. Even if one were
                    ultimately to decide that such work still innately suffers from the malaise
                    Coetzee identifies, Stephen Ramsay’s <title rend="quotes">algorithmic
                        criticism</title> offers an alternative philosophy altogether: the <title rend="quotes">algorithmic critic</title>, he argues, ought to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2011">refocus the hermeneutical problem away from the nature
                            and limits of computation (which is mostly a matter of
                            methodology)</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2011" loc="9"/>
                    </cit>, actively imagine <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2011">the artifacts of human culture as radically
                            transformed, reordered, disassembled, and reassembled</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2011" loc="85"/>
                    </cit>, and approach computational stylometry having already dispensed with any
                    inappropriately scientistic desire to achieve singular, definitive
                    conclusions.</p>
                <p>Ultimately, though, and putting the minutiae aside, the present-day significance
                    of Coetzee’s contribution depends to a large extent on how successfully the
                    discipline as it stands today negotiates Coetzee’s deeper, more philosophical
                    query: if one can largely eradicate the subjective biases of traditional
                    literary criticism by restricting one's statements to the near-neutral
                    categorical definitions of mathematics, then how can one return from the mere
                    statement of numerical values to draw meaningful natural-language conclusions,
                    without allowing those subjective biases to creep right back in? With this in
                    mind, the principal purpose of the present essay is therefore not to directly
                    assess Coetzee’s work within and around the field of stylostatistics against
                    today’s standards, but rather to provide a narrative account of this work,
                    starting with his first published journal article, <title rend="quotes">Statistical Indices of <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1969a"/>, leading through close analysis of his doctoral
                    thesis <ptr target="#coetzee1969b"/>, pivoting upon a review of Wilhelm Fucks’
                        <title rend="italic">Nach allen Regeln der Kunst </title><ptr target="#coetzee1971"/>, and ending with an essay on Samuel Beckett's <title rend="italic">Lessness </title><ptr target="#coetzee1973b"/>, which appeared
                    in the year before the publication of <title rend="italic">Dusklands</title>.
                    While this account makes few direct connections between this early critical work
                    and Coetzee's fiction, then, it is intended as a resource through which such
                    connections might later be drawn.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2 Stylostatistics and <title rend="quotes">Statistical Indices of
                            <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title> (1969) </head>
                <p>Appearing in a 1969 edition of <title rend="italic">Language and Style</title>,
                        <title>Statistical Indices of <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title>
                    constitutes an extension of the work of the renowned German stylostatistician
                    Wilhelm Fucks, and provides a succinct statement of the twenty-nine-year-old
                    Coetzee's largely optimistic approach to the field of stylostatistics at this
                    time. Published just two years later, though, his review of Fucks's <title rend="italic">Nach allen Regeln der Kunst</title> demonstrates a stark shift
                    in his thinking: by 1971, Coetzee's various explorations into the ways in which
                    statistical analyses can be used to systematically harness and codify the
                    qualitative in quantitative terms had refocused his thought to such an extent
                    that, far from endorsing such a process, he had now come to recoil against its
                    potential ramifications as a means of manipulation in contexts both social and
                    political. </p>
                <p>Put simply, we can understand Coetzee’s use of the term <q>stylostatistics</q> to
                    refer to the branch of stylistics concerned with those features of a text's
                    style that can be subjected to numerical analysis. The principal aim of the
                    stylostatistician is to strip away the subjectivity implicit in other types of
                    literary criticism, leaving only quantitative propositions that, in Coetzee's
                    words, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">will not carry the kind of connotative freight that,
                            for example, the proposition 'A's language is dense' came to carry in
                            Scrutiny criticism</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="226"/>
                    </cit>. Where the Leavisite tradition to which he alludes here founded its
                    criticism on the notion that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#leavis1930">it is upon a very small minority that the discerning
                            appreciation of art and literature depends</quote>
                        <ptr target="#leavis1930" loc="12"/>
                    </cit>, the stylostatistician attempts to evade such cultural elitism by
                    constructing formulas that enable her or him to represent certain features of a
                    given text in the form of an objective numerical value that both reveals
                    something meaningful about the text at hand and facilitates direct, quantifiable
                    comparison with other texts that have been subjected to the same analysis. By
                    defining explicitly and with axiomatic precision the processes through which he
                    or she has calculated each numerical value, the stylostatistician can, in
                    theory, provide an 'index' pertaining to a given stylistic feature that is both
                    entirely unambiguous and consistently reliable across a diverse body of texts.
                    It is essential, however, that the stylostatistician should recognise that the
                    explanatory scope of the results of her or his analysis is limited to an extent
                    covariant with the degree to which her or his terms gain meaning from their
                    natural language equivalents. In Coetzee's <title rend="quotes">Statistical
                        Indices of <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title>, for instance, the
                    quotation marks surrounding the word <q>Difficulty</q> communicate the fact that
                    he is not in the final analysis interested in producing any clear definitions of
                        <q>difficulty</q> per se: this term, as it is used in natural language, will
                    ultimately remain at least partially obscure. Given this inevitable impediment,
                    Coetzee's opening paragraph clarifies his conception of the role of
                    stylostatistical analysis: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969a">I take it as universally acknowledged that “difficult”
                            in the proposition “A's style is difficult” is a complex word, and hence
                            that the proposition in fact expresses a number of component
                            conclusions, many of them quantitative in nature and therefore capable
                            of being chiselled into numerical form. We may infer, indeed, that these
                            quantifiable components take their origin in some quantitative,
                            cumulative procedure, however loose, that we follow in our minds as we
                            read, and hence that propositions about “difficulty” and perhaps other
                            so-called qualities of style are most simply and logically formulated
                            with their quantitative and nonquantitative components kept
                            distinct.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="226"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>The stylostatistician, then, limits his or her analysis to those
                        <soCalled>component</soCalled> textual features that are <q>capable of being chiselled into numerical form</q>,
                    considering these as mere indicators of an overall
                        <soCalled>composite</soCalled> quality – in this case
                        <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled> – that, while it can never be fully
                    accounted for without recourse to inherently subjective <soCalled>Scrutiny
                        criticism</soCalled>, the critic nevertheless wishes to assess to as great a
                    degree of specificity as possible. By extension, we may deduce, any ordinary
                    language term we might use to describe the style of a given text might
                    conceivably be constructed at least in part from <soCalled>quantifiable
                        components</soCalled> that correspond to an either literally or
                    metaphorically quantitative or cumulative concept in which they in some likely
                    subconscious form participate. </p>
                <p>Within this methodological framework, <title rend="quotes">Statistical Indices of
                            <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title> has at its core two principal
                    concerns: first, to elaborate upon and refine a stylostatistical index of
                    textual <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled> proposed in 1952 by Wilhelm Fucks; and,
                    second, to use this specific elaboration and refinement as a means of
                    approaching more general and enduring issues within the field of
                    stylostatistics. Using William Shakespeare's <title rend="italic">Othello</title>, three works by John Galsworthy, and two by Aldous Huxley
                    as object texts, Fucks proposed an index of <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled>
                    based on mean word-length, with the syllable as the unit of measurement.<note>
                        Fucks's decision to use the syllable as a measure of
                            <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled> is self-evidently problematic. As
                        Coetzee points out, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">the phenomenon in which we really ought to be
                                interested is not the syllable (as Fucks assumes) but the morpheme,
                                since we can give a more precise meaning to the definition of a word
                                of many morphemes as <soCalled>difficult</soCalled> than a word of
                                many syllables (consider <q>Oopsidaisy</q>)</quote>
                            <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="232"/>
                        </cit>. Here and elsewhere, one should note, while Coetzee criticises the
                        detail of Fucks's methodology, he registers no objection to the underlying
                        principles of the venture.</note> From this initial affirmation, he
                    constructed an algorithm that enabled him to <soCalled>chisel</soCalled> the raw
                    evidence of the distribution of mono- and polysyllabic words throughout each
                    text into a corresponding numerical value, or <soCalled>trace</soCalled>. Once
                    the <soCalled>trace</soCalled> has been evaluated, it is possible to rank the
                    object texts along a scale that might for convenience be called the <title rend="quotes">Fucks Index</title>: <title rend="italic">Othello</title> was
                    seen to produce the highest trace (107.65), followed by the works of Galsworthy
                    (96.8, 94.06, and 91.07), with those of Huxley falling some distance behind
                    (62.04 and 57.72). </p>
                <p>But what, Coetzee asks, does the Fucks Index measure, exactly? And how does the
                    trace it produces correspond with the natural language notion of
                        <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled>? <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969a">[I]f we propose to describe the style of a text, an
                            index must remain meaningless until we can specify precisely what it
                            measures, i.e. with which phenomena in the text it varies
                            systematically. If the value of the trace is high, as it is for Othello,
                            what features of the language of Othello would this value enable us to
                            predict without referring to the text? If its value is low, as it is for
                            the present essay, what features of the essay are being reflected? Can
                            we specify the features both simply and informatively?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="228"/>
                    </cit> The most obvious, and least useful, answer to these questions, Coetzee
                    suggests, is that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">fullest statement of what the index measures is a
                            mathematical restatement of the definition of the index</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="228"/>
                    </cit>. In other words, what the formula tests is exactly the formula: any
                    attempt to accord ordinary-language meanings to the mathematical terms that
                    constitute the formula, however innocent such translations might seem, can only
                    detract from its precision and increase the vagueness of the conclusions.
                    Nevertheless, as Coetzee points out, this <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">represents the
                        defeat of any attempt to distinguish between a quality in the text
                            (<soCalled>difficulty</soCalled> or whatever) and a quantity which
                        measures it</quote>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969a">What we hope for is presumably a compromise: neither the
                            extreme simplicity but extreme vagueness of words like
                                <soCalled>difficulty</soCalled>, nor the tautology of the
                            restatement, but a fairly short, fairly precise set of empiric features
                            of the text, between the index and which there is a fairly steady
                            correlation. </quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="228"/>
                    </cit> So, what Coetzee proposes here is that the index will be meaningful if
                    and only if variation in the trace is consistently accompanied in the object
                    text by a commensurate variation in certain other empirically observable
                    features: if, for instance, the trace is higher in one text than another, then
                    we should reasonably be able to expect that the first text will contain fewer
                        <soCalled>clusters</soCalled> of words of more than three syllables – where
                    the term <q>cluster</q> is sufficiently defined – and that this increase ought
                    to be commensurate with the increase in the trace value. </p>
                <p>Having established this basic goal of stylostatistics as exemplified by the Fucks
                    Index, Coetzee demonstrates by counterexample that the specific formula Fucks
                    uses to calculate his trace will not always yield results that stand up to this
                    test: it is possible, he shows, to deliberately construct texts that have either
                    a high trace and a relatively high number of clusters, or a low trace and a
                    relatively low number of clusters. Moreover, the trace tends to accord
                    disproportionate weight to the values generated by words of higher syllabic
                    length: in other words, a text that has a high trace in respect of its
                    constituent mono-, di-, and trisyllabic words may find its overall trace value
                    affected in an exaggerated way by the occurrence of a couple of highly syllabic
                    words. The second of these two problems he considers as one of categorisation:
                        <q>if we are prepared to accept a word of three syllables
                        as <soCalled>difficult</soCalled> for our descriptive purposes</q>, he
                    proposes, then we can accept as valid the revised and more
                        <soCalled>efficient</soCalled> formula he constructs in the essay so as to
                    negate the biases caused by the inclusion in the analysis of those relatively
                    rare words of four or more syllables. The problem with this solution is again
                    one of unavoidable compromise: the more we impose our natural-language
                    definitions on the axioms of number, the more reliable our results will appear,
                    but the more <soCalled>connotative freight</soCalled> the definitions in our
                    conclusions will carry. For this moment at least, Coetzee is prepared to leave
                    this as a methodological dilemma for the stylostatistician: the more troubling
                    implication, however, is that the precision of our quantitative evaluations as
                    such necessarily varies in inverse proportion with their qualitative
                    meaningfulness. </p>
                <p>In <title rend="quotes">Statistical Indices of
                        <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title>, Coetzee's major reservation as to
                    the efficacy of stylostatistical analysis is manifest by the ease with which one
                    might construct a subject text designed specifically to violate the propositions
                    according to which a given index might be said to be
                        <soCalled>meaningful</soCalled>. In the case of the Fucks Index, he
                    attributes the potential for counterexamples to the fact that stylostatistical
                    analysis, like all statistical analyses of natural phenomena, operates not
                    within a fixed, deterministic space, but rather a probability space within which
                    there will inevitably exist superficially troublesome outliers:<note> A
                            <q>space</q> is a structured set of points with fixed definitions
                        regarding the behaviour of the space and the relationship between the
                        points; perhaps the most familiar example is the Euclidean plane. A
                            <q>probability space</q> is a finite space with an associated
                        probability measure that assigns a value between 0 and 1 to the space as a
                        whole. An 'outlier' is an observation that is considered not to conform to
                        the general pattern of a given data set.</note>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969a">language <term xml:lang="fr">en masse</term> exhibits
                            many of the characteristics of chance phenomena, and […] the inverse
                            correlation between the value of the trace and the degree of presence of
                            polysyllables and polysyllable clusters, while not invariable, has a
                            high probability associated with it.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="231"/>
                    </cit> This leaves us in a quandary, for, while it <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">may seem odd at first sight that something which is so
                            largely a matter of design as a literary text should exhibit
                            randomness</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="231"/>
                    </cit>, and, while this <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">kind of breakdown in the trustworthiness of the Fucks
                            trace […] will in practice occur very seldom</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="231"/>
                    </cit>, it is the nature of probabilistic distributions to throw up anomalies
                    such as these without deliberate design. So, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">[w]e cannot, unfortunately, claim that it will never
                            occur, for then we would have to show that texts like [the
                            counterexamples] are not <soCalled>natural</soCalled>, and would
                            inevitably be reduced to talk about intention</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="231"/>
                    </cit>. The thorny problem of intention, and to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969a">texts [that] are constructed with an eye to the code
                            rather than to the message</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969a" loc="231"/>
                    </cit>, had not only been a driving force behind Coetzee's work as a computer
                    poet, but also occupies a significant position in his contemporaneous work on
                    Beckett: by the time his thesis was complete, what might have initially appeared
                    as mere irritations in the practice of a few esoteric critics operating at the
                    limits of stylistic analysis would in fact shed light on problems with a far
                    greater resonance. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3 <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title> (1969) </head>
                <p>While <title rend="quotes">Statistical Indices of
                        <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled></title> might seem rather tentative in its
                    criticism of the orthodoxy of stylostatistics as an academic discipline,
                    Coetzee's doctoral thesis, <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel
                        Beckett</title>, is noticeably more sceptical from the outset. Having by now
                    immersed himself in the discourse of stylostatistical analysis for four years,
                    and having examined the relationship between language, numerical methods,
                    aesthetics, and epistemology from the position of both composer and critic,
                    Coetzee now seemed to be reaching something approaching a resolution to the more
                    profound aspects of his doubts. Crucially, the thesis begins with a reference to
                    a quotation from the mathematician and philosopher David Hilbert: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">In the course of a fusillade against what he calls
                                <q>the revolt against reason</q> in
                            present-day humanistic studies, Joshua Whatmough quotes a pronouncement
                            of David Hilbert's from 1918: <q>Everything that can
                                be an object of scientific thought at all, as soon as it is ripe for
                                the formation of a theory, falls into the lap of the axiomatic
                                method and thereby indirectly of mathematics.</q></quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="1"/>
                    </cit> Literary criticism <term xml:lang="la">qua</term> Whatmough and Hilbert,
                    then, can only be deemed to be <soCalled>scientific</soCalled> if its commitment
                    to the demands of the axiomatic method is absolute, such that its terms and
                    procedures are explicitly and rigidly defined and delineated, immutable, and
                    therefore repeatable and comparable across each and every subject that falls
                    under its critical gaze. Coetzee, however, remained unconvinced by the position
                    represented here by Whatmough and Hilbert; the four years he had spent
                    researching and writing his thesis gave him the critical tools required to
                    critique in minute detail the use of axiomatic methods within literary
                    criticism. It was on this basis that he was consequently able to recognise the
                    extent of the complexities involved in any attempt to disentangle from their
                    nested assumptions a workable distinction between natural language and the
                    language of mathematics. </p>
                <p>In service of his ambitious and interdisciplinary thesis, then, Coetzee
                    establishes his critical methodology as operating within a theoretical space
                    delimited by <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">two poles</quote> of thought he discerns
                    within the existing discourse. The first of these <soCalled>poles</soCalled> he
                    attributes to Bernard Bloch, according to whose <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">classic definition […], style had indeed become an
                            object of scientific thought, was ripe for the formation of a theory,
                            and was falling, not at all indirectly, into the lap of
                            mathematics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="1"/>
                    </cit>. Coetzee exemplifies this definition with a quotation from Bloch in which
                    the American linguist renders the <soCalled>style</soCalled> of a text as
                    reducible to <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">the message carried by the frequency
                        distributions and the transitional probabilities of its linguistic features,
                        especially as they differ from those of the same features in the language as
                        a whole</quote>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="1"/>
                    <ptr target="#bloch1953" loc="42"/>. For Bloch, then, the moment that we
                    conceptualise <soCalled>style</soCalled> as an <quote rend="inline" source="#bloch1953">object of
                        scientific thought</quote> we automatically circumscribe it in terms of a
                    propositional content – its <quote rend="inline" source="#bloch1953">message</quote> – that is fully
                    coextensive, without remainder, with the quantitative description generated by
                    stylostatistical analysis. </p>
                <p>Coetzee's selection of Bloch as the principal representative of his first
                        <soCalled>pole</soCalled> situates the terms of debate in an unmistakably
                    pointed fashion: working within the tradition of his mentor at Yale, Leonard
                    Bloomfield, Bloch was among those most responsible for the development of the
                    discipline of structuralist linguistics. By the time Coetzee came to work on
                        <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title>, this
                    tradition had effectively been superseded in terms of academic prestige by the
                    Standard Theory of generative grammar first outlined by Noam Chomsky in the late
                    1950s. Indeed, in his notes to a 1969 course on <title rend="quotes">English and
                        Linguistics</title>, Coetzee outlines a brief <title rend="quotes">History
                        of Syntax,</title> in which he characterises <title rend="quotes">American
                        Structuralism</title> by way of a single quotation from Bloomfield, the
                    implicit pessimism of which goes some way to indicating the beleaguered state in
                    which this school of linguistics was considered at the time of Coetzee's thesis: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969c">The statement of meanings is […] the weak point in
                            language-study, and will remain so until human knowledge advances very
                            far beyond its present state</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969c"/>
                    </cit>. In the sense that Bloomfield's approach to linguistics was essentially
                    positivist, determinist, and behaviourist – perhaps exemplified at its most
                    extreme in his Laplacian contention that, if only one had sufficient data, then
                    one could predict all future events, including all future speech-acts – it is
                    perhaps unsurprising that the Coetzee of 1969 was interested in but ultimately
                    sceptical of the truth-claims of the discipline Bloomfield's work inaugurated. </p>
                <p>While Coetzee's selection of Bloch as the representative of this
                        <soCalled>pole</soCalled> establishes one horn of the dialectic as a
                    particular strain of structuralist linguistics, then, and hence indicates his
                    entry-point into the discourse to which the thesis ostensibly contributes, his
                    decision to introduce this perspective in the context of two thinkers concerned
                    with, in Hilbert's case, the first principles of mathematical philosophy and, in
                    Whatmough's, <soCalled>the revolt against reason</soCalled>
                        in present-day humanistic studies, indicates from the outset
                    Coetzee's recognition of the potentially widespread ramifications of his own
                    conclusions. The terms through which he expounds his counterpoint to Bloch's
                    position, moreover, delineate the scope of the thesis in accordance not merely
                    within the boundaries of his own work as a stylostatistician, but also in such a
                    way as to facilitate an extended interrogation into certain epistemological
                    issues towards which his prior work had been at most tangentially oriented. He
                    defines the second <soCalled>pole</soCalled> by reference to the views of the
                    principal subject of the thesis, Samuel Beckett, whom he characterises as
                    reacting <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">strongly against any simplification of language […] and
                            indeed against any abstraction from words as counters in a calculus of
                            thought to words as counters in the less flexible calculus of
                            language</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="3"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>At its most fundamental level, then, Coetzee's thesis originates from a
                    compulsion to explore the sense in which Beckett's rejection of the type of
                    abstraction routinely performed by structuralist linguists such as Bloch and
                    Bloomfield constitutes a further denunciation of the apparent ease with which
                    certain terms and categories from the discourses of statistics and probability
                    theory had begun to migrate into humanistic studies. The dextrous manner in
                    which he introduces his negotiation of these terms merits close examination: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">Between the conceptions of style held by Bloch and
                            implied by Beckett there are no doubt similarities: Beckett's
                                <soCalled>writing without style</soCalled> could be interpreted as
                            writing with the statistical features of the language as a whole,
                            whatever that may be. But there is a deeper cleavage which gives the two
                            viewpoints a polar and antithetic relation. Underlying Bloch's
                            definition is the idea of the text as a collection of sets of linguistic
                            features (phonemes, morphemes, words, etc.) which can be treated like
                            members of statistical populations; and a statistical population is only
                            a metaphor for a set of points in probabilistic space. To Bloch, a word
                            can be conveniently reduced, for the purposes of study, to a
                            dimensionless and immaterial point. For Beckett, on the other hand, the
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#beckett1984">terribly arbitrary materiality of the word's
                                surface</quote><note> Coetzee's quotation of the <quote rend="inline" source="#beckett1984">terribly arbitrary materiality of the word's
                                    surface</quote> is a translation from Beckett's original German
                                of the phrase <q>fürchtliche willkürliche Materialität der
                                    Wortfläche</q>. See <title rend="quotes">German Letter of
                                    1937,</title> in <ptr target="#beckett1984" loc="53"/>.</note>
                            is, we infer, at least in 1937, a burden.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="3"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Even as he establishes the nominal focus of <title rend="quotes">The English
                        Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title> as literary <soCalled>style</soCalled>,
                    then, Coetzee indicates that his primary objective is in fact to map the process
                    by which structuralist linguists such as Bloch and Bloomfield sought to
                    transform quality into quantity, texts into statistical populations, and words
                    into dimensionless, immaterial points in probabilistic space. Viewing the
                    resulting map through the lens of Beckett's fiction, he enabled himself to touch
                    upon a variety of issues far beyond the scope of either the traditional form of
                    literary criticism he had undertaken in his MA thesis on <title rend="quotes">The Work of Ford Madox Ford</title>, or the by now stabilising orthodoxy of
                    stylistic analysis as exemplified by the work of Wilhelm Fucks. At issue in the
                    thesis were not only questions of the stylistic qualities of Beckett's work and,
                    by extension, literary texts in general; not merely metatheoretical concerns
                    regarding the discourses and methodologies of stylistics and stylostatistics;
                    and not simply the same problems of meaning construction in mathematics that had
                    exercised Hilbert, Whitehead, and their followers: while <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title> has ramifications for each of
                    these complex fields of study in isolation, its unique value is to be found in
                    its subtle and delicately-handled assimilation of these issues into a more
                    profound and further-reaching philosophical space that drew both its assumptions
                    and its responses to those assumptions from the curious matrix of ideas through
                    which each of these apparently disparate discourses passes during the various
                    stages of their construction. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.1 Traditional Versus Stylostatistical Criticism</head>
                <p>On the basis of his introduction, Coetzee suggests that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">significance of Beckett's attack on
                                <soCalled>style</soCalled> should now be becoming clearer</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>; though its superficial target might well have been the nature of
                    literary language – and especially the nature of any disparities that might
                    obtain between French and English as vehicles of literary expression – Coetzee
                    notes that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">Beckett's description of the <q>materiality of the word's surface</q> pictures language as a
                            wall between objects and their percipients</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. In the context of his own continuing investigation into the relative
                    validity of attempting to build this wall from either linguistic or mathematical
                        <soCalled>bricks</soCalled>, or a combination of the two, it is perhaps
                    useful to note that Coetzee sees the <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">position on
                        style</quote> he adopts in the thesis as being <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">plainly closer to Beckett's than to Bloch’s</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. He locates this position more specifically as one that remains equally
                    unconvinced by the methodologies of, on the one hand, critics whose use of
                    established literary-critical language defers to imprecisely defined <q>connotative freight</q> and, on the other, the prevailing
                    orthodoxies of contemporary stylistics. In the first case, for example, he
                    characterises Hugh Kenner's principal approach as constituting an attempt <q>to catch the essence of Beckett's style in a metaphorical
                        way</q>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">Thus, for example, of the <q>unique
                                translucent enumerating style</q> of <title rend="italic">Watt</title> he writes, <q>It is an austere
                                prose, not narcissistic, nor baroque. It is not opulent. It moves
                                with the great aim of some computation, doing a thousand things but
                                only necessary ones.</q></quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="9–10"/>
                    </cit> Similarly, he explains, Ludovic Janvier's <title rend="italic">Pour
                        Samuel Beckett</title> (1966) <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">has some perceptive pages on the <q>dizziness</q>
                            (vertige) induced in the reader by his mathematical comedy</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="9"/>
                    </cit>. Pointing out that both Kenner and Janvier rely in these instances upon <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">a tradition of literary criticism in which terms like
                                <q>austere</q> have an agreed meaning, and in which insight into the
                            nature of a style is a partly intuitive act</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="10"/>
                    </cit>, Coetzee recognises that though it may neither define its terms with the
                    specificity demanded by the stylostatistician nor proceed from <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">statements which can be verified by quantitative
                            analysis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="10"/>
                    </cit>, this type of traditional criticism nevertheless evades the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">general positivism</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="17"/>
                    </cit> to which he concludes stylistics – particularly in the structuralist
                    tradition represented by Bloomfield and Bloch – had by then become excessively
                    beholden. Stylistic analysis, he continues, is often predicated on ultimately
                    arbitrary processes of division that fail to take sufficient account of the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">artistic whole</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="17"/>
                    </cit> and therefore systematically neglect the fundamental truth that the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">experience of a work of literature is not necessarily
                        linear in time,</quote> and instead tacitly defer to an <q>analogy of reader to decoding device</q> that he considers <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">misleading</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="18"/>
                    </cit>. Coetzee consequently devotes much of <title rend="quotes">The English
                        Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title> to a systematic reconstitution of certain
                    arcane, technical aspects of stylostatistical practice that need not be
                    rehearsed here. More significant for the purposes of the present study are those
                    instances in the course of the thesis in which his more broadly methodological
                    allegiances begin to make themselves known; to this end, Coetzee’s analysis of
                    Beckett’s <title rend="italic">Watt </title>is highly instructive.</p>
                <p>It is probably not too controversial to state baldly that <title rend="italic">Watt</title>, begun in February 1941 and eventually published, following
                    extensive revisions, in 1953, is generally considered to be among Beckett's most
                        <soCalled>mathematical</soCalled> novels. In this sense, Coetzee's comment
                    that the novel's eponymous protagonist is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">like Leibniz's automaton with a spark of life</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="31"/>
                    </cit> and, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">[s]tanding Bergson on his head, […] something living
                            encrusted on the mechanical</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="32"/>
                    </cit> represent additions to an existing consensus rather than anything more
                    revolutionary. To clarify Coetzee's precise conception of Watt's condition,
                    though, one might first note that he considers it to be <quote rend="inline" source="#caetzee1969b">characteristic of Watt that he believes that an empirical question can be
                        solved by logical analysis</quote>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">No empirical data are introduced into his chains of
                            speculation. The multiplication of these chains depends on a maneuver in
                            four stages: statement of a question, proposal of a hypothesis,
                            breakdown of the hypothesis into components, and analysis of the
                            implications of the hypothesis and its components. [...] The third stage
                            typically breaks the chain into two or more branches. The only
                            qualification Watt demands of a hypothesis is that it answer the
                            question: his criterion is one of logic rather than of
                            simplicity.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="81"/>
                    </cit> On the one hand, then, Watt's consciousness represents the very model of
                    the supposedly perfectly closed logical system of mathematics; on the other, his
                    access to the sensory world beyond this closed system introduces experiential
                    data that consistently evade its processes of assimilation and hence are
                    habitually disregarded. This disregard, Coetzee continues, is in fact a <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">disregard for simplicity</quote> and is the <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">foundation of [Watt's] logical comedy, for simplicity is
                            the only criterion that can put a stop to an endless proliferation of
                            logical speculation. In <title rend="italic">Watt</title> we regularly,
                            with a sinking feeling, find ourselves at the beginning of infinite
                            series.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="81"/>
                    </cit> Such is the finite nature of a text – and, indeed, a consciousness –
                    however, that, whatever Watt's predilections, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">the infinite series which automatically spring up must
                            somehow be terminated</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="81"/>
                    </cit>, with inevitably absurd consequences. One such example, Coetzee reminds
                    us, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">terminates in the solipsism that is one of Watt's
                            answers to the infinities of logic: fish that need to rise and fall
                            exist because my naming of them brings them into existence</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="81"/>
                    </cit>. Without the incursion of external experiential data, Watt's case informs
                    us, a closed system of logic shall produce no meaning other than that embedded
                    in its logical categories; without a logical system predicated on experience to
                    guide its selections, however, the process through which such experiential data
                    are collected is as likely to cause the regression to terminate in absurdity as
                    in rationality; and without a referential framework in which to compare our
                    findings, moreover, we must conclude that we shall inevitably have no means of
                    telling the difference. </p>
                <p>Watt's consciousness, then, is analogous to the type of deterministic formal
                    axiomatic system of which the modern computer is perhaps the most familiar
                    model. Built from a series of axioms or rules for behaviour, the system is set
                    into motion by the intrusion of an essentially arbitrary piece of empirical
                    data, which consequently acts as its originary affirmation. As Coetzee explains,
                    with every passing instance in which Watt initiates an exhaustive combinatorial
                    analysis in response to a particular set of circumstances, the reader gains a
                    cumulative sense of the inextricability of his condition; the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">attempt to understand the nature of the simplest
                            sensory perceptions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="35"/>
                    </cit>, he elaborates, leads to a paradox born of the complex, self-referential
                    nature of the concept of infinity.</p>
                <p>Without the means to make qualitative value distinctions beyond the basic logical
                    tools with which he is endowed, then, Watt is radically unable to determine the
                    limit-point at which his analysis of each given set of circumstances might be
                    said to approximate truth to an extent sufficient to justify action. Indeed, the
                    very idea of cause and effect becomes more and more undermined as Watt's
                    experience becomes progressively <soCalled>inverted</soCalled>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">The explosion of logic, epistemology, and ontology takes
                            Watt into another zone (the asylum) in which he lives a progressively
                            inverse life. Decline and inversion are reflected in Watt's language, as
                            reported by the narrator Sam. Decline and inversion constitute what I
                            call the shape of the telos. What is still lacking is the causal
                            element. For certain reasons a certain kind of man experiences a call to
                            a certain kind of situation, and the result is decline and inversion: we
                            see the results but not the causes, unless we take the step of calling
                            Watt's whole universe absurd.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="35–36"/>
                    </cit> It is in a similar context in the essay <title rend="quotes">Samuel
                        Beckett and the Temptations of Style</title>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1973a"/> – the last to be published of the three journal
                    articles he adapted from <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel
                        Beckett</title> – that Coetzee introduces Richard Dedekind's hypothesis to
                    the effect that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">[i]f we can justify an initial segmentation of a set
                            into classes X and not-X [...], the whole structure of mathematics will
                            follow as a gigantic footnote</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973a" loc="43"/>
                    </cit>. Given that this constitutes one among very few additions he made in the
                    process of distilling sections from his thesis into forms suitable for
                    publication as journal articles, one might suggest that this aspect of his study
                    had taken on a greater significance in his thinking during the four years
                    between the completion of the thesis and the publication of the article. In
                    Coetzee's characterisation of them, both Dedekind and Beckett are <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">mathematician enough to appreciate</quote> that, on the basis
                    of merely one <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">single sure affirmation,</quote> a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">whole contingent world […] can, with a little patience,
                            a little diligence, be deduced</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973a" loc="43"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.2 Stylostatistics as a Constructivist Discipline</head>
                <p>Through an analogy with the analysis of <title rend="italic">Watt </title>that he
                    undertakes in <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel
                    Beckett</title>, then, one can clearly observe Coetzee's recognition that even a
                    representational framework so seemingly free from interference from the world of
                    unnegated affirmation as stylostatistical analysis serves as a model for
                    rejecting the <soCalled>reality</soCalled> of truths developed within closed
                    meaning systems, in favour of picturing them as merely constructivist: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">On the other hand, the smallest amplifications of
                            meaning, particularly those which were probably not under the conscious
                            control of the author - - for example, the frequencies of the words in
                            the text - - show, when quantified, what looks suspiciously like system,
                            i.e. they act like well-behaved mathematical functions. Turning the
                            syllogism upside down, we infer that well-behaved mathematical functions
                            defined on the quantified components of the text define components that
                            belong to the smaller amplifications of meaning.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="40"/>
                    </cit> In other words, certain initial – and often subconscious – affirmations
                    are ultimately responsible for determining the nature of both the component
                    features we discern as constitutive of a given text and the types of
                    mathematical function that appear to describe or even govern their behaviour.
                    Once a reader makes these affirmations, both the nominal and the functional
                    aspects of the text become ontologically linked in a manner that has
                    astonishingly little to do with the ontological status of the text prior to
                    those affirmations. Extrapolating this observation to the use of natural
                    language alongside quantitative evaluations, one can see the potential for such
                    frameworks to engender obfuscation rather than the desired objective clarity. In
                    Coetzee's example, for instance, one might question the effect of introducing an
                    index for a term such as <q>elevation in diction</q> as a descriptor for certain
                    textual features, other than to provide a misleading <soCalled>connotative
                        freight</soCalled>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">By the time sufficiently many literary works have been
                            described in terms of the same measures, the measures themselves may
                            come to have associative values with different texts. We may find, for
                            example, that a high noun-to-adjective ratio is common to Pliny and
                            Thomas à Kempis, a low ratio to Virgil and Tacitus. The ratio may then
                            become associated with a quality we may call elevation in diction. But
                            ultimately elevation will have to be defined in terms of the
                            noun-to-adjective ratio and other measures. There is no escape from the
                            absolute measure of quantification here. </quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="44"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>More troublingly, perhaps, it is not just in descriptive terms of this nature
                    that we encounter such a problem: the origins of even the most apparently basic
                    linguistic terminology are equally as precarious: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">a little computation shows us that, whatever definitions
                            of noun and verb we adopt, their effect on the noun-to-verb ratio, while
                            greater than the effect introduced by the uncertainties created by
                            implicit nouns and verbs, is considerably less than the effect that
                            could be introduced by uncertainties in the classifications <q>noun</q>
                            and <q>verb</q> […]. It does imply that the potential for disastrous
                            error is high when we depend on figures not derived from identical and
                            therefore exhaustive definitions of noun and verb for the purpose of
                            comparing the <q>nominalism</q> of different texts and authors.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="46"/>
                    </cit> Coetzee draws attention here, then, to the fatal circularity of any
                    analysis that fails from the outset to recognise the uncertainties inherent in
                    categorisations even as seemingly fundamental as <q>noun</q> or <q>verb</q>.
                    Generally, the comparison of the works of any two authors requires strict
                    definition of the terms of that comparison: the result of this comparison,
                    however, is destined ultimately to become primarily a comment on the act of
                    definition that has taken place, rather than on any inherent quality of the
                    texts or authors themselves. To Coetzee's mind, the only conceivable solution to
                    this problem that might help to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">square intuition with mathematics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="49"/>
                    </cit> would be to refine the precision of our terminological definitions:
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">our only recourse</quote>, he explains, <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">is therefore to assign different numerical weights to
                        different nouns and verbs, based on such criteria as their rarity, their
                        degree of compoundness, etc</quote>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="49"/>. Just like Watt, however, we soon find
                    ourselves at the beginning of an infinite regression: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">But now we have opened the floodgates. For we are not
                            concerned, for example, with absolute rarity (whatever that is) but with
                            rarity in a context. The position becomes untenable, for no
                            generalization is possible, and the reason for computing to ratio in the
                            first place is to have a measure of nominalism in the text, i.e. to have
                            a generalization about a certain aggregate of particulars.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="49"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Ultimately, we are left to conclude that the use of the same index on two
                    separate occasions is logically counter-intuitive: whereas two words could
                    previously become <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">equal by being used with the same
                        frequency</quote>, Coetzee explains, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">the notion of equality in meaning is tenuous</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="50"/>
                    </cit>. The consequences for stylostatistics, as the following quotation
                    suggests, are effectively fatal: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">We are faced, then, with a story in which statistical
                            analysis of the distribution of vocabulary, classification of the less
                            neutral diction, and analysis <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi> of
                            sentence structure, seem at best only to confirm our understanding of
                            the structure of the work and at worst to remain trapped in their own
                            terminology.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="54"/>
                    </cit> As such, then, these <soCalled>amplifications of
                        meaning</soCalled> – affirmations for which the critic is solely responsible,
                    ranging from the grouping of verbs under some grammatical concept such as
                    transitivity (<q>hold</q> with <q>throw</q> and <q>reveal</q> for example) to
                    the less robustly delineable association of nouns on a semantic basis
                        (<q>building</q> with <q>edifice</q> and <q>construction</q>) – are
                    necessarily echoed in the <soCalled>function</soCalled> that analysis of them
                    reveals. In other words, in stylostatistics, as in mathematics generally, our
                    observable and delineable data and our modes of observation and analysis are
                    irrevocably bound up with one another and, in a sense, offer little more than
                    tautology. </p>
                <p>Perhaps the most critical of all Coetzee's observations in <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title>, though, corresponds to a
                    brief, aborted train of thought explored in an endnote that, though it is not
                    followed through to its completion in the thesis, ramifies throughout his
                    contemporaneous work. How is it, he wonders, that certain linguistic phenomena,
                    such as the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">inverse relation […] between rank and frequency</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="240"/>
                    </cit> of lexical items in an object text are <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1969b">describable in mathematically simple terms?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="240"/>
                    </cit>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1969b">Is it coincidence, or is it one instance of isomorphism
                            between the structure of language and the structure of mathematics? In
                            the first case the Zipf-Mandelbrot law<note> As Coetzee defines it in
                                his essay on Beckett's <title rend="italic">Lessness</title>, the
                                Zipf-Mandelbrot Law describes the phenomenon such that <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">in normal discourse each extension of the length
                                    of the text adds, though more and more slowly, to the number of
                                    different lexical items called on.</quote> See <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="195"/>.</note> is a useful
                            descriptive fact, loosely a <q>law.</q> In the
                            second case it is indeed tautologous, but the consequences are too
                            immense to bear contemplation. </quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1969b" loc="240–241"/>
                    </cit></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4 Review of Wilhelm Fucks’ <title rend="italic">Nach allen Regeln der
                        Kunst</title> (1971) </head>
                <p>Coetzee, then, was unwilling to contemplate in the context of his doctoral thesis
                    the <soCalled>immense</soCalled> consequences attendant on the
                    possibility that the structure of natural language and the structure of
                    mathematics might be isomorphic. However, on the basis of Coetzee's second
                    published discussion of the work of Wilhelm Fucks – a 1971 review of the German
                    linguist's 1968 work, <title rend="italic">Nach allen Regeln der Kunst </title>–
                    one gets a clear sense of his attitude towards the philosophical machinery of
                    statistical analysis such as it emerged from his immersion in that discourse
                    during the late 1960s. Nowhere is his ambivalence towards the wider potential
                    consequences of a positivism founded on the migration of mathematical structures
                    into ostensibly non-mathematical concerns better encapsulated than in his
                    review's vivid opening description, in which he depicts Fucks as either a
                    far-sighted visionary or a reductivist brute: <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">Depending on
                        how you view him,</quote> he begins, <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1971">Wilhelm Fucks is a polymath of refreshing synoptic
                            vision or another of those muscle-men of statistics (Yule, Herdan et
                            al.) to whom a ward of kwashiorkor<note> Common in areas experiencing
                                drought and famine, and characterised most visibly by the distension
                                of the sufferer's abdomen, kwashiorkor is a form of malnutrition
                                that results from insufficient intake of protein.</note> victims or
                            a page of print is first of all a set of quantifiable phenomena and only
                            secondarily people or literature.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit> Given that Coetzee was already by this stage developing a dramatisation
                    of an extremely similar process in <title rend="italic">Dusklands</title>, it
                    seems especially significant that he chose in this review to extrapolate from
                    Fucks' seemingly harmless literary exercises to an apparently genuine fear that
                    the possible emergence of a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">speakable formalized language</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit>, developed <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">as a universal language for the technocratic
                            elite</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit>, might <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">tie succeeding generations into a twentieth century
                            positivist mythology more tightly than natural languages tie us into the
                            mythologies of the past</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>The essential purpose of <title rend="italic">Nach allen Regeln der
                    Kunst</title>, Coetzee explains, is to reiterate <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">the theme that the artist, like any other organism,
                            exhibits regularities of behaviour, which can be exposed by statistical
                            analysis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>, thereby revealing <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">the elegantly formulable mathematical distributions
                            underlying such phenomena as the lengths of sentences in a text and the
                            pitches of note-pairs in a concerto</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>. Given the philosophical reservations upon which he had predicated the
                    ambivalence at the heart of his doctoral thesis, then, it comes as no surprise
                    to find that Coetzee's response to such a project as Fucks's is at best
                    cautious. Inasmuch as it in principle welcomes the advent of a general
                    introduction to a discourse in which he was himself at this point still
                    relatively heavily intellectually invested, Coetzee's review initially praises
                    Fucks for his capacity to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">explain so patiently and with such lavish visual aids
                            his basic procedures</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit> and hence render <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">seductive […] a field which many think of as rather
                            arid</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>. Equally, while the book is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">emphatically not a handbook</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>, and does not constitute <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">a compendium of investigations into intrinsically
                            interesting stylistic topics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>, it nevertheless contains examples of such investigations that may indeed
                        <q>seduce</q> the non-specialist reader, not least by indicating the value
                    of stylostatistical procedures beyond the academy; in a chapter pointedly
                    entitled <title rend="quotes">Literary Criminology</title>, for instance, Fucks
                    demonstrates <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">inter alia that the Gospel of St. John and Apocalypse
                            are probably not from the same hand</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92"/>
                    </cit>, thereby intimating not only the literary value of such practice, but
                    also alluding to its potentially crucial application in the courtroom. </p>
                <p>Coetzee's praise is tempered, however, by his enduring conviction that the means
                    through which stylostatistical analysis enacts its negotiation between the
                    qualitative and the quantitative is intrinsically flawed. While any <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">reasonable man must be convinced that regularities of
                            all kinds, regularities of stress, of syntax, of word choice, and so
                            forth, run through literary compositions, [and] that the set of these
                            patterns comprises a great deal of what we call style</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="93"/>
                    </cit>, it nevertheless remains the case that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">overwhelming proportion of [stylostatistical indices]
                            either have no critical application or represent quantitative
                            restatements of qualitative propositions (<q>A's verse is more varied
                                than B’s</q>)</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="93"/>
                    </cit>. As he had earlier expressed at greater length in <title rend="quotes">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett</title>, Coetzee points out that this
                    problem is predicated in the first instance on the fact that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">kind of datum that the statisticians, Fucks included,
                            feel at home with is extremely elementary: word length, sentence length,
                            ictus, grammatical class, depth of subordination</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="93"/>
                    </cit>, and that he or she will only escape rather prosaic conclusions by
                    producing <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">a whole new typology of structures</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="93"/>
                    </cit> and programming his or her computer with procedures that are able to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">classify and count in a much more complex way</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit> than those that the discourse of the time seemed happy to accept. </p>
                <p>While the review is essentially concerned with commenting upon Fucks's
                    contribution to the discipline of stylistics, then, Coetzee's more considered
                    conclusions refer not strictly to issues of literary criticism, but instead to
                    an epistemological model that stylostatistical analysis covertly advocates. By
                    suggesting that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">it would be fairest to take this book as a work of
                            propaganda, a work intended to convince the uninitiated first that there
                            are regularities they had never suspected underlying behaviour</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92–93"/>
                    </cit>, Coetzee draws attention to the surreptitiously political nature of any
                    attempt to specify and formalise these <q>regularities</q>. Fucks, he explains, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">has a distaste for the <soCalled>swarms of associations
                                and emotions</soCalled> that accompany reading and for the
                                <soCalled>whole layers of primitive taboos and antiquated
                                mythology</soCalled> concealed in natural languages</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit> and hence prefers to reduce linguistic behaviour to those <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">formal phenomena of the printed text</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit> that happen, by virtue of their accordance with conveniently quantifiable
                    structures, to be amenable to inclusion within an <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">objective descriptive aesthetics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit> that is unified, comprehensive, and hence logically closed. </p>
                <p>By the end of the review, then, one is left with the clear message that, whereas
                    Fucks' <q>propaganda</q> is aimed towards assuring his
                    readers that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">a literary science of exact numerical description is a
                            good thing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="92–93"/>
                    </cit>, Coetzee is concerned here, as elsewhere throughout his work as a
                    stylostatistician, to highlight the ramifications of believing, as Fucks does,
                    in the merits of an <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">objective analysis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit>, even where this necessitates that we <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">omit a great deal</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit> in our description of the phenomenon under observation. It is in the
                    final paragraph of the piece, indeed, that Coetzee briefly discusses Fucks'
                    contemplation of the potential development of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">a <q>speakable formalized
                                language</q> as a universal language for the technocratic
                            elite</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>
                    </cit>. Though Fucks is aware of <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1971">Whorf's thesis that
                        languages have built-in epistemological biases</quote>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1971" loc="94"/>, Coetzee notes in pointed fashion the
                    book's failure to consider the possible ramifications for a future society in
                    which the language developed by the <soCalled>linguistic engineers</soCalled>
                    has enshrined in its users a positivist mythology with an even greater
                    delimiting power than 'natural language' has had on the cultures of the past and
                    present. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5 <title rend="quotes">Samuel Beckett's <title rend="italic">Lessness</title>:
                        An Exercise in Decomposition</title> (1973) </head>
                <p>In some regards, Coetzee's route from the review of <title rend="italic">Nach
                        allen Regeln der Kunst </title>to <title rend="italic">Dusklands </title>is
                    not difficult to retrace. In the most explicit thematic sense, for instance, the
                    essay prepares the context for the rationale that the two protagonists of that
                    novel share: a relentless positivist rationality, designed to locate and exploit
                    regularities underlying the thought and behaviour of others. In the final piece
                    of stylostatistical work he was to publish, however, there emerge other, more
                    subtle connections in his contemporaneous thought. Appearing in its English
                    version in 1970 – having originally been published in French, as <title rend="italic">Sans</title>, in 1969 – the subject text of Coetzee's <title rend="quotes">Exercise in Decomposition</title> displays, in his words, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">features not often encountered in connected
                            discourse</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="195"/>
                    </cit>. The <q>most notable</q> of these, Coetzee
                    elaborates, is its <q>finiteness</q>: in the sense that
                    the text of <title rend="italic">Lessness</title> is divided into two halves,
                    each consisting of the same sixty sentences, only in a different order, the
                    novella's linguistic resources are limited to just 166 lexical items, a <soCalled>finite subset</soCalled> of the natural language, English, from
                    whose theoretically infinite resources it is ultimately drawn. <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">It is this fact,</quote> Coetzee states, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">which suggests a mathematical approach to the text, an
                            approach not only via the mathematics of indeterminacy, namely
                            probability theory […] but also via combinatorial mathematics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="195"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>From this starting point, Coetzee first establishes by means of Spearman's rank
                    correlation coefficient<note> Spearman's rank correlation coefficient is a
                        measure of the correlation between two variables in a bivariate data set.
                        For example, if one wanted to measure the degree to which the height and
                        mass of each individual in a given set of <emph>n </emph>students are
                        correlative, one would first rank the students according to each of the two
                        variables (height and mass), calculate the difference in ranks for each
                        student (<emph>d</emph>) and then calculate the coefficient using the
                        formula: <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                        </figure>The resulting coefficient (<emph>r</emph><hi rend="subscript">s
                        </hi>)ranges from 1 (perfect positive correlation), through 0 (no
                        correlation), to -1 (perfect negative correlation).</note> that one cannot
                    dismiss <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">with any acceptable degree of certainty</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="195"/>
                    </cit> the hypothesis that the re-ordering of the sentences is effectively
                    random. From here, he next determines that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">unit of combination in <title rend="italic">Lessness</title> is not the word but the phrase of one or more
                            words</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="196"/>
                    </cit>, and that, by using a specified algorithm, we are enabled to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">obtain an unambiguous segmentation of the text into 106
                            different phrases varying in length from 1 to 12 words and occurring, on
                            an average, 5.7 times each</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="197"/>
                    </cit>. He goes on to demonstrate by means of methods drawn from statistics and
                    probability theory that there are <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">no closed subsets of phrases</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="197"/>
                    </cit>, that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">there is no statistical reason for rejecting the
                            hypothesis that phrases are distributed randomly over paragraphs</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="197"/>
                    </cit>, and that the occurrence of any <soCalled>clusters</soCalled> of phrases
                    that do happen to form throughout the text <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">do not fall into any […] elementary patterns</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="197"/>
                    </cit>. <title rend="italic">Lessness</title>, in short, exhibits randomness at
                    practically every conceivable textual level, actively evading capture within
                    mathematically expressible system at every turn. </p>
                <p>In the sense that it generates a relatively mechanistic and conventional form of
                    analysis, and as such is fairly typical of the discourse of computer-assisted
                    literary criticism as it existed in 1973, <title rend="quotes">Samuel Beckett's
                            <title rend="italic">Lessness</title>: An Exercise in
                        Decomposition</title> might to this point seem at best unexceptional, and at
                    worst academically indulgent. Where the essay offers an especial insight into
                    Coetzee's intellectual development, however, is in its philosophical
                    interpretation of Beckett's revolt against system. Coetzee begins this
                    interpretation, then, by establishing that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">Beckett's most recent fictions, the <title rend="italic">Residua</title>, of which <title rend="italic">Lessness</title> is one, portray an existence whose conditions are
                            stripped further and further down</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit>. This <soCalled>stripping-down</soCalled> is constituted of three
                        <soCalled>levels,</soCalled> which Coetzee characterises as follows: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1973b">The first level of this consciousness contains a past
                            womb-existence, a set of figments. The second level contains the
                            figments of the new fiction <hi rend="italic">Lessness</hi> that the
                            consciousness now inhabits: ruin, sand, body, etc. The third level
                            contains only the pair dawn-dusk, each of which eventually cancels both
                            the other and the figments for which the other is responsible.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>In <title rend="quotes">Samuel Beckett and the Temptations of Style</title>
                    <ptr target="#coetzee1973a"/>, moreover, he explains that in <title rend="italic">Lessness </title><quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">an infinite series of
                        nested consciousnesses, each dismissing the figments of its predecessor, is
                        presented in the paradigm of a two-component switching mechanism,</quote>
                    each of which ultimately <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">annihilates the figments of the other</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973a" loc="46"/>
                    </cit>. As a writer whose novels often play with multi-level stagings of
                    competing editorial effacement – most prominently, perhaps, in <title rend="italic">Dusklands</title>, <title rend="italic">In the Heart of the
                        Country</title>, <title rend="italic">Foe</title>, and <title rend="italic">Slow Man</title> – Coetzee's location of this process in <title rend="italic">Lessness</title> presents one point of methodological kinship.
                    Most interesting, however, is his attribution to Beckett of a particular
                    conception of consciousness, its representation in an apparently linear text,
                    and the value of using a mathematical analysis to determine a means for
                    exploring issues without succumbing to commitment or belief in any component met
                    along the way. In his essay, Coetzee demonstrates that <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973a">there are no determinate principles of ordering among phrases, sentences or
                        paragraphs, yet that all are interdependent and connected</quote> and that,
                    consequently, there is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">no principle of hierarchy or priority among the
                            components of the work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit>. The upshot of this lack of <soCalled>hierarchy or
                        priority</soCalled> is that any of the millions of alternative re-orderings
                    Beckett may have chosen to publish would be as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">valid as fiction</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit> as that which was, in fact, published. Similarly, the final, linear
                    ordering of the fragments is less expressive of the fundamental meaning of the
                    text than is the process through which the text came to be: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1973b">Since any fragment can combine with any other fragment,
                            and since the 106 phrasal components are not only formal elements but
                            also pretty irreducible elements of meaning, composition is a
                            combinatorial game played with creations of what I have called the
                            second level of the imagining consciousness – a level whose creations
                            are dismissed as figments – and the upshot of the game is nothing more
                            than what Sam, in <title rend="italic">Watt</title>, called <q>a pillow of old words.</q></quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Ultimately, then, Coetzee proposes that one ought not to take too seriously any
                    cumulative effects resultant from the essentially arbitrary route taken by the
                    consciousness enacted through Beckett's fiction, but rather to the ephemeral,
                    non-linear motions through which it passes within the working-out of its finite
                    process: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#coetzee1973b">The residue of the fiction is not then the final
                            disposition of the fragments but the motions of the consciousness that
                            disposes them according to the rules we have traced, and no doubt others
                            we have failed to trace.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit> The <soCalled>subject of <title rend="italic">Lessness</title></soCalled>, he ultimately concludes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coetzee1973b">is the plight of consciousness in a void, compelled to
                            reflect on itself, capable of doing so only by splitting itself and
                            recombining the fragments in wholes which are never greater than the
                            sums of their parts</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coetzee1973b" loc="198"/>
                    </cit>. Reflecting back upon Coetzee's own novels, one may note that it is far
                    from coincidental that many of them – <hi rend="italic">Dusklands</hi>, <hi rend="italic">In the Heart of the Country</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Foe</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">Disgrace</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Elizabeth Costello</hi>,
                    and <hi rend="italic">Diary of a Bad Year</hi> in particular – are not unlike
                        <hi rend="italic">Lessness</hi>, in the sense that they represent the
                    motions of a consciousness through an apparently disordered maze of assertions,
                    appearing to enact a cumulative process as the consciousness experiences,
                    affirms, and effaces various propositions, often paired in binary oppositions,
                    before seemingly arriving at fixed conclusions by the novel's end. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6 Conclusions</head>
                <p>While the force of Coetzee’s conclusions in relation to the discipline as it
                    stands today remains very much up for debate, his work during the period under
                    observation here offers a unique perspective not only on the early years of the
                    field of digital humanities, but also on the intellectual development of one of
                    the most significant novelists of the late twentieth and early twenty-first
                    centuries: one rarely emerges from the revolutionary battles of one's youth
                    unmarked, and it might be said that in order to locate those marks in the war
                    stories of a veteran, one need not only know that the war happened, but also the
                    detail of each particular battle in which the storyteller fought. As such, the
                    consequences of the present paper are threefold: firstly, critics of Coetzee’s
                    writing ought to approach the thematisation of quantification — particularly in
                    such works as <title rend="italic">Dusklands </title>(1974), <title rend="italic">In the Heart of the Country </title>(1977), <title rend="italic">Waiting for the Barbarians </title>(1980), <title rend="italic">Diary of a Bad Year </title>(2007), and <title rend="italic">The Childhood of Jesus </title>(2013) — with a greater sensitivity to the
                    questions raised here; secondly, the contemporary manifestations of those areas
                    of digital humanities with which Coetzee’s work intersects might now need to
                    reflect upon how to negotiate the paradoxes associated with quantification in
                    meaning construction, such as he has diagnosed them; and finally, we must all
                    now recognise the value of the contribution made by this most enquiring and
                    incisive of literary minds to the field of digital humanities as a whole.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="attridge2004" label="Attridge 2004"> Attridge, D. 2004. <title rend="italic">J. M. Coetzee and the Ethics of Reading.</title> Chicago:
                    University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="attwell1993" label="Attwell 1993"> Attwell, D. 1993. <title rend="italic">J. M. Coetzee: South Africa and the Politics of
                        Writing.</title> Berkeley: University of California Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beckett1959" label="Beckett 1959"> Beckett, S. 1959. <title rend="italic">Watt.</title> New York: Grove Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beckett1970" label="Beckett 1970"> Beckett, S. 1970. <title rend="italic">Lessness.</title> London: Calder &amp; Boyars.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beckett1984" label="Beckett 1984"> Beckett, S. and Cohn, R. 1984.
                        <title rend="italic">Disjecta.</title> New York: Grove Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="begam1992" label="Begam 1992"> Begam, R. 1992. An interview with JM
                    Coetzee. <title rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</title>, 33 (3), pp.
                    419-431.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bloch1953" label="Bloch 1953"> Bloch, B. 1953. Linguistic Structure
                    and Linguistic Analysis. In: Hill, A. eds. 1953. Washington DC: Georgetown
                    University, pp. 40-44.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrows2002" label="Burrows 2002"> Burrows, J. 2002. <title rend="quotes">Delta</title>: A Measure of Stylistic Difference and a Guide
                    to Likely Authorship <title rend="italic">Literary &amp; Linguistic
                        Computing</title>, 17 (3): 267-287. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="canepari-labib2005" label="Canepari-Labib 2005"> Canepari-Labib, M.
                    2005. <title rend="italic">Old Myths - Modern Empires</title>. Oxford: Peter
                    Lang.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1963a" label="Coetzee 1963a"> Coetzee, J. M. 1963. <title rend="italic">The Work of Ford Madox Ford</title>. MA. University of Cape
                    Town.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1963b" label="Coetzee 1963b"> Coetzee, J. M. 1963. Computer
                    Poem. <title rend="italic">The Lion and the Impala</title>, 2 (1), pp.
                    12-13.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1969a" label="Coetzee 1969a"> Coetzee, J. M. 1969. Statistical
                    Indices of <soCalled>Difficulty</soCalled>, <title rend="italic">Language and
                        Style</title> 2 (3), pp. 226-232. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1969b" label="Coetzee 1969b"> Coetzee, J. M. 1969. <title rend="italic">The English Fiction of Samuel Beckett: An Essay in Stylistic
                        Analysis</title>. Ph.D. University of Texas at Austin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1969c" label="Coetzee 1969c"> Coetzee, J. M. 1969. <title rend="italic">English/Linguistics 211</title>. [Lecture Notes]. National
                    English Literary Museum, Grahamstown.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1971" label="Coetzee 1971"> Coetzee, J. M. 1971. Review of
                    Wilhelm Fucks, Nach allen Regeln der Kunst. <title rend="italic">Style</title>,
                    5 (1), pp. 92-94.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1973a" label="Coetzee 1973a"> Coetzee, J. M. 1973. Samuel
                    Beckett and the Temptations of Style. In: Coetzee, J. M. and Attwell, D. eds.
                    1992. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, pp. 43-49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1973b" label="Coetzee 1973b"> Coetzee, J. M. 1973. Samuel
                    Beckett's Lessness: An Exercise in Decomposition. <title rend="italic">Computers
                        and the Humanities</title>, 7 (4), pp. 195--198.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1974" label="Coetzee 1974"> Coetzee, J. M. 1974. <title rend="italic">Dusklands</title>. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1977" label="Coetzee 1977"> Coetzee, J. M. 1977. <title rend="italic">In the Heart of the Country</title>. London: Secker &amp;
                    Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1978" label="Coetzee 1978"> Coetzee, J. M. 1978. Hero and Bad
                    Mother in Epic, a Poem. <title rend="italic">Staffrider</title>, March p.
                    36.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1980" label="Coetzee 1980"> Coetzee, J. M. 1980. <title rend="italic">Waiting for the Barbarians</title>. London: Secker &amp;
                    Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1986" label="Coetzee 1986"> Coetzee, J. M. 1986. <title rend="italic">Foe</title>. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1997" label="Coetzee 1997"> Coetzee, J. M. 1997. <title rend="italic">Boyhood: Scenes From Provincial Life</title>. London: Secker
                    &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee1999" label="Coetzee 1999"> Coetzee, J. M. 1999. <title rend="italic">Disgrace</title>. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee2002" label="Coetzee 2002"> Coetzee, J. M. 2002. <title rend="italic">Youth</title>. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee2003" label="Coetzee 2003"> Coetzee, J. M. 2003. <title rend="italic">Elizabeth Costello</title>. London: Secker &amp;
                    Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee2005" label="Coetzee 2005"> Coetzee, J. M. 2005. <title rend="italic">Slow Man</title>. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee2007" label="Coetzee 2007"> Coetzee, J. M. 2007. <title rend="italic">Diary of a Bad Year</title>. London: Harvill Secker.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzee2013" label="Coetzee 2013"> Coetzee, J. M. 2007. <title rend="italic">The Childhood of Jesus</title>. London: Jonathan Cape.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coetzeeandattwell1992" label="Coetzee and Attwell 1992"> Coetzee, J.
                    M. and Attwell, D. 1992. <title rend="italic">Doubling the Point</title>.
                    Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="craig1999" label="Craig 1999"> Craig, H. Authorial Attribution and
                    Computational Stylistics: If You Can Tell Authors Apart, Have You Learned
                    Anything About Them?<title rend="italic"> Literary &amp; Linguistic
                        Computing</title>, 14 (1): 103-113. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="egerer1999" label="Egerer 1999"> Egerer, C. 1999. Hybridizing the
                    Zero: Exploring Alternative Strategies of Empowerment in J. M. Coetzee’s Foe.
                        <title rend="italic">Joensuu: Studia Carelica Humanistica</title>, 14 pp.
                    96-101.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="forsyth1999" label="Forsyth et al. 1999"> Forsyth, R. S., D. Holmes,
                    and E. Tse. 1999. <title rend="quotes">Cicero, Sigonio, and Burrows:
                        Investigating the Authenticity of the Consolatio.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>, 14:
                    375–400.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fromm2000" label="Fromm 2000"> Fromm, H. 2000. Coetzee's Postmodern
                    Animals. <title rend="italic">The Hudson Review</title>, 53 (2), pp.
                    336-344.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="head1997" label="Head 1997"> Head, D. 1997. <title rend="italic">J.M.
                        Coetzee</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="holmes2001" label="Holmes et al. 2001"> Holmes, D. I., M. Robertson,
                    and R. Paez. Stephen Crane and the New York Tribune: A Case Study in Traditional
                    and Non-Traditional Authorship Attribution. <title rend="italic">Computers and
                        the Humanities</title> 35.3: 315–31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jahn2007" label="Jahn 2007"> Jahn, C. 2007. <title rend="italic">J.M.
                        Coetzee : Novelist and Moralist</title>. Norderstedt, Germany: GRIN
                    Verlag.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lamb2010" label="Lamb 2010"> Lamb, J. 2010. <title rend="quotes">The
                        true words at last from the mind in ruins</title>: J. M. Coetzee and
                    Realism. In: Bradshaw, G. and Neill, M. eds. 2014. <title rend="italic">J. M.
                        Coetzee's Austerities</title>. London: Ashgate, pp. 177-183.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kannemeyer2012" label="Kannemeyer 2012"> Kannemeyer, J. C. 2012.
                        <title rend="italic">J.M. Coetzee: A Life in Writing</title>. London:
                    Scribe.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kossew1996" label="Kossew 1996"> Kossew, S. 1996. <title rend="italic">Pen and Power</title>. Amsterdam: Atlanta.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="leavis1930" label="Leavis 1930"> Leavis, F. R. 1930. Mass Civilisation
                    and Minority Culture. In: Storey, J. eds. 2006. <title rend="italic">Cultural
                        Theory and Popular Culture: A Reader</title>. Harlow: Prentice Hall.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mulhall2009" label="Mulhall 2009"> Mulhall, S. 2009. <title rend="italic">The Wounded Animal</title>. Princeton: Princeton University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="paling2009" label="Paling 2009"> Paling, S. 2009. Mapping
                    Techno-Literary Spaces: Adapting Multiple Correspondence Analysis for Literature
                    and Art Informatics. <title rend="italic">Information Research</title>, 14(2)
                    paper 401.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips1998" label="Phillips 1998"> Phillips, C. 1998. Life and Times
                    of John C. <title rend="italic">English in Africa</title>, 25 (1), pp.
                    61-70.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011"> Ramsay, Stephen. 2011. <title rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>.
                    Chicago: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scott1997" label="Scott 1997"> Scott, Joanna. 1997. <title rend="quotes">Voice and Trajectory: An Interview with J. M. Coetzee.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Salmagundi: A Quarterly of the Humanities and Social
                        Sciences</title>, 114-115, (Spring-Summer 1997): 82–102.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="silvani2012" label="Silvani 2012"> Silvani, R. 2012. <title rend="italic">Political Bodies and the Body Politic in J.M. Coetzee's
                        Novels</title>. Zürich: LIT.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stewart2003" label="Stewart 2003"> Stewart, Larry L. 2003. Charles
                    Brockden Brown: Quantitative Analysis and Literary Interpretation <title rend="italic">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>, 18 (2): 129-138. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanzantengallagher1991" label="Vanzanten Gallagher 1991"> Vanzanten
                    Gallagher, S. 1991. <title rend="italic">A Story of South Africa: J. M.
                        Coetzee's Fiction in Context</title>. Cambridge: Harvard U.P.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>