<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="review" xml:lang="en">Gapping the Map: Indigenous Presence in Native Land
               Digital</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Anja <dhq:family>Keil</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-6751-8777</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>The College of William &amp; Mary</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>akeil@wm.edu </email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Anja Keil is a PhD student in American Studies at the College of William &amp;
                     Mary, Virginia. Her research interests lie at the intersection of migration
                     studies, trauma studies, and the paradigm of the state of exception. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000809</idno>
            <idno type="volume">019</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2025-09-18">18 September 2025</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list Available at: <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list Available at: <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

               <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "". Create a new <term> element for each -->
               <term corresp="#dh"/>
               <term corresp="#indigenous"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>mapping</item>
                  <item>native land</item>
                  <item>crowd-sourcing</item>
                  <item>volunteer work</item>
                  <item>education tools</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000809/000809.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Native Land Digital, an Indigenous-led mapping project, exemplifies the growth and
               impact of mapping as a tool for data visualization. Its unique focus on absence,
               rather than presence, offers opportunities for interactive humanities scholarship.
               Native Land Digital (2014– ) was founded by Victor Temprano and its Executive
               Director is Tanya Ruka (Māori): <ref target="https://native-land.ca"
                  >https://native-land.ca</ref></p>

         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>

         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Native Land Digital (NLD) is a Canadian Indigenous-led non-profit organization. Their
               digital interactive project continuously reminds us of the question that lies at its
               heart: <hi rend="italic">Whose land are we on?</hi> By mapping Indigenous
               territories, peoples, languages, and treaties, NLD actively challenges dominant
               colonial narratives of land ownership that have historically subjugated conventional
               understandings of geographic history. By critically analyzing NLD’s approach,
               methodology, and audience, this review demonstrates how the project redefines digital
               mapping as a medium for Indigenous self-representation, while also highlighting the
               strengths and shortcomings that arise within both public and scholarly conversation
               on digital mapping projects.</p>
            <p>The NLD project situates itself at the intersection of Indigenous studies,
               postcolonial theory and spatial humanities. It thereby operates in a growing global
               movement of mapping Indigenous lands digitally. NLD exists alongside a plethora of
               similar projects that emerged in the context of digital mapping such as the
               Indigenous Mapping Collective, First Nations Location, and Native Land Information
               System, just to name a few. The non-profit collective <title rend="italic">Rest of
                  World</title> coined the mapping of Indigenous land a <quote rend="inline">race to
                  put themselves on the map</quote>
               <ptr target="#mk_2023"/>. Since the emergence of Digital Humanities as <q>a
                  discipline in its own right</q> in the early 2000s, mapping has grown to be one of
               its most impactful tools for data visualization. Maps orient the viewer, situate the
               project’s aim in a large, cultural context, and visually organize large data sets
                  <ptr target="#luhmann_2021" loc="149"/>
               <ptr target="#allen_2015" loc="86–87"/>. The act of mapping serves as a <quote
                  rend="inline">representation of a world</quote>
               <ptr target="#presner_2014" loc="15"/>. Additionally, recent scholarly conversations
               on critical digital mapping emphasize its importance for community power and
               representation as Moore and Garzón argue: <quote rend="inline">Map-making can be a
                  useful tool in scaling up from the individual lived experience to building a
                  shared analysis about collective challenges</quote>
               <ptr target="#moore_2010" loc="67"/>. Mapping is not a new phenomenon, it has held a
               central role in the production of geographical data for centuries <ptr
                  target="#presner_2014" loc="16"/>
               <ptr target="#moore_2010" loc="66"/>. Consequently, mapping in an age of digital
               humanities represents an evolution of traditional cartography, offering new and
               critical opportunities of methods, media, data curation, and community representation
                  <ptr target="#presner_2014" loc="20"/>. The <q>boom</q> that mapping projects in
               digital humanities have experienced therefore does not come as a surprise. What,
               then, distinguishes NLD from other Indigenous digital mapping projects? Within the
               bounds of this review, I answer: What makes NLD unique lies in what is absent, not
               present. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Versatility</head>
            <p>As stated in the introduction, NLD falls under the category of Indigenous studies,
               postcolonial theory and spatial humanities. Its interactive map serves as an
               extension of quantitative history and derives its methodology from history and
               archaeology in the humanities, visualized by digital tools such as mapping,
               hypermedia links, and data visualization. Additionally, printable lists of
               territories, languages, and treaties serve as a textual database. The project is
               fairly intuitive to navigate. A search bar enables users to explore specific regions
               and the selecting as well as un-selecting of languages, territories and/or treaties
               allows for a more tailored investigation of these categories. Once selected,
               hyperlinks navigate the user to external pages about the nations and histories of an
               area. Additionally, the project offers the possibility to export the page’s data to
               printable image files. The landing page of NLD, however, can at times appear dense
               and visually complex. The color coding of different Indigenous nations overlaps on
               the map, which creates a blur of names, colors, and borders. From an analytical point
               of view, one could argue that this feature highlights the multifaceted and rich
               history of countries we deem as monocultural. In terms of accessibility, however, the
               pastel-colors can be difficult to navigate and differentiate, especially for
               colorblind users. It is possible to turn off the color section altogether, which,
               however, defies the purpose of the overlappings of the map. As NLD has been an
               ongoing project for a decade now, these visual tools have expanded over time. NLD was
               founded by Victor Temprano in 2014 <ptr target="#temprano_2022b"/>. What started out
               as a hobby project quickly grew into a large-scale non-profit organization. Today,
               the digital interactive map alone is not what constitutes NLD as a digital humanities
               project. In recent years, mobile apps containing the interactive map (for both iOS
               and Android) were launched with the option to drop pins and save certain regions.
               Additionally, a community blog was created on Medium.com, which invites collaborators
               to dive into and contribute to the history of selected nations and Indigenous people
                  <ptr target="#native-land_2024a"/>.</p>
            <p>Since it was founded in 2014, NLD has not only grown in size, but also in community.
               Temprano stepped down as the executive director in 2022 and was replaced by Māori
               designer Tanya Ruka. NLD now additionally consists of an Indigenous board of
               directors and an advisory council of both Indigenous and non-Indigenous members <ptr
                  target="#native-land_2024b"/>. At the heart of the project are the numerous
               volunteers who contribute to fill in the gaps of Indigenous nations on the map and
               whose contributions are monitored and fact-checked by NLD staff. </p>
            <p>The vast data sets compiled by staff, volunteers, and research projects at several
               universities in Canada are analyzed and visualized by several digital tools. Until
               2022, NLD pushed to and pulled from the Mapbox dataset into a custom-made WordPress
               plugin <ptr target="#temprano_2022a"/>. As of 2022, all data is stored in a SQL
               (structured query language) database and then built to Mapbox with Temprano’s own
               Mapster Technology as its backend. In essence, Mapbox is a tool that allows the
               sharing and uploading of maps from different sources, while the SQL database allows
               for a more efficient and easier visualization of the data. A centralized database
               ensures a clearer scope of data analysis and visualization, which in turn ensures a
               more coherent user experience of the interactive map. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Absences</head>
            <p>Given the theoretical framework of the project, it is essential for this review to
               explore the interactive map in action. The map is organized in a globe-structure that
               can be moved to and from every angle, deconstructing the euro-centric view on
               traditional world maps. Before accessing the map, the audience is presented with a
               Native Land and Territorial Acknowledgement and the goal of the project to <quote
                  rend="inline">[honor] Indigenous resilience past, present and future</quote>
               <ptr target="#native-land_2024a"/>. What catches the eye first is the presence of
               absence. While major parts of today’s North, Middle, and South America as well as
               Australia and New-Zealand are completely filled out with the color-coded names of
               Indigenous nations that at times even overlap, the majority of Europe and Africa
               remains blank. It would be presumptuous to assume that a project concerned with
               Indigenous land actively neglects a continent so rich in Indigenous nations as
               Africa. A look at the NLD staff and contributors gives a possible explanation to why
               certain continents are filled out completely while others are left blank: The team
               consists of Māori (New Zealand), Kichwa Nation (Ecuador), Payómkawichum (California,
               United States), Métis (Winnipeg, Canada), Anishinaabekwe (Minneapolis, United
               States), Bikol/Tagalog (Philippines), Tsawout First Nation (Vancouver, Canada), and
               Gitxaala (British Columbia, Canada). That might serve as an explanation and tentative
               confirmation that the project aims to establish a well-grounded framework of
               knowledge before mapping out Indigenous territories, letting Indigenous peoples
                  <q>map</q> themselves. Thus, what may initially be perceived as a shortfall in
               representation, is, in fact, a bold decision to let absence speak for itself – to not
               impose border and territory definitions on behalf of other Indigenous nations. Its
               gaps serve as a painful reminder that history’s reclamation is ongoing. </p>
            <p>Additionally, ethical implications of digital humanities projects are concerned with
               data sovereignty. Scholars who review the notion of data sovereignty, such as <ptr
                  target="#baezner_2018"/> and <ptr target="#hummel_2021" loc="10"/>, underline that
               data flows are linked to control and power of its storage and usage. For Indigenous
               data sovereignty, specifically, open data sources represent a <q>site of tension</q>.
               While open data provides opportunities to sustainably develop and visualize
               Indigenous representation, it also bears the danger of reproducing colonialist power
               dynamics, biases, and diminishing Indigenous agency over their own data <ptr
                  target="#rainie_2019"/>, 300]. A failure to respect data sovereignty can harm
               Indigenous nations more than benefitting them: <quote rend="inline">By failing to
                  respect Indigenous data sovereignty and engaging in extractive data practices,
                  companies risk perpetuating the same harms and injustices inflicted upon
                  Indigenous communities</quote>
               <ptr target="#vishal_2024" loc="3"/>. In this light, NLD provides an important
               contribution to Indigenous sovereignty by <q>gapping</q> the globe instead of mapping
               it. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Community</head>
            <p>The collaborations of NLD are manifold. Besides the numerous volunteers, who are
               encouraged to submit evidence of Indigenous territories, languages, or treaties, NLD
               partners with organizations such as Digital Democracy and Historica Canada. Notably,
               the project closely collaborates with other digital humanities projects such as Whose
               Land and Tribal Nations Maps <ptr target="#whose-land_2024"/>
               <ptr target="#native-land_2024b"/>. Those databases of digital humanities mapping
               projects are shared among them, making Indigenous mapping a cross-global community
               project with different foci. Whose Land fosters an educational-based approach by
               providing teaching material and videos. Similarly, NLD established a teacher’s guide
               in 2015, and an updated version in 2019 <ptr target="#native-land_2024c"/>. In
               addition, the project seeks a broader audience. Through volunteer work, media
               representation, and the launch of their app version, NLD presumably wants to engage
               people on a daily basis and emphasizes the land acknowledgement in everyday life, not
               merely in educational settings. Furthermore, NLD cooperates with several higher
               education institutions in Canada and the United States, such as the College of the
               North, University of Alberta, University of Saskatchewan, Florida State University,
               and UC Riverside <ptr target="#native-land_2024a"/>. In this scope, NLD conducts
               research with both undergraduate and graduate students to build their database. That
               suggests a more scholarly collaboration focus rather than an educational approach,
               even though NLD can without doubt be used as a teaching tool in a middle or high
               school classroom due to its intuitive usage.</p>
            <p>The NLD project engages a variety of users; Indigenous newscasts such as CBC News
               praise NLD for their work and careful research, and <title rend="italic"
                  >HuffPost</title> brought the project to a broader audience’s attention in 2019
                  <ptr target="#meloney_2018"/>
               <ptr target="#lewis_2019"/>. <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title> and Boston’s
               news station WBUR cite the project alongside coverage of a critical approach to
               Thanksgiving celebrations <ptr target="#sinclair_2024"/>
               <ptr target="#mosely_2020"/>. In recent years, however, engagement from and with NLD
               has grown quieter. The last update of the project’s <q>Roadmap</q> of their project
               was in April 2021 — the last community blogpost in April 2023 before a restart in
               April 2025. It is not too far-fetched to assume that an underlying reason for the
               project’s halt is its funding. As NLD is dependent on funding from institutions such
               as the Kalliopeia Foundation and Vancity Credit Union <ptr
                  target="#native-land_2024a"/>, it also raises the question of how sustainable such
               a complex mapping project (that is largely reliant on voluntary work) can be. Another
               shortcoming of the project is its reliability of data collection. How accurate can
               data be if it is crowd-sourced globally with relatively little staff to fact-check? </p>
            <p>Given the NLD’s reliance on both institutional funding and volunteer contributions,
               concerns emerge not only about the source, but also about the storage of its data.
               Although the project has moved to one SQL database and away from scattered data sets
               in 2022, the aggregation of data from such a plethora of sources carries significant
               risks of inaccuracy. A strength of the map, however, is the fact that it is possible
               to look up when which alterations were made to the map. Its continuous changes assert
               that NLD continues to evolve through global volunteer work and activism despite an
               apparent outward halt. </p>
            <p>The ability to track such evolving changes on the map provides insight into global
               cultural, historical, and political processes. Its evolving representation invites
               humanities scholars to examine how we can use digital tools to assess narratives of
               land ownership and identity formation. For American Studies scholars, the NLD project
               offers a valuable perspective on the intersection of mapping, representation, and
               sovereignty. As Dunst examines in his essay on digital American Studies, our
               disciplinary field can only benefit from what digital humanities projects have to
               offer, mainly <quote rend="inline">establishing access and providing orientation,
                  organizing communities online, and enlarging discussions in digital and analog
                  spaces</quote>
               <ptr target="#dunst_2016" loc="386"/>. Digital humanities projects are not without
               flaws, and the NLD project is no exception. Yet, digital humanities projects in
               general, and NLD in particular, serve as a reminder of what American Studies can be
               capable of achieving with a large-scale organization and visualization of
               quantitative and qualitative data. As scholars, it is essential to continuously
               reflect on the audience we aim to engage and, consequently, the methodologies we must
               employ to reach them. In light of Indigenous data sovereignty, such reflection also
               entails the decision to <q>gap</q> the map and let absence speak for itself. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allen_2015" label="Allen and Queen 2015">Allen, T., and Queen, S. (2015)
                  <title rend="quotes">Beyond the map: Unpacking critical cartography in the digital
                  humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Visible Language</title> 49(4), pp.
               86–87. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://journals.uc.edu/index.php/vl/article/view/5907"
                  >https://journals.uc.edu/index.php/vl/article/view/5907</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baezner_2018" label="Baezner and Robin 2018">Baezner, M. and Robin, P.
               (2018) <title rend="italic">Cyber Sovereignty and Data Sovereignty</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Version 2</title>. <title rend="italic">Cyberdefense Trend
                  Analysis</title>. Zürich: Center for Security Studies (CSS), ETH Zürich. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.3929/ethz-b-000314613"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3929/ethz-b-000314613</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunst_2016" label="Dunst 2016">Dunst, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital American studies: An introduction and rationale</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Amerikastudien/American Studies</title> 61(3), pp. 381–395.
               Available at: <ref target="https://amst.winter-verlag.de/article/AMST/2016/3/6"
                  >https://amst.winter-verlag.de/article/AMST/2016/3/6</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hummel_2021" label="Hummel et al. 2021">Hummel, P. et al. (2021) <title
                  rend="quotes">Data Sovereignty: A Review</title>, <title rend="italic">Big Data
                  &amp; Society</title> 8(1), pp. 1–17. https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951720982012 </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lewis_2019" label="Lewis 2019">Lewis, H. (2019) ´Native Land’ map helps
               you recognize which Indigenous territory you live on’, <title rend="italic"
                  >HuffPost</title>, last modified 17 December 2019. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/native-land-map-indigenous-territory_n_610874fae4b0497e67026c9d"
                  >https://www.huffpost.com/entry/native-land-map-indigenous-territory_n_610874fae4b0497e67026c9d</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luhmann_2021" label="Luhmann and Burghardt 2021">Luhmann, J. and
               Burghardt, M. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Digital humanities – A discipline in its
                  own right?</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for
                  Information Science and Technology</title> 73(2), pp. 148–171. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24533">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24533</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="meloney_2018" label="Meloney 2018">Meloney, N. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Our home on Nntive-Land.ca: website lets users explore Indigenous ancestral
                  territories</title>, <title rend="italic">Canadian Broadcasting
                  Corporation</title>, last modified 29 April 2018. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.cbc.ca/news/indigenous/native-land-website-traditional-territories-1.4638401"
                  >https://www.cbc.ca/news/indigenous/native-land-website-traditional-territories-1.4638401</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mk_2023" label="Mk 2023">Mk, L. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The race to
                  put Indigenous land on the map</title>, <title rend="italic">Rest of
               World</title>, last modified 20 June 2023. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://restofworld.org/2023/indigenous-land-map-tech/"
                  >https://restofworld.org/2023/indigenous-land-map-tech/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moore_2010" label="Moore and Garzón 2010">Moore, E, and Garzón, C. (2010)
                  <title rend="quotes">Social cartography: The art of using maps to build community
                  power</title>, <title rend="italic">Race, Poverty &amp; the
               Environment</title> 17(2), pp. 66–67. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.reimaginerpe.org/17-2/garzon-moore"
                  >https://www.reimaginerpe.org/17-2/garzon-moore</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mosely_2020" label="Mosely and Hagan 2020">Mosley, T. and Hagan, A. (2020)
                  <title rend="quotes">For native peoples, Thanksgiving isn't a celebration. It is a
                  national day of mourning</title>, <title rend="italic">WBUR-FM</title>, last
               modified 25 November 2020. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.wbur.org/hereandnow/2020/11/25/native-americans-thanksgiving-mourning"
                  >https://www.wbur.org/hereandnow/2020/11/25/native-americans-thanksgiving-mourning</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="native-land_2024a" label="Native Land 2024a">Native Land. (2024a) <title
                  rend="italic">Disclaimer</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://native-land.ca">https://native-land.ca</ref> (Accessed 12 October
               2024). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="native-land_2024b" label="Native Land 2024b">Native Land. (2024b) <title
                  rend="italic">Our Team</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://native-land.ca/about/our-team"
                  >https://native-land.ca/about/our-team</ref> (Accessed 12 October 2024). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="native-land_2024c" label="Native Land 2024c">Native Land. (2024c) <title
                  rend="italic">Teacher’s Guide</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://native-land.ca/resources/teachers-guide"
                  >https://native-land.ca/resources/teachers-guide</ref> (Accessed 12 October 2024). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="presner_2014" label="Presner et al. 2014">Presner, T. et al. (2014) <title
                  rend="italic">Hypercities: Thick Mapping in the Digital Humanities</title>.
               Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rainie_2019" label="Rainie et al. 2019">Rainie, S.C. et al. (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">Indigenous Data Sovereignty</title> in Tim Davies et al. (eds.)
                  <title rend="italic">The State of Open Data</title>. South Africa: African Minds,
               pp. 300–319.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sinclair_2024" label="Sinclair 2024">Sinclair, S. (2024) <title
                  rend="quotes">Indian country showed up to beat Trump. How can you show up for
                  Indian Country?</title>, <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, last modified
               12 October 2024. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2020/nov/26/native-american-us-election-"
                  >https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2020/nov/26/native-american-us-election-</ref>education-activism </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="temprano_2022a" label="Temprano 2022a">Temprano, V. (2022a) <title
                  rend="quotes">Native-Land.ca map review</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Codementor</title>, 6 August. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.codementor.io/@victorgerardtemprano/native-land-ca-map-review-1vz3m74lca"
                  >https://www.codementor.io/@victorgerardtemprano/native-land-ca-map-review-1vz3m74lca</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="temprano_2022b" label="Temprano 2022b">Temprano, V. (2022b) <title
                  rend="italic">Victortemprano.com</title>. (Accessed 12 October 2024). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vishal_2024" label="Vishal 2024">Vishal, R. (2024) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Indigenous data sovereignty: A catalyst for ethical AI in business</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Business and Society</title> 1(6), pp. 1–6. <ref
                  target="https://native-land.ca">https://doi.org/10.1177/00076503241271143</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whose-land_2024" label="Whose Land 2024">Whose Land. (2024) <title
                  rend="italic">About</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.whose.land/en/about">https://www.whose.land/en/about</ref>
               (Accessed 12 October 2024 )</bibl>
            <bibl/>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
