<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Anette <dhq:family>Hagen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9126-165X<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of South-Eastern Norway</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>anette.hagen@usn.no</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Anette Hagen is a PhD candidate at the Department of Languages and Literature Studies, University of South-Eastern Norway.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Elise Seip <dhq:family>Tønnessen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8633-3583<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Agder</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>elise.s.tonnessen@uia.no</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Elise Seip Tønnessen is Professor emeritus at Department of Nordic and Media Studies, University of Agder, Norway. Her research interests include children’s literature and readers’ response to texts across genres, media and contexts. She has published extensively on multimodality, literacy and the media cultures of young people.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000619</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date when="2022-05-12">12 May 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">added teaser and ORCIDs</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article presents a close reading of the augmented reality (AR) comic <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, which was created by Stuart Campbell.
               Possible Worlds Theory was applied to discuss how fiction, which creates its own
               possible worlds, integrates the additional layer(s) of AR into its storyworld. The
               analysis additionally sheds light on the reader’s position and how the augmented
               layer may affect the literary experience. We also discuss how the AR interface may
               contribute to digital literature more generally.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>A close reading of the AR comic by Stuart Campbell: Modern Polaxis.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head></head>
            <p>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the
               game <title rend="italic">Pokémon Go</title> took everyone to the streets with their
               small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed
               digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article,
               we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through
               digital blending in narrative fiction. </p>
            <p>AR can be defined as a system that <quote rend="inline">supplements the real world
                  with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space
                  as the real world</quote>
               <ptr target="#azumaetal2001" loc="34"/>. Used as a resource in digital literature, the
               real-world element may be a physical object or analogue medium that works with
               digital media to produce an enhanced version of a story. Hence, in this fictional use
               of AR, questions arise about the relationship between <q>real</q> and <q>virtual</q>
               worlds. </p>
            <p>In the specific case of AR comics, our question is what adding an augmented layer does to the reading experience. According to Scott McCloud the comics medium is characterised by two formal features: The blending of words and images, and the sequential reading where panels and gutters offer a participatory reading experience for the reader to fill in the blanks between the panels <ptr target="#mccloud1993"/>. Jason Helms refers to these characteristics and states that the examples of AR comics he has seen so far <quote rend="inline">do not substantially augment the reading experience,</quote> either because they only enhance certain images, and not the storyworld as such, or because they disturb the sequential flow of reading. However, he sees some possibilities, requiring that the AR layer was created hand-in-hand with the comic book, and that the reading experience would be better integrated <ptr target="#helms2017" loc="61"/>.</p>
            <p>For this article, we apply Possible World Theory to discuss how fiction, which
               creates its own possible world <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="63"/>, integrates the
               additional layer(s) of AR into its storyworld. We analyse the AR comic book <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> to explore how AR may contribute to a complex
               storyworld with several layers. We have a particular interest in how storytelling
               with digital media plays with story space across media and worlds and how this may
               affect a reader’s literary experience.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>AR literature</head>
            <figure>
               <head>Reading <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis.</title> Photo by Stuart
                  Campbell/Sutu (Used with permission).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>a photo depicting the reading experience of <title>Modern Polaxis</title>.
                  The comic is laid open on a table, and the reader's hand is visible holding a
                  phone above one of the pages. On the phone screen, we see an altered version of
                  the comic page, featuring more color.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The AR comic <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>
               <ptr target="#campbell2014a"/> consists of a physical book and an accompanying phone
               app that supplements and changes the appearance of the book’s pages (see Figure 1).
               We chose this work to study how AR functions in narrative fiction, because the app
               consistently adds a layer throughout the comic book, as Helms <ptr
                  target="#helms2017"/> suggested. AR literature is still in its becoming, and few
               examples of narrative works take advantage of AR in creative ways. A variety of
               combinations of the virtual and what appears as <q>real</q> in some sense may be
               envisioned. After concluding our analysis, we return to a discussion of how our
               findings may be relevant to AR storytelling. </p>
            <p>Other examples of AR in digital literature include <title rend="italic">57°
                  North</title>
               <ptr target="#mightycoconut2017"/>, which requires a different physical object than a
               book to come to life. This app is combined with a Merge Cube onto which the story is
               projected. Different turns in the story are chosen by tilting the cube. The potential
               for using AR with physical objects seems extensive; however, in this story, its use
               is very limited. An AR comic project, <title rend="italic">Neon Wasteland</title>
               <ptr target="#shields2020"/> was planned to launch in summer 2021; however, at this
               stage, only poster-like examples on the <title rend="italic">Neon Wasteland</title>
               website that work with the app are available for download. There are examples of AR
               studios, such as BlippAR <ptr target="#blippar2011"/>, making commercial AR campaigns
               and offering tools for AR development. They also provide an AR browser that, for
               instance, works with award-winning Indian <title rend="italic">Priya</title> comics
                  <ptr target="#devinenietal"/>, which are about a female superhero. In these
               comics, the app makes interactive elements pop out of the pages including animation,
               films, etc., along with additional features such as AR puzzles. The subjects of the
                  <title rend="italic">Priya</title> comics have transparent educational or moral
               aims; for example, the latest release, <title rend="italic">Priya’s Mask</title>
               <ptr target="#prakashetal2020"/>, is about stopping the spread of COVID-19. <title
                  rend="italic">Wonderscope</title> <ptr target="#wonderscope2019"/> is an app that
               presents stories to young children. The characters of the stories merge with the
               users’ physical space. Each story is tagged with the stories’ themes (such as
               confidence, respect and inclusion) or with facts the user may learn about (e.g.,
               solar science or fun facts). These examples show some of AR storytelling’s diversity
               and illustrate that AR has not yet established steady forms and conventions in
               literary genres. </p>
            <p>In AR literature we see a potential for combining a multitude of worlds within one
               storyworld. In the analysis of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis, </title>we
               explore the relationship between worlds and how these may affect the reader’s
               aesthetic (literary) experience. Even considering the other AR works mentioned,
                  <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> is a pioneer in AR storytelling, as it
               is one of the first AR comics of its kind. Moreover, it is an independent
               (crowdfunded) project exploring new possibilities of AR storytelling. It entails a
               very complex story, requiring an experienced reader of multimodal texts, and
               thematises complicated issues, such as ontology and psychiatry. Additionally, its
               aesthetic aims make it an interesting object for literary analysis.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Previous research on AR narratives</head>
            <p>Research on AR apps has revolved around apps designed for learning, or games such as
                  <title rend="italic">Pokémon Go</title>, whereas studies on AR’s potential
               literary contributions are lacking. Several studies have drawn attention to
               children’s AR apps and educational settings (see, e.g., <ptr target="#lietal2017"/>;
                  <ptr target="#yilmazetal2017"/>; <ptr target="#chanlin2018"/>; <ptr
                  target="#wuetal2013"/>; <ptr target="#greenetal2019"/>), while fewer studies have
               addressed AR apps aimed at a wider audience that includes teenagers and adults.</p>
            <p>Gunnar Liestøl (<ptr target="#liestol2011"/>; <ptr target="#liestol2019"/>) explored
               AR technologies’ narrative and rhetorical potential in the context of reconstructing
               historical events on location. This location perspective is a common concern in AR,
               along with an image or text as the base for the AR layer <ptr target="#lietal2017"
                  loc="621"/>. The connection to the user’s physical location is also central to
               Anders Sundnes Løvlie’s project <title rend="italic">textopia</title>, which explored
               the relations between places and literary texts. The locative system allows a user to
               listen to texts relevant to the place where they are positioned. Løvlie <ptr
                  target="#lovlie2009"/> analysed literary strategies that allow readers and writers
               to connect literature to their lived environment. With <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title>, what is of interest is the tension between the analogue medium of
               the book and the digital layer added by the AR app, not the place in which the reader
               opens the book.</p>
            <p>Weedon et al. <ptr target="#weedonetal2014"/> described an AR project called <title
                  rend="italic">Sherwood Rise</title>, which revealed interesting possible effects
               of AR that can also be relevant to the analysis of <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title>. Weedon et al. see AR as a possibility to disguise and hide
               narratives and describe them as a way to <quote rend="inline">signal the unexpected
                  and as a mechanism to narrate mystery, confusion, altered/distorted or magical
                  reality</quote>
               <ptr target="#weedonetal2014" loc="117"/>. <title rend="italic">Sherwood Rise</title>
               creates tension between the static story (i.e., the printed book) and the dynamic
               story (i.e., the AR story), which <quote rend="inline">was important to keep the
                  reader engaged across platforms</quote>
               <ptr target="#weedonetal2014" loc="118"/>. This tension also applies to <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>. The interplay between layers is a crucial
               part of AR’s contribution to the literary experience. Consequently, we argue that AR
               has the potential to enrich storyworlds. It can create possible worlds of different
               ontological statuses between which tensions may arise and expand the storyworld in
               time and space. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Theoretical perspectives </head>
            <p>In AR literature, the <q>reality</q> that is augmented through an overlay of a
               digital medium may be location-based, anchored in a geographical, spatial reality, or
               it may be image-based, represented in a physical medium <ptr target="#lietal2017"/>.
               With fictional narratives, the <q>reality</q> level does not exist independently of
               the text. This means that in fiction, AR functions as an interplay between levels
               that may be characterised as possible worlds, albeit expressed in different media.
               Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019"/> noted that possible world (PW) theory, transferred
               from its origin in philosophy and modal logic, can shed light on the narrative
               experience. For narratologists, PWs are <quote rend="inline">constructs of the
                  imagination, as objects of aesthetic contemplation, and as conditions of narrative
                  immersion</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="62"/>. In line with Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019"/>, we
               assume that immersion in a storyworld is essential to the experience of narrative
               fiction.</p>
            <p>Ryan and Bell, in their work on narrative semantics inspired by PW theory, focused on
               the internal organisation of storyworlds, which they described as <quote
                  rend="inline">entire modal universes consisting of multiple worlds</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryanandbell2019" loc="18"/>. One world will appear to the reader as the
               actual world within the text (i.e., textual actual world, TAW), whereas the others
               are alternate possible worlds (TPWs) <ptr target="#ryanandbell2019" loc="3"/>. As
               Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2015" loc="70"/> stated in her PW theory, <quote rend="inline"
                  >The central element is commonly interpreted as <said>the actual world</said> and
                  the satellites as merely possible worlds. For a world to be possible, it must be
                  linked to the centre by a so-called accessibility relation</quote>. These
               accessibility relations can be necessary, possible or impossible <ptr
                  target="#ryanandbell2019" loc="4"/>. Which world is seen as TAW is determined by
               the reader’s act of <q>recentring</q> into the narrative universe, where what appears
               as narrative facts comprises the TAW. </p>
            <p>This understanding is in line with the so-called <term>modal realism</term>
               formulated by philosopher David Lewis, who pointed out that what is actual is
               indexical: <quote rend="inline">Our actual world is only one world among others. We
                  call it actual not because it differs in kind from all the rest but because it is
                  the world we inhabit</quote> (Lewis 1979 in <ptr target="#ryanandbell2019" loc="7"
               />). A TAW may also include the characters’ private worlds, revealing their state of
               mind (i.e., beliefs, dreams, desires and fears). <quote rend="inline">Through these
                  imaginary constructs, narrative universes acquire distinct ontological
                  levels,</quote> according to Ryan and Bell <ptr target="#ryanandbell2019" loc="19"
               />.</p>
            <p>These levels are imperative for understanding how AR literature may blend worlds.
               Since AR merges digital and analogue textual experiences, it can be seen as
               transfictionality <ptr target="#saint-gelais2005"/> or transmedia storytelling <ptr
                  target="#jenkins2007"/>. Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="71"/> discussed the
               basic operations of transfictionality and sorted out three: expansion, modification
               and transposition. These have inspired our discussion of how the augmented layer
               contributes to the aesthetic experience of AR literature.</p>
            <p>Ryan <ptr target="#ryan1991"/> also presents three dimensions of storyworlds:
               completeness, distance and size; the former two are most relevant to our discussion.
               In philosophical PW theory ontological completeness is a condition for PWs to count
               as worlds. Fictional PWs, in contrast, are characterised by not being complete. On
               the contrary, Lubomír Doležel <ptr target="#dolezel1998"/> described fictional worlds
               as areas of indeterminacy. Ruth Ronen <ptr target="#ronen1994" loc="12"/> stated that
                  <quote rend="inline">the fictional world system is an independent system whatever
                  the type of fiction constructed and the extent of drawing on our knowledge of the
                  actual world</quote>. According to Ryan <ptr target="#ryan1991"/>, completeness
               does not require a total description of settings or characters; rather, it raises the
               question of how much the reader needs to know to become immersed in the storyworld.
               Missing information does not necessarily threaten completeness; indeed, it may
               encourage the reader to supply information based on their own life experiences, as in
               Wolfgang Iser’s <ptr target="#iser1978"/> reception theory, in which filling empty
               spaces and dealing with indeterminacies are vital to the reader’s encounter with the
               text. A different matter involves ontological gaps in the storyworld <ptr
                  target="#ryan2019" loc="75"/>, which may include contradictions within the TAW and
               between the PWs comprising the narrative universe. </p>
            <p>Distance concerns the storyworld’s relation to the actual world, which involves a
               range of variations, from realistic to fantastic stories. The TAW of the storyworld may deviate from the world as we know it, as long as it is consistent within its own logic. The distance from the reader’s actual world can be described in terms of how
               many rules in the actual world can be broken in the TAW of the storyworld <ptr
                  target="#ryan2019" loc="65"/>. According to what Ryan <ptr target="#ryan1991"/>
               coined the <term>principle of minimal departure</term>, readers imagine a fictional
               world to be the closest possible to the actual world they inhabit and make only the
               changes mandated by the text. A storyworld may even contain elements or events that
               the reader would consider logically impossible. Here, Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019"/>
               distinguishes between paradoxes that contribute to the plot on the one hand and
               contradiction for its own sake on the other. The former is limited to certain areas
               and may <quote rend="inline">open logical holes in the fabric of storyworlds</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="66"/>
            </p>
            <p>As mentioned previously, the reader is central in determining which possible world to
               consider actual in the storyworld. This points to the reader’s role in interpreting
               how actual and possible worlds relate within the storyworld. Umberto Eco <ptr
                  target="#eco1984" loc="246"/> includes the reader as an active part of the
               constellation of possible worlds that comprise the narrative universe. He described
               three types of possible worlds connected to the fabula, the characters and the
               reader, respectively. The first type represents the fabula as a succession of states
               mediated by events that correspond to the actual world of the narrative (i.e., the
               TAW). The second type corresponds to the characters’ mental activities, involving
               their imaginations, beliefs and wishes (i.e., TPWs, according to Ryan). The third
               type of world is found in the unfolding of the story in the reader’s mind. </p>
            <p>Including a reception perspective on the interplay between possible worlds in AR
               fiction is hence in correspondence with PW theory and the specific situation of
               reading digital narratives. The readers are central through their perceptions of what
               makes up the actual world of the text and their assessment of how this relates to the
               actual world of their own life experience. The readers also play an active part in
               interacting with the digital layer of AR.</p>
            <p>In his reception theory, Iser is concerned with what the text <emph>does</emph> in
               the encounter with the reader. He sees the text as <quote rend="inline">a network of
                  response-inviting structures</quote>
               <ptr target="#iser1978" loc="34"/>, in which meaning emerges through the reader’s
               semantic operations. He stated that <quote rend="inline">fiction devoid of any
                  connection with known reality would be incomprehensible</quote>
               <ptr target="#iser1993" loc="1"/> and that <quote rend="inline">the literary text is
                  a mixture of reality and fiction, and as such, it brings about an interaction
                  between the given and the imagined</quote>
               <ptr target="#iser1993" loc="1"/>. </p>
            <p>Iser <ptr target="#iser1993"/> described the semantic operations specific to reading
               fiction as a triad of fictionalising acts inscribed in the text and realised in the
               reading event. The first is the act of selecting recognisable elements from the
               actual world; the second is the act of combining them in new ways in the fictional
               world; the third is the contract of reading the text as fiction, which in our view
               involves an open attitude towards the PWs included in the storyworld. Iser’s
               perspectives were based on written literature, but he emphasised that these semantic
               processes do not primarily function on the level of words but rather meanings <ptr
                  target="#iser1993" loc="20"/>. </p>
            <p>We find that Iser’s argument about the interplay between the fictive, the real (or
               actual) and the imaginary (or possible) brought together by the reader’s interaction
               with the text also has relevance for reading AR literature. In the case of AR comics,
               blanks and indeterminacies may arise in the gutters between panels, or in the
               interplay between words and images and other modes in the multimodal AR ensemble. In
               the following, we take the case of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> as a
               point of departure for analysing the interplay of worlds in AR fiction, be they
               actual, possible or impossible, and we discuss the reader’s position and how the
               augmented layer may affect the literary experience. Based on this case, we finally
               discuss what the AR interface may contribute to digital literature more
               generally.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Analysis</head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> represents two different ways of seeing
               the world based on two versions of the diary of one fictional character presented in
               two media: a comic book with one or more panels on each page, and an AR app adding
               colours, animations and soundscape, effectively expanding or modifying the story
               presented in the book. The AR layer does not work unless you have the book at hand,
               whereas the book stands poorly by itself without the AR layer, as it does not present
               the full story. Together, these two elements create one aesthetic work and comprise
               one storyworld, albeit divided. The main character is presented on the <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> website as <quote rend="inline">a paranoid
                  time traveller</quote> who <quote rend="inline">believes the world we live in is a
                  holographic projection from another plane in the universe.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>From the very beginning, <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> invites the
               reader to make ontological reflections by starting with a presentation of Plato’s
               allegory of the cave. In this allegory, people are trapped and chained in a cave,
               watching a stone wall where shadows are projected from real-world elements, passing a
               fire behind them, thus resembling a shadow theatre. They believe the shadows are the
               actual world, while Polaxis states that <quote rend="inline">the shadows are as close
                  as the prisoners get to viewing reality</quote>
               <ptr target="#campbell2014b" loc="1"/>
               <note>
                  <hi rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</hi> is written in capital letters only. For
                  readability, we cite from the work using both capital and small letters. Although
                  the book is not paginated, we have provided page numbers for the content. We use
                     <q>AR</q> in front of page numbers when the reference is to the app.</note>.
               Through this, the question is raised of what is real and whether our experiences can
               be trusted to give access to real knowledge, which, in Plato’s philosophy, is the
               world of ideas. In the book version, the prisoners seem to be inside the cave,
               staring at stone walls. The AR layer adds blue skies where the stone wall used to be
               and the stone walls’ structures suddenly become trees, effectively enhancing the cave
               allegory’s question of whether the perceived reality can be trusted. This opening
               scene is positioned outside the time and space of the storyworld, serving as a
               framework for understanding — and questioning — the worlds presented through
               Polaxis’s diary. </p>
            <p>This philosophical framing may be key to understanding the text’s use of AR, with the
               analogue book representing the TAW and a TPW, while the digital enrichment of the AR
               app represents an additional PW, including comments, doubts and suspicions. Another
               philosophical reference is the principle of <quote rend="inline">time binding</quote>
               <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="4"/>, a concept known from Polish-American scholar
               Alfred Korzybski, which concerns how memories may be transferred in time and space
               through the use of symbols. In <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, this
               seems to support the main character’s efforts to escape the limitations of human
               perception and knowledge of the world. Korzybski was best known for his dictum,
                  <quote rend="inline">the map is not the territory</quote>, which indicates that
               human knowledge is limited and that no one can have direct access to reality. This
               fundamental doubt about what one perceives through the senses is set as a premise for
               the story to be told. It affects the reader’s trust in what is being told and, at the
               same time, substantiates the protagonist’s reasoning for challenging these
               limitations within the fictional world.</p>
            <p>These tensions are also connected to the book’s and the app’s subjective first-person
               viewpoint. The story is told through the paranoid and delusional Polaxis without
               other commenting viewpoints than the philosophical framing mentioned above. The
               diary’s verbal text appears to be handwritten by Polaxis and is not easily
               accessible, as it is very small and dense. This makes the text physically hard to
               read. The images in the book are mostly line drawings in black and red, and image and
               verbiage are tightly interwoven. Even though the book looks small, this is a
               comprehensive work. The amount of written verbal language is significant and central
               to conveying the story. The digital layer enriches the text with an elaborate
               soundscape, colours and animation, sometimes omitting or replacing the book’s verbal
               text. These layers present the complicated worlds that Polaxis is struggling to
               navigate, which we explore further in the next section. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The worlds of Modern Polaxis</head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis’s </title>book and AR app constitute one
               storyworld. According to Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="64"/>, <quote
                  rend="inline">[n]arratives that represent travel between different worlds in the
                  planetary or insular sense</quote> present only one storyworld. For analytical
               clarity, we first discuss what constitutes the TAW and how it relates to other
               possible worlds (TPWs) in the book before turning to the app and what it contributes
               to the storyworld’s totality. Next, we explore more closely how the storyworld
               unfolds in time and space. Then, we discuss how ontological gaps in this particular
               constellation of PWs, enabled by the digital layer, challenge how the TPWs and the
               TAW are understood. </p>
            <p>To determine what to consider the TAW of the storyworld, we looked for accessibility
               relations that connect to the reader’s actual world, relations that make up the grid
               of a TAW easily recognised by a reader. Several points in time and place connect this
               storyworld to the reader’s actual world, including geographical names (e.g.,
               Brisbane, the Amazon and St. Viateur Bagels) and specific dates (see Table 1). If
               seen in connection to the fabula as a succession of states mediated by events <ptr
                  target="#eco1984"/>, the TAW is, in a simplified version, the story of a young man
               from Brisbane with the mundane job of scanning military maps. After a traumatising
               crisis that makes him feel trapped <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="3–9"/> and a
               night <quote rend="inline">fuelled with spiced rum</quote>
               <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="17"/>, he starts a new life. He randomly travels to
               Montreal, Canada, where he meets new friends (i.e., Maki, Feliz and Hoze, and later,
               Eddie, Avel, Carlos and Javier) who help direct him to travel to Peru and explore
               drugs and shamanism. Finally, we see him five years later as a patient taking
               schizophrenia medications in a Tasmanian mental hospital. </p>
            <p> The main TPW in the book medium is represented by the protagonist’s thoughts and
               feelings expressed by verbal text and images. The multimodal comic presents the
               verbal text as coming directly from Polaxis’s mind, whereas the images place the
               reader in a position to observe Polaxis from the outside. Nevertheless, as readers
               are led to believe that the diary is both written and drawn by Polaxis, the images
               somehow still represent his perspective. The drawings in the book are, to some
               extent, realistic (although often both symbolic and exaggerated), contributing to the
               TAW of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> standing out as a complete world,
               where the subjective world of Polaxis is embedded in what Ryan characterizes as an
                  <quote rend="inline">entire universe</quote> that contains <quote rend="inline"
                  >not only an actual world of narrative facts, but a multitude of possible worlds
                  created by the mental activity of the characters</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="65"/>. </p>
            <p>As <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> is presented as Polaxis’s diary, the
               TAW and the TPW are closely intertwined; the TPW of Polaxis’s memories, beliefs and
               ideas appear as the narrative’s driving force. Hence, the accessibility relations
               between TAW and TPW are necessary for understanding Polaxis’s actions and reactions.
               In other cases, the connections are possible, since the allusions to drug abuse and
               disillusions are possible explanations of how he sees the world. Other explanations,
               such as time splitting <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="5"/>, transmigration <ptr
                  target="#campbell2014a" loc="8"/> or living in a fifth-dimensional hologram <ptr
                  target="#campbell2014a" loc="17"/>, represent accessibility relations that seem
               impossible or radically increase the distance from the reader’s actual world.</p>
            <p>The AR app presents another possible world that complicates the storyworld of <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis: the</title> so-called <emph>hidden</emph> journal of
               Polaxis. On one hand, the hidden journal in the AR layer may be seen as a description
               of a parallel world named <q>Intafrag,</q> but on the other hand, it may be seen as a
               mental possible world created by the main character’s delusions and paranoia. This
               question remains open throughout the entire story, although the last image, in which
               central characters are placed in a mental institution, might suggest the latter. The
               reader may see this plot’s driving forces as the adventurous desires of youth gone
               wrong and/or as developing a psychiatric diagnosis. However, because of this
               uncertainty, the TPW represented by the AR layer may ultimately challenge what may
               represent the TAW, thus raising doubts about the ontological statuses of all worlds
               of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> — in line with the philosophical
               framing of the cave allegory.</p>
            <div>
               <head>The worlds of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> unfolding in time and
                  space</head>
               <p>In this section, we look closely at how Modern Polaxis’s storyworld unfolds in
                  time and space and how differences in these dimensions create tensions between the
                  worlds. Table 1 summarises the stated times in the work and the places that
                  Polaxis visits at these points in time. A turning point in the story is marked
                  with the heading <quote rend="inline">RIP Polaxis of the past for this statue is
                     dedicated to the Polaxis of the future</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="18"/>. This marks the beginning of Polaxis’s
                  travels and a new way of perceiving time and space, and the book’s verbal text
                  states that <quote rend="inline">a new reality begins</quote>.</p>
               <p>Only some events are accurately dated, and there are significant gaps in the
                  story. The dates do not seem to differ much between the book and app, except for
                  once, when the in-flight magazine says 2 July <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="26"
                  />, and the journal entry <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 26"/> states 29
                  June. This would not be strange if the time difference were the other way around,
                  with the date on the magazine being before the date Polaxis wrote about the
                  flight. The fact that time seems to turn backwards represents a gap that might
                  refer to time travel. </p>
               <table>
                  <head>Overview of times and places in <title rend="italic">Modern
                     Polaxis</title></head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Time</cell>
                     <cell>Page</cell>
                     <cell>Place in book</cell>
                     <cell>Place in app</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>No date specification</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>In a cave</cell>
                     <cell>Outside</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>9 December 2008</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Dark alley + future apartment — on a ship</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>One night (retrospect)</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>Dark alley</cell>
                     <cell>Intafrag junction/space</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Two years earlier</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>A small office on the seventh floor of the Zenith building in Spring
                        Hill, Brisbane</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>One weekend</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>IT expo at Brisbane Convention Centre</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>After a night out</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>From a bench to the McDonald’s carpark</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><quote rend="inline">RIP Polaxis of the past.</quote>
                        <quote rend="inline">A new reality begins:</quote>
                        <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> of the future</cell>
                     <cell role="label"> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>7 February 2009</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>Montreal, Canada</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>11:47 pm</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>St. Viateur Bagels</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>20 minutes later</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>At a home party (in an apartment)</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell> 29 June 2009 (In app: in-flight magazine says 2 July) </cell>
                     <cell>26–27</cell>
                     <cell> Montreal &gt;&gt; Lima, On airplane, later bus. <lb/> Bus stops
                        somewhere in the Andes </cell>
                     <cell>Bus stop — ancient world of Intafrag?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>2 July 2009</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>Lima &gt;&gt; Cusco, Peru</cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>3 July 2009</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>Pisac, Peru</cell>
                     <cell>Intafrag Peru/Tibet</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell> The Yellow Rose of Texas Café, Iquitos suburbia </cell>
                     <cell>Iquitos (Peru’s gateway to the Amazon)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>7 February 2009</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell> Montreal, Canada </cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell> 2014 In app: a new time phase </cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell> Terrylands, mental hospital, Burnie, Tasmania </cell>
                     <cell>Same as the book</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The first part <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="3–17"/> tells the story of
                  Polaxis’s past in retrospect and gradually reveals his background up to the point
                  when the story is being told. This is where his connection to Intafrag and the
                  fear of its agents is first established in the AR layer <ptr
                     target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 5–6"/>. The story about the Polaxis of the
                  future, the <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, is told in the present
                  tense and moves chronologically forward in time from the party in Montreal in
                  February 2009 to Polaxis’s experiences in Peru and the Amazon in June/July 2009
                  (except for the logical gap between the flight and magazine dates). Then there is
                  a flashback to February 2009, followed by a five-year leap at the end to the
                  mental hospital. </p>
               <p>In Table 1, we see how changes in time and place move quickly forward from page to
                  page in some phases, while there are mainly two phases where time seems to come to
                  a halt: one in Polaxis’s past and one in his future. This may be seen as
                  ontological gaps in time that constitute indeterminacies in the fabula. The first
                  appears as a dream triggered by the introduction of the concept of <quote
                     rend="inline">time binding</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="4"/>. Here, Polaxis recollects a sensation of
                  burning in the book TPW and being chased by Intafrag agents through dark alleys in
                  the app. In the book layer he refers to the experience as <quote rend="inline"
                     >transcendence. Time splits in two</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="5"/>, <quote rend="inline">the breakdown of cells
                     into light</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="7"/>, <quote rend="inline">transmigration</quote>
                  and <quote rend="inline">Mind + Body transfer</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="8"/>. As the process accelerates, the AR layer
                  adds no words <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 7–10"/> but instead intensifies
                  the experience with swirling movements and scary sounds. These memories from the
                  past explain what happens to the <quote rend="inline">Polaxis of the
                     future</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="19"/>. These incidents may represent
                  corresponding ontological gaps in the two TPWs. </p>
               <p> Another example of ontological gaps in the TPWs is a corresponding experience of
                  a time in the future when Polaxis travels from Montreal to Lima. The spaces of the
                  airplane and bus seem to overlap <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="26–27"/> and
                  immediately follow the confusing experience of time going backwards (from 2 July
                  to 29 June). Hence, neither time nor space is perceived as stable: <quote
                     rend="inline">My position...Is not stable…</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="27"/>. In the AR layer, this experience is
                  presented as a <quote rend="inline">time fold</quote> (a portal between two
                  overlapping realities) <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 30"/>. The following
                  events include Polaxis’s experience in Peru, which has been given a double
                  explanation. He is invited to try Ayahuasca, <quote rend="inline">a psychoactive
                     homebrew traditionally prepared by Amazonians for the purpose of healing the
                     body of toxins and interfacing with the divine</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="31"/>, and he joins the ceremony led by the
                  shaman Javier in the Pisac sacred valley <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="37–45"
                  />. On page 46 in the book, the lost journal entry connects back to 7 February in
                  Montreal, and the AR layer connects these two timeless phases with the word <quote
                     rend="inline">purge</quote>. </p>
               <p>These experiences of time coming to a halt represent ontological gaps or
                  indeterminacies in the storyworld across book and app. The main difference
                  concerning the time perception between the analogue and digital layers is that the
                  time gaps in the book seem like <q>normal</q> gaps in time. The reader will not
                  perceive the changes in time and place as missing information, but as events that
                  have occurred but are not told. In the digital layer, however, these gaps are
                  explained as actual time travel, occasionally jumping between places. When, in the
                  end, Polaxis is in the mental hospital, he refers to an incident in Montreal five
                  years earlier: <quote rend="inline">The blow to my head knocked me unconscious. I
                     was out long enough for the plant creatures to time-bind me to this
                     reality</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 48"/>. It is as if those five years never
                  actually transpired. Hence, there is a conflict between accessibility relations
                  and the timeline of the book and the app, respectively. The alternate timeline of
                  the AR layer represents a transposition that may challenge the storyworld’s
                  logical consistency, according to Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="72"/>.</p>
               <p>The places where Polaxis visits seem to vary more between the analogue and digital
                  layers than the time references. As Løvlie <ptr target="#lovlie2009" loc="19"/>
                  explained, <quote rend="inline">the concept of <said>place</said> should not only
                     be treated as a physical location in space, but also as a psychological, social
                     and cultural phenomenon (…) <said>places</said> are spaces that are
                     valued</quote>. This is relevant to the relations between narrative spaces in
                  the worlds of <hi rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</hi>. It seems that the places in
                  the two different layers carry different values, even though the physical
                  locations of both are mostly the same. The colours, sounds and animations of the
                  AR layer reinforce the notion of being in a different place, as do the people
                  inhabiting the two different layers when changing their personalities from the
                  analogue to the digital medium. These changes are ontological gaps, creating
                  uncertainty between the two layers.</p>
               <p>As mentioned in the Theory section, relations to storyworlds can be verified in
                  the actual world; they can be possible or impossible. In <title rend="italic"
                     >Modern Polaxis</title>, references to placenames that can be verified in the
                  actual world are overrepresented in the book version. Many of the actions,
                  especially in the book version, are possible, for example, the travels, alcohol
                  and drug abuse and the parties. However, the connection to Intafrag and the
                  Intafrag agents is impossible if delusions are not taken into account. The main
                  level of possible references and real-life references is represented by the book,
                  whereas the impossible is represented largely by the app. Moreover, the illegal
                  actions concerning the actual world, such as drug abuse, are not <q>hidden</q> in
                  the journal, which perhaps indicates it is not the police or other authorities
                  that the journal is hidden from; rather, the main character in his paranoia hides
                  it from the representatives of Intafrag. </p>
               <p>The question of the distance between the world of the readers and Polaxis’s world
                  is not straightforward. It depends on which world is taken as a point of
                  departure. The idea of the parallel world of Intafrag contributes to the
                  distancing of the entire storyworld from the actual world of the reader. Even so,
                  there is a question of whether the experiences of the TPW in the AR layer, the
                  Intafrag experiences, should be seen as real experiences or as delusions caused by
                  drug abuse. The notion of drug experiences has a much shorter distance from the
                  real world than a parallel universe, even considering that some readers may
                  believe in parallel worlds. Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="66"/> states that
                     <quote rend="inline">ghost stories could be credible for people who believe in
                     the occult.</quote> However, such beliefs are not mainstream, and because of
                  that, if Intafrag is seen as a result of paranoia and delusions, the distance from
                  the real world is much shorter. </p>
               <p>The distance between the PWs of the AR layer and the book can be illustrated by
                  looking for verbal references that occur only in the app, and that may even seem
                  impossible in the TAW. Words that appear only in the app are <quote rend="inline"
                     >Intafrag</quote> (15 times) and <quote rend="inline">creatures</quote> (23
                  times). The word <quote rend="inline">key,</quote> referring to entering Intafrag,
                  is only mentioned in the app. Furthermore, <quote rend="inline">agent(s)</quote>
                  appears frequently in the app version but is only mentioned three times in the
                  book. These words connect directly to the world of Intafrag and are not compatible
                  with what would be considered the ontological rules of the TAW. Polaxis’s diary,
                  where he expresses his experiences and thoughts in the book layer, is hence closer
                  to the TAW than the AR layer, which is said to be his secret diary. </p>
               <p>Visually, certain symbols or objects of symbolic value also serve to establish
                  relationships between the TPWs. For example, a triangle first appears on page four
                  and in the AR layer is emphasised by blinking colours. Later, it reappears on a
                  pendant <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="9"/>, which is later described as an
                  anchor point <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 33"/>. These objects play an
                  essential role in time binding, which is reminiscent of Korzybski’s theory of how
                  memories may be transferred by using symbols, perhaps indicating a connection
                  between movement in time and space and inner perception (memories). </p>
               <p>Polaxis is haunted by the ambivalence of having friends but distrusting them, as
                  he is insecure about whether they are, in fact, friends or disguised Intafrag
                  agents. In the book, many characters seem to be fellow travellers whom Polaxis
                  incidentally meets. However, the AR layer reveals their relations to Intafrag. For
                  instance, on the last page, in the image from the mental hospital, the characters
                  Maki and Hoze appear to be sitting next to Polaxis on a bench. In the AR layer,
                  however, their faces are crossed out while the verbal text states, <quote
                     rend="inline">This is not Maki or Hoze. They’re Intafrag agents sent here to
                     monitor me</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 48"/>. On the same page, Dr. Affeldt is
                  labelled a <quote rend="inline">neuropsychiatrist</quote> in both the book and AR
                  layers, while earlier, his name and profession were only revealed in the AR layer.
                  Then he was presented as the founder of time-binding theory who tried to find a
                     <quote rend="inline">synthesis of the first chemical agent to disrupt
                     Intafrag</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 6"/>. Hence, Polaxis’s early suspicions of
                  being a test subject in the AR layer are explained in the book layer by Dr.
                  Affeldt, asking him to take his schizophrenia medication <ptr
                     target="#campbell2014a" loc="48"/>. </p>
               <p>At the house party in Montreal, a drug dealer named Feliz appears, and the verbal
                  text in the book describes him as a <quote rend="inline">dapper-looking
                     fellow</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="22"/>, whereas in the AR layer, he is revealed as
                  a gatekeeper holding <quote rend="inline">several ancient keys to enter
                     Intafrag</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 22"/>. Eddie, who is a character that Polaxis
                  meets on his way to Peru, has connections to Intafrag in the app layer, but he is
                  oblivious to his Intafrag experiences, which only Polaxis can see <ptr
                     target="#campbell2014a" loc="AR 32"/>. In the AR layer, normal people attending
                  a shaman ceremony in Peru become strange green creatures from Intafrag and so on.
                  Hence, the people who inhabit the worlds of <hi rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</hi>
                  are not easily trusted. These people, even if radically changing their roles in
                  the story, also connect the TPW of the AR layer with the worlds of the book layer.
                  Nevertheless, there are always some relations that remain the same, reminding the
                  reader that the layers are part of the same story. </p>
               <p>According to Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="76"/>, some fictions create worlds
                  with ontological gaps. Ontological completeness presupposes that <quote
                     rend="inline">for every contradictory pair of propositions, one must be true
                     and another false in that world</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="74"/>. In <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title>, the references to Intafrag may, for the reader, represent an
                  ontological gap in the storyworld; however, from the viewpoint of the main
                  character, Intafrag is the only truth maintained throughout this story.
                  Consequently, Polaxis’s ontological doubts are about how people and events in his
                  actual world are related to (or infiltrated by) Intafrag. Perhaps the possible
                  worlds of the book and the AR layers are ontologically different, but they are
                  still two sides of the same storyworld, according to the main character. Still,
                  there is a question of how this affects the TAW. In the case of a parallel
                  universe, it would connect to the TAW on a more profound level than in the case of
                  being a purely mental possible world. The story’s philosophical framing poses the
                  radical question of what is real. If the parallel universe of Intafrag is given
                  priority, this radically changes the understanding of the TAW, altering
                  propositions from true to false. </p>
               <p>To explore how different worlds may be perceived by the reader, the next section
                  presents a reader-oriented perspective on the simultaneous experiences of the
                  partly conflicting possible worlds depicted in <title rend="italic">Modern
                     Polaxis</title>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Reading <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title></head>
            <p>The literary experience of an AR work differs from reading a traditional book and
               other kinds of digital literature by simultaneously offering two different sides of
               the story. Physically, when reading <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, it
               is possible to read the book first and then use the app to read a different version
               of the story. We expect readers to read the book and app in parallel, first reading a
               page in the book and then seeing what the app reveals. Seeing the story change while
               reading is one thrill of the AR app. It is also crucial to understand the work as a
               whole. This is one storyworld unfolding in two different layers transpiring
               simultaneously. The starting point is that the aesthetic work comes to life through
               the act of reading <ptr target="#iser1978"/>, which is experienced through the senses
               and ultimately activates the reader’s imagination.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Fiction, imagination and sensory experience</head>
               <p>Fictional narratives invite interpretive work that caters to the imagination. As
                  Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="70"/> claims, <quote rend="inline">when a text
                     creates a storyworld, <emph>we imagine that there is more to this world than
                        what the text represents</emph>.</quote> As mentioned in the Theory section,
                  reading fiction includes a triad of fictionalising acts <ptr target="#iser1993"/>:
                  the fictive, the real and the imaginary brought together by the readers’
                  interaction with the text. Certain elements in <title rend="italic">Modern
                     Polaxis</title> expand the possibilities for imagination; for instance, the
                  people whom Polaxis meets are genuinely mysterious, and how he reaches some places
                  in his travels is unclear. This applies to both analogue and digital layers. One
                  might assume that adding information automatically narrows the possibilities for
                  the reader’s imagination. However, Intafrag creates a new space for imaginative
                  deduction and spatial immersion. In this way, <title rend="italic">Modern
                     Polaxis</title> opens itself up for the reader to create a more complex
                  storyworld based on their imagination, thus providing space for the reader’s
                  uncertainties and ambivalences in line with Polaxis’s experience of being in the
                  world. </p>
               <p>Regarding the question of how the interplay between worlds in AR literature may
                  affect the reader’s literary experience, we explore this through Iser’s <ptr
                     target="#iser1984"/> concept of aesthetic response. Iser connects aesthetics
                  with perception and sees the <term>aesthetic effect</term> as a form of
                  realisation stemming from the human senses. This view on aesthetics reflects the
                  etymological meaning of the Greek word, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >aísthēsis</foreign> – sensation. When reading AR literature, the physical
                  sensory experience is simultaneously perceived in both analogue and digital
                  layers, which creates the potential for a multitude of connections between what
                  the senses perceive and how this translates to an act of immersion and inner
                  experience. </p>
               <p>The two TWPs may be seen in light of the platonic question raised at the beginning
                  of the story. Which world is apprehended as the most real world, the one closest
                  to the TAW, as they are both materialised in the physically touchable book or the
                  alternate, mental one? The world in the book layer is generally less colourful
                  than in the digital layer. The digital layer adds perceivable differences, such as
                  colour, movement, sound and sometimes picture-like elements. The visual
                  impressions in the app layer are perceived as more salient than the book’s visual
                  expressions due to the colourfulness and movement. Adding the digital layer
                  changes the visual style, in this case giving more emphasis to affect <ptr
                     target="#painteretal2013" loc="32"/> and hence providing potentials for the
                  readers’ emotional immersion. The liveliness of the AR layer might indicate that
                  this is the most <q>real</q> part of the story. To complicate this, however, the
                  analogue layer is touchable and concrete, whereas the digital layer is volatile
                  and intangible.</p>
               <p>As an example of this layered reading experience, we will have a closer look at
                  the episode in which Polaxis travels from Montreal to Lima, following the
                  ontological gap where time seems to move backwards, as described in the previous
                  section. Pages 27-28 are part of this travel, describing Polaxis on the bus in
                  Peru <ptr target="#campbell2014a" loc="27"/> and what he sees as the bus stops <ptr
                     target="#campbell2014a" loc="28"/>. </p>
               <p>On page 27, Polaxis is depicted on a bus, stating it could be anywhere. He falls
                  asleep and wakes up <quote rend="inline">somewhere else</quote>, which turns out
                  to be Peru. Throughout the comic book the background is white and cross ruled,
                  alluding to Polaxis’s diary being jotted down in a notebook. The image is rather
                  detailed, but a line drawing. On this page the verbiage is in white on black
                  background. There are drawings depicting a chaotic mess, including elements
                  resembling tentacles and branches, over and under the outline of Polaxis on the
                  bus. The page can be read as a comics page divided in three panels horizontally,
                  in which the upper and lower panel represent a chaos foreshadowing the monster on
                  the next page. </p>
               <p> As the AR layer is projected upon the book page, colours appear in the bus window
                  displaying a photographic image of mountains in motion, to indicate that the bus
                  is driving. When looking closely, green, huge, monster-like creatures with long
                  thin insect-like legs emerge in the mountain landscape. The predominantly green
                  monsters connote the green Martians of past times science fiction, perhaps
                  pointing to the outer worldly of a parallel universe. The sound of a vehicle (the
                  bus) merges with strange sounds, perhaps guttural sounds from the monsters, and
                  sounds of large rocks falling. The sounds create feelings of great unease and may
                  be perceived as scary. This is however an interpretation; it is the reader’s
                  starting point in the principle of minimal departure <ptr target="#ryan1991"/>
                  that makes the reader perceive the engine-like noises and the moving image as the
                  bus moving. The photographic image in the AR layer brings the representation
                  closer to the real world of the reader, hence questioning the ontology of the TAW
                  of the book. The green monsters, however, appear hand drawn, perhaps leading the
                  reader to think that they are a product of Polaxis’s imagination. Projecting the
                  AR layer, the colour of the letters shifts from white to red, making them pop out,
                  which in turn gives them a greater semantic load. Polaxis in the AR layer says he
                  closed his eyes on the plane and ended up on the bus, that his position is not
                  stable and that he sees <quote rend="inline">strange shapes</quote> in the
                  distance, presumably referring to the monster-like creatures only visible in this
                  layer. It is up to the reader to draw connections between the book and the AR-
                  layer. The indeterminacy lies in which layer to believe in. Are the monsters
                  products of Polaxis’s imagination, as they are not present in the original <quote
                     rend="inline">hand-written</quote> book? What is the origin of the soundscape?
                  These are fundamental tasks of interpretation for the readers to solve through
                  their imagination. What is specific for comics reading is the interpretative work of closure that happens when the reader draws connections between panels. Adding the AR layer expands this reading space by adding a new kind of <q>gutter</q> between book and app. </p>
               <p>On the opposite page, the text states Cusco, Peru, July 2nd 2009. Words and image
                  in the book describe a rather mundane situation of the bus stopping in the Andes,
                  and construction workers building new roads and installing a traffic light system,
                  which Polaxis finds strange, as the place is quite rural and he states that there
                  is no traffic. A red, thin handwriting on the left reads: <quote rend="inline"
                     >Every [man]<note> The [man] is not written but drawn as a simple symbolic
                        presentation of <q>man</q>. </note> wants to see</quote> and this sentence
                  seems to be continued on the right with <quote rend="inline">the ancient
                     world!</quote></p>
               <p>When the AR layer is projected, a large monster appears, resembling the monsters
                  on the previous page. The animated monster is multi-coloured, but mainly green,
                  and it is not possible to identify its face or body parts. It seems to have
                  tentacles rather than humanlike limbs. The men in the picture who are raising
                  traffic lights in the book version now seem to try to control the monster. The
                  sounds resemble roars, presumably from the monster, along with distant human
                  voices. It is not possible to make out what the voices say, and again it is the
                  principle of minimal departure that makes the reader understand these sounds as
                  human voices from the workers. The red letters stating <quote rend="inline">every
                     man wants to see</quote> now say <quote rend="inline">Intafrag</quote>. They
                  turn turquoise with a red background and are surrounded by lots of spinning
                  arrows, as if symbolising confusion or a compass that is not working. This is an
                  example of the explicit Intafrag references in the AR layer. The verbal text on
                  the top of the page reveals that Polaxis does indeed feel confused, wondering
                  whether what he sees is hallucinations, or whether he actually sees Intafrag.
                  There is an evident void between the perceiving of a mundane, but odd situation in
                  a street, and the revealed monster of the AR-layer. How the layers are connected,
                  is a question of interpretation, where the perspective taken by the main character
                  is only one of many options. The soundscapes and visual layers of AR create
                  unease, merging the sounds of humans and engines with undefinable roars; and the
                  colours, movements and landscapes of the actual world with the hand drawings of
                  the monster. The AR layer questions the ontology of the textual worlds of <title
                     rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> because these elements bring the static
                  situation in the notebook to life. </p>
               <p>The experience of reading this AR comic represents new ways of viewing the
                  relations between the real and the virtual <ptr target="#farman2017"/>. Touching
                  the book while using the app maintains the physical sense of the book medium,
                  while at the same time sensing the AR layer being projected over your hands. The
                  app is transitory, it is only seen and heard when swiping over a page; as opposed
                  to the physically stable book, which can be moved from one place to another
                  without pictures and verbal text disappearing. The touchable book is held against
                  the stronger visual (i.e., colours, movement, etc.) and audible experiences of the
                  app. These sensory experiences underline and thematise the question of what is
                  real or what we may know about the world rather than providing an answer. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The game of interpretation</head>
               <p>Gaps for the reader to fill in the text occur when text segments are indirectly
                  connected and can break the expected order in the text <ptr target="#iser1984"
                     loc="302"/>. Indeterminacies require the reader to make individual decisions on
                  textual meanings. Even if there are several connections between the analogue and
                  digital layers, there are also gaps between them. The main gap consists of the
                  lack of explanation regarding the layers’ differences, raising the question of
                  what is real. An interesting aspect of the gaps in time is that, according to
                  traditional storytelling, they are perceived in the book as gaps for the reader to
                  fill, whereas the digital layer insists on explaining the gaps with time
                  travelling. This repeats the question of what is delusional and what is real. In
                  this uncertainty, the reader participates in the main character’s delusions and
                  his struggle to be in two worlds simultaneously. This distance and tension between
                  the two layers may cause the reader to feel a sense of insecurity. </p>
               <p>The tension between the layers is a driving force in the story. The reader’s
                  curiosity is driven by revealing the differences between the layers, rather than
                  by being immersed in the actual story, which is not very causally driven. This is
                  a form of indeterminacy that seems related to the interpretative work of closure
                  in comics reading. There is little explanation for why the events occur and the
                  information on characters other than Polaxis is very limited. Polaxis himself has
                  a past that is only vaguely elaborated, for instance, with an ex-girlfriend who
                  appears only in a flash. The mundane, the usual and everyday aspects of life, are
                  not emphasised in the work, nor is the causality between events. Mystery surrounds
                  Polaxis, and the reader gets a first-hand impression of his insecurity,
                  estrangement, existential anxiety and uneasiness. The work renders the impression of having access to someone’s delusional and paranoid mind as if the readers are getting to see something that is not for them to see. </p>
               <p>The line of events may not be as interesting as the way the app makes the reader
                  feel. This feeling of estrangement and uneasiness constitutes a common ground for
                  the analogue and digital TPWs. Polaxis does not seem to feel comfortable in any of
                  these worlds. This may be seen in connection to the <term>modern</term> in the
                     <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> story. The modernist feeling is
                  that of estrangement, existential anxiety and uneasiness. The threats in the app
                  come from the Intafrag agents, but Polaxis does not seem to find the real world
                  very appealing either. He wishes to travel through time and space, which is what
                  he simultaneously fears. In a way, he is lost in both worlds. </p>
               <p>Polaxis is presented as a human in a human world and thereby ontologically like
                  the reader, which is a prerequisite for immersion <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="74"
                  />. However, the potential discrepancy between Polaxis’s and the reader’s views of
                  Intafrag makes <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> a work that does not
                  effortlessly provide immersion. This is because Polaxis is not necessarily a
                  character with whom the reader identifies. However, the emotional state of
                  uncertainty and vulnerability, mainly emphasised in the AR layer, may invite
                  identification and emotional immersion. Even if the feeling of estrangement is a
                  general human experience of the modern, it might be said to connect to the story’s
                  psychological dimension. Anxiety and unease are also commonly associated with
                  psychological conditions that sometimes need professional treatment. According to
                  this view, the TPWs constitute both opposites and mutual preconditions for
                  interpretation. </p>
               <p>The narrative possibilities for tensions between the worlds in the case of <title
                     rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> counteract the human pull towards
                  everything adding up in the end. The AR layer questions whether the Intafrag
                  notions are only manifestations of the protagonist’s delusions or whether they
                  are, in fact, real. The latter acts against the conclusion implied in the end when
                  Polaxis is in a mental hospital. The aesthetic experience of the work, namely
                  frustration and feelings of alienation and unease, lies in this counteraction.
                  Since the narrative is difficult to follow, it requires the reader’s
                  concentration. Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2015" loc="68"/> defined concentration as a
                  type of <quote rend="inline">attention devoted to difficult, non-immersive
                     works</quote>. It is possible, however, to have an experience of the app
                  without understanding the full story. Perhaps the aesthetic experience of unease
                  is even stronger than the actual narration of events. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>In this section, we discuss more generally how AR can contribute to literary
               experiences. AR can enhance experiences with sound, colours and animations, but what
               can AR contribute beyond pop-up-like environments with sound effects <ptr
                  target="#helms2017"/>. Does this technology have the potential to enrich literary
               experiences in more profound ways? First, we will look at AR contributions in terms
               of Ryan’s <ptr target="#ryan2019"/> transfictional operations: extension,
               modification and transposition. Then, we discuss some differences between
               location-based and object-based AR and, lastly, the potentials concerning the degree
               of interactivity in AR works. </p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Extension</title> is a transfictional operation that <quote
                  rend="inline">adds new stories to the fictional world while respecting the facts
                  established in the original</quote>
               <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="71"/>. These additional story elements may be more or
               less true to and more or less consistent with the TAW. AR also has the potential to
               expand storytelling experiences by blending fictional worlds with the reader’s actual
               world. In AR stories, such as those of <title rend="italic">Wonderscope</title>,
               users may see the room they are in or even their hands merging into the story. This
               draws the reader closer to the narrative and invites empathy for the characters. In
               other cases, ambivalence may result from the interplay between the layers, or the
               layers may be polarised by providing alternative viewpoints and perspectives <ptr
                  target="#weedonetal2014"/>, as we see in the <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title> story. Whether the aim is to deepen the feeling of closeness and
               empathy or to open new, surprising narrative spaces, AR contributes to the
               storyworld’s extension and elaboration.</p>
            <p>In contrast to extension, <term>modification</term> more radically changes the
               original narrative’s plot <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="71"/>. These changes may
               concern the characters’ behaviours and missions, as in the case of <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, or modify how events play out and ultimately
               change the ending that feeds back in one’s interpretation of the entire story. In
               sum, the layers may offer alternative plotlines or more or less elaborate courses of
               events. <term>Transposition</term> entails a plot moving into a different temporal or
               spatial setting <ptr target="#ryan2019" loc="71"/>. Here, AR may offer new
               possibilities across the narrative dimensions of time and space. Time leaps may occur
               in narratives across media, such as books, films and theatre, but the possibility of
               operating in different times and places in the simultaneous display of analogue and
               digital layers may be specific to AR technology. More generally, AR may inspire a
               broad range of interplay between parallel or contrasting timeframes; for example, an
               AR story with historical events in one layer and something resembling the present day
               in the other (or present-day versus the future, or any other combination). </p>
            <p>The complexity of space being simultaneously perceived in two different layers is
               AR-specific. The AR layer may extend and elaborate the textual worlds in terms of new
               information and additional modes of expression, such as colour, movement and sound.
               The layers may also display more separate possible worlds than in <title
                  rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, thus inviting the creation of stories in
               parallel or contrasting worlds. Such choices may invite a great variety of options
               for spatial immersion. Spatial transpositions seem vital to AR technology. </p>
            <p>The interplay between the AR layer and a physical object or a geographical, spatial
               reality is unique to the AR experience <ptr target="#lietal2017"/>. The merging of a
               digital layer with the physical reality in which the reader’s body is located, is
               perceived differently through AR work than in other media. This adds to the relevance
               of PW theory, as the complexity of textual possible worlds plays out in different
               layers simultaneously. The AR layer can express both closeness and distance to the
               TAW; in the case of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, AR contributes to
               distancing the reader from the TAW. This interplay between different dimensions or
               worlds has significant potential for expanding the storyworld. The potential
               complexity of the interplay between worlds seems extensive through the combination of
               the physical and AR layers. However, one could also imagine a less complex
               relationship between the analogue and the digital. The PW of the AR layer may support
               or subvert the premises of other textual worlds.</p>
            <p>As previously mentioned, AR has the potential to play with both surroundings and
               artefacts. In this respect, there is a difference between space-oriented and
               object-oriented works. In location-based works, the opportunity arises to exploit the
               fact that the user must move physically from one place to another, which influences
               their experience of the story. In object-based AR, one can envision endless
               possibilities in the choice of objects onto which the story is projected, moving far
               beyond the traditional comic book medium employed in <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title>. One example is the <title rend="italic">Merge Cube</title>,
               formed like a giant dice that fits in your hand, onto which the multilinear AR story
                  <title rend="italic">57° North</title> is projected; however, the potential is not
               utilised in this app, where turning the cube has much the same function as turning a
               book page. The potential for further development appears to be extensive, with
               stories yet to be told. </p>
            <p>While interactivity in <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> is kept to a
               minimum, the possibilities for interactions in terms of tasks for the reader to solve
               or paths to choose in AR work seem endless. Using interactivity in narrative apps
               carries potentials to expand aesthetic experiences in several ways <ptr
                  target="#hagen2020"/>. The already complex combination of AR and the actual and
               possible worlds of the story may be additionally augmented through the creative use
               of interactivity. </p>
            <p>Topics about location-based AR and interactivity could be extended to future research
               on AR narratives. For this paper, we have merely touched upon some of the
               possibilities that lie in an approach based in narratology and possible world theory.
               Further research on AR and aesthetic experiences, could broaden this perspective with
               insights from multimodal theory or game studies, which would expand the understanding
               of how AR literature works. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The analysis of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> shows how AR can contribute to aesthetic experiences through the parallel structure — the simultaneous sensation of the story’s different layers that cannot be experienced in a format other than AR. The potential complexities of reading AR comics may be understood as an extension of the two dimensions characteristic of comics discussed by Scott McCloud <ptr target="#mccloud1993"/>: The juxtaposition of panels, as well as that of words and images. McCloud categorises six kinds of transitions between panels, of which action-to-action is the dominant in comics within western culture. Interestingly, he finds cultural differences, where aspect-to-aspect transitions are more common in comics from Eastern culture (Japan). This kind of transition <quote rend="inline">bypasses time for the most sake and set a wandering eye on different aspects of a place, idea or mood</quote> <ptr target="#mccloud1993" loc="72"/>.
               
               As we have pointed out in the analysis, the interpretative work of closure that is involved in connecting what happens in a sequence of panels across gutters, is multiplied in reading AR comics. Adding the AR layer may work as a new kind of <q>gutter.</q> In the case of <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, this contributes primarily to the mood by elaborating different aspects of the storyworld. </p>
            <p> Furthermore, in AR comics the digital layer caters for including new modes such as
               sound and animation to the words and images in printed comics. These are experienced
               simultaneously, and may expand, modify, transpose, or even contradict the printed
               story. The simultaneous merging of layers carries a specific potential for
               elaborating the emotional immersion in the story, rather than the sequence of actions
               unfolding in time. Hence the AR layer may be particularly interesting as it
               complements sequential art with nuances, paradoxes and embodied experience through a
               fuller multimodal orchestration. </p>
            <p> The prerequisite for such potential expansions in time and space to be successful in
               augmenting the story told, rather than disturbing the narrative drive or displacing
               attention from meaning to form, is that the AR layer is consistently integrated in
               the story, as Helms points out <ptr target="#helms2017" loc="62"/>. In the case of
                  <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title>, the AR layer affects every spread
               throughout the story, and this playing with worlds is thematically justified by
               framing the story with Plato’s allegory of the cave. It may be no coincidence that we
               find such a thorough AR strategy in a unique, stand-alone story, written, illustrated
               and animated by one artist, in close cooperation with programmer and musical
               composer. </p>
            <p>As implied in our discussion, these insights from reading <title rend="italic">Modern
                  Polaxis</title> may transfer to other kinds of AR literature through an
               understanding of panels, gutters and layers as spaces of interpretation. In Wolfgang
               Iser’s more general theory of aesthetic response, this experience of connecting
               events over time and space, can be seen as gaps, blanks and indeterminacies, which
               invite the reader into the work of interpretation by connecting syntagmatic
               combination with paradigmatic selection. This opens possibilities for telling
               multifaceted, complex stories, and this complexity is sensed through AR technology
               and at least partly driven and caused by it. In simultaneously displayed layers lie
               possibilities for unique aesthetic experiences. Hence, AR may contribute to complex
               storyworlds by presenting possible worlds in different layers and exploiting the
               spatial complexity of textual worlds specific to AR. The reader’s literary
               experiences may be correspondingly complex, as the narrative worlds expand and reach
               beyond the reader’s previous literary experiences. </p>
            <p>On a more general note, we could say that the relations between levels of reality in
               AR fiction remind us of the challenges of interpretation. Iser <ptr
                  target="#iser2000" loc="147"/> claims that any interpretation opens a liminal
               space, and he connects a poetic quality <ptr target="#iser2000" loc="150"/> to this
                  <quote rend="inline">space between</quote>
               <ptr target="#iser1996"/>. He sees interpretation as a dynamic process where this
               space invites the reader to perform new meaning. We find that this awareness of the
               game of interpretation is amplified by the layered structure of AR narratives. The
               core of the AR function lies in the different aesthetic perceptions of the layers, as
               well as in the differences and tensions of the layers, the gaps between them, and
               despite all of this, their creation of a common ground for interpretation.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="azumaetal2001" label="Azuma et al. 2001">Azuma, R., Baillot, Y.,
               Behringer, R., Feiner, S., Julier, S. and MacIntyre, B. <title rend="quotes">Recent
                  advances in augmented reality,</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>, 21(6) (2001):
               34-47. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/38.963459"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1109/38.963459</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blippar2011" label="BlippAR 2011"><title rend="italic">BlippAR</title>.
               BlippAR Group Limited, 2011. <ref target="https://www.blippar.com/"
                  >https://www.blippar.com/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="campbell2014a" label="Campbell 2014a">Campbell, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Modern Polaxis</title> [book and smartphone application software], (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="campbell2014b" label="Campbell 2014b">Campbell, S. <title rend="italic">Modern Polaxis</title> [website]. 2014. <ref
                  target="https://modernpolaxis.com/">https://modernpolaxis.com/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chanlin2018" label="ChanLin 2018">ChanLin, L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Bridging Children’s Reading with an Augmented Reality Story
               Library</title>, Libri, 68(3) (2018): 219–229. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1515/libri-2018-0017"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1515/libri-2018-0017</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="devinenietal" label="Devineni et al."> Devineni, R., et al. <title
                  rend="italic">Priya</title>. <ref target="https://www.priyashakti.com/"
                  >https://www.priyashakti.com/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dolezel1998" label="Doležel 1998">Doležel, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Heterocosmica: fiction and possible worlds</title>. Johns Hopkins University
               Press, Baltimore (1998).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eco1984" label="Eco 1984">Eco, U. <title rend="italic">The Role of the
                  Reader: Explorations in the Semiotics of Texts</title>. Bloomington, Indiana UP
               (1984).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="farman2017" label="Farman 2017">Farman, J. <title rend="quotes">When
                  Geolocation Meets Visualization.</title> In S. Morey and J. Tinnell (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Augmented Reality; Innovative Perspectives Across Art, Industry, and
                  Academia</title>. Parlor Press, Anderson, South Carolina (2017): 177-199.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greenetal2019" label="Green et al. 2019">Green, M., McNair, L., Pierce, C.
               and Harvey, C. <title rend="quotes">An Investigation of Augmented Reality Picture
                  Books: Meaningful Experiences or Missed Opportunities?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Educational Multimedia and Hypermedia</title>, 28(4)
               (2019): 357–380.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hagen2020" label="Hagen 2020">Hagen, A. <title rend="quotes">The Potential
                  for Aesthetic Experience in a Literary App,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Nordic Journal of ChildLit Aesthetics</title>, 11 (2020): 1-10.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18261/issn.2000-7493-2020-01-02"
                  >https://doi.org/10.18261/issn.2000-7493-2020-01-02</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="helms2017" label="Helms 2017">Helms, J. <title rend="quotes">Potential
                  Panels; Towards a Theory of Augmented Comics.</title> In S. Morey and J. Tinnell
               (eds), <title rend="italic">Augmented Reality; Innovative Perspectives Across Art,
                  Industry, and Academia</title>. Parlor Press, Anderson, South Carolina (2017):
               47-62.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iser1978" label="Iser 1978">Iser, W. <title rend="italic">The Act of
                  Reading: A Theory of Aesthetic Response</title>. Johns Hopkins, London
               (1978).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iser1984" label="Iser 1984">Iser, W. <title rend="italic">Der Akt des
                  Lesens: Theorie ästhetischer Wirkung</title>. W. Fink, München (1984).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iser1993" label="Iser 1993">Iser, W. <title rend="italic">The fictive and
                  the imaginary: charting literary anthropology</title>. John Hopkins University
               Press, Baltimore (1993).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iser1996" label="Iser 1996">Iser, W. <title rend="quotes">Coda to the
                  Discussion.</title> In S. Budick and W. Iser (eds), <title rend="italic">The
                  Translatability of Cultures: Figurations of the Space Between</title>. Stanford
               University Press, Stanford, CA. (1996): 294–302.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iser2000" label="Iser 2000">Iser, W. <title rend="italic">The Range of
                  Interpretation</title>. Columbia University Press, New York (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenkins2007" label="Jenkins 2007">Jenkins, H. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Transmedia Storytelling 101,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Confessions of an Aca-Fan</title> (2007). <ref
                  target="http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2007/03/transmedia_storytelling_101.html"
                  >http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2007/03/transmedia_storytelling_101.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lietal2017" label="Li et al. 2017">Li, J., van der Spek, E., Feijs, L.,
               Wang, F. and Hu, J. <title rend="quotes">Augmented Reality Games for Learning: A
                  Literature Review.</title> In N. Streitz and P. Markopoulos (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>, volume 10291, Springer
               International Publishing (2017): 612–626. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-58697-7_46"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-58697-7_46</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liestol2011" label="Liestøl 2011">Liestøl, G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Situated Simulations Between Virtual Reality and Mobile Augmented Reality:
                  Designing a Narrative Space.</title> In B. Furht (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Handbook of Augmented Reality</title>, Springer.
               https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4614-0064-6_14</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liestol2019" label="Liestøl 2019">Liestøl, G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Augmented Reality Storytelling: Narrative Design and Reconstruction of a
                  Historical Event in situ,</title> <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                  Interactive Mobile Technologies (iJIM)</title>, 13(12) (2019): 196–206.
               https://doi.org/10.3991/ijim.v13i12.11560</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lovlie2009" label="Løvlie 2009">Løvlie, A.S. <title rend="quotes">Poetic
                  Augmented Reality: Place-bound Literature in Locative Media.</title>
               <title rend="italic">MindTrek '09: Proceedings of the 13th International MindTrek
                  Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era</title>, September 2009: 19–28.
                  <ref target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/proceedings/10.1145/1621841"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1145/1621841.1621847</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccloud1993" label="McCloud 1993">McCloud, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Understanding comics</title>. Harper Perennial, New York (1993). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mightycoconut2017" label="Mighty Coconut 2017">Mighty Coconut. <title
                  rend="italic">57° North</title>. Mighty Coconut (2017). <ref
                  target="https://www.mightycoconut.com/57north"
                  >https://www.mightycoconut.com/57north</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="painteretal2013" label="Painter et al. 2013">Painter, C., Martin, J.R. and
               Unsworth, L. <title rend="quotes">Reading Visual Narratives.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Image Analysis of Children’s Picture Books</title>. Equinox,
               Sheffield (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="prakashetal2020" label="Prakash et al. 2020"> Prakash, S., Fini, S., and
               Kazemifar, N. <title rend="italic">Priya's Mask</title>. Rattapallax, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ronen1994" label="Ronen 1994">Ronen, R. <title rend="italic">Possible
                  worlds in literary theory</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
               (1994).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan1991" label="Ryan 1991">Ryan, M.-L. <title rend="italic">Possible
                  Worlds, Artificial Intelligence and Narrative Theory</title>. Indiana University
               Press, Bloomington (1991).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2015" label="Ryan 2015">Ryan, M.-L. <title rend="italic">Narrative as
                  Virtual Reality 2: Revisiting Immersion and Interactivity in Literature and
                  Electronic Media</title>. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2019" label="Ryan 2019">Ryan, M.-L. <title rend="quotes">From Possible
                  Worlds to Storyworlds: On the Worldness of Narrative Representation.</title> In A.
               Bell and M-L. Ryan (eds), <title rend="italic">Possible Worlds Theory and
                  Contemporary Narratology</title>. University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln
               (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryanandbell2019" label="Ryan and Bell 2019">Ryan, M.-L. and Bell, A.
                  <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Possible Worlds Theory Revisited.</title> In
               Alice Bell and Marie-Laure Ryan (eds), <title rend="italic">Possible Worlds Theory
                  and Contemporary Narratology</title>. University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln
               (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="saint-gelais2005" label="Saint-Gelais 2005">Saint-Gelais, R. <title
                  rend="quotes">Transfictionality.</title> In D. Herman, M. Jahn and M.-L. Ryan
               (eds), <title rend="italic">The Routledge Encyclopedia of Narrative Theory</title>.
               Routledge, London (2005): 309–10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shields2020" label="Shields 2020">Shields, R. <title rend="italic">Neon
                  Wasteland</title>. (2020) <ref target="https://www.neonwastelandgame.com/"
                  >https://www.neonwastelandgame.com/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weedonetal2014" label="Weedon et al. 2014">Weedon, A., Miller, D., Franco,
               C. P., Moorhead, D. and Pearce, S. <title rend="quotes">Crossing Media Boundaries:
                  Adaptations and New Media Forms of the Book,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Convergence</title>, 20(1) (2014): 108–124. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1354856513515968"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1177/1354856513515968</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wonderscope2019" label="Wonderscope 2019">
               <title rend="italic">Wonderscope</title>. Within Unlimited Inc., vers. 1.18, 2019.
               Apple App Store, <ref target="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/wonderscope/"
                  >https://apps.apple.com/us/app/wonderscope/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wuetal2013" label="Wu et al. 2013">Wu, H-K., Lee, S. W-Y. Chang, H-Y. and
               Liang, J-C. <title rend="quotes">Current Status, Opportunities and Challenges of
                  Augmented Reality in Education,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Computers &amp; Education</title>, 62 (2013): 41–49. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.compedu.2012.10.024"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compedu.2012.10.024</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="yilmazetal2017" label="Yilmaz et al. 2017">Yilmaz, R. M., Kucuk, S. and
               Goktas, Y. <title rend="quotes">Are Augmented Reality Picture Books Magic or Real for
                  Preschool Children Aged Five to Six?</title>
               <title rend="italic">British Journal of Educational Technology</title> 48(3) (2017):
               824-841. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/bjet.12452"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/bjet.12452</ref></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
