<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities
                    Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in
                    Digital Humanities Centers</title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Mila <dhq:family>Oiva</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Turku (Finland)</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>milaoiva@tlu.ee</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Mila Oiva is a Cultural Historian, digital humanist and expert on Russian
                            and Polish history. She is currently finalizing her work as a
                            postdoctoral researcher at the University of Turku in Finland and
                            starting as a senior research fellow at the CUDAN ERA Chair, Tallinn
                            University, Estonia. Her research focuses on computer-assisted analysis
                            of transfer and circulation of knowledge, ranging from the 19th century
                            press through the Cold War era trans-systemic interactions to the 21st
                            century internet discussions.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000464</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital humanities</item>
                        <item>transfer of knowledge</item>
                        <item>research facilitation</item>
                        <item>social networks</item>
                        <item>organization</item>
                        <item>digital communication tools</item>
                        <item>space</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
            <change who="BRG" when="2022-07-27">Revised encoding to pass validation</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
                <p>This article examines digital humanities (DH) centers as focal points of the
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge. It is based on the assumption that the
                    manner in which the knowledge-transfer activities of DH communities are
                    facilitated affects the knowledge they produce. Following an analysis of eight
                    semi-structured interviews of directors, researchers, and administrators, the
                    article considers how DH professionals describe the facilitation of the
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in DH centers. It demonstrates that the
                    transfer of knowledge in DH centers is based on overlapping layers of organic
                    networks and stable organizational structures that support various kinds of
                    knowledge-sharing practices. The transfer of knowledge in DH centers combines
                    the exchange of ideas in the same physical space with online communication at
                    various levels, ranging from outside academia to the internal communication of a
                    research group. Further, the factors that enable information flow also have the
                    capability to restrict potentially meaningful information from entering into the
                    field. As a result, this article suggests that it is important to continue the
                    discussion on the boundaries for the transfer of knowledge in DH.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            	<p>This article examines digital humanities (DH) centers as focal points of the
            		interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the <ref
                        target="https://whatisdigitalhumanities.com/"
                        >whatisdigitalhumanities.com</ref> web page reveals a new definition for
                    digital humanities (DH)<note>In this article, I use the concept of digital
                        humanities for the sake of clarity, although the practices of culture
                        analytics, computational social sciences, and others come close to those of
                        DH.</note> each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800
                    participants in the <title rend="italic">Day of DH</title>, from 2009 to 2014,
                    state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in
                    humanities research and teaching <ptr target="#whatisdigitalhumanities"/>. In
                    the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that
                    the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches <ptr target="#terras2010a"/>
                    <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2010"/>. While there are almost as many ways of
                    verbalizing the definition of DH as there are individuals involved in it, it
                    seems that many of us agree that DH operates in the intersection of what has
                    traditionally been considered to be humanities disciplines and computing.</p>
                <p>Therefore, it is valid to state that DH is a field that is rooted in
                    interdisciplinarity. The dynamics, challenges, and promises of DH all emerge
                    from the interaction of diverging disciplines and approaches. The
                    interdisciplinary character of DH emphasizes the social aspects of research,
                    where intellectual communication becomes an integral part of a research process.
                    The centers and laboratories that have been established in various universities
                    have become important nodes in the global <quote rend="inline">web of
                        DH,</quote> owing to their ability to bring people together. These spaces
                    are focal points in the interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge, as they connect
                    humanities, social sciences, computer sciences, mathematics, and knowledge in
                    other fields to produce new understanding, host a multitude of projects, and
                    bring different departments and organizations together as part of a wider DH
                    network. One could say that DH centers are the hubs of DH, which both support
                    and gain their energy from the constant transfer of knowledge among various
                    actors.</p>
                <p>If transfer of knowledge is crucial both for DH centers and the field, how do DH
                    centers manage and facilitate the interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge? How
                    is transfer of knowledge promoted so that individual scholars gain an
                    understanding what is being done in the other disciplines, and collaboration of
                    interdisciplinary research groups has less obstacles? The practices,
                    facilitation, and organization of DH projects and communities have been gaining
                    increasing scholarly interest over the past years. The themes that encompass the
                    tasks and institutional models of DH centers <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>, the
                    best ways to manage DH projects <ptr target="#tabak2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#reed2014"/>, the steps needed for establishing a DH community <ptr
                        target="#galinarussell2015"/>, or collaboration and communication <ptr
                        target="#vangorpandbron2019"/>
                    <ptr target="#matres2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#griffin2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#keener2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemensetal2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#deegan2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2009"/>, have been topical in the ongoing discussion.
                    Simultaneously, interdisciplinary research and knowledge transfer within
                    organizations has been widely examined in management studies, thereby enabling
                    categorizations of the features of knowledge transfers <ptr
                        target="#siedlokandhibbert2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012"/>. These studies have provided important
                    information on the features of DH research and indicated factors that are
                    generally considered crucial in information transfers. However, thus far, it is
                    not very clear how the DH field facilitates interdisciplinary transfer of
                    knowledge and what this reveals about the field in general. </p>
                <p>Understanding the practices, structures, and the community underlying knowledge
                    construction — which knowledge transfer is a crucial part of — is important for
                    grasping what DH research is based on and its various nuances. Knowledge is
                    inseparable from the communities that create it, its context, structure, and the
                    means with which it is produced and shared. It is an ongoing social
                    accomplishment, constituted and re-constituted in practice <ptr
                        target="#krishnaveni2012" loc="37"/>
                    <ptr target="#orlikowski2002" loc="249, 253, 270"/>. Thus, the manner in which
                    DH communities function and in which their knowledge transfer activities are
                    facilitated influences the knowledge they produce.</p>
                <p>This article studies how DH professionals describe the interdisciplinary transfer
                    of knowledge that takes place in DH centers and what they see as the main ways
                    of facilitating these transfers. Responding to this research question
                    contributes to the discussions on the premises on which DH research produces
                    knowledge by exploring the field from the perspective of transfer of knowledge.
                    The underlying idea is that understanding how knowledge is transferred within
                    the field enables us to analyze what kind of knowledge DH research produces and
                    identify the potential limitations for our knowledge base. The ways we make DH
                    possible influences the ways we conduct research and, finally, the outcomes of
                    our research. </p>
                <p>The current study is based on eight interviews with DH facilitators in
                    (alphabetical order): Comhis Collective (Helsinki, Finland); HELDIG (Helsinki,
                    Finland); Northeastern University Library Digital Scholarship Group (from now on
                    NULDSG, Boston Mass., USA); NULab (Northeastern University, Boston Mass., USA);
                    and University College London Digital Humanities Center (from now on UCLDH,
                    London, UK).<note>The transcriptions of the interviews and the interview
                        questions of <title rend="italic">FSD3362 Facilitating Digital Humanities
                            Research 2017</title> are stored at the Finnish Social Sciences Data
                        Archive <ref
                            target="https://services.fsd.uta.fi/catalogue/FSD3362?lang=en&amp;study_language=en"
                            >https://services.fsd.uta.fi/catalogue/FSD3362?lang=en&amp;study_language=en</ref>
                        and available for research and teaching purposes. The interviews were
                        collected in connection to <title rend="quotes">From Roadmap to Roadshow: A
                            collective demonstration and information project to strengthen Finnish
                            digital history</title> project. The principal investigator of the KONE
                        Foundation funded project was Professor Mats Fridlund (Aalto University,
                        Finland) and the author worked in close collaboration with Dr. Petri Paju
                        (University of Turku, Finland).</note> The interviewees worked in different
                    positions in DH centers — they were directors, leading scholars, managers, and
                    administrators — and thus the expertise of the interviewees comes with different
                    perspectives toward facilitating DH research. The idea of the interviews was to
                    collect the experiences of DH facilitators and practitioners and analyze how
                    they describe the organizational, infrastructure and practice based obstacles
                    for DH research, and their solutions to overcome them. The overarching question
                    of the semi-structured interviews was <quote rend="inline">how does your
                        center/group facilitate DH research?</quote> excavated by detailed questions
                    on the everyday practices of the institution. The used analysis method was
                    thematic analysis with inductive essentialist approach <ptr target="#braun2006"
                    />. Following this approach, the article identifies platforms of and recurrent
                    practices and obstacles related to transfer of knowledge in the interviews. The
                    small sample of interviews, even if collected in three countries, does not
                    represent all the DH centers or even all the aspects of the studied centers.
                    However, being experienced and well-networked DH professionals working in
                    thriving DH centers, the interviewees’ visions related to the field furthers the
                    discussion on how the ways DH is facilitated affects the outcomes of the field.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Interdisciplinary DH and Transfer of Knowledge</head>
                <p><quote rend="block">I think that one of the most interesting results [of the
                        NULab] are some of the unexpected results of the crossed collaboration that
                        has come out of it.[Interview with Ryan Cordell]</quote></p>
                <p>When describing the activities at the NULab Ryan Cordell drew a picture of
                    interdisciplinary collaboration, where <quote rend="inline">people from computer
                        sciences work together with the people from English, people in political
                        science and journalism work together, folks from African-American studies
                        collaborate with computer scientists, [all] working together on
                        memes</quote> [Interview with Ryan Cordell]. In fact all the interviewees
                    considered interdisciplinarity to be rooted in the core idea of DH research, and
                    the main factor that made DH research fascinating. Consequently, they described
                    the work in DH centers resulting from the activities of people belonging to
                    different disciplines, departments, and organizations [Interview with Élika
                    Orgtega] [Interview with Sarah Connell] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen] [Interview
                    with Caroline Klibanoff] [Interview with Mikko Tolonen] [Interview with Melissa
                    Terras] [Interview with David Beavan].</p>
                <p>DH centers, as understood in this article, are <emph>spaces</emph> manifested
                    through a variety networks, collaborations, organizational structures, digital
                    presence and occasionally, but not always, in physical premises <ptr
                        target="#oivaandpawlickadeger2020"/>. Although the studied centers reside at
                    academic institutions, their physical <soCalled>location</soCalled> can be fluid
                    and non-bounded. Simultaneously, interdisciplinary research can be defined as a
                    mode of research that transgresses the traditional boundaries of disciplines and
                    is more extensive or powerful than the sum of the components <ptr
                        target="#siedlokandhibbert2014" loc="197"/>. Research literature identifies
                    various forms of interdisciplinary research, and the typology of
                    interdisciplinary collaboration continues to be debated. For example, scholars
                    classify interdisciplinary research into <hi rend="italic"
                        >multidisciplinary</hi>, <hi rend="italic">transdisciplinary</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="italic">interdisciplinary</hi> research depending on the level and
                    process of integration of the participating disciplines <ptr target="#klein2014"/>
                	<ptr target="#siedlokandhibbert2014" loc="198–199"/>
                    <ptr target="#huutoniemi2010" loc="83"/>. Regardless the intensity of
                    interdisciplinary integration, it seems that the first step required for
                    interdisciplinary collaboration leading to fruitful mixes of disciplinary
                    approaches, is the transfer of knowledge from one discipline to another. </p>
                <p>The concept of <quote rend="inline">transfer of knowledge</quote> in its basic
                    form implies <quote rend="inline">conveyance of knowledge from one place, person
                        or ownership to another.</quote> Transfer of knowledge does not imply
                    transfer of an entire replica of the knowledge to the receiver, as the knowledge
                    can be modified in the receiving unit <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012" loc="27"/>.
                    Transfer of knowledge is a loose concept that has been studied in various kinds
                    of research that analyze activities between countries and organizations,
                    including within and outside academia <ptr target="#fullwood2013" loc="130"/>.
                    Because of its fluidity, transfer of knowledge can also be used as an analytical
                    tool in studying the facilitation of interdisciplinary collaboration, such as DH
                    research. </p>
                <p>When discussing everyday interdisciplinary practices, the interviewees referred
                    to versatile activities of interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge, varying from
                    listening to talks held by scholars from other disciplines to integrated
                    collaboration and joint production of research findings. The reasons for
                    organizing all these activities lays in the ways we understand where
                    interdisciplinary research can lead us. The research literature reveals both
                    cynical and optimistic reasons for interdisciplinary researcher interaction.
                    Interdisciplinary research has been a fashionable buzzword in science and
                    innovation policy, where it has been assumed that increased collaboration leads
                    to increased productivity of scientific achievements and innovations. This has
                    led to expanded usage of the term in the funding applications, but not always in
                    research practice <ptr target="#siedlokandhibbert2014" loc="194"/>. In addition
                    to using interdisciplinary research as a label for being competitive in grant
                    calls, there is also genuine belief that only by going beyond the boundaries of
                    disciplines will we be able to understand and respond to the complex problems of
                    the world <ptr target="#podesta2013" loc="40"/>. Furthermore, interdisciplinary
                    researcher interaction can profoundly change the premises of research <ptr
                        target="#svensson2010" loc="163"/>. According to the interviewees, the main
                    point of interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge was the potential of reaching
                    unexpected outcomes. For them, at its best, interdisciplinary collaboration
                    leads to new findings and forming new understanding. The experiences of the
                    interviewees demonstrated that the results of an interdisciplinary collaboration
                    can be more than the sum of the contributors and lead to outcomes that no one
                    could expect [Interview with Mikko Tolonen] [Interview with Ryan Cordell].
                    Interdisciplinary collaboration is the salt and pepper — and most likely also
                    the chili and honey — of DH research, that promises reaching for the
                    epoch-making findings.</p>
                <p>While there are high expectations for interdisciplinary collaboration,
                    implementing it in practice is not easy. The interviewees noted that the main
                    challenges of such a collaboration are related to divergent ways of
                    understanding issues, varying from the basic assumption of the preferred
                    outcomes of research and concepts, to more concrete questions of what makes a
                    paper, or how to name authors, and to different institutional and individual
                    expectations [Interview with Sarah Connell] [Interview with Melissa Terras]
                    [Interview with Ryan Cordell]. The challenges of interdisciplinary collaboration
                    have been discussed widely in different fields <ptr target="#podesta2013"/>]
                        <ptr target="#romerolankao2013" loc="35, 38"/>
                	<ptr target="#olson2014" loc="3–4"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2009" loc="229"/>, including DH literature. The latest
                    studies in DH have identified misconceptions and distrust among different
                    disciplines and schools, as well as structural and promotion-related obstacles
                    to collaborative research <ptr target="#keener2015" loc="¶43"/>
                    <ptr target="#klein2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#zorich2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>. Obstacles often arise when differing disciplinary
                    cultures with distinctive practices need to achieve something together. At its
                    worst, attempted collaboration among various disciplinary cultures can lead to
                    collisions due to epistemological and methodological differences,
                    discipline-driven understanding of the context, and uneven technical skills <ptr
                    	target="#terras2010b" loc="175–176, 183–184"/>
                    <ptr target="#siedlokandhibbert2014" loc="204"/>. In addition to the social
                    challenges for interdisciplinary understanding, the literature has identified
                    several obstacles for information flows in DH research, which result from
                    combinations of siloed organizational structures and administration, using
                    processes of digital tools that create bottlenecks in information flows, lack of
                    collaboration, differences in understanding among different disciplines, unclear
                    knowledge-sharing practices, and lack of continuity and maintenance <ptr
                        target="#nygren2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#terras2010b" loc="186"/>.</p>
                <p>This brings us to the question that if transfer of knowledge is simultaneously
                    challenging and crucial for DH, how can we enable and support fruitful
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge? In her interview, Élika Ortega offered
                    a path for finding a solution to the challenge of understanding gap between
                    disciplines. She compared the interdisciplinary research of DH to a wide
                    spectrum of perspectives, where scholars coming from different disciplines
                    reside — literature scholars sit next to anthropologists, while mathematicians
                    are located closer to computer scientists in the spectrum. According to Ortega,
                    it can be difficult to understand someone at the other end of that spectrum,
                    while scholars in neighboring disciplines are easier to understand: <quote
                        rend="block">I think there are [problems in interdisciplinary
                        understanding]. [ — ] If we stretched out that spectrum, I guess some of us
                        [the DHers] would end up in one extreme, and some other would end up in the
                        other end, [ — ] but there are all of the steps in between. So, if this end
                        and that end are not necessarily communicating right away, then there are
                        steps to follow to one or the other, or to the middle point where that can
                        be sort of translated. And they translate little by little, like move
                        knowledge from one to the other. To move it through the spectrum. So, I
                        think it definitely happens, and the bigger the group the more that
                        happens.[Interview with Élika Ortega]</quote></p>
                <p>For Ortega, interdisciplinary research in DH is about a step-by-step transfer of
                    understanding along the spectrum, transmission of knowledge from one discipline
                    to the neighboring one, and onward from that. An analysis of the interviews of
                    this study reveals that implementing gradual transfer of knowledge requires
                    people with differing knowledge (actors), networks, and spaces facilitating
                    communication as well as motivation and supporting practices. The following
                    sub-sections of this article will discuss how these features support
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in DH centers.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Creation and Maintenance of Networks</head>
                <p>The core of the interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in DH centers are
                    networks. When asked about the main activities of the DH centers, the
                    interviewees described various methods of creating and maintaining
                    interdisciplinary networks to support informal communication and structured
                    transfer of knowledge. The first and most crucial step in enabling
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge is to enable people from different
                    disciplines to meet and communicate with each other. All the interviewees
                    indicate that building and maintaining the network and ensuring that people meet
                    each other on a regular basis to share their thoughts and ideas are the core of
                    facilitating DH research. The DH centers enable this meeting of people by
                    organizing weekly meetings, seminars, talks, tutorials, workshops, office hours,
                        <soCalled>speed-dating,</soCalled> speaker series, hackathons, summits
                    compiling all local DH projects, and meetings of smaller groups and other less
                    and more formal meetings that bring people together. [Interview with David
                    Beavan] [Interview with Ryan Cordell] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen] [Interview
                    with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Sarah Connell] [Interview with Mikko
                    Tolonen] [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff]. When meeting each other, the
                    representatives of different disciplines discuss and share ideas that often
                    foster new thoughts <ptr target="#galinarussell2015"/>. The networking
                    activities of DH centers are not necessarily different from other academic
                    environments, but because people come to DH from different disciplines, enhanced
                    attention must be given to getting people together, thereby making building and
                    maintaining networks more essential. </p>
                <p>The interviewed DH specialists indicated that they used various paths for
                    networking and sharing experiences and information in the community. Moreover,
                    they also added that numerous facilitators had carefully shaped the different
                    forms of the meetings to enable the highest level of transfer of knowledge.
                    Thus, one can say that they do not merely gather people together in the same
                    room and hope for the best but that they have created several routines or
                    practices that support the sharing of information. For example, at
                    Northeastern’s NULab and Digital Scholarship Group, administrators organize
                    various meetings so that there are moments where everybody talks and not only
                    the invited speakers [Interview with Sarah Connell].</p>
                <p>The transfer of explicit knowledge in DH centers takes place in courses and
                    workshops. A few centers offer consultation sessions on various themes, as well
                    as help students and scholars to launch projects that contain methods that are
                    new for them [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff]. Although formal education is
                    usually directed at students, there is also a need to learn new things among
                    scholars who have completed their formal education. Director of HELDIG, Eero
                    Hyvönen, indicated that they organize DH courses not only for students but also
                    scholars with the hope that the latter would update their knowledge and add new
                    elements to their knowledge base [Interview with Eero Hyvönen].</p>
                <p>Interestingly, numerous interviewees emphasized the importance of informal
                    meetings, although the centers also organize more formal event [Interview with
                    Ryan Cordell] [Interview with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. For
                    example, Ryan Cordell mentioned how he had learned new methods from informal
                    conversations with colleagues in other disciplines [Interview with Ryan
                    Cordell]. Thus, it appears that informal events ease the processes of becoming
                    acquainted with others and building trust as they allow free-flowing discussion
                    in a less hierarchical atmosphere, which contribute to the transfer of tacit
                    knowledge. Informal meetings may lead to something that the interviewees
                    described as <quote rend="inline">unexpected results of crossed
                        collaboration</quote> [Interview with Ryan Cordell] [see also Interview with
                    Mikko Tolonen]. Along the same lines, Phillips et al. describe in this special
                    issue the <quote rend="inline">serendipitous accidents</quote> as one of the key
                    engines of their lab <ptr target="#phillips2020"/>. It appears that open and
                    unplanned interdisciplinary encounters foster unexpected results, which include
                    the promise and potential of interdisciplinary research.</p>
                <p>Further, the interviewees described how sharing information at various levels
                    translates into different kinds of activities in their work, such as learning
                    new methods, establishing new projects, teaching, etc. According to them, the
                    outcomes of the transfer of knowledge can assume many forms. A discussion with a
                    colleague can translate into a new angle in a research project, teaching, or
                    form the basis of a new invention. Things learned in a workshop can be
                    transformed into a grant proposal, applied to research, or implemented in
                    teaching [Interview with Ryan Cordell] [Interview with Sarah Connell]. </p>
                <p>The active networking — or <soCalled>colliding</soCalled>
                        (<soCalled>törmäyttäminen</soCalled> in Finnish) of people, as formulated by
                    Eero Hyvönen — is not an accidental activity. In fact, it is in the very core of
                    creating a thriving DH center. The goal of constant networking and communication
                    across disciplines is the establishment of interdisciplinary research groups,
                    which will be helpful when applying for funding. For Melissa Terras, <quote
                        rend="block">[p]art of the thing is that it's good for people to meet
                        regularly, because if you have a chance to meet people in the seminars then
                        when the grant call comes in, then you will find more easily people to work
                        with grant applications, you can put people together with other people, you
                        can network when you know a lot of people, when you know a lot of people you
                        will be able to put together them when needed. So, the Center is set up to
                        be a mailman that helps people to get to know each other.[Interview with
                        Melissa Terras]</quote></p>
                <p>According to the interviewees, extensive and lively networks, promoted by active
                    linking of people, are an important aspect of <soCalled>social
                        security</soCalled>. Furthermore, they are also crucial for the center’s
                    survival in the academic world, where a great part of funding is competitive
                    project-based external funding. Therefore, the DH centers, for example NULab,
                    have created paths that support the establishment of successful research groups
                    from serendipitous interdisciplinary encounters in DH meetings and networking by
                    providing small <soCalled>seed grants,</soCalled> which, hopefully, lead to
                    receiving external research grants [Interview with Sarah Connell].</p>
                <p>Throughout the interviews, it became evident that the studied DH centers function
                    as umbrellas for loose, rather informal and dynamic networks of scholars,
                    students, librarians, museum experts, activists, and university administrators.
                    When asked about the number of people involved in the activities of the centers,
                    the interviewees found it difficult to define exact numbers, because there is a
                    different number of participants in various events and the form and strength of
                    involvement of the people varies. Many of the interviewees identified layers of
                    involvement of people in the various activities of the DH center. They indicated
                    that some people are strongly involved in a research group, while others may be
                    more actively participating, for example, in a speaker series [Interview with
                    Sarah Connell] [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff] [Interview with Ryan Cordell]
                    [Interview with David Beavan]. In addition, partner organizations — such as
                    libraries, museums, and archives — can be integrally involved in research
                    projects, teaching, or participating in the open events [Interview with Melissa
                    Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. Thus, thriving DH communities tend to be
                    larger than merely the <soCalled>official</soCalled> employed members of the DH
                    center, as they involve people with different layers of memberships and
                    networks. Out of these, the interconnections that can be called
                        <soCalled>micro</soCalled> and <soCalled>macro</soCalled> networks are
                    crucial for DH centers. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Micro- and Macro-networks</head>
                <p>The functions and purposes of transfer of knowledge vary in the different layers
                    of the DH networks. For an individual DH scholar, networks make learning what is
                    being done in other disciplines more reachable: if you know people from
                    different disciplines, it is easier to ask questions on new methods or
                    unfamiliar approaches when you encounter them. Simultaneously at the
                        <soCalled>micro</soCalled> (the collaborative research groups) and the
                        <soCalled>macro</soCalled> (the wider cross-institutional) layers of the DH
                    center the networks have different functions.</p>
                <p>The actual face-to-face everyday interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in DH
                    centers takes place in the core units of research and working groups.
                    Collaboration on a particular theme facilitates the efficient transfer of
                    knowledge among participants. For example, Élika Ortega identified
                    interdisciplinary working groups focusing on concrete common themes as a good
                    way to start interdisciplinary collaboration: <quote rend="block">I don’t think
                        we have discussed [challenges of interdisciplinary collaboration] that much,
                        but we are looking into creating working groups based on salient things that
                        we could identify. Some people were talking that we could start a working
                        group on images, where people working with archival images, or memes, or
                        photography, let say. Then there was this idea to establish a social media
                        working group. So that’s the way that we try to bring our heads together
                        despite our… I don’t want to say differences, but … various profiles.
                        [Interview with Élika Ortega]</quote></p>
                <p>The micro networks of collaborative research groups, which enable recurring
                    meeting and discussion with representatives of other disciplines interested in
                    the same topic form the Communities of Practice (CoP). CoPs are informal groups
                    of people bound together by a common purpose and are considered particularly
                    good for facilitating transfer of tacit knowledge and informal circulation of
                    information <ptr target="#klein2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#fragaszy2013"/>. People who participate in micro-networks learn,
                    in concrete terms, the approaches and understandings of scholars in other
                    disciplines, which is difficult to transfer through other means. </p>
                <p>The interviewees indicated various ways to prevent challenges in transfer of
                    knowledge in the micro-networks. As discussed earlier, the challenges of
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge may include misconceptions, lack of
                    understanding, trust, or even respect arising from the differences in
                    disciplinary cultures. In addition, work in interdisciplinary research teams
                    comes with an integrated form of collaboration that can be new, particularly in
                    terms of humanists who are often trained to work alone [Interview with Mikko
                    Tolonen] <ptr target="#terras2010b" loc="173"/>. In order to overcome the
                    challenges of interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in research teams, the
                    involved scholars must understand and respect the diverging approaches of their
                    collaborators [Interview with Melissa Terras]. Thus, behind the façades of
                    sophisticated methods and shiny visualizations, the very core of a successful DH
                    team is based on the basic human needs of being recognized and respected,
                    besides the desire to expand scholarly knowledge. Furthermore, for facilitating
                    collaboration, the research teams need to have explicit discussions on the joint
                    goals of the project as well as the different ways of crediting in different
                    disciplines in order to ensure that everybody leaves the project with the
                    requisite <soCalled>credits</soCalled> [Interview with Ryan Cordell].</p>
                <p>Other scholars have also indicated that agreeing upon the modes of communication,
                    milestones, expected roles and obligations, means of conduct, and modes of
                    publication at the very beginning of a project can foster open communication and
                    prevent misunderstandings. Teams must devote time for the participants to build
                    trust and get to know each other so that they may work together efficiently. For
                    a DH project to be successful, there must be an emphasis on maintaining
                    communication, good human management, and sufficient face-to-face time <ptr
                        target="#terras2010b" loc="185, 187"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#suominen2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#taskinen2018"/>.</p>
                <p>In addition to interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge in micro-networks,
                    communication across organizational boundaries is crucial for DH centers.
                    Building and maintaining networks beyond institutional boundaries, and even
                    outside the universities or academic circles, was considered important by the
                    directors and managers of established DH centers. Apart from university faculty,
                    a well-working DH network also includes specialists from libraries, archives,
                    museums, public and non-governmental organizations, and businesses [Interview
                    with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen] [Interview with Sarah
                    Connell].</p>
                <p>In order to attract people from other organizations and expand the borders of the
                    DH community, the events are usually open to anyone who is interested in walking
                    in. <quote rend="block">Many of our events are public, we have a lot of
                        researchers from other institutions. Occasionally we get real people from
                        the public, which is lovely when that happens, or sometimes professionals
                        working in industry, and things like that.[Interview with David
                        Beavan]</quote></p>
                <p>DH centers organize formal organizational meetings and industry advisory panels,
                    to which they invite representatives of different organizations; in addition,
                    they maintain the information flow through informal meetings. Melissa Terras
                    describes the breathtakingly wide networks that require active maintaining, but
                    are indispensable for the UCLDH: <quote rend="block">[--] we have an industry
                        advisory panel twice a year, so we have meetings with the British Library,
                        British Museum, National Gallery and range of other people… London
                        Metropolitan Archives and the industry hearing panels, so we have a whole
                        network. In addition to that I spend a lot of time, two or three hours a
                        week, just meeting people and hearing what's going on. There are a lot of
                        people from different institutions that I go out for coffee we just get
                        together and chat about stuff about what's happening so that I can keep
                        together these networks and if something happens. Often grant applications
                        [come at] a very short term and you need to make a project very quickly and
                        you need to know who am I going to call and ask to participate in the
                        project. Networking is very important. I think it takes a certain type of
                        person to do that and it takes a certain type of a drive to do that. It´s
                        important to know what is going on in different places.[Interview with
                        Melissa Terras]</quote></p>
                <p>As discussed earlier, interorganizational networking is crucial for enabling
                    information flow among people and for a prompt launching of cross-organizational
                    project applications. Moreover, keeping oneself updated on the developments
                    outside the university provides an important understanding of the directions of
                    evolution in the realm of digitality in a wider context.</p>
                <p>The physical context of the DH center — the city and the country in which it is
                    located — influences how the center regards external collaboration. The
                    existence of potential collaborative and rival organizations in close proximity
                    provide opportunities for collaboration and a background for comparison and
                    competition [Interview with Élika Ortega] [Interview with Sarah Connell]
                    [Interview with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen].</p>
                <p>Interestingly, the interviews reveal how location in a prominent city with
                    several major universities (such as Boston or London) and in smaller cities with
                    fewer local universities (like Helsinki) make the DH centers mindful about their
                    position. In major cities, the scale of comparison can be within the city, while
                    in smaller locations, the broader international context becomes significant.
                        <quote rend="block">I guess another thing that has helped us here in this
                        particular context is… I mean Boston is a really weird city to do anything
                        academic, because there are, I guess 50 universities in the city. There are
                        the heavy weights, like the MIT and Harvard, who, I mean any normal person
                        is thinking that whatever I might be doing they are doing it better!
                        [laughs] Because it´s MIT and Harvard, right! That is interesting, and
                        obviously they are awesome in everything that they do, they have such long
                        and important institutional histories that they follow that they might not
                        be adopting newer trends as DH as readily. So that is where I think
                        Northeaster, our dean, and the NULab has made a big dent. In the absence of
                        having a big DH center in Harvard or MIT, and there are people doing it, and
                        doing it really well, although not as widespread as we do it here. So we
                        have had this opportunity to be competitive by doing this thing here, and we
                        have got the institutional support. I think that’s a higher level thinking
                        about the strategies.[Interview with Élika Ortega]</quote></p>
                <p><quote rend="block">Everything in Finland is so small that everybody understands
                        that we need to do things together, if we need to accomplish something
                        bigger. This is why we have been able to do bigger projects in Finland. [ —
                        ] This does not happen often abroad. One reason for that can be that there
                        are so strong players who can manage by themselves also. [ — ] This is why
                        we have created our agenda around the idea of a network so that we will
                        collaborate with all major institutions, and not so that the collaboration
                        would happen only within the university. [Interview with Eero
                        Hyvönen]</quote></p>
                <p>In the interview with the Finnish DH center, the collaboration instruments at the
                    level of the European Union — such as CLARIN and DARIAH — were mentioned as
                    important channels of collaboration [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. In the
                    interviews with the US and UK DH centers, international collaboration was not
                    explicitly mentioned, although both institutions accommodate several
                    international projects. It appears that for centers in smaller countries,
                    comparable foreign organizations provide meaningful reference points. </p>
                <p>Further, the means through which DH centers facilitate the transfer of knowledge
                    in micro- and macro-networks are similar — <soCalled>colliding</soCalled> people
                    on a regular basis! However, the purposes of these networks are different. While
                    practical work on a joint theme enables transfer of tacit knowledge, the general
                    inter-organizational meetings also provide — in addition to potential strength
                    in funding applications — an important context for the center. Although the
                    networks are different, they are both crucial for the centers and they support
                    each other. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Organizational Structure – the Glue that Holds Together</head>
                <p>Although the divergent, loose, and dynamic networks of interested individuals are
                    the core of DH centers, the organizational structures of the centers also have
                    an important role in facilitating knowledge transfers. The organizational
                    structures provide sustainability and continuity to the dynamic and
                    ever-changing networks. The employment status of the members of DH centers
                    varies and in addition to the tenure positions, a great number of people work
                    part-time or have short-term contracts. This creates instability and may lead to
                    situations where tacit knowledge, lessons learned, best practices, and even
                    knowledge on the methods or deeper understanding of certain data are lost with
                    dynamic changes <ptr target="#reed2014" loc="¶26"/>. A concrete illustration
                    of this is that at least three of the eight interviewees have changed their
                    positions by the publication of this article. In DH, accumulated knowledge is
                    not stored only in publications but also in the logics of the methods and the
                    datasets employed. Although a lack of continuity and maintenance of knowledge
                    might not be crucial problems for an individual research project, it can create
                    knowledge gaps in the field in the longer run. Creating continuity by supporting
                    documentation, accumulation, and storage of knowledge in one way or another is
                    an increasingly important task of DH centers. </p>
                <p>The interviews did not address continuity directly, but they revealed many ways
                    in which the functions of the staff of DH centers support this. In addition to
                    the support for networking, the interviewees listed providing know-how through
                    networks, the ability to hint what needs to be addressed with specific
                    questions, sharing practical advice on how to begin and run a DH project, and
                    providing support in writing grants as crucial tasks. In many DH centers, the
                    coordinator works as a crucial node for maintaining and supporting, keeping
                    everything on track, and ensuring that communication works [Interview with Sarah
                    Connell] [Interview with David Beavan]. In addition, to the fact that they
                        <quote rend="inline">make the information flow,</quote> they also seem to
                    function as crucial institutional memory of the organizations. As Sarah Connell
                    describes, <quote rend="block">[w]e are especially useful for being someone you
                        can contact with an idea and say “I want to do this and I don’t know how, I
                        don’t even know who else is doing this, I even don’t know if this has been
                        done four hundred times” and we’ll either know — because between the three
                        of us Elizabeth, David and me — we have a fairly diverse expertise, or we’ll
                        know who to ask. So, we are a good place for people who can’t see their next
                        step in digital research. [Interview with Sarah Connell]</quote></p>
                <p>The DH centers develop new resources for research and maintain a knowledge base
                    by listing available tools and informally sharing information and the best
                    practices of the uses of them. For example, the Comhis Collective (and other
                    research groups affiliated with HELDIG) produce new data sets, methods, analysis
                    pipelines, and tools with tutorials and e-learning packages that they are
                    sharing with others in the spirit of open science [Interview with Mikko Tolonen]
                    [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. The codes, manuals, and information on the
                    developed methods, tools, data sets, and pipelines require maintenance. Since
                    research groups are often temporary settings, there is a need for institutional
                    and more stable settings that support external dissemination of the new
                    knowledge and ensure more stable storage of the documentation. </p>
                <p>For a DH center, resources, information on them, where they exist, and how they
                    can be used is fundamental for creating continuity through accumulated
                    knowledge. The resources are often scattered around university campuses, and DH
                    centers also pool resources with different institutions. <quote rend="block">[At
                        the Northeastern University] the infrastructure is scattered around the
                        campus. Some of it is at the neural sciences institute or at the library [ —
                        ] I think that is an advantage. Given all that, I don’t think that in big
                        institutions not all the infrastructure is going to be in one place. The
                        idea of distributed infrastructure is very useful. If you are going to try
                        something like that it would be useful to have an assessment of what kind of
                        infrastructure is [already] available and where [to whom], and who can do
                        what better, or more carefully. Because then the work can be done, and the
                        communications can happen in synchronous email or Slack, or regular meetings
                        monthly or so.[Interview with Élika Ortega]</quote></p>
                <p>In addition to the fact that the tools must exist, there is a need to spread
                    awareness of their availability with the help of lists and meetings. DH centers
                    require organizational structures and administration to keep dynamic networks
                    together, maintain organizational memory, and ensure continuity. Being points
                    that concentrate information on past projects, collected resources, and
                    available tools, the organizational structures of DH centers facilitate and
                    support the transfer of knowledge in the longer term.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Shared Physical Space as a Transmitter</head>
                <p>The interviews with DH professionals reveal that although work in DH is about
                    handling digital data with digital tools, physical proximity is an important
                    factor facilitating the transfer of knowledge also in the DH field [see also
                        <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>]. Sharing the same space is an important
                    transmitter of understanding, and it appears to be a response to the challenges
                    of interdisciplinary transfer of tacit knowledge. If, as suggested by the
                    research literature, the transfer of tacit knowledge requires interaction and
                    proximity of people <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012" loc="28"/>, how do DH centers
                    actually provide it? </p>
                <p>According to the experiences of the interviewees, proximity can be achieved in
                    different ways. Certain DH centers have permanent spaces dedicated for joint
                    meetings and workshops, lab spaces with special equipment, or office space for
                    the staff, while others arrange meetings at a variety of locations with no
                    single permanent physical space. At the time of the interviews, the Boston
                    NULab, NULDSG, and HELDIG had, or were about to have, their own spaces for
                    meetings and individual work. Simultaneously, UCLDH does not have its own
                    physical premises apart from one lab space, but the members of the network meet
                    regularly in various places. Even if DH labs would have physical spaces, often,
                    the majority of the affiliated people do not have offices there, as they might
                    work in their home departments or in libraries. </p>
                <p>Further, numerous interviewees considered the existence of a permanent physical
                    space as a crucial part of the center’s activities, although they described
                    different ways of organizing physical proximity as optimal [Interview with
                    Caroline Klibanoff] [Interview with Mikko Tolonen] [Interview with Sarah
                    Connell] [Interview with Ryan Cordell] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. According
                    to Mikko Tolonen, the possibility to surround oneself only with issues of
                    interest in the digital world can hinder fruitful encounters of unknown ideas,
                    which can happen easier in the analog world’s face-to-face encounters: <quote
                        rend="block">In all kinds of development informal meetings are crucial. It
                        is not a coincident that the concentrations of know-how are often located in
                        a small area. It makes you to exchange ideas. [ — ] When people meet each
                        other, it may lead to something unexpected. In digital world you can
                        demarcate exactly the kind of bubble you want to, but [physically] you are
                        forced to meet [all kinds of] people when you are getting yourself a coffee.
                        [ — ] It is easy to establish different kinds of centers to the Internet.
                        You can just make a website and call it something, but it does not mean that
                        things will actually happen there. If you have some kind of physical
                        presence, it forces things to start happening! [Interview with Mikko
                        Tolonen]</quote></p>
                <p>Some interviewees emphasized the importance of joint space where people can enter
                    easily for facilitating informal exchange of ideas, thereby increasing
                    (interdisciplinary) communication. Being in the same room makes one actually
                    understand what is going on in there [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff].
                    Certain interviewees considered informal collective work to be the preferable
                    use of the joint DH space: <quote rend="block">The importance of people being
                        proximate to each other, that’s something that I think should be taken quite
                        seriously. [ — ] So, thinking about how we want things to work in the NULab,
                        we do want this space to be one for informal collective work. Where I’m
                        doing something on my computer and you are doing something on your computer
                        and then lean over, talk, talk, talk, go back to your own separate thing. We
                        will try to see if that happens organically, and if it doesn’t we are going
                        to make it happen [ — ] by scheduling some structured work time. [ — ] I
                        think that we are really still trying to figure out what’s the best way that
                        we can have this space help to make the community to take shape.[Interview
                        with Sarah Connell]</quote></p>
                <p>In addition to joint collaborative working spaces, the interviewees mentioned the
                    benefits of having (separate) offices located in close proximity to each other.
                    When asked about the benefits of belonging to the DH center, the interviewees
                    indicated learning from scholars in other disciplines by actively working with
                    them. One of the factors that they believed to promote such learning was the
                    location of office spaces in close proximity, which led to everyday
                    conversations and experimenting with new methods. For example, being located in
                    the same corridor encourages people to have quick conversations, which can be
                    more effective from the viewpoint of transfer of knowledge than long but rare
                    meetings [Interview with Ryan Cordell]. As an effect of proximity, <quote
                        rend="inline">things start happening.</quote> By establishing everyday micro
                    contacts and sharing small things, it is easier to understand the other person:
                        <quote rend="block">I think proximity is important if you want to actually
                        work together. When we were separated, we got together and had our meeting,
                        and talked that we should work on this or that, and you go your separate
                        ways and you don´t see them again until the next meeting, and things just
                        don´t really happen. And there is awful lot of value, I think, in being in
                        proximity, you are by, you meet more often and start talking, and start
                        exchanging ideas. Even just with Ben over there [in the next office] we chat
                        a lot, get into debates, and the whole thing. I just think it´s useful,
                        there are things that can be done virtually, and things that just can´t.
                        [Interview with Ryan Cordell]</quote></p>
                <p>According to Eero Hyvönen, it is essential for a DH center to have physical
                    premises; at the time of the interview, HELDIG was on the verge of acquiring a
                    permanent space, with seminar rooms, collaborative spaces, and offices for the
                    core staff. However, not all the staff was to have offices there, and Hyvönen
                    stated that people in other departments could be crucial for spreading knowledge
                    of DH research [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. </p>
                <p>Although a few interviewees emphasized the importance of physical proximity, not
                    all DH centers have set spaces or even feel that they would need such a space.
                    Having a <quote rend="inline">place of one’s own</quote> can be useful, but it
                    is not critical if the center staff arranges alternative meeting spaces. The
                    UCLDH is predominantly a virtual center that does not have a set space. The
                    scholars have their individual offices in different parts of the university,
                    where they meet with their collaborators. The center organizes a host of events,
                    where people meet face-to-face, but they do not need a set <soCalled>DH
                        space</soCalled> for that [Interview with Melissa Terras]. Being located in
                    central London makes availability of physical space scarce. In addition, the
                    interviewees felt that having no physical space makes the organization nimbler,
                    more flexible, and interdisciplinary; this is because physical space also
                    implies additional responsibility, and more complex financial structures.
                    Therefore, there is no need for a physical space when a network already exists
                    and functions [Interview with David Beavan].</p>
                <p>At the level of research teams, physical proximity is not always possible. For
                    example, although the Comhis Collective is located in Helsinki, not all its team
                    members are present in the same premises or even in the same country. For them,
                    Slack and other digital collaboration tools enable the flow of information among
                    all team members. However, if there is a reliance solely on digital
                    collaboration tools, there is a threat that the persons who are not physically
                    present will not be aware of the latest developments. Therefore, in order to
                    make collaboration smooth, all the team members periodically get together in the
                    same space for days of intensive collaboration [Interview with Mikko Tolonen].
                    For teams working remotely, in-person meetings can be important platforms for
                    reviewing what has been done, planning future activities, and also for resolving
                    problematic questions that are difficult to solve through conference calls or
                    emails <ptr target="#reed2014" loc="¶35"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>. Physical meetings are often more necessary at the
                    beginning of a project, so that the people get used to each other. After getting
                    to know each other by being present in the same room, it is easier for the
                    scholars to engage in more informal communication, even online <ptr
                        target="#podesta2013" loc="44"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Digital Transfers of Knowledge Within and Outside the Community</head>
                <p>In addition to physical proximity, digital communication tools are crucial for
                    transfer of knowledge in DH centers. The different layers of networks and the
                    level of integration of people at the DH centers are reflected in the uses of
                    divergent communication channels, varying between openly accessible to anyone
                    interested and closed usage of specific groups. The channels utilized — such as
                    email lists, Facebook, Twitter, Slack, Google Drive, Trello, and others — all
                    facilitate different kinds of communication and transfer of knowledge. Each
                    channel has different functions and follower potential, which influences the
                    kind of communication which they can be used for [Interview with Sarah Connell]. </p>
                <p>In addition to the technical features directing the usage of a digital
                    communication tool, each channel has a distinctive culture of communication that
                    one has to know to be able to communicate effectively. Certain channels
                    facilitate low-barrier informal communication more easily, which includes asking
                        <soCalled>stupid</soCalled> questions, while others contain more formal and
                    public communication. For example, the interviewees stated that a Slack channel
                    is a good means for low-barrier communication and asking questions, while a
                    list-serv — used by the same community — appears more suitable for disseminating
                    information, but nobody uses it for asking questions. Moreover, Slack’s
                    chat-like functions serve as a low-barrier connector [Interview with Caroline
                    Klibanoff] [see also <ptr target="#evalyn2020"/>]. In Slack, you can also see
                    all the people who are involved in the channel, while it is more difficult to
                    identify the recipients of an email sent to a list-serv. </p>
                <p>For internal sharing of information, discussions, and keeping things on track,
                    numerous DH research projects — the micro-networks of DH centers — use
                    internet-based communication tools like Slack, digital to-do lists like Trello,
                    and shareable Google documents [Interview with Mikko Tolonen] [Interview with
                    Sarah Connell] [Interview with Ryan Cordell]. <quote rend="block">Yes, there is
                        a lot of Slack! I think most of the individual projects have their own Slack
                        [channel]. [ — ] Different projects figure out their own communication
                        channels, but I think a lot of them are on Slack. [Interview with Ryan
                        Cordell]</quote></p>
                <p>Transfer of tacit, non-verbalized knowledge requires informal communication. It
                    is easier to share tacit knowledge when people are in the same location, but it
                    appears that collaborating teams that already know each other can maintain
                    sharing of tacit knowledge and emotional ties through digital communication
                    tools as well <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012"/>. Working together and knowing
                    each other for a longer period can give birth to a shared mini culture, where
                    the members of the group share the internal meanings of emojis or words <ptr
                        target="#evalyn2020"/>. For example, Mikko Tolonen referred to the Comhis
                    collective’s Slack humor as an important component of collaboration [Interview
                    with Mikko Tolonen]. Tacit knowledge is often learned in shared collaborative
                    experiences, and learning tacit knowledge requires participation and
                        <soCalled>doing</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012"/>. Moreover, transfer of tacit knowledge may be
                    possible if the tool itself and its code of conduct are familiar to users. In DH
                    research, explicit knowledge can be found in articles and on the Internet, but
                    tacit knowledge is received in close connection and collaboration with
                    colleagues. </p>
                <p>In practice, digital and physical presence often overlap and, occasionally,
                    transfer of knowledge can take place synchronously via physical proximity as
                    well as a variety of digital channels such as Slack, Google Drive, and Twitter.
                        <quote rend="block">Often, even if we are physically present, we are
                        simultaneously digitally present. Even if we are in the same room, the
                        communication may happen in one of the chat options, Skype, or elsewhere.
                        [Interview with Mikko Tolonen]</quote></p>
                <p>Both digital and physical presence have different strengths and weaknesses in
                    transfer of knowledge. Physical proximity eases the process of getting to know
                    people and the transfer of tacit knowledge, and constant proximity makes things
                    happen faster and collaboration more efficient. Simultaneously, digital
                    communication tools make communication possible even over distances: a team
                    member can participate in a weekly meeting through Skype while being located in
                    a different country. In addition, it can also be easier to go back to earlier
                    conversations in a chat — although not too old ones, since they may be already
                    difficult to find in Slack for example —, and new people can join in a
                    conversation that was initiated a month earlier.</p>
                <p>The online communication within DH centers and macro-networks is vital for DH
                    centers. The centers studied here take internet and social media communication
                    very seriously [Interview with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]
                        <ptr target="#terras2012"/>. <quote rend="block">We are digital first, which
                        means that we don´t really do off-line communication, we don´t do much print
                        communication. [ — ] But we want to have a very good digital presence, which
                        we take very seriously. We have a website, and Facebook and Twitter. [ — ]
                        We like to be creative in our design, within the limits of the content
                        management system we have to work with. We have a very good designer, who is
                        part of the team, who does all the work on the website. We keep our Twitter
                        feed up-to date, we keep our Facebook up-to date with all the activities
                        that we are doing. I think we have around 5 000 followers on Twitter. It´s
                        not a small thing. That means that with the digital presence, if something
                        happens [that we want to inform people of], with all the members of the
                        team, we can distribute a message to the potential audience of 30 000 people
                        within a second. We take that seriously. Any digital research facility
                        should take digital presence seriously. [Interview with Melissa
                        Terras]</quote></p>
                <p>Websites and social media are important tools for spreading information to the
                    public regarding the activities of a DH center. Thus, internet presence is
                    crucial for maintaining the public image of a center and providing members of a
                    community with a web identity [Interview with Eero Hyvönen] spreading
                    information regarding what DH is and what its impact is has become crucial for
                    establishing the field <ptr target="#galinarussell2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Websites and social media create channels for reaching out to new people
                    interested in DH and in potentially joining the community. In a discussion at
                    the NULDSG weekly meeting, numerous participants — in particular the younger
                    ones — stated that social media provided them with the first encounter with DH
                    and the people engaging with it. Having some knowledge of a DH center and its
                    people <soCalled>digitally</soCalled> before actually coming to the meetings was
                    a crucial first step for them. Without this connection, it would have been too
                    big a step to reach out and contact a DH center and its people, or move from
                    other parts of the country to Boston to become involved in DH. </p>
                <p>In addition to attracting new people, well-designed and active digital presence
                    is also of significance for obtaining funding and to be recognized by the larger
                    society. It is a means to determine how the funding has been used, what kinds of
                    activities the center holds, and if granted external funding, how
                        <soCalled>well</soCalled> it may potentially be used. Lack of an active
                    digital presence gives an impression of an outdated or inactive center. <quote
                        rend="block">We are aware of the fact that blog posts as a publication genre
                        can sometimes be incredibly helpful. I’ve assigned about fifteen blog posts
                        as I’m teaching this fall because it’s the best, clearest and shortest way
                        to introduce an important and complicated topic. But sometimes a blog post
                        is just the obligatory one that takes way longer to write than it should,
                        and doesn’t end up having a lot of readership and doesn’t really benefit the
                        person who wrote it. So we try to think whether the blog post is the best
                        format to share a piece of information. We tend to use our blog posts partly
                        to share research and also because we do have a lot of events, and we often
                        get the <quote rend="inline">I wish I could go, but…</quote>. We Tweet the
                        blogpost wrap ups, if you couldn’t go at all, you can at least see the
                        links, and get the sense what the talk was about.[Interview with Sarah
                        Connell]</quote></p>
                <p>However, maintaining active digital presence requires effort. Several people are
                    needed to support the distribution of knowledge from the DH center to the
                    outside world by maintaining a website and social media channels [Interview with
                    Sarah Connell] [Interview with Élika Ortega] [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff]
                    [Interview with Melissa Terras] [Interview with Eero Hyvönen]. For example, the
                    NULab travel funds require reporting on the conference or the event visited
                    through a blog post, which adds a variety of content to the site [Interview with
                    Ryan Cordell]. It is also preferable to share the social media post
                    responsibility to people who are more naturally inclined toward such
                    information, so that an active Twitter user posts on Twitter [Interview with
                    Sarah Connell], while a constant Facebook hang-around posts on Facebook. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Boundaries for Knowledge Transfer</head>
                <p>In addition to the multilayered knowledge transfers powered by interconnected
                    face-to-face and online networks, communication within and outside DH centers
                    also has restrictions. When defining and creating a space (of communication), we
                    also set boundaries to it. The barriers to transfer of knowledge in DH centers
                    are physical, digital, language-related, structural, social, and cultural. </p>
                <p>Constructing a physical space invites certain participants but eliminates others.
                    David Beavan indicated, when discussing the absence of physical premises of
                    UCLDH, that while a physical space could increase communication among the core
                    members having offices in the space, it could potentially also restrict other
                    people’s access and cut them out [Interview with David Beavan]. Although, in
                    principle being open to the outside world, in practice access to the spaces of
                    the DH centers studied here is not easy for an outsider: for example, to enter
                    the space, an individual may need an access pass to the library, a key code, or
                    merely know how to navigate through the labyrinth of a university campus. It is
                    very unlikely that a person would enter these DH spaces accidentally. One of the
                    reasons for the practical restrictions is that open premises often demand that
                    someone is present to oversee that the space, which is often equipped with the
                    latest technology, is used for its intended purpose by the destined people.</p>
                <p>Similarly, while digital communication tools facilitate interaction, they are not
                    factually open to everyone. Certain channels, particularly those used by defined
                    groups, allow entrance only by invitation. Communication in a small, non-public
                    group is often easier and less formal and potentially makes exchange of ideas
                    smoother [Interview with Caroline Klibanoff]. Thus, absolute openness of all
                    physical premises and digital tools would eliminate the boundaries that make the
                    DH center identifiable and water down the safer closed spaces of communication. </p>
                <p>Although boundaries are necessary, it is important to discuss who and what kind
                    of knowledge we welcome. Is there knowledge that is left out from the
                    information flows? In recent years, the DH field has been discussing the need
                    for a variety of approaches and the threat of
                        <soCalled>retro-humanism</soCalled> focusing only on the canonical
                    representation of the humanities <ptr target="#risam2015"/>
                	<ptr target="#martinandrunyon2016" loc="20–21"/>. There is also strong advocacy
                    of the use of a variety of languages, exemplified by the use of multiple
                    languages at the DH2018 conference in Mexico City. </p>
                <p>Language creates bubbles of DH communities (this article is aimed at the English
                    language bubble) and determines hierarchies based on the competence and fluency
                    of the speaker/writer. Participation in international (English language)
                    communication demands special attention from the DH centers in a
                    non-English-speaking country. In order to enable smooth international
                    collaboration, the content on the HELDIG websites was written in English right
                    from the outset, and the expansion of the staff by including international
                    recruits pushed the Comhis Collective to change their operational language to
                    English. <quote rend="block">Until recently everybody in the Collective were
                        Finnish-speakers, but now almost all the new members come from elsewhere,
                        and we had to change our operating language and Slack humor [into
                        English].[laughs] [Interview with Mikko Tolonen]</quote></p>
                <p>In Finland, where academia is practically tri-lingual — using Finnish, Swedish,
                    and English — a change in the operating language is not a big problem. However,
                    it sets additional linguistic requirements for individual researchers who are
                    willing to enter the international scholarly streams of transfer of
                    knowledge.</p>
                <p>Alongside linguistic barriers, the underlying structures and logic of scholarly
                    crediting and financing influence the ways in which research is conducted, even
                    if, in general, the motivation of DH scholars to participate in
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge is high. The widely discussed issues of
                    crediting for open-access publishing, opening up of the used code or data, joint
                    publications, or potential failures of tests (that are an integral part of
                    developing something new) are issues that can either promote or hinder
                    interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge and the ultimate emergence of new
                    knowledge. </p>
                <p>Therefore, social and cultural boundaries and the questions of who is invited to
                    a research group, whose knowledge is valued as important, or whose work we know
                    of are not issues that are solely related to DH; they are also related to the
                    larger academia and societies in general <ptr target="#griffin2018"
                    	loc="¶11–12"/>
                    <ptr target="#ostling2018"/>. One can also ask to what degree are scholars
                    associated with the more well-renowned centers more likely to have their
                    knowledge more valued <emph>because</emph> of their association? The
                    interviewees, being integral participants in the DH field, did not extensively
                    discuss the issues of social and cultural boundaries. At the core, it is often
                    difficult to see the challenges in the margins; therefore, this study cannot
                    comprehensively cover this issue. However, a few reflections from DH
                    professionals may contribute important perspectives to the discussion. The
                    interviewees indicated that, to a great extent, DH is a question of
                    self-identification and a sense of belonging: <quote rend="block">DH is at this
                        point still a self-reported, or self-adopted title. [ — ] It is a conceptual
                        magnet. Once you identify yourself as a digital humanist, then you start
                        participating to the community. [Interview with Élika Ortega]</quote></p>
                <p>Because DH is about self-identification, it would be important to create an
                    atmosphere of openness that facilitates the inclusion of a variety of people
                    into the field. This would ensure that the interdisciplinary processes of
                    transfer of knowledge have sufficient variety to draw on. In other words, if
                    knowledge is inseparable from the communities that create it, use it, and
                    transform it <ptr target="#krishnaveni2012" loc="37"/>, we must ensure that the
                    community is not too narrow. Further, if inclusion is the first step to
                    accessing equality, but not a sufficient one <ptr target="#martinandrunyon2016"
                        loc="37"/>, further studies would be required on the effects of
                    infrastructures, practices, the general logic underlying information flow in DH,
                    and the varied nature of the DH community.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>The interdisciplinary character of DH amplifies the social aspects of its
                    knowledge construction; therefore, it is crucial to study the means through
                    which transfer of knowledge is facilitated in this field. This article suggests
                    that transfer of knowledge requires people with varied knowledge, networks,
                    physical and virtual spaces facilitating communication, motivation, and
                    practices that support it. The interviews reveal that the studied DH centers,
                    the focal points of the transfer of knowledge of the field, combine the elements
                    of the transfer of knowledge in a variety of ways and, therefore, function as
                    engines of diverse information flows. DH centers facilitate interdisciplinary
                    and inter-organizational matchmaking and exchange of ideas by maintaining a
                    variety of networks and institutional memory as well as by providing physical
                    and digital spaces for exchange of explicit and tacit knowledge. Further, the
                    interviews indicate that in order to form a dynamic unit, in addition to the
                    top-down strategy-driven infrastructures, DH centers must nurture free-floating
                    networks of people [see also <ptr target="#fickers2020"/>]. Maintaining respect
                    for other perspectives and the willingness to learn and share new approaches is
                    crucial for the field. The questions of exclusion and inclusion, who is
                    recognized as a recognizable DH scholar, and what kind of information we value
                    are crucial for defining the kind of scholarship and research outcomes we wish
                    to achieve in the field in the future. The organizations running DH centers
                    should pay attention to these features, and adjust them to the specifics of
                    their cultural, geographical, academic and organizational environment. And, most
                    importantly, for each individual DH practitioner it is essential to consider how
                    our own practices affect the inclusiveness of transfer of knowledge in the
                    DH.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Interviews</head>
                <p>[Interview with David Beavan] Associate Director for Research for University
                    College London (UCL) Centre for Digital Humanities (UCLDH) and Research Manager
                    (Arts and Humanities), by Mila Oiva, November 20, 2017, Skype.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Sarah Connell] Assistant Director of the Women Writers Project
                    (Digital Scholarship Group, Northeastern University Library) and the NULab for
                    Texts, Maps, and Networks by Mila Oiva October 17, 2017, Boston Mass., USA.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Ryan Cordell], Assistant Professor and Core Faculty member of
                    NULab at the Northeastern University, by Mila Oiva, October 16, 2017, Boston
                    Mass., USA.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Eero Hyvönen] Director of the Helsinki Center of Digital
                    Humanities HELDIG, by Mila Oiva September 20, 2017, Otaniemi, Espoo, Finland.
                    Translations from Finnish to English by Mila Oiva.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Caroline Klibanoff] Coordinator at the Northeastern University
                    Library Digital Scholarship Group (NULDSG), by Mila Oiva, October 11, 2017,
                    Boston Mass., USA.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Élika Ortega] Assistant Professor at the Department of Cultures,
                    Societies, and Global Studies and Core Faculty at the NULab for Texts, Maps and
                    Networks at Northeastern University, by Mila Oiva, October 17, 2017, Boston
                    Mass., USA.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Melissa Terras], Director of the University College London
                    Digital Humanities Center (UCLDH), by Mila Oiva, August 29, 2017, Skype.</p>
                <p>[Interview with Mikko Tolonen] Professor of Digital Humanities and Leader of the
                    Comhis Collective at HELDIG, University of Helsinki, by Mila Oiva, August 22,
                    2017, Helsinki, Finland. Translations from Finnish to English by Mila Oiva.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="braun2006" label="Braun and Clarke 2006">Braun, V. and Clarke, V.
                        <title rend="quotes">Using thematic analysis in psychology.</title> in
                        <title rend="italic">Qualitative Research in Psychology</title>, 3 (2)
                    (2006): 77-101.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deegan2011" label="Deegan and McCarty 2011">Deegan, M. and W. McCarty.
                        <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Ashgate, Farnham (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="evalyn2020" label="Evalyn et al 2020">Evalyn, L., C. Henderson, J.
                    King, J. Lockhart, L. Mitchell and S. Conklin Akbari. <title rend="quotes">One
                        Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective
                        Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment.</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000474/000474.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000474/000474.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fickers2020" label="Fickers and Heijden 2020">A. Fickers and T. van
                    der Heijden. <title rend="quotes">Inside the Trading Zone. Thinkering in a
                        Digital History Lab</title> in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000472/000472.html">
                        http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000472/000472.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fragaszy2013" label="Fragaszy Troyano and Rhody 2013">Fragaszy
                    Troyano, J. and L. M. Rhody. <title rend="quotes">Expanding Communities of
                        Practice. Introduction to the Issue.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> [Online], October 23,
                    (2013). Available from: <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-2/expanding-communities-of-practice/"
                        >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-2/expanding-communities-of-practice/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fullwood2013" label="Fullwood et al 2013">Fullwood, R., J. Rowley and
                    R. Delbridge. <title rend="quotes">Knowledge Sharing amongst Academics in UK
                        Universities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Knowledge Management</title> [Online], 17(1)
                    February 15, (2013): 123–-136. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1108/13673271311300831"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1108/13673271311300831</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galinarussell2015" label="Galina Russell 2015"> Galina Russell, I..
                        <title rend="quotes">Creating a Regional DH Community — A Case Study of the
                        RedHD.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> [Online], 9(3) (2015).
                    Available from:<ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/3/000221/000221.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/3/000221/000221.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="griffin2018" label="Griffin and Hayler 2018">Griffin, G., and M. S.
                    Hayler. <title rend="quotes">Collaboration in Digital Humanities Research –
                        Persisting Silences.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12(1) (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huutoniemi2010" label="Huutoniemi et al 2010">Huutoniemi, K., J. T.
                    Klein, H. Bruun and J. Hukkinen. <title rend="quotes">Analyzing
                        Interdisciplinarity: Typology and Indicators.</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Research Policy</title> [Online], 39(1) February 1, (2010):
                    79–88. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.respol.2009.09.011"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.respol.2009.09.011</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="keener2015" label="Keener 2015">Keener, A. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Arrival Fallacy: Collaborative Research Relationships in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> [Online], 2 (2015). Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000213/000213.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000213/000213.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2010" label="Kirschenbaum 2010">Kirschenbaum, M.G.. <title
                        rend="quotes">What Is Digital Humanities and What’s It Doing in English
                        Departments?</title> in <title rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</title>, no. 150
                    (2010): 1–7.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2014" label="Klein 2014">Klein, J. T. <title rend="italic"
                        >Interdisciplining Digital Humanities: Boundary Work In An Emerging
                        Field</title>, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor MI (2014). <ref
                        target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.12869322.0001.001"
                        >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.12869322.0001.001</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="krishnaveni2012" label="Krishnaveni and Sujatha 2012">Krishnaveni, R.,
                    and R. Sujatha. <title rend="quotes">Communities of Practice: An influencing
                        factor for effective knowledge transfer in organizations.</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">IUP Journal of Knowledge Management</title> 10(1), (2012):
                    26-40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="martinandrunyon2016" label="Martin and Runyon 2016">Martin, J. D. III,
                    and C. Runyon. <title rend="quotes">Digital humanities, digital hegemony:
                        Exploring funding practices and unequal access in the digital
                        humanities.</title> in <title rend="italic">SIGCAS Comput. Soc.</title>
                    [Online], 46(1) (2016):, 20-26. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2908216.2908219"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/2908216.2908219</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="matres2018" label="Matres, Oiva and Tolonen 2018">Matres, I., M. Oiva
                    and M. Tolonen. <title rend="quotes">In Between Research Cultures — The State of
                        Digital Humanities in Finland</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Informaatiotutkimus</title> 37, no 2 (June 13, 2018). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.23978/inf.71160"
                        >https://doi.org/10.23978/inf.71160</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nygren2014" label="Nygren, Foka, and Buckland 2014">Nygren, T., A.
                    Foka, and P. Buckland. <title rend="quotes">The status quo of digital humanities
                        in Sweden: Past, present and future of digital history.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">H-Soz-Kult. Kommunikation und Fachinformation für die
                        Geschichtswissenschaften</title> [Online], October 23, (2014). Available
                    from: <ref target="http://www.hsozkult.de/debate/id/diskussionen-2402"
                        >http://www.hsozkult.de/debate/id/diskussionen-2402</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oivaandpawlickadeger2020" label="Oiva and Pawlicka-Deger 2020">Oiva,
                    M. and U. Pawlicka-Deger. <title rend="quotes">Lab and Slack. Situated Research
                        Practices in Digital Humanities — Introduction to the DHQ Special
                        Issue.</title> in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                    [this issue].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olson2014" label="Olson and Olson 2014">Olson, J. S., and G. M. Olson.
                        <title rend="italic">Working Together Apart: Collaboration over the
                        Internet.</title> Synthesis Digital Library of Engineering and Computer
                    Science. Morgan and Claypool, (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="orlikowski2002" label="Orlikowski 2002">Orlikowski, W. J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Knowing in Practice: Enacting a Collective Capability in
                        Distributed Organizing</title>. in <title rend="italic">Organization
                        Science</title> [Online], 13(3) June 1, (2002):, 249-273. Available from:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1287/orsc.13.3.249.2776"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1287/orsc.13.3.249.2776</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2020" label="Phillips et al 2020">N. M. Phillips, A. Babbitt,
                    S. Cho, J. Kane, C. Mejeur, and C. Pearson <title rend="quotes">Creating spaces
                        for interdisciplinary research across literature, neuroscience, and DH. A
                        case study of the Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab
                        (DHLC).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> [this issue].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="podesta2013" label="Podestá et al 2013">Podestá, G. P., C. E.
                    Natenzon, C. Hidalgo, and F. Ruiz Toranzo. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Interdisciplinary production of knowledge with participation of
                        stakeholders: A case study of a collaborative project on climate
                        variability, human decisions and agricultural ecosystems in the Argentine
                        Pampas.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Environmental Science and Policy, Rethinking Integrated
                        Assessments and Management Projects in the Americas</title> [Online], 26
                    February 1, (2013): 40-48. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2012.07.008"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2012.07.008</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reed2014" label="Reed 2014">Reed, A. <title rend="quotes">Managing an
                        established digital humanities project: Principles and practices from the
                        twentieth year of the William Blake Archive.</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> [Online], 8(1) (2014). Available from:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000174/000174.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000174/000174.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                        the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">English Faculty Publications: Salem State University</title>,
                    (2015). <ref target="http://digitalcommons.salemstate.edu/english_facpub/4"
                        >http://digitalcommons.salemstate.edu/english_facpub/4</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="romerolankao2013" label="Romero-Lankao et al 2013">Romero-Lankao, P.,
                    M. Borbor-Cordova, R. Abrutsky, G. Günther, E. Behrentz, and L. Dawidowsky.
                        <title rend="quotes">ADAPTE: A tale of diverse teams coming together to do
                        issue-driven interdisciplinary research.</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Environmental Science and Policy, Rethinking Integrated Assessments and
                        Management Projects in the Americas</title> [Online], 26 February 1, (2013):
                    29-39. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2011.12.003"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2011.12.003</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siedlokandhibbert2014" label="Siedlok and Hibbert 2014">Siedlok, F.
                    and P. Hibbert. <title rend="quotes">The organization of interdisciplinary
                        research: Modes, drivers and barriers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Management Reviews</title>
                    [Online], 16(2), (2014): 194-210. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1111/ijmr.12016"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1111/ijmr.12016</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2009" label="Siemens 2009">Siemens, L.. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><q>It’s a Team If You Use <quote rend="inline">Reply All</quote></q>:
                        An exploration of research teams in digital humanities environments</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> [Online],
                    24(2), (2009): 225-233. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp009"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp009</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2011" label="Siemens 2011">Siemens, L.. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Balance between On-Line and In-Person Interactions: Methods for the
                        Development of Digital Humanities Collaboration.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le Champ Numérique</title> 2, no. 1 (May
                    17, 2011). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.259"
                        >https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.259</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemensetal2011" label="Siemens et al 2011">Siemens, L., R.
                    Cunningham, W. Duff and C. Warwick. <title rend="quotes">A Tale of Two Cities:
                        Implications of the Similarities and Differences in Collaborative Approaches
                        within the Digital Libraries and Digital Humanities Communities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 26, no. 3
                    (September 1, 2011): 335–48. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr028"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr028</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="suominen2018" label="Suominen 2018">Suominen, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >History of Digital Cultures</title>. Presentation at <title rend="italic"
                        >the Digital History Method Roadshow</title>, University of Turku, Finland,
                    February 5, (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2010" label="Svensson 2010">Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The landscape of digital humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> [Online], 4(1) (2010).
                    Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tabak2017" label="Tabak 2017">[Tabak 2017] Tabak, E. <title
                        rend="quotes">A hybrid model for managing DH Projects.</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> [Online], 11(1) (2017).
                    Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000284/000284.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000284/000284.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taskinen2018" label="Taskinen, Kivimäki and Männistö 2018">Taskinen,
                    I., V. Kivimäki and A. Männistö. <title rend="quotes">Big data and history of
                        war experience</title>. Presentation at the Digital History Method Roadshow,
                    University of Tampere, Finland, February 7, (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2010a" label="Terras 2010a">Terras, Melissa. <title
                        rend="quotes">Present, Not Voting: Digital Humanities in the Panopticon:
                        Closing Plenary Speech, Digital Humanities 2010.</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 26, no. 3 (September
                    1, 2011): 257–69. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr016"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr016</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2010b" label="Terras 2010b">Terras, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        digital classicist: Disciplinary focus and interdisciplinary vision.</title>
                    In <title rend="italic">Digital Research in the Study of Classical
                        Antiquity</title>, edited by G. Bodard and S. Mahony. Ashgate, Farnham
                    (2010): pp. 171-189.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2012" label="Terras 2012">Terras, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        impact of social media on the dissemination of research: Results of an
                        Experiment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> [Online], October 2,
                    (2012). Available from: <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-3/the-impact-of-social-media-on-the-dissemination-of-research-by-melissa-terras/"
                        >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-3/the-impact-of-social-media-on-the-dissemination-of-research-by-melissa-terras/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vangorpandbron2019" label="Van Gorp and Bron 2019">Van Gorp, Jasmijn,
                    and Marc Bron. <title rend="quotes">Building Bridges: Collaboration between
                        Computer Sciences and Media Studies in a Television Archive Project.</title>
                    in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 013, no. 3 (October
                    14, 2019). Available from: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/3/000375/000375.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/3/000375/000375.html</ref> .</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whatisdigitalhumanities" label="What is digital humanities">What is
                    Digital Humanities web page [Online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://whatisdigitalhumanities.com/"
                        >https://whatisdigitalhumanities.com/</ref> (last visited January 31,
                    2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zorich2012" label="Zorich 2012">Zorich, D. M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Transitioning to a digital world: Art history, its research centers, and
                        digital scholarship.</title> in <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title> [Online], June 26, (2012). Available from: <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-2/transitioning-to-a-digital-world-by-diane-zorich/"
                        >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-2/transitioning-to-a-digital-world-by-diane-zorich/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ostling2018" label="Östling et al 2018">Östling, J., D. Larsson
                    Heidenblad, E. Sandmo, A. Nilsson Hammar, and K.H. Nordberg. <title
                        rend="quotes">The History of Knowledge and Circulation of Knowledge. An
                        Introduction.</title> In <title rend="italic">Circulation of Knowledge:
                        Explorations in the History of Knowledge</title>, edited by J. Östling, E.
                    Sandmo, D. Larsson Heidenblad, A. Nilsson Hammar, and K. H. Nordberg, 9–33.
                    Lund: Nordic Academic Press, 2018.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
