<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Dangers
					of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title>
				
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					
					<dhq:author_name>Sara <dhq:family>Diamond</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-8346-2811</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>OCAD University Faculty of Arts &amp; Science</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>sdiamond@ocadu.ca</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Sara Diamond (she/her/they) is an OCAD University Research Chair and Professor and leads its Visual Analytics Lab. She served as president of OCAD U (2005 – 2015) leading OCAD U to full university status, building its capabilities in art, design and technology and collaborating with Indigenous colleagues to prioritize Indigenous knowledge and culture and efforts in decolonization. In 1996 she founded and led the Banff New Media Institute at The Banff Centre. She co-authored <title rend="italic">Euphoria &amp; Dystopia: the Banff New Media Dialogues</title>, 2012 with Sara Cook and was Editor-in-Chief of <ref target="http://www.horizonzero.ca">http://www.horizonzero.ca</ref>, an online dialogue, exhibition, and critical environment dedicated to Canadian new media (2001-2004). Diamond’s funded and published research spans design, visualization, media art and social history, public policy in arts and communication and computer science.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000670</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					>017<!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue">1<!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date when="2023-05-26">26 May 2023</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Article written by Sara Diamond for the special issue on Project Resiliency. The papers in this special issue were first presented at a symposium organized by the Endings Project team at the University of Victoria.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					
					<list type="simple">
						<item>archives</item>
						<item>art</item>
						<item>cultural heritage institutions</item>
						<item>data curation</item>
						<item>audiovisual media</item>
						<item>indigeneity</item>
						<item>media history</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item>project resiliency</item>
						<item>Banff New Media Institute</item>
						<item>Daniel Langlois Foundation</item>
						<item>Crista Dahl Library and Archive</item>
						<item>Sara Diamond Fonds</item>
						</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple"/>
						</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000670/000670.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				
				<p>
					This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds at VIVO Media Art Centre's Crista Dahl Library and Archive – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.[1] In the instances of the BNMI and DLF, disappearance has meant the removal from public access. Disappearance has a second meaning in the context of digital media whether online or platform (such as CDs, DVDs)
				</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				
				<p>Disappearing archives</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head></head>
			<p>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute
				(BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product
				of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media
				context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and
				human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third
				personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond
				Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives;
				administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and
				Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership
				strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the
				BNMI and DLF archives.<note> The BNMI archive does not contain complex
					interactive new media art works. The Langlois Collection includes
					documentation of video, web, CD, and interactive works but few are online.
					My collection includes video and web works. New Media archiving is
					demanding because of changing platforms - many works have found a home with
					the Archives of Digital Art (ADA) and Rhizome, discussed later in this
					essay.</note> In the instances of the BNMI and DLF, disappearance has meant
				the removal from public access. Disappearance has a second meaning in the
				context of digital media whether online or platform (such as CDs, DVDs). As
				Grau, Hoth, and Wandl-Vogt (<ref target="#grau">2019</ref>) stress: <quote rend="inline">Due to lack of institutional
				support and rapid changes in storage and presentation media, works that
				originated ten years ago can no longer be recovered technically for exhibition
				or preservation purposes</quote> <ptr target="#grau2019" loc="20"/>. Giselle Beiguelman further asks, “How to deal in the
				field of preservation and conservation with files that disappear, works that
				stop functioning, services that vanish from one day to the next <ptr target="#beiguelman2019" loc="118"/>?
				Media art works and Internet art rely on connections to databases, links, and
				third-party servers and services. Moreover, many works are interactive and
				contributor-driven so there is no easy beginning and end and often exist in many
				versions. Both interpretations of disappearance address the challenge that, as
				Sue Breakell suggests, <quote rend="inline">the records do not simply go through a life cycle from
				creation and currency through to interactivity and the archive but move in and
				out of currency</quote> <ptr target="#breakell2008" loc="4"/>. This is in part an argument to sustain institutional
				archives that mark a specific time period and to exert best practices such as
				emulation in preserving digital materials and licensing to allow the use of
				copyrighted materials. It is also an argument for the creators of collections,
				whether inside institutions (BNMI), or as alternative archives (DLF, CDMLA), to
				negotiate clear accessioning and deaccessioning relationships with their own
				institution (The Banff Centre) or potential partner institutions (DLF, CDMLA)
				early in the process of creating or acquiring an archive, or as soon as there is
				a perceived sense of the significance of that collection, whether within the
				institution and/or the stakeholders that it serves. </p>
			<p>The period of the late 1990s through the early twenty-first century was one of
				intense interest in archives on the part of institutions, governments, curators,
				and artists, and coincides with the creation of the BNMI and the DLF
				documentation centre. The <q>allure</q> of the archive, as Sue Breakell (<ref target="#breakell2015">2015</ref>) notes,
				was sparked by a heightened engagement with memory and the emergence of memory
				technologies (such as databases, hard drives, and centralized server storage).
				The drive to digitize meant that some records would be left behind, fueling
				concerns about inclusion, and about who should have the right to choose which
				materials would be digitized. The massive production of online materials seemed
				to some to be a gift towards a universal human memory; to others, <quote rend="inline">the more
				absolute knowledge on the Internet becomes, the harder it is to comprehend as it
				[knowledge] transforms into an unreadable amount of data</quote> <ptr target="#hoth2021"/>. </p>
			<p>Post-modernism challenged the authoritative nature of historical records and
				archives, in part instigated by Michel Foucault’s (<ref target="#foucault1969">1969</ref>) analysis of archives as
				a demonstration of relationships and institutions in process, perpetually
				incomplete repositories that represent power, through what is present and absent
				in their contents. Jacques Derrida in Archive Fever: A Freudian Impression,
				argues for the political nature of the archive, observing that power resides in
				control over its content and access. Anticipating the rise of the Internet and
				digital preservation, he astutely described a contemporary obsession with
				archives and the desire to preserve. He painted a tension between the public
				domain and personal memory materials that plays out today, for example, in
				debates about the right to be forgotten,<note> This is the argument that an
					individual should be able to have their records removed from social media
					and other Internet sites. </note> or the ways that social media intermingle
				personal and institutional commentary and politics, or the growing interface
				between personal health data collection and medical records. In An Archival
				Impulse (<ref target="#foster2004">2004</ref>), Hal Foster recognizes the archival turn and analyzes three kinds
				of artists’ works: those that use archival content, those where the artist
				performs methods drawn from archival practices, and those in which artists
				create unique archives. Powerful works have occurred when archivists invite
				artists into collections to create new interpretations. The Artist-in-Residency
				Program at the City of Portland Archives and Record Centre supported Portland
				Archives artists-in-residence Garrick Imatini and Kaia Sand. They interviewed
				selected subjects who were documented in the city’s Police Bureau’s surveillance
				fonds of 576 activists, augmenting the police fonds with <quote rend="inline">lives embedded, yet
				silenced, in the records</quote>, resulting in a new understanding of that history
				and the expungement of criminal records <ptr target="#carbone2015" loc="51"/>. Antonio
				Muntadas’ The File Room is at the same time both an emulation and critique of 
				archival practices and an archive in its own right. It is a project
				intentionally without an ending, a travelling installation of physical archival
				files and a connected and collectively created and ongoing database of instances
				of censorship–political, cultural, and scientific.<note> It opened in 1994 and
					the database was hosted over the years at several sites, eventually
					migrating to Rhizome (a digital arts archive) who upgraded and restored it
					for exhibition in 2016 at its affiliate the New Museum and online
					presence</note> The historical context provides a framework for motivations
				and activities at the core of the three case studies that follow. </p>
			<p>Archives and archivists have various standards to guide them in considering which
				collections to acquire, the methods of accessioning collections and conditions
				to deaccession collections. The Canadian Council of Archives (<ref target="#cca2018">CCA, 2018</ref>)
				describes accessioning as, <quote rend="inline">… the physical and legal addition of predominantly
				unpublished documentary material to an archival repository’s holdings. It
				follows an archival appraisal decision identifying the records as having
				enduring value in relation to the acquisition mandate and policies of the
					repository.</quote><note> The CCA’s National Archival Accession Standard Working
					Group (NAASWG) wrote a content standard for archival accession information
					which governs metadata standards, information sharing, research within and
					across archives, and management of digital archives. See
						<ref target="http://archivescanada.ca/CWG_AccessionStandard">http://archivescanada.ca/CWG_AccessionStandard</ref>.</note> The Society of
				American Archivists (SAS) provides terms, process and considerations for
				deaccessioning <ptr target="#society2017"/>. Deaccessioning represents the removal of materials from
				an archive and is perceived by most archives to be a component of best
				practices, but it is understandably controversial. SAS argues that policy and
				guidelines are needed, with clear options for the materials deaccessioned.
				Decisions should be made by archivists, the archive, and its home institution.
				Processes need to be transparent, properly documented, and overseen in an
				ethical manner. The SAS suggests that deeds of gift should include clear
				deaccessioning terms. Reasons for deaccessioning materials include reappraisal
				of a collection’s relevance to institutional mandate, frequency of use, its
				potential research value, whether it would be more meaningful and better used in
				a different repository, its condition, and maintenance costs. Other
				considerations include the ability to define provenance, or legal requirements
				to retain documents over time periods. Archives ideally seek a transfer of fonds
				to a different repository. They may return materials to original owners, or they
				may sell the collection or, ultimately, destroy the records. These routes are
				relevant for the case studies considered below. </p>
			<p>Also relevant are increased options in collections management and permissions,
				given the rise of digitization and the acquisition of creative media works. The
				British Archive for Contemporary Writing has adopted two complementary
				practices, the creation of a <q>storehouse</q> and a <q>collection.</q> The first is the
				short-term loan of writers’ archives to support thematic archival research, for
				example for six months rather than the 20 years minimum required by most
				archives <ptr target="#whibley2019"/>. The goal is that emerging writers will see BACW as a
				trusted agent, and that writers will provide their archives to the collection as
				their careers mature <ptr target="#eastanglia2022"/>. Licensing is an
				alternative to <q>deposit</q> as it allows multiple institutions to hold digital
				materials and retains the originator’s copyright. For example, with a deposit
				license, such as that of the Oxford University Research Archive (<ref target="#ora2014">ORA, 2014</ref>), the
				intellectual property creator retains their rights and can continue to license
				it and earn revenue and agrees to grant the University a non-exclusive,
				sub-licensable, worldwide license to store and access the work to the public. </p>
			<p>The last decades have witnessed continued dialogue within the archival community
				and between communities and archivists that shift archival best practices in
				relation to Indigenous records and records of other vulnerable groups. This
				includes replevin, or repatriating holdings to Indigenous groups at their
				request, or the renegotiation of ownership and access with Indigenous peoples
				for archives remaining in collections. Call 70 of Canada’s Truth and
				Reconciliation Commission requires the inclusion of Indigenous recordkeepers and
				researchers, their perspectives, and their methodologies within the Canadian
				archival system. Critical archival studies foster archival practices that resist
				reinforcing oppression based on race, class, gender, sexuality, and ability.
				Instead, the goal is to develop inclusive, accessible, multivocal sites for
				cultural participation and dissemination <ptr target="#caswell2019"/>. </p></div>
			<div>
			<head>
				The Case Studies
			</head>
			<div>
				<head>The Banff New Media Institute</head>
			
			<p>The Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) ran from 1995 to 2010 at The Banff Centre
				(TBC) in Alberta, Canada, on the heels of the centre’s early history of virtual
				reality and new media research. It was an international think tank on the
				present and future practices of new media, with leaders engaged in developing
				the science and technologies, creative and design practices, jurisprudence,
				business models, and theories; it was also a training hub and business
				incubator, with three research labs and a co-production program. BNMI staff
				curated exhibitions and events both at the Walter Phillips Gallery on site and
					abroad.<note> To see the breadth of the events and participants explore
						<ref
						target="https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/"
						>https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/</ref>.</note>
				Over the course of its first ten years, it held over 150 summits, symposia,
				workshops, conferences, and events which were recorded (audio) and from which
				relevant records such as release forms, agendas, analysis of events, and other
				memorabilia were kept. Co-productions were described and catalogued, and the
				documentation made available on-line, as were exhibition descriptions and
				documentation. The BNMI created Horizonzero.ca, a Heritage Canada funded
				experimental online gallery and site for discourse regarding the new media world
				which acted as a guide back to the summits and co-productions. </p>
			<p>The BNMI team were attentive to gender imbalance in the growth of the new media
				industry, the presence of female identified creative practitioners and their
				lack of inclusion in festivals, and the burgeoning of a diverse global creative
				new media community. As much as possible there was mitigation against digital
				exclusion, accepting George Gerbner’s concept of <q>symbolic annihilation,</q> where
				absence from the historical record removes practices and voices that could shape
				the future, a concept applied to archives by Caswell <ptr target="#caswell2016"/> <ptr target="#caswell2014"/>.<note> For example, the sequential events Bridges (co-created
					with Celia Pearce from the University of Southern California), Bridges 2,
					and Skinning Our Tools bear testimony to the ways that the BNMI insisted on
					bringing discussions of race and Indigenous identity to art, science, and
					technology tables.</note> A feature of BNMI was its deep commitment to
				Indigenous creators and technical leaders, whose creative practices and
				self-governed events were supported by BNMI (such as <title rend="italic">Drum Beat
					to Drum Byte</title>., two gatherings regarding Indigenous practices and
				presence on the Internet that were two decades apart). Indigenous artists,
				technicians, theorists, curators, and elders engaged in all manner of BNMI
				activities. BNMI also built collaborations with local Indigenous
					communities.<note> Jules Bergis (<ref target="#bergis">2016</ref>) underscores the danger that digital
					archives in particular, because of technical and programming needs will
					exclude traditionally marginalized groups.</note> Despite its government
				and industry funding the BNMI fearlessly hosted agonistic debates over video
				game sexism, algorithmic bias, anthropocentric notions of intelligence,
				open-source vs copyright, bioengineering and environment, and other
				controversial topics.<note> The BNMI was funded by the Canadian Tri-council
					research agencies, Alberta research, Telefilm Canada, the Canada Council
					for the Arts, Heritage and Industry Canada, international councils, and
					Canadian and international industry. </note>
			</p>
			<p>In synch with Foucault, Derrida, and Foster’s calls to reexamine the archives, the
				BNMI held summits and workshops that considered the transition to digital
				archives; events debated memory and history, the archive versus the database and
				their ultimate integration, and the question of what should be digitized and how
				it should be conserved, with titles such as <title rend="quotes">Media, Material and Culture:
				Communicating Canada’s Heritage</title>. <title rend="quotes">Unforgiving Memory</title>. and <title rend="quotes">ReFresh</title>. (which
				have become the biannual Media Art History conferences).<note>
					<ref target="https://www.mediaarthistory.org/mah-conf-series"
						>https://www.mediaarthistory.org/mah-conf-series</ref>.</note> These
				strengthened the accelerating <q>archive fever</q> within the BNMI and the belief
				that it must leave a record of this complex era. That intuition is rewarded
				today as the BNMI fonds include documentation of prescient debates that are in
				contemporary reprise (such as the nature of social media, gender, and race bias
				in AI systems, the mapping potential of GPS/GIS technologies, or control over
				data), and engage deeply diverse actors regarding technologies, systems, tools,
				and creative expressions that have shaped our lives today.<note> These include
					machine learning, genomics, neuroscience, nanotechnology, Artificial
					General Intelligence, social media, blogs, mobile devices and their
					affordances, Augmented and Virtual Reality, open source, streaming, and
					digital currencies.</note>
			</p>
			<p>For the archive project, a decade of audio recordings and documents were digitized
				and brought up to 2005 standards and a physical archive and finding aid were
				created by a professional archivist seconded from the National Archives Canada.
				There was an online interface which was searchable by events, names, and dates,
				and it was easily accessed on TBC’s website, as was the co-production catalogue.
				The BNMI team felt a contractual, financial, and emotional connection to the
				fonds. We had raised a significant amount of public funding to build this
				collection and create a related book. Speakers had signed release forms and
				expected that the associated materials would be present on the BNMI web site.
				The same contractual and affective bonds were not shared across The Banff
				Centre. In 2005 the BNMI team hoped that the fonds could reside with the Paul
				Fleck Library and Archive at the Banff Centre, but the Archive had no interest
				in the physical or digital archive nor did the archivist at that time recognize
				value in placing the BNMI fonds online.<note> This memory was provided by Susan
					Kennard, who was the Director of the BNMI from 2005 – 2010.</note> I left
				TBC in 2005; Susan Kennard, then Director of the BNMI, left in 2010; and TBC
				closed the BNMI shortly afterwards. The digital archive persisted, available on
				the main web site, and was well used. Dr. Sarah Cook and I co-edited the book
					<title rend="italic">Euphoria and Dystopia: The Banff New Media Institute
					Dialogues</title> and it was published in 2011 by TBC and University of
				Waterloo’s Riverside Press.<note> It included essays reflecting on the
					activities and themes of the BNMI, transcripts from the BNMI archives,
					information on attendees, and a visualization of BNMI activities. A DVD
					documenting horizonzero.ca was bundled with the book. The full version is
					available here: <ref
						target="https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/"
						>https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/</ref>.
				</note> The e-book version in 2013 was meticulously linked to the online archive
				as a thematic, discursive, and critical finding aid. The BNMI efforts
				represented a strategy for archival access comprising multiple interpretive
				publications (the e-book and Horizonzero.ca) linked to a digital archive. This
				approach is appropriate for reinvigorating archives, introducing fonds to new
				audiences, and making them available for creative interpretation by artists and
				new generations of scholars. </p>
				
				<figure>
					<head>Euphoria &amp; Dystopia and Horizonzero.ca DVDs – physical traces of digital
						archives</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>Screenshot of a book cover for a book entitled <title rend="quotes">Euphoria and Dystopia</title>. Image 2 is a screenshot of a poster for an event called horizon^0</figDesc>
				</figure>
			</div>
				<div>
			<head>Euphoria &amp; Dystopia and Horizonzero.ca DVDs – physical traces of digital
				archives</head>
			<p>In 2016 Indigenous artist Cheryl L’Hirondelle found that the archive was no longer
				accessible and sounded an alert. Indeed, it had been removed after a change of
				leadership and a web rebranding and would never return to its original online
				form, thus severing all the meticulous links made to several thousand digital
				records and to the digital archives from other publications. Two years later,
				The Banff Centre did not renew the HorizonZero.ca domain or pay the small fee
				for hosting, so this legacy of the BNMI also disappeared. </p>
			<p>Contributors to the archive – most poignantly Indigenous artists and historians –
				along with other scholars and archivists, the book publisher Philip Beesley,
				Sarah Cook, and I appealed to The Banff Centre to return the archive to
				researchers and the public again through a digital interface and volunteered to
				find or contribute funding. In 2018 TBC’s archivist John Yolkowski stepped in
				and moved the project from an IT-led web site initiative to an archive-led
				initiative. The physical fonds moved to the Paul Fleck Library and Archives and
				were accessioned. Work began and a number of documents were made available on
				the TBC’s archive site and mirrored on Alberta on Record.<note>
					<ref target="https://albertaonrecord.ca/banff-new-media-institute"
						>https://albertaonrecord.ca/banff-new-media-institute</ref>.</note>
				Then Yolkowski left. Indigenous artists and media historians insisted that the
				Indigenous media arts history be reconstructed, as TBC was an epicenter of
				Indigenous and international media production, new media, and digital arts
				creativity. The Banff Centre acted on this in 2021 and hired a team of
				researchers to undertake an oral history of Indigenous media art at TBC, which
				is now completed. These efforts underscore the responsibility (Bergis, 2016)
				that institutions bear in relation to their engagement with Indigenous and other
				equity seeking communities if they collect and represent their data. </p>
			<p>Perhaps The Banff Centre leadership perceived the BNMI archive as the expression
				of a specific leadership and their program priorities, not as an archive. While
				many institutions do retain program records, they are rarely featured as part of
				a current marketing web site. There was no continuity in Banff’s Indigenous
				leadership, and hence no awareness of the archive’s Indigenous contents or
				advocate. Institutional memory is fragile at best; however, the formal nature of
				an archive and the policies surrounding it can create some ballast. The
				collection represented consciously collected and ordered institutional records,
				but it was not an archive – in this period it was not yet appraised or perceived
				as having <q>enduring</q> institutional value and hence formally accessioned. Rather,
				it was a counter archive within an institution. TBC has a deaccessioning policy
				in place for its visual art collection, and its Paul Fleck Library and Archives
				holdings, but the BNMI archive, treated as an orphan record of program contents,
				was not covered under this policy. </p>
			<p>It is valuable, nonetheless, to consider the principles of deaccessioning in
				collections management as defined by the SAS (<ref target="#sas2017">2017</ref>). Richard Gerrard (<ref target="#gerrard2013">2013</ref>) in
				his instructional text on deaccessioning lays out the rigorous staged nature of
				removing collections: due diligence institutional governance processes are
				required. The driver should be to improve the collection, and the goal of
				disposal to find a new home more able to house a collection. Writing on
				<title rend="quotes">Archival Appraisal and Deaccessioning</title> in <title rend="italic">Indigitization:
					Tools for Digitizing and Sustaining Indigenous Knowledge</title> (<ref target="#larson2020">2020</ref>), Kayla
				Lar-son says of deaccessioning that materials should be returned to the original
				donors or holders of a collection. This principle is relevant for HorizonZero.ca
				as the <q>tell</q> issue included a reversioning of the Elderspeak website of the
				Meadow Lake Tribal Council with their permission as they could no longer host
				the original Elderspeak collection of stories. The issue was edited by Cheryl
				L’Hirondelle who undertook that reversioning. With the end of Horizonzero.ca, an
				unforeseen consequence was that MLTC lost access to Elderspeak although it is
				present on the Internet Archive.<note>
					<ref
						target="https://web.archive.org/web/20160316203351/http://www.horizonzero.ca/elderspeak/index.html"
						>https://web.archive.org/web/20160316203351/http://www.horizonzero.ca/elderspeak/index.html</ref>.</note>
				With L’Hirondelle’s support, MLTC will work with the DVD version and
				L’Hirondelle’s original files to repatriate the files and recreate the site. </p>
			<p>A formal agreement should have been put in place for the care and transition of
				the BNMI records and the maintenance of HorizonZero, or for its disciplined
				disposal to another identified archive. As its creators, we should have built in
				redundancy and distributed the responsibility for maintenance while we were still
				working at TBC (Endings Symposium chat 14:08:32), and possibly created a fund to
				upgrade and support the fonds. In the Q. and A. of my presentation at the
				Project Endings conference, Martin Holmes urged <quote rend="inline">archives, mirrors, repos, web
				servers, Internet Archive — make as many copies as possible.</quote> We should have
				arranged for a second repository. Alternatively, The Banff Centre could have
				returned the BNMI archive to Cook, Diamond, and Beesley and enabled them to find
				a home, as several institutions stepped up to offer to take it — but even that
				would have required staff effort and institutional prioritization.<note> In
					another example, the leadership of Toronto’s Design Exchange brought back
					the original curator of its collection for the sole purpose of finding it a
					new home; they followed Canadian Museum Association standards and it now
					resides with the ROM and the Canadian Museum of History.</note> The
				physical and some digital archives are available on site to researchers who
				travel to The Banff Centre. In 2022 Jessica Zimmerman, the new archivist of the
				Paul Fleck Archive, reached out with a commitment to <quote rend="inline">find a home for the BNMI
				story,</quote> integrating it into The Banff Centre’s history and timeline and
				revitalizing its online presence, including its audio recordings and previous
				archival interface. Banff is initiating this process and I will collaborate with
				the archives to seek funds for these endeavors. They may redescribe material
				into AtoM<note><quote rend="inline">AtoM stands for Access to Memory. It is a web-based,
					open source application for standards-based archival description and access
					in a multilingual, multi-repository environment</quote> (<ref
						target="https://www.accesstomemory.org/en/"
						>https://www.accesstomemory.org/en/</ref>). </note>
				to afford greater public accessibility and retrieval options and create a Rules
				for Archival Description (RAD) standard-compliant finding aid for easier access
				for distance researchers.<note>AtoM (Access to Memory) provides the following definition of an
					archival description, <quote rend="inline">Archival description is a body of information about
						an archival record or records. The descriptions provide contextual
						information about the archival materials and are arranged into hierarchical
						levels (<ref
							target="https://www.accesstomemory.org/en/docs/2.3/user-manual/glossary/glossary/#term-fonds"
							>fonds</ref>, series, files, items, and variations of these in
						accordance with institutional standards).</quote> <ref
							target="https://www.accesstomemory.org/en/docs/2.3/user-manual/add-edit-content/archival-descriptions/#archival-descriptions"
							>https://www.accesstomemory.org/en/docs/2.3/user-manual/add-edit-content/archival-descriptions/#archival-descriptions</ref>.</note> Demand for access to the archive has grown and The
				Banff Centre seeks to revitalize its digital programs and celebrate its fifty
				years of work with Indigenous communities. The collection now fits CCA’s
				criteria for accessioning (<ref target="#cca2018">2018</ref>). This plan would mean that the BNMI’s role and
				impact will be visible to the current generation of scholars, artists, and
				researchers, heralding a happy ending. </p>
				
				<figure>
					<head><title rend="inline">Unforgiving Memory</title> summit event agenda - Alberta on Record provides access to
						several BNMI documents digitized in 2018.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>Screenshot of an event called "Unforgiving Memory" agenda. The agenda also includes brands who sponsored the event</figDesc>
				</figure>
		
			</div>
				<div>
			<head>
				Daniel Langlois Foundation Documentation Centre
			</head>
			<p>The second case study underscores the importance of establishing a back-up
				repository. The Daniel Langlois Foundation Centre for Research and Documentation
				was initiated in 1998 by Jean Gagnon with the support of Daniel Langlois, the
				co-founder of Softimage.<note>Jean Gagnon provided details of the motivation
					for these initiatives and the transition process in an interview with me in
					March of 2021.</note> It became an important repository for the new
				media art works funded by the foundation and an expanded place to collect
				archives from artists, institutions and events that represented the history of
				media arts.<note> The collection grew to comprise 2691 video works
					or source documents, DVDs, documentary works and documentation of art
					works, 2084 files of artists, festivals, biennales, 764 audio documents,
					documentation, and CD-ROMs by artists. From 2000 to 2005 the Centre
					acquired 6,000 books.</note>
				Langlois renovated the Ex-Centris buildings which included theatres, gathering
				spaces, and a home for the documentation centre’s materials, with offices for
				visiting researchers. The DLF bought collections including those of stellar
				video artists the Vasulkas, and EAT, Experimental Art and Technology — the 9
				EVENINGS OF THEATRE AND ENGINEERING, an exhibition that heralded the opening of
				an American epoch of art and science collaboration. A robust web presence
				accompanied the centre, allowing users to identify artists and projects. In
				2005, the Documentation and Conservation of Media Arts Heritage (DOCAM) network,
				led by Alain de Pacard, was spearheaded by DLF, and comprised 20 institutions,
				from universities, to the prestigious new media journal <title rend="italic"
					>Leonardo</title>, to digital media centres and museums, with funding from
				SSHRC. It sought to create standards for the documentation, exhibition, and
				archiving of new media art works. DOCAM and the Education Centre invited
				artists, curators, and historians into this rich collection through a series of
				residencies. For example, in her residency, Dr. Caroline Langill produced <ref
					target="https://www.fondation-langlois.org/html/e/page.php?NumPage=742">
					<title rend="italic">Shifting Polarities: Proposing a Canon of Canadian
						Electronic Media Art, 1970-1990</title>
				</ref> (2006), an influential treatise that made the case that the contemporary
				art canon must expand to integrate new media art.<note>
					<ref target="https://www.fondation-langlois.org/html/e/page.php?NumPage=742">https://www.fondation-langlois.org/html/e/page.php?NumPage=742</ref>.</note>
			</p>
			<p>Over time Langlois’ attention drifted. His investments were not flourishing, and
				the cinemas at Ex-Centris were bleeding $2 million/year. By 2006, concerned
				about the sustainability of the documentation centre, Gagnon began approaching
				DOCAM members as well as the La Cinémathèque québécoise to take the centre’s
				holdings and turn them into an archive. Acquisition contracts stipulated that
				the Foundation was legally responsible to find a not-for-profit home if it
				stopped functioning. Gagnon left in 2008. Langlois was hard hit by the 2008
				financial crash. Access to the documentation centre ended with the collection
				boxed up and stored. International scholars and donors alike began to pressure
				the DLF to find a home for the collection. Ultimately, contractual obligations
				with individuals or agents who had donated their records, user activism, and the
				commitment of an individual, Jean Gagnon, resulted in a safe landing for this
				valuable archive. This transfer represents a deaccessioning best practice as
				defined by the SAS (<ref target="#sas2017">2017</ref>). </p>
			<p>La Cinémathèque québécoise accepted the fonds as the director Pierre Renault was
				interested in new media. Gagnon moved to the CQ as head of collections in 2010.
				He immediately began negotiations with the DLF, and secured a grant of $75,000
				to move and update the finding aid and web site; the collection formally moved
				on October 11, 2011. No further acquisitions would occur, hence avoiding a
				debate about whether CQ should begin to acquire new media art works which could
				have halted the transfer of the collection. The DLF collection remains one of
				CQ’s most popular archives, with valuable holdings like the records of 1960s 
				Xerox artist Sonia Sheridan.<note> Xerox is used here to
					denote that Sheridan used Xerox processes rather than that she was a Xerox
					employee. </note>
			</p>
					<p>The DLF site also leads to the DOCAM project web site.<note> <ref target="https://www.docam.ca/index-2.html">https://www.docam.ca/index-2.html</ref>. </note> DOCAM research
				identified and investigated five axes that distinguish methodologies and tools
				needed to address the preservation and technological documentation of electronic
				works of art, relevant to all archives, museums, libraries, and other collecting
				agencies managing new media and digital arts collections:
				<quote rend="inline">conservation, documentation, cataloguing, history of technologies
				and terminology.</quote> DOCAM includes case studies conducted with museum partners.<note> Partners are the
							National Gallery of Canada, Musée d’art contemporain de Montréal, Montreal
							Museum of Fine Arts, and Canadian Centre for Architecture including artists
							such as Janet Cardiff, Stan Douglas, Gary Hill, Nam June Paik, David
							Rokeby, Greg Lynn, and Bill Viola. Resources include a <title rend="italic"
								>Preservation Guide for Technology-Based Artwork</title>; a <title
									rend="italic">Cataloguing Guide for New Media Collection</title>; a  <title
										rend="italic">Documentary Mode</title> adapted to media arts; <title
											rend="italic">DOCAM Glossauru</title>, a bilingual terminological tool;
							and a <title rend="italic">Technological Timeline</title>, which includes both
							media artworks and technological components.</note> The association of the DOCAM and DLF sites is valuable
				because DOCAM provides a contextual understanding of the works in the collection
				as well as wisdom for current archives that collect physical, online, or
				post-Internet art (online with physical expression). Langlois recently
				subsidized the conversion of elements of the collection through emulation,
				including works with online links from Flash to HTML5 as many artists’ websites
				and related CD-ROM and DVD projects were built in Flash in the early 2000s.,
				Although proprietary, Flash provided highly malleable graphic design tools. This
				is a positive example of the archive’s originator in concert with the current
				archive taking responsibility for the ongoing maintenance of the fonds. </p>
			<p>When asked if he regretted the path that he took to create a media arts
				documentation centre, Gagnon indicated his belief that there was no other route
				available at the time. He had just left his role as Media Arts curator at the
				National Gallery of Canada and there was no capacity or interest there.<note> After Jean Gagnon left, the NGC terminated the role of media arts
					curator.</note> He is concerned that CQ
				remains dependent on him for deep knowledge of the archive because there is no
				time or resources there to train another expert. </p>
			
				
				<figure>
					<head>Sub-navigation through La Cinémathèque québécoise to Daniel Langlois Foundation
						documentation centre interface, 2021</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>Screenshot of a website with tabs for themes, works, artists, and publications. the header image includes images from the archive</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Sara Diamond Fonds, Crista Dahl Media Library &amp;
					Archive
			</head>
			
				<p>The Crista Dahl Media Library &amp; Archive (CDMLA) is housed within the VIVO
					Media Arts Centre
				and holds a  significant repository of 8000 items, including video art,
				documentary, experimental documentary, narrative, synaesthetic, animation, and
				event documentation videotapes by artists and independent producers. The
				collections represent sixty years of production, an extensive archive of
				publications from the video and media art world and documentation of events,
				exhibitions, organizations, social movements, government policies, as well as
				the history of VIVO, founded in 1973. Over the last decade it has expanded its
				efforts to create fifteen special collections, as well as nine major fonds and
				five minor fonds. The CDMLA fonds align with Foster’s description of artists’
				engagement with archives. The CDMLA has developed finding aids and projects
				including exhibitions built from the collections and fonds with artists’
				residencies to reinterpret contents. They have raised funds to digitize aspects
				of the archive and provide effective navigation interfaces. In 2016-17, VIVO
				approached me to donate my materials to them from my earlier life as an artist,
				activist, and academic. I was the board president and an artist and curator
				there for many years. </p>
			<p>My archive, built over the last four years, holds multiple sub-collections: the
				Women’s Labour History Project; my personal video art and new media works
				including the extensive <ref target="http://www.codezebra.ca/"
					>www.codezebra.ca</ref> Post-Internet art project which itself consists of
				software, a website, performances, wearable art, and artifacts;<note>
							CodeZebra was emulated from Flash onto the HTML5 platform, maintaining the
							initial quality of its integrated web sites which began in 1997 and
							continued until 2004. Unfortunately, several of the servers where the
							original games and software resided are no longer connected and
							reconstructing the links from the last version of the software to the site
							is a project requiring future efforts.</note> Amelia Productions, a
				five-person feminist collective (1980–1982) of which I was a member; and
				documents regarding international solidarity, Indigenous rights, feminism,
				LGBTQ2+, anti-censorship activities, labour activism, and curriculum
				development. The experimental documentaries of the Women’s Labour History
				Project and its photographic and print exhibitions relied heavily on film,
				television, photographic, and institutional archives in Canada and British
				Columbia — hence components of this collection are archives of archives, acting
				as a means of understanding what was collected and what was absent. The oral
				histories in the archive compensated for the sparse records regarding women
				workers available in archives. The art works are available on the site under a
				licensing agreement <ptr target="#ora2014"/>. </p>
			<p>Archivist Karen Knights has created a permanent online exhibition Women and West
				Coast Labour: Eighty years of action for equity in domestic and workplace labour
				by women in B.C.<note>
					<ref
						target="http://www.vivomediaarts.com/archive/women-and-west-coast-labour/"
						>http://www.vivomediaarts.com/archive/women-and-west-coast-labour/</ref>.</note> featuring two
				sub-exhibitions. One on women’s activism holds Chambermaids and Whistlepunks
				1900–1970, featuring oral histories of labor organization from the Women’s
				Labour History Project, and the fonds of Amelia Productions. A second
				exhibition, Working Women in Focus 1970–1980, presents the fonds of the Women in
				Focus feminist artist-run production, distribution, and exhibition centre.</p>
			
				<figure>
					<head>Women’s Labour History Project fonds launch page, Crista Dahl Library and
						Archives</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>screenshot of the homepage for the women's labour history project. the website includes navigation and information about the project</figDesc>
				</figure>
				
				
			<p>As with Jean Gagnon and the DLF, VIVO relies on one person, Karen Knights, who is
				the current driving force behind the media archive, just as it relied on Crista
				Dahl for the print and print materials archive. I moved forward with the
				donation with the stipulation that we bring Simon Fraser University into the
				project as a formal partner, acting on lessons learned from the BNMI and DLF
				archives. Copies of my Women’s Labour History Project audio collection reside in
				the Royal British Columbia Museum archives, which were the first repository, and
				the SFU archive, where I am an alumna and recipient of an Honorary Doctorate.
				SFU has made a contractual commitment to acquire my collection should VIVO need
				to deaccession it. The responsibility for the digitization, maintenance, and
				dissemination of this fonds is shared between the archive (CDMLA), SFU, and me,
				the living donor. While there are currently affective ties to the collection on
				the part of VIVO, SFU, and me, the former could wane with generational change.
				We have curated a partnership to create an ecosystem that will link my fonds at
				VIVO with nine other relevant collections and interested organizations and
				research centres.<note>The partnership is comprised of OCAD University’s Centre for the Study of the Black Canadian Diaspora (CBCD) and Visual Analytics Laboratory (VAL), Simon Fraser University Archives (SFUA) and SFU Library Special Collections and Rare Books (SCRB), City of Vancouver Archives (CVA), The Royal British Columbia Museum (RBCM), the BC Labour Heritage Centre (BCLHC), BLAK, a Black artists’ centre in Surrey, B.C., and Satellite Video Exchange Society’s VIVO Media Arts Centre programming committee and Crista Dahl Media Library &amp; Archive (CDMLA).</note> Partners will gain by
				examining the histories and methodologies that shaped their institutions and
				fonds and by making connections between historical and contemporary actors
				including originating communities and individuals to explore reinterpretation
				and redescription.</p>
			<p>Our methods to develop the bridge are highly collaborative and include
				participatory design <ptr target="#simonsen2013"/> incorporating Sabharwal’s
				concept of <q>socialized digital curation</q> (<ref target="#sabharwal2021">2021</ref>); visualization <ptr target="#harris2019"/> <ptr target="#bahde2017"/>; and research-creation (<ref target="#sabharwal2014">2014</ref>) in a case study
				approach. We will undertake workshops to create the specification for the
				ecosystem and develop microsites that foreshadow the design. Metadata,
				annotation, and social media tagging tools <ptr target="#fatona2021"/> <ptr target="#allisoncassin2020"/>
				will be applied through metadata and redescription workshops with Indigenous,
				Black, and other community groups. Artist-in-the-archives and researcher
				workshops will encourage exploration, discovery, application, integration, and
				dissemination of archival contents. We will sketch visualizations that show
				relationships between fonds and metadata. A series of historical case studies by 
				Dr. Andrea Fatona, Dana Claxton and Dr. Karrmen Crey, Karen Knights, and me will include research,
				curation, and/or artmaking. </p></div>
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>
				Conclusions
			</head>
			<p>Perhaps institutions, creators of archives, and their users all bear
				responsibility for the protection and continuity of archives. Individuals have
				affective ties to the artists and archives that house their work and that they
				have built, but it is not viable to rely only on a few knowledgeable and
				emotionally-attached individuals. Collections within institutions, alternative
				archives, and significant fonds would benefit from strategies and contracts that
				address deaccessioning and alternative repositories. Temporary forms of
				accessioning such as the storehouse may serve to test interest in a collection
				before its donation. Where possible, donor commitments to raise dollars for
				maintenance and dissemination in partnership with archives are beneficial but
				should not lead to excluding the acquisition of fonds from marginalized groups.
				Institutions need to address duty of care for fonds representing Indigenous
				knowledge and history. Knowledge dissemination that creates new interest and new
				proponents for an archive including its recovery and rereading is both an
				individual and an institutional responsibility. Dr. Jennifer Kennedy from
				Queen’s University serves as an example — she is exploring the BNMI archives to
				understand contemporary feminist practices in new media that were sparked
				through encounters at the BNMI events and its co-productions and became a strong
				advocate for its revitalization (<ref target="#bnmi2021">2021</ref>). The partnership between VIVO, other
				archives, and community organizations and underrepresented groups should
				stimulate ongoing interpretation of my fonds. And the renewal of the BNMI’s
				Indigenous media archive through oral histories is testimony to effective user
				activism. </p>
			</div>
			
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="alberta2016" label="Alberta Foundation 2016"> Alberta Foundation for the Arts. <title rend="quotes">Collection Management
					Policy</title>. Available at:
					<ref target="https://www.affta.ab.ca/sites/default/files/AFACollection_CollectionManagementPolicy_20161213.pdf">https://www.affta.ab.ca/sites/default/files/AFACollection_CollectionManagementPolicy_20161213.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="albertaa" label="Alberta on Record n.d.a"> Alberta on Record. <title rend="quotes">Banff New Media Institute</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://albertaonrecord.ca/banff-new-media-institute;rad?sf_culture=fr"
					>https://albertaonrecord.ca/banff-new-media-institute;rad?sf_culture=fr</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="albertab" label="Alberta on Record n.d.b"> File 1.G - 12 <title rend="quotes">Unforgiving Memory</title>. Agenda, BNMI. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="allisoncassin2020" label="Allison-Cassin 2020"> Allison-Cassin, S. <title rend="quotes">Indigenous knowledge architecture and
					metadata workshops</title>. <title rend="italic">Social ecology of vulnerable media</title>,
					Vulnerable Media Lab. June 2020. Available at: <ref
						target="http://vulnerablemedialab.ca/indigenous-knowledge-architecture-and-metadata-workshops/"
						>vulnerablemedialab.ca/indigenous-knowledge-architecture-and-metadata-workshops/.</ref>
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="archivescanada2018" label="Archives Canada 2018">Archives Canada (2018) <title rend="quotes">CCA Canadian Archives Information
					Standard (CAAIS) National Archival Accession Standard Working Group (NAASWG)</title>. Available at: 
					<ref target="http://archivescanada.ca/CWG_AccessionStandard#Accessioning_e">http://archivescanada.ca/CWG_AccessionStandard#Accessioning_e</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="artspace2014" label="Artspace 2014"> Artspace
					Editors. <title rend="quotes">How the Art World Caught Archive Fever</title>. Jan. 22, 2014. Available at:
					<ref target="https://www.artspace.com/magazine/art_101/art_market/the_art_worlds_love_affair_with_archives-51976">https://www.artspace.com/magazine/art_101/art_market/the_art_worlds_love_affair_with_archives-51976</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bahde2017" label="Bahde 2017"> Bahde, A. <title rend="quotes">Conceptual data visualization in archival finding aids:
					Preliminary user responses</title>. <title rend="italic">Libraries and the Academy</title>,
					17(3): pp. 485–506. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beiguelman2019" label="Beiguelman 2019"> Beiguelman, Giselle. <title rend="quotes"
						>Museums of Losses for Clouds of Oblivion</title>. In O. Grau, J. Hoth, and
					Wandl-Vogt (eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Art through the Looking Glass:
						New strategies for archiving, collecting and preserving in digital
						humanitie</title>s. Austria: Edition Donau-Universität (2019).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="belkin2008" label="Belkin 2008"> Belkin, N. J. <title rend="quotes">Some (what) Grand Challenges for Information
					Retrieval</title>. <title rend="italic">ACM SIGIR Forum</title>, 42(2008): 47–54.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bergis2016" label="Bergis 2016"> Bergis Jules, (2016) <title rend="quotes">Confronting Our Failure of Care Around the
					Legacies of Marginalized People in the Archives</title>. <title rend="italic">Medium</title>. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://medium.com/on-archivy/confronting-our-failure-of-care-around-the-legacies-of-marginalized-people-in-the-archives-dc4180397280">https://medium.com/on-archivy/confronting-our-failure-of-care-around-the-legacies-of-marginalized-people-in-the-archives-dc4180397280</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="birkin2015" label="Birkin 2015"> Jane (2015) <title rend="quotes">Art, Work, and Archives: Performativity and the
					Techniques of Production</title>, November 2015, <title rend="italic">Archive Journal</title>. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://www.archivejournal.net/essays/art-work-and-archives/">https://www.archivejournal.net/essays/art-work-and-archives/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="breakell2008" label="Breakell 2008">Breakell, Sue (2008) <title rend="quotes">Negotiating the Archive</title>. <title rend="italic">Tate Papers</title> #9. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://www.tate.org.uk/research/publications/tate-papers/09/perspectives-negotiating-the-archive">https://www.tate.org.uk/research/publications/tate-papers/09/perspectives-negotiating-the-archive</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="breakell2015" label="Breakell 2015"> Breakell, Sue. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Archival practices and the practice of
					archives in the visual arts’ Archives and Record</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal of the Archives
					and Records Association</title>, 36(1) pp. 1–5. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/23257962.2015.1018151"
						>https://doi.org/10.1080/23257962.2015.1018151</ref>.
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="canadianarchitect2019" label="Canadian Architect 2019">Canadian Architect. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Design Exchange to Deaccession
					Collection and Pivot to Programming</title>. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://www.canadianarchitect.com/design-exchange-to-deaccession-collection-and-pivot-to-programming/">https://www.canadianarchitect.com/design-exchange-to-deaccession-collection-and-pivot-to-programming/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cbc2009" label="CBC 2009">CBC Montreal. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Film Fans Boo Closure of Ex-Centris Cinema</title>. Jan. 14,
					2009. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/montreal/montreal-film-fans-boo-closure-of-ex-centris-cinema-1.862563">https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/montreal/montreal-film-fans-boo-closure-of-ex-centris-cinema-1.862563</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="carbone2020" label="Carbone 2020">Carbone, Kathy. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Archival Art: Memory Practices,
					Interventions, and Productions</title>, <title rend="italic">Curator: The Museum
						Journal</title> 63(2), pp. 257–263.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="carbone2015" label="Carbone 2015"> Carbone, Kathy (2015) <title rend="quotes">Artists in the Archive: An Exploratory Study
					of the Artist-in-Residence Program at the City of Portland Archives &amp;
					Records Center</title>, <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title> 79 (Spring 2015), pp. 27–52.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="caswell2019" label="Caswell &amp; Cifor 2019"> Caswell, M. &amp; Cifor, M. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Neither a
					beginning nor an end: Applying an ethics of care to digital archival
					collections</title> in <title rend="italic">The Routledge International Handbook of New
						Digital Practices in Galleries, Libraries, Archives, Museums, and Heritage
						Sites</title>. Routledge.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="caswell2016" label="Caswell, Cifor &amp; Ramirez 2016"> Caswell, Michelle, Cifor, Marika &amp; Ramirez,
					Mario H. (2016) <title rend="quotes">To Suddenly Discover Yourself Existing: Uncovering the Impact
					of Community Archives</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title>,
					79(1) (SPRING/SUMMER 2016), pp. 56–81. Published by:
					Society of American Archivists.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="caswell2014" label="Caswell 2014"> Caswell, M. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Seeing yourself in history: Community archives
					and the fight against symbolic annihilation</title>, <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>, 36(4),
					pp. 26–37. ISSN: 0272-3433, electronic ISSN 1533-8576. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cohen2014" label="Cohen 2014"> Cohen, H. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Research creation: A scholarship of creativity</title>,
					<title rend="italic">Journal of the New Media Caucus</title>. Available at:
					<ref
						target="http://median.newmediacaucus.org/research-creation-explorations/research-creation-a-scholarship-of-creativity/"
						>http://median.newmediacaucus.org/research-creation-explorations/research-creation-a-scholarship-of-creativity/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cook2012" label="Cook &amp; Diamond 2012"> Cook, Sarah &amp; Diamond, Sara (2012) <title rend="italic"
					>Euphoria and Dystopia: The Banff new media dialogues</title>. Banff: Banff
					Centre Press and University of Waterloo, Riverside Architectural Press. Available at:  <ref
						target="https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/"
						>https://livingarchitecturesystems.com/publication/euphoria-dystopia/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cinematheque2011" label="Cinémathèque québécoise &amp; Daniel Langlois Foundation &amp; Cinema Press Release"> Cinémathèque québécoise and Daniel Langlois Foundation and Cinema Press Release
					(2011). Available at: <ref
						target="http://nt2.uqam.ca/en/repertoire/la-fondation-daniel-langlois"
						>http://nt2.uqam.ca/en/repertoire/la-fondation-daniel-langlois</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="deleuze1988" label="Deleuze 1988"> Deleuze, Gilles. (1988) <title rend="italic">Bergonism</title>. Princeton:
					Zone Books.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="diamondbattershill2021" label="Diamond-Battershill Chat 2021">Project Endings Symposium, April 16, 2021.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="diamond2021" label="Diamond Q &amp; A 2021">Project Endings Symposium, April 16, 2021.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fatona2021" label="Fatona 2021"> Fatona, A. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Digging us: making visible Black Canadian
					narratives</title> in Crooks, J., Fontaine, D. &amp; Forni, S. (eds.), <title rend="italic">History, art,
					and Blackness</title>. McGill-Queen’s University Press. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hall2004" label="Hall 2004">Foster, Hal. (2004) <title rend="quotes">An Archival Impulse</title>, <title rend="italics">October</title> 110, Fall 2004,
					pp. 3–22.<title rend="italic"> © 2004 Hal Foster</title>.
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="foucault1969" label="Foucault 1969">Foucault, Michel (1969). <title rend="italic">The Archaeology of
						Knowledge</title>. Trans. A. M. Sheridan
							Smith. London and New York: Routledge, 2002. ISBN 0-415-28753-7.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gagnon2001" label="Gagnon 2001">Gagnon, Jean. (2001) Consumption: Jean Gagnon Presentation, CRUMB
					Seminar Presentation. Available at: <ref
						target="http://www.crumbweb.org/getPresentation.php?presID=19&amp;op=4&amp;sublink=&amp;fromSearch=1"
						>http://www.crumbweb.org/getPresentation.php?presID=19&amp;op=4&amp;sublink=&amp;fromSearch=1</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gagnon2021" label="Gagnon 2021"> Gagnon, Jean (2021) <title rend="quotes">Interview with Sara Diamond</title>. Zoom, March 2021. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gerrard2013" label="Gerrard 2013">Gerrard, Richard. (2013) An Introduction to the Deaccession and
					Disposal of Collections. Ontario Museums Association. Available at:
					<ref target="https://members.museumsontario.ca/sites/default/files/members/AnIntroductionToTheDeaccessionAndDisposalOfCollections29May2013.pdf">https://members.museumsontario.ca/sites/default/files/members/AnIntroductionToTheDeaccessionAndDisposalOfCollections29May2013.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="grau2019" label="Grau, Hoth, Wandl-Vogt 2019">Grau, Oliver, Hoth, Janina &amp; Wandl-Vogt, Eveline (eds.).
					(2019) <title rend="italic">Digital Art through the Looking Glass: New strategies
						for archiving, collecting and preserving in digital humanities</title>.
					Austria: Edition Donau-Universität. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="harris2019" label="Harris &amp; Harris 2019"> Harris, K. &amp; Harris, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Data visualization
					tools for archives and special collections</title>, <title rend="italic">MAC
						Newsletter</title>, pp. 26–29. Available at:  <ref target="https:/ecommons.udayton.edu/imri_faculty
							_publications/39">https:/ecommons.udayton.edu/imri_faculty
					_publications/39</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hoth2021" label="Hoth 2021">Hoth, Janina. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Databases and the Representation of Knowledge</title>,
					<title rend="italic">ADA Net, Media Art Research Thesaurus</title>. Available at:  <ref
						target="http://mediaartresearch.org/analysis.html"
						>http://mediaartresearch.org/analysis.html</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hoth2019" label="Hoth 2019">Hoth, Janina. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Historicization in the Archive: Digital art and
					originality</title>.  In Grau, Oliver, Hoth, Janina &amp;
					Wandl-Vogt, eds. (2019) <title rend="italic">Digital Art through the Looking Glass:
						New strategies for archiving, collecting and preserving in digital
						humanities</title>. Austria: Edition Donau-Universität. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kennedy2021" label="Kennedy 2021">Kennedy, Jen. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Across the Nebraska Border and the
					virtual-material divide: contextualizing Shu Lea Cheang’s Brandon, 1994–1999</title>,
					In <title rend="italic">International Journal of Performance Arts and Digital Media</title>, 17(2):
						Affiliated Issue with 2020 <title rend="italic">College Art Association Annual Conference</title> Panel <title rend="quotes">Flesh and Circuit: Rethinking Performance and Technology</title> (Chicago,
						IL, USA), Guest Editors: Conor McGarrigle and EL Putnam.
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="langill2006" label="Langill 2006"> Langill, Caroline (2006)
					<title rend="italic">Shifting Polarities: Proposing a Canon of Canadian
						Electronic Media Art, 1970-1990</title>. Available at:
					<ref target="https://www.fondation-langlois.org/html/e/page.php?NumPage=742">https://www.fondation-langlois.org/html/e/page.php?NumPage=742</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="larson2020" label="Lar-Son 2020"> Lar-Son, Kayla. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Archival Appraisal and Deaccessioning</title>,
					<title rend="italic">Indigitization – Tools for Digitizing and Sustaining Indigenous Knowledge</title>. Available at:  <ref
						target="https://www.indigenization.ca/"
						>https://www.indigenization.ca</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lacinematheque2011" label="La Cinémathèque québécoise et la fondation Daniel Langlois 2011">Daniel Langlois Foundation. (2011), <title rend="quotes">La
					Cinémathèque québécoise et la fondation Daniel Langlois ont conclu uneentente
					permettant ainsi d'assurer la conservation et l'accessibilité de la collection
					de la foundation</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.cinematheque.qc.ca/en/collections/daniel-langlois-fondation/"
						>https://www.cinematheque.qc.ca/en/collections/daniel-langlois-fondation/</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="muntadas1994" label="Muntadas 1994 – present">Muntadas, Antonio (1994 – present). Available at: <ref
					target="http://www.medienkunstnetz.de/works/the-file-room/"
					>http://www.medienkunstnetz.de/works/the-file-room/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="nass2014" label="Nass 2014">Nass, M. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Derrida's Preoccupation with the Archive in ‘The
					Beast and the Sovereign’</title>, <title rend="italic">SubStance</title>: 43(2), ISSUE 134: <title rend="italic">Fabled
						Thought: On Jacques Derrida's <title rend="italic">The Beast &amp; the Sovereign</title></title>, pp. 20–36.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ora2014" label="Oxford Research Archives 2014">ORA. (2014) <title rend="quotes">ORA deposit license</title>. <title rend="italic">Version</title> 5:27
					November 2014.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sadharwal2021" label="Sabharwal 2021"> Sabharwal, A. (2021). <title rend="quotes">Functional frameworks for socialized
					digital curation: Curatorial interventions and curation spaces in archives and
					libraries</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title>, 69(3), pp. 672–695. Project MUSE,
					DOI: 10.1353/lib.2021.009.
				</bibl>
				
				<bibl xml:id="simonsen2013" label="Simonsen &amp; Robertson 2013">Simonsen, Jasper, and Robertson, Toni. (2013) <title rend="italics">International Handbook of Participatory Design</title>. Routledge.</bibl>
				
				<bibl xml:id="smith2020" label="Smith 2020">Smith, Madelaine Page. (2020) <title rend="italic">Caring for the Moving
					Image in Art Museums: Matters in Media Art and the Stewardship of
					Time-Based Media Artworks</title>. Thesis Department of Cinema Studies New
					York University.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="smith2017" label="Smith, Bossen &amp; Kanstrup 2017"> Smith, R. C., Bossen, C., &amp; Kanstrup, A. M.
					(2017) <title rend="quotes">Participatory design in an era of participation</title>, <title rend="italics">CoDesign</title>, 13(2), pp.
					65–69. DOI: 10.1080/15710882.2017.1310466.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="society2017" label="Society of American Archivists 2017">Society of American Archivists (2017)
					<title rend="italic">Guidelines for Reappraisal and Deaccessioning</title>, Revised by the Technical Subcommittee on Guidelines for Reappraisal and Deaccessioning, and approved by the SAA Council. Available at: <ptr target="https://www2.archivists.org/sites/all/files/GuidelinesForReappraisalDeaccessioning_2017.pdf"/>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="eastanglia2022" label="University of East Anglia 2022">University of East Anglia. 2022. Available at: 
					<ref target="https://www.uea.ac.uk/library/british-archive-for-contemporary-writing/about-us">https://www.uea.ac.uk/library/british-archive-for-contemporary-writing/about-us</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="vivo2021" label="VIVO Media Arts Centre 2021"> VIVO Media Arts Centre 2021. Available at:  <ref target="https://www.vivomediaarts.com/"
					>https://www.vivomediaarts.com/</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="whibley2019" label="Whibley, Sara 2019">Whibley, Sara. (2019) Week 2 – Collection Strategy and the
					Storehouse Model at the British Archive for Contemporary Writing. Available at:
					<ref target="https://archivecultureclub.wordpress.com/2019/02/10/week-2-collection-strategy-and-the-storehouse-model-at-the-british-archive-for-contemporary-writing/">https://archivecultureclub.wordpress.com/2019/02/10/week-2-collection-strategy-and-the-storehouse-model-at-the-british-archive-for-contemporary-writing/</ref>.
				</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
