<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Critical Collection History of Nineteenth-century
               Women’s Letters: Overcoming the Occluded Archive with Data-Driven
               Methods<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Ilona <dhq:family>Pikkanen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9435-7163<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>The Finnish Literature Society</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ilonapikkanen@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ilona Pikkanen is a senior researcher in the Research Department at the Finnish
                     Literature Society. A historian specialising in nineteenth-century historical
                     culture and historiographical narratology, she is also the coordinator of the
                     Finnish Network of Nineteenth-Century Studies. Since 2017, she has also
                     participated in the Helsinki Digital Humanities Hackathons. She is the
                     Principal Investigator of the digital humanities consortium project <hi
                        rend="italic">Constellations of Correspondence: Large and Small Networks of
                        Epistolary Exchange in the Grand Duchy of Finland</hi> (2021–2025), which is
                     funded by the Research Council of Finland.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Matti <dhq:family>La Mela</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0340-9269<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Uppsala University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>matti.lamela@abm.uu.se</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Matti La Mela is an Associate Professor (docent) in Digital Humanities at the
                     Department of ALM, Uppsala University. La Mela’s background is in social
                     science history, and he has broad experience in multidisciplinary digital
                     humanities research. His current research regards digital history of patents,
                     innovation, and access rights to nature, involving the digitisation of
                     historical source materials from the 19th and 20th centuries. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Hanna-Leena <dhq:family>Paloposki</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1412-8622<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>hannaleena.paloposki@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Hanna-Leena Paloposki is an art historian who specialises in the networks of
                     nineteenth-century artists, transnational cultural relations and exhibition
                     studies. She has worked at the Finnish Literature Society as a researcher and
                     data expert on the digital humanities consortium project <hi rend="italic"
                        >Constellations of Correspondence: Large and Small Networks of Epistolary
                        Exchange in the Grand Duchy of Finland</hi> (2021–2025), which is funded by
                     the Research Council of Finland. She also has extensive experience of working
                     with collections management and archival collections at the Finnish National
                     Gallery.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jouni <dhq:family>Tuominen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4789-5676<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Helsinki and Aalto University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jouni.tuominen@helsinki.fi</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jouni Tuominen is a university researcher at the University of Helsinki,
                     Helsinki Institute for Social Sciences and Humanities (HSSH). He is a computer
                     scientist specialized in ontology repositories and services, linked data
                     publishing methods, ontology models for legacy data, and tooling for digital
                     humanities. He has worked in multidisciplinary research projects on cultural
                     heritage, history, archeology, parliamentary data, and legal data, and
                     collaborated with museums, libraries, and archives on their collection
                     cataloging and cultural heritage data publishing processes since 2007. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp="#history"/>
               <term corresp="#archives"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Critical Collection History</item>
                  <item>Archives</item>
                  <item>Semantic Web Technologies</item>
                  <item>Women’s History</item>
                  <item>Cultural Heritage Institutions</item>
                  <item>Historical Correspondence</item>
                  <item>Networks</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000791/000791.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This paper presents a “virtual archive” of women’s epistolary exchange in
               19th-century Finland. By harmonising metadata from over 1.2 million letters and over
               100,000 correspondents across key cultural heritage organisations and leveraging
               linked open data, we gain an unprecedented view of 19th-century epistolary
               communication and 20th-century archival practices. Using quantitative analysis,
               enriched metadata, and network visualisations, we explore the gendered nature of
               these collections. Are women archival protagonists, or are their materials embedded
               within the collections of male relatives? Do the data reveal overlooked women with
               extensive archival networks absent from historical narratives? We introduce the
               framework of “critical collection history,” which combines theoretical debates and
               research interests from critical archival studies and digital history and combines
               them with contemporary digital methods. This approach underscores the necessity for
               scholars using data-driven methods in historical research to critically engage with
               digitised archives. Moreover, critical collection history highlights how “big
               cultural heritage metadata” can expose archival biases and enhance our understanding
               of source limitations – biases that digital scholarship may unintentionally
               perpetuate.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Who gets remembered in the archives? This article explores how 1.2 million letters
               reveal hidden networks of 19th-century Finnish women — and what their traces (or
               absence) say about history, memory, and digital methods.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1 Introduction</head>
            <p>A few years ago, we contacted the key cultural heritage organisations in Finland and
               asked what we thought was a simple question touching on central historical source
               material: ‘How many nineteenth-century letters do you have in your collections?’ The
               answer was simple, though not quite what we expected: ‘There is no way of knowing.’
               This means that neither the organisations nor the humanities scholars who regularly
               use these materials have a comprehensive view of the extent or basic structural
               characteristics of these collections. Consequently, we cannot assess their inherent
               biases or distortions, nor can we evaluate the representativeness of the collections
               in relation to nineteenth-century ‘epistolary cultures’.</p>
            <p>A reasonable follow-up question is why information about archived material is
               important. After all, scholars have successfully used the contents of epistolary
               collections to answer a wide variety of historical research questions since the
               establishment of national and other archival institutions and the development of
               historical methods based on primary sources. A lack of interest in the ‘logics’ or
               ‘ethnographies’ (Dirks, 2002) of complete archival collections is likely due to
               hermeneutic and microhistorical research interests among scholars immersed in
               historical epistolary exchange. It is also due to the difficulty of obtaining
               accurate and comparable quantitative data on vast and diverse materials accumulated
               over decades or even centuries and catalogued in astonishingly diverse ways. However,
               when combined with the latest digital humanities technologies, collection-level
               archival metadata offers untapped potential for historical enquiry.</p>
            <p>In this paper, we suggest that the research agenda of digital historians should be
               expanded to include questions about the composition of archival collections. We
               analyse a new digital archive constructed by combining letter metadata (e.g.
               information about senders, recipients, dates and quantities of letters) from
               databases, finding aids and archival catalogues of person and family archives held in
               various Finnish cultural heritage organisations. This ‘big metadata’ (Enqvist &amp;
               Pikkanen, 2024) transcends organisational boundaries, enabling us to obtain
               quantifiable and comparable information about the collections. When we transform it
               into linked open data and connect it to external sources, such as biographical and
               other datasets and ontologies, we can enrich the data with categories not present in
               the archival metadata, such as the gender of letter writers and recipients. This
               allows us to observe relations that are simply not detectable in traditional archives
               of printed finding aids or organisational archival databases.</p>
            <p>This paper argues that a fruitful intersection exists between digital humanities,
               computational humanities, and critical archival studies, which we refer to as
               ‘critical collection history’. While it may be possible to conduct such research
               using traditional methods, we aim to demonstrate that, at its most effective and
               ambitious, critical collection history is digital collection history. Repurposing
               information stored in archival finding aids and other repositories of archival
               metadata using computational methods provides us with an unprecedented and powerful
               tool with which to explore the interplay between historical source criticism and the
               archival politics of inclusion and exclusion (Whose materials are preserved by
               cultural heritage organisations and made available for scholarly and other
               purposes?). This approach also allows us to gain new perspectives on the interaction
               of historical actors within past contexts.</p>
            <p>There is a well-established international scholarly tradition of compiling and
               editing carefully curated collections of correspondence. In the last 15 years, such
               data have been published as digital research resources and, in many cases, as linked
               open data. Projects such as the EU-funded large-scale Reassembling the Republic of
               Letters (RRL), the Dutch Circulation of Knowledge and Learned Practices in the
               17th-century Dutch Republic (CKCC) and the German correspondence metadata aggregator
               correspSearch, mainly focus on the epistolary materials of learned men, because
               traditional epistolary editions have centred on this group.</p>
            <p>Our material allows us to adopt a more comprehensive perspective. In what follows, we
               will address the gendered aspects of nineteenth-century epistolary collections in
               Finland. We are particularly interested in the traces that nineteenth-century women
               left in archival collections. The nineteenth century has been characterised as the
               golden age of letter writing (Lahtinen et al., 2011) and women have been identified
               as the main protagonists of this development (Monagle et al., 2023). Does
               quantitative analysis of the collected epistolary metadata confirm these qualitative
               findings? Based on our data, did women play a prominent role in epistolary
               communication? Do they ‘own’ their collections and archives? By delving into the
               collected metadata, can we find individuals who are not part of our current scholarly
               canon? Throughout the paper, we will revisit a broader question: Does the material
               tell us more about twentieth-century archival practices or particular developments in
               nineteenth-century society?</p>
            <p>Compared to previous publications of linked open data on epistolary metadata, there
               are certain methodological and interpretative difficulties associated with the use of
               large collections of metadata gathered directly (‘bottom-up’) from cultural heritage
               organisations. The primary challenges pertain to the commensurability of the archival
               collections themselves and the validation of the results. There are no comparable
               epistolary metadata datasets that we can use to measure the significance and/or
               Finnish and nineteenth-century specificity of our findings. The best approach is to
               use the entire dataset to provide context and calibration for its constituent parts
               (i.e. different organisational or thematic collections), and vice versa.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2 Literature Review</head>
            <p>The rapid expansion of big data and digital humanities since the early 2000s has
               emphasised the importance of understanding the shape or contours of (digital)
               archives and corpora. The research framework proposed in this paper is similar to
               recent studies that have examined the ‘anatomies’ of historical data collections and
               the processes involved in their creation, both before and during digitisation (e.g.
               Tolonen, Mäkelä, and Lahti, 2022; Beelen et al., 2023; Ortolja-Baird and Nyhan,
               2022). It has been suggested that large digital datasets require a new kind of
               critical attitude; those who produce and use such data must pay particular attention
               to its local context: how it was acquired and prepared, its strengths and weaknesses,
               and whether it is fit for purpose (Loukissas, 2019, pp. 8, 195; Ahnert et al., 2020,
               pp. 54–55). At the same time, it has been recognised that much digitised historical
               material can be analysed using computational methods. Indeed, quantitative analysis
               is particularly effective when we want to interrogate the characteristics,
               structures, and properties of digital archives and collections and reflect on the
               relationship between datasets and the phenomena they represent or model (Hyvönen et
               al., 2021, p. 53; Guldi, 2023, p. 29; Bode, 2020, pp. 4–5).</p>
            <p>Over the past few decades, researchers in archival and cultural studies have been
               addressing the same questions, albeit mostly in the context of analogue archives,
               close-reading individual collections. Since the archival turn of the 1990s and early
               2000s, there has been growing interest in analysing the processes involved in
               creating, organising, appraising, and describing archival holdings, as well as the
               ways in which these processes reproduce and/or challenge existing hierarchies,
               dominant discourses, and ideologies (Edquist, 2021, p. 109; see also Schwartz and
               Cook, 2002; Taavetti, 2016; Ketelaar, 2017; Mikkola, Olsson, and Stark, 2019).
               Critical archival studies pay attention to the processes prior to the possibility of
               digitisation. Like critical theory on a wider social scale, these studies are
               emancipatory in nature (Caswell et al., 2017, p. 2). They seek to highlight
               injustices in current archival research and practice, offering recommendations for
               improvement. As with researchers working with large digital corpora, the importance
               of analysing the logics, classification systems and exclusions of archival
               collections has been emphasised (Dirks, 2002). Recently, digital techniques have
               emerged for studying curatorial practices and the historical and cultural context of
               museum curation and archival appraisal (e.g. Salway and Baker, 2020; van Lange, van
               Nispent, and Keijzer, 2022; Enqvist and Pikkanen, 2024). Paradigmatic quantitative
               studies of letter collections are the results of the aforementioned RRL project (e.g.
               Hotson and Wallnig, 2019), as well as various case studies that use network analysis
               (e.g. Ahnert and Ahnert, 2019).</p>
            <p>3 Description of dataset</p>
            <p>Our study uses information from letter catalogues and databases from the Grand Duchy
               of Finland (1809–1917). However, as sets of correspondence often extend beyond the
               designated end year of 1917, we have also included these data where available.<note>
                  The data has been collected and processed in the digital humanities consortium
                  project Constellations of Correspondence: Large and Small Networks of Epistolary
                  Exchange in the Grand Duchy of Finland (2021–2025), funded by the Research Council
                  of Finland (decision numbers 339828, 340834 and 339918).</note> The dataset is
               available online<note> The dataset has been published on Zenodo: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15210589"
                     >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15210589</ref>.</note>, ‘upcycling’ these
               collections for reuse as FAIR data for research, as suggested by Scheltjens (2023).
               The current version of the dataset comprises around 1.2 million letters featuring
               approximately 114,052 unique actors (senders and recipients) from nine organisations
               and four digital editions (see Table 1)<note> The dataset does not include archives
                  from public entities, as these were excluded from the data collection process due
                  to project resource constraints.</note>.</p>
            <p>Letter catalogues have also been used to create datasets in various other projects.
               The information in these catalogues varies considerably (see Kudella, 2019, for more
               on modelling in the RRL project, for example). In our case, the archival metadata
               includes basic information about the senders and recipients (whether individuals,
               groups, or families). While dates are often clearly delineated in some well-curated
               collections, more often than not, they are given as the span of a set of
               correspondence (e.g., 25 letters between 1870–1895). Beyond archival organisations,
               we have knowledge of the archival collections in which the letters are held. In
               Finnish cultural heritage organisations, personal materials, including letters, are
               organised in separate ‘collections’, or ‘archives’ as they are usually called. In the
               Anglophone world, such collections are often referred to as ‘papers’ (for example,
               ‘the Cecil Papers’, referring to a collection gathered by William Cecil (1520–1598)
               and his son, Robert Cecil (1563–1612)). However, to avoid conceptual confusion
               between organisations and their collections, the term ‘fonds’ will be used when
               discussing a body of records created and accumulated organically, reflecting the
               functions of its creator (Fonds, 2024).</p>
            <table>
               <head>Number of letters and actors (metadata) in the dataset extracted from the
                  letter catalogues of the cultural heritage organisations. Source: The Constellations
                  of Correspondence (CoCo) dataset (19 February 2025). The actors in different
                  organisations are partly overlapping. *The number includes actors retrieved also from
                  the letter content.</head>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Cultural Heritage Organisation</cell>
                  <cell>Years covered (within 1809-1917)</cell>
                  <cell>Letters and actors in the dataset</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Åbo Akademi University Library</cell>
                  <cell>1809–1917</cell>
                  <cell>366 614 / 27 299</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Albert Edelfelts brev (Albert Edelfelt’s Letters, SLS) </cell>
                  <cell>1867–1901</cell>
                  <cell>1310 / 5774</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Elias Lönnrot Letters (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>1823–1887</cell>
                  <cell>6296 / 1117</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Finnish National Gallery</cell>
                  <cell>1809–1917</cell>
                  <cell>11 092 / 2901</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gallen-Kallela Museum</cell>
                  <cell>1895–1914</cell>
                  <cell>144 / 4</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>J. W. Snellman, kirjeet (J. W. Snellman Letters) </cell>
                  <cell>1826–1881</cell>
                  <cell>1563 / 4733*</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>The Migration Institute of Finland</cell>
                  <cell>1881–1917</cell>
                  <cell>359 / 35</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>The National Archives of Finland</cell>
                  <cell>1809–1917</cell>
                  <cell>292 073 / 32 372</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>The National Library of Finland</cell>
                  <cell>1809–1917</cell>
                  <cell>281 157 / 33 746</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Serlachius Museums </cell>
                  <cell>1883–1899</cell>
                  <cell>411 / 136</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>The Society of Swedish Literature in Finland (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>1862–1917</cell>
                  <cell>175 990 / 13 762</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>The Finnish Literature Society (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>1809–1917</cell>
                  <cell>108 157 / 13 256</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Zacharius Topelius Skrifter (Zacharias Topelius Writings, SLS) </cell>
                  <cell>1829–1898</cell>
                  <cell>1407 / 71</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Total</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>1 246 573 / 114 052 (unique)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The metadata are transformed into linked open data by an automatic transformation
               pipeline (see Drobac et al., 2023b for a detailed description). The resulting data
               model builds on international standards, such as CIDOC CRM (Doerr, 2003), Dublin Core
               and ICA Records in Contexts, to promote interoperability with other datasets. The
               data model aims to facilitate the modelling of relevant metadata properties collected
               from source datasets. The most central classes in the current data model are
               ‘Letter’, ‘Actor’, ‘Place’, and ‘Time-Span’. Provenance (the MetadataRecord class)
               and archival/collection-level information (the Series, Fonds, and Organisation
               classes) are also included.</p>
            <p>To represent actors (senders and recipients of a letter) in different source
               datasets, we use an adapted version of the proxy concept from the Open Archives
               initiative Object Reuse and Exchange (OAI-ORE) specification. In our case, a proxy
               signifies a particular viewpoint on a person or group within a designated source. In
               the harmonisation process, proxies that are identified (through
               deduplication/disambiguation workflow (Drobac, Leskinen, and Wahjoe, 2023a), matching
               based on a trained probabilistic data linkage Splink model<note> See information on
                  the Splink Python package: <ref
                     target="https://moj-analytical-services.github.io/splink/index.html"
                     >https://moj-analytical-services.github.io/splink/index.html</ref>
               </note>) to represent the same person or group are linked through a shared instance
               of the class ProvidedActor. This class is an adaptation of the Europeana Data Model’s
               (Doerr et al., 2010) class ProvidedCHO (Provided Cultural Heritage Object). In
               Europeana, the ProvidedCHO ‘represents the Cultural Heritage Object that Europeana
               collects descriptions about’. In practice, a proxy represents a ‘local’, or
               source-specific, view of an actor (with metadata ingested from that source), whereas
               a ProvidedActor represents a ‘global’ view of the actor by assembling all the
               information about the actor from various sources. The core classes and properties of
               the data model are presented in Table 2.</p>
            <table>
               <head>The core classes and properties of the CoCo data model.</head>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Property URI</cell>
                  <cell>C</cell>
                  <cell>Range</cell>
                  <cell>Description</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>LETTER (:Letter)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:was_authored_by</cell>
                  <cell>1..n</cell>
                  <cell>:ActorProxy</cell>
                  <cell>Sender/creator of the letter</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:was_addressed_to</cell>
                  <cell>1..n</cell>
                  <cell>:ActorProxy</cell>
                  <cell>Recipient of the letter</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:has_time-span</cell>
                  <cell>0..n</cell>
                  <cell>crm:E52_Time-Span</cell>
                  <cell>Time of sending</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:was_sent_from</cell>
                  <cell>0..n</cell>
                  <cell>:PlaceProxy</cell>
                  <cell>Place of sending</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:was_sent_to</cell>
                  <cell>0..n</cell>
                  <cell>:PlaceProxy</cell>
                  <cell>Place of receiving</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:type</cell>
                  <cell>0..n</cell>
                  <cell>:LetterType</cell>
                  <cell>Type, e.g., letter, telegram</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:series</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>:Series</cell>
                  <cell>Series the letter is part of</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:fonds</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>:Fonds</cell>
                  <cell>Archival collection the letter is part of</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:archival_organization</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>:Organization</cell>
                  <cell>The organisation that has archived the letter</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>dct:source</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>:Source</cell>
                  <cell>Data source</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:metadata</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>:MetadataRecord</cell>
                  <cell>Original metadata record</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>METADATA RECORD (:MetadataRecord)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:original_record</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Datasheet row or document paragraph as in source data</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:number_of_letters</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Integer, can be interpreted (e.g. "[[1]]")</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>ACTOR PROXY (:ActorProxy)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>rdf:type</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>rdfs:Class</cell>
                  <cell>:PersonProxy, :GroupProxy, ...</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:floruit</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>crm:E52_Time-Span</cell>
                  <cell>Time of Flourishing</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:proxy_for</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>:ProvidedActor</cell>
                  <cell>The provided actor that connects different proxies</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PROVIDED ACTOR (:ProvidedActor)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>rdf:type</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>rdfs:Class</cell>
                  <cell>:ProvidedPerson, :ProvidedGroup, ...</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>crm:P98i_was_born</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>crm:E67_Birth</cell>
                  <cell>Birth event (time, place)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>crm:P100i_died_in</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>crm:E69_Death</cell>
                  <cell>Death event (time, place)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>bioc:has_gender</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>schema:Gender</cell>
                  <cell>Gender</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>bioc:has_occupation</cell>
                  <cell>0...n</cell>
                  <cell>bioc:Occupation</cell>
                  <cell>Occupation</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>bioc:has_person_relation</cell>
                  <cell>0...n</cell>
                  <cell>bioc:Person_Relationship_Role</cell>
                  <cell>Relation to other person (in role)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PLACE PROXY (:PlaceProxy)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:proxy_for</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>:ProvidedPlace</cell>
                  <cell>The provided place that connects different proxies</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>PROVIDED PLACE (:ProvidedPlace)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>crm:P89_falls_within</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>:ProvidedPlace</cell>
                  <cell>Place higher in hierarchy</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>geo:lat</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:decimal</cell>
                  <cell>Latitude of the coordinates</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>geo:long</cell>
                  <cell>0..1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:decimal</cell>
                  <cell>Longitude of the coordinates</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>FONDS (:Fonds)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>skos:prefLabel</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>xsd:string</cell>
                  <cell>Preferable label</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:archival_organization</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>:Organization</cell>
                  <cell>The organisation that has formed the fonds</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>:records_creator</cell>
                  <cell>0..n</cell>
                  <cell>:ActorProxy</cell>
                  <cell>Records creator</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4 Methodology</head>
            <p>Our study is based on the availability of epistolary metadata as Linked Open Data
               (LOD). Having transformed the metadata collected from various cultural heritage
               organisations into a harmonised data model, we can analyse the resulting dataset as a
               whole, while taking into account the differences in archival practices between the
               organisations that provided us with data. As illustrated in Figure 1, our research
               can be extended from examining a single collection or the collections of a single
               archival organisation to exploring the combined dataset (or union catalogue), thereby
               capitalising on the inherent links between collections and organisations.</p>
            <p>Figure 1 shows how many person-actors the different organisations have in common.
               Making the data available in a machine-readable, structured format (RDF) and in a
               SPARQL endpoint means that we have a multidimensional dataset that enables evolving
               historical research questions and allows us to query the data in rich and meaningful
               ways. Linking the data entities (e.g. person-actors) to external sources enriches the
               dataset with contextual information, providing ways to obtain details such as the
               biographical background of the people in the dataset. At the same time, possible
               links to external data sources, such as the National Biography of Finland or
               Wikidata, indicate that the person in question is recognised as relevant, at least
               from today’s perspective. The data for the studies reported in this paper were
               generated by formulating SPARQL queries to select subsets of the dataset. </p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image9.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 1. Shared person-actors between the archival organisations. Source: CoCo
               dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The size of the edges represents but is not
               proportional to the amount of shared person-actors. The edge labels describe the
               amount of shared person-actors between the two organisations. The graph includes
               organisations with at least 10 shared person-actors.</p>
            <p>In addition to SPARQL queries, we use the LetterSampo Finland semantic portal<note>
                  The portal is available online: LetterSampo Finland. Finnish Nineteenth-Century
                  Letters on the Semantic Web: <ref target="https://kirjesampo.fi/en/"
                     >https://kirjesampo.fi/en/</ref>.</note>. Based on the Sampo model (Hyvönen,
               2022), the portal is implemented using the Sampo-UI programming framework (Ikkala et
               al., 2022). It allows users to search, browse and analyse letters, actors (people and
               organisations), archival organisations and collections (fonds), and places in the
               dataset. The interface is based on the faceted search paradigm (Tunkelang, 2009) and
               enables users to search for letters from a specific time period, sent by a particular
               person and archived by a particular organisation, for example. Visualisations include
               the yearly distribution of letters, top correspondents, and correspondence networks.
               Data including letter-sending locations can be visualised on a map.</p>
            <p>Some cultural heritage organisations have built up their collections over decades or
               even centuries, during which time cataloguing practices, descriptive concepts and
               standards have changed. In some cases, the material was initially handled by
               non-specialists. Combined with the creative individualism of archivists, this has
               resulted in a wide variety of finding aid formats, presenting one of the challenges
               of data modelling work and transforming letter catalogues into machine-readable data.
               The solution is to engage in continuous dialogue about humanistic knowledge interests
               and the emerging data model. A linked open data solution has proven suitable for
               modelling cultural heritage metadata relating to archives and historical figures.
               However, perhaps even more important is the way in which the modelling process forces
               us to consider the ‘things’ being modelled. What are the catalogued collections of
               letters, and how can we conceptualise phenomena such as epistolary culture? As
               Arianna Ciula et al. (2018, p. 345) write, models can be learnt from ‘at two
               different stages, in the creation of the model and in its application and successive
               manipulation’. In the case of epistolary metadata, modelling the letter collections
               has led us to focus on specific aspects of the collections themselves.</p>
            <p>In addition to the properties provided by the linked data, we use network analysis to
               construct specific correspondence networks. These networks illustrate changes in
               women’s centrality over time, helping us to visualise the gendered structure of
               nineteenth-century archival collections. Our focus is on contacts established through
               correspondence rather than on the direction of interaction through letter-writing.
               The main reason for this is the partiality of our collections (more on this below).
               The intention behind these network visualisations is not to examine how the network
               functions, but rather to offer an alternative viewpoint on the women in our
               collection data through their interconnectedness. The layout used is a force-directed
               model, meaning that the most important nodes in terms of connectivity remain at the
               centre of the network. Although our primary focus is on the networks as collections,
               we also highlight other themes relating to nineteenth-century women’s historical
               correspondence as reflected in our dataset.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5 Case study</head>
            <p>One way to challenge the boundaries of archival organisations and their collections
               is to create a virtual collection of metadata relating to women’s letters. We will
               proceed in three steps, firstly discussing the quantitative results in terms of the
               total number of women actors and women as so-called records creators, then examining
               the ten most active women in terms of letters, and finally exploring the position of
               women in specific correspondence networks over time. Our findings will be
               contextualised in relation to archival practices, scholarly focus, and the
               modernisation of nineteenth-century society. Finally, we will assess the
               representativeness of our dataset as a whole. To this end, the Åbo Akademi University
               Library and the Finnish Literature Society will serve as sample datasets and main
               points of comparison. These organisations have exceptional collections covering
               different geographical regions and representing the two national languages, Swedish
               and Finnish.</p>
            <p>The current dataset comprises 114,052 actors, 24.1% of whom are female. While this
               figure is higher than that observed in previous European projects, it is less
               pronounced than expected based on research emphasising that women’s epistolary
               activity peaked in the nineteenth century (Monagle et al., 2023). However, when we
               filter out groups and administrative units, and consider all person-actors in the
               dataset, the percentage of female actors rises to 29%. In the Åbo Akademi data, the
               proportion of female actors is 31.7%, and in the Finnish Literature Society data, it
               is 32.5%. Furthermore, of the 1,246,573 letters, on average 38% were sent by women
               (alone or together with someone), and the corresponding percentage of letters
               received was 36%.</p>
            <p>In addition to examining the characteristics of the entire pool of person-actors,
               collecting and enriching epistolary metadata gives us access to another class of
               actors. In archival parlance, these are known as ‘records creators’ or ‘entities of
               origin’. These are individuals, families, corporations or administrative units that
               ‘create, receive or accumulate a body of records, personal papers or objects’
               (Entity, 2024). Their names are usually found in catalogue headings and indexes of
               letter collections. Archival fonds contain letters received by such entities, but
               often also letters sent by them. These may be copies kept by the entity or originals
               added to the collection at a later date. Often, there are also letters sent and
               received by other entities that may have had a family or other connection with the
               original records creator. The Finnish Literature Society provides a basic list of
               records creators on its website to serve as an entry point to its epistolary
               material. In contrast, the Åbo Akademi University Library provides online access both
               to its epistolary database and the database of records creators; however, it remains
               difficult to find and combine information about actors who are not records creators,
               even if they had extensive collections.</p>
            <p>By comparing the total dataset of person-actors with that of records creators, we can
               see that the status of records creator is granted to a select few. Although the
               number of actors varies greatly between our two sample organisations, only around 2%
               of them are also records creators in both cases. In the case of the Åbo Akademi, we
               can see that the gender of records creators is relatively close to that of the
               overall actor data, but it is significantly higher in the Finnish Literature
               Society’s collections (37.5% female). By contrast, the National Library of Finland
               has a very ‘masculine’ catalogue of epistolary fonds: 85% of records creators are
               men, with only 14.6% being women. These differences can be explained by the archival
               policies and constituencies of these organisations. The Åbo Akademi University in
               Turku was founded in 1919 to serve the Swedish-speaking minority in newly independent
               Finland. Its collections include materials representing the old Swedish-speaking
               aristocracy and intelligentsia — the country’s early political and cultural elite. In
               contrast, the Finnish Literature Society, founded in 1831, has a very different
               profile. Its collections reflect the ideas of nineteenth-century Finnish-language
               nationalists in the fields of folklore studies and Finnish language and literature.
               The collections include the personal archives of literary writers, translators,
               literary critics, and others. Through the National Library’s connection to the
               University of Helsinki, professors, researchers, and other academics are well
               represented in the library’s archival collections as professional groups.</p>
            <p>​​Linking to external data sources provides additional insight into the actors and
               records creators, as well as the general characteristics of the entire dataset. Only
               19% of all actors can be enriched with information provided by links to databases and
               repositories of historical narratives that can be captured with digital methods.
               However, these individuals are responsible for 85% of all letters. This means that we
               have a very prominent group of individuals who have left an extensive trace of
               themselves in the form of letters and other personal papers, despite being few in
               number, and a large number of individuals with few letters and connections. Such
               ‘long tails’ have been observed in other epistolary collections of a different nature
               (Ahnert and Ahnert, 2019, p. 31). When it comes to the narrower group of records
               creators, however, about 80% of them can be linked to external resources, suggesting
               a continuing scholarly interest in them. Collected lists of records creators can
               therefore serve as a kind of ‘who’s who’ of nineteenth-century Finland and
               nineteenth-century studies. The collections of prominent records creators have also
               preserved the correspondence of individuals who would otherwise have left little or
               no archival trace.</p>
            <p>Thus, we can see that nineteenth-century epistolary collections in general, and the
               group of records creators in particular, are dominated by literate elites and the
               middle classes. This is consistent with what we know about the development of
               literacy in this north-eastern corner of Europe. At the beginning of the nineteenth
               century, writing skills were still rare, despite the fact that half of all Finns
               could read. It was not until the introduction of primary schools in the 1860s that
               literacy and text comprehension really began to spread. Statistics from the
               Evangelical Lutheran Church indicate that, by 1880, 86.3% of the population could
               read, though only 12.4% were literate. By 1900, the literacy rate had risen to 38.6%,
               reaching 55.3% ten years later. (Latomaa and Nuolijärvi, 2002). The educated elite
               and middle classes also appear to have taken care to preserve their correspondence in
               personal, family and manor archives. These archives were transferred to cultural
               heritage organisations when they began collecting private archival material in the
               late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.</p>
            <p>These organisations operate under the principle of provenance (<hi rend="italic"
                  >respect des fonds</hi>), which emphasises preserving records according to their
               origin and within the units in which they were collected. However, a digital, virtual
               metadata archive provides an opportunity to challenge established practices and offer
               new perspectives on archival materials. For instance, we can explore the collections
               of notable politicians and academics, or large family holdings, and ‘liberate’
               mothers, sisters, and daughters by granting them independent status as virtual
               records creators, thereby ensuring their immediate visibility and discoverability.
               One such individual is Aline Reuter (née Procopé).</p>
            <p>Table 3 presents the ten most active women in the entire dataset, ranked by the
               number of letters. Interestingly, only half of these women are linked to content-rich
               external resources; that is to say, they have a Wikipedia page or an entry in the
               National Biography of Finland. For these women, we have readily available
               occupational information. In contrast, much less information is at our disposal for
               the other four women – the ‘dark horses’ of our virtual archive. Aline Reuter’s
               correspondence at the Åbo Akademi comprises 8,178 letters (3,072 sent and 5,106
               received). This makes it one of the largest collections of letters from a
               nineteenth-century woman in our current dataset. You might think that such a large
               collection, covering a period considered so formative for Finnish nationalism and
               studied by generations of historians, would be used extensively. This does not seem
               to be the case, however. The few mentions that shed light on her life can be found in
               the National Biography entries of her three famous professor sons and in the Reuter
               family entry (see, for example, Autio, 1997a and 1997b). There are also Wikipedia
               pages (e.g. ‘Edvin Titus Feodor Reuter’) and a Geni.com profile (‘Aline Reuter’)
               which, for technical reasons, cannot be used to enrich the data. These sources
               provide information about her lifespan (1828–1916) and some details about her family
               (husband and four sons).</p>
            <table>
               <head>Ten most active female authors in the CoCo dataset. Source: CoCo dataset (19
                  February 2025). Note: AEL (Albert Edelfelt’s Letters), FNG (The Finnish National
                  Gallery), SKS (The Finnish Literature Society), NAF (The National Archives of
                  Finland), NLF (The National Library of Finland), SLS (The Society of Swedish
                  Literature in Finland), ÅA (The Åbo Akademi University Library).</head>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Total letters</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>Records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Procopé (Reuter), Aline (1828–1916)</cell>
                  <cell>8178</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS,ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>3 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Wrede, Hedvig Gustava Matilda (1854–1917)</cell>
                  <cell>5582</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>2 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Söderhjelm, Alma (1870–1949)</cell>
                  <cell>5567</cell>
                  <cell>author, historian, full professor, docent, essayist, professor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅÂ)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Aalberg, Ida (1857–1915)</cell>
                  <cell>5485</cell>
                  <cell>actor, stage actor, theatrical director</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Talvio, Maila (1871–1951)</cell>
                  <cell>5396</cell>
                  <cell>writer, honorary doctorate, translator</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Ackté, Aino (1876–1944)</cell>
                  <cell>5242</cell>
                  <cell>opera singer, librettist</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (FNL)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Granfelt (Lavonius), Magdalena Lovisa (1877–1946)</cell>
                  <cell>5183</cell>
                  <cell>teacher</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gripenberg, Aleksandra (1857–1913)</cell>
                  <cell>5078</cell>
                  <cell>member of parliament, writer, chairperson, politician, editor, public
                     figure</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Haahti, Hilja Theodolinda (1874–1966)</cell>
                  <cell>5004</cell>
                  <cell>author, translator, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Reuter, Anna Hildur Elisabeth (1855–1936)</cell>
                  <cell>4944</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>1 (no)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>However, obituaries of Aline Reuter in the newspapers provide further insights into
               her life. She had 13 children in total, many of whom died young. She homeschooled the
               surviving children until they reached grammar school age, and she acquired such
               excellent skills in subjects such as Latin and mathematics that, when her son Odo
               Reuter, a professor of zoology, became blind, Aline Reuter (now in her 80s) took over
               his professional correspondence and proofread his papers. However, more than her
               obvious intellectual agility, the obituaries emphasise her ‘rich inner life’ and
               remind readers that ‘there were no great events in her life’ (see, for example, <hi
                  rend="italic">Dagens Press</hi>, 1916). This statement alone arouses curiosity
               about the contents of Reuter’s extensive collection of letters, tempting one to
               immerse oneself in her ‘epistolary space’ (How, 2003) and reflect on its
               representativeness, for example with regard to the experienced, personal nationalism
               of nineteenth-century women (Eiranen, 2021) or other significant ways of discursively
               shaping oneself and one’s surroundings (Monagle et al., 2023, p. 12).</p>
            <p>‘Mother Aline’ is thus a prime example of a marginalised or forgotten person who only
               becomes clearly visible when we recontextualise her letters in the collected and
               enriched metadata. Indeed, it is only through the combined metadata that we can
               confirm the extraordinary quantity of surviving correspondence. By way of comparison,
               the most extensive set of male correspondence is that of Senator Leopold (Leo)
               Mechelin (1839–1914), whose entire collection of letters from various organisations
               totals 14,399.</p>
            <p>We can make further observations about the gender distribution in the Finnish
               nineteenth-century data with the help of network analysis and simple degree metrics,
               which build on the above analysis of the number of contacts each person had. This
               enables us to visually assess the extent to which the women in our letter collections
               were connected. As our dataset spans over a hundred years, we decided to examine two
               periods in more detail: 1830–1860 and 1880–1910, which reflect the socio-economic,
               legal and social changes that affected women’s correspondence in the modernising
               Grand Duchy of Finland. From the 1860s onwards, women gradually gained access to
               higher education. As the country’s economy liberalised, women’s legal and economic
               rights were strengthened, and they participated in associations and societal
               movements. Hypothetically, this meant that women’s epistolary networks became more
               similar to those of men, and we were interested to see if we could find traces of
               this in the archived epistolary material.</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image8.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 2. Correspondence network in 1830–1860, women’s nodes are marked with blue,
               and others with orange. Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The complete
               core network, with the size of the nodes relative to their degree (non-weighted): the
               number of correspondence contacts of the person. The highest degree is 266. The
               layout is Yifan Hu generated with Gephi 0.10.1. See Appendix 2 for statistics.</p>
            <p>As expected, looking at the position of women in the correspondence networks reveals
               that their connectivity increases as we move from the first to the second period. At
               the same time, the ‘archival status’ of the most well-connected women and their links
               to external biographical databases undergoes a significant change. As illustrated in
               Figure 2, during the initial period of letter correspondence (1830–1860), men
               dominate the centre of the network, with most women (represented by blue nodes)
               situated in the middle and outer spheres. The ten most connected women are also not
               central figures from an archival perspective (see Appendix 2, Table 2). As they are
               not records creators, the bulk of their letters have been archived as part of their
               families’, husbands’ or sons’ fonds. Furthermore, linking to external databases has
               only resulted in links to genealogical databases. Professional information was only
               found for two women (Fredrika Runeberg and Elisabeth Blomqvist), who have also
               attracted academic interest (e.g. Klinge, 2006; Konttinen, 2000). The situation is
               quite different for the ten most connected men of this period (see Appendix 2, Table
               1): they are all records creators; their letters originate from 7–9 archival
               organisations; and they are well linked to external sources, including Wikipedia.</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image7.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 3. Correspondence network in 1880–1910, women’s nodes are marked with blue,
               and others with orange. Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The complete
               core network, with the size of the nodes relative to their degree (non-weighted): the
               number of correspondence contacts of the person. The highest degree is 528. The
               layout is Yifan Hu generated with Gephi 0.10.1. See Appendix 2 for statistics.</p>
            <p>During the second period (1880–1910), women were more centrally positioned within the
               network, as illustrated in Figure 3. The profile of the women with the most
               connections in this later period is very different to that in the earlier period:
               nine out of ten of these women are records creators, and their letters are widely
               distributed across different archival organisations (see Appendix 2, Table 4). These
               women are well-known cultural figures – artists, writers and politicians – and are
               well connected to external data sources. They also have a Wikipedia entry. Their
               network profiles thus differ significantly from those of lesser-known figures such as
               ‘Mother Aline’, who, despite her extensive correspondence, plays a more peripheral
               role in the network. In both periods, the biggest difference in our metadata between
               men and women is that women have significantly fewer contacts, even those who worked
               in the public and private sectors in the late nineteenth century (such as the social
               activist and politician Aleksandra Gripenberg; see Table 3 and Appendix 2, Table 4
               and Appendix 3, Table 2). Based on archival materials, women’s epistolary networks
               were narrower. However, as noted above, the ties were proportionally stronger in
               terms of the number of letters exchanged.</p>
            <p>In addition, networks consisting exclusively of correspondence between women provide
               further insight into the organisation of archival collections, the focus of scholarly
               interest and the changes brought about by the modernisation of the country. The
               configurations of women’s correspondence networks are illustrated in Figure 4 for the
               periods 1830–1860 and 1880–1910. During the earlier period, women exchanged
               significantly less correspondence, and their networks formed several distinct but
               small clusters. While most of the women are the same as in the full network, the
               shape of the network now suggests a predominance of family networks, as previous
               research (Monagle et al., 2023) has suggested. However, further data analysis and
               qualitative research are needed to confirm this. Additionally, many of the women’s
               letters are uniquely archived at Åbo Akademi, likely due to the institution’s
               substantial collection of family archives from the Swedish-speaking population. For
               the second period (1880–1910), the situation is very different, as can be seen from
               the shape and size of the network in Figure 4. The women were highly interconnected,
               with significant nodes at the centre of the network. Examining the most central women
               reveals that, with the exception of two individuals, all of those in the ‘women's
               network’ and the broader network remain the same during this period, albeit with
               slightly different rankings (see Appendix 3). Therefore, in the latter period, it is
               not possible to identify separate clusters of women’s correspondence. Instead,
               women’s correspondence is interwoven with the networks of the country’s artistic and
               cultural elite, whose correspondence is spread across all the archival organisations
               in our dataset.</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image5.png"/>
               <graphic url="media/image6.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 4. Correspondence networks that contain only women for the years 1830–1860
               (top) and 1880–1910 (bottom). Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The
               complete network, with the size of the nodes relative to their degree (non-weighted):
               the number of correspondence contacts of the person. The layout is Yifan Hu generated
               with Gephi 0.10.1. See Appendix 3 for statistics.</p>
            <p>Despite these extensive collections, archived materials only provide patchy and
               partial access to nineteenth-century epistolary communication. When we compare the
               dataset — and thus the collections of the largest Finnish cultural heritage
               organisations — with statistics on all letters sent in the Grand Duchy of Finland, it
               is clear that coverage and representativeness are low (Figure 5). The collected
               metadata does not reflect the growth in letter correspondence in the country, which
               was driven by the expansion of trade, commerce and administration, as well as the
               development of technologies that supported easy and affordable letter exchange, such
               as cheap postage and stationery, prepayment of letters and increasing delivery speeds
               (Pietiäinen, 1988). After the mid-1880s, when literacy rates began to rise, archival
               coverage decreased further still. It appears that archival organisations lacked the
               means or interest to preserve everyday correspondence in the Grand Duchy, and
               lower-class individuals and small businesses may not have had the inclination to
               create personal archives. Therefore, an interesting question is whether we can
               estimate what materials are missing. Can we see what is not there?</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image1.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 5. Share of the CoCo letters among all paid letters sent in Finland (blue,
               left), and number of letters in the CoCo database per year (orange, right). Note:
               Information about paid letters for years 1845, 1855, 1865, and 1877–1917. (Source:
               Pietiäinen, 1988)</p>
            <p>At the start of the data collection, we asked cultural heritage organisations to
               estimate the proportion of their collections that were unorganised and uncatalogued
               (see Appendix 1). The results of this survey clearly demonstrate a growing shortage
               of resources for the labour-intensive work of archival description. However, it is
               reasonable to assume that letters added to collections since the nineteenth century,
               perhaps up to the 1980s, were more thoroughly indexed due to the greater availability
               of human resources relative to the size of the collections. Nevertheless, the
               collections do not represent a random sample of nineteenth-century epistolary
               culture, as evidenced by the social and cultural status of most of the records
               creators. Therefore, while cultural heritage organisations’ collections are not
               representative of the majority of letters sent, especially in the late nineteenth
               century, they do reflect the membership of the elite and upper middle classes
               relatively well.</p>
            <p>However, what has been preserved of the total body of correspondence that once
               existed is often coincidental, even among the literate elite. For instance, Senator
               Mechelin received 12,129 letters, which are kept in his family’s collection at the
               National Archives. However, we only have 2,270 of his letters (mainly in the
               collections of other individuals in five different organisations). Assuming that
               people mostly replied to the letters they received, this kind of disparity in the
               material points to definite gaps in the collections. Conversely, it is more
               challenging to determine whether the proportion of female actors (24% of the total,
               and 29% of those for whom gender can be identified) and the proportion of letters
               sent and received by them (38% and 36%, respectively) is indicative of missing
               material. Similar, large-scale datasets of epistolary metadata from other European
               countries are lacking, making it difficult to compare our findings and results. The
               closest we have are the results of the ambitious RRL projects mentioned above, which
               provide a rare insight into the gender distribution of epistolary material from
               earlier centuries. The datasets currently available in Germany and the Netherlands
               show an overwhelmingly male correspondence of 85%, but this is understandable given
               the projects’ premises.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>6 Discussion</head>
            <p>In the era of flourishing research on LGBTQIA+ histories, exploring the role of women
               as archival protagonists may not seem very revolutionary. In fact, the first attempt
               to enable sustained research on women’s history in Finland was made in the mid-1990s
               with the publication of <hi rend="italic">Naisia, asiakirjoja, arkistoja: Suomen
                  naishistorian arkistolähteitä</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Women, Documents, Archives:
                  Sources for Women’s History in Finland</hi>, Härkönen, 1994), which identified
               various archival collections of potential interest to the emerging field of gender
               history. However, as we have demonstrated, applying data science methods can render
               the process of critically revising archival collections much more systematic and
               powerful. Epistolary metadata is, of course, only one type of information that can be
               used to interrogate the role and visibility of different social, cultural, or ethnic
               communities in our social narratives. Indeed, cultural heritage metadata may offer a
               more affordable and realistic way of making dispersed archival and museum collections
               accessible and researchable than mass digitisation projects. However, metadata alone
               can be frustrating for scholars accustomed to interrogating vast textual archives,
               and a dialogue between digital and more traditional research methods is required.
               Nevertheless, using ‘pure’ metadata enables us to ‘map missing bricks in the wall of
               knowledge’, for instance by categorising individuals and social groups whose
               biographies do not yet exist (Guldi, 2024, p. 525) – a task we have begun with the
               help of Aline Reuter, among others.</p>
            <p>Jo Guldi has recently referred to such digital approaches as ‘counting the silences’
               (Guldi, 2024, p. 524). ‘Silence’ is a buzzword used by scholars to refer to missing
               data or issues that archives cannot or will not ‘talk about’. It is often used
               interchangeably with terms such as ‘gaps’, ‘bias’ and ‘occlusion’ (see also Carter,
               2006, p. 217). To clarify, Guldi (2023, pp. 30–37) distinguishes between occlusion
               and bias. For Guldi, a digital humanist who works with large textual corpora, the
               Occluded Archive is an archive that is closed to view. It consists of materials that
               we cannot access for various reasons. Occlusion operates at the level of political
               and historical factors, as well as archival organisation (e.g. which social groups
               are literate, which archives are preserved, and how relevant documents are hidden in
               separate datasets). For Guldi, bias is ‘dirt’ or ‘filth’ in the textual content. This
               powerful metaphor refers to racist, misogynistic and other expressions and narratives
               that carry a heavy ideological burden. Historians are usually aware of such omissions
               and biases, which they identify as part of their work. However, these factors are not
               always considered when data science methods are applied to materials.</p>
            <p>Our data consist of metadata from the letter collections; we do not have the content
               of the letters in our dataset. This means that we need to introduce an additional
               feature of occlusion: the partly accidental and partly selective nature of the entire
               life cycle of historical and archived materials. Many archival theorists interpret
               ‘silences’ as tangible gaps in the archival record. These gaps can arise from
               everyday practices such as the accidental disappearance or deliberate destruction of
               materials prior to and after archiving, or from appraisal and subsequent rejection in
               a cultural heritage organisation (Fowler, 2017; Edquist, 2021). The historical
               reasons for this kind of fundamental, irreversible non-preservation vary, and there
               is little evidence of such processes producing structural bias in historical sources.
               However, it may be possible to model some gaps using digital methods or conduct the
               time-consuming task of searching organisational records for traces of decision-making
               processes. In this paper, we have identified both gaps (in the representativeness of
               the data, compared with the information available on nineteenth-century postal
               activity and literacy) and silences (in the lack of research on certain notable women
               in our dataset) by examining what has been preserved in the collections of Finnish
               cultural heritage organisations. A persistent ‘silence’ is often only recognised in
               retrospect, for example, when a paradigmatic change in theory or technology allows a
               new view of the archived material.</p>
            <p>​​It is true that material separated into different repositories or organisations is
               a strong occluding factor. However, occlusion also occurs within individual
               organisations. A key factor here is how organisations prioritise the creation of
               metadata and categorise catalogued documents as open and accessible or closed (e.g.
               Sherratt, 2019). Only collections that have been organised and described can be made
               available to researchers and other users (see Appendix 1). Furthermore, it has been
               argued that creating a fonds and assigning a records creator carries significant
               intellectual and hegemonic weight, yet these decisions often remain invisible
               (Drucker, 2021, p. 326; Friedrich, 2021, pp. 312–317).</p>
            <p>Digital humanities scholars often work with materials that were originally indexed in
               a library context. While these bibliographic databases, catalogues, and digitised
               repositories are incomplete and less representative than many scholars might hope
               (see, for example, Bode, 2020), they do comprise fairly homogeneous sets of
               materials. Furthermore, issues of archival access and its political constraints are
               frequently examined in the context of sensitive government records (e.g. Risam, 2019;
               Sherratt, 2019). However, it is also important to recognise these mechanisms in
               relation to cultural heritage materials and those held in private archival
               organisations. All organisations whose letter metadata are included in our dataset
               have their own acquisition policies, enabling them to accept or reject archival
               material offered to them, provided they justify their decisions. Compared to material
               generated in library contexts and governmental organisation records, archival
               organisations’ vast collections, particularly person and family collections, seem
               more ‘wild’, especially when considering material beyond the high research canon.
               Cataloguing categories vary, information comes in different formats, and many
               collections are only partially organised, with huge backlogs of unorganised
               material.</p>
         </div>
            <div>
               <head>7 Conclusion</head>
            <p>In this paper, we introduce the framework of Critical Collection History. Using the
               powerful qualities of Linked Open Data, this framework finds relevant features in a
               dataset comprising over a million letters and over 100,000 actors. It is motivated by
               discussions in the fields of critical archival studies and digital humanities. We
               argue that critical collection history occurs when the boundaries of cultural
               heritage organisations and their collections are erased and the structure of
               traditional paper archives is challenged and ‘weirded’. At the most general level,
               critical collection history asks whose actions and experiences are important enough
               to be archived and catalogued, and which individuals and groups are visible in
               finding aids, indexes and external research repositories. Digital technologies enable
               us to examine archival collections individually and collectively as large sets of
               historical data, not as static and inherently objective entities providing direct
               access to the past, but as multi-layered, dynamic and processual entities resulting
               from various historical, socio-economic and political processes. Similar to many
               contextualising approaches to digital collections (e.g. Beelen et al., 2023), the aim
               is not to ‘correct’, but to identify how such processes and layers manifest in the
               collections in question. Furthermore, we are not merely users of archival data; we
               are also actively involved in making the archival record more visible (or ‘louder’)
               in the digital space (Johnson, 2017). For instance, we make decisions about modelling
               the data and solving problems related to resource constraints when obtaining source
               data (Drobac et al., 2023b).</p>
            <p>This article discusses materials that mainly comprise person and family collections
               held in private archival organisations. These collections are widely used by scholars
               and favoured as case studies in archival research (Edquist, 2021), yet they are
               rarely considered in postcolonial and other critical approaches. As a case study, we
               have created a virtual archive of ‘epistolary women’. Our analyses suggest that the
               collections available to us as linked data are relatively representative of the upper
               echelons of nineteenth-century society. However, it is more difficult to assess
               whether the proportion of female person-actors (29% of all actors and 26–34% of the
               more filtered group of records creators in two sample organisations) accurately
               represents women’s epistolary activities. Nevertheless, network analysis indicates
               that the available epistolary metadata reflects changes in women’s societal roles
               brought about by modernisation. This demonstrates that even partial datasets can
               reveal significant historical phenomena and be profitably used by humanists, provided
               the gaps or ‘missingness’ are understood and acknowledged (Ryan and Ahnert,
               2021).</p>
            <p>In addition, we have identified certain epistemic silences: women who do not feature
               in our current research canon but who have substantial archival collections that
               could offer valuable insights into a variety of historical topics. Overall, the
               results are tentative but promising. However, we must bear in mind that the current
               data include four online publications of letters and letter metadata from only nine
               cultural heritage organisations – albeit the largest and most central – and only from
               those collections that have been indexed at the level of individual letter exchanges.
               Nonetheless, despite all the gaps and omissions discussed in this paper, the
               collected metadata provides the most comprehensive sample available of who actually
               sent and received letters in nineteenth-century Finland.</p>
            <p>This article has demonstrated the potential of linked open data and critical
               collection history in identifying gendered structures within epistolary metadata
               collections. In the future, we can continue to explore women’'s correspondence as a
               historical phenomenon by focusing more qualitatively on the women we identify using
               data-driven methods. Furthermore, we can direct our historical research towards
               archival collections as the outcome of specific political, cultural, and
               socio-economic pressures – pressures that leave their mark, turning the archives
               themselves into artefacts of history (Burton, 2005, p. 6). To achieve this, we should
               digitise the acquisition registers of various organisations and study their
               decision-making processes relating to archival appraisal where possible. While many
               organisational histories touch on these issues – most recently Petra Hakala’s (2023)
               study of the Swedish Literature Society in Finland’s archival collections – a
               combined history focusing on private epistolary collections as a case study remains
               to be written. A critical collection history is also always a history of the
               construction of collective identity; it can reveal whose experiences are available to
               us as historians, and also whose experiences have been narrativised as history at
               different stages in the past.</p>
            </div>
         
         
         
         
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Appendix 1: Survey about the current situation of letter metadata held by Finnish
               cultural heritage organisations</head>
            <p>The project <hi rend="italic">Constellations of Correspondence – Large and Small
                  Networks of Epistolary Exchange in the Grand Duchy of Finland </hi>(CoCo) has
               launched a survey on nineteenth-century letter collections in Finnish cultural
               heritage organisations. To date, 57 archives, libraries and museums have responded.
               The survey contains 18 questions to help understand the current situation and the
               challenges of aggregating collection metadata. Here, we present results relevant to
               this paper in Figures 1–3. In summary, 86% of respondents either have or possibly
               have nineteenth-century letters in their archival collections. The word ‘possibly’ is
               explained by the fact that only 33% have catalogued all their letters. Conversely,
               14% have not catalogued them at all. Regarding archival finding aids, only 36% of
               respondents with nineteenth-century letters have catalogues in electronic form, such
               as databases, Excel files, or Word documents. This makes the content
               machine-readable, but additional structuring and harmonising is required.<figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image2.png"/>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Appendix 1, Figure 1. Survey about cultural heritage organisations’ letter
               catalogues:  ‘Does your organisation have nineteenth-century letters in its
               collections?'</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image4.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Appendix 1, Figure 2. Survey about cultural heritage organisations’ letter
               catalogues: ‘How large proportion of your nineteenth-century letter collections have
               been catalogued?’</p>
            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="media/image3.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Appendix 1, Figure 3. Survey about cultural heritage organisations’ letter
               catalogues: ‘How large proportion of your catalogue metadata on nineteenth-century
               letter collections is in electronic form?’</p>
         </div>
         
         
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Appendix 2: Top 10 male and female authors in the complete correspondence network
               based on degree (non-weighted), 1830–1860 and 1880–1910.</head>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Lönnrot, Elias (1802–1884)</cell>
                  <cell>1 (266)</cell>
                  <cell>author, botanist, collector, folklorist, full professor, hymnwriter,
                     lexicographer, linguist, pedagogue, philologist, physician, physician writer,
                     poet, professor, writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>archive (ELL)</cell>
                  <cell>11 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Armfelt, Alexander (1794–1875)</cell>
                  <cell>2 (135)</cell>
                  <cell>minister-secretary, count, chancellor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (FNA)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Topelius, Zachris (1818–1898)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (125)</cell>
                  <cell>amanuensis, author, children’s writer, full professor, historian, history
                     teacher, journalist, poet, professor, rector, school teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ZTS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>archive (ZTS)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Ilmoni, Immanuel (1797–1856)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (125)</cell>
                  <cell>director, full professor, Master of Philosophy, physician, professor,
                     prosector, secretary, senior accountant</cell>
                  <cell>ELL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gottlund, Carl Axel (1796–1875)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (119)</cell>
                  <cell>author, explorer, historian, lecturer, linguist, translator, writer</cell>
                  <cell>ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF, SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Mannerheim, Karl Gustaf (1797–1854)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (111)</cell>
                  <cell>count, County governor, doctor of both laws, entomologist, judge,
                     notary</cell>
                  <cell>JVSL, NAL, NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Cygnaeus, Fredrik (1807–1881)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (104)</cell>
                  <cell>author, docent, full professor, historian, literary critic, poet, rector,
                     school teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>11 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Runeberg, Johan Ludvig (1804–1877)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (87)</cell>
                  <cell>author, school teacher, full professor, journalist, priest, lecturer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Schauman, Berndt Otto (1821–1895)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (87)</cell>
                  <cell>amanuensis, intendant, member of the Diet of Finland, non-fiction writer,
                     politician, writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Rein, Gabriel (1800–1867)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (83)</cell>
                  <cell>member of Diet ofFinland, historian, full professor, rector, lecturer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 2, Table 1. Ten authors with highest degree (non-weighted) in 1830–1860.
               Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The information about occupations,
               archive, fonds, and external links concerns all letters by the author. AEL (Albert
               Edelfelt’s Letters), ELL (Elias Lönnrot’s Letters), JVSL (Johan Vilhelm Snellman’s
               Letters), FNG (The Finnish National Gallery), SKS (The Finnish Literature Society),
               NAF (The National Archives of Finland), NLF (The National Library of Finland), SLS
               (The Swedish Literature Society in Finland), ÅA (The Åbo Akademi University
               Library).</p>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Runeberg, Fredrika (1807–1879)</cell>
                  <cell>61 (25)</cell>
                  <cell>writer, journalist, novelist, editor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gadd, Carolina Lovisa (1810–1867)</cell>
                  <cell>81 (19)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NLF</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>1 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Tengström (Bergbom), Johanna Carolina (1803–1885)</cell>
                  <cell>98 (16)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>JVSL, NLF, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Armfelt, Wava</cell>
                  <cell>108 (15)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>0 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Collan (Wasenius), Johanna (1814–1901)</cell>
                  <cell>115 (14)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>son (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Tengström (Kellgren), Anna Sofia (1826–1906)</cell>
                  <cell>118 (14)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>JVSL, NLF, SLS</cell>
                  <cell>husband (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>af Brunér, Emma (1814–1857)</cell>
                  <cell>119 (14)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>2 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Blomqvist, Elisabeth (1827–1901)</cell>
                  <cell>132 (12)</cell>
                  <cell>director, head teacher, painter, painter and varnisher</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>von Haartman, Naema Aurora (1822–1866)</cell>
                  <cell>135 (12)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Westzynthius (Haartman), Margaretha Sophia (1807–1894)</cell>
                  <cell>146 (11)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>1 (no)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 2, Table 2. Ten female authors with highest betweenness in 1830–1860.
               Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The information about occupations,
               archive, fonds, and external links concerns all letters by the author.</p>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Mechelin, Leopold (1839–1914)</cell>
                  <cell>1 (528)</cell>
                  <cell>banker, deputy, director, doctor of both laws, entrepreneur, full professor,
                     politician</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NAF)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Palmén, Ernst Gustaf (1849–1919)</cell>
                  <cell>2 (476)</cell>
                  <cell>historian, member of parliament, member of the Diet of Finland, politician,
                     professor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Topelius, Zachris (1818–1898)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (473)</cell>
                  <cell>amanuensis, author, children’s writer, full professor, historian, history
                     teacher, journalist, master’s degree, poet, professor, rector, school teacher,
                     writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ZTS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>archive (ZTS)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Schybergson, Magnus Gottfrid (1852–1925)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (356)</cell>
                  <cell>historian, full professor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Setälä, Emil Nestor (1864–1935)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (333)</cell>
                  <cell>anthropologist, Chancellor, diplomat, linguist, member of parliament,
                     Minister for Foreign Affairs of Finland, Minister of Education, politician,
                     senator, university teacher</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Aspelin-Haapkylä (Aspelin), Eliel (1847–1917)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (325)</cell>
                  <cell>art historian, full professor, counselor of state</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Colliander, Otto Immanuel (1848–1924)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (305)</cell>
                  <cell>bishop, politician, priest</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NAF)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Cygnaeus, Gustaf (1851–1907)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (269)</cell>
                  <cell>journalist, lecturer, newspaper editor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Schauman, Berndt Otto (1821–1895)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (252)</cell>
                  <cell>amanuensis, intendant, member of the Diet of Finland, politician,
                     writer</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, FNG, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Palmén, Johan Axel (1845–1919)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (238)</cell>
                  <cell>member of Diet of Finland, full professor, ornithologist, entomologist,
                     geographer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 2, Table 3. Ten authors with highest degree (non-weighted) in 1880–1910.
               Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The information about occupations,
               archive, fonds, and external links concerns all letters by the author.</p>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Aalberg, Ida (1857–1915)</cell>
                  <cell>21 (182)</cell>
                  <cell>actor, stage actor, theatrical director</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (FNL)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gripenberg, Aleksandra (1857–1913)</cell>
                  <cell>31 (157)</cell>
                  <cell>member of parliament, writer, editor, chairperson</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Käkikoski, Hilda (1864–1912)</cell>
                  <cell>40 (145)</cell>
                  <cell>member of parliament, politician, teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Friberg, Maikki (1861–1927)</cell>
                  <cell>60 (114)</cell>
                  <cell>editor, journalist, suffragist, teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NAF)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Westermarck, Helena (1857–1938)</cell>
                  <cell>63 (112)</cell>
                  <cell>editor, historian, painter, painter and varnisher, visual artist,
                     writer</cell>
                  <cell>FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Söderhjelm, Alma (1870–1949)</cell>
                  <cell>68 (103)</cell>
                  <cell>author, docent, essayist, full professor, historian</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Talvio, Maila (1871–1951)</cell>
                  <cell>79 (95)</cell>
                  <cell>writer, translator, honorary doctorate</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Ackté, Aino (1876–1944)</cell>
                  <cell>83 (90)</cell>
                  <cell>opera singer, librettist</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (FNL)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Elfving (Runeberg), Lina (1841–1916)</cell>
                  <cell>89 (84)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NLF, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>husband (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Åström, Emma Irene (1847–1934)</cell>
                  <cell>91 (83)</cell>
                  <cell>lecturer, school teacher, teacher</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 2, Table 4. Ten female authors with highest degree (non-weighted) in
               1880–1910. Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025). Note: The information about
               occupations, archive, fonds, and external links concerns all letters by the
               author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Appendix 3: Top 10 female authors in the correspondence network with only women
               based on degree (non-weighted), 1830–1860 and 1880–1910</head>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Runeberg, Fredrika (1835–1857)</cell>
                  <cell>1 (8)</cell>
                  <cell>writer, journalist, novelist, editor</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, ELL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Tallqvist, Alina Fredrika (1835–1899)</cell>
                  <cell>2 (8)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>af Brunér, Emma (1814–1857)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (8)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>2 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Westzynthius (Haartman), Margaretha Sophia (1807–1894)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>1 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Westzynthius, Emilia Teodora (Emmy) (1835–1906)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>no</cell>
                  <cell>3 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>von Haartman, Naema Aurora (1822–1866)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Thuneberg, Yolanda Aurora (1826–1888)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Collan (Wasenius), Johanna (1814–1901)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>NLF, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>son (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Tengström (Kellgren), Anna Sofia (1826–1906)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (6)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>JVSL, NLF, SLS</cell>
                  <cell>husband (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Blomqvist, Elisabeth (1827–1901)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (5)</cell>
                  <cell>director, head teacher, painter, painter and varnisher</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, JVSL, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>family (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 3, Table 1. Ten authors with highest degree (non-weighted) in the letter
               network containing only women, 1830–1860. Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025).
               Note: The information about occupations, archive, fonds, and external links concerns
               all letters by the author.</p>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Degree rank and value (non-weighted)</cell>
                  <cell>Occupations</cell>
                  <cell>Archives</cell>
                  <cell>records creator</cell>
                  <cell>External links (in Wikipedia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Gripenberg, Aleksandra (1857–1913)</cell>
                  <cell>1 (96)</cell>
                  <cell>member of parliament, writer, editor, chairperson</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Friberg, Maikki (1861–1927)</cell>
                  <cell>2 (71)</cell>
                  <cell>editor, journalist, suffragist, teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NAF)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Käkikoski, Hilda (1864–1912)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (71)</cell>
                  <cell>member of parliament, politician, teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (SKS)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Westermarck, Helena (1857–1938)</cell>
                  <cell>4 (55)</cell>
                  <cell>editor, historian, painter, painter and varnisher, visual artist,
                     writer</cell>
                  <cell>FNG, NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Åkerman, Emma (1851–1931)</cell>
                  <cell>5 (52)</cell>
                  <cell>poet, teacher, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS</cell>
                  <cell>family (NLF)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Aalberg, Ida (1957–1915)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (51)</cell>
                  <cell>actor, stage actor, theatrical director</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (FNL)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Elfving (Runeberg), Lina (1841–1916)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (49)</cell>
                  <cell>-</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NLF, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>husband (SLS)</cell>
                  <cell>3 (no)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Söderhjelm, Alma (1870–1949)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (41)</cell>
                  <cell>author, docent, essayist, full professor, historian</cell>
                  <cell>AEL, FNG, NAF, NLF, SKS, SLS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>8 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Hagman, Lucina (1853–1946)</cell>
                  <cell>9 (39)</cell>
                  <cell>chairperson, head teacher, member of parliament, politician, professor,
                     teacher, women’s rights activist, writer</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SLS, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (NAF)</cell>
                  <cell>7 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Åström, Emma Irene (1847–1934)</cell>
                  <cell>10 (37)</cell>
                  <cell>lecturer, school teacher, teacher</cell>
                  <cell>NAF, NLF, SKS, ÅA</cell>
                  <cell>yes (ÅA)</cell>
                  <cell>6 (yes)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Appendix 3, Table 2. Ten authors with highest degree (non-weighted) in the letter
               network containing only women, 1880–1910. Source: CoCo dataset (19 February 2025).
               Note: The information about occupations, archive, fonds, and external links concerns
               all letters by the author.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>Computing resources of the CSC – IT Center for Science were used in our work.</p>
         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ambrosino_etal2018" label="Ambrosino et al. 2018">Ambrosino, A. et al.
               (2018) <title rend="quotes">What topic modeling could reveal about the evolution of
                  economics</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Economic Methodology</title>,
               24(4), pp. 329–348.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="authors_alliance2021" label="Authors Alliance 2021">Authors Alliance.
               (2021) <title rend="quotes">Update: Librarian of Congress Grants 1201 Exemption to
                  Enable Text Data Mining Research</title>, <title rend="italic">Authors
                  Alliance</title>, 27 October. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.authorsalliance.org/2021/10/27/update-librarian-of-congress-grants-1201-exemption-to-enable-text-data-mining-research/"
                  >https://www.authorsalliance.org/2021/10/27/update-librarian-of-congress-grants-1201-exemption-to-enable-text-data-mining-research/</ref>
               (Accessed: 19 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bailey_etal2017" label="Bailey et al. 2017">Bailey, T.P., Scott, A.L. and
               Best, R.D. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Cost Differentials between E-Books and Print
                  in Academic Libraries</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.5860/crl.76.1.6"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5860/crl.76.1.6</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bnf_nd" label="BNF n.d.">Bibliothèque nationale de France. (n.d.) <title
                  rend="quotes">Gallica: The BNF Digital Library</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.bnf.fr/en/gallica-bnf-digital-library"
                  >https://www.bnf.fr/en/gallica-bnf-digital-library</ref> (Accessed: 20 October
               2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bjork2021" label="Björk 2021">Björk, B.-C. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Why
                  Is Access to the Scholarly Journal Literature So Expensive?</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">portal: Libraries and the Academy</title>, 21(2), pp. 177–192.
               Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/pla.2021.0010"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1353/pla.2021.0010</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bode2018" label="Bode 2018">Bode, K. (2018) <title rend="italic">A World
                  of Fiction: Digital Collections and the Future of Literary History</title>.
               University of Michigan Press. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.3998/mpub.8784777"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3998/mpub.8784777</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bode2020" label="Bode 2020">Bode, K. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Why You
                  Can't Model Away Bias</title>, <title rend="italic">Modern Language
                  Quarterly</title>, 81(1), pp. 95–124.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="borgman2018" label="Borgman 2018">Borgman, C.L. (2018) <title
                  rend="quotes">Open Data, Grey Data, and Stewardship: Universities at the Privacy
                  Frontier</title>, <title rend="italic">Berkeley Technology Law Journal</title>,
               33(2), pp. 365–412. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.15779/Z38B56D489"
                  >https://doi.org/10.15779/Z38B56D489</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bosch_etal2019" label="Bosch et al. 2019">Bosch, S., Albee, B. and
               Romaine, S. (2019) <title rend="italic">Deal or No Deal | Periodicals Price Survey
                  2019</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Journal</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.libraryjournal.com/story/Deal-or-No-Deal-Periodicals-Price-Survey-2019"
                  >https://www.libraryjournal.com/story/Deal-or-No-Deal-Periodicals-Price-Survey-2019</ref>
               (Accessed: 19 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="burns_etal2009" label="Burns et al. 2009">Burns, J. et al. (2009) <title
                  rend="quotes">JSTOR - Data for Research</title>, in <title rend="italic">Research
                  and Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries</title>, pp.
               416–419.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="chalmers_edwards2017" label="Chalmers and Edwards 2017">Chalmers, M.K. and
               Edwards, P.N. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Producing "one vast index": Google Book
                  Search as an algorithmic system</title>, <title rend="italic">Big Data &amp;
                  Society</title>, 4(2), p. 205395171771695. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951717716950"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951717716950</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="chu_etal2023" label="Chu et al. 2023">Chu, T., Song, Z. and Yang, C.
               (2023) <title rend="quotes">How to Protect Copyright Data in Optimization of Large
                  Language Models?</title> Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2308.12247"
                  >https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2308.12247</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crane_nd" label="Crane n.d.">Crane, G.R. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Perseus Digital Library</title>. Tufts University. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu</ref>
               (Accessed: 20 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="estabrook_warner2003" label="Estabrook and Warner 2003">Estabrook, L. and
               Warner, B. (2003) <title rend="italic">The Book as the Gold Standard for Tenure and
                  Promotion in the Humanistic Disciplines</title>. Urbana-Champaign: University of
               Illinois.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="eve2014" label="Eve 2014">Eve, M.P. (2014) <title rend="italic">Open
                  Access and the Humanities: Contexts, Controversies and the Future</title>.
               Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="falagas_etal2008" label="Falagas et al. 2008">Falagas, M.E. et al. (2008)
                  <title rend="quotes">Comparison of PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science, and Google
                  Scholar: strengths and weaknesses</title>, <title rend="italic">The FASEB
                  Journal</title>, 22(2), pp. 338–342. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.07-9492LSF"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.07-9492LSF</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="fanon2021" label="Fanon 2021">Fanon, F. (2021) <title rend="italic">The
                  Wretched of the Earth</title>. 60th anniversary edition. Translated by R. Philcox.
               New York: Grove Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="feeney2017" label="Feeney 2017">Feeney, M. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >What Can Text Mining Reveal about the Use of Newspapers in Research?</title>, in
                  <title rend="italic">Collecting, Preserving, and Transforming the News - for
                  Research and the Public</title>. <title rend="italic">IFLA International News
                  Media Conference</title>, Reykjavik, Iceland.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="fisher2020" label="Fisher 2020">Fisher, K. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Copyright and Preservation of Born-digital Materials: Persistent Challenges and
                  Selected Strategies</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title>,
               83(2), pp. 238–267. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.17723/0360-9081-83.2.238"
                  >https://doi.org/10.17723/0360-9081-83.2.238</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gale_cengage2014" label="Gale Cengage 2014">Gale Cengage. (2014) <title
                  rend="quotes">Eighteenth Century Collections Online</title>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gius_jacke2022" label="Gius and Jacke 2022">Gius, E. and Jacke, J. (2022)
                  <title rend="quotes">Are Computational Literary Studies Structuralist?</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 7(4). Available at:
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.46662"
                  >https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.46662</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="goldstone_underwood2012" label="Goldstone and Underwood 2012">Goldstone,
               A. and Underwood, T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">What can Topic Models of PMLA Teach
                  Us About the History of Literary Scholarship?</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, 2(1).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="guldi2021" label="Guldi 2021">Guldi, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">The
                  Official Mind's View of Empire, in Miniature: Quantifying World Geography in
                  Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of World
                  History</title>, 32(2), pp. 345–370.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gusenbauer_haddaway2020" label="Gusenbauer and Haddaway 2020">Gusenbauer,
               M. and Haddaway, N.R. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Which academic search systems are
                  suitable for systematic reviews or meta‐analyses? Evaluating retrieval qualities
                  of Google Scholar, PubMed, and 26 other resources</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Research Synthesis Methods</title>, 11(2), pp. 181–217. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1002/jrsm.1378"
               >https://doi.org/10.1002/jrsm.1378</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hawkins2021" label="Hawkins 2021">Hawkins, S. (ed.) (2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Access and control in digital humanities</title>. Abingdon, Oxon ;
               New York, NY: Routledge.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hegghammer2021" label="Hegghammer 2021">Hegghammer, T. (2021) <title
                  rend="quotes">OCR with Tesseract, Amazon Textract, and Google Document AI: a
                  benchmarking experiment</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Computational
                  Social Science</title>, 5(1), pp. 861–882. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42001-021-00149-1"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/s42001-021-00149-1</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="helms_krieser2023" label="Helms and Krieser 2023">Helms, S. and Krieser,
               J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Copyrights, Professional Perspective - Copyright
                  Chaos: Legal Implications of Generative AI</title>, <title rend="italic">Bloomberg
                  Law</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.bloomberglaw.com/external/document/XDDQ1PNK000000/copyrights-professional-perspective-copyright-chaos-legal-implic"
                  >https://www.bloomberglaw.com/external/document/XDDQ1PNK000000/copyrights-professional-perspective-copyright-chaos-legal-implic</ref>
               (Accessed: 15 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="janicke_etal2015" label="Jänicke et al. 2015">Jänicke, S. et al. (2015)
                  <title rend="quotes">On Close and Distant Reading in Digital Humanities: A Survey
                  and Future Challenges</title>, in <title rend="italic">STAR-State of The Art
                  Report</title>. Eurographics Conference on Visualization (EuroVis), Ed. R. Borgo,
               F. Ganovelli, and I. Viola.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="jockers2013" label="Jockers 2013">Jockers, M. (2013) <title rend="italic"
                  >Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>. Urbana-Champaign:
               University of Illinois Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="jung2020" label="Jung 2020">Jung, G. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Do
                  Androids Dream of Copyright?: Examining AI Copyright Ownership</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Berkeley Technology Law Journal</title>, 35(4), pp.
               1151–1178.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="knibbs2023" label="Knibbs 2023">Knibbs, K. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The
                  Battle Over Books3 Could Change AI Forever</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Wired</title>, 4 September. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.wired.com/story/battle-over-books3/"
                  >https://www.wired.com/story/battle-over-books3/</ref> (Accessed: 15 October
               2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="loc_nd" label="Library of Congress n.d.">Library of Congress (no date)
                  <title rend="quotes">What is a MARC Record and Why is it Important?</title>
               Available at: <ref target="https://www.loc.gov/marc/umb/um01to06.html"
                  >https://www.loc.gov/marc/umb/um01to06.html</ref> (Accessed: 20 October
               2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcdonough_etal2010" label="McDonough et al. 2010">McDonough, J. et al.
               (2010) <title rend="quotes">Preserving Virtual Worlds Final Report</title>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="neh_nd" label="NEH n.d.">National Endowment for the Humanities. (n.d)
                  <title rend="quotes">Appropriations of the National Endowment for the
                  Humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.neh.gov/neh-appropriations-history"
                  >https://www.neh.gov/neh-appropriations-history</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="nih_nd" label="NIH n.d.">National Institute of Health. (n.d) <title
                  rend="quotes">Appropriations of the NIH</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Appropriations of the NIH</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.nih.gov/about-nih/what-we-do/nih-almanac/appropriations-section-1"
                  >https://www.nih.gov/about-nih/what-we-do/nih-almanac/appropriations-section-1</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="nsf_nd" label="NSF n.d.">National Science Foundation (n.d) <title
                  rend="quotes">Appropriations of the NSF</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Appropriations of the NSF</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://new.nsf.gov/about/budget/fy2023/appropriations#:~:text=The%20%22Consolidated%20Appropriations%20Act%20of,above%20the%20FY%202022%20appropriation"
                  >https://new.nsf.gov/about/budget/fy2023/appropriations#:~:text=The%20%22Consolidated%20Appropriations%20Act%20of,above%20the%20FY%202022%20appropriation</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="neudecker_etal2021" label="Neudecker et al. 2021">Neudecker, C. et al.
               (2021) <title rend="quotes">A survey of OCR evaluation tools and metrics</title>, in
                  <title rend="italic">The 6th International Workshop on Historical Document Imaging
                  and Processing</title>. HIP '21: The 6th International Workshop on Historical
               Document Imaging and Processing, Lausanne Switzerland: ACM, pp. 13–18. Available at:
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3476887.3476888"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1145/3476887.3476888</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="pike2022" label="Pike 2022">Pike, G. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Copyright
                  and AI</title>, <title rend="italic">Information Today</title>, 39(9), pp.
               26–27.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piper2020" label="Piper 2020">Piper, A. (2020) <title rend="italic">Can We
                  Be Wrong: The Problem of Textual Evidence in a Time of Data</title>. Cambridge:
               Cambridge University Press (Elements in Digital Literary Studies).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="poole2013" label="Poole 2013">Poole, A.H. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Now
                  is the Future Now? The Urgency of Digital Curation in the Digital
                  Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>,
               7(2).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="project_gutenberg_nd" label="Project Gutenberg n.d."><title rend="quotes"
                  >Project Gutenberg</title> (n.d.). Urbana, Illinois.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, S. (2011) <title rend="italic"
                  >Reading machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>. Urbana-Champaign:
               University of Illinois Press (Topics in the Digital Humanities).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="reisner2023" label="Reisner 2023">Reisner, A. (2023) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Revealed: The Authors Whose Pirated Books Are Powering Generative AI</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title>, 19 August. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/08/books3-ai-meta-llama-pirated-books/675063/"
                  >https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/08/books3-ai-meta-llama-pirated-books/675063/</ref>
               (Accessed: 13 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="riddell2014" label="Riddell 2014">Riddell, A.B. (2014) <title
                  rend="quotes">How to Read 22,198 Journal Articles: Studying the History of German
                  Studies with Topic Models</title>, in <title rend="italic">Distant Readings:
                  Topologies of German Culture in the Long Nineteenth Century</title>. Rochester:
               Boydell &amp; Brewer, pp. 91–114.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="saveri_butterick2023" label="Saveri and Butterick 2023">Saveri, J. and
               Butterick, M. (2023) <title rend="quotes">LLM litigation</title> · Joseph Saveri Law
               Firm &amp; Matthew Butterick, <title rend="italic">LLM Litigation</title>. Available at:
                  <ref target="https://llmlitigation.com/">https://llmlitigation.com/</ref>
               (Accessed: 13 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sekhon_etal2023" label="Sekhon et al. 2023">Sekhon, J., Ozcan, O. and
               Ozcan, S. (2023) <title rend="quotes">ChatGPT: what the law says about who owns the
                  copyright of AI-generated content</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                  Conversation</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://theconversation.com/chatgpt-what-the-law-says-about-who-owns-the-copyright-of-ai-generated-content-200597"
                  >http://theconversation.com/chatgpt-what-the-law-says-about-who-owns-the-copyright-of-ai-generated-content-200597</ref>
               (Accessed: 15 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="spk_nd" label="SPK n.d.">Stiftung Preußischer Kulturbesitz (n.d.) <title
                  rend="quotes">Deutsche Digitale Bibliothek (German Digital Library)</title>.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.preussischer-kulturbesitz.de/en/about-us/tasks-of-national-interest/deutsche-digitale-bibliothek.html"
                  >https://www.preussischer-kulturbesitz.de/en/about-us/tasks-of-national-interest/deutsche-digitale-bibliothek.html</ref>
               (Accessed: 20 October 2023).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="thompson2002" label="Thompson 2002">Thompson, J.W. (2002) <title
                  rend="quotes">The Death of the Scholarly Monograph in the Humanities? Citation
                  Patterns in Literary Scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">Libri</title>,
               52(3). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/LIBR.2002.121"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1515/LIBR.2002.121</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="underwood2019" label="Underwood 2019">Underwood, T. (2019) <title
                  rend="italic">Distant Horizons: Digital Evidence and Literary Change</title>.
               Chicago: Chicago UP.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
