<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Orientation: <title rend="quotes">Man and His Tool,
                        Again?</title></title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Nicole <dhq:family>Starosielski</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>New York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nicole.starosielski@nyu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Assistant Professor of Media, Culture, and Communication at New York University.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000211</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2015-09-02">2 September 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>A response to Jamie "Skye" Bianco's "Man and His Tool, Again? Queer and Feminist Notes on Practices
                    in the Digital Humanities and Object Orientations Everywhere."</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>A response to Jamie Bianco's <title rend="quotes">Man and His Tool, Again?</title></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p> The first time that I taught Jamie Skye Bianco’s digital essay <title rend="quotes">Man and His Tool, Again?</title> a number of my students, frustrated with the
                tediousness of having to click each part of the text before moving to the next,
                simply downloaded the PDF file and read it from beginning to end. Others, unsure of
                the essay’s operations, clicked through the quotations without ever removing their
                mouse from the text. Most of the students had only a vague understanding of how
                their experience was being algorithmically (algorythmically, in Bianco’s terms)
                constructed. In the discussion that followed, it became clear that we had not all
                read the same essay. We were differently oriented to the text’s fragmentations, the
                temporal and spatial arrangement of sentences and quotations, and the computational
                scripts underlying their delivery. Our embodied reading practices did more than
                shape our opinions about Bianco’s piece, they were integral to the composition of
                the argument itself.</p>
            <p> The orientation of <title rend="quotes">Man and His Tool, Again?</title> foregrounds
                a longstanding observation that texts and technologies are not neutral conduits for
                meaning, but are actively produced in their readers, viewers, and users. The work
                uses digital methods to play with text and context, with coherence and
                fragmentation, and with visibility and invisibility. The HTML version of the project
                positions the user as an agent in the production of the argument, and, in laying
                bare the conditions of its operation, confronts her with the contradictions that
                underlie digital tools. In order to grasp these dynamics, we cannot simply read
                Bianco’s essay at the level of surface text, but must also grapple with the code
                beneath it. </p>
            <p>On the most basic level, the essay is a summary of findings using one of the most
                simple and pervasive digital humanities methods: the counting of word frequency in a
                written corpus. It uses exemplary works to stand in for a field, in this case two
                edited anthologies of digital humanities scholarship, and counts the reoccurrence of
                a set of key terms. Bianco finds that there are 700 uses of tool#, approximately ~8
                per essay, in contrast with approximately ~3.5 uses of rac# (including race, racism,
                and racial), fem# (feminism, feminist, femme, female, fem, feminine), queer# (queer,
                queerer), gender# (gender, gendered), and sex# (sexuality, sex, sexual, sexy,
                sexually) per essay. She also presents a series of observations that focus our
                attention on the differential emphasis of digital humanities work on tools, compared
                to race, gender, and sexuality: for example, she observes that 70% of the essays
                make no mention of rac#, fem#, queer#, gender#, sex# and 70 of these occurrences are
                in one essay alone. To take a neutral view of word frequency analysis, or to simply
                read the text in bold on the PDF version of the essay (as many of my students did),
                one might conclude that the relative frequency of tool# to rac#, fem#, queer#,
                gender#, and sex# is proof of the marginalization of race, gender, and sexuality in
                the digital humanities. </p>
            <p>The essay, however, does not simply present us with this data, but layers it into an
                interface that makes visible the problematics of data compilation, interpretation,
                and presentation. The project is structured such that the analysis of keywords is
                separated into fragments, ranging in length from a word to a sentence. When the user
                moves their mouse over one of these fragments, a quotation including tool#, rac#,
                fem#, queer#, gender#, and sex# from one of the digital humanities collections
                appears. Clicking on this text causes another quotation to replace it. To reveal the
                next fragment of the analysis, the user must move their mouse away from the
                quotation. What results is a juxtaposition of an argumentative thread that analyzes
                the meaning of key terms with a quotation thread that reveals the contexts in which
                they were used. Bianco points out that such contexts are essential for understanding
                the function of any individual word. Indeed, a citation from her own article in the
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> uses the term
                tool# to focus critical attention on the ideologies embedded in tool-building:
                    <q>Tools are also about something other than
                    themselves.</q> In turn, even when rac#, fem#, queer#, gender#, and sex#
                appear, they might align with existing structures of power. Sexy, for example, is
                used in the phrase <soCalled>sexy librarian.</soCalled> The terms feminine and
                masculine are used to reinstate a binary approach to gender. The structuring of the
                digital essay asks the user to stitch together the fragments of the argumentative
                thread, all the while being interrupted by the hidden contexts stripped out of the
                word frequency analysis.</p>
            <p>There is a play with visibility here, one that builds on a long history of feminist
                and queer reading practices. To merely click through the quotations, one would
                literally fail to see the argument. The piece forces the reader to pause, to move
                her indexical pointer away from the quotations in order to reveal the feminist
                analysis. This not only instantiates a particular politics of visibility, in which
                we must unearth voices hidden beneath, but requires an active and embodied reader to
                move through the work, clicking each fragment to move the narrative along. This
                structure draws our attention to the ways in which feminist or queer arguments are
                not visible in the surface text, but rather in our performance of it. In the PDF
                version, a read-only text, these kinds of relationalities are written out. Digital
                technologies in the essay are therefore not merely used to extract data and present
                it as evidence for an argument about the concerns of the digital humanities, but to
                undermine the truth-telling status of the data itself, a process that complicates
                our relationship to the tools that produced it. </p>
            <p>To fully understand this intervention, and to critically assess the way that Bianco
                uses digital technologies, we need to look at the technical construction of the
                project. To view the scripts that underlie the essay, the user should first view the
                page source (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>To reveal the menu and view the page source on a Mac, CTRL-click on the
                        screen.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure> Compared to many websites, the page source of this essay is relatively
                legible. The project has been built in such a way that, instead of clicking through
                many separate webpages to access different parts of the text, everything is
                contained on a single page, with sentence fragments and quotations revealed and
                hidden via a hide-show script (<ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>). As a result,
                almost all of the material, with the exception of the formatting (contained in a
                separate stylesheet), can be easily accessed. This code could be easily copied and
                reproduced by other digital humanities scholars. <figure>
                    <head>The hide-show script that governs the operations of “Man and His Tool,
                        Again?”</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure> The project’s operations are also relatively simple: there are only two
                scripts that dictate the majority of its functionality. The first is a basic
                hide-show script, repeated one hundred and one times: <dhq:example>
                    <p>$("#argumentfragment1").click(function(){</p>
                    <p>$("#argumentfragment1").hide(); </p>
                    <p>$("#argumentfragment2").show();</p>
                </dhq:example> This function determines that when an argument fragment is clicked,
                it is hidden and a second argument fragment is revealed. This instantiates the play
                of visibility described above at the level of the code. Each click does not allow us
                to navigate to a different location, but merely replaces what came before it,
                showing a new piece of information in the same exact spot on the page. We are not
                moving anywhere. Moreover, these fragments do not accrete, but are lost as we
                continue to click through the work. </p>
            <p>The second set of functions – <q>onmouseover</q> and <q>onmouseout</q> – replaces
                each argument fragment with a quotation when the user moves their mouse over it.
                Thus, in Figure 3, when the user hovers over the text <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Inventories run through algorithms…</quote> the quotation <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Databases were recognized as valuable tools quickly; so were graphical
                    applications’ (Eiteljorg 23)</quote> is revealed. When the user removes their
                mouse from the text (<q>onmouseout</q>), <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Inventories run
                    through algorithms…</quote> is shown again. Both of these text fragments are
                referred to as <q>obj.innerHTML</q> – they are objects embedded inside the HTML,
                revealed at select moments in response to user input. <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>The <q>onmouseover</q> and <q>onmouseout</q> functions.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure> These functions could have been set up in drastically different ways.
                Bianco might have written an iterative script, storing all of these fragments in a
                database located elsewhere. She might have written the code so that sentence
                fragments were periodically released on all parts of the screen, eventually
                mirroring the PDF version. Instead, she constructed the program such that each user
                would have to click through all one hundred and one fragments (requiring embodied
                labor) and that these fragments would disappear (perhaps signifying the continual
                erasure of feminist and queer histories). While the text is difficult to navigate,
                the code remains accessible, and the project refutes the values that are often
                circulated in the world of programming, such as efficiency and elegance. It does not
                presume a high level of expertise. By simply copying and pasting this page source,
                any user could replicate the essay using different content. These choices,
                instantiated in the code, produce a vastly different set of relationalities between
                readers and machines than the PDF version of the essay – one that orients us as
                embodied readers, potential hackers, and participants in the silencing and making
                visible of feminist narratives.</p>
            <p>If one were simply to review the data produced by Bianco’s word frequency search, it
                might be tempting to imagine a tool that could reveal privilege, a program that
                searches a broader digital humanities corpus for keywords rac#, fem#, queer#,
                gender# and sex#, and gauging their relative frequency, assigns each text a
                privilege ranking. It is precisely this imaginary that Bianco seeks to disrupt.
                Towards the end of the essay, she references a well-known quote from Audre Lorde:
                    <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure> Bianco’s essay draws into relief the ways in which the use of digital
                tools such as word frequency analysis often require the erasure of context and
                complexity, distilling multi-faceted cultural processes down to modular fragments.
                If these are the master’s tools, indeed they will never dismantle the broader
                regimes of classification and containment of racial, gendered, and sexual
                differences. Yet, at the same time she speculates that if we were to <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">jettison the <soCalled>man and his tool</soCalled>
                    business</quote> we might be able to produce other kinds of digital technologies
                and experiences. This essay is one such example. It takes into account the questions
                of embodied engagement and the differential relationships we have to digital
                systems. Rather than assume a universal set of values such as transparency and
                coherence, it plays with visibility and fragmentation at the level of text and code. </p>
            <p>In order to recognize the differences that matter, however, whether between HTML and
                PDF versions of this project or between the markup of <soCalled>gendered
                    gaze</soCalled> and <soCalled>sexy librarian,</soCalled> we must engage in a
                feminist and queer code studies, one that can discern how the design of the programs
                and scripts that underlie the construction of digital objects invisibly affect our
                own orientations.<note> For insightful discussions relating to feminist and queer
                    code, see Arielle Schlesinger, <title rend="quotes">A Feminist &amp;&amp; A
                        Programmer,</title> HASTAC Blog, <ref target="http://www.hastac.org/blogs/ari-schlesinger/2013/12/13/feminist-programmer">http://www.hastac.org/blogs/ari-schlesinger/2013/12/13/feminist-programmer</ref>;
                    Kara Keeling, <title rend="quotes">Queer OS,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal </title>53, no. 2 (Winter 2014); Zach Blas
                    and Micha Cardenas, <title rend="quotes">Imaginary Computational Systems: Queer
                        Technologies and Transreal Aesthetics,</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> AI &amp; Society </title>28 (2013): 559-566; Mark Marino,
                        <title rend="quotes">Disrupting Heteronormative Codes: When Cylons in Slash
                        Goggles Ogle AnnaKournikova.</title> Proceedings of Digital Arts and Culture
                    2009.</note> One that can assess systems not simply in terms of the visible
                traces of race, gender, and sexuality, but the ways that digital systems are always
                already implicated in the definition of what and how we can know. </p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>