<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Systematic bias in humanities datasets: ancient and
               medieval coin finds in the FLAME project<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Lee <dhq:family>Mordechai</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8474-0473<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lee.mordechai@mail.huji.ac.il</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Lee Mordechai is a Senior Lecturer at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem’s
                     History Department. Much of his work concerns Late Antiquity and he has worked
                     on FLAME for about a decade.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Alan <dhq:family>Stahl</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Princeton University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>astahl@princeton.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Alan Stahl is Curator of Numismatics at Princeton University and teaches in the
                     departments of Art &amp; Archaeology, Classics and History. One of his first
                     publications was in Computers and the Humanities in 1978.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mark <dhq:family>Pyzyk</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7542-4252<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Getty Research Institute </dhq:affiliation>
               <email>pyzmark@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mark Pyzyk is Data Analyst and Facilitator at the Getty Research Institute in
                     Los Angeles, CA. He is also Co-Director of the Coin Finds of Ukraine project,
                     which digitizes classical Greek coin finds on the territory of modern Ukraine.
                     His interests span technology (ancient and modern), the digital humanities,
                     numismatics, and ancient Greek social/political history. Recent publications
                     include "Coercive Labouring Economies—10,000 BCE to 500 CE" (A Cultural History
                     of Slavery and Human Trafficking, Bloomsbury 2024) and “Digital Technology in
                     Historical Research: Contemporary Scholarly Current” (Eastern European
                     Historical Herald, 2024).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Ilia Curto <dhq:family>Pelle</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0009-0005-9992-9227<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Princeton University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ilia Curto Pelle is a first-year PhD student at the History department of
                     Princeton University. His primary interest lies in the study of economic
                     networks and exchange in the Eastern Mediterranean between the 5th and 10th
                     centuries. He has also worked with the FLAME Project in the roles of Assistant
                     Coordinator and Project Manager since the start of 2020.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000770<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Digital Humanities </item>
                  <item>digital numismatics</item>
                  <item>digital humanities projects</item>
                  <item>late antiquity</item>
                  <item>numismatics</item>
                  <item>Roman Empire</item>
                  <item>economic history</item>
                  <item>digital humanities methodology</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000770/000770.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>FLAME is an online digital humanities project providing economic data for
               investigations of the transition from Late Antiquity to the Early Middle Ages (CE
               325-750) in Western Eurasia and North Africa. While accumulating, entering, and
               displaying the data, the project’s leadership has become increasingly aware of the
               inherent distortions in these data. These deviations operate on various levels, from
               the disparate events that provide the coin finds that serve as the basis of its data
               to previously unexamined scholarly biases that underpin such a quantitative approach
               to historical analysis. By systematically examining these phenomena, we hope to frame
               a discussion of such inherent biases in other digital humanities undertakings.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>


         <div>
            <head>Introduction </head>

            <p>When did antiquity end and when did Western Eurasia become medieval? FLAME (Framing
               the Late Antique and Medieval Economy), a collaborative digital humanities project
               based at Princeton University, aims to provide answers to this question through the
               examination of coin data from the period of this transition — roughly 325–750 CE.
               FLAME gathers as much coin-find evidence as possible, digitizes it, and visualizes
               the results. In a series of conferences, we have examined this period and reflected
               upon the possibilities that FLAME raises for framing (or re-framing) the discussion
               of the ancient economy.</p>

            <p>In this paper, we outline the shape of FLAME, starting with its questions and
               motivations and describing its methodology and presentation. We highlight several
               issues that demonstrate more general challenges to digital humanities projects,
               particularly those that synthesize large and disparate bodies of evidence. We explore
               the issue of systematic bias across our project layers. Beginning with the ancient
               evidence itself, we suggest a typology of the bias that we have dealt with in the
               course of the project, including biases that result from the project design itself.
               We conclude that this bias creates insuperable obstacles for certain kinds of goals,
               such as comprehensiveness, or even acceptable levels of representation for certain
               regions, in pursuing big-data analysis in ancient history. The data is significant,
               but there are also important lessons to be learned from its defects: among them how
               to present systematic bias to users, as well as how to use data in ways that account
               for identified biases. </p>
         </div>

         <div>

            <head>1. Introduction to the FLAME project</head>
            <div>
               <head/>
               <div>

                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">The question of the late antique - early medieval
                        transition</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>The nature of the transformation of Western Eurasia from the “ancient world” to
                     the beginning of the medieval one has long been debated. With the development
                     of scholarship, the types of the evidence used to attempt to answer this
                     question have continuously expanded. The classic studies on this subject, from
                        <ptr target="#gibbon_1776"/> to <ptr target="#dopsch_1923"/> and <ptr
                        target="#pirenne_1922"/>, based their arguments to a great extent on the
                     sparse literary and legal sources that survive from the fourth through the
                     eighth centuries CE. At the beginning of the twenty-first century, two major
                     works brought material culture into the conversation: <ptr
                        target="#mc_cormick_2001"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">Origins of the European Economy: Communications and Commerce,
                        A.D. 300-900 </hi> and <ptr target="#wickham_2005"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">Framing the Early Middle Ages: Europe and the Mediterranean,
                        400-800</hi>. McCormick cited the importation of Arabic and Byzantine
                     coinage into Europe c. 750-900 as one of the catalysts of the development of a
                     distinctive European economy, but otherwise ignored earlier monetary
                     developments and was more anecdotal than systematic in his use of the evidence
                     of coin finds to illustrate commercial relations.<note> Cf. <ptr
                           target="#smith_2003"/>. For a critical view of the use of numismatic
                        evidence, <ptr target="#stahl_2003"/>.</note> Wickham avoided McCormick’s
                     Eurocentric approach and used a meticulous study of ceramic manufacture and
                     distribution to establish patterns of continuity and rupture of exchange around
                     the Mediterranean. He was explicit in his intention to eschew numismatic
                     analysis, explaining his decision in a footnote that expressed hope that future
                     studies would examine coinage more carefully.<note>
                        <ptr target="#wickham_2005" loc="702"/> n. 17: <quote rend="inline">Coinage
                           is … the other artisanal product which has been used as an economic guide
                           … I have relied on it less than on ceramics, in part to avoid an
                           over-complex exposition; in part because it is often unclear how much
                           coin distributions tell us about economics as opposed to the structures
                           of public administration and of diplomatic gift exchange … All the same,
                           coinage is a crucial indicator, and I would hope that future comparative
                           studies give it proper weight</quote>. </note>
                  </p>

                  <p>The outlines of the changes in minting from antiquity to the Middle Ages have
                     long been clear. In the fourth century CE, the Roman Empire, which controlled
                     the Mediterranean and beyond in antiquity, had been using a trimetallic system
                     of gold, silver, and bronze in the Mediterranean world, while its Sasanian
                     (Persian) rival to the East used a currency that consisted almost entirely of
                     silver. By the eighth century, monetary economies in the region morphed into
                     new forms and standards. A silver-based monetary economy developed in Europe, a
                     bimetallic one of gold and bronze in Byzantium in the northeast Mediterranean,
                     and a trimetallic system in the extensive lands of the Umayyads in the greater
                     MENA (Middle East and North Africa) region. The extent and volume of the
                     circulation of the coins that these economies used can be determined only from
                     a careful compilation and study of modern coin finds. Although digital tools
                     facilitate the analysis and visualization of the resulting patterns in the
                     literature, an understanding of the underlying forces shaping this data is
                     necessary. Only a critical reflection on the processes that led to the
                     deposition, excavation, study, and compilation of late antique coins can help
                     overcome the biases inherent in these processes and contribute to the
                     historical narrative of the period.</p>

                  <p>FLAME was formed in 2013, in the context of the annual Stone Lectures at
                     Princeton which Chris Wickham delivered. It began as an explicit attempt to
                     take Wickham’s aforementioned footnote to illuminate the economic history of
                     western Eurasia from the fourth to eighth century by assembling and presenting
                     numismatic data. From the beginning, its creators conceived it as a resource
                     database, that is, making the data available to others online but also meeting
                     and managing the expectation of a broader audience than its creators.<note> For
                           <q>resource database</q>, see also <ptr target="#lockyear_2016" loc="160"
                        />.</note> In retrospect, the project’s inception influenced several
                     subsequent biases.<note> For a comparative account of how the beginning of a
                        digital numismatics project influences its later development, see <ptr
                           target="#gruber_lockyear_2015"/>.</note> Although FLAME began with the
                     necessary academic expertise in numismatics, represented by Princeton’s
                     numismatist, Alan Stahl, who came up with the idea for the project, the early
                     stages of the project did not include any digital technical expertise and
                     included rudimentary and unstandardized Excel files. Then-graduate student Lee
                     Mordechai <q>grew</q> into the role of technical director over time. As a
                     result, FLAME developed organically and benefitted from formal expertise in the
                     digital humanities only after a couple of years. Most initial members were
                     postdocs and graduate students affiliated with Princeton at the time. Project
                     development was inconsistent until the hiring of Mark Pyzyk as full-time
                     project manager in 2020. The subsequent regular discussions in the project’s
                     weekly meetings were crucial in thinking about and fleshing out the biases
                     underlying FLAME, as well as attempts to resolve them and how to communicate
                     them to FLAME’s audience. FLAME’s leadership defined the temporal delimitation
                     of the project to c. 325-750 CE and divided the project into two consecutive
                     stages that would examine the simpler question of coin minting and the far more
                     complex problem of coin circulation. </p>

                  <p>As FLAME operated for several years without funding, its leadership prioritized
                     rapid data collection which would both serve as a proof-of-concept for
                     subsequent funding, as well as producing results that its many non-tenured
                     members could use in their research. In retrospect, this decision introduced
                     and amplified existing (but then unrecognized) biases. For example, each member
                     of FLAME was given responsibility for a defined region of western Eurasia. They
                     worked independently of each other, coordinating with the leadership. This
                     accelerated data gathering but probably also sharpened differences between
                     regions, compounding the problems in regional biases (see below). Although many
                     additional contributors have joined FLAME over the years, the rationale
                     underlying the project’s spatial division remains an organizing principle and
                     the project’s temporal limits have not moved. From an early stage, the project
                     decided to focus on a few key variables relevant to its driving questions and
                     ignore others. For example, FLAME records a coin’s metal but ignores its
                     weight, as well as descriptions of text or images it might bear. This was
                     another decision that expedited data gathering, but it also resulted in fewer
                     variables for cross-checking and made it more difficult to address some of the
                     project’s subsequent biases. A key subsequent decision, taken a few years
                     later, was to import data from other digital sources - again greatly increasing
                     the amount of data in FLAME but introducing its own biases (discussed
                     below).</p>

                  <p>Today, FLAME’s application provides comprehensive data to its users while also
                     highlighting the many gaps in current scholarly knowledge. It encourages
                     historians and other users to be more cognizant of these unknowns and their
                     implications, fostering a more methodological and transparent approach to the
                     study of the economic aspects of the transition between Late Antiquity and the
                     Middle Ages. This paper focuses on the methodological and theoretical
                     contribution of FLAME to the broader discourse in the digital humanities.</p>
               </div>

               <div>

                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Technical Approach</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>FLAME experimented with several different data structures before settling on
                     its current format. FLAME’s core is a relational database (SQL Server). Project
                     members add to and edit the database through an Admin Panel website, developed
                     in JavaScript. The public version of this website includes a list of possible
                     values for FLAME’s key variables such as metal, denomination and mint.<note>
                        <ref target="http://csla100w.princeton.edu:83/"
                           >http://csla100w.princeton.edu:83/</ref>. </note> Automatic tests within
                     the Admin Panel highlight potential issues with existing entries — for example,
                     coins with dates outside the project’s range — which require additional
                     attention from project contributors and administrators. </p>

                  <p>FLAME’s users interact with a graphic user interface (GUI). The GUI is based on
                     a map, developed in ArcGIS and JavaScript, on which the project’s data is
                     displayed. A side panel allows users to run advanced searches and place filters
                     on the data, with most results displayed on the map. Additional results may
                     appear in tabular or graph formats. FLAME’s design encourages exploration of
                     the results through customization. For example, when visualizing the coinage
                     output of a mint over time in a histogram, users can color-code different
                     elements based on the metallic content of coins minted in that location; the
                     data behind the histogram can then be exported in several formats (e.g. CSV,
                     XLS).</p>

                  <p>FLAME has imported data from other projects and datasets. Some of these
                     projects are openly accessible online. Others consist of data collected by
                     individuals, who then decided to donate it to FLAME. The decision to import
                     data resulted in an increase in the size of FLAME’s database by an order of
                     magnitude but also led to multiple challenges in using and maintaining these
                     data (see below for biases). Each of these datasets is idiosyncratic in its
                     coverage and data structure, so FLAME converts the data to its own format using
                     custom-built scripts. Since these other projects and datasets are continuously
                     updated but have no API (Application Programming Interface), the process is
                     undertaken on an ad hoc basis, using custom-written scrapers and data
                     transformations, leaving the resultant data unlinked except for a reference URL
                     on FLAME’s side for users wishing to follow entries back to their source. For
                     this reason, FLAME keeps a record of the dataset, from which the information is
                     derived. Since the data is not linked according to a wider linked open data
                     standard, the same data points could appear in two different datasets with
                     different names. As digital numismatic projects operate autonomously, two or
                     more databases could and often do end up containing the same coin finds but
                     digitized and classified them according to different criteria, depending on the
                     idiosyncratic goals or structure of these projects. To evaluate potential
                     duplicate data, FLAME developed an additional program that suggests possible
                     duplicates, which are then checked by project staff.<note> This program was
                        developed by Mary Alice Jouve in 2022 at Princeton University.</note>
                  </p>

                  <p>Beginning in parallel to FLAME’s public launch in 2021, the project has begun
                     to place more emphasis on User Experience (UX) to make the site and web
                     applications more user-friendly. FLAME’s leadership has periodically observed
                     and interviewed potential users — specialist and non-specialist academics, as
                     well as some students. These interviews have resulted in changes to the
                     public-facing user interface (UI), as well as the development of new features.
                     The emphasis on UX developed further through collaboration with the University
                     of Houston’s SYRIOS project, a National Endowment for the Humanities-funded
                     project that illustrates the history of ancient Syria through coinage.<note>
                        FLAME provided UX testers to Houston’s students in a user experience course.
                        Testing was conducted on FLAME’s Circulation Module as part of the
                        development of a future mapping tool for the SYRIOS project. For more
                        information on SYRIOS, see: <ref target="https://syrios.uh.edu/"
                           >https://syrios.uh.edu/</ref>.</note>
                  </p>

                  <p>Within the typology of digital humanities projects, FLAME shares some of its
                     characteristics with other projects that work with material culture, and more
                     specifically projects that focus on numismatics.<note> See also Breier 2010 for
                        the connections between archaeology (i.e. broader material culture) and
                        numismatics with regards to specifically GIS databases.</note> As such,
                     FLAME’s development coincides with that of several other digital projects
                     concerned with ancient numismatics. These projects were generally developed
                     organically as digital versions of traditional reference publications that
                     include as much data as possible that conform to certain criteria. Thus, for
                     example, the Online Coins of the Roman Empire (OCRE) represents a catalog of
                     all coin types minted in the Roman Empire until 491 CE and was based on the
                     Roman Imperial Coinage (RIC) series of reference works. Other projects include
                     the Coin Hoards of the Roman Empire (CHRE) project, which aims to collect all
                     the information about coin hoards in the Roman Empire and beyond between c. 30
                     BCE and 400 CE, and the Portable Antiquities Scheme (PAS), which includes
                     archaeological objects found in England and Wales — mostly finds made and
                     reported by the public, including coins. Both these projects collected new
                     material and had no published precedent, but were nonetheless perceived as
                     digital versions of printed catalogs. </p>

                  <p>FLAME shares some of its core features with these projects. For example, like
                     FLAME, both the CHRE and PAS projects include a GUI, but unlike FLAME, both
                     CHRE and PAS place more emphasis on their data than their visual
                     representation. Both are also similar to FLAME in their data structure,
                     separating data at the level of individual coins and finds of coins found
                     within a common archaeological context. These approaches emerged organically in
                     different projects, resulting in different architectures. A subsequent
                     collaborative ontology, nomisma.org, was later established in an attempt to
                     provide stable digital representations of numismatic concepts between these and
                     other numismatic projects. Projects such as OCRE and PAS have organized at
                     least some of their data in a Nomisma-compliant manner, although the many
                     technical challenges have slowed collaboration, including with FLAME.<note>
                        <ref target="http://nomisma.org/datasets">http://nomisma.org/datasets</ref>.
                        Challenges include the high technical skill needed to meet the entry-level
                        for fitting data to the nomisma.org structure and the difficulties (and
                        cost) of revising existing projects to conform to this structure. This will
                        be discussed in depth in a future publication. </note>
                  </p>

                  <p>Other digital numismatic projects focus almost always on a single political
                     entity (e.g., the Roman Empire) and/or a limited region (e.g., France). FLAME,
                     however, attempts to push the discussion forward by aggregating and harmonizing
                     data from different sources during a time of major change in its database.
                     Other numismatic projects facilitate answering numismatic research questions,
                     such as classifying coins into types, attempting to provide digital catalogs of
                     coins that share some variable, or finding patterns across coin finds.<note>
                        See for example <ptr target="#lockyear_2016" loc="165"/>.</note> FLAME, on
                     the other hand, has as its core a historical question — the nature of the Late
                     Roman to Medieval transition — that is primarily concerned with change over
                     time whether through coin production (i.e. how many coins were produced) or
                     coin circulation (i.e. which coins circulated where). This has heightened our
                     sensitivity to data biases — regional, temporal, and compositional with respect
                     to coin find contents — at the level of project design. While our digital
                     numismatic colleagues are all well aware of these topics (we are under no
                     illusions here), FLAME has been incentivized by the nature of its starting
                     questions to dig deeper into these factors: how, otherwise, could we claim to
                     accurately pursue our main question?</p>
               </div>

            </div>

            <div>

               <head>2. Issues of bias</head>

               <p>Over several years of working on FLAME’s development, reflecting on its features,
                  and receiving feedback from colleagues, we have concluded that FLAME’s data
                  contains serious gaps, reflecting biases that affect all stages in the process of
                  discovering, preserving and publishing coins. In theory, numismatics seems like an
                  ideal candidate for digitization because some of its variables–such as the number
                  of coins found or the year in which a coin was minted–are easily quantifiable and
                  thus facilitate further analyses. Although some earlier publications treated
                  biases in digital numismatics anecdotally, providing little empirical data or
                  theoretical reflection on them, there has been little systematic analysis on
                  issues addressing entire assemblages of numismatic materials.<note> An overview of
                     the use of data from finds and their use in the reconstruction of circulation
                     as a basis for historical inference can be found in <ptr target="#howgego_1995"
                        loc="88–95"/>. More focused on the period covered by FLAME are the chapters
                     in <ptr target="#naismith_2018b"/>, especially <ptr target="#naismith_2018a"/>
                     and <ptr target="#rovelli_2018"/>. See also <ptr target="#naismith_2011"
                        loc="199–251"/>. Such discussions consider the different types of evidence
                     supplied by hoards and excavations, but do not explore the issues involved with
                     comparing records of coin finds from different modern countries or such issues
                     as the differential motivations of archaeologists in what they choose to
                     excavate and to publish. Nor do they deal with the questions introduced by the
                     assembly of large amounts of data from multiple sources.</note> However, a
                  closer look at the numismatic evidence collected in the field — FLAME’s basic data
                  — reveals several types of biases, which we originally assumed could be minimized
                  through the accumulation of data. Once we had about a million coins in our
                  database, we believed, our database would be a more or less acceptable proxy for
                  the coins that were produced and circulated in Late Antiquity. In retrospect, this
                  view was naive. At present we believe that many of the biases we describe are
                  intractable in the near future and that tackling them would require significant
                  targeted research. As a result, despite the amount of data it contains, FLAME is
                  not a representative sample of the ancient monetary circulation. </p>

               <p>We treat bias below on a spectrum of proximity to the ancient past. That is, the
                  closer the bias is to the historical material we propose to examine–e.g.,
                  individual transactions of coins, the burial of hoards, and so on–the more primary
                  we consider it. Critically, we insist on counting FLAME itself as a source of bias
                  that stands between researchers and the ancient past, sitting at the furthest
                  remove from the historical processes we provide insight into.<note> There is a
                     long methodological literature on the practice of history and the historian’s
                     standing in relation to the past. Post-war historiography — for instance, <ptr
                        target="#collingwood_1946"/>; <ptr target="#carr_1961"/>; <ptr
                        target="#oakeshott_1983"/>; <ptr target="#white_1986"/> — focuses intensely
                     on the problem of historical objectivity. Much of this tradition is helpfully
                     synthesized in <ptr target="#novick_1988"/>. We do not engage directly with
                     this literature in the present article, but the notion of a fundamental
                     disconnect between historians and historical material, and the alienation of
                     the past from investigators in the present, stems from this 20th-century
                     scholarship.</note> Figure 1 below summarizes some of the biases that shaped
                  the patterns of the survival of coins of which scholarship is aware. It utilizes
                     <q>corpora</q> of coins - with a corpus consisting of a group of coins that
                  share some key characteristic (e.g. all coins found in southern France or all
                  coins produced in Constantinople). The figure demonstrates that only a tiny
                  fraction of coins survives and enters scholarly awareness. </p>


               <figure>
                  <head>The figure proceeds from left to right.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png" style="width: 700px"/>
               </figure>

               <p>The shaded area highlights the decrease from the total number of coins minted in
                  Late Antiquity on the left to the number represented in the FLAME database on the
                  right. In each of the three corpora (e.g., regions) the number of coins is reduced
                  over time for various reasons — some do not enter or survive in the soil and
                  others are not excavated or published. Within the figure, Corpus 1 is partially
                  excavated but never published; Some of the coins from Corpus 2 survive to appear
                  in FLAME; and Corpus 3 is partially published but FLAME utilizes it only in a
                  limited manner. The figure is not drawn to scale; while the amount of coins
                  produced at any point in Late Antiquity or the Early Middle Ages is unknown,
                  comparative evidence suggests that only an extremely small fraction of coins (i.e.
                  far less than 1%) produced would be reported in scholarship.</p>

               <p>In the following section, we introduce four classes of bias: primary, secondary,
                  tertiary, and FLAME project bias. We begin, however, with Regional Bias (see next
                  section), as we believe that this methodological <q>layer</q> best illustrates the
                  complexities of the problem. While it is useful to think about proximity to the
                  past as a factor in data bias, Regional Bias shows that we must not fool ourselves
                  into isolating these categories from one another.</p>



               <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Regional Bias</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Much of the bias in FLAME’s data emerges from regional differences rooted in
                     modern national or institutional factors, such as law, cultural organization,
                     national historical memory, or political circumstance — to say nothing of
                     economic reality. These national differences strongly influence the discovery,
                     preservation, and publication of archaeological objects. The absence of a
                     substantive rule of law can be ruinous to the cultural heritage of a region.
                     The most common form that this takes is the looting and selling of artifacts.
                     Such trade in looted goods has been regulated internationally since 1970 but
                     with unequal implementation.<note> Specifically through the <hi rend="italic"
                           >UNESCO Convention on the Means of Prohibiting and Preventing the Illicit
                           Import, Export and Transfer of Ownership of Cultural Property</hi>. Of
                        course, implementation of the convention is left up to individual states
                        that are signatories to the treaty. In the United States, the issue is
                        governed primarily through the <hi rend="italic">Convention on Cultural
                           Property Implementation Act</hi> of 1982.</note> Those artifacts that are
                     not effectively controlled make their way through various channels to an
                     enormous market of collectors. In a global context, the vast majority of
                     countries are significantly affected by artifact looting. Even countries like
                     France, the United Kingdom, or the United States, which more effectively
                     regulate objects found within their borders, serve as an endpoint for artifacts
                     illicitly exported from other nations.<note>
                        <ptr target="#davis-marks_2020"/>; <ptr target="#mead_2020"/>.</note>
                     Ongoing warfare can also degrade or destroy a country’s cultural heritage.
                     Thus, regions such as Syria, Libya, and more recently Ukraine have suffered
                     serious loss of heritage objects and structures.<note> For Libya: <ptr
                           target="#brodie_2019"/>, <ptr target="#kane_2015"/> and <ptr
                           target="#mugnai_et_al_2017"/>. For Syria: <ptr target="#almohamad_2021"/>
                        and <ptr target="#casana_2015"/>. Ukraine’s loss of cultural heritage due to
                        war is more recent — scholarship will no doubt emerge over the coming years
                        regarding its extent.</note>
                  </p>

                  <p>The circumstances particular to each region can be easily observed on FLAME’s
                     map of coin finds. Thus, FLAME’s users might be surprised to see that Italy and
                     Turkey at present contain considerably fewer coin finds in FLAME than England
                     and France. Italy and Turkey were far more central components in the late
                     antique monetized macro-economy and therefore we would expect them to be better
                     represented. That this is not the case is probably the result of modern
                     regional biases, rather than any ancient pattern of circulation and deposition.
                     FLAME has attempted to lessen such disparities, for example, through the
                     establishment of coordinated teams in such under-reported areas. </p>

                  <figure>
                     <head>Global distribution of coin finds in FLAME.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png" style="width: 700px"/>
                  </figure>


                  <p>Numismatists with knowledge of these regions will be mostly unsurprised by
                     this. Most are aware that archaeological and scholarly circumstances are more
                     favorable in some places than in others. The question is why. Though a tempting
                     guess, it is not always a matter of wealth. Italy, for example, is a wealthy
                     country with a dynamic academic culture and a strong interest in excavating and
                     publishing archaeological materials on its territory. And yet we find
                     comparatively little published material there compared to some other countries.
                     On the other hand, Romania–significantly poorer today than Italy, but even more
                     so under communism–is among the best-excavated and published numismatic
                     contexts in Europe for late Roman coins. This was because its communist
                     government was strongly invested in establishing Romania’s <q>Roman</q> roots
                     and devoted enormous resources to supporting archaeological work, including
                     coin evidence, that furthered this ideological objective.</p>

                  <p>FLAME has approached this problem by investigating why a given region looks the
                     way that it does in FLAME. Answers are rarely simple and often require
                     considering the legal, political, and historical contexts that have shaped the
                     disciplinary histories and coin publication records of the region. These
                     factors have remained largely invisible to non-experts and seldom discussed in
                     publication, even among specialists. </p>
               </div>




               <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Case Study: The United Kingdom</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>One of the best examples of such regional bias can be found in the United
                     Kingdom, which shows the influence of politics and law on the shape of modern
                     scholarship not only externally, in relation to other countries, but internally
                     as well. This bias explains the stark differences in coin finds reported in
                     England and Wales versus Scotland and Northern Ireland (discussed further
                     below).</p>

                  <figure>
                     <head>Coin find distribution in the British Isles and Northwestern
                        France.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg" style="width: 700px"/>
                  </figure>


                  <p>The main force behind this distortion has been the Portable Antiquities Scheme,
                     a government program operating since 1997 within the parameters of several
                     national heritage laws but in particular the Treasure Act — which deals with
                     archaeological finds of precious metal objects.<note> A recent (2023) amendment
                        to the Treasure Act would allow any metal object of exceptional
                        historical/value to be defined as treasure. This would close the loophole
                        that allowed exceptional items such as the Crosby Garrett Helmet (an
                        extremely rare example of a Roman bronze cavalry helmet) to be sold on the
                        market, in this case for the equivalent of $3.6 million in 2010. </note> The
                     PAS regulates and (sometimes controversially) incentivizes the discovery and
                     reporting of archaeological objects found by private individuals. While
                     individuals are required by law to report significant discoveries of more than
                     a single coin if gold or silver, or more than ten base metal (i.e. bronze)
                     coins, the PAS framework facilitates the process, preventing some of the more
                     important archaeological objects from being funneled into gray and black
                     markets. The objects are first inspected by local authorities — Field Liaison
                     Officers (FLOs) — who analyze, categorize, photograph, and record the objects
                     in an online database .<note>
                        <ref target="https://finds.org.uk/database"
                           >https://finds.org.uk/database</ref>.</note> Under most circumstances,
                     the reporters will receive the objects back, at which point they are free to do
                     with them what they want - and many do sell their finds to museums or on the
                     market. This process is arguably a great incentive for them to report their
                     finds or at least removes significant disincentives to doing so. The PAS is
                     therefore a point of contrast to the many countries where found artifacts are
                     considered the property of the state, with no (or limited) compensation offered
                     to finders. The data gleaned from the process is published by PAS online,
                     freely and openly. This has meant huge gains in coin find data for England and
                     Wales in the years since its adoption.</p>

                  <p>This bias is obvious when comparing England, a peripheral and minor part of the
                     Atlantic-Mediterranean macro-economy for much of the period FLAME covers, with
                     Mediterranean countries. Thus, England and Wales’s 1355 coin finds far
                     outnumber those of core economic regions in antiquity like Italy (467), Turkey
                     (265), and Egypt (74). This has much to do with the structure of reporting in
                     the UK, as well as the resources — and the legal enforcement efforts — devoted
                     to making the system work. As we mentioned earlier, because Scotland and
                     Northern Ireland do not participate in the PAS, the publication of coin finds
                     discovered on their territory lags significantly behind England and Wales. This
                     leads to a significant distortion in the British data encoded in FLAME; at the
                     moment, FLAME records almost nothing about coin circulation in the United
                     Kingdom outside of England and Wales. The British case study therefore
                     demonstrates the extent of some of the biases underlying intra- and
                     international variations within FLAME’s data, biases that would remain unknown
                     by most of the project’s users.</p>

               </div>




               <div>

                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Primary biases (ancient) </hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>The regional biases discussed above are a modern phenomenon. But other biases
                     lie much closer to the materials themselves and to the ancient economic
                     activity of which they were a part. What we define as primary biases derive
                     from lived experience in Late Antiquity and the early medieval period. Since we
                     cannot fully reconstruct lived experience in the past, many of these biases are
                     theoretical. Therefore, we must use proxies to answer questions about, e.g.,
                     the differential loss of coins. The few scholarly attempts made to understand
                     the effects of primary biases on the modern numismatic landscape (i.e., the
                     coins that scholars are left to work with in the present) have generally based
                     their studies on theoretical models derived from modern economic
                        phenomena.<note> Many of these questions focus less on numismatic materials
                        themselves and more on problems inherent in theoretical models meant to fill
                        in large-scale historical gaps — for instance, statistical formulae designed
                        to infer the size of the ancient coin supply from the meager evidence left
                        to us today. For scholarship critiquing efforts at reconstructing Roman
                        Republican monetary production by <ptr target="#crawford_1974 "/>and <ptr
                           target="#hopkins_1980"/>, see: <ptr target="#buttrey_1993"/>; <ptr
                           target="#de_callataÿ_1995"/>; <ptr target="#howgego_1992"/>; <ptr
                           target="#katsari_2003"/>; <ptr target="#lockyear_1999"/>. While other
                        articles appear on topics such as randomness in coin survival (e.g. <ptr
                           target="#robertson_1986"/>), no methodological topic other than ancient
                        monetary production has received the widespread and sustained attention of
                        numismatists. </note> The vast differences between societies over time,
                     however, obstruct such an analogy. For example, there are obvious issues
                     inherent in comparing a monetary economy, where transactions and taxes were
                     paid in precious metal coins, to one where payments are primarily in credit and
                     most cash denominations are bills.</p>

                  <p>In the pre-modern world, coins served as means of exchange and holders of
                     wealth; they were issued in three metals (alloys based on gold, silver, and
                     copper, respectively) and in various denominations (standards of fineness and
                     weight holding a fixed value in the monetary system, e.g., in the contemporary
                     United States, coins of 1, 5, 10, 25, or 50 cents). At various times and places
                     in antiquity, certain metals and denominations were available, corresponding to
                     different sectors and levels of economic activity. In general, gold-based
                     coinages were used for extraordinary, costly transactions (e.g., purchases of
                     land) and constituted the principal medium for storing wealth. Copper-based
                     coins were used for everyday transactions. Silver-based coinages, between gold
                     and copper in value, were used for salaries and middle-range purchases, and
                     could also facilitate day-to-day exchanges and larger purchases. </p>

                  <p>Virtually all ancient and medieval coins available for collecting and study
                     have spent most of the time since their minting underground. They may have been
                     buried intentionally or accidentally. The chief reason for intentionally
                     burying coins in antiquity was that there were few alternatives to save wealth
                     securely. Pre-modern societies rarely had any form of deposit banking, and so
                     individuals or institutions usually put saved coins along with other precious
                     objects into a vessel, burying them somewhere they could be dug up when needed.
                     Such <q>hoards</q> frequently comprised the highest-value coins available to
                     whoever hid them. Hoarding was relatively common in the pre-modern world,
                     though perhaps more so in times of perceived insecurity (e.g., war). If the
                     burier failed to retrieve the coins, they might come down to us as a hoard.
                     Other intentional contexts for coin deposits would be the burial of individuals
                     or other ritual offerings. Such cultural practices lead to biases in the coins
                     that survive up to our times — for example, the clear bias towards high-value
                     gold and silver coins in most hoard finds. </p>

                  <p>Other coins ended up in the ground through a different mode — accidental loss.
                     The vast majority of coins found in excavations and single finds — which
                     represent random accidental losses — are copper. The simple act of accidentally
                     dropping a coin during a transaction or travel would have been the first step
                     in this process, but the likelihood that the person would have recognized the
                     loss and retrieved the coin is far more likely in the case of high-value coins,
                     especially in antiquity where a single gold coin could be worth hundreds of
                     bronze coins. Also important is the fact that copper is often less bright in
                     color than gold or silver. As artificial lighting was rare, many transactions
                     took place outdoors in dusty or muddy locations that were close to the color of
                     copper. Such coins were less likely than gold or silver to attract the
                     attention of passersby. Another factor in the predominance of copper coins in
                     archaeological contexts is their generally fiduciary nature; that is, their
                     value was dependent on the state’s commitment to convertibility into precious
                     metal coinage. In cases of demonetization, for example as part of a coinage
                     reform, such coins would be worthless and might be casually discarded. Within
                     this context, silver coins issued within a tri-metallic system might be
                     significantly under-represented in modern samples since they were noticeable
                     enough to be observed and retrieved when lost (as opposed to copper), but not
                     valuable enough to be well-represented in hoards (as opposed to gold).</p>
               </div>



               <div>

                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Secondary bias (archaeology)</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>The second class of bias focuses on the archaeological context in which coins
                     are found, as well as the various natural and technical processes at play in a
                     coin’s survival over time and its subsequent discovery. Excavations are the
                     most common legal context from which buried coins are intentionally retrieved.
                     Within excavations, coins are valued as chronological indicators for a
                     particular archaeological layer. Most excavation coins are presumed to be the
                     result of unintentional loss and so, as sketched out above, are usually
                     copper-based and small. They are often in bad physical shape owing to wear
                     (since they were used daily), direct contact with corrosive environments (e.g.,
                     soil), and the greater susceptibility of copper to corrosion compared to silver
                     or gold. These factors tend to coincide with each other, often corroding coins
                     to the point that they are unreadable. A case in point is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >minimi</hi> of the fifth and sixth centuries CE, a designation for coins of
                     about 10 mm in diameter, often poorly struck in the first place. The
                     categorization of such coins as <hi rend="quotes">unattributed</hi> or <hi
                        rend="quotes">unidentified</hi>, — if they are recognized at all in the
                     course of excavation — is a source of bias on sites, especially when dealing
                     with strata associated with Late Antiquity. On the other hand, prominent
                     features on certain denominations might allow for partial identification. For
                     example, the sixth- and seventh-century Byzantine 40-nummi bronze piece is
                     quite large and heavy and carries a large M which is easily identifiable even
                     if other features are illegible.</p>

                  <figure>
                     <head>The two left images are of a 5 nummi of Justin I (518-527) excavated in
                        Antioch on June 12, 1937; it is 12 mm in diameter - <ref
                           target="https://catalog.princeton.edu/catalog/coin-4308">Coin: 4308 - </ref>
                        <ref target="https://catalog.princeton.edu/numismatics"
                           >https://catalog.princeton.edu/numismatics</ref>
                        <ref target="https://catalog.princeton.edu/catalog/coin-4308">.</ref> The
                        two images on the right are of a 40 nummi piece of Justin I (518-527),
                        purchased from Peter J. Donald; it is 33 mm in diameter: <ref
                           target="https://figgy.princeton.edu/catalog/4b89031e-fef8-423d-833a-184a26f25818"
                           >Coin: 17215 - </ref>
                        <ref target="https://catalog.princeton.edu/numismatics"
                           >https://catalog.princeton.edu/numismatics.</ref></head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg" style="width: 700px"/>
                  </figure>


                  <p>A further source of bias among coins from excavations is the process of site
                     selection by archaeologists. Some of these are limited by definition - for
                     example, built-over areas in modern cities generally allow for only limited
                     archaeological excavations. Moreover, Late Antiquity, the period FLAME
                     investigates, has traditionally attracted less scholarly and public interest
                     than e.g. Greco-Roman antiquity, a period that remains the focus of many
                     excavated sites, or sectors within larger excavations. In FLAME’s case, this
                     probably contributes to the sharp reduction in coin finds between the beginning
                     and end of the period, with which the project is concerned. This imbalance in
                     the results of excavations often stems from ideological interests (for example,
                     demonstrating the level of civilization or identity of certain site
                     inhabitants). This might operate at the level of the archaeologists, those
                     granting funding or permits for excavations, or both. For instance, it is
                     common for excavations in Greece or Turkey for much of the 20th century to
                     bulldoze (often literally) through levels associated with medieval or late
                     antique remains, usually to reach Hellenistic and Classical layers, which
                     scholars, funders, and governments considered more prestigious. This affected
                     not only what came out of the ground, but where it went (into a bucket or a
                     museum showcase), as well as how it was preserved, cataloged, studied, and
                     published.</p>

                  <p>Besides excavation contexts, coins are often discovered in hoard contexts.
                     Hoards are typically defined as two or more coins thought to have been buried
                     together, often in a vessel or other container, which exhibit a radically
                     different pattern of coin preservation. As hoards were usually buried in
                     secret, they are often found outside of habitation areas excavated by
                     archaeologists. In the nineteenth century, hoards were frequently discovered by
                     farmers as the result of adopting deeper plows or through exploitation of areas
                     that had been abandoned since the Middle Ages. The expansion of urban areas –
                     with their deeper digging for infrastructure (e.g. building foundations,
                     sewers, utilities, etc.) – as well as transportation routes (e.g. roads and
                     railways) resulted in more hoard finds as well. In more recent times, the use
                     of metal detectors has greatly increased the rate at which such finds are made
                     (hence the phenomenon of “detectorists” in the United Kingdom, who are a major
                     constituent of the aforementioned Treasure Act and PAS policies). Whether such
                     coins are brought to the attention of government authorities or local
                     numismatists varies greatly depending on legislation and policy, and is a major
                     source of bias affecting FLAME’s database and circulation map, as discussed
                     above.</p>
               </div>



               <div>

                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tertiary (scholarship)</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>A third class of bias derives from the scholarship upon which FLAME draws, in
                     particular its unevenness in key variables such as the number of publications
                     (e.g. articles, archaeological reports) or the ratio of excavated-to-published
                     coin finds. These biases are also largely intractable as they stem from broader
                     trends in scholarship and publication practices (e.g., who studies what? Who
                     publishes, where and for what reasons?). </p>

                  <p>In light of modern academia’s pressures on scholars’ time, researchers must
                     decide how to allocate limited time and attention. This touches upon, but is
                     not the same as, the archaeological biases discussed above. Scholarly bias may
                     take the form of prioritizing certain academic activities over others.
                     Archaeologists, for example, often prioritize excavating sites over publishing
                     the results. Because of this, many sites that are excavated are not — and
                     likely will not be — published. A 2001 survey of archaeological excavations in
                     Israel revealed that fewer than 20 percent of excavations carried out in the
                     seasons between 1970–1989 had published their results.<note>
                        <ptr target="#kletter_de-groot_2001"/>. </note> Similarly, the major salvage
                     excavations in Beirut’s city center over the 1990s and 2000s had at least 15
                     different teams excavating over 200 sites. Only a handful of these have been
                     published to date.<note>
                        <ptr target="#mordechai_2019" loc="208–210ff"/>. For a comparison between
                        published and unpublished coins see p. 227 and <ptr target="#abou_2018"
                        />.</note>
                  </p>

                  <p>Similar decisions are made within excavations themselves. For example, as
                     discussed above, researchers decide to excavate certain strata and features and
                     not others based on <hi rend="italic">ad hoc </hi>criteria. In the case of
                     Beirut, the published excavation sites bulldozed the layers above the
                     destruction layer of 551, making it extremely difficult to understand post-551
                     Beirut. Even after the excavation of a site, the numismatic material is often
                     challenging for the average archaeologist to deal with. Although the ideal
                     solution is to bring in a numismatic specialist, in reality many coins remain
                     unpublished because such a specialist is unavailable.</p>

                  <p>Relatively few hoard finds of coins are published after their discovery and
                     many of the publications lack key details like the mint of origin and
                     denomination of the coins. Coins are often deposited with regional
                     archaeological services or local museums; their contents can be reconstructed
                     only by an inspection of such an institution’s accession records or its
                     physical storage facilities. Many, perhaps a majority in some countries, of
                     discovered hoards are immediately dispersed on the collectors market, with no
                     record made of their contents. </p>

                  <p>A further bias derives from the notorious decentralization of numismatic
                     publications, an existing problem exacerbated by FLAME’s scope. Reports of
                     finds can appear in local and relatively inaccessible journals, excavation
                     reports, edited volumes, festschrifts, and journal articles, among others. Many
                     of these are not systematically used for disseminating numismatic research.
                     This phenomenon already makes it difficult to locate all these reports, so that
                     FLAME’s information is more representative of the most accessible publications
                     rather than the whole of numismatic scholarship. It also favors English or
                     other standard research languages (e.g., German over Armenian), often published
                     by Western-oriented presses.</p>

                  <p>There is, in general, no comprehensive centralized resource to track coin
                     finds, even at the national level. Such attempts have been attempted in the
                     past with various levels of success — for example Kropotkin’s survey of Roman
                     and Byzantine coin finds in the Soviet Union or Militky’s equivalent inventory
                     in the Czech Republic.<note>
                        <ptr target="#kropotkin_1961"/>; <ptr target="#kropotkin_1962"/>; <ptr
                           target="#militkỳ_2010"/>. </note> The latter example indicates that
                     additional biases intrude at the sub-national level, with certain counties or
                     regions being better covered than others (Prague, for instance, is hugely
                     overrepresented among Czech coin finds).<note> Drapelova, Pavla, <title
                           rend="quotes">Working on the FLAME database: the Czech
                           Perspective</title>, Talk given at the FLAME conference <hi rend="italic"
                           >Networks in Transition: Monetary Exchange from Antiquity to the Middle
                           Ages</hi>, March 18, 2022.</note> Even the PAS reports of British finds
                     include only material discovered since its inception in 1997; earlier finds
                     have to be added from traditional sources. While there are a few aggregated
                     numismatic publications that aim to report on all recent numismatic
                        papers,<note> E.g. <hi rend="italic">Byzantinische Zeitschrift</hi>, whose
                        annual bibliography goes well beyond the geographic and chronological limits
                        of the Byzantine Empire. <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Literature</hi>, which
                        used to contain an annotated bibliography and index of important
                        publications of coin finds of all eras, was discontinued in 2013. <hi
                           rend="italic">Coin Hoards</hi>, which at first was an independent
                        periodical covering finds of coins of all periods, now focuses only on
                        hoards of ancient Greek coinage.</note> they are rarely comprehensive and
                     tend to briefly survey an enormous number of diverse publications, leading to
                     relatively low resolution. </p>

                  <p>Finally, the unequal products of scholarship resulting from the biases above
                     contribute to biases in reference works – the catalogs and other methodological
                     apparatus most scholars use to identify a coin or better understand a
                     numismatic process. As a general rule of thumb, the more coins are available
                     for study (through publication, ideally), the better the resulting product.
                     There are other factors as well — for example, the popularity of certain topics
                     over others. While good catalogs for Roman imperial coins (e.g. aforementioned
                     Roman Imperial Coinage series) have appeared from the 1920s, their Byzantine
                     equivalents date only to the 1970s. Comprehensive catalogs of Sasanid Persian
                     coins date to the 2000s and are still incomplete today.<note>
                        <ref
                           target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/oeai/forschung/altertumswissenschaften/numismatik/sylloge-nummorum-sasanidarum"
                           >https://www.oeaw.ac.at/oeai/forschung/altertumswissenschaften/numismatik/sylloge-nummorum-sasanidarum</ref>.
                     </note> Other types of coinage — for example that of central Asia — are barely
                     covered by any scholarship. </p>

                  <p>The biases listed above mean that FLAME better represents — in both quality and
                     quantity of information — areas and periods with good reference works such as
                     the Roman Mediterranean compared to areas that are less well covered such as
                     central Asia.</p>
               </div>



               <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">FLAME project biases</hi>
                  </head>

                  <p>Previous sections have described biases in FLAME's data at the level of coinage
                     itself, as well as regional contexts affecting the discovery, preservation, and
                     publication of coin finds. These are, in essence, exogenous to FLAME. There
                     are, however, biases inherent to FLAME itself that involve how the project is
                     structured, institutionally and operationally. </p>

                  <p>Most FLAME researchers are volunteers who provide the numismatic data for
                     regions about which they have some expertise. In general, they work alone,
                     coordinating their activity through project representatives. The participation
                     of such individuals does not, generally, arise in a vacuum, and is structured
                     by pre-existing individual and disciplinary contexts. Many early participants,
                     for example, were Princeton University graduate alumni. Subsequently,
                     volunteers might have seen a conference presentation on the project given by a
                     FLAME representative, or they might have been put in touch by someone with
                     knowledge of the project. Such weak ties follow familiar paths, generally
                     through North American and Western European universities.<note> On weak ties,
                        see <ptr target="#granovetter_1983"/>, 1973). The point is that such
                           <q>acquaintance</q> ties, found in low-density social networks, are
                        important binding agents between different organizations and therefore play
                        a large role in mobility between networks. Conferences, visiting
                        scholarships, and summer seminars are good mechanisms to establish such weak
                        ties.</note> Many contributors were first visiting scholars at Princeton or
                     had passed through programs such as Dumbarton Oaks' numismatic summer seminar
                     (co-taught by Stahl) or that of the American Numismatic Society. Disciplinary
                     and institutional networks play a critical role in the shaping of such work,
                     which favors some regions over others. For example, the authors of this
                     article, who have constituted the leadership of FLAME, all specialize in
                     aspects of northern Mediterranean and European scholarship. When FLAME has
                     attempted research on coin finds in regions where its leadership has fewer ties
                     such as North Africa, the Indian subcontinent, or East Asia, it has run into
                     problems recruiting individuals who might help. These are limitations we have
                     sought to address, with varying degrees of success.</p>

                  <p>In certain cases, enough researchers studied a particular region that it made
                     sense to organize them into clusters working under a regional coordinator. Up
                     to this point, five regional clusters have come together to work on FLAME. This
                     has included groups focused on the Anatolian peninsula, the Iberian peninsula,
                     Southern Italy, Ukraine, as well as a group working at the University of
                     Hamburg focusing on early Islamic coinage. That the last group departs from the
                     typical regional focus is a result of scholarly specialization — most FLAME
                     scholars focus their research on pre-Islamic (e.g., Roman, Byzantine, etc.) or
                     Islamic coins but not both categories.</p>

                  <p>At both the individual and cluster levels, biases affect the data structurally
                     and, occasionally, more or less at random. Structurally, FLAME’s biases
                     intersect with the modern secondary biases that we identified above. Thus, some
                     countries are better able to support individuals and groups of scholars or have
                     particular national priorities that favor the publication and reporting of
                     coins, such as the Romanian example cited above. These factors affect the
                     potential for collaboration with scholars from these countries.</p>

                  <p>There are likewise biases that FLAME imported from other projects (with biases
                     of their own) through their datasets. Examples include the Coin Hoards of the
                     Roman Empire (CHRE), the Portable Antiquities Schema (PAS), Antike Fundmünzen
                     in Europa (AFE), the Early Islamic dataset (EI), and the Thessaloniki dataset
                     (THS). <note>A full list of external data sources, including descriptions of
                        the organization, project, and principal investigators, can be found at:
                           <ref target="https://coinage.princeton.edu/flames-datasets/"
                           >https://coinage.princeton.edu/flames-datasets/</ref>.</note> It is safe
                     to assume that all these projects suffer from many of the same biases we have
                     described above. The extent to which they identify or publish information on
                     these biases varies but is often minimal, and so their specific project biases
                     are largely outside of our capacity to address.</p>


               </div>

            </div>
         </div>



         <div>
            <head>3. Lessons for Digital Humanities</head>

            <p>FLAME demonstrates that while powerful digital tools may help to address
               archaeological and historical topics, they cannot overcome problems in source
               materials. Biases that have plagued different research questions generally persist
               and we are unable to even gauge their severity, except in outline, because we cannot
               say how many materials have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been discovered, reported, or
               published in various regions. This makes the exercise of gauging robustness in late
               antique and medieval coin data more epistemological than technical. In our opinion,
               there is no technical solution to this problem. FLAME itself has introduced its own
               biases to its digital representation of the research question — biases that derive
               from its implementation, visual design, and varied experience of its contributors.
               All in all, many of these issues are intractable and will not be resolved in the
               foreseeable future — a feature we feel FLAME shares with other digital humanities
               projects, which have acknowledged similar biases to varying degrees. The ORBIS
               Project, for instance — a digital itinerary planner and travel-time calculator for
               the Roman world — was significantly affected by project-level biases that led to the
               inclusion of the Black Sea in the project’s data but not the Red Sea.<note> So, while
                  the Black Sea is modeled in ORBIS and mentioned at multiple points in <ptr
                     target="#scheidel_2013"/>, <ptr target="#scheidel_2014"/>, the Red Sea is not.
                  That is in spite of a comparably good guide — that is, comparable to Arrian’s <hi
                     rend="italic">Periplus of the Euxine Sea</hi>, which was the basis for the
                  Black Sea data — being available in the Hellenistic <hi rend="italic">Periplus of
                     the Erythrean Sea</hi>. The difference lay in the composition of project staff.
                  While the Black Sea inclusion was supported by one of the ORBIS participants —
                  Mark Pyzyk — the Red Sea had no comparable advocate and was presumably excluded
                  for this reason.</note> The Mapping the Republic of Letters project — a mapping
               application that visualizes connections between intellectuals and scholars of Early
               Modern Europe — has noted Primary and Secondary Biases that it considers to be insuperable.<note>
                  <ptr target="#edelstein_kassabova_2020"/>. One example was the dearth of English
                  letters addressed to or from the philosopher Voltaire. The authors conclude that
                  this dearth did not result from data errors or lack of evidence but from a
                  systematic lack of interest in England on the part of Voltaire himself. They too
                  concluded that such lacunae were insuperable and were interesting in
                  themselves.</note> The recognition of such blind spots is important in
               establishing the limits at which projects in the digital humanities can operate
               effectively and the extent to which scholars might draw conclusions from accumulated
               digital data.</p>

            <p>The biases involved in the collection, analysis, and presentation of data do not mean
               that FLAME’s efforts, or those of any other digital humanities project, are useless.
               On the contrary, FLAME has forced us, its creators, to reflect more systematically on
               biases underlying scholarship on the late antique economy, many of which have not
               been formally discussed in scholarship. The result is a more critical approach to the
               broader research question, and one that translates across the digital humanities.</p>

            <p>FLAME’s mapping application is invaluable to scholars, moreover, not only because it
               makes explicit the totality of information available to scholars of this period (it
               is a reflection of scholarship, after all, and not the ancient world itself), but
               because it makes imaginable the information that is missing. Thus, while numismatists
               will not, presumably, cease their research because of the sudden revelation of how
               much they do not know (something they already suspect), they can and should be more
               self-conscious about it, and about where and how this is so. Moreover, scholars whose
               interests are methodological or historiographical now have a tool to examine not only
               the late antique and medieval economy, but also the basis on which knowledge of it is
               built. In this context, much of FLAME’s work over the past few years has moved
               towards making its biases and other issues more transparent to project users. These
               were not questions we considered during the first years of the project, when we were
               more concerned about providing data to historians studying the ancient economy. </p>

            <p>We have pursued two separate strategies to address systematic bias in FLAME’s data.
               The first marks certain kinds of bias directly in FLAME’s user interface, associating
               coin finds directly with particular biases that afflict them. These are communicated
               through pop-up tabs that appear when users click on coin finds. These bias labels,
               each of which expands to provide a detailed definition of the bias, as well as a link
               to the entry on our website, are dynamically generated, based on an automated set of
               criteria that assign bias on a case-by-case basis. These biases are most often at the
               primary level, where certain coin features help to identify them. For example, in
               Figure 8, the status of High Use Bias is based almost entirely upon the metal of the
               coin — bronze coins tend to be used more than gold or silver coins, and so finds that
               are characterized primarily by bronze or other base metallic coinages are assigned
               this bias.</p>

            <figure>
               <head/>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png" style="width: 700px"/>
            </figure>

            <p>Figure 8: A coin-find just east of London, England, with main panel (upper right) and
               secondary bias panel (lower left).</p>

            <p>In other cases, we have been unable to assign biases based on coinage alone. Regional
               biases have required considerable case-specific descriptions, and we have therefore
               adopted a unique format to communicate these. This is the second of our two-pronged
               approach to addressing bias. For regions like Britain, we have asked area experts to
               write short essays explaining the particulars of the region in somewhat more detail
               than what we saw above. These essays are posted as PDFs on a resources page on the
               FLAME website, but they are also integrated directly into our UI and can be accessed
               through the same bias tab described above (see Fig. 8, where the bullet “Regional
               Bias: Britain” provides direct access to a PDF of the bias essay). Such links to
               discussions of possible regional biases are assigned automatically to any find on the
               territory of the region in question. A list of biases we have identified appears on a
               dedicated page on our website, a link to which appears in all bias tabs.<note>
                  <ref target="https://coinage.princeton.edu/biases-in-flames-data/"
                     >https://coinage.princeton.edu/biases-in-flames-data/</ref>.</note> This list
               is not comprehensive for FLAME or any other historical numismatic project. In both
               the application and this paper, we have attempted to compromise responsibly, settling
               for a level of explicitness and systematicity.</p>

            <p>In this context, we believe that the best strategy for addressing these issues is to
               use the powerful digital platforms we have built to highlight them. We encourage
               users to engage with substantial critical approaches to the underlying data through a
               few mouse clicks, for example through the regional bias essays, and by constantly
               reminding users that these biases exist. This coupling of data and bias warning would
               have been extremely difficult, if not impossible, to do using traditional publication
               practices. Transparently highlighting biases in our data and presentation and making
               that information available to project users are key steps towards the production of
               more robust research.</p>
         </div>



         <div>

            <head>4. Conclusion</head>

            <p>All scholars who work in historical and archaeological disciplines are aware that the
               evidence upon which they draw is incomplete and not fully representative of past
               conditions. Source analysis is a basic component of the training of historians and
               modern archaeological inquiry is accompanied by an understanding of the selective
               nature of the evidence that comes from excavations. Within this scholarly context,
               FLAME introduces an unprecedented concentration of relevant data - and tools to
               analyze and visualize it - for questions regarding the late antique and medieval
               economy. Yet this presentation also introduces profound challenges. Historians
               trained in the traditional humanities are rarely prepared to contend with problems
               inherent in large-scale quantitative datasets such as those underlying FLAME. On the
               other hand, although digital humanities scholarship has produced impressive tools for
               viewing, accessing and using data, it often does so without integrating traditional
               humanistic insights that might realistically temper expectations for such data, at
               least not to a level that satisfies more traditional colleagues. A large database
               with sophisticated graphical representations, based on finds of over a million coins,
               might appear to some scholars as a robust proxy for past conditions, but, as we have
               seen, such an assumption is naive, since the data carries multiple layers of biases.
               In this regard, FLAME’s emphasis on revealing the biases and their impact on the
               shape of our data is a major contribution. Once scholars are thoroughly acquainted
               with the biases inherent in its data and their presentation, the FLAME database can
               serve as the basis for discussions of one of the key transitions in global history,
               using more data — and more precise data — than has ever been possible before.</p>

            <p>FLAME’s case suggests that other digital humanities projects should reflect on the
               biases they replicate, introduce, or inherit from other projects as early as
               possible. These reflections should be made public and be considered part of a more
               robust presentation of the project, whether in formal settings such as conferences or
               in project materials such as publications. The online presence of the project and its
               documentation should include discussions of these biases that are accessible to
               users, including the project’s attempts to acknowledge and ideally resolve them. If
               possible, the project should also incorporate this more critical discourse into its
               user interface. A shared discussion following such norms would benefit a broad range
               of digital humanities projects and make their results more robust. </p>

            <p>The future of digital projects such as FLAME is inherently interdisciplinary. Their
               continued improvement requires the engagement and support of the broader community —
               with scholars to explore its data, critique its design, suggest improvements to its
               interface and functionalities, and contribute additional material. We hope that
               designers of and contributors to these future projects find the results of our
               introspective processes outlined above useful. </p>



         </div>
      </body>


      <back>
         <listBibl>

            <bibl xml:id="abou_2018" label="Abou 2018">Abou Diwan, G. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Base-Metal Coinage Circulation in Byzantine Beirut 491-641 CE</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">American Journal of Numismatics</title>, 30, pp. 163–218.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="almohamad_2021" label="Almohamad 2021">Almohamad, A. (2021) <title
                  rend="quotes">The destruction and looting of cultural heritage sites by ISIS in
                  Syria: The case of Manbij and its countryside</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >International Journal of Cultural Property</title>, 28(2), pp. 221–260.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="breier_2011" label="Breier 2011">Breier, M. (2011) <title rend="quotes"
                  >GIS for Numismatics – Methods of Analyses in the Interpretation of Coin
                  Finds</title>, in K. Kriz, W. Cartwright, and L. Hurni (eds) <title rend="italic"
                  >Mapping Different Geographies</title>. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer Berlin
               Heidelberg, pp. 171–182.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="brodie_2019" label="Brodie 2019">Brodie, N. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Criminal Organization of the Transnational Trade in Cultural Objects: Two
                  Case Studies</title>, in S. Hufnagel and D. Chappell (eds) <title rend="italic"
                  >The Palgrave Handbook on Art Crime</title>. London: Palgrave Macmillan UK, pp.
               439–461.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="buttrey_1993" label="Buttrey 1993">Buttrey, T.V. (1993) <title
                  rend="quotes">Calculating Ancient Coin Production: Facts and Fantasies</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">The Numismatic Chronicle</title>, 153, pp. 335–351.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="carr_1961" label="Carr 1961">Carr, E.H. (1961) <title rend="italic">What
                  is History?</title> New York: Vintage.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="casana_2015" label="Casana 2015">Casana, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Satellite Imagery-Based Analysis of Archaeological Looting in Syria</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Near Eastern Archaeology</title>, 78(3), pp. 142–152.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="collingwood_1946" label="Collingwood 1946">Collingwood, R.G. (1946) <title
                  rend="italic">The Idea of History</title>. Claredon Press. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crawford_1974" label="Crawford 1974">Crawford, M.H. (1974) <title
                  rend="italic">Roman republican coinage</title>. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="davis-marks_2020" label="Davis-Marks 2020">Davis-Marks, I. (2020) <title
                  rend="quotes">Officials Seize 27,400 Artifacts Looted by a Single French Treasure
                  Hunter</title>, <title rend="italic">Smithsonian Magazine</title>, 18 December.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/french-officials-seize-more-27000-looted-archaeological-artifacts-180976590/"
                  >https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/french-officials-seize-more-27000-looted-archaeological-artifacts-180976590/</ref>
               (Accessed: 20 September 2024).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="de_callataÿ_1995" label="De Callataÿ 1995">De Callataÿ, F. (1995) <title
                  rend="quotes">Calculating ancient coin production: seeking a balance</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">The Numismatic Chronicle</title>, 155, pp. 289–311.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dopsch_1923" label="Dopsch 1923">Dopsch, A. (1923) <title rend="italic"
                  >Wirtschaftliche und soziale Grundlagen der europäischen
               Kulturentwicklung</title>. 2nd ed.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="edelstein_kassabova_2020" label="Edelstein and Kassabova 2020">Edelstein,
               D. and Kassabova, B. (2020) <title rend="quotes">How England Fell off the Map of
                  Voltaire’s Enlightenment</title>, <title rend="italic">Modern Intellectual
                  History</title>, 17(1), pp. 29–53.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gibbon_1776" label="Gibbon 1776">Gibbon, E. (1776) <title rend="italic"
                  >The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title>. London (Modern library of the
               world’s best books).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="granovetter_1983" label="Granovetter 1983">Granovetter, M.S. (1973) <title
                  rend="quotes">The Strength of Weak Ties</title>, <title rend="italic">American
                  Journal of Sociology</title>, 78(6), pp. 1360–1380.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gruber_lockyear_2015" label="Gruber and Lockyear 2015">Gruber, E. and
               Lockyear, K. (2015) <title rend="quotes">From dBase III+ to the semantic web:
                  twenty-five years of the Coin Hoards of the Roman Republic database</title>, in A.
               Traviglia (ed.) <title rend="italic">Across Space and Time. Papers from the 41st
                  Conference on Computer Applications and Quantitative Methods in
                  Archaeology</title>, pp. 336–346.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hopkins_1980" label="Hopkins 1980">Hopkins, K. (1980) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Taxes and trade in the Roman Empire (200 BC–AD 400)</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >The Journal of Roman Studies</title>, 70, pp. 101–125.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="howgego_1992" label="Howgego 1992">Howgego, C. (1992) ‘<title
                  rend="quotes">The Supply and Use of Money in the Roman World 200 B.C. to A.D.
                  300*</title>’, <title rend="italic">The Journal of Roman Studies</title>, 82, pp.
               1–31.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="howgego_1995" label="Howgego 1995">Howgego, C. (1995) <title rend="italic"
                  >Ancient History from Coins</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kane_2015" label="Kane 2015">Kane, S. (2015) ‘Archaeology and Cultural
               Heritage in Post-Revolution Libya’, <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern Archaeology</hi>,
               78(3), pp. 204–211.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="katsari_2003" label="Katsari 2003">Katsari, C. (2003) <title rend="quotes"
                  >The statistical analysis of stray coins in museums. The Roman provincial
                  coinage</title>, <title rend="italic">Nomismatika Khronika</title>, 22, pp.
               47–52.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kletter_de-groot_2001" label="Kletter and De-Groot 2001">Kletter, R. and
               De-Groot, A. (2001) <title rend="quotes">Excavating to excess?: The last decade of
                  archaeology in Israel and its implications</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal
                  of Mediterranean Archaeology</title>, 14(1), pp. 76–85.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kropotkin_1961" label="Kropotkin 1961">Kropotkin, V.V. (1961) <title
                  rend="italic">Клады римских монет на территории СССР [Hoards of Roman coins on the
                  territory of the USSR]</title>. Издательство Академии наук СССР. Москва: Институт
               археологии Академии наук СССР.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kropotkin_1962" label="Kropotkin 1962">Kropotkin, V.V. (1962) <title
                  rend="italic">Клады византийских монет на территории СССР [Hoards of Byzantine
                  coins on the territory of the USSR]</title>. Издательство Академии наук СССР.
               Москва: Институт археологии Академии наук СССР (Свод археологических источников
               (САИ), Вып. Е4-04).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lockyear_1999" label="Lockyear 1999">Lockyear, K. (1999) <title
                  rend="quotes">Hoard structure and coin production in antiquity — an empirical
                  investigation</title>, <title rend="italic">The Numismatic Chronicle
                  (1966-)</title>, 159, pp. 215–243.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lockyear_2016" label="Lockyear 2016">Lockyear, K. (2016) <title
                  rend="quotes">The Coin Hoards of the Roman Republic database: The history, the
                  data, and the potential</title>, <title rend="italic">American Journal of
                  Numismatics (1989-)</title>, 28, pp. 159–184.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mc_cormick_2001" label="McCormick 2001">McCormick, M. (2001) <title
                  rend="italic">Origins of the European economy : communications and commerce, A.D.
                  300-900</title>. Cambridge, UK ; New York: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mead_2020" label="Mead 2020">Mead, R. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The
                  Curse of the Buried Treasure</title>, <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title>,
               9 November. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2020/11/16/the-curse-of-the-buried-treasure"
                  >https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2020/11/16/the-curse-of-the-buried-treasure</ref>
               (Accessed: 20 September 2024).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="militkỳ_2010" label="Militkỳ 2010">Militkỳ, J. (2010) <title rend="italic"
                  >Finds of Greek, Roman and early Byzantine coins in the territory of the Czech
                  Republic.</title> 1: Bohemia: Vol. 2. Warsaw: Moneta.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mordechai_2019" label="Mordechai 2019">Mordechai, L. (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">Berytus and the aftermath of the 551 earthquake</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Late Antiquity – Studies in Source Criticism</title>, (17–18), pp.
               197–241.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mugnai_et_al_2017" label="Mugnai et al. 2017">Mugnai, N. et al. (2017)
                  <title rend="quotes">Libyan Antiquities at Risk: protecting portable cultural
                  heritage</title>, <title rend="italic">Libyan Studies</title>, 48, pp.
               11–21.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="naismith_2011" label="Naismith 2011">Naismith, R. (2011) <title
                  rend="italic">Money and Power in Anglo-Saxon England: The Southern English
                  Kingdoms</title>, 757–865. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="naismith_2018a" label="Naismith 2018a">Naismith, R. (2018a) <title
                  rend="quotes">Introduction</title>, in R. Naismith (ed.) <title rend="italic"
                  >Money and coinage in the Middle Ages</title>. Brill, pp. 1–18.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="naismith_2018b" label="Naismith 2018b">Naismith, R. (ed.) (2018b) <title
                  rend="italic">Money and coinage in the Middle Ages</title>. Brill.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="novick_1988" label="Novick 1988">Novick, P. (1988) <title rend="italic"
                  >That Noble Dream: The <title rend="quotes">Objectivity Question</title> and the
                  American Historical Profession</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University
               Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="oakeshott_1983" label="Oakeshott 1983">Oakeshott, M. (1983) <title
                  rend="italic">On History and Other Essays</title>. Basis Blackwell.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="pirenne_1922" label="Pirenne 1922">Pirenne, H. (1922) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Mahomet et Charlemagne</title>, <title rend="italic">Revue belge de Philologie et
                  d’Histoire</title>, 1(1), pp. 77–86.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="robertson_1986" label="Robertson 1986">Robertson, A.S. (1989) <title
                  rend="quotes">The accidents of survival</title>, in L.A. Carradice (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 10th International Congress of Numismatics,
                  London, September 1986</title>. Belgium: International Association of Professional
               Numismatists, pp. 245–250.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rovelli_2018" label="Rovelli 2018">Rovelli, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
                  >From the Fall of Rome to Charlemagne</title>, in R. Naismith (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Money and coinage in the Middle Ages</title>. Brill, pp.
               63–92.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="scheidel_2013" label="Scheidel 2013">Scheidel, W. (2013) <title
                  rend="quotes">Explaining the maritime freight charges in Diocletian’s Prices
                  Edict</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Roman Archaeology</title>, 26, pp.
               464–468.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="scheidel_2014" label="Scheidel 2014">Scheidel, W. (2014) <title
                  rend="quotes">The shape of the Roman world: modelling imperial
                  connectivity</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Roman Archaeology</title>,
               27, pp. 7–32.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="smith_2003" label="Smith 2003">Smith, J.M. (2003) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Origins of the European Economy: Communications and Commerce AD 300-900. Michael
                  McCormick</title>, <title rend="italic">Speculum</title>, 78(3), pp.
               956–959.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="stahl_2003" label="Stahl 2003">Stahl, A.M. (2003) <title rend="quotes">The
                  Origins of the European Economy–A Debate with Michael McCormick</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Early Medieval Europe</title>, 12(3), pp. 293–299.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="white_1986" label="White 1986">White, H. (1986) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Historical Pluralism</title>, <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>,
               12(3), pp. 480–493.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wickham_2005" label="Wickham 2005">Wickham, C. (2005) <title rend="italic"
                  >Framing the early Middle Ages: Europe and the Mediterranean 400-800</title>.
               Oxford ; New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>






            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

            <bibl/>

         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
