<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">The New Place of Reading: Locative Media and the Future of
          Narrative</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Brian <dhq:family>Greenspan</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Carleton University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>brian_greenspan@carleton.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Brian Greenspan is an Associate Professor in the Department of English and the
              doctoral program in Cultural Mediations at Carleton University. He is the designer and
              founding director of the Hypertext and Hypermedia Lab, and co-designer of the
              StoryTrek locative authoring and reading system. His research interests include
              utopian narratives, digital cultures, and the intersections between them.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000103</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2011-11-15">15 November 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2011-04-17" who="Alyssa">began encoding</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Locative technologies hold out the promise to transform literary space in all of its
          dimensions, including its represented spaces, reading interfaces, and the very spaces
          within which literature is produced and consumed. Yet, despite the growing use of
          location-based technologies, authors and readers alike have been slow to take to
          site-specific narrative due to limitations inherent in both the current design of locative
          media systems and our received notions of what constitutes the narrative experience.</p>
            <p>This paper argues that new mobile reading platforms in general are altering conceptions
          of literary space in highly conflicted ways, by radically expanding the sites where
          narratives can be accessed and experienced even as they reinforce a residual notion of
          literary reading as a sedentary and decontextualized experience. Locative media likewise
          hold out the promise of increased mobility and contextual awareness, but confront several
          cultural and technological factors preventing such an enhanced emplacement of narrative,
          factors that current performance-oriented approaches cannot fully address. At the level of
          cognitive engagement, the conditioned expectation of being
            <soCalled>transported</soCalled> to a remote fictional world interferes with readers'
          appreciation of the locative narrative's close ties to the real world, as well as the contextual
          effects it elicits by means of transportation through the actual world. At the technical
          level, the discontinuous algorithms of place that inform the architecture of most locative
          media systems hinder the perception of narrative patterning and flow across more extensive
          spaces.</p>
            <p>Locative media thus operationalize the spatial tension between conventionally sedentary
          modes of literary engagement and new modalities of mobility, a tension that is
          constitutive of our present mediality. The study concludes with a discussion of StoryTrek,
          a next-generation locative hypernarrative system designed to enable more complex, dynamic
          and fluid modes of embodied narrative spatiality. By encouraging the user to actively form
          complex narrative links between real and fictional spaces, StoryTrek enables utopian forms
          of spatial play that neutralize both the spatial limitations of current locative media
          design and the sedentary reading practices that continue to structure the experience of
          digital literature.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Forget sedentary reading: new locative narratives literally transport readers through
          both fictional and actual spaces.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>The New Place of Reading: Locative Media and the Future of Narrative</head>
         <div>
            <head>The Changing Spaces of Reading</head>
            <p>Prognostications about the future course of technology will inevitably seem quaint in
          hindsight, but if the current convergence of handheld mobile devices, location-based
          services and eBook readers continues, then the future of reading will be less a matter of
          time than a matter of space. For well over a decade, artists and authors like Kate
          Armstrong and Teri Rueb, interactive audio installations like <ref target="#proboscis">
                  <title rend="italic">Urban Tapestries</title>
               </ref>, <ref target="#micallef2003">
                  <title rend="italic">[murmur]</title>
               </ref>, <ref target="#lovlie2009">
                  <title rend="italic">textopia</title>
               </ref> and <ref target="#knowltona">
                  <title rend="italic">34 North 118 West</title>
               </ref>, and alternate reality game designers such as Blast
          Theory and 7scenes, have all successfully integrated locative media with narrative
          experiences in ways that challenge our very definitions of the literary. As artistic
          practice, locative media represent a productive hesitation between literary fiction,
          documentary, audio-visual installation, and site-specific theatrical performance; as
          cultural practices, they are located in the everyday sites of commerce and leisure within
          both natural and built environments, at the crux of the user's public and private
          identities. Site-specific digital literature is thus perfectly situated to engage large
          audiences who already adopt locative media for other purposes, including the massive
          global geocaching and alternate reality gaming communities, those who daily use
          GPS-enabled applications for activism, flash mobs and other civil disturbances, and anyone
          who uses new mobile location-based apps and services for shopping, wayfinding, tourism or
          recreation. Add to this install base the millions of book lovers who are embracing the
          explosion of popular mobile reading formats and platforms for eBooks and audio books, and
          the potential audience for locative narrative seems vast indeed.</p>
            <p>And yet, the growing use of location-based technologies in a wide variety of social
          contexts has not produced a sizeable audience for locative media storytelling. Locative
          narrative, like literary hypertext, remains an avant-garde and coterie practice, still
          largely unknown as an artistic medium, let alone as a popular fictional genre. Authors and
          readers alike have been slow to take to site-specific narrative due to limitations
          inherent in both the current design of locative media systems and our received notions of
          what constitutes a narrative experience. Even literary critics who take notice of locative
          texts have tended to underplay the medium's affinities with conventional literary
          narrative and apparently natural precedents such as epic poetry or the literature of
          place, choosing instead to trace the evolution of locative media from modes of cultural
          engagement having no necessary narrative content, such as games, psychogeographical
            <soCalled>situations</soCalled> or site-specific theatre. Locative theorists have
          de-emphasized the medium's narrative dimension while attending to its lyrical,
          archaeological and, most significantly, performative dimensions. For example, both Chris
          Eaket <ptr target="#eaket2008"/> and Rita Raley have rightly argued that locative media,
          like cybertexts generally, demand heightened degrees of performativity from their users,
          whom Raley describes less as readers than as embodied, multimodal <quote rend="inline" source="#raley2010">participants</quote>: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#raley2010">critical engagement [with mobile
              narrative] requires a range of cognitive and bodily activities, only one of which is
              reading in the sense of the visual processing of linguistic signs. That is, reading in
              the physical environment particular to mobile media quite often also involves seeing,
              moving, listening, touching. Participating in a mobile narrative is then precisely
              that — physical participation that is also understandable as performance</quote>
                  <ptr target="#raley2010" loc="303"/>
               </cit>. Raley's description perfectly captures the
          total environmental involvement demanded by many locative artworks, and also suggests an
          explanation for their lack of popularity, since literary enthusiasts are still more likely
          to approach reading as a sedentary mental activity at odds with the modes of embodied
          interactivity popular among gamers and geocachers. As empirical studies of hypertext users
          have shown (<ptr target="#miall2001"/>; <ptr target="#pope2006"/>), not everyone wants to
          be forced to perform their own stories.</p>
            <p>Performance-oriented approaches can account for the uniquely embodied interactivity of
          locative media, but do less to account for the conventional features of printed literature
          which they retain, including a primarily textual emphasis; a narrative arc; a reliance on
          novelistic discourse, focalization and identification; and, most significantly for the
          present discussion, the experience of being <soCalled>transported</soCalled> to a
          fictional world, a phenomenon that occurs only in narrative media <ptr target="#greenetal2004" loc="313–4"/>. Understood as the cognitive and emotional process
          by which readers become absorbed into fictional worlds, <term>transportation</term> has
          been empirically demonstrated to operate through a complex blend of effects that depend on
          a reader's attention, awareness, identification and affect, but is usually explained by
          analogy to physical travel. In order to be transported to a fictional world, it is said
          that a reader first has to leave the real world behind: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#gerrig1993">At the
              core of the metaphor of being transported lie readers' subjective reports of having
              left the real world behind when visiting narrative worlds</quote>
                  <ptr loc="157" target="#gerrig1993"/>
               </cit>. Young readers are trained from an early age
          to inhabit printed fictions as spaces framed off from the real world, and to focus
          attention on these represented spaces while detuning their real-world contexts of reading.
          Even literary critics rarely attend to the relation between the settings and chronotopes
          (or time-spaces) represented within narratives, and those actual spaces in which readers
          are themselves situated.</p>
            <p>Because the metaphorical departure is experientially real, narrative transportation can
          interfere with the new mobility enabled by digital reading devices. The reader of a
          printed text might have to leave the real world behind in order to be transported to a
          fictional world, thereby <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#green2004">los[ing] access to . . . the world of
              origin</quote>
                  <ptr target="#green2004" loc="248"/>
               </cit>; but with locative narrative quite the
          opposite is true, as being transported to the fictional world is literally dependent on
          transportation through the real world. This study argues that locative media hold out the
          promise of an enhanced mobility and situational awareness, but fail to overcome the
          expectation of conventional narrative transportation that continues to structure narrative
          worlds as spatially contained and isolated from the real world. The readerly detachment
          experienced at the level of cognitive engagement is reinforced at the technical level by
          the discontinuous algorithms of place that inform the current design and implementation of
          most locative media systems, and which prevent users from narrativizing their physical
          environments. Far from representing <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#raley2010">a challenge to the hegemony
              of words</quote>
                  <ptr loc="303" target="#raley2010"/>
               </cit>, then, locative narratives mobilize printed
          literature's traditional mode of decontextualized engagement within new spatial contexts
          in ways that often interfere with the performance of place, foregrounding the productive
          tension between the traditional experience of fictional transportation and new modalities
          of mobility that constitutes our present medial condition. I conclude by describing
          StoryTrek, an innovative system for the authoring and reading of location-based narratives
          designed to elicit controlled artistic effects from the spatial tension between
          conventionally sedentary modes of literary engagement and more dynamic, continuous and
          complex models of spatial interaction. By putting both conventional literary
          transportation and new locative mobilities into play, StoryTrek neutralizes the tension
          between them, and opens a space for newly emergent narrative media.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Contexts of Mobile <soCalled>Reading</soCalled>
            </head>
            <p>Although the mobile revolution certainly provides the broader context for
          locative media <ptr target="#raley2010" loc="301"/>, neither the increasing familiarity of
          location-based services and mobile applications nor the growing popularity of reading apps
          for mobile devices have done much to enhance the popularity of locative storytelling. In
          fact, new eBook and audio book formats remediate reading habits and assumptions associated
          with printed literature that prevent a broader recognition of the literary potential of
          locative media. New eBook and audio book platforms are altering conceptions of literary
          space in highly conflicted ways, by radically expanding the sites where narratives can be
          accessed and experienced, even as they reinforce a residual notion of literary reading as
          a sedentary experience that <soCalled>transports</soCalled> the reader to a fictionalized
          space removed from the actual world. The case of audio books helps to demonstrate why new
          mobile reading platforms have done little to promote the wider adoption of locative
          narratives. The comparison is informative, as the majority of successfully implemented
          locative narratives to date have used portable audio devices tied to GPS receivers to
          trigger playback of pre-recorded story segments as the user approaches certain geospatial
          coordinates. This technical modality, which tends less toward literacy than a <quote rend="inline" source="#ong2002">second orality</quote>
               <ptr target="#ong2002"/>, has encouraged the emphasis on performativity in critical
          approaches to the locative.</p>
            <p>An audio delivery format allows users of locative media to safely navigate the physical environment while
          building upon their personal engagements with popular mobile audio listening technologies.
          Portable audio books, including recordings of literary recitations as well as eBook
          devices that support mp3 format or text-to-speech, are enabling a culture of ubiquitous
          mobile (if not location-aware) <soCalled>reading.</soCalled> Many now listen to audio
          books while walking, driving, mowing the lawn, or performing other activities not
          traditionally associated with reading. In a study of the effect of portable mp3 players on
          how people listen to music, Michael Bull characterizes the iPod as a device that enables
          the <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2005">accompanied solitude</quote> of the individual listening
          experience combined with social proximity, providing listeners with <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2005">an intoxicating mixture of music, proximity and privacy whilst on the
              move</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bull2005" loc="343, 344"/>
               </cit>. He stresses that the same portable
          technologies that bind users to consumer culture also provide a background accompaniment
          to the <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2005">personalised narratives</quote> they create while moving
          through their daily lives in order to aestheticize and bring sense to the unpredictable
          and chaotic urban environment, <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2005">spaces of freedom</quote> within the
          culture of capitalism that help to manage individuals' utopian hopes and desires <ptr loc="351, 346–7" target="#bull2005"/>. Bull describes this activity as largely
          non-interactive, since the iPod enables a user to become absorbed in self-created
          narratives while detuning one's immediate surroundings, so that the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2005">disjunction between the interior world of control and the external one
              of contingency and conflict becomes suspended</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bull2005" loc="353"/>
               </cit>. In this way, new recording and playback media
          are changing not only the customary spaces of listening, but the entire auditory
          experience.</p>
            <p>If listening to music while strolling through the city allows individuals to
          reorder the contingency of the streets, the immersive attention and cognitive overhead
          required to follow and become lost in a previously scripted narrative are likely to
          preclude the creation of the sort of personalized narratives that Bull describes. Audio
          books likewise absorb the user into an alternate space, but it is a represented space that
          is less easily connected to the auditor's external environment. They offer a more complete
          detachment from capitalized urban space than that which Bull observes among music
          listeners, encouraging an even deeper withdrawal from communal space into a private
          literary realm.</p>
            <p>In her pioneering study of audio books, Deborah Philips emphasizes that although iPods
          and similar devices allow literary texts to be experienced in the company of others,
            <quote rend="inline" source="#philips2007">[t]he literary culture that has been harnessed by that market
            remains strikingly unchanged by the technology. . . . [W]ithin the world of the audio
            book, the stratifications of high- and lowbrow, the <soCalled>classic</soCalled> and
              <soCalled>popular</soCalled> fiction remain stable,</quote> preventing a broader
          democratization of literary culture <ptr loc="299, 303" target="#philips2007"/>. Audio
          books have failed to produce new literary genres that exploit the dynamic, interactive,
          multiplayer and performative features that are so integral to the experience of hypertext
          literature, videogames and social media: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#philips2007">The websites and
              marketing materials for audio books make very little of the ways in which an audio
              book is a different commodity from a printed text</quote>
                  <ptr target="#philips2007" loc="300"/>
               </cit>. Whereas the downloadable mp3 track has
          changed not only listening conditions but also music production, fragmenting the album format
          for easier download and optimizing the musical composition itself for smaller headphones,
          the vast majority of audio books exist as spoken versions of printed texts — perhaps
          abridged, but otherwise unaltered in their linear structure, content and
            interactivity.<note>Although interesting advances have been made with interactive
            audiobooks <ptr target="#rober2006"/>, there are also signs that mobile technologies are
            starting to explore new conceptions of the literary. For instance, <title rend="italic">Electric Literature</title>, a bi-monthly literary anthology billed as the first
            literary app for iPhone, features animated trailers for stories as well as Single
            Sentence Animations, a mode of cinematic ekphrasis in which artists interpret a single
            sentence from a featured author's text; and Simon &amp; Schuster has issued
            similarly <soCalled>enhanced</soCalled> ebooks for the iPad that embed scalable video
            within the text. eBook publishers have yet to explore the locative dimension,
            however.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Locating the eBook</head>
            <p>It is not surprising, then, that the coming of the eBook should be compared to the mobile
          audio revolution of recent decades: Amazon's Kindle eBook reader was hailed upon its
          arrival as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2007">the iPod of books</quote>
                  <ptr target="#pressman2007"/>
               </cit>, while recent months have brought widespread
          speculation about whether Apple's iPad will transform the book publishing industry in the
          same way the iPod revolutionized the music industry <ptr target="#evans2010" loc="8"/>. As
          with audio books, the mass appeal of eBooks is predicated precisely on their portability
          and ease of reading on the bus, the beach, in the coffee shop or in bed (even if their
          expense still makes reading in the bathtub a risky undertaking). As consumer technologies,
          eBooks are positioned within the general shift towards mobility, promising increased
          access to literary texts worldwide while making large personal libraries portable for
          ubiquitous access. The Amazon Kindle, Barnes and Noble Nook and iRex DR800SG e-readers all
          allow users to purchase and download books from anywhere with cellular reception, greatly
          multiplying the sites of literary distribution. Amazon expressly markets its Kindle reader
          as a device for collapsing distance: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#amazon">Our vision for Kindle is to
              have every book ever printed, in every language, available in 60 seconds from anywhere
              on earth</quote>
                  <ptr target="#amazon"/>
               </cit>. At the same time, its portability promises to increase
          the user's mobility: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#amazon">You can send your documents directly to
              your Kindle and read them anytime, anywhere </quote>
                  <ptr target="#amazon"/>
               </cit>. This
          expanded mobility reflects the demands of an increasingly flexible and globalized
            <soCalled>creative economy,</soCalled> in which spaces of production and consumption
          blur, and both work and leisure become increasingly subject to time- and space-shifting.
          The very name of Amazon's new eBook reader software for Windows, Kindle Everywhere, cloaks
          the corporate goal of total market penetration in the usability ideals of ubiquity,
          interoperability and democratic access.</p>
            <p>While eBook devices are already affecting production methods and distribution channels,
          there is less evidence of radical change in how literature is consumed. eBook readers
          arguably lend literature an expanded mobility, increasing the range and density of textual
          dissemination and reception, but do not fundamentally change how readers relate to and
          interact with these newly expanded sites of reading at the associative or cognitive
          levels. Even as they embrace digital media's portability and ease of dissemination, current eBook
          hardware and software are radically altering literary space at the levels of access and
          storage, while attempting to remediate the relative permanence and stability of
          conventional printed literature at the level of interface, content and experience. eBook
          readers are currently designed and marketed to remediate the form, scale and experience of
          a printed novel as closely as possible. These eBook readers take extraordinary measures to
          approximate the look and feel of a printed book. The Bookeen Cybook, for instance,
          features a wifi-enabled, grayscale e-ink display in a pocketbook format, bound together in
          a genuine artificial leatherette binding designed to emulate <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#mitchell1996">the
              look and feel of tree flakes encased in dead cow</quote>
                  <ptr target="#mitchell1996" loc="56"/>
               </cit>. The iRex iLiad uses a metal bar to emulate
          the action of turning a physical page (moreover, you have to think of it this way to turn
          the page in the right direction, as clicking forward will by default move the story
          backwards). Even the Stanza iPhone app features an elaborate visual and haptic simulation
          of a turning page. Although implemented to enhance usability, these conventions inherited
          from the print medium in fact constrain the user's notion of what reading ought to be. In
          so doing, they hide the fact that reading in the digital age no longer need, or generally
          does, look anything like the solitary, sedentary and immersive practice demanded by printed
          books.</p>
            <p>Megan Benton has traced this social obsession with the look and feel of the printed book
          to the 1920s, showing how books became especially important in this period as signifiers of
          cultural capital. At this time, she observes, there were two kinds of Americans: those who
          valued books for their own sake, and those who treated them as <quote rend="inline" source="#benton2000">things,</quote> commodities to provide amusement or impress the neighbours, like a new
          radio or automobile. In a growing commodity culture, spawned by new industrial methods and
          advertising, editors, publishers and critics took notice of what some called <quote rend="inline" source="#benton2000">domestic bookaflage,</quote> the selection and presentation of books in
          one's home so as to project the cultural persona that others would perceive <ptr loc="17–20" target="#benton2000"/>. However quaint such notions may seem today, the fact
          is that Cybooks, Kobos and Kindles are all so much domestic bookaflage, updated for
          digital consumers; only instead of acting as camouflage for a lack of literacy, eBook
          devices disguise our contemporary <term>hyperliteracy</term>, our constant engagement with
          reading and writing across new media and modalities in new spaces and social contexts. As
          Katherine Hayles has shown, the idealized detachment and disembodiment of the literary
          experience results from a long history involving social and legal definitions of literary
          work and property. The kind of close, immersive reading that has come to define both
          scholarly and casual engagements with <soCalled>the literary</soCalled> demands a
          certain detachment from one's own immediate, embodied setting, and disconnection from the
          world of commerce and mere <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2005">information</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hayles2005" loc="143–7"/>
               </cit>. Current eBook readers are designed to
          remediate this conventional experience of disconnection, encouraging transportation while
          carefully curtailing the kinds of connectivity and situational awareness that characterize
          other mobile devices.</p>
            <p>eBooks do not change existing conceptions of literary space so much as they extend them
          outside of traditional reading settings. Mobile devices have radically altered the sites
          at which people read while not only continuing to ignore the user's context and situation
          in the world, but promising to overcome it entirely through ubiquitous product
          distribution. eBooks, like audio books, do not generally connect narratives to new
          locations or change the spatial contexts of reading so much as they recreate this learned
          sense of disconnection, encouraging mobile readers to decontextualize and <soCalled>leave
            behind</soCalled> ever more real-world locations. Even when taken on the road,
          narratives experienced on Kindles and iPods reproduce the sense of
            <soCalled>placelessness</soCalled> demanded by immersive reading, setting them apart
          from the growing number of mobile apps that use GPS or wifi to sense the user's location
          in order to provide contextually specific and geographically relevant information. For
          instance, LibraryThing's Local Books app for iPhone will find libraries, bookstores,
          literary readings or book fairs near the user's current location; by contrast, neither the
          eReader Pro, Stanza nor iBooks reading apps offer any locative awareness, all tending
          instead to enable conventional immersive reading in ways that obviate the effects of
          locality. Ignoring one's immediate context while engaging in immersive reading allows a
          reading subject to ignore his ephemeral, quotidian or grossly material
          historical and geographical situation, while attending instead to supposedly
            <soCalled>timeless</soCalled> literary knowledge and values. Gutenberg elegists may
          bemoan the rise of <soCalled>distracted</soCalled> modes of reading encouraged by online
          news sources, blogs, twitter feeds and other social media, but eBooks still await the
            <soCalled>casual</soCalled> revolution that will liberate them from the constraints of
          literary transportation, and reconnect them to the world of information.<note>Of course,
            reading is never actually a <soCalled>placeless</soCalled> phenomenon. New research into
            the cultural geographies of specific reading locales offers some evidence that the
            supposed <soCalled>placelessness</soCalled> of reading may depend upon its exact
            opposite: that is, privileged access to specific sites of reading as well as the leisure
            time in which to visit those sites. For example, in her study of the reading habits of
            young adults in a rural Canadian community, Paulette Rothbauer shows that for rural
            youth with no access to sites of reading or clear articulations to a local print
            culture, reading is literally a placeless activity that occurs outside of any reading
            community. </note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Place of Reading and the Reading of Place</head>
            <p>Locative narratives provide precisely the interactive and performative element that is
          currently missing from eBooks and audio books, which may explain why they have not gained
          a wider appreciation. To begin with, most locative narratives must be experienced
              <term>
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">in situ</foreign>
               </term>, running directly counter to the
          model of mass dissemination that governs both printed literature and eBooks. Of course, it
          is precisely this site-specificity and contextual awareness that give locative narrative
          the potential to utterly transform our understanding of literary space. As Jeremy Hight
          puts it, locative media allow us <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hight2010">to move narrative from the
              printed page and literary journals to alternate spaces and new possibilities of
              dissemination, audience and community. Publication now can be signal, air, a spot of
              land. It can be on maps, and it can be only transcribed by a person as they move. . .
              . <soCalled>Place</soCalled> is semantically read more as a point, a specific
              designation or end point, while <soCalled>space</soCalled> is read more as an open
              area, place of storage, an area to be filled . . . .</quote>
                  <ptr loc="322" target="#hight2010"/>
               </cit>. While Hight evokes the expanded catalogue of
          narrative locations enabled by locative media, his distinction between isolated
            <soCalled>places</soCalled> and extensive <soCalled>spaces</soCalled> only emphasizes
          what I argue to be the locative's most serious technical limitation. Most locative systems
          function only within specified locales, and are furthermore designed to respond to
          relatively isolated geospatial coordinates. Anne Galloway rightly warns that it is
              <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2010">impossible to reduce locative media to discrete (or stable)
              objects of computation, or to singular representations</quote>
                  <ptr target="#galloway2010" loc="30"/>
               </cit>; nevertheless, it is fair to say that most
          locative apps and artworks alike remain technically limited to a punctuated model of
          spatial interaction. Locative systems typically provide set feedback at specific
          coordinates on the model of geospatial tagging, leaving the user to infer the spatial and
          narrative connections between isolated points of interest (POIs), a design model they
          share with the commercial navigation systems that guide users to their destinations
          through turn-by-turn directions by way of rest stops and service stations. By breaking
          down our subjective experience into easily commodifiable atoms of time-space, and
          positioning us in relation to local sites of commerce and exchange as tokens of our medial
          progress, such devices allegorize our contemporary obsession with the here-and-now, and
          our inability to perceive any socio-political organization beyond capitalism.</p>
            <p>Likewise, most locative narratives function by connecting discrete narrative moments to
          specific points on the grid, such that audio clips or text lexia are activated whenever a
          user reaches a particular location. The system knows where the user is at any given
          moment, but does not understand how she got there, or the implications of her particular
          path, approach, or style of navigation. Such works tend to privilege the node over the
          edge and site over duration, presenting not a story so much as a tour of disconnected
            sites.<note>This limitation perhaps explains the technical and conceptual reliance of
            rich locative narrative works such as 34N113W, John Klima's Saint Joe or Teri Rueb's
            TRACE on linear modes of transportation (be it subways, trains or hiking trails) for
            narrative constraint.</note> While users will inevitably perceive connections
          between the narrative segments triggered at distinct waypoints, such locative systems do
          little algorithmically to encourage either their authors or readers to make these
          schematic connections more explicit. They are incapable of responding to more complex
          patterns in the user's physical context, ever-changing style of motion, or embodied
          interactions with the environment. Just as reading practices inherited from print literacy
          continue to encourage readers to disconnect the fictional narratives they read from their
          actual spatial environments, so design conceptions borrowed from navigational and
          location-based services limit the interactivity, responsiveness and spatial awareness of
          locative narratives.</p>
            <p>This situation is beginning to change, with locative works like <title rend="italic">InterUrban</title>
               <ptr target="#spellman2004"/>, <title rend="italic">URBAN ENCOUNTER</title>
               <ptr target="#giles2009"/> and <title rend="italic">The Interpretive Engine for Various
            Places on Earth</title>
               <ptr target="#knowltonb"/> offering a narrative experience that taps into the dynamic,
          context-specific and communal sensibility enabled by new networked media. In the same
          spirit, we have developed StoryTrek, a prototype authoring and reading tool for locative
          hypernarrative that breaks out of the design specifications currently limiting
          site-specific narrative. Our system represents a departure from the <soCalled>waypoint and
            graffiti</soCalled> model of interaction offered by most locative and augmented reality
          applications. Such applications know where you are at any given moment, and can provide
          information about your immediate surroundings - the digital equivalent of a road sign or
          memorial plaque - but have no idea how you got there or where you might go next.</p>
            <p>Instead of linking geospatial points to static narrative segments, the StoryTrek
          authorware enables the creation of spatial stories that respond in real time to the vector
          of the user's physical movement and ever-changing geospatial context, providing narrative
          patterns matched on-the-fly to the user’s location, route and style of navigation. The
          authorware enables the creation of locative narratives, or <term>storytreks</term>, by
          layering story patterns (inspired by Mark Bernstein's structural <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bernstein2003">patterns of hypertext</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bernstein2003"/>
               </cit>) over Google maps, while the reading tool tracks
          the user's physical movement through these areas, matching her motion pattern with any
          number of relevant story patterns. Users navigate our system simply by walking through an
          urban or natural environment with a GPS-enabled mobile device in hand, while the story
          follows along, tacking and turning in response to the reader's unstructured motion. With
          conventional hypertext narratives, readers can to some extent direct the path of the story
          by choosing from a series of in-text hyperlinks, although numerous theorists have
          questioned the degree to which the reader is actually freed to choose his own path, rather
          than merely choosing from among multiple rails laid down by the author. StoryTrek frees
          readers from the confines of the link, setting them loose to follow any path
          in the world while the story tags alongside, transforming the act of linking into an even
          more eventful, agential and contextualized process.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>The StoryTrek Authorware.</head>
               <graphic url="...000103/resources/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>For our initial test implementation, Pippin Barr of the IT University of Copenhagen
          created <title rend="italic">Crisis 22</title>, a suspense/horror narrative that focuses
          on a character's repeated experience of a traumatic event enacted through space, in homage
          to Michael Joyce's <title rend="italic">afternoon: a story</title>
               <ptr target="#barr2008"/>. This surreal love story documents the inner turmoil and regrets
          of a solitary narrator as he wanders through a landscape that appears realistic and
          allegorical by turns. As you move forward through the streets, the system returns a
          present-tense narrative of walking through a city toward a rendezvous. Turning around and
          backtracking in this particular storytrek fills in the protagonist’s back-story, while
          turning away from a straight path yields digressive actions taking place around him.
          Pause, and the system knows that you are lingering, and triggers an interior monologue.
          Wherever you decide to go, the system presents a coherent but dynamically changing
          narrative cued to your relative location and movement. The narrative experience arises
          from the interactions of the story's internal logic with the reader's immediate physical
          environment and activity over time.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>Pippin Barr's <title rend="italic">Crisis 22</title>.</head>
               <graphic url="...000103/resources/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Crisis 22</title> was built atop a Google map of Carleton University
          in Ottawa, but its fictional and functional settings are ambiguous. Unlike other locative
          systems tied to specific geospatial coordinates, our system is designed to respond to
          narrative and navigational patterns, allowing stories produced and set in one particular
          location to be experienced in any given place the user happens to be. This unique
          locational layering feature allows specific locative narratives to be widely disseminated
          and experienced by users in a variety of spatial contexts, greatly enhancing the medium's
          mobility over <quote rend="inline" source="#lovlie2009">place-bound</quote> approaches <ptr target="#lovlie2009"/>. It also multiplies the story's settings: the fictional setting
          of the story, the implied geophysical setting for which it was originally produced, and
          the specific user's physical context all interact to produce an entirely new kind of
          narrative spatiality. In her survey of the various uses of maps in digital narrative,
          Marie-Laure Ryan describes four different types of textual spaces upon which hypermedia
          literature relies: the space of the textual world; the spatial architecture of the text;
          the material space of the textual representation; and the spatial environments in which
          the texts actually reside, be they in libraries or in databases <ptr target="#ryan2004"/>.
          These levels are not strictly hierarchical, and frequently overlap even in non-adaptive
          hypertext narratives. They can also be further subdivided: for instance, the space of the
          textual world combines the various spatial attributes of language with the conventions
          governing narrative chronotopes, while the material space of the textual representation
          comprises the spatial attributes of the interface along with the semiotics of iconography,
          typography, spatial layout and page design. In practice, StoryTrek foregrounds the
          interfaces and overlaps between all of these spatial levels, moving between questions of
          how space gets into narrative and how narrative gets back into space.</p>
            <p>StoryTrek has significant implications for the authoring and structuring of locative
          media, for the concept of the link, and for the <soCalled>worlding</soCalled> effects of
          digital narrative and games. The system repurposes readerly disorientation as the basis
          for a richly contextual experience, transcoding the navigational barriers of conventional
          hypertext (random jumps, drifting, backtracking, and so on) into a meaningful form of
          input. This sense of embodiment and agency at times enhances the user's experience of
          narrative immersion: after all, walking is a natural form of interactivity that tends not
          to interfere with the user's immersion in the story world to the degree that interacting
          with a mouse does. And yet, traveling with StoryTrek does not always make it easier to
          become lost in a fictional world, as when reading a novel on a train; on the contrary, our
          preliminary observations suggest that novel and unexpected effects occur as the user
            <soCalled>toggles</soCalled> her attention between the storyworld and the real world.
          Qualitative user tests reveal that when the represented space of the textual world corresponds closely to the
          actual spatial environment of the text, it sometimes functions as a welcome navigational
          aid that encourages narrative immersion and conventional transportation, while at other
          times proving highly disorienting and disruptive to the immersive experience. The system
          complicates and redefines spatial description, spatial deixis, focalization and
          identification, processes that are not fully understood even where printed narratives are
          concerned.</p>
            <p>StoryTrek constantly raises tensions between real and represented spaces; for instance,
          some users who wanted to emulate the spatial action of the story were prevented by busy
          road traffic or impassable physical terrain. These users reported real anxiety and
          frustration at this inability to enact the story bodily, one mark of the tension between
          habitually sedentary reading habits and the emergent performativity of locative media. Our
          system requires readers to abandon their decontextualized reading habits and develop new
          strategies for linking real and textual spaces. Catherine Emmott has shown that readers
          construct <quote rend="inline" source="#emmott1998">mental representation[s]</quote> of the <quote rend="inline" source="#emmott1998">spatio-temporal context[s]</quote> of narratives by combining general
          knowledge of the world, in the form of <quote rend="inline" source="#emmott1998">basic perceptual schema about
            how the world works,</quote> with <quote rend="inline" source="#emmott1998">text-derived</quote> knowledge
            <ptr target="#emmott1998" loc="177"/>. We have observed StoryTrek users drawing on
          perceptual cues of their immediate environment as a third source of knowledge about the
          story, using phenomenal data about the world around them to help fill the
            <soCalled>gaps</soCalled> in the fictional world. Users have playfully identified
          passers by with characters in the story, an imaginative repurposing of serendipitous
          encounters that Bull also documents among iPod users <ptr loc="351" target="#bull2005"/>.
          We have witnessed StoryTrek users run away from invisible threats, join a group of
          children at play when <soCalled>instructed</soCalled> to do so by the text, and even dip a
          toe in the nearby river to engage with the story while testing how responsive the system
          is to her specific location and actions. These embodied performances add a new dimension
          to the act of narrative linking, and present an alternative to the aesthetic of
          fragmentation and montage characteristic of so many hypertext narratives.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
               <head>Sarah and Celine read <title rend="italic">Crisis 22</title>.</head>
               <graphic url="...000103/resources/figure03.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>Celine tests the boundaries of StoryTrek.</head>
               <graphic url="...000103/resources/figure04.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>From Spatial Play to Spatial Politics</head>
            <p>This simple act of dipping one’s feet has far-reaching implications for digital
          narrative. According to Ryan, readers of conventional narratives tend to operate through
            <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan1980">the principle of minimal departure</quote>: except where explicitly
          told otherwise, readers will assume that that the fictional world closely resembles their
          own world — that the fictional sky is blue and that humans need to eat and breathe <ptr target="#ryan1980"/>. StoryTrek readers tend to follow a different principle, attempting
          to forge unusually close links between the real and fictional worlds, yet without
          necessarily leading to either immersion or the one-to-one mapping characteristic of
          conventional realism. Instead, meaning is created through the reader’s self-conscious
          linking of different layers of space and context. If conventional transportation allows
          readers to leave their <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#greenetal2004">public self-consciousness behind</quote>
                  <ptr target="#greenetal2004" loc="317"/>
               </cit>, then storytreks encourage them to enact
          their experiences of the narrative world publicly and self-consciously. In our user tests
          so far, readers have gone out of their way to create interpretive links between the text
          and the real world and to perform them publicly, binding their reading experiences to
          those of a larger community of users. Green et al. assume that readers require a strict
          boundary between the real and represented worlds in order to be transported, noting that
          where situational factors affect narrative transportation at all, they primarily do so in
          negative ways. Real-world distractions can call a reader back to the real world, just as
          negative environmental factors may encourage a reader to escape to a fictional world <ptr loc="321" target="#greenetal2004"/>. Green et al. project that new media could enhance
          transportation through interactivity, but only by allowing users <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#greenetal2004">to
            easily leave their physical and psychological realities behind and become fully immersed
            as an active participant in the narrative of an alternate, <soCalled>virtual</soCalled>
            reality</quote>
               <ptr loc="323" target="#greenetal2004"/></cit>. However, our experience with StoryTrek shows how
          real-world factors might well produce an enhanced form of transportation that allows
          readers to keep one foot in the real world (if not always in the river).</p>
           <p>Janet Murray has argued that in artistic representations, <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1997">[t]here is
            a discomfort in not knowing the limits of the illusion,</quote> and that the experience
             of immersion in a fictional world is maximized by the <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1997">combination of
               tremendous immediacy with a clearly demarcated border,</quote> the <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1997">digital equivalent of the theater's fourth wall</quote> that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1997">will allow us to surrender to the enticements of the virtual environment</quote>
                  <ptr target="#murray1997" loc="120, 103"/>
               </cit>. StoryTrek denies such surrender to an
          immersive aesthetic by constantly encouraging users to cross the border between the real
          and represented setting, turning the discomfort of porous borders into a source of
          transgressive pleasure. These potentially disruptive effects raise several key design
          issues surrounding the spatial experience of hypertext narrative, including user
          (dis)orientation, navigational aids, and the relationship between cognitive, textual and
          virtual maps; at the same time, they can encourage the development of critical
          perspectives regarding the user's spatial situation within a global context. Whitson et
          al. have described the shift by some videogame producers away from the traditionally
          immersive first-person shooter perspective (which is closer to the experience of literary
          transportation than some dare to admit) <ptr target="#whitson2008"/>. In order to
          encourage social gaming, <soCalled>neo-immersive</soCalled> games like those produced for
          the <title>Wii</title> use a combination of gestural computing and group
          play to emphasize the embodied nature and social context of digital gaming. Such games
          encourage users to divide their attention between immersion in the represented game world
          and interactivity with other players in the real world in a way that enriches both
          experiences and enables critical self-reflection. StoryTrek brings this neo-immersive
          aesthetic to literary narrative, using locative awareness to disrupt the reader's
          immersion in the story and enable a newly situated critical awareness.</p>
            <p>The urge to transform one's decontextualized reading into a publically performed
          interpretation suggests the storytrek's potential as a political and utopian art form,
          which ultimately may have less to do with the unfolding of time than a creative
          interaction with space. From its very inception, the utopian genre was less a blueprint
          for the perfect society than a rhetorical structure or toolkit for playing with and
          reconfiguring social space. As Louis Marin has famously shown, Thomas More's <quote rend="inline" source="#marin1984">minutely detailed description . . . of the [Utopian] city's space</quote>
          reveals many <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#marin1984">blind spots and empty spaces . . . . the political
              places [of Renaissance society] that have been erased from the map</quote>
                  <ptr target="#marin1984" loc="131"/>
               </cit>. <title rend="italic">Utopia</title>
          describes a shifting, indeterminate space in which several competing residual social
          structures (monasticism, feudalism, communism) overlap, effectively cancelling out or
            <soCalled>neutralizing</soCalled> one another, and thereby clearing a space for
          new social formations that could not yet be fully articulated in More's day.</p>
            <p>StoryTrek enables a similar utopian <soCalled>spatial play</soCalled> by
          permitting the reader to participate in an ergodic <quote rend="inline" source="#marin1984">point-by-point
            negation or canceling</quote> of her lived social context <ptr loc="85" target="#marin1984"/>, thus opening up real space to imaginary alternatives. Whereas
          printed utopias achieve such spatial play discursively and rhetorically, StoryTrek invites
          the user to enact utopian negations through a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2007">procedural
              rhetoric</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bogost2007"/>
               </cit> that takes full-body motion as input. Readers stroll,
          run, leap and zigzag across their physical terrain, activating fictional worlds through
          their mobile devices. As is characteristic of utopian spatial play in general, these
          fictional worlds do not replace the real world outright with fully formed utopian
          alternatives, but rather engage reality in a dialectic, neutralizing it point-by-point to
          prepare the ground on which new social configurations might emerge. At the same time,
          StoryTrek neutralizes the sedentary reading practices that continue to structure the
          experience of digital literature: the labour of reading can no longer be described as a
          purely leisurely activity, but instead becomes a profoundly social act in which the reader
          actively and publicly forms interpretive links between her fictional and actual
          contexts.</p>
            <p>While the StoryTrek authorware does not dictate the themes or content of the spatial
          narratives that users create, its emphasis on mapping and mobility encourages critical
          reflection on socio-cultural borders, the politics of space and travel, uneven global
          development, and the migration of populations, or what David Harvey calls the utopian
            <quote rend="inline" source="#harvey2000">spaces of hope</quote> that mediate between individual bodies,
          collective identities and global processes <ptr target="#harvey2000" loc="49"/>. We are
          currently hoping to exploit the system's potential for location-aware utopian spatial play
          through several ongoing projects that open rifts in space within which to imagine social
          alternatives. One such initiative involves the creation of an <soCalled>archival atlas</soCalled> of New World utopias that maps historical fictions, photos,
          plans, blueprints and visionary descriptions of urban spaces onto actual geospatial sites.
          By turning national archives inside-out, liberating these forgotten and dispersed literary
          traces from their storage boxes, we hope to infuse geographical sites with historical
          context - in particular, the indigenous, immigrant, environmental, and other
            <soCalled>minor</soCalled> histories effaced by imperialism and the project of
          modernity. We are using the city streets themselves as a <term>dialectical
            interface</term> that layers residual social structures onto emergent configurations,
          and links historical images and accounts of social migration, upheaval and urban renewal
          to more recent cartographies of uprise. If locative media <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2010">involve persistent tensions between pasts, presents, and futures that make certain
              identities and objectives possible or probable, and others impossible or
              improbable</quote>
                  <ptr loc="32" target="#galloway2010"/>
               </cit>, then they also present the opportunity to
          contour those possibilities toward social progress.</p>
            <p>Other storytreks likewise engage the user in ludic explorations of emplaced social
          alternatives. Valerie Bherer, Cindy Ma and Elise Vist used StoryTrek to create <title rend="italic">Isolation U.</title>, an Alternate Reality Game in which you play a
          zombified undergrad at a post-apocalyptic campus, trying to survive the fast-spreading
          conformity virus. The game bears some similarities with ZombieTruth.com and Zwatch.org,
          collaborative alternate reality games that write an imaginary zombie virus (H1Z1) into the
          fabric of official government pandemic websites, in a viral exploit that piggybacks an
          alternate reality onto actual biopolitical databases. However, the embodied and locative
          dimensions of <title rend="italic">Isolation U.</title> set it apart: the game uses
          motion-awareness to enact a physical quest that explores ideas of individual and
          collective agency through the symbolic landscape of the campus. As the user explores the
          campus, a story unfolds through the StoryTrek reader from the perspective of a newly
          arrived student who only wants to meet people and fit in. This fictional avatar's
          descriptions of the near-future campus, in which a private corporation has replaced all
          vestiges of traditional academic governance structures, are mapped onto the user's own
          perceptions of the actual campus. Walking into particular areas of campus will activate
          fictional advertisements for commercial products and services, or trigger encounters with
          corporate executives and groups of students happily consuming the recommended commodities;
          exploring other areas will lead to run-ins with student radicals, non-player characters
          who will try to convince your avatar that the university is brainwashing students through
          a zombie virus that compels conformity in purchasing habits. Although based on the history
          and geography of our own university, the game will work anywhere with functional GPS
          access, encouraging users to recreate the actual campus through spatial play, replacing
          the familiar spaces in which they live and work with contextualized, hypothetical and
          experiential alternatives <ptr target="#greenspan2011"/>. <title rend="italic">Isolation
            U.</title> thus forces reflection on how private interests are colonizing public spaces
          of learning by targeting students at the very sites in which they work and play. At the
          same time, the game's kinetic algorithms allow users to repurpose the socio-technical
          networks through which capitalism and locative media alike operate, and to
            <soCalled>win</soCalled> actual geophysical space back from corporate sponsors in order
          to unlock the school’s mystery.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Salaam Copenhagen</title>, currently in development by Rilla Khaled
          and Pippin Barr, is based in the daily experience of immigrants living in Nørrebro, the
          largest Muslim quarter of Copenhagen. It integrates a number of narrative strands, each
          presenting the perspective of a particular Muslim character or avatar associated with a
          certain street. The user's varying movements through the streets yield different
          storylines that reflect the character's interactions and struggles with mainstream Danish
          culture, some positive, others less so. The narrative's primary goal is to help young
          Danish users identify with and understand the specific challenges faced by the local
          Muslim population, in the most embodied way possible <ptr target="#khaled2010"/>. We
          anticipate that the added agency afforded by the StoryTrek interface will make the social
          barriers that face the user's avatars all the more poignant. We are also planning to test
          this storytrek with users in other cities far removed from its fictional setting, to see
          how well its intercultural insights travel to other socio-political contexts.</p>
            <p>These narratives all demonstrate how we might give narrative direction to locative media
          and location-based services, instead of just taking directions from them. Galloway
          argues that we need to look squarely at the present of locative media in order to assess
          how predictions about its future can create <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2010">alliances and
            obligations</quote> that realize certain paths of development while precluding other
          visions <ptr target="#galloway2010" loc="34"/>. StoryTrek narratives allow readers to
          apprehend their location within cultural, political and technical alliances, and to forge
          pathways toward new kinds of community. While it is unlikely that such locative narratives
          will soon replace eBooks and audio books or alter decontextualized reading practices, they
          do point the way out of the locative's emphasis on the here-and-now, and toward more
          embodied, dynamic, collective and multiply contextualized applications.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>I am indebted to the StoryTrek design team, Pippin Barr, Robert Biddle, Chris Eaket and
          Rilla Khaled, as well as the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada for
          their generous support of our research.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Amazon.com" xml:id="amazon" key="amazon">Amazon.com <title rend="quotes">Kindle, Wi-Fi, Graphite, 6" Display with New E Ink Pearl Technology</title>. Accessed August 2, 2010.<ref target="http://www.amazon.com/Kindle-Wireless-Reader-Wifi-Graphite/dp/B002Y27P3M">http://amazon.com</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl label="Barr 2008" xml:id="barr2008" key="barr2008">Barr, Pippin. <title rend="italic">Crisis
            22</title>. Storytrek. Ottawa, ON: Hypertext and Hypermedia Lab, 2008.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="benton2000" label="Benton 2000" key="benton2000">Benton, Megan L. <title rend="italic">Beauty
            and the Book: Fine Editions and Cultural Distinction in America</title>. New Haven: Yale
          University Press, 2000.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Bernstein 2003" xml:id="bernstein2003" key="bernstein2003a">Bernstein, Mark. <title rend="quotes">Patterns of Hypertext.</title> Eastgate Systems, at <ref target="http://www.eastgate. com/patterns/Patterns.html">http://www.eastgate.
            com/patterns/Patterns.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bherer2009" label="Bherer et al. 2009" key="bherer2009">Bherer, Val, Cindy Ma and Elise Vist.
            <title rend="italic">Isolation U</title>. Storytrek. Ottawa, ON: Carleton University
          Hypertext and Hypermedia Lab, 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Bogost 2007" xml:id="bogost2007" key="bogost2007">Bogost, Ian. <title rend="italic">Persuasive
            Games: The Expressive Power of Videogames</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press,
          2007.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="boluk2011" label="Boluk &amp; Lenz 2011" key="boluk2011">Boluk, Stephanie and Wylie Lenz,
          eds., <title rend="italic">Generation Zombie: Essays on the Living Dead in Modern
            Culture</title>. Jefferson, NC.: McFarland Press, 2011.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Bull 2005" xml:id="bull2005" key="bull2005">Bull, Michael. <title rend="quotes">No Dead Air!
            The iPod and the Culture of Mobile Listening,</title> in <title rend="italic">Leisure
            Studies</title> 24.4 (October 2005): 343-355.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="eaket2008" label="Eaket 2008" key="eaket2008">Eaket 2008. Eaket, Chris. <title rend="quotes">Project [murmur] and the Performativity of Space,</title> in <title rend="italic">Theatre Research in Canada</title> 29.1 (Spring 2008): 29-50, at <ref target="http://www.lib.unb.ca/Texts/TRIC/vol29 _1/tric29_1art02.pdf">http://www.lib.unb.ca/Texts/TRIC/vol29 _1/tric29_1art02.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Emmott 1998" xml:id="emmott1998" key="emmott1998">Emmott, Catherine. <title rend="quotes">
                  <soCalled>Situated Events</soCalled> in Fictional Worlds: The Reader's Role in
            Context Construction,</title> in <title rend="italic">European Journal of English
            Studies</title> 2.2 (1998): 175-194.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="evans2010" label="Evans 2010" key="evans2010a">Evans, Bob. <title rend="quotes">Steve Jobs
            Torpedoes Another Stale Model.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Information Week</title> (February 15, 2010): 8.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Galloway 2010" xml:id="galloway2010" key="galloway2010">Galloway, Anne. <title rend="quotes">Locating Media Futures in the Present; Or How to map Emergent Associations &amp;
            Expectations,</title> in <title rend="italic">Aether: The Journal of Media
            Geography</title>, 5A (March 2010): 27-36.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gerrig1993" label="Gerrig 1993" key="gerrig1993">Gerrig, Richard J. <title rend="italic">Experiencing Narrative Worlds: On the Psychological Activities of Reading</title>. New
          Haven: Yale University Press, 1993.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Giles et al. 2009" xml:id="giles2009" key="giles2009">Giles, Thierry, Michael Marianek and
          Sarah K. Freidel, <title rend="quotes">URBAN ENCOUNTER: Location-Based Collective
            Storytelling,</title> presented at MobileHCI'09, September 15-18, 2009, Bonn,
          Germany.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="green2004" label="Green 2004" key="green2004">Green, Melanie C. <title rend="quotes">Transportation Into Narrative Worlds: The Role of Prior Knowledge and Perceived
            Realism,</title> in <title rend="italic">Discourse Processes</title> 38.2 (2004):
          247-266.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Green et al. 2004" xml:id="greenetal2004" key="greenetal2004">Green, Melanie C., Timothy C. Brock
          and Geoff F. Kaufmann. <title rend="quotes">Understanding Media Enjoyment: The Role of
            Transportation into Narrative Worlds,</title> in <title rend="italic">Communication
            Theory</title> 14.4 (November 2004): 311-327.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="greenspan2011" label="Greenspan 2011" key="greenspan2011">
               <title rend="quotes">A Brain is a
            Terrible Thing to Waste: Isolation U. and the Campus Zombie</title>, forthcoming in
          Stephanie Boluk and Wylie Lenz, eds.<title rend="italic">Generation Zombie:Essays on the Living Dead in Modern Culture</title>. Jefferson, NC.: McFarland Press, 2011.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Harvey 2000" xml:id="harvey2000" key="harvey2000">Harvey, David. <title rend="italic">Spaces of
            Hope</title>. Berkeley: The University of California Press, 2000.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hayles2005" label="Hayles 2005" key="hayles2005">Hayles, N. Katherine. <title rend="italic">My
            Mother Was a Computer: Digital Subjects and Literary Texts</title>. Chicago: The
          University of Chicago Press, 2005.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Hight 2010" xml:id="hight2010" key="hight2010">Hight, Jeremy. <title rend="quotes">Locative
            Narrative, Literature and Form,</title> in Jörgen Schäfer and Peter Gendolla, eds. <title rend="italic">Beyond the Screen: Transformations of Literary Structures, Interfaces and Genres</title>.
          317-330.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="khaled2010" label="Khaled &amp; Barr 2010" key="khaled2010">Khaled, Rilla and Pippin Barr.
            <title rend="italic">Salaam Copenhagen</title>. Storytrek. Copenhagen: IT Copenhagen,
          2010.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Klima 2006" xml:id="klima2006" key="klima2006">Klima, John. <title rend="quotes">Saint
            Joe.</title> Locative installation for the 13th Annual International Symposium of
          Electronic Art, San Jose, 2006, at <ref target="http://2006.01sj.org/ content/view/53/49">http://2006.01sj.org/ content/view/53/49</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="knowltona" label="Knowlton et al. a" key="knowltona">Knowlton, Jeff, Naomi Spellman and Jeremy
          Hight. <title rend="italic">34 North 188 West: Mining the Urban Landscape</title>. <ref target="http://www.34n118w.net/34N">http://www.34n118w.net/34N</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Knowlton et al. b" xml:id="knowltonb" key="knowltonb">Knowlton, Jeff, Naomi Spellman and Brandon
          Stow. <title rend="italic">The Interpretive Engine for Various Places on Earth</title>.
            <ref target="http://engine.34n118w.net">http://engine.34n118w.net</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lovlie2009" label="Løvlie 2009" key="lovlie2009">Løvlie, Anders Sundnes. <title rend="italic">Poetic Augmented Reality: Place-bound Literature in Locative Media</title>. Proceedings
          of the 13th International MindTrek Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era,
          Tampere, Finland, 2009: 19-28.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Marin 1984" xml:id="marin1984" key="marin1984">Marin, Louis. <title rend="italic">Utopics: The
            Semiological Play of Textual Spaces</title>. Robert A. Vollrath (trans.). New York:
          Humanity Books, 1984.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="miall2001" label="Miall &amp; Dobson 2001" key="miall2001">Miall, David S. and Teres
          Dobson. <title rend="quotes">Reading Hypertext and the Experience of Literature,</title>
          in <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Information</title> 2.1 (2001), at <ref target="http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/viewArticle/35">http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/viewArticle/35</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Micallef et al. 2003" xml:id="micallef2003" key="micallef2003">Micallef, Shawn, Gabe Sawhney and
          James Roussel. <title rend="quotes">[murmur].</title> Locative installation, Toronto, at
            <ref target="http://murmurtoronto.ca/about.php">http://murmurtoronto.ca/about.php</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell1996" label="Mitchell 1996" key="mitchell1996">Mitchell, William J. <title rend="italic">City of Bits: Space, Place, and the Infobahn</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press,
          1996.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Murray 1997" xml:id="murray1997" key="murray1997">Murray, Janet. <title rend="italic">Hamlet on
            the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in Cyberspace</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT
          Press, 1997.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ong2002" label="Ong 2002" key="ong2002">Ong, Walter J. <title rend="italic">Orality and
            Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word</title> (2nd ed). New York: Routledge,
          2002.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Philips 2007" xml:id="philips2007" key="philips2007">Philips, Deborah. <title rend="quotes">Talking Books: The Encounter of LIterature and Technology in the Audio Book,</title> in
            <title rend="italic">Convergence</title> 13.3 (2007): 293-306.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="pope2006" label="Pope 2006" key="pope2006">
               <title rend="quotes">A Future for Hypertext
            Fiction,</title> in <title rend="italic">Convergence</title> 12.4 (2006):
          447-465.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Pressman 2007" xml:id="pressman2007" key="pressman2007">Pressman, Aaron. <title rend="quotes">Buy
            Amazon – Kindle is the iPod of Books.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Bloomberg Businessweek</title> (November 19, 2007), at <ref target="http://www.businessweek.com/ investing/insights/blog/archives/2007/11/buy_amazon_-_kindle_is_the_ipod_of_ books.html">http://www.businessweek.com/
            investing/insights/blog/archives/2007/11/buy_amazon_-_kindle_is_the_ipod_of_
            books.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="proboscis" label="Proboscis" key="proboscis">
               <title rend="italic">Urban Tapestries</title>.
            <ref target="http://proboscis.org.uk/projects/urban-tapestries">http://proboscis.org.uk/projects/urban-tapestries</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Raley 2010" xml:id="raley2010" key="raley2010">Raley, Rita. <title rend="quotes">Walk This Way:
            Mobile Narrative as Composed Experience</title>, in Jörgen Schäfer and Peter Gendolla,
          eds. <title>Beyond the Screen: Transformations of Literary Structures, Interfaces and Genres</title>. 299-316.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rober2006" label="Röber et al. 2006" key="rober2006">Röber, Niklas, Cornelius Huber, Knut
          Hartmann, Matthias Feustel and Maic Masuch. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Audiobooks:
            Combining Narratives with Game Elements,</title> in <title rend="italic">Technologies
            for Interactive Digital Storytelling and Entertainment</title>. Berlin: Springer, 2006:
          358-369.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Rothbauer 2009" xml:id="rothbauer2009" key="rothbauer2009">Rothbauer, Pauline. <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Placelessness of Reading Among Older Teens in a Canadian Rural
            Municipality,</title> in <title rend="italic">Library Quarterly</title> 79.4 (2009):
          465-483.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rueb2005" label="Rueb 2005" key="rueb2005">Rueb, Teri. <title rend="italic">itinerant</title>. Locative installation, Boston, 2005, at <ref target="http://www. turbulence.org/Works/itinerant">http://www.
            turbulence.org/Works/itinerant</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Rueb 1996" xml:id="rueb1996" key="rueb1996">Rueb, Teri. <title rend="italic">TRACE: a memorial
            environmental sound installation</title>. Locative installation, Yoho National Park,
          British Columbia, 1996, at <ref target="http://www. terirueb.net/trace/index.html">http://www. terirueb.net/trace/index.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ryan2004" label="Ryan 2004" key="ryan2004">Ryan, Marie-Laure. <title rend="quotes">Cyberspace, Cybertexts, Cybermaps,</title> in <title rend="italic">Dichtung
            Digital</title> (2004), at <ref target="http://www.brown.edu/Research/dichtung-digital/2004/1-Ryan.htm">http://www.brown.edu/Research/dichtung-digital/2004/1-Ryan.htm</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Ryan 1980" xml:id="ryan1980" key="ryan1980">Ryan, Marie-Laure. <title rend="quotes">Fiction,
            Non-Factuals, and the Principle of Minimal Departure,</title> in <title rend="italic">Poetics</title> 9 (1980): 403-422.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="schafer2010a" label="Schäfer &amp; Gendolla 2010a" key="schafer2010a">Schäfer, Jörgen and Peter
          Gendolla, eds., <title rend="italic">Beyond the Screen: Transformations of Literary
            Structures, Interfaces and Genres</title>. New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction Publishers,
          2010.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Spellman &amp; Knowlton 2004" xml:id="spellman2004" key="spellman2004">Spellman, Naomi and
          Jeff Knowlton. <title rend="italic">InterUrban</title>. Locative installation for Mobile
          Connections, Futuresonic, Manchester, UK, 2004. at <ref target="http://interurban.34n118w.net">http://interurban.34n118w.net</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="whitson2008" label="Whitson et al. 2008" key="whitson2008">Jennifer Whitson, Chris Eaket, Brian
          Greenspan, Minh Quang Tran, Natalie King. <title rend="quotes">Neo-Immersion: Awareness
            and Engagement in Gameplay,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2008
            Conference on Future Play: Research, Play, Share</title>, November 03-05, 2008, Toronto,
          Ontario, Canada, pp. 220-223, New York: ACM, 2008, at <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1496984.1497028">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1496984.1497028</ref>.</bibl>

         </listBibl>

      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>