<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!-- article title in English -->Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of <title>Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title> </title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jason <dhq:family>Boyd</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Ryerson University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jason.boyd@ryerson.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jason Boyd is an Associate Professor of English and Director of the Centre for Digital Humanities at Ryerson University. 
                        Prior to this, he was the Digital Projects Manager and Associate Director and Managing Editor of the Records of Early English Drama
                        (REED)’s <title rend="quotes">Patrons and Performances</title> database. He was the TEI Editor for REED’s <title rend="italic">Fortune Theatre Records Prototype Digital Edition</title> (2013)
                        and a co-author of the project's comprehensive white paper (<ref target="https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:33411">https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:33411</ref>).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000572</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    >015</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2021-10-15">October 15, 2021</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000572/000572.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p><title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title> offers a collection of essays focused on Shakespeare’s (or Shakespeare-adjacent) plays and how they 
                can be newly-understood and newly-edited with a range of digital repositories, creation platforms, and tools. 
                The collection provides solid content and provocative ideas about the possible paths to integrating Shakespeare’s and other early modern English-focused content online.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Review of <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            
            <div>
                <head/>
        <p>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are
            hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development
            of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of <title rend="italic"
                >Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media</title> argue that <quote rend="inline">the state of computing
            in Shakespeare studies</quote> functions as <quote rend="inline">a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy
            in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation
            technologies</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="2"/>. As a case in point,
            the editors relate that twenty years ago, in 1997-8, a sort of precursor to their
            collection appeared in the form of a pair of special issues of <title rend="italic"
                >Early Modern Literary Studies</title>. The essays there focused on two new/nascent
            digital scholarly resources: the <title rend="italic">Early Modern English Dictionaries
                Database</title> (<title rend="italic">EMEDD</title>), under the editorship of Ian
            Lancashire, and <title rend="italic">Internet Shakespeare Editions</title> (ISE), under
            the editorship of Michael Best. Today, <title rend="italic">EMEDD</title> has been
            superseded by <title rend="italic">Lexicons of Early Modern English</title> (<title
                rend="italic">LEME</title>), edited by Lancashire, and <title rend="italic">ISE</title>
            (now under the editorship of Janelle Jenstad) has been joined by sibling projects
            like <title rend="italic">Queen’s Men Editions</title> (<title rend="italic">QME</title>), <title
                rend="italic">Digital Renaissance Editions</title> (<title rend="italic">DRE</title>) and
            the <title rend="italic">Map of Early Modern London</title> (<title rend="italic"
                >MoEML</title>). While the essays in the present collection bring together text editing
            and historical linguistic analysis in digital scholarship, the editors point out
            that a divergence persists between these two fields that is mirrored in the
            differing directions that <title rend="italic">LEME</title> and <title rend="italic">ISE</title>
            have taken towards their texts: the former along a <q>dynamic text</q> path facilitating
            lexical research across a corpus of period glossaries, the latter along a
            <q>hypertextual edition</q> path facilitating enhanced reading and study of individual
            Shakespeare plays. The editors point to signs of convergence of these divergent
            paths, and one of the sources of interest in this collection for the digital
            humanist (Shakespearean and non-Shakespearean) is the ways the essays suggest how –
            in the digital humanities test bed that is digital Shakespeare – such diverging
            scholarly activities and foci (the word and the text, the micro and the macro) might
            be integrated in or across future digital scholarly environments. </p>
        <p>On the whole, the essays in this collection focus on Shakespeare’s (or
            Shakespeare-adjacent) plays and how they can be newly understood and newly edited
            with primary resources such as <title rend="italic">LEME</title>, <title rend="italic">Early
                English Books Online</title> (<title rend="italic">EEBO</title>), digital
            editing/publishing platforms like <title rend="italic">ISE</title> and <title rend="italic"
                >QME</title>, and some common digital tools like <title rend="italic">Voyant
                    Tools</title>, Python scripts, and spreadsheet software. In addition, Laura Estill
            and Andie Silva’s essay <title rend="quotes">Storing and Accessing Knowledge: Digital Tools for the
            Study of Early Modern Drama</title> provides a critical if somewhat cursory survey of some
            other key online resources that are currently available to scholars of early modern
            drama: the <title rend="italic">English Short Title Catalogue</title> (<title rend="italic"
                >ESTC</title>), the <title rend="italic">Database of Early English Plays</title> (<title
                    rend="italic">DEEP</title>), <title rend="italic">Early Modern London Theatres</title>
            (<title rend="italic">EMLoT</title>), <title rend="italic">Patrons and Performances</title>,
            and the <title rend="italic">World Shakespeare Bibliography</title> (<title rend="italic"
                >WSB</title>).</p>
        <p>Shakespeare’s language/word usage is the focus of the essays of Part I, “Old words
            through new media: Re-reading Shakespeare with <title rend="italic">EEBO-TCP</title> and
            <title rend="italic">LEME</title>.” As the editors point out in their prefatory marks
            to this section, <title rend="italic">LEME</title> and <title rend="italic">EEBO-TCP</title>
            (and their interlinking) now compel editors of early modern play texts to rethink
            how they gloss words, given that they can now not only explain words that
            contemporary readers might find obscure, but also identify words that Shakespeare’s
            contemporaries would have found unfamiliar, and which therefore prompt closer
            examination of the speeches and scenes in which these unfamiliar (or “hard”) words
            are present. </p>
        <p>The first essay here, Valerie Wayne’s <title rend="quotes">Beyond the <title rend="italic">OED</title> Loop:
            Digital Resources and the Arden 3 <title rend="italic">Cymbeline</title>,</title> begins by
            pointing out the reliance of editors of Shakespeare on the <title rend="italic">Oxford
                English Dictionary</title> (<title rend="italic">OED</title>) in determining the
            uniqueness of Shakespeare’s deployment and development of English vocabulary and
            word usage, and the reliance of the <title rend="italic">OED</title> on Shakespeare (and
            his editors) as a source for new usages of words and new coinages — the so-called <soCalled><title
                rend="italic">OED</title> Loop.</soCalled> One way around this loop is the <title rend="italic"
                    >Early English Books Online-Text Creation Partnership</title> (<title rend="italic"
                        >EEBO-TCP</title>), comprising (as of July 2016), 60,331 texts coded for searching,
            which Wayne uses in conjunction with <title rend="italic">LEME</title> and the <title
                rend="italic">OED</title> to <quote rend="inline">assist in the recovery of words once thought to be
            errors in early texts, correct claims for coinages, clarify occluded meanings, and
            detect the most prevalent forms and spellings</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="15"/>.
            (As the following essay by Lancashire and Tersigni notes, as of 2018, <title
                rend="italic">LEME</title> comprised about <quote rend="inline">665,000 word-entries in 199 lexical
            works from about 1475 to 1702,</quote> with <title rend="italic">LEME</title> and the <title
                rend="italic">OED</title> <quote rend="inline">overlap[ping] by less than 5% in the quotations they
                    offer</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="29"/>). Wayne
            proceeds to demonstrate how such documentary editing is done using specific examples
            from <title rend="italic">Cymbeline</title>, in the process — even if only provisionally,
            given the material still forthcoming on these resources — revealing doubtful
            editorial emendations, clarifying cruxes in the interpretation of phrases, calling
            into question Shakespeare as the coiner of certain words and word usages, recovering
            often downplayed or not fully appreciated sexual meanings, and determining the usual
            spelling of a proper name (it’s <title rend="italic">Innogen</title>, not <title
                rend="italic">Imogen</title>). As Wayne points out: <quote rend="inline">Both databases enable forms of
            recovery and argument that were barely possible a decade or two ago and are of
            immense help to an editor</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="24"/> who wants
            to do a historically sensitive analysis of Shakespeare’s use of language.</p>
        <p>Ian Lancashire and Elisa Tersigni’s <title rend="quotes">Shakespeare’s Hard Words, and Our Hard Senses,</title>
            like Wayne’s essay, shows how <title rend="italic">LEME</title> can provide more
            historically accurate and more coherent glosses on Shakespeare words. Noting that
            <quote rend="inline">no editors have yet annotated Shakespeare’s works for the relative difficulty of
                their words to his contemporaries</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="27"/>,
            they use <title rend="italic">LEME</title> to explore how Shakespeare’s contemporary
            audiences understood his language and how that affected the perception of his
            characters, focusing on <title rend="italic">Richard III</title> and <title rend="italic">The
                Tempest</title>. They note a marked difference in what words contemporary editors
            gloss and what words were considered <soCalled>hard</soCalled> by those who created glossaries in the
            early modern period, and compare the differing deployment of hard words in the
            speeches of Richmond and Richard to their troops before the Battle of Bosworth,
            which, they argue, Shakespeare employed innovatively to <quote rend="inline">illuminate his
                characters</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="28"/>. Using the <title rend="italic">Hard Word
                    Annotator</title>, a <title rend="italic">LEME</title> tool that accepts plaintext
            versions of modern-spelling Early Modern texts and identifies the hard words in
            them, they analyze the entirety of <title rend="italic">The Tempest</title> <quote rend="inline">to test
            whether hard words are used consistently as part of the characterization,</quote>
            concluding that the <quote rend="inline">percentage of hard words used by characters reflects their
                personality, occupation, race, gender, and social status</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="32"/>. The bookish
            Prospero, perhaps unsurprisingly, emerges as the leader in the use of hard words,
            which Lancashire and Tersigni cleverly suggest explains Prospero’s repeated
            interruption of his recounting of his past life in Act 1, Scene 2: to confirm that
            Miranda (and the audience) are still paying attention to a speech peppered with
            baffling words. Their analysis also supports the decision by some editors to
            reassign to Prospero a speech (also in Act 1, Scene 2) assigned to Miranda in the
            First Folio, given that the frequency of hard words is more in character with
            Prospero’s vocabulary than his daughter’s.</p>
        <p>The remaining two essays of Part I, Daniel Aureliano Newman’s <title rend="quotes">Terms of Art in Law
            and Herbals,</title> and Elizabeth Bernath’s <title rend="quotes">‘Strangers enfranchised’: Shakespeare’s <title
                rend="italic">Hamlet</title> and the Mother Tongue,</title> use <title rend="italic"
                    >LEME</title> and <title rend="italic">EEBO</title> in conjunction to explore, in the
            former, the use of herbal and legal <soCalled>terms of art</soCalled> (or what we would call jargon) in
            <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, <title rend="italic">King John</title>, and <title
                rend="italic">The Winter’s Tale</title> (with a particularly compelling
            contribution to, if not resolution of, the vexed issue of Perdita’s <quote rend="inline">streak’d
            Gilly-vors</quote>), and, in the latter, a comparison of hard words in <title rend="italic"
                >Hamlet</title> against the diachronic evidence of the <soCalled>enfranchisement</soCalled> of hard
            words in the English <soCalled>mother tongue.</soCalled> As with Lancashire and Tersigni’s analysis of
            Richmond’s speech in <title rend="italic">Richard III</title>, Bernath argues that, in
            Hamlet’s soliloquies, Shakespeare provides glosses, often synonyms, for (still) hard
            words within the speeches themselves.</p>
        <p>The essays of Part I together offer a compelling case for the important insights that
            can result from textual databases whose encoding, data structures, and search tools
            can enable sophisticated and wide-ranging linguistic research queries. The remaining
            four essays (besides the Estill and Silva essay previously mentioned) broaden the
            scope beyond words and language, shifting, in effect, from a ‘<title rend="italic"
                >LEME</title> orientation’ to an ‘<title rend="italic">ISE</title> orientation.’ Andrew
            Griffin’s <title rend="quotes">Text, Performance, and Multidisciplinarity: On a Digital Edition of <title
                rend="italic">King Leir</title>,</title> describes how the capaciousness of digital
            editions enables the <title rend="italic">Queen’s Men Editions</title> (QME) to avoid the
            prescriptivism that invariably manifests in print versions of performance editions,
            given their limited ability to incorporate a full range of production examples.
            Instead of a transhistorical or ahistorical or ideal conceptualization of a
            performance of a play, the <title rend="italic">QME</title> of <title rend="italic">King
                Leir</title>, by collaborating with a team who staged a production of the play, can
            link to its specific production details (in the form of images and videos) within
            the context of production notes that detail possible performance options considered,
            discussion about these options, and what option was eventually chosen (and why). Toby Malone’s
            <title rend="quotes">A Digital Parallel-Text Approach to Performance Historiography</title> describes a
            prototype parallel-text digital edition (created using spreadsheet software)
            enabling comparative analysis of the Quarto 1 and Folio versions of <title
                rend="italic">Richard III</title>, along with 10 historical promptbooks and performance
            editions ranging from the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to 20<hi
                rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries relating to historically significant
            Shakespearean actors such as Colly Cibber, David Garrick, John Philip Kemble, Edmund
            Kean, William Charles Macready, and Henry Irving. Malone argues that <quote rend="inline">[o]ne simple
            and ubiquitous digital tool — a spreadsheet — makes the systematic, large-scale, and
            flexible comparative close reading of performance texts possible </quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="122"/>
            in ways that print parallel texts cannot.
            While some digital humanities scholars might scoff at the use of a general-use
            spreadsheet program for a (prototype) digital edition, such a tool has the advantage
            of realizing and ensuring some degree of longevity to an digital edition than one
            created through a digital humanities-specific comparison and collation tool like the
            now-defunct <title rend="italic">Juxta Commons</title>, a web service that was until
            recently offered by <title rend="italic">NINE</title>S (<title rend="italic">Networked
                Infrastructure for Nineteenth-Century Electronic Scholarship</title>), developed at
            the University of Virginia. </p>
        <p>Michael Ullyot and Adam James Bradley’s <title rend="quotes">Past Texts, Present Tools, and Future
            Critics: Toward <title rend="italic">Rhetorical Schematics</title>,</title> can be regarded as
            occupying a transitory place between a focus on word analysis and a focus on textual
            editing, given its focus on rhetorical figures. In the essay, the authors discuss
            their creation of a Python script designed to process plaintext corpora like Martin
            Mueller’s <title rend="italic">Shakespeare His Contemporaries</title> (comprising
            Shakespeare’s plays along with most of the plays written within a generation before
            and after his active career as a playwright) to find a rhetorical scheme called <hi rend="bold">gradatio</hi>, which is a series of <hi rend="bold"
                    >anadiploses</hi>. The essay cites an example of <hi rend="bold">gradatio</hi>
            from <title rend="italic">As You Like It</title> (Act 5, Scene 2): “For your brother and
            my sister not sooner met but they <hi rend="bold">looked</hi>; no sooner <hi rend="bold">looked</hi> but they <hi rend="bold">loved</hi>; no sooner <hi rend="bold"
                >loved</hi> but they <hi rend="bold">sighed</hi>; no sooner <hi rend="bold"
                    >sighed</hi> but they asked one another the <hi rend="bold"
                            >reason</hi>; not sooner knew the <hi rend="bold">reason</hi> but they sought
            the remedy; and in these degrees have they made a pair of stairs to marriage.” While
            the Python script itself is not included, a fairly clear description of it is: its
            goal was “to break text files into sentences, to tokenize their words and lemmatize
            their tokens, to insert clause breaks based on punctuation, and finally to use
            Regular Expressions to look for matching lemmas…within four words of the clause
            breaks” <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="147"/>. The script identified 114
            instances of what it was told was <hi rend="bold">gradatio</hi> in 400 plays for
            analysis and evaluation, leading the researchers to contemplate not only the
            efficacy of the script, but their critical understanding of <hi rend="bold"
                >graditio</hi> itself. The authors concede that there might be instances of <hi rend="bold"
                    >gradatio</hi> this script did not identify but argue that their
            modest purpose was to obtain <quote rend="inline">more complete results than we could gather without the
            algorithm.</quote> They also concede that such scripts appear to only be effective at
            identifying rhetorical schemes <quote rend="inline">of direct repetition and variation</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="147"/>
            of words or phrases, and so cannot be
            used to locate a broad spectrum of rhetorical figures in digital texts corpora.</p>
        <p>In envisioning practical future solutions for <quote rend="inline">a more nuanced, multivalent,
            tool-enhanced criticism</quote> that would extend their script and integrate the textual
            edition and the database (or, in other words, <title rend="italic">ISE</title> and <title
                rend="italic">LEME</title>), Ullyot and Bradley they propose <quote rend="inline">an unobtrusive
            plug-in for <title rend="italic">ISE</title> that makes [its editions] interoperable with
            databases</quote> and that <quote rend="inline">preserve[s] close reading while promoting distant reading,
            balancing our attention to local phenomena with our ambient awareness of comparable
            phenomena</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="152–3"/>. They argue that such
            interoperability requires that textual corpora have APIs, as <title rend="italic"
                >Folger Digital Texts</title> does: <quote rend="inline">An API for the <title rend="italic">ISE</title>
            would allow its texts to offer limitless new questions, which these interoperable
            databases can illuminate</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="154"/>.</p>
        <p>The idea of limitlessness that the interoperability of digital resources promises is
            clearly in evidence in Diane K. Jakacki’s <title rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">Internet Shakespeare
                Editions</title> and the Infinite (Editorial) Others: Supporting Critical Tagsets
            for Linked Editions,</title> which also takes up the topic of integration/interoperability,
            albeit in a less speculative and more grounded (and consequently wary) fashion. As
            the editor of the <title rend="italic">ISE</title>’s edition of <title rend="italic">Henry
                VIII</title>, as well as the Technical Editor of <title rend="italic">ISE</title>,
            Jakacki is alert to both the possibilities and the pitfalls of interoperable,
            networked digital editions. The key challenge the essay addresses is <quote rend="inline">to what degree
            we should engage in acts of editorial disruption that allow us to move forward
            towards infinity [the infinity represented by other potential editions] while
            maintaining editorial stability across digital projects</quote> <ptr target="#jenstad2020" loc="158"/>.
            As she considers her <title rend="italic">Henry VIII</title>
            edition beyond the additional TEI encoding she has used and that she demonstrates
            can be valuable for aiding an editor’s critical interpretation, and starts to
            consider it as part of a network that ties it in with digital resources like <title
                rend="italic">MoEML</title> and <title rend="italic">DRE</title>, a digital edition of a
            single play starts to stretch out towards an unfinishable infinity: Jakacki makes
            reference to how a non-peer reviewed edition of Samuel Rowley’s <title rend="italic"
                >When You See Me You Know Me</title> that she intended to include in her edition of
            <title rend="italic">Henry VIII</title> (presumably as an appendix) was, with the
            launch of <title rend="italic">DRE</title>, re-envisioned as a peer-reviewed edition of
            Rowley’s play for <title rend="italic">DRE</title> that would serve as a companion edition
            to her <title rend="italic">ISE</title> of <title rend="italic">Henry VIII</title>. She also
            mentions the idea of creating a shared Personography of all the characters that
            appear across <title rend="italic">ISE</title>, <title rend="italic">QME</title>, and <title
                rend="italic">DRE</title>. The challenge Jakacki points out, with legitimate
            concern, is that considering the creation of an edition in light of how it can be
            interoperable with other digital resources can significantly add to an editor’s task
            and timelines to completion. Indeed, such work can potentially take an editor far
            from their initial interest: the text(s) of a Shakespeare play. Can editing ever be said to 'end' in an interoperable digital environment?</p>
        <p>There is much more to the essays in this collection that I have not foregrounded and
            that would be of value to scholars primarily interested in
            historical linguistic analysis, Shakespeare studies and scholarly editing. While readers
            primarily interested in the technical side of digital humanities may find the essays
            less than forthcoming (Ullyot and Bradley, for example, do not provide the actual
            Python script they created, and so one cannot judge whether it could be modified or
            extended to detect similar or other textual structures) and vague on future
            directions and modes of development, especially regarding cyberinfrastructures for
            interoperability, there is solid content and provocative ideas in this collection
            about the possible paths (or perhaps path?) to making Shakespeare’s texts digitally
            accessible in all their complexity as well as early modern English texts and culture
            more broadly. If the editors’ claim that Shakespeare is the test bed for new
            developments in digital humanities is true, we should continue to look to the
            digital remediation of the author’s old texts for inspiring new digital tools.</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jenstad2020" label="Jenstad, Kaethler, and Roberts-Smith 2020">Jenstad, J., Kaethler,
                    M., &amp; Roberts-Smith, J. (eds). <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Language in
                        Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title>, Routledge, London (2020).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
