<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English--></title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"
                        ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation/>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
                <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
                    <term corresp=""/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/NNNNNN/NNNNNN.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Unjust Readings: Against the New New Criticism" offers a theoretical and methodological defence of the use of digital humanities methods for literary interpretation. 
                    I argue that extant critiques of DH from Fish, Da, Eyers and others depend on an unexamined notion of the appropriate work of the humanities and, in particular, 
                    of literary interpretation. Their claim, that critics should simply "just read" obscures the manner in which literary interpretation is never simply 'just reading.' 
                    I argue that DH not only raises interpretive possibilities that would be impossible without digital tools but also foregrounds the methodological choices and theoretical 
                    paradigms that so often are unstated, or implicit, in traditional humanities work. Inherent to the interpretive act that moves between the digital and the humanities is 
                    a need to state how the critic works between the two, thereby making the interpretive frame explicit. I then demonstrate a number of examples, from my research and the work of others, 
                    that demonstrate this productive capacity of DH in order to further refute that critics should simply 'just read' the texts.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p> x
                </p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Unjust Readings: Against the New New Criticism</head>
                <q>I had no wish to read more and no need to do so.</q> –Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>
                
                <p><name>Nan Z. Da</name>’s (2019) <title rend="quotes">The Computational Case Against Computational Literary Study</title> is a
                major critique of Computational Literary Studies that attempts to challenge it at
                both the methodological and theoretical levels. Her essay <quote rend="inline">works at the empirical
                level</quote> to identify <title rend="quotes">technical problems, logical fallacies, and conceptual flaws</title> as
                well as methodological inconsistencies and questionable results of a number of CLS
                projects. She asserts that for these projects, <quote rend="inline">what is robust is obvious … and what
                is not obvious is not robust</quote> <ptr target="#da2019"/>.</p>
                
                <p><name>Da</name>’s argument is, by now, well known and has been thoroughly examined, challenged,
                and defended in a number of venues; the goal here is not to rehash the debates of
                the past few years. Rather, in what follows, I examine the interpretive implications
                of Da’s argument, shifting the grounds from the so-called <quote rend="inline">empirical level</quote> to
                examine the humanistic foundation of her critique and the implications of sliding
                from her challenge to CLS 
                
                <note>She claims to be analyzing a subfield <quote rend="inline">variously
                known as cultural analytics, literary data mining, quantitative formalism,
                literary text mining, computational textual analysis, computational criticism,
                algorithmic literary studies, social computing for literary studies, and
                computational literary studies</quote> <ptr target="#da2019"/>.</note>
                
                to the broader critique of the digital humanities made by many of her subsequent supporters. I argue that <name>Da</name>’s
                critique of CLS, and the subsequent debates concerning her work, open up paradigms
                of reading and, in doing so, have a tell us a great deal about the general state of
                the humanities, and the attendant discourse of humanism that undergirds a number of
                critiques of digital humanities.</p>
                
                <p>Of the numerous responses to <name>Da</name>’s work, <name>Stanley Fish</name>’s (2019) <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title> is perhaps
                the most controversial and least surprising. After first acknowledging his lack of
                <quote rend="inline">real credentials in the field,</quote> <name>Fish</name> then asserts that this lack of expertise has
                absolutely no bearing on his <quote rend="inline">pronouncing on the Digital Humanities because my [his]
                objections to it are lodged on a theoretical level in relation to which actual
                statistical work in the field is beside the point.</quote> He jokes that while his daughter
                is a statistician, he understood hardly twenty percent of her recent lecture on
                <quote rend="inline">some issue in bio-medical statistics</quote>; he comprehends so little of the topic, he
                cannot identify it. Yet where this mere twenty percent of understanding (presumably
                this measurement is a statistical Dad joke on his part) impedes his grasp on his
                daughter’s lecture, this is not the case with digital humanities. <name>Fish</name> needn’t
                follow the methods or mathematical reasoning by which digital humanities scholars
                make their arguments because he doesn’t <quote rend="inline">care what form these analyses take. I know
                in advance that they will fail.</quote> As he sees it, his ignorance has no effect on his
                ability to assess this field.</p>
            
                <p><name>Fish</name>’s <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title>is his latest in a series of arguments against Computational
                Literary Studies and Digital Humanities. His central critique, throughout these
                complaints, is that digital projects <quote rend="inline">crank up a huge amount of machinery in order
                to produce something that was obvious from the get go</quote>
                
                <note> This self-citation borrows, in content and form, from his own 1973 essay, <title rend="quotes">What Is Stylistics and
                Why Are They Saying Such Terrible Things About It</title> (Fish 1973). In this critique
                of <name>Louis Milic</name>’s <title rend="italic">A Quantitative Approach to the Style of
                Jonathan Swift</title>, <name>Fish</name> (1982) asserts that <quote rend="inline">there is nothing in the
                machinery that Milic cranks up to authorize the leap (from the data to a
                specification of their value) he makes</quote> <ptr target="#fish1982"/>. In his more recent <title rend="quotes">The Interpretive
                Poverty of Data</title> (2018) (in which he dredges up the case of Milic once again) he
                recycles the phrasing further: <quote rend="inline">More often than not, the mountainous machinery
                it usually cranks up labors to produce something less even than a mouse; you
                wade through a whole lot of charts, distribution patterns, selection patterns,
                contiguity patterns and find waiting for you at the other end something that
                would have been obvious from the get-go to a ten year old</quote> <ptr target="#fish2018"/>.</note> 
                
                and that <quote rend="inline">they just dress up garden variety literary intuition in numbers</quote><ptr target="#fish2019"/>.
                He goes on to insist that <quote rend="inline">the interpretive conclusions they draw from the
                assembled data are entirely arbitrary, without motivation except the motivation to
                have their labors yield something, yield anything. Either their herculean efforts do
                nothing or when something is done with them, it is entirely illegitimate</quote><ptr target="#fish2019"/>.
                This critique echoes <name>Fish</name>’s past arguments where he describes DH as an
                <quote rend="inline">antimethdology that refuses closure</quote> <ptr target="#fish2012"/> while also arguing that digital
                forms of interpretation are meaningless <quote rend="inline">because the data, just sitting there in all
                its empty bulk, can be made to support anything</quote> <ptr target="#fish2018"/>. He elsewhere insists
                that <quote rend="inline">The desire to generate insight into human expression by ‘scientific’ means is
                futile,</quote> <ptr target="#fish2019b"/> thereby leading to an irreconcilable difference between <quote rend="inline">real
                interpretation</quote> and <quote rend="inline">corpus linguistic analysis</quote> <ptr target="#fish2018"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Da</name> works <quote rend="inline">at the empirical level</quote> to challenge the novelty and conclusions of CLS
                whereas <name>Fish</name>’s critique works at <quote rend="inline">the theoretical level</quote> to challenge the paradigms
                of reading and interpretation upon which (he believes) DH depends. In this vague and
                ill-conceived division, both critics draw on a false dichotomy. As <name>Katherine Bode</name>’s
                recent <title rend="quotes">What’s the Matter with Computational Literary Studies? </title>argues, there is a
                <quote rend="inline">fundamental agreement between critics and proponents of CLS: that computation is
                separate from literary phenomena</quote> <ptr target="#bode2023"/>. <name>Bode</name> calls for a ‘performative CLS’
                that is <quote rend="inline">Attuned to the coconstitution of computational methods and objects – with
                each other, and with literary subjectivities and textualities</quote> <ptr target="#bode2023"/>. I extend <name>Bode</name>’s
                argument to demonstrate that <name>Da</name> and <name>Fish</name>’s illusory splitting of the interpretive
                act inadvertently bolsters the claims of the digital humanities by offering a fresh
                critique of the humanities more generally.</p>
            
                <p>Yet, to return to <name>Fish</name>’s argument, what fields and methods is he assessing? While
                <name>Fish</name> uses DH and CLS interchangeably, <name>Da</name> is explicitly discussing Computational
                Literary Studies: <quote rend="inline">Digital humanities … is not the object of my [her] critique</quote> <ptr target="#da2019"/>.
                Does <name>Fish</name>’s slip from CLS to DH throughout his numerous critiques indicate
                that his lack of understanding extends beyond ‘the empirical’? While the
                distinctions between the two are unclear and also shifting (as <name>Katherine Bode</name> points
                out in her response to <name>Da</name>’s article), the terms cannot be used interchangeably as
                <name>Fish</name> does. <note> Generally speaking, CLS can be understood as a textual subset of
                DH. The authors of <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title> argue that <quote rend="inline">Digital
                Humanities projects can be described by sketching their structure at several
                levels</quote> <ptr target="#burdick_etal2012"/> including, but not limited to: design,
                computation, processing, digitization, classification, description, metadata,
                organization, navigation, curation, analysis, editing, modeling, prototyping.
                See also <title rend="italic">Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader</title> for a
                number of definitions. <name>Katherine Bode</name> suggests that <quote rend="inline"><name>Da</name>’s idiosyncratic
                definition of CLS is partly a product of problematic divisions within digital
                literary study</quote> but also insists that <name>Da</name>’s definition <quote rend="inline">omits what I’d call
                digital literary scholarship: philological, curatorial, and media archaeological
                approaches to digital collections and data</quote><ptr target="#bode2019"/>.</note> Is this just a
                careless mistake or does <name>Fish</name>’s slip — or is it a move — from CLS to DH indicate his
                desire to broaden <name>Da</name>’s case against a narrow subset of CLS to a critique against the
                larger project of DH? Given the pattern of repetition in <name>Fish</name>’s work, one might ask
                whether this most recent iteration is an original argument aimed specifically at DH
                or merely a recycling of his past critiques of stylistics refashioned to suit his
                new target? Indeed, to what degree does the existence of a throughline in his
                arguments indicate that Fish is actively transposing his criticism of stylistics
                onto the digital humanities in order to draw a false equivalency between the two? </p>
            
                <p>As I hope to show, these are not idle questions. Critics of DH cloak traditional
                articulations of humanities scholarship within <emph>methodological</emph>
                criticisms of DH. Their attack on computational modes of analysis depends upon
                the defense of a reified vision of <quote rend="inline">the humanities, as it has been traditionally
                understood</quote> <ptr target="#fish2012"/>. This traditional vision of the humanities, what <name>Jamie
                “Skye” Bianco</name> <ptr target="#bianco2012"/> terms “retro-humanism,” is anti-theoretical and ahistorical in
                that it imagines that conceptions of humanities work and scholarship are settled
                rather than the terrain of ongoing struggle. In contrast to <name>Said</name>’s assertion that
                <quote rend="inline">Criticism … is always situated; it is skeptical, secular, reflectively open to its
                own failings</quote> <ptr target="#said1975"/>, 
                
                <note> The work of <name>Sylvia Wynter</name> <ptr target="#wynter1987"/>, for instance,
                demonstrates the relationship between the <quote rend="inline">Overrepresentation </quote>of <quote rend="inline">Man</quote>as an
                epistemic category and methods of reading. She insists upon <quote rend="inline">‘Minority’ Literary
                Criticism</quote> <quote rend="inline">In order to introduce and integrate … several ‘new objects of
                knowledge’</quote> which <quote rend="inline">call equally for the construction of new conceptual tools and
                theoretical foundations, which this time go beyond <emph>not</emph>
                only the hegemonic paradigms of literary criticism but also beyond the grounding
                analogic of the episteme … of which our present practice of literary criticism …
                is an inter-connected component</quote><ptr target="#wynter1987"/>.</note>,
                
                these critics offer unexamined assertions of the <quote rend="inline">optimal utility</quote> <ptr target="#da2019"/> <note> <name>Da</name> asserts that 
                <quote rend="inline">It may be the case that computational textual analysis has a threshold of optimal utility</quote> 
                <ptr target="#da2019"/> with no reflection on whether “<quote rend="inline">utility</quote> is an appropriate measure for
                modes of reading or what kind of utility she is asserting. Similarly, <name>Tom
                Eyers</name>’s critique <quote rend="inline">laments the loss of humanist sensitivity</quote> <ptr target="#eyers2013"/> that comes
                with digital humanities should rankle any critic with a cursory understanding of
                postcolonial, Black, diasporic, feminist, or queer criticisms and theories, all
                of which have shown the serious limitations of conceiving of traditional forms
                of <quote rend="inline">humanist sensitivity</quote><ptr target="#eyers2013"/>. <name>Eyers</name> also misunderstands the function of exegesis
                throughout his article, arguing that DH scholarship fails <quote rend="inline">to consider the
                crucial conflict between the methodology employed and the wider, catholic form
                of interpretation argued for</quote> <ptr target="#eyers2013"/>. While simultaneously arguing that DH
                practitioners fall prey to the <quote rend="inline">alluring transparency afforded by the sharp
                technological lenses,</quote> he contradictorily also states that DH practitioners,
                <quote rend="inline">while acknowledging the fundamental discrepancy between the act of computation
                itself and the subsequent act of critical interpretation, nonetheless considers
                the gap easily and unproblematically surmountable</quote> <ptr target="#eyers2013"/>. <name>Eyers</name>’s argument is not only
                internally contradictory, it demonstrates a shocking lack of familiarity with
                the numerous DH critics who, as I will show, have spent a large portion of their
                careers theorizing <quote rend="inline">the gap</quote> between the digital and the humanities.</note> of
                humanities work or plea for a return to some prelapsarian <quote rend="inline">humanist sensitivity</quote>
                <ref target="#eyers2013"/>. Their expressions of retro-humanism circumvent the combined
                methodological-theoretical questions that are, in fact, one of DH’s most significant
                contributions to humanities scholarship. This retro-humanism, indicates that the
                attacks on DH constitute an idealized, unsituated criticism that articulate a narrow
                conception of the proper questions, methods and objects of analysis for the
                humanities. 
                
                <note> This is evident even in a critique like <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and
                Archives): A Political History of the Digital Humanities</title> <ptr target="#allington_etal2016"/>
                in which the authors draw a stark division between scholarship and
                denigrated service work (which, as <name>Lauren Klein</name> notes, are <quote rend="inline">performed
                disproportionally by women and people of color</quote> <ptr target="#klein2019"/> while offering a
                singular historical genesis of DH via the University of Virginia. They also
                strangely dismiss <name>Johanna Drucker</name> as <quote rend="inline">an eclectic scholar and artist with an
                idiosyncratic relationship to the humanities</quote> <ptr target="#allington_etal2016"/>.</note>
               
                Yet, in doing so, they inadvertently raise the more important questions of what it
                is we do when we read, what we mean by the ‘empirical’ and ‘theoretical’ levels of
                interpretation, and, more generally, what we mean by humanistic inquiry. <name>Fish</name>
                stumbles into this realization when he worries that the <quote rend="inline">digital humanities
                completely change our understanding of what a humanities goal (and work in the
                humanities) might be</quote> <ptr target="#fish2012b"/>. Where most DH scholars would respond to <name>Fish</name>’s worry
                with a celebratory, ‘Yes!’, <name>Fish</name>, <name>Da</name>, <name>Eyers</name> and others instead set themselves the
                task of defending a largely unexamined notion of retro-humanism. As such, his
                ongoing attack on DH constitutes perhaps the clearest instance of this desire to
                redefine the humanities according to this retro model and therefore merits sustained
                attention. </p>
            
                <p>One method of assessing the true target of <name>Fish</name>’s critique is via the computational
                literary methods that he and Da attack. A quick analysis of his <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title> reveals
                that it is 630 words long with no paragraph breaks. <name>Fish</name> spends 280 words, 44% of
                the reply, asserting his own lack of expertise in the field and his position that
                this lack of expertise doesn’t impede his assessment. Another 84 words comprise
                quotes from <name>Da</name>’s article, thus leaving a mere 266 words, or 39% of the piece, for
                <name>Fish</name>’s actual argument.</p>
            
               <p>While this is clearly a banal and overly simplistic example, the use of basic
                calculations to determine that a mere 40% of the <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title> actually asserts an
                argument tells us something about Fish’s most recent intervention. Our quick
                statistical analysis leads us to a number of research questions relevant to <name>Fish</name>’s
                argument: does this piece mark a decline or increase in the amount of actual
                original argumentation compared to his previous pieces? Do the numbers suggest that
                <name>Fish</name> is running out of things to say, or is he happy to just bolster <name>Da</name>’s critique? </p>
            
                <p>In order to develop this CLS approach to <name>Fish</name>’s argument, we might follow <name>Fish</name>’s
                gloss on his own critical methodology: <quote rend="inline">first the interpretive hypothesis and then
                the formal pattern, which attains the status of noticeability only because an
                interpretation already in place is picking it out</quote> <ptr target="#fish2019"/>. We might therefore go to
                a dataset of Fish’s arguments <quote rend="inline">armed with a hypothesis</quote><ptr target="#fish2019"/> about the
                development, or lack thereof, of <name>Fish</name>’s understanding and critique of digital
                humanities. By measuring the quantity of self-citation in his arguments (defined as
                the number of words he quotes from his own work) along with the quantity of quotes
                from others one could calculate the rate of change of <name>Fish</name>’s (un)originality. </p>
            
              <p>Yet, pursuing such a line of interpretation first requires distinguishing between
                argument, context, and citation in a far more systematic fashion. Can one always
                identify a given sentence as distinctly a citation or part of an original argument?
                How might we justify such a taxonomy? How do we formalize the process by which we
                move from <quote rend="inline">the interpretive hypothesis</quote> to <quote rend="inline">the formal pattern</quote> and, finally, to
                <quote rend="inline">the status of noticeability? </quote>Indeed, doesn’t <name>Fish</name>’s citation of <name>Da</name> and his own
                self-citation constitute a component of his argument, and shouldn’t it therefore
                should be counted within our measure of his original argumentation? </p>
            
                <p>The results of such an analysis might not be wholly surprising and would likely be
                guilty of the charge <name>Da</name> lays at CLS: <quote rend="inline">what is robust is obvious … and what is not
                obvious is not robust</quote> <ptr target="#fish2019"/>. Yet what <emph>is</emph> interesting about
                this hypothetical analysis is that it demonstrates how, even in such an apparently
                simplistic numerical analysis of a small number of texts, decisions are required
                that formally structure input and method, thereby requiring a precise definition of
                terms and a complex theorizing of the relationship between data and interpretation
                at the outset of such a project. Questions of method mutate into questions of the
                theoretical, exegetical, and heuristic bases of the project. To map the percentage
                of argument, repetition, and citation requires that we establish meaningful
                linguistic and computational categories for these terms. Questions we would have to
                ask might include: What are the histories of these terms and how do we account for
                changing definitions in our computational analysis? Can we clearly distinguish
                between <name>Fish</name>’s shifting targets of stylistics, DH, and CLS? How do particular terms
                or phrases within the Fish corpus signal that he is arguing, quoting, or
                paraphrasing and, as our analysis progresses and we are inevitably confronted by
                text that exceeds any of our definitions, how do we theorize iteratively,
                restructuring our terms and computational analysis in ways that better reflect the
                texts we encounter?</p>
           
                <p>This iterative grappling with methodological questions is the key dimension of CLS
                and DH work that <name>Da</name> and <name>Fish</name> overlook: DH scholarship requires a self-reflexive
                attention to methodology and theory that both refines theoretical conceptions of the
                relationship between the digital and the humanities while also reframing humanities
                inquiry more generally. As <name>Alan Liu</name> (2013) argues, <quote rend="inline">digital humanities method …
                consists in repeatedly coadjusting human concepts and machine technologies until …
                the two stabilize each other in temporary postures of truth that neither by itself
                could sustain</quote> <ptr target="#liu2013"/>. Indeed, counter to <name>Tom Eyers</name>’s (2013) argument that DH scholars
                fail <quote rend="inline">to consider the crucial conflict between the methodology employed and the
                wider, catholic form of interpretation argued for,</quote> <ptr target="#eyers2013"/> DH scholarship is replete with
                critics who make the engagement with that so-called conflict a guiding
                methodological concern. <name>Jim Egan</name>, for instance, explains, </p>
            
                <p><quote rend="inline">DH appeals to me for precisely the same reason as theory … DH and theory each ask
                those interested in the humanities to ask themselves why we do what we do the way we
                do it. What do we learn when we close-read a literary text? What assumptions about
                our goals, aims, and values are embedded within the methods of close-reading? What
                relationship does history bear to literature — what, after all, is the difference
                between the categories of history and literature, if any, and what ends do these
                distinctions serve? Indeed, why do we have literature departments at all?</quote> <ptr target="#egan2016"/>.</p>
            
                <p>The widening scope of questions that <name>Egan</name> traces is familiar to DH scholars who find
                that their digital projects lead them towards complex questions concerning the
                broader implications of their work. <name>Rosanne G. Potter</name>, <emph>writing in
                1988</emph>, describes the paradigmatic problem as <title rend="quotes">Literary Criticism and
                Literary Computing: The Difficulties of a Synthesis.</title> She concludes that we need
                <quote rend="inline">moderation in all things, computational and critical</quote> <ptr target="#potter1988"/> and that the key to
                digital humanities work is <quote rend="inline">Knowing when to go to quantitative methodologies and
                when to walk away from them</quote> <ptr target="#potter1988"/>. <name>Potter</name>’s point is that the synthesis remains
                difficult, if not impossible, but that wrestling with that difficulty remains
                worthwhile.</p>
            
                <p>This productive conflict between humanistic understanding and quantitative
                measurement informs <name>Johanna Drucker</name>’s (2011) argument that <quote rend="inline">we
                reconceive of all data as capta,</quote> particularly as <quote rend="inline">capta is ‘taken’
                    actively while data is assumed to be a ‘given’</quote> <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>. <name>Drucker</name>’s (2011) insistence on the
                taken, textual quality of capta <quote rend="inline">acknowledges the situated, partial, and
                constitutive character of knowledge production, the recognition that knowledge is
                constructed, taken, and not simply given as a natural representation of preexisting
                fact</quote> <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>.<note> She writes that “humanistic inquiry” of digital and visual modes of
                representation <quote rend="inline">requires first and foremost that we reconceive all data as
                capta. Differences in the etymological roots of the terms data and capta make
                the distinction between constructivist and realist approaches clear. Capta is
                ‘taken’ actively while data is assumed to be a ‘given’ able to be recorded and
                observed. From this distinction, a world of differences arises</quote> <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>.</note> For <name>Liu</name>
                (2013), the “meaning problem” of digital humanities arises because <quote rend="inline">It is not clear
                epistemologically, cognitively, or socially how human beings can take a signal
                discovered by a machine and develop an interpretation leading to a humanly
                understandable concept</quote> <ptr target="#liu2013" loc="414"/>. For scholars such as <name>Drucker</name>, <name>Liu</name>, <name>Andrew Piper</name>,
                <name>Tanya Clement</name>, and <name>Susan Brown</name>, working in the conflict or gaps between the
                computational and the literary, between signal and interpretation, enables new
                research questions and forms of collaboration while also foregrounding
                methodological questions that often remain implicit or unremarked upon within
                traditional humanities scholarship. </p>
            
                <p>Where <name>Fish</name> is content to assume that his readers will inherently understand terms
                like “garden variety literary intuition,” agree on what constitutes “the status of
                noticeability” or consent to his definition of “intentional,”
                
                <note> For <name>Fish</name>, intentionality is a key aspect of literary interpretation insofar as an observed
                textual pattern must correlate with author intentionality in order for a reading
                to be coherent. Yet he relies on a colloquial, implicit understanding of intent
                that forecloses certain readings. <name>Said</name> (1975), for instance, conceives of intent
                as <quote rend="inline">the link between the idiosyncratic view and the communal concern</quote> and as a
                <quote rend="inline">notion that includes everything that later develops out of it, no matter how
                eccentric the development or inconsistent the result</quote> <ptr target="#said1975"/>.</note>
                
                DH and CLS scholars must define their computational and humanities terms far more carefully
                both as they are represented in software models and employed as part of an argument.
                These definitions require precision not only due to the intense scrutiny that CLS
                and DH work is under but also because of the implicit difficulty of thinking through
                the relation between the literary and the computational. <name>Franco Moretti</name> (2013)
                describes this as “operationalizing,” the process wherein concepts of textual
                interpretation are <emph>operationalized</emph> in software: <quote rend="inline">building a
                bridge from concepts to measurement, and then to the world … from the concepts of
                literary theory, through some form of quantification, to literary texts</quote> <ptr target="#moretti2013"/>. <name>Piper</name>, in
                his (2019) articulation of the “theory gap” and “self-reflexive gap” of cultural
                analytics, writes that literary <quote rend="inline">Computation forces us to rethink our current
                disciplinary practices in the humanities from the ground up. What counts as
                evidence? What is the relationship between theory and practice? How do we account
                for the technological mediations of our critique?</quote> <ptr target="#piper2019"/>.</p>
            
                <p>For <name>Clement</name> (2019), the situating of <quote rend="inline">digital humanities within a humanist
                epistemological framework must also entail an explicit articulation of our
                methodological perspectives, or how our techniques are tied to theory</quote><ptr target="#clement2019"/>. I would go a
                step further to say (drawing on <name>Alan Galey</name> and <name>Stan Ruecker</name>’s (2010) examination of
                “How a prototype argues”) that our techniques <emph>are </emph>theory.
                <name>Clement</name> explains the benefits of this methodological articulation, writing that it
                “gives us an opportunity to explain why we do what we do, which in turn allows us to
                argue for the specific contributions of our findings to ourselves, to other
                humanists, to those possible collaborators in other disciplines who rely on
                methodology as a signpost, and to the world.” To theorize the relationship between
                the digital and the textual, <name>Clement</name> adapts <name>Marjorie Perloff</name>’s (2004) notion of
                “differential reading” as the dialogical movement between close and distant
                reading.<note> Clement (2019) interprets four central aspects of Perloff’s
                differential reading: <quote rend="inline">As rhetoric or practical criticism … As philosophy … As
                art of a unique aesthetic construct … [and] As cultural production</quote><ptr target="#clement2019"/>.</note>
                Notably, where <name>Perloff</name>’s notion of differential reading remains largely implicit
                throughout her argument in <emph>Differentials</emph> (2004), <name>Clement</name>’s
                adaptation of the concept is more fully developed. Where <name>Perloff</name>, like <name>Fish</name>, is
                content to let her concepts unfold as part of her poetic interpretation, thus
                relegating method to the background of the interpretive act, <name>Clement</name>’s attempt to
                situate the digital in relation to the humanities, by operationalizing differential
                reading, requires a more explicit methodological framework.</p>
            
                <p>It is telling that the struggle with methodological questions has become such a
                prominent aspect of DH scholarship, particularly as practitioners are required to
                develop novel methods for transposing humanities questions into computational
                spaces. <name>Brown</name> (2011) describes this, perhaps paradigmatic, DH question as the ‘gap’
                between the digital and the humanities: </p>
            
                <p><quote rend="inline">Working at the gap between humanities research questions and digital humanities
                development allows digital tools and research results to emerge from a dialectical
                relationship, allowing the research process to change in concert with the production
                of new modes of engaging in research. Scholars must make explicit the priorities and
                categories that inform their work</quote><ptr target="#brown2011"/>.</p>
           
                <p><name>Brown</name>’s articulation of the methodological gap is borne out of her extensive
                experience theorizing, developing, adjusting, and revising major digital humanities
                projects including the Orlando Project, the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory,
                and the Linked Infrastructure for Networked Cultural Scholarship Program. While the
                terms of <name>Brown</name>’s, <name>Clement</name>’s and <name>Piper</name>’s methods for working in the gap or reading
                differentially might seem abstract, that is partially the point: their method
                emerges from the challenge of particular projects, not predetermined by the
                expectations of computational or humanities modes of analysis. Indeed, as <name>Roopika
                Risam</name> (2020) argues, <quote rend="inline">The relationship between theory and praxis is integral to the
                digital humanities</quote><ptr target="#risam2020"/> and critical DH takes up the challenge of theorizing that
                relationship as a core dimension of its practice.</p>
            
                <p><name>Fish</name>’s, <name>Da</name>’s, and <name>Eyers</name>’s critiques of DH and CLS fail to account for the
                theoretically and methodologically productive challenges of working in the gap. For
                Fish and Da the space of the gap is not a space of productive possibility but one of
                incommensurability and lack. <name>Fish</name> (2019) is clear in his condemnation: <quote rend="inline">CLS or
                Digital Humanities is a project dedicated to irresponsibility masked by diagrams and
                massive data mining</quote><ptr target="#fish2019"/>.<note> Ironically, while <name>Fish</name> mischaracterizes the field,
                treating a small subset of DH work as representative of the whole enterprise, he
                finds himself, here, in agreement with a number of DH scholars. <name>Drucker</name> (2011),
                for instance, has demonstrated the misuse of diagrams and graphical display in
                the visualization of data and calls for <quote rend="inline">a new approach that uses humanities
                principles to constitute capta and display</quote><ptr target="#drucker2011"/> as well for <quote rend="inline">imaginative action and
                intellectual engagement with the challenge of rethinking digital tools for
                visualization on the basic principles of the humanities</quote><ptr target="#drucker2011"/>. <quote rend="inline">Niels Kerssens</quote> (2019)
                has stressed the constructedness of data, arguing that <quote rend="inline">data has no ground of
                existence independent of the human imagination of data</quote><ptr target="#kerssens2019"/>.</note> The digital and
                the humanities are, in <name>Fish</name>’s view, only made to appear compatible through a
                rhetorical sleight of hand that employs indecipherable diagrams, illegible charts,
                and anti-theoretical data mining. While more careful in her final condemnation, <name>Da</name>
                (2019) essentially agrees, concluding her article with the suggestion that because
                the gap has not been fully theorized or the results of dialectically moving between
                the digital and the humanities are not fully developed, the entire CLS project is
                doomed to fail. She writes: </p>
           
                <p><quote rend="inline">The basic criteria should always be to not confuse what happens mechanically with
                insight, to not needlessly use statistical tools for far simpler operations, to
                present inferences that are both statistically sound and argumentatively meaningful,
                and to make sure that functional operations would not be far faster and more
                accurate if someone just read the texts. It may be the case that computational
                textual analysis has a threshold of optimal utility, and literature — in particular,
                reading literature well — is that cut-off point</quote><ptr target="#da2019"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Da</name>’s argument presumes that notions of <quote rend="inline">statistically sound and argumentatively
                meaningful</quote><ptr target="#da2019b"/> scholarship are clear, unchanging over time, and that CLS does not, and
                will not, contribute to such work. Yet, as her acknowledgment of the numerous errors
                in her original article (2019b) demonstrate, these concepts were unclear to her at
                the time of her writing and, indeed, are not settled facts. Statisticians disagree
                over what counts as “statistically sound”<note> See, <name>Wasserstein</name> and <name>Lazar</name> (2016)
                and, <name>Diettrich</name> and <name>Kong</name> (1995).</note> just as literary scholars debate what
                constitutes an “argumentatively meaningful” observation. </p>
            
                <p>Yet these outright terminological and argumentative errors are minor compared to the
                bigger problems in both <name>Fish</name>’s and <name>Da</name>’s critiques, namely the manner in which their
                attacks on DH attempt to conceal the gap of their own interpretive practices.
                Invoking the language of “optimal utility” or the “functional operation” of
                particular critical frameworks and contrasting DH with an unexamined notion of
                “reading literature well” sutures the productive, conflictual space of the gap in
                which criticism reflects on its own activity. This is evident in <name>Fish</name>’s (2019)
                paraphrase of <name>Da</name>’s argument at the end of his <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title>: <quote rend="inline">The antidote to the
                whole puffed-up thing is nicely identified by Professor <name>Da</name> in her final paragraph:
               ‘just read the texts’</quote><ptr target="#fish2019"/>.</p>
           
                <p>In contrast with careful theorizing, wrestling with difficult “operationalizing”
                questions, interpreting, and “minding the gap” between the computational and the
                humanities, <name>Fish</name> and <name>Da</name> attempt to close the gap of their own critical practice and
                smuggle in their own retro-humanist methodology in their call to “just read the
                texts.” This is not an insignificant move, particularly as it asserts that one can,
                in fact, “just read” or, in Da’s naive formulation, read “literature well.” The
                methodological laziness of this final section of Da’s piece would be surprising
                given the intense and unforgiving scrutiny to which she subjects CLS methods until
                one recognizes that this is not mere sloppiness but a strategic move that asserts
                the vision of reading and criticism that both she and Fish contrast with DH. </p>
            
                <p>To debunk such simplified, unexamined notions of interpretation, one critic has
                lucidly demonstrated how notions of “just reading” circumvents criticism to conceal
                its inner logic, particularly as it constructs the very objects it purports to
                describe: </p>
           
                <p>Strictly speaking, getting “back-to-the-text” is not a move one can perform, because
                the text one gets back to will be the text demanded by some other interpretation and
                that interpretation will be presiding over its production. This is not to say,
                however, that the “back-to-the-text” move is ineffectual. The fact that it is not
                something one can do in no way diminishes the effectiveness of claiming to do it. As
                a rhetorical ploy, the announcement that one is returning to the text will be
                powerful so long as the assumption that criticism is secondary to the text and must
                not be allowed to overwhelm it remains unchallenged <ptr target="#fish1982"/>.</p>
           
                <p>When the <name>Fish</name> of 1982 identifies the imperative to “just read the text” as a
                “rhetorical ploy,” he warns us against the Fish of 2019 whose imperative to “just
                read” is precisely such a rhetorical move aimed at circumventing the critical
                possibilities of digital humanities as well as the “worldliness” (Said) of criticism
                more generally. <title rend="quotes">Throughout Is There A Text in This Class?</title>
                (1982) Fish challenges unexamined notions of “just reading” by investigating whether
                the reader, the text, or the interpretive community is the “source of meaning.” He
                engages in a sustained attack on New Criticism by attending to the dialogical
                relationship that emerges out of the gap between methodology and textual meaning. We
                cannot just read the text, <name>Fish</name> argues, because we constitute the text through our
                acts of reading and our responses to the existing critical paradigms by which we
                come to experience and know the text. In this sense, <name>Fish</name> demonstrates the manner in
                which criticism occurs temporally: the text is an organizing centre around which
                “communities of readers” respond to other communities and form a range of
                interpretations over time. <note> <name>Fish</name>’s (1982) argument is mirrored in the form of
                his collection, as he reveals how his criticism is part of a temporal unfolding
                that is only possible as a response to <name>Wimsatt</name> and <name>Beardsley</name>. He writes, <quote rend="inline">The
                fact that I was making such an argument was a direct consequence of the fact
                that it had already been made, and the position I proceeded to take was dictated
                by the position that had already been taken … To the degree that this argument
                was influential … it constrained in advance the form any counterargument might
                take</quote><ptr target="#fish1982"/>.</note>
            </p>
            
                <p>In a kind of <emph>Looper</emph>-esqe turn, the temporal unfolding of
                Fish’s criticism has resulted in his becoming the very New Critic whose naive
                assertion of “just reading” he once sought to expose. Yet this New(er) Criticism 2.0
                that claims to ‘just read the texts’ retains the same problems as Wimsatt and
                Beardsley’s original vision. As <name>Jonathan Culler</name> (1981) explains, <quote rend="inline">New Criticism’s
                dream of a self-contained encounter between innocent reader and autonomous text is a
                bizarre fiction. To read is always to read in relation to other texts, in relation
                to the codes that are the products of these texts and go to make up a culture</quote><ptr target="#culler1981"/>. New
                Criticism purports to close the gap of interpretation, imagining that the critic has
                unmediated access to the text. In place of a criticism that assesses the grounds of
                its own articulation and theorizes the terms of its own practice, Fish and Da follow
                their New Critical forebears by attempting to delimit the act of criticism to the
                act of reading. For <name>Culler</name>, however the problem is worse than merely <emph
                >how </emph>critics read: <quote rend="inline">the most important and insidious legacy of
                the New Criticism is the widespread and unquestioning acceptance of the notion that
                the critic’s job is to interpret literary works</quote><ptr target="#culler1981" loc="5"/>. The call to ‘just read’ is
                misleading because it delimits critical reflection on the task of criticism itself
                by refusing to acknowledge the worldliness of the text and critic. </p>
            
                <p>Again, <name>Fish</name> (1982) is instructive in his elucidations of the inescapable, and
                necessary, dimensions of criticism to reflect on its own task, particularly as
                criticism can debunk innocent notions of “reading literature well”: </p>
           
                <p><quote rend="inline">It is often assumed that literary theory presents a set of problems whose shape
                remains unchanging and in relation to which our critical procedures are found to be
                more or less adequate; that is, the field of inquiry stands always ready to be
                interrogated by questions it itself constrains. It seems to me, however, that the
                relationship is exactly the reverse: the field of inquiry is <emph>constituted</emph> 
                by the questions we are able to ask because the entities that
                populate it come into being as the presuppositions — they are discourse-specific
                entities — of those questions</quote><ptr target="#fish1982"/>.</p>
            
                <p>The field of inquiry, what we might mean by “reading literature well,” is not
                predetermined by a series of hallowed, Arcadian principles of criticism but, rather,
                is <emph>constituted </emph>by the questions we are able to ask.” <name>Fish</name> is
                thus in agreement with <name>Brown</name> in her (2011) assertion that <quote rend="inline">Working at the gap
                between humanities research questions and digital humanities development allows
                digital tools and research results to emerge from a dialectical relationship,
                allowing the research process to change in concert with the production of new modes
                of engaging in research</quote><ptr target="#brown2011" loc="218"/>. <name>Fish</name>’s observation remains true today: if we
                conceive of CLS or DH scholarship as generating a set of questions that cannot be
                asked by traditional methods of literary scholarship then we see the manner in which
                this work reconstitutes the field in new ways, requiring critics to iteratively
                theorize the terms and methods of their work.
               
                <note> How, then, do <name>Da</name> and <name>Fish</name>
                conceive of “reading well” or “just reading” the texts? To answer such a
                question, we might turn again to CLS in an effort to understand what <name>Da</name> (2019)
                means by “just reading.” <name>Da</name> uses the word “just” twenty-four times throughout
                her article, most of which are to comment on the relative insignificance of an
                aspect of CLS scholarship. These uses of the term are characterized by
                statements such as: <quote rend="inline">CLS claims that literary critics will no longer make
                unsupported claims about whole periods of literary history using just a few
                texts”“corpus ‘entropy,’ ... is just another way of saying ‘two words that
                appear together’”“‘narrative events’ are just 3-gram length subject+verb+object
                sequences”“all the things that appear in CLS — network analysis, digital
                mapping, linear and nonlinear regressions, topic modeling, topology, entropy —
                are just fancier ways of talking about word frequency changes</quote><ptr target="#da2019"/>. Throughout her
                article, <name>Da</name> uses “just” liberally and rhetorically in order to smooth over false
                equivalencies (topic modeling is not a fancier way of “talking about word
                frequency changes”) and to undermine or misrepresent the claims of CLS scholars
                (<name>Algee-Hewitt</name>’s arguments about “corpus entropy” are not just about “two words
                that appear together). Her use of the term “just” is, as <name>Fish</name> warns, a
                “rhetorical ploy” designed to minimize the complexity of CLS arguments in order
                to dismiss them. In these instances, she uses “just” to assert critical
                expertise that she may not, in fact, possess, while also to conceal the
                complexity of a number of CLS projects with false simplicity. <name>Da</name> also uses “just”
                to signify a rational, no-nonsense approach to literary scholarship that
                contrasts effectively with what she argues is CLS’s overwrought method of sound
                and fury. She writes: <quote rend="inline">If the authors wanted to nonarbitrarily study the change
                in topics covered in journal articles over time, they could have just saved time
                by looking at journal abstracts</quote><ptr target="#da2019"/>. <quote rend="inline">Couldn’t someone trained in poetry just find,
                read, and classify [all the short poems that exist in the world]?</quote><ptr target="#da2019"/> <quote rend="inline">Functional
                operations would not be far faster and more accurate if someone just read the
                texts</quote><ptr target="da2019"/>. Again, <name>Da</name>’s use of “just” represents a complex CLS procedure (topic
                modeling the entirety of a corpus of literary journals or training an algorithm
                to identify a poem as a haiku) as an overly-complex version of a far more
                straightforward form of interpretation (‘just’ read every abstract of thousands
                of articles in journals, ‘just’ read every short poem in the world). </note>
                
                Indeed, this is what <name>Fish</name> and <name>Da</name> primarily miss in their methodological critique of
                DH and CLS: these methods enable not “just” new forms of asking the same questions
                but, expand the “field of inquiry” of the humanities by the “questions we are able
                to ask” using these methods. </p>
           
                <p>In what follows, I will turn from the theoretical to the practical, and discuss two
                projects that raise new questions and address a number of <name>Fish</name>’s and <name>Da</name>’s concerns,
                including the claims that DH results are typically obvious, non-robust, or always
                over-promised and underdeveloped. These examples are representative of a critical
                digital humanities that expand the field of humanities inquiry into digital spaces
                while also reflecting critically on the exclusion or silencing of particular voices
                within traditional conceptions of the humanities. Furthermore, these projects
                demonstrate that DH work is not singularly playful or hypothesis-generating but can
                also answer meaningful research questions, generate plausible new interpretations of
                texts, and productively situate texts within broader social discourses. Yet, equally
                important, these cases demonstrate that it through a critical dialogue between the
                digital humanities and its analogue counterpart that these projects did not merely
                refine their own method but, in grappling with the relation between the digital and
                the humanities, also developed a richer sense of humanistic inquiry more generally.
                These interpretations would have been impossible by “just reading the texts” and
                instead work in the gap between the digital and the humanities in order to force the
                humanities to contend with its own silences and structural exclusions. </p>
            
                <p>The first example comes from the University of British Columbia in the late 1960s
                when an upstart graduate student, <name>Sandra Djwa</name>, was completing her doctoral
                dissertation. The subject of <name>Djwa</name>’s thesis, a study of the continuity of poetic
                style in Canadian poetry from its earliest moments to its manifestation in the
                1960s, was viewed as uninteresting and marginal by her department, where Canadian
                poetry was regarded as a relatively minor and uninteresting area of study.
                
                <note> As she describes it in our recent correspondence: <quote rend="inline">My colleagues saw no use
                whatever for computer concordances and would not give me any academic credit for
                the work I had done in this area.</quote></note>
                    
                <name>Djwa</name> would go on to be a major figure in Canadian literature in the latter half of the twentieth century.</p>
            
                <p><name>Djwa</name> set herself the enormous task of disagreeing with a number of <name>Northrop Frye</name>’s
                arguments in his infamous conclusion to <name>Carl Klinck</name>’s <title rend="italic">Literary History of Canada</title>
                (1965). <name>Djwa</name> was writing in the shadow of the <title rend="italic">Literary History</title>, an ur-text of
                Canadian literature that attempted to marshall together scattered pockets of
                Canadian literary scholarship. <name>Frye</name>’s “Conclusion” was the final statement of the
                <title rend="italic">Literary History</title>, a closing gesture that organized a variegated and uneven jumble of
                texts and histories into a cohesive articulation of national literature via a
                thematic mode of criticism. In the <title rend="italic">Literary History</title> and elsewhere, <name>Frye</name> argues that
                Canadian literature evinces a “garrison mentality” wherein the Canadian writer
                imagines themselves fortified against indifferent, external forces. <name>Frye</name>’s
                “Conclusion” attempted to marshal together the diverse and uneven chapters in the
                <title rend="italic">Literary History</title> and to do he claims that Canadians struggle to survive in the face
                of the harsh elements. <name>Frye</name>’s work set the tone for Canadian Literature for years;
                one of <name>Djwa</name>’s central goals was to develop a method to disagree with <name>Frye</name>’s
                thesis.</p>
            
                <p>Making her project even more contentious, <name>Djwa</name> elected to use computational literary
                studies as a component of her research. While writing her dissertation, <name>Djwa</name>
                received a grant from the newly established UBC Computing Centre to use their IBM
                7044 mainframe computer to develop a “Computational Concordance” of Canadian poetry.
                This concordance took seven years to complete and accompanied her dissertation as a
                thematic guide for fourteen Canadian poets, ranging from <name>Isabella Valancy Crawford</name>
                to <name>Irving Layton</name>. As she explains in her article, <title rend="quotes">Canadian Poetry and the Computer</title>
                (1970): </p>
            
                <p><quote rend="inline">The procedure followed was the same in all cases. Each poet’s published books ...
                were key-punched on computer cards at the rate of one typographical line per
                computer card. The ... cards containing the poet’s canon were then fed into an IBM
                7044 computer for printout. Following [manual] proofreading and necessary
                corrections, the computer drew up a word frequency count. This is an alphabetical
                index listing every word that a poet uses and indicating its frequency of
                appearance. On the basis of the critic’s understanding of a poet’s work, and taking
                into consideration both the frequency of occurrence of particular words and the
                apparent collocations or associations of clusters of words, a selected list of words
                under the heading of thematic categories was then drawn up by hand</quote><ptr target="#crawford1970"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Djwa</name> happily notes, in the handout for her presentation at <title rend="quotes">The Learned Societies,
                 ACCUTE, Winnipeg, June 1970,</title> (1970) that this “convenient” process produced
                approximately 300,000 computer cards which were then used to create a “selective,
                associative thesaurus” of poetic terms. <name>Djwa</name> employs <name>Brown</name>’s method of “minding the
                gap” between the digital and the humanities: reading and proofreading punch cards in
                order to compare the “word frequency count” against “the critic’s understanding of a
                poet’s work” and the “apparent collocations or associations of clusters of words.”
                From this, <name>Djwa</name> develops a <quote rend="inline">selected list of words under the heading of thematic
                categories </quote><ptr target="#djwa1970"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Djwa</name>’s work is not merely notable for its historical significance as an early,
                largely unknown DH project by a woman, but also for the manner in which her turn to
                digital methods required that she develop new paradigms for engaging in humanities
                research. She is asking questions that are only partially formed while
                simultaneously inventing, on the go, a method for working through them. She wrestled
                with familiar questions in DH: which words to exclude (stopwords), how to contend
                with words that are very similar but with different suffixes (stemming), how to
                treat multiple editions of a poem, and how to “read” this computational concordance
                alongside her more traditional dissertation. Furthermore, she had to define, far
                more accurately than <name>Frye</name>, what she meant by “unity” in a poetic tradition,
                thematicism, and cluster.</p>
            
                <p><name>Djwa</name> and <name>Frye</name> were, in many respects, beginning from the same research question: ‘Is
                there a thematic or formal continuity between Canadian writers that enables critics
                to identify a distinct Canadian literature?’ <name>Djwa</name> responded to <name>Frye</name>’s inductive
                approach with her own deductive, digital method that enriches our understandings of
                theme, image, and national literature. It is in the exchange between these two
                visions of humanistic inquiry that Djwa developed her analysis.</p>
            
                <p>The history of <name>Djwa</name>'s work also reveals the manner in which marginalized and emerging
                voices use new, digital methods to challenge convention, transform scholarly
                debates, and pose new questions. Indeed, the influence of her concordance became
                particularly complex when poet <name>P.K. Page</name>, one of the subjects of <name>Djwa</name>’s study, wrote
                    to her requesting to know the word clusters and themes in her poetry. <name>Djwa</name> employed
                digital methods to challenge the authority of the male, established,
                central-Canadian dominance of <name>Klinck</name>, <name>Frye</name>, and others, and to reconstitute the
                field of inquiry by asking new questions enabled by her DH project.
                
                    <note> <name>Djwa</name> (1973) worries that critics might dismiss her entire project <quote rend="inline">as simply vague
                    transcendental aspiration, the Canadian backwash of Victorian romanticism</quote><ptr target="#djwa1973"/>. Yet,
                    she persists: <quote rend="inline">granted that the common terms of diction are also very probably
                    inherited, a more helpful approach might be the question of whether or not our
                    poets did something unique with their particular inheritance. Did they construct
                    a particular myth or cosmology from the common terms of romantic diction; and,
                    if so, was there any continuance of myth or diction?</quote><ptr target="#djwa1973"/>.<name>Djwa</name> shows that <name>Charles
                    G.D. Roberts</name> <quote rend="inline">consistently uses the word ‘dream’ and that it most commonly
                    collocates with ‘sleep,’ ‘vision,’ ‘spirit,’ and ‘mystic’” all in order to
                    demonstrate how “the ‘dream’ emerges primarily as a description of the poet’s
                    aspiration towards ‘the Spirit of Beauty’ beyond nature</quote><ptr target="#djwa1973"/>. She then demonstrates
                    how <quote rend="inline"><name>Archibald Lampman</name> adopts <name>Roberts</name>’ dream metaphor and with it much of his
                    poetic myth</quote>. After moving through a number of observations of the concordance
                    in dialogue with close readings of the poems, she concludes that <quote rend="inline">there was, in
                    fact, a very close relationship between the major poet of the 1880s, <name>Sir Charles
                    G. D. Roberts</name>, and the major poets of the 1920’s, <name>E.J. Pratt</name> - a bend in the
                    stream of Canadian poetry rather than the sharp break suggested by present
                    critical comment. Further, it is possible that <name>A.J.M. Smith</name>, <name>D.C. Scott</name>, <name>A.M.
                    Klein</name>, although busy carving out new provinces for poetry, were also fully aware
                    of the work done by their predecessors and contemporaries</quote><ptr target="#djwa1973"/>.</note> 
                
                Her digital work enables her to directly challenge <name>Frye</name>’s cruel north thesis: <quote rend="inline">the isolation of
                [the] cold north hypothesis is an over-simplification when discussing the
                development of Canadian poetry, as it represents a concept which does not, in fact,
                appear to emerge in the earliest poets</quote><ptr target="#djwa1964"/>. Her work thus employs digital
                methods to offer a new conception of national poetic continuity and to foreground
                authors who were otherwise marginalized from the national canon. </p>
            
                <p><name>Lauren F. Klein</name>’s (2020) <title rend="quotes">Dimensions of Scale: Invisible Labor, Editorial Work, and
                the Future of Quantitative Literary Studies</title> offers a compelling second example of
                the use of digital humanities methods to reassess modes of reading, labour, and
                humanities research. Klein’s project employs the distant reading method of topic
                modeling to read the corpora of a collection of abolitionist newspapers. Topic
                modeling is a statistical method of distant reading wherein a topic modeling
                algorithm attempts to iteratively group together related words, called topics,
                across a large corpus
                
                <note> For a more detailed discussion of topic modeling see
                <name>Blei</name> (2012), <name>Brett</name> (2012), <name>Underwood</name> (2012), <name>Barrett</name> (2016), 
                <name>Churchill</name> and <name>Singh</name>
                (2022). </note> 
                    
                in order to identify topics, that would be invisible to an
                individual reader. <name>Klein</name> writes, <quote rend="inline">Framed in this way, topic modeling becomes a
                meaningful analytical tool indeed: it not only enables a view from a distance but
                also helps bring to light certain invisible aspects of knowledge production</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>. <name>Klein</name>
                builds on the work of <name>Lisa Rhoady</name>, <name>Rachel Buurma</name>, and others who have used topic
                modeling to identify subtle trends in large corpora. </p>
            
                <p><name>Klein</name> begins with the observation that two female editors of her collection of
                abolitionist publications, <name>Mary Ann Shadd</name> and <name>Lydia Maria Child</name>, engaged in a great
                deal of invisible labour in their efforts to keep the publications afloat, fill the
                publications with material, and advocate on behalf of the abolitionist cause. She
                argues that </p>
            
                <p><quote rend="inline"><name>Shadd</name>’s editorial work exemplifies … invisible labor, a term that has come to
                encompass the various forms of labor that are literally invisible because they take
                place out of sight, or economically invisible because they take place away from the
                marketplace. … The project of infusing value and credit into invisible labor … is a
                feminist one because, among other reasons, the primary example of invisible labor is
                unpaid domestic work, which has historically been performed by women</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Klein</name>’s intuition is that topic modeling can provide a broad and unique view of her
                corpus that can unearth <name>Shadd</name>’s and <name>Child</name>’s invisible labour. She employs digital
                methods to <quote rend="inline">consider how a topic model of a set of abolitionist newspapers can be
                used to better understand <name>Child</name>’s strategy of editorial <emph
                >copia</emph>. … And … Shadd’s similarly invisible editorial work</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Klein</name> compares her topic model of the collection of abolitionist newspapers to a
                similar model of <title rend="italic">Frederick Douglass’ Paper</title> (<quote rend="inline">the title that
                Douglass would adopt when [Douglass’s] <title rend="italic">The North Star </title> merged
                with another abolitionist title</quote>)<ptr target="#klein2020"/> and shows how the papers edited by
                <name>Shadd</name> and <name>Child</name> were far more concerned with quotidian experience and reflections on
                nature, foreign affairs, and family life than <name>Douglass</name>’s paper. <name>Klein</name> demonstrates
                that <name>Child</name>’s and <name>Shadd</name>’s presence as editors employed depictions of family and daily
                life, including recipes, songs, and local news, in order to draw readers to the
                abolitionist cause. Furthermore, <name>Klein</name> argues, the topic models of the newspapers
                <quote rend="inline">crystallizes just how intent <name>Shadd</name> was on expanding her readers’ sense of the
                possibilities of black life</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/> by representing Black quotidian experience in her
                papers. More broadly, <name>Klein</name> argues that the breadth of topics identified in <name>Shadd</name>’s
                editorial work demonstrates how, in <name>Frances Smith Foster</name>’s (2005) terms, <quote rend="inline">people of
                African descent used their print culture to help reinvent themselves as African
                Americans and to construct African America</quote><ptr target="#foster2005"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Klein</name> uses her distant reading methods to inform her research into <name>Child</name>’s archives,
                specifically in relation to a letter in which <name>Child</name> explains suffering under a
                “flood” of labour and correspondence connected to her invisible editorial duties.
                <name>Klein</name> convincingly argues that, </p>
            
                <p><quote rend="inline">In <name>Child</name>’s letter is found, on the one hand, an additional justification for a
                quantitative approach to analyzing the <emph>Standard</emph>. … the letter
                provides evidence of a form of intellectual labor that cannot be precisely located
                by any literary research method. <name>Child</name>’s own arguments — the “three editorials” that
                she claims she would have written had she not been consumed by her editorial work —
                never made it out of her head. For this reason, we do not have the text of those
                editorials to analyze</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>.</p>
            
                <p><name>Klein</name> uses <name>Clement</name>’s differential reading to move between close analysis of <name>Child</name> and
                <name>Shadd</name>’s writing and distant analysis of their archives to foreground the invisible
                labour of these female abolitionists. Topic modelling is a “meaningful analytical
                tool” for Klein because it brings <quote rend="inline">to light certain invisible aspects of knowledge
                production</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>. <name>Klein</name>’s topic modeling of <name>Child</name>’s archives, for instance,
                demonstrates a “fairly event split between political topics” concerned with
                abolition and “and the ‘miscellaneous material’ <name>Child</name> deployed as a ruse” to draw an
                apolitical or uncommitted readership to the abolitionist cause. She is able to
                conclude, from these topics, that <name>Child</name> effectively blended her political agenda
                with the miscellany in order to further her abolitionist goals. It is as a result of
                her topic modeling work (alongside her archival research and reading of <name>Child</name>’s
                correspondence) that <name>Klein</name> is able to argue that acknowledge <quote rend="inline">the full range of
                labor — the various forms it entailed and the degrees of effort it involved — that
                Child contributed to the abolitionist cause</quote><ptr target="#klein2020"/>.</p>
            
                <p>To return to <name>Brown</name>’s formulation, both <name>Klein</name> and <name>Djwa</name>’s projects represent moments of
                minding the gap between the digital and the humanities, identifying the particular
                ways in which digital projects require a renewed consideration of humanities work.
                <name>Djwa</name>’s development of her computational concordances soon give rise to questions of
                what actually constitutes a national poetic tradition. <name>Klein</name>’s topic modeling
                reflects both on the meaning of a topic, attendant as it is to both the implicit and
                explicit content of the papers she analyzes, and the forms of unrecognized labour
                that Black women engage in as part of their projects of freedom making. Yet beyond
                these practical, methodological concerns, both examples employ the digital in order
                to challenge the received orthodoxy of their respective fields. Djwa’s thematic
                concordance of Canadian poets describes a counter-tradition that identifies a number
                of thematic clusters of Canadian poetry that challenge <name>Frye</name>’s cruel north thesis.
                <name>Klein</name>’s analysis demonstrates how digital methods can provide insight into Black
                women’s invisible work in their writing. </p>
           
                <p>Examples such as these are countless.
                
                <note> For recent examples, see <name>Roopika Risam</name>
                and <name>Kelly Baker Joseph</name>’s <title rend="quotes">The Digital Black Atlantic
                </title>(2021), particularly <name>Sayan Bhattacharyya</name>’s (2021) <title rend="quotes">Text Analysis for
                Thought in the Black Atlantic</title> and my own (2021) discussion of using distant
                reading methods to analyze <name>Austin Clarke</name>’s literary corpus. See also <name>Richard
                Jean So</name>’s <title rend="quotes">Redlining Culture: A Data History of Racial
                Inequality and Postwar Fiction</title> (2020) which employs DH to demonstrate
                the bias towards white authors in postwar American publishing. See also <name>Mark
                Algee-Hewitt</name>, <name>J.D. Porter</name>, and <name>Hannah Walser</name>’s (2020) <title rend="quotes">Representing Race and
                Ethnicity in American Fiction, 1789-1920</title> which uses digital methods to analyze
               racial discourse in 18,000 novels published between 1789 and 1920.</note>
               
                The Orlando Project and the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory are two projects
                that make women’s writing and feminist epistemologies the basis for digital
                humanities research. The Early Modern Map of London project brings together DH
                methods of textual analysis, GIS mapping, and natural language processing to
                identify heretofore-invisible networks of relationships in London. The Women’s
                Writers project employs TEI methods to understand the transatlantic reception,
                circulation, and readership of women’s writing. The Linked Infrastructure for
                Networked Cultural Scholarship (LINCS) project employs linked, open data and the
                semantic web to connect disparate and bespoke humanities project, working from the
                intuition that linked datasets will reveal new insights about their shared
                materials. </p>
            
                <p><name>Fish</name>’s and <name>Da</name>’s attacks on CLS and DH neglect the manner in which these digital
                methods challenge retro-humanism as well as the hegemony of particular voices within
                traditional conceptions of humanities work. By restricting their criticism to the
                textual analytics subset of DH, <name>Fish</name> and <name>Da</name> offer a narrow conception of the field
                and of its possibilities to interrogate power as a component of humanities work.
                Indeed, <name>Klein</name> (2020) identifies the manner in which the retro-humanist critique of
                DH excludes those who use digital tools to recover overlooked texts, compile new
                datasets, and preserve fragile archives” in order to challenge the hegemony of the
                “individualistic, masculinist mode of statistical criticism” and offer a competing
                vision of the humanities. Their critiques cannot account for the exciting and
                invigorating ways in which “the black digital humanities promotes a system of
                changes,” particularly as <quote rend="inline">a mechanism for deregulating the tendency of
                technological tools, when employed in the digital humanities, to deemphasize
                questions about humanity itself</quote><ptr target="#gallon2016"/>. Similarly, their retro-humanist
                vision excludes the manner in which <quote rend="inline">black digital practice is the interface by
                which black freedom struggles challenge reproduction of black death and
                commodification</quote><ptr target="#johnson2018"/>. Indeed, DH scholars <quote rend="inline">argue for positioning
                queerness as a central element of DH methodologies</quote><ptr target="#ruberg_etal2018"/>, for
                the way they insist that DH <quote rend="inline">investigations must incorporate race from the outset,
                understanding and theorizing its function as a ghost in the digital machine</quote><ptr target="#mcpherson2012"/>, 
                and for the manner in which DH work must be informed by <quote rend="inline">critical
                race and ethnic studies; feminist, gender, queer studies; postcolonial,
                transnational, diaspora; disability studies; DIY (Add your own!)</quote><ptr target="#risam2015"/>. In
                place of this worldly, critical DH, <name>Fish</name> and <name>Da</name> offer the naive conception of
                “reading literature well” as a subtle retro-humanism that falsely <quote rend="inline">represents <emph>
                a fundamental opposition in thinking</emph> between humanities
                theorists and deliberately anti-theoretical DH ‘builders’</quote><ptr target="#nowviskie2014"/>.</p>
            
                <p>Digital humanities work is not merely important because it brings humanities work to
                bear on the digital technologies, texts, and modes of being that have become
                increasingly important in our lives. It is also important because working in the
                space of the gap crucially requires that we re-envision what we mean by the
                humanities. Advocates of retro-humanism know full well that the humanities have
                always been a site of struggle and they conceal that struggle in their call to a
                return to past principles of “optimal utility,” “humanist sensitivity,” or “the task
                of interpretation as traditionally conceived.” At a time when the very value of the
                humanities is under siege, DH offers opportunities to transform narrow visions of
                the humanities’ ‘value’ into humanities-based interrogations of the <quote rend="inline">value of value</quote>
                <ptr target="#butler2014"/>. The challenge for digital humanities now is not <quote rend="inline">choose between the
                philosophical, cultural, and computational,</quote><ptr target="#bianco2012"/> or to demonstrate how DH
                accords with past visions of humanities work. Rather, our challenge is to respond to
               <name>Diana Brydon</name>’s (2011) call that “the humanities need a new humanism” and to dwell in
                the gap between the digital and the humanities in order to investigate humanism’s
                source code and write it anew. </p>
        </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="algeehewitt_etal2020" label="Algee-Hewitt et al 2020"> Algee-Hewitt, M. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes"> Representing race and
                    ethnicity in American fiction, 1789-1920</title>,<title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 5(2). 
                    Available at: <ref target="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/18509-representing-race-and-ethnicity-in-american-fiction-1789-1920">https://culturalanalytics.org/article/18509-representing-race-and-ethnicity-in-american-fiction-1789-1920 </ref> 
                    (Accessed 20 February 2024).  
      </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allington_etal2016" label="Allington et al. 2016">Allington, D. et al. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A Political History of Digital Humanities</title>,
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/">lhttps://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/</ref>
                    (Accessed 25 June 2019). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="augustineofhipposaint1940" label="Augustine, of Hippo, Saint 1940">Augustine, of Hippo, Saint (1940) <title rend="italic">The confessions of Saint Augustine</title>. New York: Peter Pauper Press.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barrett2016" label="Barrett 2016">Barrett, P. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Paraphrasing the oaraphrase or what I learned from reading every issue of Canadian Literature &amp; SCL / ELC</title>,<title>Canadian Literature</title>, 228-9, pp. 208-225. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barrett2021" label="Barrett 2021">Barrett, P. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Austin Clarke’s digital crossings</title>, in Roopika Risam and Kelly Baker Josephs (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Digital Black Atlantic</title>. 
                    Minneapolis: Minnesota Press, pp. 84-94. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bhattacharyya2021" label="Bhattacharyya 2021">Bhattacharyya, S. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Text analysis for thought in the Black Atlantic</title>, in Roopika 
                    Risam and Kelly Baker Josephs (eds.) <title rend="italic">The Digital Black Atlantic</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, pp. 77-83. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bianco2012" label="Bianco 2021"></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="blei2012" label="Blei 2012">Blei, D. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Probabilistic topic models</title>, <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title> 55(4), pp. 77-84. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bode2019" label="Bode 2019">Bode, K. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Computational iterary studies: Participant forum responses, Day 3</title>, <title rend="italic">In the Moment</title>, 3 April 2019. Available at: 
                    <ref target="https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/">https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bode2023" label="Bode 2023">Bode, K. (2023) <title rend="quotes">What’s the matter with computational literary studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>, 49(4), pp. 507-529.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brett2022" label="Brett 2022">Brett, M. R. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Topic modeling: A basic introduction</title>, <title>Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, 2(1). Available at: <ref target="https://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-1/topic-modeling-a-basic-introduction-by-megan-r-brett/">https://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-1/topic-modeling-a-basic-introduction-by-megan-r-brett/.</ref>
                (Accessed 10 March 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2011" label="Brown 2011">Brown, S. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Don’t mind the gap: Evolving models of scholarly production across the digital-humanities divide</title>, in Daniel Coleman and Smaro Kamboureli (eds.) 
                    <title rend="none">Retooling the humanities: The Culture of research in Canadian universities</title>. Edmonton: University of Alberta Press, pp. 203-232.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brydon2011" label="Brydon 2011">Brydon, D. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Do the humanities need a new humanism?</title>, in Daniel Coleman and Smaro Kamboureli (eds.) <title rend="italic">Retooling the humanities: The culture of research in Canadian universities</title>. Edmonton: University of Alberta Press, pp. 233-262.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick_etal2012" label="Burdick et al 2012">Burdick, A. et al. (2012) <title rend="italic">Digitial humanities.</title> Cambridge: MIT Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="butler2014" label="Butler 2014">Butler, J. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Ordinary, incredulous</title>, in Peter Brooks and Hilary Jewett (eds.) <title rend="quotes">The humanities and public life</title>. New York: Fordham University Press, pp. 15-39.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="churchill_etal2022" label="Churchill et al. 2022">Churchill, R. and Singh, L. (2022) <title rend="quotes">The evolution of topic modeling</title>, <title rend="italic">ACM Computing Surveys</title>, 54(10s), pp. 1-25. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clement2013" label="Clement 2013">Clement, T. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Text analysis, data mining, and visualizations in literary scholarship”</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary Studies in the Digital Age: An Evolving Anthology</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/text-analysis-data-mining-and-visualizations-in-literary-scholarship/">https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/text-analysis-data-mining-and-visualizations-in-literary-scholarship/</ref>. (Accessed 25 June 2019).
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="culler1981" label="Culler 1981">Culler, J. D. (1981) <title rend="italic">The pursuit of signs: Semiotics, literature, deconstruction</title>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="da2019b" label="Da 2019b">Da, N.Z. (2019b) <title rend="quotes">Errors</title>, in <title rend="italic">In the moment</title>. 2 April 2019. Available at: <ref target="https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/">https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/</ref>. (Accessed 10 June 2019). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thecomputationalcase" label="The Computational Case against Computational Literary Studies">No author (2019) <title rend="quotes">The computational case against computational literary studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>, 45(3), pp. 601-39. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dietterich_etal1995" label="Dietterich et al. 1995">Dietterich, T. G. and Kong, E.B. (1995) <title rend="quotes">Machine earning bias, statistical bias, and statistical variance of decision tree algorithms</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://www.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~irjohnso/coursenotes/uqc832/tr-bias.pdf">http://www.cems.uwe.ac.uk/~irjohnso/coursenotes/uqc832/tr-bias.pdf</ref>. (Accessed 18 June 2019). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="djwa1970" label="Djwa 1970">Dwja, S. (1970) <title rend="quotes">Canadian poetry and the computer</title>, <title rend="italic">Canadian Literature</title>, 46, pp. 43-54. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="djwa1964" label="Djwa 1964">Djwa, S. (1964) <title rend="italic">Metaphor, world view and the continuity of Canadian poetry: A study of the major English Canadian poets with a computer concordance to metaphor</title>. University of British Columbia, PhD dissertation.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Humanities approaches to graphical display</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 005(1). Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>. (Accessed 10 May 2022). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="egan2016" label="Egan 2016">Egan, J. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Literary data mining: A review of Matthew Jockers, Macroanalysis: Digital methods and literary history.</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10(3). Avalaible at: <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhqdev/vol/10/3/000266/000266.html#:~:text=Matthew%20Jockers'%20Macroanalysis%20asks%20us,data%20mining%20for%20studying%20literature">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhqdev/vol/10/3/000266/000266.html#:~:text=Matthew%20Jockers'%20Macroanalysis%20asks%20us,data%20mining%20for%20studying%20literature</ref>. (Available 5 June 2022). 
                 </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eyers2013" label="Eyers 2013">Eyers, T. (2013 <title rend="quotes">The perils of the ‘digital humanities’: New positivisms and the fate of literary theory</title>, <title rend="italic">Postmodern Culture</title>, 23(2). Available at: <ref target="https://www.pomoculture.org/2015/07/08/the-perils-of-the-digital-humanities-new-positivisms-and-the-fate-of-literary-theory/">https://www.pomoculture.org/2015/07/08/the-perils-of-the-digital-humanities-new-positivisms-and-the-fate-of-literary-theory/</ref>. (Accessed 20 February 2022). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fanon1961" label="Fanon 1961">Fanon, F. (1961) <title rend="italic">The wretched of the earth</title>, trans. Richard Philcox. New York: Grove Press.                 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fee1981" label="Fee 1981">Fee, M. (1981) <title rend="italic">English-Canadian literary criticism, 1890 – 1950: Defining and establishing a national literature</title>. University of Toronto, PhD dissertation. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2019" label="Fish 2019">Fish, S. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Afterword: Computational literary studies: Participant forum responses, day 3</title>, <title rend="italic">In the Moment</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/">https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3-5/</ref>. (Accessed 10 June 2019).
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2019b" label="Fish 2019b">Fish, S. (2019b) <title rend="quotes">If you count it, they will come</title>, <title rend="italic">New York Journal of Law and Liberty</title>, 12(2), pp. 333-351.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish1982" label="Fish 1982">Fish, S. (1982) <title rend="italic">Is there a text in this class? The authority of interpretive communities</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2012" label="Fish 2012">Fish, S. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Mind your p’s and b’s: The digital humanities and interpretation</title>, <title rend="italic">Opinionator</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/23/mind-your-ps-and-bs-the-digital-humanities-and-interpretation/">https://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/23/mind-your-ps-and-bs-the-digital-humanities-and-interpretation/</ref>. (Accessed 20 May 2019).
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2012b" label="Fish 2012b">Fish, S. (2012b) <title rend="quotes">The digital humanities and the transcending of mortality</title>, <title rend="italic">Opinionator</title>, 9 January 2012. Available at: <ref target="https://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/09/the-digital-humanities-and-the-transcending-of-mortality/">https://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/09/the-digital-humanities-and-the-transcending-of-mortality/</ref>. (Accessed 20 May 2019). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2018" label="Fish 2018">Fish, S. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The interpretive poverty of data</title>, <title rend="italic">Balkanization</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://balkin.blogspot.com/2018/03/the-interpretive-poverty-of-data.html">https://balkin.blogspot.com/2018/03/the-interpretive-poverty-of-data.html</ref>. (Accessed 25 May 2019). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foster2005" label="Foster 2005">Foster, F.S. (2005) <title rend="quotes">A narrative of the interesting origins and (somewhat) surprising developments of African-American print culture</title> <title rend="italic">American Literary History</title>, 17(4), pp. 714-40. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galeyetal_2010" label="Galey et al. 2010">Galey, A. and Ruecker, S. (2010) <title rend="quotes">How a prototype argues</title>, <title rend="italic">Library and Linguistic Computing</title>, 25(4), pp. 405-424. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Making a case for the Black digital humanities</title>, in Matthew F. Gold &amp; Lauren Klein (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, pp. 42-49.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gilroy1993" label="Gilroy 1993">Gillroy, P. (1993) <title rend="italic">The Black Atlantic: Modernity and double-consciousness</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, J.M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Markup bodies: Black [life] studies and slavery [death] studies at the digital crossroads</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>, 36(4), pp. 57-79. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="keith2006" label="Keith 2006">Keith, WJ. (2006) <title rend="italic">Canadian literature in English, volume 2</title>. Erin, ON: The Porcupine's Quill Press.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kerssens2019" label="Kerssens 2019">Kerssens, N. (2019) <title rend="quotes">De-agentializing data practices: The shifting power of metaphor in 1990s discourses on data mining</title>, <title rend="italic">CA: Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 1(1). Available at: <ref target="http://culturalanalytics.org/2019/05/de-agentializing-data-practices-the-shifting-power-of-metaphor-in-1990s-discourses-on-data-mining/">http://culturalanalytics.org/2019/05/de-agentializing-data-practices-the-shifting-power-of-metaphor-in-1990s-discourses-on-data-mining/</ref>. (Accessed 10 June 2020). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2019" label="Klein 2019">Klein, L.F. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Computational literary studies: Participant forum responses, Day 3</title>, <title rend="italic">In the Moment</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3/">https://critinq.wordpress.com/2019/04/03/computational-literary-studies-participant-forum-responses-day-3/</ref>. (Accessed 10 December 2020). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dimensionsofscale2020" label="Dimensions of Scale 2020">No author (2020) <title rend="quotes">Dimensions of scale: Invisible labor, editorial work, and the future of quantitative literary studies</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 135(1), pp. 23-39. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2013" label="Liu 2013">Liu, A. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The meaning of the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 128(2), pp. 409-423. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Why are the digital humanities so white? or thinking the histories of race and computing</title>, in Matthew K. Gold (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, pp. 139-160.  
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, F. (2013) <title rend="quotes">'Operationalizing’: or, the function of measurement in modern literary theory</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary Lab</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://litlab.stanford.edu/LiteraryLabPamphlet6.pdf">https://litlab.stanford.edu/LiteraryLabPamphlet6.pdf</ref>. (Accessed 12 December 2020). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2014" label="Nowviskie 2014">Nowviskie, B. (2014) <title rend="quotes">On the origin of ‘hack’ and ‘yack’</title>, <title rend="italic">Bethany Nowviskie</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://nowviskie.org/2014/on-the-origin-of-hack-and-yack/">https://nowviskie.org/2014/on-the-origin-of-hack-and-yack/ </ref>. (Accessed 14 June 2019).  
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perloff2004" label="Perloff 2004">Perloff, M. (2004) <title rend="italic">Differentials: Poetry, poetics, pedagog</title>. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2016" label="Piper 2016">Piper, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">There will be numbers</title>, <title rend="italic">CA: Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 1(1). Available at: <ref target="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11062-there-will-be-numbers">https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11062-there-will-be-numbers</ref>. (Accessed 25 June 2019).  
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="potter1988" label="Potter 1988">Potter, R. (1988) <title rend="quotes">Literary criticism and literary computing: The difficulties of a synthesis</title>, <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>, 22(2), pp. 91-97. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, R. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Beyond the margins: Intersectionality and the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 0009(2). Available at: <ref target="https://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html">https://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html</ref>. (Accessed 20 June 2020). 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_etal2021" label="Risam et al. 2021">Risam, R. and Josephs, K.B. (2021) <title rend="italic">The ditgial Black Atlantic</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruberg_etal2018" label="Ruberg et al. 2018">Ruberg, B., Boyd, J., and Howe, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Toward a Queer digital humanities</title>, in Elizabeth Losh and Jacqueline Wernimont (eds.) <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional Feminism and Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: The University of Minnesota Press, pp. 108-127.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="said1975" label="Said 1975">Said, E.W. (1975) <title rend="italic">Beginnings: Intention and method</title>. New York: Columbia University Press.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thetexttheworld1975b" label="The Text, the World, the Critic 1975b">No author (1975b) <title rend="italic">The bulletin of the midwest modern language association</title>, 8(2), pp. 1-23. 
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="so2020" label="So 2020">So, R.J. (2020) <title rend="italic">Redlining culture: A data history of racial inequality and postwar fiction</title>. New York: Columbia University Press.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2012" label="Underwood 2012">Underwood, T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Topic modeling made just simple enough</title>, <title rend="italic">The Stone and the Shell</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://tedunderwood.com/2012/04/07/topic-modeling-made-just-simple-enough/">https://tedunderwood.com/2012/04/07/topic-modeling-made-just-simple-enough/</ref>. (Accessed 25 June 2019).
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wasserstein2016" label="Wasserstein 2016">Wasserstein, R. L. and Lazer, N. A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Editorial</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Statistician</title>, 70(2), pp. 129-33.
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wynter1987" label="Wynter 1987">Wynter, S. (1987) <title rend="quotes">On disenchanting discourse: ‘Minority’ literary criticism and beyond</title>, <title rend="italic">Cultural Critique</title>, 7, pp. 204-244. 
                </bibl>
      

            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>