<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Paul A. <dhq:family>Broyles</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>North Carolina State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>pabroyle@ncsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Paul A. Broyles is a Lecturer in English at North Carolina State
                            University, where he previously held a CLIR Postdoctoral Fellowship in
                            Data Curation for Medieval Studies. He serves as Technical Director of
                            the Society for Early English and Norse Electronic Texts (SEENET) and
                            Technical Editor of the <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman Electronic
                                Archive</title>. His technical work includes programming and data
                            management for digital humanities projects; other research areas include
                            medieval romance, geographic thought, and textual transmission.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000455</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-19">19 June 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2020-03-20" who="murelj">Created filed; began encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Digital editions are easily modified after they are first published — a state of
                    affairs that poses challenges both for long-term scholarly reference and for
                    various forms of electronic distribution and analysis. This article argues that
                    producers of digital editions should assign meaningful version numbers to their
                    editions and update those version numbers with each change, allowing both humans
                    and computers to know when resources have been modified and how significant the
                    changes are. As an examination of versioning practices in the software industry
                    reveals, version numbers are not neutral descriptors but social products
                    intended for use in specific contexts, and the producers of digital editions
                    must consider how version numbers will be used in developing numbering schemes.
                    It may be beneficial to version different parts of an edition separately, and in
                    particular to version the data objects or content of an edition independently
                    from the environment in which it is displayed. The article concludes with a case
                    study of the development of a versioning policy for the <title rend="italic"
                        >Piers Plowman Electronic Archive</title>, and includes an appendix
                    surveying how a selection of digital editions handle the problem of recording
                    and communicating changes.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Examines versioning practices and policies as social products to argue for
                transparency in assigning meaningful version numbers to digital editions</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new
                    materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such
                    changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and
                    one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are
                    comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books
                    can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers
                    instinctively recognize G. Thomas Tanselle’s <quote rend="inline">central truth
                        . . . that books are not meant to be unique items and are normally printed
                        in runs of what purport to be duplicate copies</quote>
                    <ptr target="#tanselle1980" loc="18"/>.<note><ref target="#tanselle2001"
                            >Tanselle (2001)</ref> objects to the idea that electronic texts are in
                        any way more fluid than printed texts. Modifying electronic files, Tanselle
                        says, alters outputs no more completely or undetectably than does the
                        resetting of type. But Tanselle undervalues the ways in which digital
                        textuality (especially online) collapses the space between creation and
                        publication: a revised forme is not broadcast into copies already printed,
                        but changes made to a file on a webserver will immediately appear to anyone
                        visiting the website, even if they have previously visited it, unless they
                        have taken pains to archive a copy, and any savvy web user understands that
                        an online resource may not be the same as last time they visited. The print
                        world may be following the electronic: in today’s publishing environment,
                        books are <q>born digital</q>, designed on computer screens and printed with
                        laser printers or with plates that are designed to be disposable and can be
                        regularly recycled and recreated. I learned about current publishing
                        practices from a talk by Matthew Kirschenbaum <ptr
                            target="#kirschenbaum2017"/>, which has considerably influenced my
                        thinking. Today’s printed books thus share in digital instability, and their
                        bibliographers and archivists will need to be concerned with many of the
                        issues of digital revision and versioning that I discuss in this
                        article.</note> Moreover, printed volumes are self-identical: a single copy
                    of a book remains the same object and carries the same text unless acted upon by
                    outside forces, like the environment, natural deterioration, or a human hand.
                    Standards for scholarly citation, which solidified around print resources, take
                    advantage of this objectual stability. Referencing a book means identifying its
                    author and title, its edition number (if specified), and the details of its
                    publication (perhaps including the year of its most recent printing or issue).
                    Where the details of a particular copy matter (for instance for incunabula, or
                    where the argument is bibliographic), the writer might go so far as to specify a
                    library or archive and shelfmark. Armed with that information, readers can find
                    and consult an appropriate copy.</p>
                <p>By contrast, online digital resources can be expanded or corrected long after
                    their initial release<note>As is frequently noted — see for example <ref
                            target="#schreibman2013" loc="¶41">Schreibman (2013), ¶41</ref> and <ref
                            target="#sahle2016" loc="29–30">Sahle (2016), 29-30</ref>.</note> — not
                    necessarily by publishing a new edition that can occupy the shelf beside the
                    previous, nor even through a stop-press correction that will affect volumes
                    printed after it is made, but simply by updating some files on a webserver, with
                    the result that anyone accessing the resource from that point on will see the
                    revised form. Indeed, this mutability is one of the defining promises of digital
                    textuality. Jerome McGann, in his influential essay <title rend="quotes">The
                        Rationale of Hypertext</title> (first published online in 1995), contrasts
                    the physical book, which <quote rend="inline">literally closes its covers on
                        itself</quote> when it is published, with the hypertext archive that <quote
                        rend="inline">need never be <q>complete</q></quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                        >will evolve and change over time, it will gather new bodies of material,
                        its organizational substructures will get modified, perhaps quite
                        drastically</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mcgann1995"/>
                    <ptr target="#mcgann1996" loc="27, 29"/>. Less poetically perhaps, but no less
                    significantly, errors can be corrected with relative ease. And anyone who has
                    tried to maintain a digital resource over any duration knows that, quite apart
                    from willful content revisions, changes may not merely be possible but required
                    in order to keep it operational.<note>These might be changes to underlying
                        technologies, such as updating a piece of software on a webserver or
                        upgrading to a version of a web framework designed for newer browsers, but
                        they might also be changes in support of the long-term interoperability and
                        accessibility of underlying data, such as migrating data to a new encoding
                        standard after an old one has become obsolete.</note></p>
                <p>While the open-endedness of digital resources, the potential for evolution and
                    infinite expansion, has excited scholars (the creators of large digital
                    editorial projects among them), the inherent changeability of digital materials
                    also poses threats to the scholarly ecosystem. Looking beyond the by now
                    well-known problem of <term>link rot</term>, in which online resources linked in
                    references simply disappear from the internet, research on science communication
                    has identified the problem of <term>context drift</term>, in which links
                    function but the content on the website has changed since it was referenced <ptr
                        target="#klein2014"/>; a study published in 2016 found that as many as 75%
                    of webpages referenced in scholarly literature in Science, Technology, and
                    Medicine have changed since they were cited <ptr target="#jones2016"/>. Though
                    results would likely be different if examining citations of digital scholarly
                    editions, which are my concern in this article, the issue of <term>context
                        drift</term> highlights the problems that digital mutability poses to the
                    scholarly record. Indeed, the Committee on Scholarly Editions of the Modern
                    Language Association (MLA CSE) has identified <quote rend="inline">the challenge
                        of maintaining the scholarly ability to be referenced in view of the ways
                        that interfaces change over time</quote> as a central issue facing digital
                    scholarly editions <ptr target="#MLAC2016" loc="7"/>.</p>
                <p>In this article, I focus on digital scholarly editions, arguing that in order to
                    make sure such editions are citeable and their history is intelligible, their
                    creators and publishers must assign version numbers in tandem with any changes
                    made to edition content. By digital scholarly editions, I refer to any
                    electronic resources that encode textual objects for scholarly study.<note>This
                        definition is broadly similar to that offered in <ref target="#sahle2016"
                            >Sahle (2016)</ref>. <term>Textual objects</term> is an intentionally
                        expansive term, most obviously encompassing literary and historical works
                        and documents, but potentially describing any materials that could be
                        encoded and edited. I make no distinction between <q>edition</q> and
                            <q>archive</q> (see <ref target="#price2009">Price (2009)</ref>), and
                        also refer to the organizations and publishing outlets that create and
                        provide access to edition materials as <q>projects</q> and to their outputs
                        as <q>texts</q> or, more generally, <q>resources</q>. The versioning
                        problems with which I am concerned affect editions of all size, from ad-hoc
                        encodings of individual documents to large digital archives encompassing
                        many edited texts. While I am primarily thinking of richly encoded editions
                        such as those based on Text Encoding Initiative standards, the issues and
                        solutions I present would apply equally to plain text files.</note> While
                    the same considerations might apply to many kinds of digital scholarly resource,
                    I choose to focus on digital editions for a few reasons. For one thing, perhaps
                    more than other areas of digital scholarship in the humanities, digital
                    scholarly editing constitutes a clear community of practice, with a longstanding
                    tradition of editorial theory and a widely (though certainly not universally)
                    shared technical standard in the form of the Guidelines of the Text Encoding
                    Initiative (TEI). For another, the concern with textual histories within
                    scholarly editing and other fields under the umbrella of textual scholarship
                    suggests that editors of all people ought to be particularly attentive to the
                    way textual resources transform in time.</p>
                <p>But perhaps most significantly, digital editions occupy a hybrid position in the
                    scholarly ecosystem that makes it especially important to be able to identify
                    and track the changes they go through and the states in which they exist.
                    Digital editions, as I understand them, are simultaneously scholarly
                    publications and data sources. Like all scholarly editions, digital editions are
                    a product of interpretation, scholarly judgment, and the imposition of codes and
                    conventions onto the material being remediated; that is to say, they are works
                    of scholarship, produced according to the research and critical judgment of
                    their creators. Like other scholarly publications, digital editions can be
                    formally vetted through peer review processes.<note>In addition to peer review
                        processes offered by publishers, professional organizations have created
                        mechanisms for peer reviewing digital editions. The Modern Language
                        Association’s Committee on Scholarly Editions (MLA CSE) seal, awarded to
                        Approved Editions, is available to print and digital editions alike. Member
                        organizations of the Advanced Research Consortium — the Medieval Electronic
                        Scholarly Alliance (MESA), 18thConnect, Nineteenth-Century Scholarship
                        Online (NINES), ModNets, and Studies in Radicalism Online (SIRO) — also
                        facilitate peer review processes for digital resources including digital
                        editions. According to the ARC, when a node approves a resource, the node’s
                        director issues a letter “geared toward tenure and promotion committees”
                        that <quote rend="inline">highlights equivalencies to print
                            publications</quote>
                        <ptr target="#SPR"/>.</note> And in general, digital editions are presented
                    in user interfaces that support the reading and study of the provided text,
                    rather than simply providing encoded files for a user to download.<note>Of the
                        thirty projects surveyed in the Appendix, only The Proceedings of the Old
                        Bailey in my assessment prioritizes access to textual data over the reading
                        of text. Turksa et al. emphasizes the degree to which editors, not to
                        mention funders and potential publics, respond to the presentation of
                        digital editions. The massive body of writing emphasizing the flexible
                        displays and interfaces of digital editions implicitly understands them as
                        resources that users will interact with through reading interfaces <ptr
                            target="#turska2016" loc="¶2–5"/>; see for example <ref
                            target="#tanselle1995" loc="591–592">Tanselle (1995), 591-2</ref> and
                            <ref target="#shillingsburg1996" loc="163–166">Shillingsburg (1996),
                            163-6</ref>. Shillinsburg suggests that digital editions are not well
                        suited for novice or pleasure readers <ptr target="#shillingsburg1996"
                            loc="165"/>, a proposition echoed by <ref target="#gabler2010" loc="46"
                            >Gabler (2010)</ref>: <quote rend="inline">we read texts in their native
                            print medium, that is, in books; but we study texts and works in
                            editions – in editions that live in the digital medium.</quote> However,
                        note Krista Stinne Greve Rasmussen’s assertion that the role of reader is
                        the foundation for more involved forms of textual study and knowledge
                        creation <ptr target="#rasmussen2016" loc="128"/>.</note> But editions also
                    provide data on multiple levels. Most basically, they provide texts
                    corresponding to particular documents or works that scholars may reference and
                    cite in publications, treating the edition as a surrogate for the object it
                    edits and using the text it offers as a basis for analysis: that is, as
                        data.<note>That is, while commentators have praised the ways in which
                        digital editions expose the editorial process and invite readers to
                        interrogate the editors’ methods (see for example <ref target="#smith2004"
                            >Smith (2004), 317-318</ref>; <ref target="#gabler2010">Gabler (2010),
                            48</ref>), digital editions still typically produce texts (even if those
                        texts are multiple or provisional), and readers may well want to reference
                        those texts as texts, using them as a basis for literary analysis, rather
                        than engaging with them as arguments about text. A study of users of the
                        Font Gaia digital library (which includes digitized content, digital
                        exhibits, and digital editions) found that the most common use for the
                        library was to consult documents online, though users were primarily
                            <q>scanning</q> and reading selectively rather than reading in full —
                        occupying, the study’s author notes, Rasmussen’s <q>user</q> role <ptr
                            target="#leblanc2018" loc="295, 297, 303–304"/>.</note> Humans are by no
                    means the only potential consumers of the data embedded in digital editions.
                    Texts and metadata can form raw material for analysis, including computer-aided
                    study and incorporation into large corpora. And the dream of the fully networked
                    digital edition, functionally integrated and cross-referenced by other editions
                    and systems, grows ever more practical with the development of shared
                    infrastructures and standards.<note>See <ref target="#kalvesmaki2014">Kalvesmaki
                            (2014)</ref> for a discussion the Canonical Text Services (CTS) standard
                        for digital cross-references. The in-progress Distributed Text Services
                        specification builds on the work of CTS to develop systems for computers to
                        query and retrieve data from digital editions <ptr target="#DTS2019"
                        />.</note> Digital editions, then, are simultaneously publications and data,
                    potentially offering interfaces both to humans and to machines, and it is
                    essential that these multiple consumers be able to understand the evolution of
                    digital editions and precisely reference different states as editions are
                    revised.</p>
                <p>Version numbers, I argue, offer a simple and practical method not merely for
                    identifying a state of a resource, but for communicating something of its
                    history and the relationship among its states. Yet defined, citable version
                    numbers still seem to be a rarity in the world of digital editions, and no
                    consensus practice exists in the field regarding how different versions of an
                    electronic textual resource should be identified, or what it is that version
                    numbers should communicate.<note>In the <ref target="#appendix1">Appendix </ref>
                        I present the results of an examination of thirty digital editions, finding
                        that only 23% give their material version numbers, and only 13% version
                        individual data files representing distinct texts. Major works devoted to
                        scholarly editing in the digital age also omit discussion of versioning
                        materials post-publication. <ref target="#shillingsburg1996">Shillingsburg
                            (1996), 169</ref> and <ref target="#kline2008">Kline and Perdue (2008),
                            288</ref> both comment approvingly on the ability of editors to make
                        corrections to published electronic editions, and both devote attention to
                        managing data during the preparation of an edition, but neither offers
                        concrete suggestions for managing changes to materials after publication.
                        The essays in <ref target="#burnard2006">Burnard et al. (2006)</ref>, offer
                        a good deal of practical insight into data issues of digital editions, and
                        two address head-on the challenges posed by the mutability of digital
                        editions <ptr target="#berrie2006"/>
                        <ptr target="#deegan2006"/>, but none of the contributions suggests clear
                        practices for publicly versioning materials. The MLA CSE’s Guidelines for
                        Editors of Scholarly Editions ask editors to consider the importance of
                            <quote rend="inline">permanence or fixity</quote> as well as the
                        benefits of “openness and fluidity” (§1.2.3), and ask those charged with
                        vetting editions in all media to determine whether a correction file will be
                        available (§2, questions 22.3-4), and in the case of digital editions
                        whether edition materials have been deposited in a long-term repository (§2,
                        question 28.4); however, the guidelines offer no standards for how digital
                        editions should make users aware of changes or ensure long-term reference
                            <ptr target="#MLAC2011"/>. <ref target="#pierazzo2015">Pierazzo (2015),
                            186-187</ref> directly addresses the problem of versioning, perhaps
                        heralding a needed increase of attention toward the issue. Pierazzo’s
                        suggestion is to embed a revision control system within a digital edition; I
                        will discuss the limitations of that approach below. </note> Although
                    textual scholarship has created sophisticated frameworks for understanding
                    revision and the evolution of texts, I suggest that software developers have
                    much to teach editors about versioning living resources in ongoing development
                    and publication. This essay argues that a new version number should be attached
                    each time an edition is updated, that version numbers should communicate
                    something meaningful about the scope of changes to the resource, and that the
                    encoded informational content of an edition should be versioned separately from
                    the interfaces through which users access that information. After outlining
                    considerations involved in assigning version numbers, I conclude with a case
                    study of the development of a versioning policy for the <title rend="italic"
                        >Piers Plowman Electronic Archive</title>, a longstanding scholarly resource
                    that has published editions of multiple texts in evolving formats.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Approaches to Change</head>
                <p>The fundamental changeability of digital resources, including digital editions,
                    poses challenges to longstanding scholarly paradigms of authority and
                    completeness. Kathleen Fitzpatrick has suggested that the capacity — indeed, in
                    some circumstances, the necessity — for digital writing to change over time
                    might suggest a fundamental change in our understanding of scholarly writing,
                    from product to process <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2011" loc="66–72"/>. But new
                    paradigms only slowly beget the practices needed to support them. Paul Fyfe has
                    argued that we have not sufficiently theorized how digital scholarship deals
                    with the problem of error <ptr target="#fyfe2012"/>. Correcting error is
                    relatively simple, but scholarly practices surrounding correction lag
                    behind.</p>
                <p>For digital editions in particular, change is a double-edged sword. Although few
                    editors would now claim to be producing “definitive editions,” the goal of any
                    editor is presumably to produce an accurate text representing the document or
                    work being edited according to that editor’s theory of the object of
                        study.<note>For one statement on the impossibility of a definitive edition,
                        see <ref target="#tanselle1992" loc="74">Tanselle (1992), 74</ref>. On an
                        edition as presenting a theory about the work being edited, see <ref
                            target="#cerquiglini1999" loc="22">Cerquiglini (1999), 22</ref>.</note>
                    Thus, the ability to incorporate corrections and continuously present the most
                    accurate possible text in one sense enhances the reliability and scholarly value
                    of digital editions by contrast to print, where errors discovered after
                    publication can be corrected only in later printings or by issuing errata. But
                    that same flexibility underscores the need to be able to clearly identify
                    particular states of the resource. Consider a scholar who bases an argument on a
                    particular reading taken from a diplomatic text presented in a digital edition.
                    The editors later discover that they have made an error in their transcription
                    and update the edition. Without a way to identify the specific state of the
                    resource when it was cited, the error may appear to have been the scholar’s, and
                    the scholarly record is muddled. Similarly, archivists seeking to preserve a
                    digital edition can more effectively capture its history if the resource clearly
                    signals when changes occur. And computer systems that ingest and process data
                    from digital editions (for instance aggregating texts from multiple
                    publications, or analyzing the text of an edition and recording statistical
                    information in a database) have the same needs as human researchers: to know in
                    what form they have accessed a resource and when changes have occurred. Citation
                    styles, clerical practices, and technical measures have all attempted to offer
                    solutions to the problem of digital change, but I argue that explicit versioning
                    of resources can more effectively meet the needs of digital reference.</p>
                <p>When citation guides were first faced with the problem of the mutability of
                    digital resources, some suggested that researchers citing online publications
                    should include in their citations the date on which they accessed the material
                        <ptr target="#gibaldi1995" loc="§4.9.1"/>
                    <ptr target="#turabian1996" loc="§8.141"/>
                    <ptr target="#gibaldi1998" loc="§6.9.1"/>
                    <ptr target="#PM2001" loc="4.16.71ff"/>.<note>The most recent edition of the APA
                        style guide eliminates the recommendation to provide access dates <ptr
                            target="#PM2010" loc="§6.31ff"/>. By contrast, the 2003 edition of
                            <title rend="italic">The Chicago Manual of Style</title> initiated the
                        still-standing Chicago style recommendation against access dates. It also
                        warned against including revision dates, though that stance has since
                        weakened <ptr target="#CM2003" loc="§17.12"/>.</note> Access dates recognize
                    that online resources evolve, but they are concerned with a researcher’s
                    activity (visiting a website) rather than with the resource itself. Unless a
                    resource happens to have been archived on that particular day, a date of access
                    does not point to a particular form of the material (and there is, of course, no
                    guarantee that the resource did not change later on the day it was cited).
                        <title rend="italic">The Chicago Manual of Style</title> accordingly
                    suggests that <quote rend="inline">access dates in online citations are of
                        limited value</quote> and does not recommend including them in citations
                        <ptr target="#CM2017" loc="§14.12"/>. And for computer systems interacting
                    with a resource, recording the date of last access does nothing to determine
                    whether it has changed since that last access.</p>
                <p>Another way of dealing with the problem of mutating resources — the method most
                    endorsed by the TEI, and the most widely used way in which digital editing
                    projects appear to deal with textual change (see <ref target="#appendix1"
                        >Appendix</ref>) — is manually creating a log of revisions. Attaching
                    revision metadata to files allow records of revisions to be closely associated
                    with the files themselves, though this information does not make it possible to
                    reference particular states of the text. The TEI Guidelines provide the XML
                    element <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code> in the header of each file to record
                    narrative explanations of changes and the reasons and agents behind them in
                    individual <code>&lt;change&gt;</code> elements associated with each revision
                        <ptr target="#TEI2019" loc="§2.6"/>. Because change logs are simply written
                    records of modifications, they are not tied to the TEI, or to any particular
                    metadata format. The <title rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</title>'s <ptr
                        target="#folsomprice"/>, for example, maintains a public change log in the
                    form of a blog that provides clear descriptions of modifications to the <title
                        rend="italic">Archive</title>, from corrections of typos to pervasive
                    metadata updates <ptr target="#WWAC2019"/>.<note>The blog also provides
                        descriptions of additions and modifications to the <title rend="italic"
                            >Archive</title> website apart from updates to the XML data, though the
                        blog description notes that minor changes in appearance and events such as
                        server outages are not recorded. </note> Individual XML files also carry the
                    TEI <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code> element. <title rend="italic">The Whitman
                        Archive</title>’s approach models thoroughness and transparency in
                    disclosing ongoing modifications to a digital resource. But the <title
                        rend="italic">Archive</title> largely obscures these revision histories from
                    users of the site. The change blog is hosted at a different web domain from the
                        <title rend="italic">Archive</title> itself, and the revision lists embedded
                    in file metadata are not displayed in the reading interface provided on its
                    website — probably the context in which most users will encounter the texts. In
                    contrast, the <title rend="italic">William Blake Archive</title>
                    <ptr target="#eaves2017"/> extracts this revision history and presents it in a
                    human–readable format in an Electronic Edition Information section associated
                    with each object in its collection. This section of the display makes the file
                    history more directly available to readers conducting research within the <title
                        rend="italic">Archive</title> and conceivably allows readers to cite the
                    date of the last revision, but still does not supply a specific identifier
                    pointing unambiguously to a particular state of the file. The many editorial
                    projects that use change logs store and expose that information in a wide
                    variety of ways, but share an interest in recording what kinds of changes were
                    made, when, and (often) by whom — without necessarily offering a way to
                    reference a state of the resource resulting from a particular set of
                    changes.</p>
                <p>Nor do change logs offer any way to get back to prior versions of a resource; a
                    user can understand what has changed, but not access an earlier form. The
                    increasing embrace of revision control systems (RCSs) such as Git in the digital
                    humanities has suggested the possibility of automated, systematized methods for
                    tracking revision history and providing access to specific states of a project
                    or file.<note>These systems are also known as version control systems; I use the
                        term revision control systems to emphasize the fact that these systems
                        record project data and changes to it, but do not identify versions of the
                        data unless those versions are explicitly labeled within the RCS. The terms
                        are essentially interchangeable in their typical use; Git, for example,
                        identifies itself as a <quote rend="inline">version control system</quote>
                        on its homepage but as a <quote rend="inline">revision control
                            system</quote> in its manual <ptr target="#git"/>
                        <ptr target="#gitum"/>.</note> Elena Pierazzo proposes that RCSs should be
                    embedded in digital edition software, exposing the evolution of an edition and
                    providing access to previous states <ptr target="#pierazzo2015" loc="185–186"
                        />.<note>RCSs can still be useful for presenting and exploring project
                        history even if not embedded within the edition. For one endorsement, see
                            <ref target="#escobarvarela2016">Escobar Varela (2016) ¶¶34-35</ref>.
                        Release tagging, which Escobar Varela highlights, can be used in tandem with
                        version numbering to label a particular state of the repository as
                        representing a specific version — but this works effectively only where the
                        contents of the repository are versioned together as a unit.</note>
                    Wiki-based editions, such as <title rend="italic">A Social Edition of the
                        Devonshire MS</title>
                    <ptr target="#siemens"/>, are one existing model enacting Pierazzo’s hope for
                    editions with built-in RCSs. Christian Wittern goes even further, suggesting
                    that distributed RCSs such as Git might furnish a new ecosystem for scholarly
                    publishing of digital editions, allowing the maintenance of fine-grained
                    revision histories as well as the coexistence of multiple revisions of a single
                    file carried out by different scholars <ptr target="#wittern2013" loc="§4"
                    />.</p>
                <p>RCSs make file history accessible, but do not necessarily identify or make
                    intelligible meaningful developmental stages. While different RCSs provide
                    different features, broadly, they operate by storing the content of each file as
                    well as a precise record of each change made to any file. As a result, all
                    changes are reversible, and it is possible to retrieve any previous state of a
                    file as it was stored in the RCS repository, as well as any previous state of
                    the repository as a whole. In order to facilitate retrieving earlier states,
                    RCSs do (unlike change logs) provide unambiguous identifiers for a particular
                    state of a file. In Git, for instance, each commit has an associated hash: a
                    cryptographically generated key that can be used to identify and retrieve a
                    particular state of the repository. A particular version of a file, or of the
                    whole project, can thus be identified through an associated hash. However, they
                    are not necessarily meaningful to human users. Git hashes, produced using the
                    SHA-1 algorithm, take the form of forty-digit hexadecimal numbers (usually cited
                    only by their first few digits). The hashes of successive commits bear no
                    visible relationship to each other; indeed, given two hashes but no access to
                    the repository containing the data, it is not possible to determine which
                    represents the more recent state of the data. Other RCSs use different
                    mechanisms, some of which are more straightforwardly numeric, but identifiers
                    within RCSs are inevitably tied to the details of the system and may not
                    correspond to human editors’ understanding of their processes. They cease to
                    identify states of a file or resource if that file is archived elsewhere, or
                    even if the project migrates to a new RCS.<note>It would be possible to
                        automatically embed information regarding RCS revisions into data files so
                        they preserved the information even if removed from the RCS, as one project
                        profiled in the <ref target="#appendix1">Appendix</ref> did; see <ref
                            target="#note56">note 56</ref>. However, such measures are workarounds
                        that highlight the extent to which RCS revision numbers differ from version
                        identifiers created specifically for a resource.</note></p>
                <p>Revision control is an important tool for data management in the digital
                    humanities. But explicit, deliberate versioning of data should go beyond
                    recording revision history or providing an arbitrary identifier for a particular
                    state of a file (bound to a specific RCS). Versioning should communicate
                    information that helps both humans and computers understand how that version
                    relates to others and the context in which users should approach it. Assigning
                    version numbers to digital editions would permit humans and computer systems not
                    only to refer to a particular state of the edition, but to understand the
                    relationship between any two copies. Adopting clear versioning practices aids
                    both the preservation and the reuse of data, and the producers of digital
                    editions can benefit from practices developed both in the fields of textual
                    scholarship and software development in producing useful version numbers for
                    digital editions.</p>
                <p>The problem of versioning data is by no means unique to digital editions; it is a
                    pressing issue of research data management and publication across disciplines.
                    The W3C recommendation on <title rend="quotes">Data on the Web Best
                        Practices</title> highlights the importance of versioning data and
                    specifically indicates the value of standardized, meaningful version numbers
                    that not only identify versions, but suggest how they differ <ptr
                        target="#lóscio2017" loc="§8.6 and Best Practice 7"/>. But despite
                    increasing recognition of the importance of clearly versioning research data,
                    standard practices around versioning have yet to cohere in the research data
                    community; a guide to data versioning from the Australian National Data Service
                    is replete with language like <quote rend="inline">no agreed standard or
                        recommendation</quote> and <quote rend="inline">no one way</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ANDS"/>. Still, emerging data infrastructures support a move
                    toward more transparent and explicit versioning. For instance, the research data
                    repository Zenodo introduced support for versioned Digital Object Identifiers
                    (DOIs) in 2017, allowing depositors to update their data and permitting
                    researchers to cite both specific versions and a whole concept independent of
                    version <ptr target="#nielsen2017"/>.<note>I collaborated with Daniel Paul
                        O’Donnell to use Zenodo to publish and version the source code for the
                        online republication of his digital edition of <title rend="italic">Cædmon’s
                            Hymn</title>
                        <ptr target="#odonnell2018"/>.</note> Particularly within the Open Science
                    movement, the growing emphasis on data publication has translated into attention
                    on data versioning.</p>
                <p>However, the textual digital humanities, and digital editing in particular, have
                    been slower to adopt versioning practices. Editors’ awareness of the problem of
                    textual variance should make them more attuned to the need to track and
                    publicize the evolution of their own editions. The practices of textual
                    criticism point to the value of developing versioning protocols for digital
                    editions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Textual Versioning</head>
                <p>When textual scholars use the term <term>version</term>, they mean something
                    different from (though related to) the way the term is used in software
                    development. Because my argument that digital editions need versioning policies
                    lies at the intersection of these fields, it will be useful to survey the ways
                    in which the two fields think about versioning. Literary scholars and textual
                    critics might speak of the Quarto and First Folio versions of Shakespeare’s
                        <title rend="italic">King Lear</title>, or the A, B, and C versions of the
                    fourteenth-century alliterative poem <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman</title>
                    — or to distinct draft versions produced during the course of Thoreau’s revision
                    of the single manuscript of <title rend="italic">Walden</title>. Software
                    developers (or users), on the other hand, might refer to version 5.2.1 of the
                    Linux kernel, or to Apple’s iOS 12.4 (eliding the word <q>version</q> entirely).
                    Do these concepts have anything to do with each other? Though their orientation
                    is different — textual scholarship is focused on historical analysis, software
                    development on ongoing maintenance, publication, and support — both fields share
                    a common concern with making it easier to understand variation and evolution, a
                    concern likewise relevant to the problem of changes in digital editions.</p>
                <p><q>Version</q>, as used by textual critics and editors, generally denotes a
                    distinct state of a work or a document that has transformed in time. Literary
                    works exist in different versions because of alterations during the course of
                    their composition and transmission — alterations by the author or by someone
                    else, willed or unwilled. So, a campaign of authorial revision of a work would
                    produce a new version of that work, as might the copying of a medieval
                    manuscript in which a scribe introduced changes (even unintentional ones), or
                    the publication of an expurgated edition long after an author’s death. These
                    versions have independent value as forms in which creators conceived and
                    audiences encountered the work. Donald H. Reiman in 1987 argued for what he
                    called <quote rend="inline">versioning</quote>, as a counterpoint to editing:
                    rather than producing complicated, expensive critical editions, he suggests, it
                    may be more productive to publish accessible texts of major forms in which a
                    work existed, such as important editions and authorial manuscripts, allowing
                    readers to compare the texts themselves <ptr target="#reiman1987"/>. (The
                    profusion of digital documentary editions suggests that Reiman’s dream is
                    increasingly being realized.)<note>On the prominence of documentary editing in
                        the digital sphere, see <ref target="#pierazzo2014">Pierazzo
                        (2014)</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>Both genetic critics and those concerned with the <q>sociology of the text</q>
                    have emphasized the coherence and vitality of individual versions of developing
                    works, pointing to the inadequacy of the notion of final authorial intention and
                    calling for editorial and critical engagement with versions as coherent
                        units.<note>I cite only a few productive samples from these wide-ranging
                        debates. For a concise and helpful, though dated, overview, see <ref
                            target="#greetham1992">Greetham (1992), 335-346</ref>.</note> Hans
                    Zeller argued that individual variants in witnesses to a work cannot be
                    considered in isolation, as had been common under the principles of eclectic
                    editing; rather, we must recognize <quote rend="inline">the relationship of its
                        elements to one another and to the whole, and therefore to what constitutes
                        a text as a text, to what makes it into a particular version</quote>
                    <ptr target="#zeller1975" loc="237"/>. Peter L. Shillingsburg identifies the
                    concept of version as <quote rend="inline">a means of classifying copies of a
                        Work according to one or more concepts that help account for the variant
                        texts or variant formats that characterize them</quote>
                    <ptr target="#shillingsburg1991" loc="50"/>. A version is thus a concept, not a
                    thing; it is distinct from any physical embodiment (which might not represent it
                    reliably), and versions come into being through the act of reading, as readers
                    create them to organize textual variants <ptr target="#shillingsburg1991"
                        loc="51, 73"/>. John Bryant, articulating his concept of the <quote
                        rend="inline">fluid text</quote> defined by the flow among different
                    versions, echoes the notion of versions as <quote rend="inline">critical
                        constructs</quote> but also emphasizes their relationality: all versions
                    exist in relation to other versions; they come into being through revision
                    (which may or may not be intended); they are <quote rend="inline">pulsings of .
                        . . collective energy</quote> that can involve both authors and the
                    editorial and cultural forces surrounding and following them; they have their
                    own conceptions of the work and speak to their own readerships <ptr
                        target="#bryant2002" loc="88–90"/>. While these and other theories of the
                    concept of version differ on points such as the precise degree, nature, and
                    agency of the changes that can produce a new version, they share a sense that
                    versions are distinct and alive, and their coexistence is part of what
                    constitutes a work.</p>
                <p>These sophisticated frameworks for textual change may seem far from the problems
                    of labeling changes as a digital edition is revised, and from the
                    straightforward numerical approaches that I will draw from software development.
                    But textual-critical accounts of versioning remind us that readers (and, we
                    might add for our purposes, machines) encounter individual texts as coherent
                    units, and these discrete forms have existence and meaning independent of the
                    work as a whole. The kind of versioning this article focuses on is not teasing
                    out key moments in the life of a work that is the object of study, but
                    identifying moments of change in the evolving life of the published edition. In
                    other words, echoing Hans Walter Gabler’s understanding of the contents of an
                    edition, this article is concerned with versioning the editor’s text and the
                    editorial discourses attached to it <ptr target="#gabler2010" loc="45"/>. An
                    edition might present one or more versions of a work or of a document (indeed,
                    the ability to present more versions in more dynamic forms has long been
                    heralded as one of the most exciting potentials of digital editions), but what I
                    address in this article is the need to version that edition as an edition, to
                    keep track of the changes that occur within the edition itself.<note>This is
                        not, of course, to suggest that the edition exists apart from the history of
                        the work edited. A new edition becomes the latest entry in the textual
                        history of the work it edits — it might even be said to constitute a version
                        of that text — and a future study of the reception or evolution of the work
                        might include the edition as one of its objects of study. But for the
                        purposes of publication and data management, we need to think of the edition
                        as its own unit and manage its evolution.</note> Versioning, as I use the
                    term, means assigning version identifiers to public materials as they develop;
                    it is a publication practice rather than a critical practice.</p>
                <p>That leaves the practical problem (unresolved by textual-critical theories of
                    versions, which focus on more complicated analyses) of how to communicate the
                    state of the edition to its users, whether humans or software programs. Existing
                    publishing practices a not great help. Print publication simply has not
                    developed conventions for describing ongoing revisions. Minor errors discovered
                    after printing might be dealt with by issuing a list of errata; a more thorough
                    revision might occasion the publication of a new edition. This publishing logic
                    features in the closest the TEI Guidelines come to addressing the versioning of
                    texts. The <code>&lt;editionStmt&gt;</code> section of the TEI header groups
                    together information about an “edition” of a TEI-encoded text <ptr
                        target="#TEI2019" loc="§2.2.2"/>. The Guidelines link the intellectual
                    foundations of the concept of edition to the idea of a <q>master copy</q>, while
                    simultaneously noting that the concept does not really apply to electronic
                    texts. Nevertheless, the primacy of the print concept of edition leads the
                    Guidelines to distinguish between <quote rend="inline">substantive
                        changes</quote> (such as the encoding of new information throughout the
                    file) and <quote rend="inline">minor changes . . . which do not amount to a new
                        edition</quote> (such as error corrections or conversation between
                    encodings) — a distinction that the Guidelines themselves acknowledge to be
                    somewhat arbitrary and subjective. These <quote rend="inline">minor
                        changes</quote> can be recorded in <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code>, but
                    there is no mechanism for labeling them. Confusing the issue still more, the
                    Guidelines treat edition as synonymous with version, level, and release, while
                    using the terms revision and update for minor changes below the level of
                    edition. Finally, the Guidelines offer two rather different ways of recording
                    version information in the same element. The edition (or version) can be
                    recorded either descriptively, with a phrase like <q>new edition</q> as the
                    content of the <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code> element, or with a <quote
                        rend="inline">formal identification (such as a version number) for the
                        edition</quote> in the <code>@n</code> attribute. The Guidelines introduce a
                    concept broadly similar to the print concept of edition, but one that lacks the
                    technical underpinnings (the setting of type) that gave the concept its meaning
                    in print, and that lacks the expressive power for dealing with digital
                    textuality in a comprehensive way.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Technical Versioning</head>
                <p>The shortcomings of the TEI’s print-inspired model suggest that we might look
                    elsewhere for models to describe changes in computer-encoded data files with
                    sufficient granularity. The field of software development has, over a period of
                    decades, developed software version numbers as a system of practice for tracking
                    the development of complex, digital objects — pieces of software — as they are
                    published and revised. Software version numbers also situate the objects they
                    describe in their developmental histories, but from the inside: rather than
                    analytically describing objects after the fact, they are assigned during the
                    development and release process to track ongoing work. Software version numbers
                    facilitate many kinds of reference: they track changes to a piece of software,
                    help users know when updates are available, facilitate technical support by
                    unambiguously identifying a particular state of that software with all its
                    particularities, and promote interoperability by allowing computer programs to
                    determine whether they are compatible. Despite its straighforwardness, software
                    versioning is a rich signifying practice, and it offers a model that suggests
                    practical solutions for editors of digital editions.</p>
                <p>Version numbers, at their most basic, delineate stages in the development of an
                    object — for instance, a piece of software — by quantifying them and assigning
                    ordered numbers to the object. It would be possible in principle to use a single
                    whole number, which increases with every change. However, this approach, which
                    fails to distinguish the scope of the changes that have been made, is
                    insufficient for dealing with complex software objects. It is instead common
                    practice to subdivide the version number into parts according to the scale of
                    the difference from what has come before. The most common approach is to segment
                    the version number, using a period to divide the parts. Version numbers with
                    either two or three segments are common. A piece of software with version 2.7.4
                    would thus signify major version 2, minor version 7, revision or patch
                        4.<note>In general, the individual numbers making up each segment are
                        independent integers, so that 3.11.15 is a valid version number with major
                        version 3, minor version 11, revision or patch 15.</note> (The meanings of
                    the first two numbers are typically major and minor version; what, exactly,
                    later numbers communicate is less consistent, though they often indicate small
                    revisions intended to fix errors without adding features or altering
                    behavior.)</p>
                <p>The meanings of these sequences are not fixed; different software creators are
                    free to construct their version numbers in different ways, and there are no
                    universal criteria for distinguishing major and minor releases — although some
                    recent efforts, which I will discuss, have attempted to make version numbers
                    more systematically intelligible. But broadly, major version releases are likely
                    to introduce significant changes to a product: for instance, a new user
                    interface, a large set of new capabilities, or technical changes that make files
                    produced with the new version incompatible with previous versions. Minor
                    versions might introduce features that do not substantially alter the nature of
                    the product, or correct problems that have been discovered. Smaller releases,
                    like patches, are likely to fix individual errors.</p>
                <p>This way of conceptualizing versions is at heart hierarchical, with each level in
                    effect <q>containing</q> those below it. In general, bumping the version number
                    at any level resets all the levels below it to zero, so that, for instance, the
                    major release that follows 2.4.7 is given version number 3.0.0. Conceptually,
                    the life of a major version consists of all the releases under that major
                    version number, not just the original point zero release. This hierarchy roughly
                    parallels the way the edition–impression–issue–state model subdivides the
                    bibliographic object (see <ref target="#bowers2005">Bowers (2005), 37-42,
                        406-411</ref>; <ref target="#tanselle1975">Tanselle (1975)</ref>). An
                    edition, in bibliographical terms, is created whenever a given text is typeset;
                    setting new type constitutes a fundamental change in the essence of the object
                    even if the text remains unchanged. A new edition is a kind of new major
                    version, an object that on some level shares identity with what came before but
                    also represents a significant break. Other categories are grouped beneath this,
                    expressing different levels of identity change with an edition subdivided into
                    impressions (the copies printed at once) and impressions divided into issues
                    (copies intended as a unit of sale) (see <ref target="#tanselle1975">Tanselle
                        (1975), 28n14</ref>). Sheets of books even get <q>patches</q>, changes
                    correcting individual errors; in his attempts to distinguish issue from state,
                    Fredson Bowers suggests that minor textual corrections, along with small
                    supplements, produce only new states and not new issues because they are simply
                        <quote rend="inline">delayed attempts to construct an <q>ideal
                        copy</q></quote>, much as software patches do not seek to extend
                    functionality or change intended behavior but merely make the software conform
                    to existing expectations <ptr target="#bowers2005" loc="67"/>.</p>
                <p>The point, of course, is not that software versioning and bibliographic
                    description map the same procedures to different media. Each practice is
                    informed by different practical needs, disciplinary contexts, and underlying
                    technologies. Rather, I wish to point to a broad correspondence in approach
                    between the two procedures, even though they bear different relationships to
                    their subject matter: both organize intellectual objects hierarchically,
                    categorizing and subdividing around questions of essential identity and of
                    imagined ideal state.</p>
                <p>But bibliographic classification, as an analytical practice, is rooted in the
                    evidence of specific changes. Software versioning, by contrast, has been accused
                    of being arbitrary and inconsistent — and at times of being driven by market
                    forces rather than technological logic. A few efforts to make versioning
                    practices more consistently meaningful help clarify what version numbers can
                    actually assert about an object.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Calendar Versioning</head>
                <p>One approach to versioning software, which has been called Calendar Versioning,
                    highlights the temporality of releases <ptr target="#hashemi2019"/>.<note>The
                        CalVer proposal was released in 2016, but as the authors note, the practices
                        they describe predate the document. Rather than trying to impose a standard
                        format, the CalVer convention seeks to provide a common vocabulary and
                        expose influential practices.</note> This approach recognizes that knowing
                    when a software object was released may be the most important way to identify
                    and evaluate it. Microsoft has offered the most widely visible version of this
                    practice, with releases like Windows 95, 98, and 2000. (It is worth noting,
                    however, that these are merely public release names and the software actually
                    carries a different version number distinct from the release name.) But a
                    variety of other software uses Calendar Versioning in less dramatic ways: the
                    Ubuntu Linux distribution, for instance, offers what look like fairly
                    traditional version numbers, but the first segment of the version numbers is the
                    last two digits of the current year, followed by the month, so that as of the
                    time of writing, the most recent version (released in April 2019) is 19.04. This
                    approach has appealed to at least one digital editor; the texts edited by
                    Jeffrey C. Witt from Peter Plaoul’s commentary on Peter Lombard’s Sentences
                    carry version numbers that employ a form of Calendar Versioning, as detailed in
                        <ref target="#appendix1">the Appendix</ref>.</p>
                <p>In emphasizing date as what identifies an object, calendar versioning resembles
                    scholarly citation practices, which emphasize publication dates, and sometimes
                    access dates — although calendrical version numbers clearly and uniquely
                    identify particular resource states, as access dates do not. Calendar Versioning
                    privileges temporal sequence above all else; it suggests that when an object was
                    produced is the most salient information for assessing it. It also establishes a
                    sequence of versions, chiefly by relating them in time. Thus, Calendar
                    Versioning is effective for allowing users to assess the age of a particular
                    resource, to understand which versions were produced earlier and later, and to
                    determine whether a more recent version is available. But it does not indicate
                    not scope: it is impossible to tell from version numbers alone whether two
                    versions are differentiated by the correction of a minor error or by a
                    significant overhaul.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Semantic Versioning</head>
                <p>Even generic versioning practices have tended to make the degree of difference
                    among versions greater than in Calendar Versioning, differentiating major and
                    minor versions according to the relative degree of change. However, these
                    approaches have appeared inconsistent to some critics: different developers or
                    companies make different decisions regarding what constitutes minor and major
                    versions, and these decisions are sometimes driven by market forces as a new
                    major version might generate excitement or drive customers to upgrade. The
                    Semantic Versioning specification, created by Tom Preston-Werner, is an attempt
                    to specify rigorously and technically what version numbers (or, more precisely,
                    what changes in version numbers) actually mean <ptr target="#preston-werner"
                        />.<note>Ironically, at the time of writing, the Semantic Versioning
                        specification suffers from its own versioning problems; the version cited
                        differs in two minor details from the version available at <ref
                            target="https://semver.org/">https://semver.org/</ref> (archived at <ref
                            target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230500/https://semver.org/"
                            >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230500/https://semver.org/</ref>),
                        though both are labeled as version 2.0.0.</note> I will dwell slightly
                    longer on Semantic Versioning, because it has provoked a debate that exposes a
                    fundamental question not merely of how versions should be identified but what
                    versioning is for — a debate that helps expose for the creators of digital
                    editions the role that versioning practices might play in communicating with the
                    public and interfacing with larger systems.</p>
                <p>Semantic versioning is based on the traditional [major].[minor].[patch] format,
                    but attempts to codify something largely implicit but inconsistently practiced
                    in community practices for giving version numbers to software: that the
                    different portions of a version number reflect different kinds of change.
                    Semantic versioning is most concerned with libraries and packages (that is,
                    pieces of software designed to be used by other pieces of software), and
                    specifically with what are called their APIs (Applications Programming
                    Interfaces): the formal methods through which other programs interact with the
                    package. (It is worth noting, however, that the Semantic Versioning
                    specification is itself semantically versioned; the application of these
                    principles is not restricted to packages or libraries.)</p>
                <p>Semantic Versioning is primarily concerned with whether changes to a package
                    break backwards compatibility. That is, have you changed the way your API works
                    so that the same command, issued to the new version, will produce different
                    results? The central principle is that any breaking change to the API (that is,
                    one that will cause the same command to have different results) is a new major
                    version. A release that adds new functions while maintaining backwards
                    compatibility is a new minor version, while a patch version is one that simply
                    fixes bugs, provided the fix does not break backwards compatibility. Semantic
                    versioning is designed especially for use with package managers, programs that
                    can automate procuring and updating the packages needed to build or run a piece
                    of software.</p>
                <p>Semantic Versioning sits especially uneasily at the intersection of intellectual
                    and mechanistic understandings of versioning. Jeremy Ashkenas, an influential
                    JavaScript developer and vocal critic of Semantic Versioning, argues that the
                    system <quote rend="inline">prioritize[s] a mechanistic understanding of a
                        codebase over a human one. . . . It’s alright for robots, but bad for
                        us</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ashkenas2015"/>.<note>In light of this article’s argument, it is
                        worth pointing out that Ashkenas posted his manifesto to GitHub’s Gist
                        service, which versions files using Git. The document has been revised
                        several times since its creation, and the hash in the URL allows me to link
                        to a particular state of the document, but does not provide a way to signal
                        how the state I cite (the most recent at the time of writing) relates to
                        other states.</note> Ashkenas suggests that, in an environment where other
                    developers may write source code relying on a project’s bugs, the definition of
                    a <q>breaking</q> change is subjective — a point others contest. Perhaps most
                    significantly for Ashkenas and other detractors, small function changes might
                    under Semantic Versioning require an increase in the major version number (say,
                    from 2.3.1 to 3.0.0) — a change that implies a major rethinking of the software
                    that may not, in fact, exist (and can cause version numbers to balloon).
                    Ashkenas agitates in favor of what others disparagingly call <q>Sentimental
                        Versioning</q> and he playfully labels <quote rend="inline">Romantic
                        Versioning</quote>: a system under which a developer’s understanding of the
                    magnitude of the change and the relationship between versions defines the
                    version number.<note>For a satiric presentation of <q>sentimental
                        versioning</q>, see <ref target="#tarr">Tarr (n.d.)</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The crux of the debate around Ashkenas’s rejection of Semantic Versioning, which
                    riled a community of developers whose projects were affected by an update that
                    Ashkenas declined to label a new major version, is whether version numbers are
                    intended for human or machine consumption. Software processes that decide
                    whether it is safe to update a given library do not care what a developer’s
                    sense of the change is; humans, on the other hand, may be misled by seeing a
                    major release that actually consists of a conceptually minor change.</p>
                <p>Why should scholars at the intersection of physical book study and digital
                    scholarship be concerned with a four-year-old squabble among software
                    developers, much of which involved how developer practices integrate with
                    automated systems? The Semantic Versioning debate is particularly interesting
                    for digital textuality because it draws attention to the different kinds of
                    weight that version information can carry, and the different systems into which
                    it integrates. Software developer Niels Roesen Abildgaard has attempted to
                    nuance the Semantic Versioning debate by suggesting that software exists on a
                    continuum between interfaces directly with users and interfaces exclusively with
                    other software; user-facing software, like games or (to a lesser extent) desktop
                    applications, is most suitable for Romantic Versioning, since human
                    understanding is paramount, while software libraries would benefit from Semantic
                    Versioning because relatively few humans will look at them directly, but they
                    will often be included in other software systems <ptr target="#abilgaard2015"/>.
                    The Semantic/Romantic debate draws our attention to the fact that version
                    numbers provide an interface for understanding software changes, and that this
                    interface is conditioned by purpose and audience: a key insight for considering
                    how users of digital editions might interact with version numbers and what
                    information they can convey.</p>
                <p>The focus on versioning as a communicative interface, designed to work in a
                    system with a clear audience to satisfy a defined purpose, helps us understand
                    the complexity of digital editions as objects to be versioned. Digital editions
                    operate within multiple systems at once. They are typically created first and
                    foremost as objects for <emph>reading</emph>, to be studied closely by
                    individuals. They are also sources of data, furnishing both character data and
                    metadata that can be manipulated and analyzed in a variety of ways. And they are
                    objects of citation, which must be unambiguously referenced in scholarly
                    environments. McDonough et al. point out that people using and analyzing digital
                    objects for different purposes may have profoundly different (though
                    interrelated) needs in terms of how they are categorized <ptr
                        target="#mcdonough2010" loc="§18"/>.</p>
                <p>Moreover, digital editions are complex, layered objects. At base, they consist of
                    one or more transcriptions or constructed texts, which may have been collated or
                    further analyzed to produce altered texts. In most cases, these texts have been
                    encoded using a markup language to identify features, define structure, and
                    incorporate metadata; at the level of information, they are accompanied by
                    products of scholarly analysis, such as a critical apparatus and various
                    annotations. And in most cases, they are accessed through a software interface
                    for reading, which may well be unique to the edition or project in question, and
                    perhaps through APIs that provide data upon request. Even if the content of the
                    edition began life encapsulated in a manageable format like a single XML file,
                    the reading interface will encompass a multitude of files and technologies, like
                    CSS and JavaScript files executed on a user’s computer and other processes, such
                    as XSLT transformations, that may occur on a server entirely out of a user’s
                    sight (so that the user may not even directly receive the underlying data files
                    without requesting them). Any APIs the edition provides will operate similarly,
                    extracting and transforming data to answer the requests it receives.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Describing Electronic Literature</head>
                <p>Given the complexity of digital editions as textual objects, one place we might
                    turn for more robust ways to describe them as temporal, bibliographic objects is
                    work done by electronic literature scholars in classifying and categorizing
                    their materials. (Digital editions are indeed a form of electronic literature,
                    albeit one that has not attracted much study outside the field of editorial
                    theory.) Matthew Kirschenbaum in a 2002 article postulated a set of terms for
                    describing first-generation electronic objects inspired by Bowers’s classic
                    bibliographical typology <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2002"/>. Layer, version, and
                    release refer to the whole software object — another hierarchy. Layer refers to
                    a whole integrated environment of software and data; adding a brand new software
                    interface, for example, might constitute a new layer. <term>Version</term> is
                    somewhat subordinate to layer and describes the life sequence of the software; a
                    new layer creates a new major version, while refining an existing layer creates
                    a new minor version. <term>Release</term> seems to be primarily a matter of
                    distribution channel: releases are <quote rend="inline">computationally
                        compatible . . . but . . . not functionally integrated</quote>, and
                    Kirschenbaum’s example is of a work released both online and on CD-ROM
                    (presumably with the same underlying software) <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2002"
                        loc="48"/>.</p>
                <p>Within the total software object so described are individual objects — individual
                    digital entities. Kirschenbaum offers a file as an example of an object, but it
                    is worth noting that Kirschenbaum’s objects are independent of the data format
                    in which they are stored. These are described by <term>states</term>: <quote
                        rend="inline">the computational composition of an object in some particular
                        data format.</quote> For example, separate PNG and JPEG files representing
                    the same image are different states of the same underlying object. Instance
                    exists at the interplay between state and the software environment in which it
                    operates: an image displayed in a particular program, which might (intentionally
                    or inadvertently) render it differently from other programs. And finally, there
                    is <term>copy</term>, a single instance of a state of an object, for example,
                    the copy of an image that a web browser downloads and stores on a user’s
                    computer (as distinct from the copy on the server).</p>
                <p>I rehearse this categorization at length because it represents a particularly
                    thorough and robust attempt to think through the distinctive properties of
                    electronic objects, and it, too, points to some of the properties we must
                    consider when evaluating digital editions. Kirschenbaum’s seven-part system is
                    certainly too detailed and cumbersome to be used as a versioning system in
                    itself — though a refined version, adapted for the era of networked publishing,
                    might ultimately prove valuable when scholars of future decades write
                    bibliographic accounts of digital editions. But his approach might suggest what
                    sorts of features versioning needs to account for.</p>
                <p>From the perspective of digital editions, the central insight of Kirschenbaum’s
                    proposal is his distinction between the whole software environment and the
                    individual components that compose it. An electronic text, consisting of both
                    data and a technical environment in which that data is remediated for a reader,
                    cannot usefully be described in total; media objects simultaneously precede
                    their instantiation in a particular technical environment and become entangled
                    in the systems that display them. Kirschenbaum applied this schema to works of
                    electronic literature; those discussed in his account appear to have evolved in
                    relatively well-defined, separable releases that can be thought of as an issue
                    of all parts at once. His descriptive vocabulary seems to reflect this tendency:
                    terms addressing the whole software environment are concerned with evolution,
                    while those concerned with individual objects are concerned with
                    instantiation.</p>
                <p>This particular division would work well for describing digital editions of the
                    CD-ROM era, where the production of physical copies created a distinct issue of
                    the whole, including both data and display software. But versioning all the
                    parts together appears less appropriate for the <q>continuous publishing</q>
                    practices of the web era, where individual components (and most importantly
                    individual documents) may be updated independently, not to mention the
                    prevalence of digital editions in large archives containing many documents, and
                    even in semi-distributed systems like Jeffrey Witt’s Scholastic Commentary and
                    Text Archive (SCTA), which promises to aggregate related, interoperable editions
                        <ptr target="#witt"/>
                    <ptr target="#witt2018"/>. If Peter Boot and Joris van Zundert are correct that
                    distributed, networked systems combining many data sources and services are the
                    future of digital editions (<q>the digital edition 2.0</q>, as they call it),
                    versioning all the components of an edition as a single unit may well become
                    completely impossible <ptr target="#boot2011"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Versioning Object and Environment</head>
                <p>Accordingly, rather than versioning whole systems, we should offer separate
                    treatment of objects and environments. <term>Objects</term>, here, are the
                    edition content: the texts or other resources being presented online, as
                    represented in the edition (<emph>not</emph> the physical objects being edited).
                        <term>Environment</term> describes the whole system within which these
                    objects are rendered and consumed: a web of server-side and client-side
                    electronic processes that work in tandem with a user’s local computer
                    environment to display an edition, or that provide data to other systems upon
                        request.<note>Boot and van Zundert stress the importance of versioning the
                        individual resources within the edition-networks they imagine, and suggest
                        that the systems for managing data and services should even handle the
                        versioning of platform infrastructure such as the operating systems on which
                        technical services may depend <ptr target="#boot2011" loc="148"/>.</note>
                    Put another way: objects are the underlying data, the textual and editorial
                    content that editors create and incorporate into the edition, regardless of the
                    specifics (technical or visual) of its realization. Environment encompasses the
                    interfaces through which that data is made available to users (the visual layout
                    of an edition on the screen, APIs that permit machine-driven access to edition
                    data), as well as the software environments that enable these forms of
                            access.<note><ref target="#witt2018">Witt (2018)</ref> argues for making
                        APIs the foundational avenues of data access and for constructing user
                        interfaces as applications that consume data through APIs — if adopted at
                        scale, an elegant approach to multiplicity and reuse.</note></p>
                <p>In arguing for the separation of object from interface, I do not mean to imply
                    that interfaces are <q>mere</q> technical contributions, separate from the
                    intellectual work of editing.<note>See <ref target="#badley2012">Bradley
                            (2012)</ref> for one critique of the marginalization of collaborators
                        with technical expertise as <q>techies</q>, which Bradley argues improperly
                        reduces technical contributions to <quote rend="inline">support work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bradley2012" loc="11"/> rather than recognizing the important
                        intellectual contributions and innovations that all partners bring to the
                        table. Bradley specifically notes the importance of <quote rend="inline"
                            >blending of the understanding of the materials with which one is
                            working with an understanding of how to exploit the technology to
                            emphasize what is important</quote> as one important area of partnership
                            <ptr target="#bradley2012" loc="14"/>. I hope it will be clear that the
                        separation of versioning I propose is not meant to downplay the intellectual
                        importance of the technological components, either from the perspective of
                        labor or from the perspective of scholarly resources.</note> Nor am I
                    suggesting that a reader or user of an edition can experience content in some
                    pure way, uninflected by the way it is presented. The layout (interface) even of
                    traditional print editions constitutes an argument about the material and its
                    character <ptr target="#eggert2013"/>. The vaunted flexibility of digital
                    editions means an edition may contain and present its material in multiple ways,
                    indeed, through quite different interfaces, yet these interfaces will
                    inescapably condition the material and make arguments about understanding it
                        <ptr target="#andrews2018"/>. Certainly, the form in which a text is
                    encountered conditions understandings of that text, and citing the environment
                    in which it is encountered will be necessary both to understanding conclusions
                    drawn from the edition and to recognizing intellectual contributions to
                        it.<note> A related problem exists in the study of videogames, where many
                        older games are experienced using emulators and researched through ROM files
                        extracted from original media by third parties. For a discussion of the
                        bibliographic description of such objects, see <ref target="#altice2015"
                            >Altice (2015), 333-341</ref>, which argues among other things that
                        videogame scholars should cite even the emulators they use to examine such
                        files.</note></p>
                <p>Despite the entanglement of content and presentation for scholarly understanding,
                    versioning objects separately from their environments has both intellectual and
                    practical benefits. One influential idea in software design, and key principle
                    of the modern web, is the separation of form and content: the principle that
                    documents should be encoded according to their underlying structural logic,
                    without intermixing instructions regarding how that content is to be
                        displayed.<note>For example, in modern web development, the accepted best
                        practice is for the structure of the document to specified in HTML, while
                        formatting is applied using CSS. For a discussion of this principle, see
                            <ref target="#berners-lee1998">Berners-Lee (1998)</ref>. In the context
                        of digital editing, see <ref target="#pichler2014">Pichler and Bruvik
                            (2014)</ref>.</note> The separation of form and content has
                    understandably been drawn into question by scholars gesturing toward the
                    outpouring of work on the materiality of text.<note>For a critique of the
                        separation from the standpoint of textual studies, see <ref
                            target="#galey2010">Galey (2010), 110-114</ref>.</note> Nevertheless,
                    this distinction operates at a technical level in many digital editions, and
                    offers a model by which digital editions may be implemented and preserved. The
                    TEI guidelines, perhaps the most common standard for textual encoding of digital
                    editions (see <ref target="#franzini2019">Franzini et al. (2019), 16</ref>),
                    endorse and support the separation of form and content.<note>The TEI Guidelines
                        credit this separation as a characteristic of the XML encoding language,
                        which emphasizes <q>descriptive</q> rather than <q>procedural</q> markup:
                        that is, the markup categorizes pieces of a document according to what they
                        mean or the structural purpose they serve rather than according to how they
                        should be formatted; the formatting of a published document should be
                        accomplished through other mechanisms <ptr target="#TEI2019" loc="§v.1"/>.
                        That is not to say that the TEI Guidelines lack any facilities for
                        describing the appearance of texts, but the Guidelines stress that
                        components related to visual appearance are intended to describe a source
                        document, not its desired output appearance (§1.3.1.1.3), and note that
                        markup describing the visual features of a source document is descriptive
                        markup (§v.2).</note> C. M. Sperberg-McQueen has gone so far as to suggest
                    that it is a best practice for digital editions to provide multiple interfaces,
                    not just to support multiple ways of interacting with the text but also to force
                    editors to make sure they are not basing their encoding on desired display
                    rather than the logic of the content <ptr target="#sperberg-mcqueen2009"
                        loc="35–36"/>. While others might argue for tighter control over the
                    presentation of an edition as an editorial responsibility,<note><ref
                            target="#régnier2015">Régnier (2014), 76</ref>, argues that <quote
                            rend="inline">philologists can . . . be held responsible for the
                            functional and aesthetic quality of the digital framework to which they
                            entrust their work</quote> and insists that <quote rend="inline">they
                            have to collaborate on the invention of digitized text standards</quote>
                        like the visual codes that coalesced as standards for print
                        scholarship.</note> the edition content and presentation are still
                    technically and intellectually separable even when they are thought of as
                    forming a single intellectual unit. Put another way: Sperberg-McQueen
                    distinguishes among the infinite array of facts concerning a particular text,
                    the selection of facts that are contained as information within a particular
                    edition, and the presentation of those facts, for instance through arrangement
                    on the screen. The selection of facts — the total information content available
                    in an edition, whether exposed in a particular form or not — exists, as encoded
                    data, apart from the mechanisms that present those facts, even where the
                    selection of facts and the development of the user interface have informed each
                    other and where they are intended to go together <ptr
                        target="#sperberg-mcqueen2009" loc="31"/>.<note>Sperberg-McQueen declares
                        that the selection and presentation together constitute the interface of an
                        edition. I use the term interface differently, to refer to a mechanism
                        through which the edition exposes its information, whether displaying it
                        visually through a graphical user interface (GUI) or exposing it to other
                        computer programs by means of an application programming interface
                        (API).</note> Unless a creator goes to extreme lengths, against all norms of
                    software design, to create a boutique piece of software in which data and
                    display are fully entangled, it is likely that any digital edition (regardless
                    of the standards or ad-hoc principles followed) will contain data objects that
                    can be meaningfully versioned apart from their display systems.</p>
                <p>Moreover, at a practical level, objects and environments are likely to evolve
                    separately, both before and after an edition is published. An editor who learns
                    of an error in a reading can correct it by making a change in a data file; in
                    many online publishing environments, no further action will be required for the
                    correction to appear in the edition.<note>Other platforms might require the
                        edition’s maintainers to perform some action to update the data file’s
                        derivatives, for example running a script to generate new HTML files for web
                        display by applying an XSLT transformation to a source XML file. Only if the
                        edition is exceptionally tightly packaged is it likely that the software of
                        the edition must also be regenerated, and even if it is, the resulting
                        display software will not be materially different.</note> Similarly, the
                    developers and maintainers of digital editions can often make changes from
                    tweaking the text styling to rearranging the graphical user interface to adding
                    major new features for textual analysis without altering the data files.
                    Versioning data objects can also aid preservation. Because the underlying data
                    in most edition objects is at heart textual, data files can be relatively easily
                    archived in repositories designed for storing texts, like the Oxford Text
                    Archive <ptr target="#OTA"/> and TextGrid <ptr target="#TGC2006"/>. Depositing
                    an edition’s data is not the same as preserving the edition, and work on the
                    preservation of the interfaces should continue (informed by work in the field of
                    software preservation), but such deposits can help allow the labor represented
                    by an edition to live on as data even if its software becomes
                        inaccessible.<note>For an introductory overview to issues of digital
                        preservation, see <ref target="#kilbride2016">Kilbride (2016)</ref>. For a
                        discussion focused on digital editions, see <ref target="#deegan2006">Deegan
                            (2006)</ref>. In combining text with (sometimes custom-built) software
                        interfaces, digital editions present problems closely related to those
                        involving other electronic literature. <ref target="#liu2005">Liu et al.
                            (2005)</ref> argue for the value of creating an XML-based format that
                        can make content and portions of the experience of such works available even
                        where the full experience cannot be recreated due to the obsolescence of
                        software or hardware.</note></p>
                <p>As publishing practices evolve, being able to refer to objects separate from
                    their environments may increasingly become a practical necessity. Boot and van
                    Zundert’s vision of a networked, distributed <quote rend="inline">digital
                        edition 2.0</quote> involves bringing data together with services offered by
                    different providers, and they explicitly argue that editions should not provide
                    their own <quote rend="inline">advanced services</quote>
                    <ptr target="#boot2011" loc="144"/>. Users of digital editions may already be
                    prepared to work with data apart from interfaces; in a recent survey about
                    digital editions, a majority of respondents rated the ability to download and
                    reuse data from editions <quote rend="inline">very important</quote>
                    <ptr target="#franzini2019" loc="15"/>. Even without such a shared
                    infrastructure, thinking separately about object and interface helps prepare us
                    for the future agitated for by Peter Robinson, where digital editors abandon the
                    practice of providing their own interfaces and leave textual display to others
                        <ptr target="#robinson2013"/>. Increasingly, those working in the field of
                    digital editing recognize the value of publication frameworks and software
                    packages that allow editors to present their work without having to develop
                    entirely new software.<note>See, for example, <ref target="#turska2016">Turska
                            et al. (2016)</ref>, which argues that encoded data are the most
                        important output of editing projects but suggests that editors are concerned
                        with presentation and so lowering the barriers to publication will help them
                        get down to the business of creating data.</note> Alternative environments
                    need not be software systems; as discussed below, the <title rend="italic">Piers
                        Plowman Electronic Archive</title> has begun publishing printed volumes
                    produced from its XML data, providing paper-based access to the edition.
                    Versioning objects and environment separately means that our versioning
                    practices can recognize the intellectual identity between an encoded document
                    (for example, an XML file in the TEI vocabulary) and its rendering (for example,
                    its rendering as an HTML page as a result of an XSLT transformation). They
                    remain the same object, even if the mediating layers change.<note><ref
                            target="#gants2010">Gants (2010), 133-134</ref>, considering the issues
                        involved in describing a work of interactive fiction that takes the form of
                        a computer program, proposes a similar identity. Using Bowers’s
                        bibliographic framework, Gants compares the source code for the game to a
                        single setting of type; compiling the game into executable code that will
                        run on separate operating systems, he suggests, is analogous to reimposition
                        in other formats.</note></p>
                <p>Although the remainder of this article focuses on versioning data objects,
                    versioning software environments (including the web platforms that display
                    digital editions) is also important for the future health of the digital
                    scholarly ecosystem, and should be an area of further work for the field. A
                    FORCE11 working group has emphasized the importance of scholars citing the
                    software they use in their research, for reasons of credit, provenance, and
                    reproducibility, and has indicated that one goal of software citation should be
                    to identify and facilitate access to a specific version of the software <ptr
                        target="#smith2016"/>. Although the primary focus of software citation
                    movements has been software executed locally by researchers, such principles
                    might furnish a starting place for citation of web-based environments in which
                    the contents of digital editions are accessed. Publishers of digital editions
                    might facilitate such citations by assigning their online software platforms
                    specific version numbers, incremented with every update, even when the web
                    interface is specific to a single project. Researchers citing a digital edition
                    might then cite both the data underlying the edition and the platform in which
                    they accessed the edition. Publishers might also consider making the source code
                    of online platforms available under open source licenses, potentially enabling
                    future researchers to recreate an earlier version of an online platform that has
                    since been updated or discontinued. Of course, such steps are at best partial.
                    The ways in which a user experiences the data mediated by an online edition
                    platform depend not merely on website code, but on underlying elements of the
                    web architecture (such as the specific versions of software running on the web
                    server) and on features of a user’s own computer, such as operating system, web
                    browser, and specific settings. Research into the preservation and curation of
                    software as a part of the scholarly record is ongoing, and as the field of
                    digital editing and publication continues to mature, it will need to become
                    involved in these broader conversations.<note>For an overview of the importance
                        and challenges of software preservation and curation and a discussion of the
                        role research libraries might play, see <ref target="#chassanoff2018"
                            >Chassanoff et al. (2018)</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>But there is lower-hanging fruit for editors and publishers of scholarly
                    editions, who have yet to develop standards for the comparatively
                    straightforward versioning of edition contents, standards that would benefit the
                    field of scholarly editing. Versioning the contents of digital editions would
                    represent a significant step forward for citeability and preservation of the
                    scholarly record even while difficult issues regarding software environments
                    await future work. We can, and should, version the data objects that form the
                    information content of our digital editions, starting now.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Developing Versioning Protocols for <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman
                        Electronic Archive</title> Data Objects</head>
                <p>I will turn now to a case study based on my work in creating a formal versioning
                    policy for the <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman Electronic Archive</title>
                    (PPEA) <ptr target="#duggan2019"/>, an open-access online resource that aims to
                    document the complete medieval and early modern textual tradition of the Middle
                    English alliterative poem <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman</title> through
                    TEI-encoded documentary editions of individual witnesses and critical editions
                    of archetypal texts. This long-running project, which began in 1987,
                    demonstrates both the need for and the challenge of clear versioning
                        practices.<note>On the history of the PPEA, see <ref target="#knowles2014"
                            >Knowles and Stinson (2014)</ref>. On its early publication practices,
                        see <ref target="#duggan2005">Duggan and Lyman (2005)</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The first seven PPEA editions were published on CD-ROM, from 2000 to 2011, in
                    separate partnerships between the Society for Early English and Norse Electronic
                    Texts (SEENET) and the University of Michigan Press, Boydell and Brewer, and the
                    Medieval Academy of America. The first two CD-ROMs were encoded in SGML
                    presented using the proprietary Multidoc Pro SGML browser; later editions were
                    encoded in XML and published using software that ran within a web browser. In
                    2014, all texts were made openly available online, in a new web interface
                    created by the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the
                    University of Virginia. The new online <title rend="italic">Archive</title> saw
                    the release of previously unpublished editions; older editions were updated to
                    XML conforming to the P4 version of the TEI guidelines. Since 2014, intermittent
                    changes have been made to the appearance and function of the web editions.
                    Forthcoming updates will create additional versions of existing texts: the
                        <title rend="italic">Archive</title> is in the process of updating its texts
                    to TEI P5, and the newly launched PPEA in Print series publishes print volumes
                    derived from electronic texts.<note>The first volume of this series was
                        published in 2018: <ref target="#burrow2018">Burrow and Turville-Petre
                            (2018)</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>In addition to changes in medium, file format, and technical infrastructure, the
                    PPEA, like any project of its age and scope, has had to deal with errors in its
                    materials. The web versions of the texts were updated to correct known errors.
                    These changes were not explicitly recognized on the pages for the text. For
                    texts originally published on CD-ROM, the website used to provide Errata lists
                    recording corrections to the CD-ROM texts. However, these lists are no longer
                    maintained given the age of the CD-ROMs, and Errata lists were never created for
                    texts first published online. The corrections made to files spanned a wide range
                    of types and significances, including changes to the format of line numbers (but
                    not the lineation), minor changes to markup unlikely to affect the output on the
                    screen, and the correction of textual errors.</p>
                <p>As part of a CLIR Postdoctoral Fellowship in Data Curation for Medieval Studies
                    at the North Carolina State University Libraries, I set out to create standards
                    for assigning version numbers to texts. My primary goals were (1) to allow users
                    of the <title rend="italic">Archive</title> to record and cite unambiguously
                    which version of a text they consulted; (2) to permit previously published
                    versions of texts to be archived and retrieved; (3) to make the history of a
                    given text legible; and (4) to allow users with references to two versions of
                    the same text to have a basic understanding of the relationship between them.
                    From the start, I was concerned only with versioning published resources; while
                    we might use prerelease identifiers to track the evolution of unpublished
                    resources internally, what I sought to define was how we would assign version
                    numbers to editions beginning at the moment of their publication and
                    encompassing all successive published changes.<note>Publication, for our
                        purposes, means the official appearance of an edition on the public pages of
                        the PPEA website. Because in digital scholarship the lines between
                        unpublished and published materials have become increasingly blurred — many
                        editors and projects, including the PPEA, make draft materials available —
                        it may be appropriate to version prerelease materials as well, and similar
                        procedures could apply. However, in drawing a distinction between
                        unpublished and published materials, I emphasize that published materials
                        have been officially recognized as appropriate for reference and citation,
                        so users expect to be able to rely on it. Formal versioning practices
                        support that implicit contract with users.</note></p>
                <p>A few fundamental decisions guided my work. One early, crucial question was what
                    resource was actually being versioned. First, guided by Kirschenbaum’s work, I
                    concluded that edition content and the way that content is displayed cannot be
                    described by the same version numbers. While versioning our display software is
                    a long-term desideratum, my immediate goal was to version editions’
                    informational content. Accordingly, any version numbers we provided would have
                    to refer to the source files for an edition — in this case, the TEI-encoded XML
                    — rather than to its rendered text. The decision to privilege the XML made sense
                    as the XML files can be easily archived, and because it recognizes the markup of
                    an edition as a significant intellectual product. Versioning the XML files also
                    allows us to link them with any derivatives produced from them: derivatives
                    which can include not just electronic renderings but print volumes.<note><ref
                            target="#odonnell2008">O'Donnell (2008)</ref> uses the example of an
                        earlier SEENET publication of his edition of <title rend="italic">Cædmon’s
                            Hymn</title> to argue that print works can be outputs of digital
                        editing. For the current print series, volumes are produced by transforming
                        the XML source into LaTeX markup (which might be finessed by hand to improve
                        page layout). The LaTeX markup is compiled into a PDF, which is used to
                        print the physical volume. The physical book is thus the product of
                        transformations of the XML source, just like the web display. The copyright
                        page of the print book contains a statement of the version number from which
                        it was printed, asserting the identity between them.</note> For instance,
                    editions published in the PPEA in Print series carry a statement on the
                    copyright page declaring the version of the XML files to which the print text
                    corresponds.</p>
                <p>Choosing XML files as the objects of versioning has additional consequences. The
                    component files of an edition will be versioned separately. Each full edition
                    consists of, at minimum, separate XML files for the introduction and the edited
                    text. If the versioned objects are XML files, a change to the text does not
                    affect the status of the introduction. Even though the PPEA conceives of each
                    edition as a single coherent publication, and they are peer reviewed as integral
                    wholes, they are made up of separate data sources whose version histories must
                    be managed independently. (This is a more practical approach than creating data
                    packages versioned as a single unit because it allows us to include a file’s
                    version number within the file itself without having to modify files that have
                    not otherwise changed.)</p>
                <p>One more question concerned what resources must actually be versioned. The PPEA
                    website contains many pages with background information and supplementary
                    resources that are not part of individual editions — some of which, such as site
                    credits, may change frequently. Further, editions include files such as prefaces
                    that are not necessarily advancing the same sort of scholarly claims. At least
                    for the time being, I decided to version only content subject to peer review,
                    meaning the text, apparatus, and introductions of editions.</p>
                <p>Establishing some priority of changes that gives a sense of their scope is
                    essential to make version numbers useful. Thus I sought to distinguish changes
                    on the grounds of their scale and significance.<note>Inspired in part by the
                        careful and precise distinctions suggested by Semantic Versioning, I at
                        first attempted to theorize <q>breaking changes</q> for the digital edition,
                        trying to identify what kinds of change would render two states of the same
                        file <q>incompatible</q> with each other. However, I soon realized that
                        identifying <q>breaking changes</q> requires committing to a particular
                        theory of the digital edited text and the primary form of interface it
                        provides. People using the edition mainly as a documentary text will have
                        different concerns from those most interested in the editors’ arguments;
                        those studying dialect will prioritize different features from those
                        examining scribal decoration and again from scholars interested in markup
                        practices; readers working directly with the XML files will have a very
                        different experience of changes from the probable majority who are reading
                        through the mediation of a web interface. In the context of digital editing,
                        nearly every change is potentially a breaking change for someone (a claim
                        Ashkenas made even about many software packages).</note> Changes that
                    systematically affected the editorial or markup approaches to a file seemed to
                    constitute a highest level of change. A file’s markup might change completely —
                    it might, indeed, be recreated from the ground up in a new format (for instance
                    in HTML rather than XML) — without any differences being visible to users of the
                    edition. However, given the intellectual significance of the way a text is
                    marked up, these two files would be radically different from each other as data.
                    Accordingly, I reasoned, the conversion of a file from one markup language to
                    another (from SGML to XML, or between major versions of an encoding scheme, like
                    the transition from TEI P4 to P5) would constitute a major release (at the
                    highest level of versioning), because even if the intent is to keep the textual
                    content the same, the different affordances of different file formats and
                    encoding schemes mean that the nature of the file has fundamentally
                        changed.<note>On the intellectual and technical differences between P4 and
                        P5, see <ref target="#wittern2009">Wittern et al. (2009)</ref>, which
                        observes that one of the changes it discusses marks <quote rend="inline">a
                            fundamental change in the relationship between textual content and
                            markup</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wittern2009" loc="285"/>. Automated tools were developed to
                        aid the transition from P4 to P5, and for simple files those tools might
                        suffice, but the differences between P4 and P5 are sufficiently significant
                        that at the conversion requires careful assessment and may require manual
                        intervention. Because changes of this nature are interpretative, and
                        distributed throughout the document, they amount to a significant
                        overhaul.</note> A file modified in this way is incompatible with previous
                    versions in a concrete sense, because changed elements and structure mean that
                    the files can no longer be compared directly to each other by analytical tools
                    that process the underlying XML, and software that worked with earlier versions
                    may not display it successfully. (However, minor changes to how data is stored
                    or expressed, like a switch between minor versions of TEI or a change in
                    character encoding from ISO-8859-1 to UTF-8, maintain the fundamental identity
                    of the file and do not rise to the level of a major release.) Similarly,
                    systematic editorial revisions to a file, I suggested, would constitute a new
                    major release, because they represent a far-reaching editorial reassessment that
                    disrupts intellectual continuity with the existing version. In its relationship
                    to preceding material, a major release is in some ways comparable to a new
                    edition of a print book (marked by a new setting of type), or to a significant
                    version in the text-critical sense.</p>
                <p>Since one of the central goals of a digital edition is to present one or more
                    texts, any changes to readings are necessarily significant. I therefore proposed
                    that individual changes to the text that do not rise to the level of systematic
                    revision might constitute a middle level, less high than systematic changes but
                    greater than other forms of change. The concept of a <q>patch</q>, a change
                    intended only to correct an error and restore expected behavior, does not apply
                    to an edition, because edition contents may have been used as the grounds for
                    scholarly argument and the change from a mistaken reading to a correct one may
                    thus have great scholarly significance. If changes to text are regarded as the
                    more significant form of local change, then changes to paratext, including
                    editorial content, might be at the lowest level. These three levels of change
                    seemed well suited to the common three-level version number format. I therefore
                    initially proposed that version numbers take the following form: [systematic
                    changes to encoding or editing].[changes to text].[changes to paratext]. I
                    outlined the meanings of these segments as follows: <list type="unordered">
                        <item>The first segment, <hi rend="italic">systematic changes</hi>, would
                            increase when we make a large number of changes systematically across
                            the text that have a significant effect on its markup or on the how it
                            is edited as a whole.</item>
                        <item>The second segment, <hi rend="italic">changes to text</hi>, would
                            increase when we make any change to our representation of what is on the
                            page. Most obviously this includes alterations of readings, but it also
                            includes highlighting and other features present in the source
                            document.</item>
                        <item>The third segment, <hi rend="italic">changes to paratext</hi>, would
                            increase when we make changes to paratextual content that is not in the
                            source document, such as editorial notes and apparatus.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>This proposal sparked discussion with other project leaders. One specific point
                    of debate was the extent to which version numbers should reflect the file
                    history. Following the conventions of software versioning (and of bibliographic
                    classification), I proposed that when any segment of the version number changed,
                    all segments to the right should revert to zero. (So, for instance, version
                    2.1.3 might be followed by 3.0.0.) Our discussion raised the possibility that
                    this practice hid file history, as after a systematic change it would no longer
                    be clear how many changes to text or paratext had occurred. An alternate
                    proposal was that each segment would increment independently without being
                    reset, so that the number of changes of each type would be permanently visible.
                    That alternative proposal raised its own complications. For one, it deviates
                    from the practices typical of software version numbering, and so would likely
                    prove confusing to users: the practice of zeroing-out later segments is
                    culturally familiar not just from annual demands that we upgrade our phone
                    operating systems, but from its cultural currency in the form of phrases like
                        <q>web 2.0</q>. In addition, it creates a false impression of precision,
                    because any number of changes might be bundled into a single update to the file.
                    (For instance, a single update might include three separate alterations to the
                    text and two to the paratext, but the final two segments of the version number
                    would each increase only by one, concealing the actual number of changes.) And
                    there is in any case a hierarchical bibliographical logic to the major version’s
                    resetting the clock on other forms of revision: if a major version compares to a
                    new edition, such a significant change establishes a new baseline against which
                    less significant changes can be measured going forward.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most troubling aspect of three-level version numbers from the
                    perspective of the PPEA, however, was the realization that not all files that
                    need to be versioned can have changes at three levels. Files consisting purely
                    of editorial material, such as introductions, do not have distinct textual and
                    paratextual content in the manner of edited texts, and so version numbers would
                    have to express all changes to these files in either the text or paratext
                    segment, with the other segment remaining permanently at zero (or omitted
                    entirely). The idea of versioning different XML files according to different
                    principles, or of having a version number segment that would always remain zero
                    for some files, seemed too unwieldy. And, of course, for readers interacting
                    with and citing primarily editors’ comments, it is not necessarily the case that
                    changes to text will be the most significant changes.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, despite the potential advantages offered by three-part version
                    numbers, we ultimately elected to adopt a simpler, two-part system for version
                    numbers, in the form of [major version].[minor version], where the segments have
                    the following meanings: <list type="unordered">
                        <item>The first segment, <hi rend="italic">major version</hi>, increases
                            when we make a large number of changes systematically across the text
                            that have a significant effect on its markup or on the how it is edited
                            as a whole. Moving from P4 to P5 of the TEI protocols, which requires
                            non-trivial changes in markup across the text, is an example of a change
                            that would increase the number of the major version
                                segment.<note>However, some types of widespread changes do not rise
                                to the level of constituting a new major version, because they are
                                intellectually trivial and do not involve theories of the text or
                                its encoding. One example previously encountered by the project is
                                changing the format in which line numbers are written without
                                changing the numbers themselves.</note> The significance of any
                            program of changes must be assessed by the resource’s maintainers in
                            terms of the needs of the community that will use the resource, as the
                            Semantic Versioning debate suggests.</item>
                        <item>The second segment, <hi rend="italic">minor version</hi>, increases
                            when we make any other change. These include corrections to readings,
                            updates to notes or paratexts, modification of markup, or changes of any
                            other kind as long as they do not rise to the systematic, significant
                            status that would constitute a new major version.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Users in possession of an XML file should be able to determine the version from
                    that file, so the policy stipulates that wherever possible, the version number
                    should be recorded internally within the file to which it applies. In TEI
                    documents, we record the version number using the <code>@n</code> attribute
                    within the <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code> element in the
                        <code>&lt;editionStmt&gt;</code> section of the header. We also recommend
                    documenting the revision history of the file using <code>&lt;change&gt;</code>
                    elements within the <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code> section of the header; the
                    version number should be attached to each change newly introduced within a
                    particular version using the @n attribute on the <code>&lt;change&gt;</code>
                    entity. In this way, we can both identity particular states of files and
                    construct a human-readable history of how the file developed. Where version
                    numbers and change histories cannot practically be included in the file itself,
                    we will store them in a supplementary text file to be archived and distributed
                    with the data files.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The practices considered and developed by the PPEA offer a starting point for
                    versioning digital projects, laying out standards for what needs to be versioned
                    and how version numbers can make the status of files and their histories more
                    intelligible. Other projects, with different needs, materials, data formats, and
                    philosophies may need to develop different strategies in order to make their
                    material comprehensible and usable. Development of standard practices would
                    benefit the field of digital editing as a whole. And standards and mechanisms
                    for versioning will have to continue to evolve alongside ongoing developments in
                    the field of digital editing. The versioning protocol developed for the PPEA is
                    based on a document-driven paradigm of the digital edition — that is, on a model
                    in which key informational components of the edition are contained in individual
                    XML files, to which version numbers can be attached. But this model is a notably
                    simple one, even in the context of the TEI. XML documents need not be
                    self-contained; an XML document can virtually include content drawn dynamically
                    from other sources, a design pattern that Alan Liu terms “data pours” and finds
                    characteristic of the modern web <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="59–63"/>. Each
                    source file could be versioned individually, but the compound XML that is
                    processed to render the edition may never before have existed as a coherent
                    whole; such hybrid documents threaten a nearly endless proliferation of
                    versions, not to mention challenging technical measures to expose the version
                    number of each element. And more complicated paradigms may become increasingly
                    common in sophisticated digital editions of the future. For instance, in
                    editions developed according to the principles of <quote rend="inline"
                        >stand-off</quote> markup, there may be a <quote rend="inline"
                        >source</quote> document containing a core stream of textual data, designed
                    to work in tandem with various kinds of markup stored outside that document <ptr
                        target="#TEI2019" loc="§16.9"/>.<note>Desmond Schmidt argues that stand-off
                        markup is essential to interoperability and should become the dominant
                        approach to digital editing. In stand-off markup, a resource and its markup
                        might reside in different files, and depending on technical and procedural
                        approaches might have to be versioned separately. Stand-off markup also
                        complicates the notion of versioning because stand-off markup is entangled
                        with the text to which it is applied: though the markup may be stored
                        externally, changes to the <quote rend="inline">source</quote> document are
                        likely to necessitate corresponding changes to the stand-off annotations in
                        order to maintain their relationship. Schmidt’s discussion offers one
                        possible way forward: he describes his stand-off alternative to a
                        conventional document-based edition as a <quote rend="inline">bundle</quote>
                        of materials in separate files, and notes that this collection of files
                        might be stored in a single container files <ptr target="#schmidt2014"
                            loc="¶47–48"/>. An editorial bundle consisting of a <quote rend="inline"
                            >source</quote> document, stand-off files, and metadata might thus be
                        versioned as a single unit, in the same way that multiple research data
                        files may be combined into a data package consisting as multiple files,
                        versioned as one unit.</note> Some editions may even avoid storing data in
                    documents that map to a traditional file system, opting instead for databases or
                    other complex storage structures.<note>See for example <ref
                            target="#kuczera2016">Kuczera (2016)</ref>.</note> Versioning practices
                    will require ongoing consideration to keep pace with the shifting field. These
                    are conversations the digital editing community needs to begin to have.</p>
                <p>Until even an initial community consensus emerges, individual projects will have
                    to develop their own approaches to versioning their data — approaches that will
                    shift in tandem with their needs, infrastructures, material, and scale.
                    Accordingly, instead of a set of rules, I conclude with three principles that
                    can help to guide discussions about versions of texts: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Digital editions must version their underlying data and communicate
                            those versions to users, independent of how that data is displayed. This
                            is not the same as tracking file history in version control; nor is it
                            the same as the bibliographical analysis scholars of future generations
                            may want to perform. It is a declarative act in which digital editors
                            make assertions about the state of their work. Where editorial projects
                            offer reading interfaces or APIs, they should strongly consider
                            versioning their software environments, due to the complicated
                            technological interactions required to display a text. However,
                            versioning the data itself is of paramount importance. Wherever
                            possible, editions should provide direct access to their versioned data
                            (for example, in the form of TEI-encoded XML files) so that users can
                            examine the data directly, apart from its interface.</item>
                        <item>Versioning is social. As debates in the software community have
                            suggested, versioning is not an abstract concept, but is inherently tied
                            to <emph>use</emph>. Developing versioning principles will requires
                            editorial projects to have a use-model of their resources, one that
                            takes into account what kinds of changes are intellectually and
                            practically significant. This means, for instance, deciding what types
                            of object are fundamental to the resource and at what level they should
                            be versioned. (A single epigraph, or a corpus? Chapter or novel? Poem or
                            volume? The entire archive offered by a large project? Given both
                            creators and users, how should we understand the resource as
                            transforming?)</item>
                        <item>Digital editions must explicitly scope their revisions, delivering
                            version numbers that communicate with users (based on their needs) the
                            scale and significance of the change. It should be possible to
                            understand through version numbers not only what version of a resource
                            is most recent, but how <q>compatible</q> they are, how likely it is
                            that the differences have a significant impact on their intellectual
                            coherence or their probable uses. Both in individual projects and the
                            field of digital editing as a whole, we should develop explicit
                            guidelines that make these versions meaningful.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Kirschenbaum has claimed that despite the significant technical challenges of
                    digital preservation, its greatest challenges are <quote rend="inline"
                        >ultimately — and profoundly — social</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2008" loc="21"/>. The same, I would argue, is true of
                    the issues surrounding the evolution and internal histories of digital editions.
                    The field must begin to develop standards and practices for managing resource
                    histories — standards and practices that ideally should not be limited to any
                    one file format or encoding scheme, but can help organize data of many forms,
                    for many purposes, now and in the future. And other practices will need to
                    develop around those standards: for instance, support for versioning in emerging
                    APIs for digital scholarly text. Version numbers, I argue, can help meet these
                    needs, and it is time for digital editors to begin discussing and using
                    them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>My thanks to Timothy Stinson for his feedback on this article, and to Matthew
                    Kirschenbaum for his comments on an earlier version of this work. I am also
                    grateful to my many generous interlocutors at the BH and DH conference where I
                    first presented these ideas, and to anonymous reviewers at DHQ. This research
                    was made possible by the support of a CLIR Postdoctoral Fellowship in Data
                    Curation for Medieval Studies at the North Carolina State University Libraries.
                    Another version of this article will be published as <title rend="quotes"
                        >Versioning and Digital Editions</title>, in <title rend="italic">Book
                        History and Digital Humanities</title>, Wacha, H. and Vareschi, M. (eds),
                    Center for the History of Print and Digital Culture and University of Wisconsin
                    Press, Madison, forthcoming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix1">
                <head>Appendix 1</head>
                <p>To get an idea of existing versioning practices in existing digital editions, I
                    examined versioning and revision-tracking practices in the thirty <quote
                        rend="inline">interesting editions/projects</quote> singled out for
                    recommendation in Patrick Sahle’s online <title rend="italic">Catalogue of
                        Digital Editions</title>
                    <ptr target="#sahle2019"/>. These resources, comprising projects with start
                    dates ranging from 1995 to 2018 and covering multiple fields, languages, and
                    kinds of material, offer a convenient sampling of available digital editorial
                    work. I examined each resource and attempted to determine whether it provided
                    version numbers and whether it kept granular revision histories. To attempt to
                    learn a project’s practices, I examined its opening page, pages describing the
                    project and its technical and editorial policies, credits pages, citation
                    instructions, and a small sampling of pages displaying texts belonging to the
                    edition. Where a project provided direct access to its underlying data files
                    (typically in the form of TEI-encoded XML), I also examined a few of these files
                    to see if version numbers or revision histories were represented in the data
                    files. Because my examination of the data files of any individual project was
                    limited and manual, it is possible that a project includes version information
                    or revision history in a file I did not examine, or discusses these matters in a
                    portion of the site I did not access; however, my examination suggests broadly
                    whether such information is accessible to site users. My findings are summarized
                    in the table below, followed by brief discussion.</p>
                <table>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell role="label">Project Name<note>I give the short titles provided by
                                Sahle in order to facilitate easy cross-referencing with his list,
                                where fuller citations and hyperlinks are available. On August 4,
                                2019, I used the Internet Archive Wayback Machine (<ref
                                    target="https://web.archive.org">https://web.archive.org</ref>)
                                to archive a copy of the landing page for each site on Sahle’s list,
                                as well as all the links from that page that the Archive was able to
                                automatically follow. That process does not preserve the sites in
                                full, but it does establish a partial record of how the sites
                                presented themselves when I consulted them. The archived versions
                                may be accessed by entering the URL for each site at the Wayback
                                Machine and navigating to the date in the site
                            history.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="label">Project–wide version number</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Version numbers for individual documents</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Change logs in data files<note>I recorded a project as
                                keeping change logs in data files if I actually found such logs (for
                                instance, in a &lt;revisionDesc&gt; element) or if the project’s
                                technical documentation discusses creating them.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="label">Other detailed change logs</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Provides date of last update<note>Resources offering
                                version numbers or change logs often record the dates of the
                                changes; this column notes only those instances where a site records
                                the date of last update in the absence of other change information.
                                With the exception of <title rend="italic">Van Gogh</title>, the
                                resources listed in this column provide a single date of last update
                                for the site as a whole.</note></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts Digital Edition</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Bayeux-Tapestry Digital Edition<note>I accessed the online
                                sample of this resource. The URL button at the top of the screen,
                                which provides a recommended citation, describes this as the
                                    <q>revised edition</q>, and gives the publication date as 2011.
                                The Credits page provides only the original date of 2003. I have not
                                considered that statement of a revised edition, which does not seem
                                to be repeated elsewhere, to constitute a version
                            identifier.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Samuel Beckett - Digital Manuscript Project<note>Most of
                                the materials published by this project are available only to
                                subscribers; in addition to the project’s documentation, I consulted
                                the freely available demo versions of a few texts made available on
                                the site.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Burckhardt Source</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Lord Byron and his Times</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Canterbury Tales Project: The Miller's Tale on
                            CD-ROM</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Canterbury Tales Project: The Nun's Priest's Tale on
                            CD-ROM</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Dante Alighieri: Commedia - A Digital Edition<note>I
                                accessed the online sample of this resource.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Alfred Escher - Briefedition</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Faustedition / Johann Wolfgang Goethe: Faust.
                            Historisch-kritische Edition</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">In Transition: Selected Poems by the Baroness Elsa von
                            Freytag-Loringhoven</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Diary of William Godwin</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Thomas Gray (1716-1771) Interactive Online
                            Commentary</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"><note>A Website History page provides updates on additions
                                to the site materials, and individual pages, such as the Finding Aid
                                resource, contain their own revision histories. The About page
                                claims that <quote rend="inline">versioned corrections and revisions
                                    of the pages take place continuously</quote>
                                <ptr target="#huber2019"/>, but I have not been able to find version
                                identifiers or retrieve old versions — though the same page notes
                                that archived versions of the site are available upon
                                request.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Charles Harpur Critical Archive</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Wolfgang Koeppen: Jugend - Textgenetische Edition</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Hugo von Montfort - Das poetische Werk</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Newton Project</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Proceedings of the Old Bailey, London 1674 to
                            1834</cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Petrus Plaoul - Editio Critica Commentarii in libris
                                Sententiarum<note>The URL provided by Sahle directs to the Plaoul
                                Commentary as housed within the Scholastic Commentaries and Texts
                                Archive (<ref
                                    target="http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/questions/plaoulcommentary"
                                    >http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/questions/plaoulcommentary</ref>).
                                It is this form of the resource that I have examined.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Complete Writings and Pictures of Dante Gabriel
                            Rossetti - A Hypermedia Archive</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Arthur Schnitzler - Digitale historisch-kritische Edition
                            (Werke 1905 bis 1931)</cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Codex Sinaiticus</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Bichitra: Online Tagore Variorum</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Digital Thoreau</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Vincent van Gogh - The Letters</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X<note>Each data file includes an XML comment at the
                                beginning of the file that provides both the data and time when the
                                project data was last modified and a <q>SVN Revision</q> number:
                                presumably the revision number in the Subversion repository in which
                                the project is stored. (Apache Subversion is a revision control
                                system predating Git.) This comment is likely created using an
                                automated software tool when changes are committed to the Subversion
                                repository, and all files appear to be labeled with the time and
                                revision number of the latest commit to the project repository as a
                                whole. I do not count these SVN revision numbers as version numbers
                                because, as I discuss in this article, versioning involves intention
                                and judgment. (Moreover, the revision numbers are not displayed
                                outside of the data files.) However, SVN revision numbers do
                                resemble project-wide version numbers more than do Git commit
                                hashes: in SVN, revision numbers take the form of integers and each
                                is one greater than the previous. Accordingly, these revision
                                numbers could be used both to identify a particular state of the
                                project and to understand the sequence among versions of a
                                file.</note></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Van Nu en Straks. De Brieven</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Lope de Vega - La Dama Boba - EDICIÓN CRÍTICA Y ARCHIVO
                            DIGITAL</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Digital Vercelli Book</cell>
                        <cell role="data"><note>The Project Info menu option describes the site
                                release as <q>Second digital edition (beta 2).</q> However, the six
                                listed revisions suggest a more complicated change history than this
                                numbering expresses, so I do not count it as a meaningful site-wide
                                version number. The <q>second edition</q> appears to refer to the
                                platform rather than to the underlying data or to the site as a
                                whole.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X<note>Does not provide access to underlying TEI files.
                                The list of changes accompanying the edition exists in a format that
                                might have been generated using &lt;change&gt; elements in the
                                &lt;revisionDesc&gt; section of the TEI header, though it is
                                impossible to be sure without the underlying XML.</note></cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Carl-Maria-von-Weber-Gesamtausgabe (WeGA) [Digitale
                            Präsentation]</cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">The Walt Whitman Archive</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data">X</cell>
                        <cell role="data"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Total Number</cell>
                        <cell role="data">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data">9</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data">3</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Of the projects represented, 18 (60%) acknowledge in some form that their
                    resources may change over time. The most common form of acknowledging changes,
                    practiced by thirteen projects (43%), is maintain a change log, which typically
                    records a description of changes, the date on which they were made, and who made
                    them. Four projects provide a list of changes as part of the website (in the
                    case of the <title rend="italic">Vercelli</title>, I suspect generated from the
                    underlying data files, which are not accessible). These vary in detail; <title
                        rend="italic">Schnitzler</title> focuses on the addition of new content and
                    features; <title rend="italic">Old Bailey</title> discusses corrections but
                    often summarizes changes made to many records simultaneously; the <title
                        rend="italic">Whitman Archive</title> provides a detailed description of
                    revisions in an external blog. Ten projects, all encoded in TEI XML or a
                    derivative format, store revision lists in each data file using the
                        <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code> element; the <title rend="italic">Whitman
                        Archive</title> is noteworthy in providing both internal and external change
                    logs.</p>
                <p>Supplying version numbers is a rarer approach. Seven projects (23%) employ
                    version numbers in some capacity. This total is split almost evenly between
                    projects that assign a single version number to a given state of the project (3;
                    10% of the total) and those that version separate texts or data files
                    independently (4; 13% of the total). Surprisingly, only three projects combine
                    version numbers with a detailed listing of changes; in all cases one version
                    number applies to the resources as a whole, though one of the projects records
                    changes to individual files while the other two announce sitewide changes
                    (including new features) in tandem with new versions.</p>
                <p>The three projects using sitewide version numbers all use conventional
                    two-segment version numbers.<note>At the time of writing, <title rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of the Old Bailey</title> is on version 8.0, <title
                            rend="italic">Schnitzler</title> is on beta version 2.0, and <title
                            rend="italic">WeGA</title> is on version 3.4.</note>
                    <title rend="italic">Schnitzler</title> is the only project to explicitly
                    explain the meaning of its version numbers, the two segments of which correspond
                    to major and minor releases: major releases are marked by the release of
                    significant new functionality or materials, as anticipated by the phases mapped
                    out by the Release Plan, while minor versions correspond to minor updates <ptr
                        target="#izb2019"/>.<note>However, it is ambiguous whether all content
                        changes register in the site’s version history, which currently only notes
                        the addition of a new resource in conjunction with the release of Beta 2.0.
                        Following its explanation of its versioning practices, the site explains,
                            <quote rend="inline">Kleinere, z.B. von Benutzern gemeldete Fehler
                            (Bugfixing und inhaltliche Fehlerkorrekturen) werden laufend
                            behoben</quote> [Smaller, e.g. user-reported errors (bugfixes and
                        content corrections) are continuously fixed]; it is unclear whether these
                        ongoing corrections are recorded or versioned.</note> Generally, these
                    project-wide version numbers assign clear version numbers that clearly
                    communicate something about the scope of their changes.</p>
                <p>By contrast, the projects that grant version numbers to individual documents or
                    data files use a much wider array of formats. Of the four projects that version
                    individual resources, two conceive of versioning by analogy to print. The <title
                        rend="italic">Rossetti Archive</title>, on the pages for individual works
                    within the archive, refers not to versions of its materials but to editions. At
                    the bottom of the page for each item in the archive, the site gives an
                        <q>Electronic Archive Edition</q> number as an integer; an item might be
                    listed as edition 1 or 2.<note>I was able to locate only two texts in the
                        Archive with a stated Archive Edition number of 2: <ref target="#hunt">Hunt
                            (n.d.)</ref>; <ref target="#MDGR">Masterpieces of D.G. Rossetti (n.d.)</ref>.
                            For neither does the publicly available XML source include any
                        metadata on revisions (the &lt;revisionDesc&gt; element is empty in both),
                        so it is impossible to get a sense of what sorts of changes constitute a new
                        edition. Possibly the publication of a new edition was considered to reset
                        the revision state of the document, so that records of changes from the
                        previous edition need not be preserved. It is also possible that the second
                        edition resulted from creating the resources anew a second time. I looked
                        for such materials by conducting a Google search of the rossettiarchive.org
                        domain for the phrase “Electronic Archive Edition: 2” (and higher
                        numbers).</note> Inspecting the XML files reveals that the book analogy is
                    suggested in part by the TEI; the edition number is given in the document header
                    using the <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code> element.<note>The <title rend="italic"
                            >Rossetti Archive</title> is not actually encoded in TEI, which its
                        creators found insufficient for the needs of their materials <ptr
                            target="#mcgann2001" loc="89–90"/>. However, the <title rend="italic"
                            >Archive</title>’s encoding principles drew upon the standards of the
                        TEI, and the <code>&lt;editionStmt&gt;</code> element of the file header is
                        one component derived from the TEI. Early version of the TEI Guidelines are
                        available at <ref target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html"
                            >https://tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html</ref>. For the earliest version
                        of the <code>&lt;editionStmt&gt;</code> recommendation readily available
                        online, see <ref target="#sperberg-mcqueen1999">Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard
                            (1999), §5.2.2</ref>.</note> (<title rend="italic">Lord Byron</title>
                    similarly attaches an integer edition number to the <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code>
                    element, though it uses the <code>@n</code> attribute, where <title
                        rend="italic">Rossetti</title> makes the edition number the element’s
                    content; <title rend="italic">Lord Byron</title> does not display this number in
                    the reading interface.) These numbers provide a mechanism for recording changes,
                    but the number’s low resolution combined with the ambiguity of the
                        <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code> element and the lack of a stated versioning
                    policy means that it is difficult to be certain the edition number will be
                    updated with any change.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Petrus Plaoul</title>, as available in the Scholastic
                    Commentaries and Texts Archive, also refers to a state of one of its digital
                    texts as an edition, but the identifiers it assigns suggests a more robust way
                    of thinking about textual state. The identifier for an <q>edition</q> might take
                    the form <q>2011.10-dev-master</q>, accompanied by the date <q>October 04,
                        2011</q>; these appear at the head of every text on the site (for example,
                        <ref target="#plaoul2011">Plaoul, 2011</ref>). These identifiers offer a
                    form of Calendar Versioning, labeling a state of the text according to when it
                    last changed, combined with what appears to be technical control information.
                    The dot separation between the year and month visually evokes standard formats
                    for version numbers. But of the projects profiled, only <title rend="italic"
                        >Codex Sinaiticus</title> explicitly refers to states of its material as
                    versions. The website detaches this information from the presentation of the
                    text; I found the version number listed only on the XML Download page, where it
                    is also accompanied by a revision date <ptr target="#XMLD"/>. The version number
                    — 1.04 at the time of writing — is stored in the downloadable XML file, attached
                    to the <code>@n</code> attribute of the <code>&lt;edition&gt;</code> element and
                    also labeled “Version 1.04” in the content of that element, where it is
                    accompanied by a date of last update (March 25, 2014). The
                        <code>&lt;revisionDesc&gt;</code> element enumerates changes made to the XML
                    file and parenthetically links each to the version number of the file in which
                    the change was made. Of the projects examined, <title rend="italic">Codex
                        Sinaiticus</title> alone offers detailed version numbers capable of
                    registering the scope of revisions, and it is also alone in explicitly
                    articulating the link between labeled version and the revision history.</p>
                <p>The field of digital editing as a whole shows an understanding of the importance
                    of acknowledging resource change; a majority of the editorial projects surveyed
                    take some steps to show how the current state of the resources differs from
                    earlier forms in which the same resource was available. Based on the prevalence
                    of various approaches to change, it appears that at least a partial consensus
                    has formed within the field about using change logs to describe to human readers
                    the changes that have occurred. By comparison, labeling specific states of the
                    resource through the use of version numbers or other identifiers is much less
                    common, and even among projects that do explicitly version resources, practices
                    are wildly inconsistent. Should whole websites be versioned, or individual
                    texts? What constitutes a version? What form should version numbers take? This
                    article has argued that version numbers are necessary for data management and
                    interoperability among digital editions. The significant disparities in existing
                    practices highlight the need for a field-wide conversation to develop practices
                    around versioning practices.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="abilgaard2015" label="Abilgaard 2015">Abildgaard, N.R. (2015) <title
                        rend="quotes">On Versioning</title>. 5 February. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://blog.hypesystem.dk/on-versioning"
                        >http://blog.hypesystem.dk/on-versioning</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target=" http://web.archive.org/web/20190803210015/http://blog.hypesystem.dk/on-versioning"
                        >
                        http://web.archive.org/web/20190803210015/http://blog.hypesystem.dk/on-versioning</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="altice2015" label="Altice 2015">Altice, N. (2015) <title rend="italic"
                        >I am Error: The Nintendo Family Computer / Entertainment System
                        Platform</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="andrews2018" label="Andrews and Zundert 2018">Andrews, T.L. and
                    Zundert, J.J.V. (2018) <title rend="quotes">What Are You Trying to Say? The
                        Interface as an Integral Element of Argument</title>. In Bleier, R. et al.
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editions as Interfaces</title>,
                    Books on Demand, Norderstedt, pp. 3-33. urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-91064. Available at:
                        <ref target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/id/eprint/9106"
                        >http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/id/eprint/9106</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ashkenas2015" label="Ashkenas 2015">Ashkenas, J. (2015) <title
                        rend="quotes">Why Semantic Versioning Isn’t</title>. GitHub Gist. Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="https://gist.github.com/jashkenas/cbd2b088e20279ae2c8e/39e281d9bc8f3090dd79347b5271aa9b30c2bb8b"
                        >https://gist.github.com/jashkenas/cbd2b088e20279ae2c8e/39e281d9bc8f3090dd79347b5271aa9b30c2bb8b</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803210633/https://gist.github.com/jashkenas/cbd2b088e20279ae2c8e/39e281d9bc8f3090dd79347b5271aa9b30c2bb8b"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803210633/https://gist.github.com/jashkenas/cbd2b088e20279ae2c8e/39e281d9bc8f3090dd79347b5271aa9b30c2bb8b</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ANDS" label="Australian National Data Service n.d.">Australian
                    National Data Service (n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Data Versioning</title>.
                    Australian National Data Service. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.ands.org.au/working-with-data/data-management/data-versioning"
                        >https://www.ands.org.au/working-with-data/data-management/data-versioning</ref>
                    (viewed 1 September 2017). Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803211318/https://www.ands.org.au/working-with-data/data-management/data-versioning"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803211318/https://www.ands.org.au/working-with-data/data-management/data-versioning</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berners-lee1998" label="Berners-Lee 1998">Berners-Lee, T. (1998)
                        <title rend="quotes">Web Architecture from 50,000 Feet</title>. W3C.
                    September. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Architecture.html"
                        >https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Architecture.html</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803211651/https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Architecture.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803211651/https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Architecture.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berrie2006" label="Berrie et al. 2006">Berrie, P. et al. (2006) <title
                        rend="quotes">Authenticating Electronic Editions</title>. In Burnard et al.
                    2006, pp. 269-276.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boot2011" label="Boot and Zundert 2011">Boot, P. and Zundert, J.
                    (2011) <title rend="quotes">The Digital Edition 2.0 and The Digital Library:
                        Services, not Resources</title>. In Fritze, C. et al (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Digitale Edition und Forschungsbibliothek: Beirtäge der
                        Fachtagung im Philosophicum der Universität Mainz am 13. und 14 Januar
                        2011</title>, Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden, pp. 141-152.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bowers2005" label="Bowers 2005">Bowers, F. (2005) <title rend="italic"
                        >Principles of Bibliographical Description</title>. Oak Knoll Press, New
                    Castle, DE. First published 1949.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley2012" label="Bradley 2012">Bradley, J. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">No Job for Techies: Technical Contributions to Research in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>. In Deegan, M. and McCarty, W. (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities</title>,
                    Ashgate, Farnham, Surrey, pp. 11-26.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bryant2002" label="Bryant 2002">Bryant, J. (2002) <title rend="italic"
                        >The Fluid Text: A Theory of Revision and Editing for Book and
                        Screen</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burnard2006" label="Burnard et al. 2006">Burnard, L., O'Brien O'Keefe,
                    K., and Unsworth, J, eds. (2006) <title rend="italic">Electronic Textual
                        Editing</title>. Modern Language Association, New York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrow2018" label="Burrow and Turville-Peter 2018">Burrow, J.A. and
                    Turville-Peter, T., eds. (2018) <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman: The
                        B-Version Archetype (Bx)</title>. Society for Early English and Norse
                    Electronic Texts, Raleigh, NC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cerquiglini1999" label="Cerquiglini 1999">Cerquiglini, B. (1999)
                        <title rend="italic">In Praise of the Variant: A Critical History of
                        Philology</title>. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chassanoff2018" label="Chassanoff et al. 2018">Chassanoff, A. et al.
                    (2018) <title rend="quotes">Software Curation in Research Libraries: Practice
                        and Promise</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Librarianship and
                        Scholarly Communication</title>, 6 (1). <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.7710/2162-3309.2239"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.7710/2162-3309.2239</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="CM2003" label="Chicago Manual 2003"><title rend="italic">The Chicago
                        Manual of Style</title> (2003) 15th ed. University Of Chicago Press,
                    Chicago.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="CM2017" label="Chicago Manual 2017"><title rend="italic">The Chicago
                        Manual of Style</title> (2017) 17th ed. University of Chicago Press,
                    Chicago.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deegan2006" label="Deegan 2006">Deegan, M. (2006) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collection and Preservation of an Electronic Edition</title>. In Burnard et
                    al. 2006, pp. 358-370.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DTS2019" label="Distributed Text Services 2019"><title rend="quotes"
                        >Distributed Text Services (DTS)</title> (2019). Distributed Text Services.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/"
                        >https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/</ref> (viewed 3
                    August 2019).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duggan2005" label="Duggan and Lyman 2005">Duggan, H.N. and Lyman, E.W.
                    (2005) <title rend="quotes">A Progress Report on <title rend="italic">The Piers
                            Plowman Electronic Archive</title></title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Medievalist</title>, 1. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/dm.5"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/dm.5</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duggan2019" label="Duggan et al. 2019">Duggan, H.N., Stinson, T.L.,
                    and Turville-Petre, T., eds. <title rend="italic">Piers Plowman Electronic
                        Archive</title>. Society for Early English and Norse Electronic Texts.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://piers.chass.ncsu.edu"
                        >http://piers.chass.ncsu.edu</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eaves2017" label="Eaves et al. 2017">Eaves, M., Essick. R.N., and
                    Viscomi, J., eds. (2017). <title rend="italic">The William Blake
                    Archive</title>. Chapel Hill, NC. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.blakearchive.org/"
                    >http://www.blakearchive.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eggert2013" label="Eggert 2013">Eggert, P. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Apparatus, Text, Interface: How to Read a Printed Critical Edition</title>.
                    In Fraistat, N. and Flanders, J. (eds), <title rend="italic">The Cambridge
                        Companion to Textual Scholarship</title>, Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge, pp. 97-118.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="escobarvarela2016" label="Escobar Varela 2016">Escobar Varela, M.
                    (2016) <title rend="quotes">The Archive as Repertoire: Transience and
                        Sustainability in Digital Archives</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10(4). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190804175354/http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190804175354/http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2011" label="Fitzpatrick 2011">Fitzpatrick, K. (2011)
                        <title rend="italic">Planned Obsolescence: Publishing, Technology, and the
                        Future of the Academy</title>. New York University Press, New York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="folsomprice" label="Folsom and Price n.d."><title rend="italic">The
                        Walt Whitman Archive</title>. Center for Digital Research in the Humanities,
                    University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://whitmanarchive.org">https://whitmanarchive.org</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="franzini2019" label="Franzini et al. 2019">Franzini, G., Terras, M.
                    and Mahony, S. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Digital Editions of Text: Surveying
                        User Requirements in the Digital Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title>, 12(1). <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/3230671"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/3230671</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fyfe2012" label="Fyfe 2012">Fyfe, P. (2012) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Electronic Errata: Digital Publishing, Open Review, and the Futures of
                        Correction</title>. In Gold, M.K. (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, pp.
                    259-280.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gabler2010" label="Gabler 2010">Gabler, H.W. (2010) <title
                        rend="quotes">Theorizing the Digital Scholarly Edition</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literature Compass</title>, 7, 43-56. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00675.x"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00675.x</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galey2010" label="Galey 2010">Galey, A. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Human Presence in Digital Artifacts</title>. In McCarthy, W. (ed),
                        <title rend="italic">Text and Genre in Reconstruction: Effects of
                        Digitization on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and Institutions</title>, Open
                    Book Publishers, Cambridge, 93-117. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.openbookpublishers.com/reader/64/#page/104/mode/2up"
                        >https://www.openbookpublishers.com/reader/64/#page/104/mode/2up</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gants2010" label="Gants 2010">Gants, D.L. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Descriptive Bibliography and Electronic Publication</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Essays and Studies</title>, 2010, 121-141.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibaldi1995" label="Gibaldi 1995">Gibaldi, J. (1995) <title
                        rend="italic">MLA Handbook for Writers of Research Papers</title>. Modern
                    Language Association of America, New York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibaldi1998" label="Gibaldi 1998">Gibaldi, J. (1998) <title
                        rend="italic">MLA Style Manual and Guide to Scholarly Publishing</title>.
                    Modern Language Association of America, New York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="git" label="Git n.d."><title rend="quotes">Git</title>. (n.d.) Git.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://git-scm.com">https://git-scm.com</ref>
                    (viewed 22 July 2019). Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803215454/https://git-scm.com/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803215454/https://git-scm.com/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gitum" label="Git User's Manual n.d."><title rend="italic">The Git
                        User’s Manual</title>. (n.d.) Version 2.22.0. Git. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://git-scm.com/docs/user-manual.html"
                        >https://git-scm.com/docs/user-manual.html</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803235925/https://git-scm.com/docs/user-manual.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803235925/https://git-scm.com/docs/user-manual.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greetham1992" label="Greetham 1992">Greetham, D.C. (1992) <title
                        rend="italic">Textual Scholarship: An Introduction</title>. Garland, New
                    York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hashemi2019" label="Hashemi 2019">Hashemi, M. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">Calendar Versioning</title>. CalVer: Timely Software
                    Versioning. 1 July. Available at: <ref target="http://calver.org"
                        >http://calver.org</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803215814/http://calver.org/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803215814/http://calver.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huber2019" label="Huber 2019">Huber, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                        >About</title>. <title rend="italic">Thomas Gray Archive</title>. 2 July.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.thomasgray.org/about/index.shtml"
                        >http://www.thomasgray.org/about/index.shtml</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803220008/https://www.thomasgray.org/about/index.shtml"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803220008/https://www.thomasgray.org/about/index.shtml</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hunt" label="Hunt n.d.">Hunt, W.H. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Pre-Raphaelitism and the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood</title>. 2nd Archive
                    Edition. In McGann, J.J. (ed), <title rend="italic">The Complete Writings and
                        Pictures of Dante Gabriel Rossetti: A Hypermedia Archive</title>, Rossetti
                    Archive. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/nd467.h9.1914.1.rad.html"
                        >http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/nd467.h9.1914.1.rad.html</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target=" http://web.archive.org/web/20190803221443/http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/nd467.h9.1914.1.rad.html"
                        >
                        http://web.archive.org/web/20190803221443/http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/nd467.h9.1914.1.rad.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="izb2019" label="Informationen zum Beta-release 2.0 2019"><title
                        rend="quotes">Informationen zum Beta-release 2.0</title>. (2019) 17 April.
                        <title rend="italic">Arthur Schnitzler digital</title>. Beta 2.0. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://www.arthur-schnitzler.de/edition/beta"
                        >https://www.arthur-schnitzler.de/edition/beta</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803221659/https://www.arthur-schnitzler.de/edition/beta"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803221659/https://www.arthur-schnitzler.de/edition/beta</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jones2016" label="Jones et al. 2016">Jones, S.M. et al. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Scholarly Context Adrift: Three out of Four URI References
                        Lead to Changed Content</title>. <title rend="italic">PLoS One</title>,
                    11(12), e0167475. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0167475"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0167475</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kalvesmaki2014" label="Kalvesmaki 2014">Kalvesmaki, J. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Canonical References in Electronic Texts: Rationale and Best
                        Practices</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                    Quarterly</title>, 8(2). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000181/000181.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000181/000181.html</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="https://web.archive.org/web/20190803222140/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000181/000181.html"
                        >https://web.archive.org/web/20190803222140/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000181/000181.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kilbride2016" label="Kilbride 2016">Kilbride, W. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Saving the Bits: Digital Humanities Forever?</title> In
                    Schreibman, S., Siemens, R. and Unsworth, J. (eds), <title rend="italic">A New
                        Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, Wiley Blackwell, Malden, MA, pp.
                    408-419.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2002" label="Kirschenbaum 2002">Kirschenbaum, M.G. (2002)
                        <title rend="quotes">Editing the Interface: Textual Studies and First
                        Generation Electronic Objects</title>. <title rend="italic">TEXT</title>,
                    14, 15-51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2008" label="Kirschenbaum 2008">Kirschenbaum, M.G. (2008)
                        <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New Media and the Forensic
                        Imagination</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2017" label="Kirschenbaum 2017">Kirschenbaum, M.G. (2017)
                        <title rend="quotes">Post Scripts: Graphologies of Bookmaking after
                        Adobe</title>. Paper presented to BH &amp; DH: Book History and Digital
                    Humanities, Madison, WI, 22 September.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2014" label="Klein et al. 2014">Klein, M. et al. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Scholarly Context Not Found: One in Five Articles Suffers from
                        Reference Rot</title>. <title rend="italic">PLoS One</title>, 9, e115253.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0115253"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0115253</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kline2008" label="Kline and Perdue 2008">Kline, M.J. and Perdue, S.H.
                    (2008) <title rend="italic">A Guide to Documentary Editing</title>. University
                    of Virginia Press, Charlottesville.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knowles2014" label="Knowles and Stinson 2014">Knowles, J. and Stinson,
                    T. (2014) <title rend="quotes">The Piers Plowman Electronic Archive on the Web:
                        An Introduction</title>. <title rend="italic">The Yearbook of Langland
                        Studies</title>, 28, 225-238.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuczera2016" label="Kuczera 2016">Kuczera, A. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Editions beyond XML – Graph-based Digital
                        Editions</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd
                        Histo–Informatics Workshop, Krakow, Poland, 11 July 2016</title>, 37-46.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1632/paper_5.pdf"
                        >http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1632/paper_5.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="leblanc2018" label="Leblanc 2018">Leblanc, E. (2018) <title
                        rend="italic">Design of a Digital Library Interface from User Perspective,
                        and its Consequences for the Design of Digital Scholarly Editions: Findings
                        of the Fonte Gaia Questionnaire</title>. In Bleier et al. (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editions as Interfaces</title>, Books on
                    Demand, Norderstedt, pp. 287-315. urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-91215 Available at: <ref
                        target="https://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/9121/"
                        >https://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/9121/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2004" label="Liu 2004">Liu, A. (2004) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Transcendental Data: Toward a Cultural History and Aesthetics of the New
                        Encoded Discourse</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>,
                    31, 49-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2005" label="Liu et al. 2005">Liu, A. et al. (2005) <title
                        rend="quotes">Born-Again Bits: A Framework for Migrating Electronic
                        Literature</title>. Version 1.1. 5 August. Electronic Literature
                    Organization, Vancouver. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://eliterature.org/pad/bab.html"
                        >https://eliterature.org/pad/bab.html</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803223824/https://eliterature.org/pad/bab.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803223824/https://eliterature.org/pad/bab.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lóscio2017" label="Lóscio et al. 2017">Lóscio, B.F., Burle, C., and
                    Carlegari, N., eds. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Data on the Web Best Practices:
                        W3C Recommendation</title>. 31 January. W3C. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-dwbp-20170131/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-dwbp-20170131/</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803224048/https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-dwbp-20170131/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803224048/https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-dwbp-20170131/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="MDGR" label="Masterpieces of D.G. Rosetti n.d."><title rend="italic"
                        >Masterpieces of D. G. Rossetti (1828-1882): Sixty Reproductions of
                        Photographs from the Original Oil-paintings</title>. (n.d.) 2nd Archive
                    Edition. In McGann, J.J. (ed), <title rend="italic">The Complete Writings and
                        Pictures of Dante Gabriel Rossetti: A Hypermedia Archive</title>, Rossetti
                    Archive. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/ac-gowans.759.2r735m393.rad.html"
                        >http://www.rossettiarchive.org/docs/ac-gowans.759.2r735m393.rad.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcdonough2010" label="McDonough et al. 2010">McDonough, J. et al.
                    (2010) <title rend="quotes">Twisty Little Passages Almost All Alike: Applying
                        the FRBR Model to a Classic Computer Game</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 4(2). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000089/000089.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000089/000089.html</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="https://web.archive.org/web/20190803224557/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000089/000089.html"
                        >https://web.archive.org/web/20190803224557/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000089/000089.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann1995" label="McGann 1995">McGann, J. (1995) <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Rationale of Hypertext</title>. 6 May. IATH WWW Server. Available at:
                        <ref target="http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/public/jjm2f/rationale.html"
                        >http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/public/jjm2f/rationale.html</ref>. Archived
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803224726/http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/public/jjm2f/rationale.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803224726/http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/public/jjm2f/rationale.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann1996" label="McGann 1996">McGann, J. (1996) <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Rationale of HyperText</title>. <title rend="italic">TEXT</title>, 9,
                    11-32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann2001" label="McGann 2001">McGann, J. (2001) <title rend="italic"
                        >Radiant Textuality: Literature after the World Wide Web</title>. Palgrave,
                    New York.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="MLAC2011" label="MLA Committee 2011">MLA Committee on Scholarly
                    Editions (2011) <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for Editors of Scholarly
                        Editions</title>. 29 June. MLA, New York. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/Guidelines-for-Editors-of-Scholarly-Editions"
                        >https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/Guidelines-for-Editors-of-Scholarly-Editions</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225011/https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/Guidelines-for-Editors-of-Scholarly-Editions"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225011/https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/Guidelines-for-Editors-of-Scholarly-Editions</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="MLAC2016" label="MLA Committee 2016">MLA Committee on Scholarly
                    Editions (2016) <title rend="quotes">MLA Statement on the Scholarly Edition in
                        the Digital Age</title>. May. Modern Language Association of America, New
                    York. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.mla.org/content/download/52050/1810116/rptCSE16.pdf"
                        >https://www.mla.org/content/download/52050/1810116/rptCSE16.pdf</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225220/https://www.mla.org/content/download/52050/1810116/rptCSE16.pdf"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225220/https://www.mla.org/content/download/52050/1810116/rptCSE16.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nielsen2017" label="Nielsen 2017">Nielsen, L.H. (2017) <title
                        rend="quotes">Zenodo now supports DOI versioning!</title> 30 May. Zenodo
                    Blog. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://blog.zenodo.org/2017/05/30/doi-versioning-launched/"
                        >http://blog.zenodo.org/2017/05/30/doi-versioning-launched/</ref>. Archived
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225348/http://blog.zenodo.org/2017/05/30/doi-versioning-launched/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225348/http://blog.zenodo.org/2017/05/30/doi-versioning-launched/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odonnell2008" label="O'Donnell 2008">O’Donnell, D.P. (2008) <title
                        rend="quotes">Resisting The Tyranny of the Screen, or, Must a Digital
                        Edition be Electronic?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Heroic Age</title>, 11. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.heroicage.org/issues/11/em.php"
                        >https://www.heroicage.org/issues/11/em.php</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225437/https://www.heroicage.org/issues/11/em.php"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225437/https://www.heroicage.org/issues/11/em.php</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odonnell2018" label="O'Donnell 2018">O'Donnell, D.P., ed. (2018)
                        <title rend="italic">Cædmon’s Hymn: A Multimedia Study, Edition, and
                        Archive</title>. Internet Edition [source code]. Version 1.1. 21 April.
                    Zenodo. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1226549"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1226549</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="OTA" label="Oxford Text Archive n.d.">The Oxford Text Archive (n.d.)
                    University of Oxford, Oxford. Available at: <ref target="ttps://ota.ox.ac.uk"
                        >https://ota.ox.ac.uk</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pichler2014" label="Pichler and Bruvik 2014">Pichler, A. and Bruvik,
                    T.M. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Digital Critical Editing: Separating Encoding
                        from Presentation</title>. In Apollon, D., Bélisle, C. and Régnier, P.
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Critial Editions</title>, University of
                    Illinois Press, Urbana, Chicago, and Springfield, pp. 179-199.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2014" label="Pierazzo 2014">Pierazzo, E. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Documentary Editions and the Others</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</title>, 35. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html"
                        >http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>. Archived
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225830/http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803225830/http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2015" label="Pierazzo 2015">Pierazzo, E. (2015) <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and
                        Methods</title>. Routledge, London. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315577227"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315577227</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="plaoul2011" label="Plaoul 2011">Plaoul, P. (2011) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Lectio 14, De Fide</title>. 2011.10-dev-master. 4 October. Witt, J.C. (ed),
                        <title rend="italic">Scholastic Commentaries and Texts Archive</title>,
                    LombardPress. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/lectio14"
                        >http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/lectio14</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230348/http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/lectio14"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230348/http://scta.lombardpress.org/text/lectio14</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="preston-werner" label="Preston-Werner n.d.">Preston-Werner, T. (n.d.)
                        <title rend="quotes">Semantic Versioning</title>. Version 2.0.0. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://semver.org/spec/v2.0.0.html"
                        >https://semver.org/spec/v2.0.0.html</ref>. Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230451/https://semver.org/spec/v2.0.0.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803230451/https://semver.org/spec/v2.0.0.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="price2009" label="Price 2009">Price, K.M. (2009) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Edition, Project, Database, Archive, Thematic Research Collection: What’s
                        in a Name?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3(3). Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000053/000053.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000053/000053.html</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803231004/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000053/000053.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803231004/http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000053/000053.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="PM2001" label="Publication Manual 2001"><title rend="italic"
                        >Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association</title> (2001)
                    American Psychological Association, Washington, DC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="PM2010" label="Publication Manual 2010"><title rend="italic"
                        >Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association</title> (2010)
                    American Psychological Association, Washington, DC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rasmussen2016" label="Rasmussen 2016">Rasmussen, K.S.G. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Reading or Using a Digital Edition? Reader Roles in Scholarly
                        Editions</title>. In Driscoll, M.J. and Pierazzo, E. (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>,
                    Open Book Publishers, Cambridge, pp. 119-133. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095.07"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095.07</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="régnier2014" label="Régnier 2014">Régnier, P. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Ongoing Challenges for Digital Critical Editions</title>. In
                    Apollon, D., Bélisle, C. and Régnier, P. (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Critical Editions</title>, University of Illinois Press, Urbana, pp.
                    58-80.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reiman1987" label="Reiman 1987">Reiman, D.H. (1987) <title
                        rend="quotes"><q>Versioning</q>: The Presentation of Multiple Texts</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Romantic Texts and Contexts</title>, University of
                    Missouri Press, Columbia, pp. 167-180.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="robinson2013" label="Robinson 2013">Robinson, P. (2013) <title
                        rend="quotes">What Digital Humanists Don’t Know about Scholarly Editing;
                        What Scholarly Editors Don’t Know about the Digital World</title>. Paper
                    presented to Social, Digital, Scholarly Editing, University of Saskatchewan,
                    11-13 July. Available at: <ref
                        target=" https://www.academia.edu/4124828/SDSE_2013_why_digital_humanists_should_get_out_of_textual_scholarship"
                        >
                        https://www.academia.edu/4124828/SDSE_2013_why_digital_humanists_should_get_out_of_textual_scholarship</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sahle2016" label="Sahle 2016">Sahle, P. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                        >What is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title> In Driscoll, M.J. and
                    Pierazzo, E. (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and
                        Practices</title>, Open Book Publishers, Cambridge, pp. 19-40. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/obp.0095.02"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/obp.0095.02</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sahle2019" label="Sahle 2019">Sahle, P. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Some particularly interesting editions/projects</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">A Catalog of Digital Scholarly Editions</title>. Version 3.0,
                    snapshot 2008ff. 19 February. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_interesting.html"
                        >http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_interesting.html</ref>. Archived at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803232312/http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_interesting.html"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803232312/http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_interesting.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schmidt2014" label="Schmidt 2015">Schmidt, D. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Towards an Interoperable Digital Scholarly Edition</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>, 7.
                    doi: <ref target="10.4000/jtei.979">10.4000/jtei.979</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="SPR" label="Scholarly Peer Review n.d."><title rend="quotes">Scholarly
                        Peer Review</title>. (n.d.) ARC. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://ar-c.org/about/peer-review/"
                        >http://ar-c.org/about/peer-review/</ref> (viewed 15 July 2019). Archived
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803233452/http://ar-c.org/about/peer-review/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803233452/http://ar-c.org/about/peer-review/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibman2013" label="Schreibman 2013">Schreibman, S. (2013) <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Scholarly Editing</title>. In Price, K.M. and Siemens,
                    R. (eds), <title rend="italic">Literary Studies in the Digital Age: An Evolving
                        Anthology</title>, MLA Commons, New York. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/digital-scholarly-editing/"
                        >https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/digital-scholarly-editing/</ref>.
                    Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803233920/https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/digital-scholarly-editing/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803233920/https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/digital-scholarly-editing/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg1991" label="Shillingsburg 1991">Shillingsburg, P.L.
                    (1991) <title rend="quotes">Text as Matter, Concept, and Action</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</title>, 44, 31-82.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg1996" label="Shillingsburg 1996">Shillingsburg, P.L.
                    (1996) <title rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age</title>.
                    University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens" label="Siemens et al. n.d.">Siemens, R. et al., eds. (n.d.)
                        <title rend="italic">A Social Edition of the Devonshire MS (BL Add. MS
                        17492)</title>. WikiBooks. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/The_Devonshire_Manuscript"
                        >https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/The_Devonshire_Manuscript</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2016" label="Smith et al. 2016">Smith, A.M. et al. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Software Citation Principles</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >PeerJ Computer Science</title>, 2:e86. doi: <ref
                        target="10.7717/peerj-cs.86">10.7717/peerj-cs.86</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2004" label="Smith 2004">Smith, M.N. (2004) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Electronic Scholarly Editing</title>. In Schreibman, S., Siemens, R. and
                    Unsworth, J. (eds) <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital
                        Humanities</title>, Blackwell, Malden, MA, pp. 306-322.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen2009" label="Sperberg-McQueen 2009">Sperberg-McQueen,
                    C.M. (2009) <title rend="quotes">How to Teach Your Edition How to Swim</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 24, 27-39.
                        <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqn034"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqn034</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen1999" label="Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard 1999"
                    >Sperberg-McQueen, C.M. and Burnard, Lou, eds. (1999) <title rend="italic"
                        >Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. Revised
                    Reprint. May. TEI P3 Encoding Initiative, Chicago, Oxford. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/GL/P3/index.htm"
                        >https://tei-c.org/Vault/GL/P3/index.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle1975" label="Tanselle 1975">Tanselle, G.T. (1975) <title
                        rend="quotes">The Bibliographical Concepts of Issue and State</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of
                        America</title>, 69, 17-66.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle1980" label="Tanselle 1980">Tanselle, G.T. (1980) <title
                        rend="quotes">The Concept of Ideal Copy</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Studies in Bibliography</title>, 33, 18-53.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle1992" label="Tanselle 1992">Tanselle, G.T. (1992) <title
                        rend="italic">A Rationale of Textual Criticism</title>. University of
                    Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle1995" label="Tanselle 1995">Tanselle, G.T. (1995) <title
                        rend="quotes">Critical Editions, Hypertexts, and Genetic Criticism</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Romanic Review</title>, 86, 582-593.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle2001" label="Tanselle 2001">Tanselle, G.T. (2001) <title
                        rend="quotes">Thoughts on the Authenticity of Electronic Texts</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</title>, 54, 133-136.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tarr" label="Tarr n.d.">Tarr, D. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Sentimental Versioning, Version One dot Oh, okay then</title>. Available
                    at: <ref target="http://sentimentalversioning.org"
                        >http://sentimentalversioning.org</ref> (viewed 15 July 2018). Archived at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190803234954/http://sentimentalversioning.org/"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190803234954/http://sentimentalversioning.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TEI2019" label="TEI Consortium 2019">TEI Consortium (2019) <title
                        rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interachange</title>. Text Encoding Initiative. Version 3.6.0, revision
                    daa3cc0b9. 16 July. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"
                        >https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TGC2006" label="TextGrid Consortium 2006-2014">TextGrid Consortium
                    (2006-2014) <title rend="italic">TextGrid: A Virtual Research Environment for
                        the Humanities</title>. TextGrid Consortium, Göttingen. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://textgrid.de">https://textgrid.de</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turabian1996" label="Turabian et al. 1996">Turabian, K.L., Grossman,
                    J.B. and Bennett, A.B. (1996) <title rend="italic">A Manual for Writers of Term
                        Papers, Theses, and Dissertations</title>. 6th ed. University of Chicago
                    Press, Chicago.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turska2016" label="Turska et al. 2016">Turska, M., Cummings, J. and
                    Rahtz, S. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Challenging the Myth of Presentation in
                        Digital Editions</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                        Initiative</title>, 9. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1453"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1453</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="WWAC2019" label="Walt Whitman Archive Changelog 2019"><title
                        rend="quotes">Walt Whitman Archive Changelog</title>. (2019) Blogger.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://wwa-changelog.blogspot.com"
                        >http://wwa-changelog.blogspot.com</ref> (viewed 3 August 2019).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="witt" label="Witt n.d.">Witt, J.C., ed. (n.d.) The SCTA Reading Room.
                    Scholastic Commentaries and Texts Archive. LombardPress. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://scta.lombardpress.org">http://scta.lombardpress.org</ref>
                    (viewed 3 August 2019).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="witt2018" label="Witt 2018">Witt, J.C. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Scholarly Editions and API Consuming Applications</title>. In
                    Bleier, R. et al. (eds) <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editions as
                        Interfaces</title>, Books on Demand, Norderstedt, pp. 219-247.
                    urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-91182. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/id/eprint/9118"
                        >http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/id/eprint/9118</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wittern2013" label="Wittern 2013">Wittern, C. (2013) <title
                        rend="quotes">Beyond TEI: Returning the Text to the Reader</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>, 4. doi: <ref
                        target="10.4000/jtei.691">10.4000/jtei.691</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wittern2009" label="Wittern et al. 2009">Wittern, C., Ciula, A. and
                    Tuohy, C. (2009) <title rend="quotes">The Making of TEI P5</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 24(3), 281-296.
                        <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp017"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp017</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="XMLD" label="XML Download n.d."><title rend="quotes">XML Download of
                        the Electronic Transcription of Codex Sinaiticus</title> (n.d.) <title
                        rend="italic">Codex Sinaiticus</title>, Codex Sinaiticus Project. Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://codexsinaiticus.org/en/project/transcription_download.aspx"
                        >http://codexsinaiticus.org/en/project/transcription_download.aspx</ref>
                    (viewed 1 August 2019). Archived at: <ref
                        target="http://web.archive.org/web/20190801161134/http://www.codexsinaiticus.org/en/project/transcription_download.aspx"
                        >http://web.archive.org/web/20190801161134/http://www.codexsinaiticus.org/en/project/transcription_download.aspx</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zeller1975" label="Zeller 1975">Zeller, H. (1975) <title rend="quotes"
                        >A New Approach to the Critical Constitution of Literary Texts</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</title>, 28, 231-264.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
