<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Best Laid Plans: Case Studies of the Loss of Four Early (1996-2003) Digital Humanities Websites</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Dr. Drew E. <dhq:family>VandeCreek </dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Northern Illinois University Libraries</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email></email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000758</idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date><!-- include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024 --></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
<!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                	
                	<!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp=""/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000758/000758.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This study examines factors contributing to the loss of four grant funded, free use digital humanities websites funded by the 
                    National Endowment for the Humanities' Education Development and Demonstartion Program, 1996-2003: Decision Point! at Auburn University,
                    Hawthorne in Salem at North Shore Community College (Danvers, MA), the New Deal Network at the Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt Institute (Hyde Park, NY) 
                    and River Web at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. The evidence shows that website loss did not occur suuddendly. In all four cases, 
                    organizations that accepted program funds to create online materials ultimately failed to develop or continue procedures to manage them effectively. 
                    As the organizationsor organizational divisions that developed these websites struggled to sustain them or indicated an unwillingness to do so any longer, 
                    their creator(s) asked a college, university, or research library, to take responsibility for them, without success. Online materials became subject 
                    to increased risk of loss in both contexts in part due to rapid technological change,often expressed in accelerating software product update cycles, 
                    combined with a general lack of funding and personnel available for addressing it after the end of grant period. Several other elements also played 
                    parts in website loss however, often shaping the ways in which technological developments and financial circumstances did their damage. In three instances 
                    website creators discovered that common vicissitudes of organizational life, including revised objectives, changing tactics used to achieve them, 
                    and new administrative personnel compromised website sustainability. In two cases adminstrators' responsibility for risk management led them to remove 
                    legacy websites made obsolete by new technology. In one case research pursung technological innovation in the retrieval and management of large data sets 
                    contributed to the loss of a funded resource. Finally, simple, inexplicable failure also contributed to that website's demise. These four cases can provide 
                    a digital humanities community increasingly concerned about the sustainability of grant funded online materials with additional evidence of how technological 
                    change and financial shortfalls threaten these resources. In doing so, it can also show how more complex organizational dynamics often contribute 
                    to website loss.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
            <head></head>
                <div>
                    <head>1.1 Introduction</head>
                    <p>Between 1996 and 2023, the National Endowment for the Humanities’ Education Development and Demonstration (NEH-EDD) program provided 
                        financial support for 59 projects producing free-use digital humanities websites. A recent survey of this program’s funded materials 
                        found that while 40 remained online in September 2020, 19 had become unavailable (VandeCreek, 2022).  This study examines four of these 
                        lost NEH-EDD funded online resources: Decision Point! at Auburn University, Hawthorne in Salem at North Shore Community College 
                        (NSCC; Danvers, MA), the New Deal Network at the Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt Institute (FERI; Hyde Park, NY), and River Web 
                        at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC). By the time of this article’s preparation, information about many 
                        of the 19 lost websites had become scarce or nonexistent. However, sufficient data remained to consider the impact of the loss of these four. 
                        Moving from those instances supplying less information to those furnishing more, this inquiry provides a brief history of each website. 
                        The accounts frame several questions pertaining to legacy website sustainability.  How did the digital humanists that created the resources 
                        seek to sustain them? How did the institutions responsible for presenting the four websites under review attempt to do so? 
                        In the period that these websites remained online, how effectively did they function? What factors contributed to their loss? 
                        Finally, what does the record of these websites’ loss tell us about the larger state of legacy website sustainability efforts 
                        in the period spanning 1996-2023?</p>
                    
                    <p>The evidence shows that website loss did not occur suddenly. In all four cases, organizations that accepted NEH-EDD funds to create 
                        online materials ultimately failed to develop or continue procedures to manage them effectively. As the organizations or organizational 
                        divisions that developed these websites struggled to sustain them or indicated an unwillingness to do so any longer, their creator(s) 
                        asked a college, university, or research library to take responsibility for them, without success.</p>
                    
                    <p> The four histories include information from direct correspondences with website creators, project staff members, and technical personnel, 
                        as well as NEH records available online, organizational press releases, archival materials, magazine and newspaper articles, and other documents. 
                        In each case two major factors contributed to NEH-EDD grant recipients’ inability to sustain websites and libraries’ unwillingness to do so. 
                        Online materials became subject to increased risk of loss in part due to rapid technological change, often expressed in accelerating software 
                        product update cycles, combined with a general lack of funding and personnel available for addressing it after the end of a grant period. 
                        Several other elements also played parts in website loss however, often shaping the ways in which technological developments and financial circumstances 
                        did their damage. They combined in complex ways. In three instances website creators discovered that common vicissitudes of organizational life, 
                        including revised objectives, changing tactics used to achieve them, and new administrative personnel compromised website sustainability. 
                        In two cases administrators’ responsibility for risk management led them to remove legacy websites made obsolete by new technology. 
                        In one case research pursuing technological innovation in the retrieval and management of large data sets contributed to the loss of an NEH-EDD funded resource. 
                        Finally, simple, inexplicable failure also contributed to that website’s demise. A review of these four cases can provide 
                        a digital humanities community increasingly concerned about the sustainability of grant funded online materials with additional evidence of how technological change 
                        and financial shortfalls threaten these resources. In doing so, it can also show how more complex organizational dynamics often contribute to website loss. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                 <head>1.2 Literature Review</head>
                    <p>Free-use websites produced with short-term grant funding occupy an important position in the field of digital humanities. 
                        Many provide large searchable databases of primary source materials that do not appear anywhere else online (Burdick, et al., 2012, 9, 24, 57, 92; Cantara, 2006, 38-40; 
                        Cunningham, 2010, 5-6; Maron & Pickle,2014, 17;  Palmer, 2004, 348; Trace & Karadkar, 2017, 491). Several authors have recently identified the time between the 
                        mid-1990s and approximately 2010 as a period in which online digital project development thrived (Holmes & Takeda, 2023, paragraph 6; Smithies, et al., 2019, 
                        paragraph 16; Crompton, 2023, paragraph 3). While many digital humanists expected the online materials that they created to remain available in the long term, 
                        they remained largely unaware of the complex work and considerable cost required for websites’ continued availability (Maron & Pickle, 2014, 16; Edmond & Morselli, 2020, 1019). 
                        By 2010 researchers had increasingly begun to take note of sustainability issues arising from this corpus (Cunningham, 2010, 5-6; Kretzchmar & Potter, 2010, passim; Maron & Pickle, 
                        2014, passim; Kilbride, 2016, passim; Sweeney, et al., 2017, passim; Smithies, et al., 2019, paragraph 2).</p>
                    <p>Analyses of the problem have often focused on technical and financial factors threatening legacy materials (Edmond & Morselli, 2020, abstract; Jordanova, 2019, 223). 
                        Although multiple technical issues have threatened websites, researchers have frequently emphasized web software’s rapid update cycles and progress toward official deprecation 
                        (Smithies, et al., 2019, paragraphs 36, 44; Holmes & Takeda, 2023, paragraphs 8, 38, 43; Holmes, Jenstad, & Huculak, paragraph 7; Barone, et al., 2015, section 3, paragraph 2; 
                        Cohen & Rosenzweig, 2006, 240-243; Clement, et al., 2013, 119; Maron & Pickle, 2014, 9; Barone, et al., 2015, section three, paragraph two). They note that as each cycle passes 
                        without an update, databases and other types of web software became increasingly obsolete under what Langmead and Quigley have called “the intense pressures of digital innovation” 
                        (Langmead & Quigley, 2015, 2).</p>
                    <p>Many researchers have encouraged organizations that developed free-use websites with grant funds to continue to manage the resources in an active, systematic manner by continuing to update 
                        and replace web technologies. (Kretzchmar & Potter, 2010, 439-440; Maron & Pickle, 2014, 32; Kilbride, 2016, 483, 486; Theide, 2017, section 2). These activities require trained personnel 
                        or funds to outsource the work, however. Jessica Otis has pointed out that online digital projects have not fit neatly into well-established processes for funding humanities scholarship 
                        (Otis, 2023a, paragraph 1; also see McGann, 2010, 4). Three of the organizations examined in this study are public institutions of higher education. In this period many public colleges and universities 
                        faced shrinking state funding allocations, as well as reduced revenues derived from enrollments, especially after 2010 (Li, 2017, Introduction; State Higher Education Executive Officers, passim; 
                        Undergraduate Enrollment, 2023). Devoting funds to sustaining legacy websites represented a new departure in a context marked by many administrators and faculty members’ lack of understanding of and skepticism 
                        toward digital humanities (Maron & Pickle, 2014, 5-6; Brennan, 2017, passim; Greetham, 2012, passim; Grusin, 2013, passim). In many cases host institutions could not provide the staff time or financial wherewithal 
                        needed to update website software after grant support had ended. In one case reviewed by Barone, et al., a website became unavailable as database and server technology advanced. The site’s database became incompatible 
                        with current operating systems and failed. Since the original project grant period had expired, team members could not find the funds needed to reprocess the data for use in a different database engine 
                        (Barone et al., 2015, section 3, paragraph 2).</p>
                    <p>In this context researchers have proposed two alternatives. Many have called for the creators of grant-funded, free-use websites to preserve the materials in web archives (Brown, 2006, passim; Masanes, 2006, passim; Gomes & Costa, 2014, passim). 
                        Several publications have observed that this approach would not secure materials residing within a database, however (Barone, et al., 2015, discussion, paragraph 1; Pennock, 2013, 11; Carlin, 2018, 1). Concerned observers 
                        have also encouraged libraries to take responsibility for sustaining legacy digital humanities websites originally developed elsewhere within their larger organization, or even outside of it altogether. 
                        (Cunningham, 2010, 5-6; Kretzchmar & Potter, 2010, 439, 442; Kunda & Anderson-Wilk, 2011, 901-903; Kilbride, 2016, 483; Sweeney, et al., 2017, passim; Lucky & Harkema, 2018, 194). 
                        None have examined libraries’ financial capacity for doing so.</p>             
                    <p>In 2019 James Smithies and co-authors noted the large number of grant-funded materials that had disappeared from the live web after their grant support ran out and argued that the trend had brought 
                        research in the field to an inflection point (Smithies, et al., paragraph one). Other digital humanists reviewing older websites’ status concurred and explored how this situation had come about. 
                        They found that in many cases an attempt to achieve active management produced an ad hoc system of sustainability measures lacking dedicated funding and specific protocols. 
                        Although legacy materials often survive online, they are becoming increasingly obsolete (VandeCreek, 2023; Otis, 2023b, section 2, paragraphs 1-2). 
                        Joanna Tucker characterizes legacy websites as materials in limbo (Tucker, 2022, 107). Another study describes them as slowly fading away, becoming “digital wastelands” 
                        (Barats, et al., 2023, passim). In 2023 digital humanities developers at the University of Victoria (CA) concluded that sustaining online materials using technology requiring regular updates 
                        had proven to be an unmanageable task (Holmes, Jenstad, & Hukulak, 2023, paragraph 7). They went on to note that this was not an unusual situation. 
                        Their research, conducted as a part of the Endings Project, suggested that it had become the norm for legacy digital humanities websites (Holmes & Takeda, paragraphs 14-15).</p>                
                    <p>The emergence of the Endings Project marked a sea change in the discussion and practice of website sustainability. Its members have designed and implemented a method for converting legacy 
                        websites including databases to a more durable, albeit limited, format (Holmes & Takeda, 2023, passim; Holmes, Jensted & Huculak, 2023, paragraph 22). They argue that this approach dramatically 
                        increases online resources’ chances of survival and encourage other organizations seeking to sustain digital humanities websites to put it to use (Holmes & Takeda, 2023, paragraphs 44-45). 
                        Several large American digital humanities centers have begun to do so (Otis 2023b, section 4, paragraphs 1-8; Foley, Goeke-Smith, & Rehberger, 2023; Viglianti, 2018). 
                        These developments provide an opportunity to look back on earlier practices in specific organizational contexts from a historical perspective and consider the Endings Project’s 
                        approach to website sustainability from a critical perspective.</p>
                    <p>A review of the histories of four NEH-EDD websites that disappeared from use will provide additional information about how the reckoning that Smithies, et al., and the Endings Project have identified came to be. 
                        This article will use the case study method that informed several recent discussions of legacy website sustainability but provide a greater level of detail and discuss events in chronological order (Davis, 2019; Cummings, 2023; Otis, 2023b). 
                        Although the cases generally bolster researchers’ emphasis on how rapid technological change and financial shortfall undermined legacy websites’ viability to the point of failure, they also support Margaret Hedstrom’s argument that 
                        common types of organizational change hinder librarians and archivists’ attempts to preserve digital materials (Hedstrom, 2003, ix). She discusses how changes in an organization’s 
                        direction, purpose, and management influence efforts to curate libraries and archives’ digital collections, but also mentions their relevance to online resources. To date, other researchers have not pursued her latter observation in detail. 
                        Each type of organizational change, alone or together, can prevent the planning, policymaking, and resource allocation activities that comprise the substance of successful digital resource management (Hedstrom, 1997, 190). 
                        Revised organizational goals and new administrative personnel undermined the online status of Hawthorne in Salem and the New Deal Network. These events took place within single organizations, 
                        but the history of River Web and additional aspects of the New Deal Network’s history also demonstrate how events within other organizations, or other units of a larger organization, shaped legacy website sustainability. 
                        In each case they changed the partnership arrangements that had developed and sustained projects.</p>
                    <p>Hedstrom’s emphasis on digital materials’ organizational context also sheds new light on research that has noted that websites relying on obsolete web technology made the networks on which they resided vulnerable to malicious hackers 
                        (Smithies, et al., 2019, passim; Cummings, 2023, paragraphs 15-16; Holmes, Jenstad, & Huculak, 2023, paragraph 21; Otis, 2023b, section 2, paragraph 2). Decision Point! and Hawthorne in Salem each relied on outdated web software 
                        and provided bad actors with ready opportunities to enter Auburn University and NSCC’s information technology networks, respectively. Aware that hackers gaining access to their network might easily gather 
                        sensitive data, administrators at each institution removed NEH-EDD funded materials from use. Their actions introduce a new dimension to the discussion examining administrators’ roles in sustaining legacy digital humanities websites. 
                        Authors encouraging grant recipient organizations and libraries to manage legacy websites in an active manner have often understood administrators as potential providers of funding and personnel needed to sustain online materials 
                        (Kretzchmar & Potter, 2010, 439-440, 442; Maron & Pickle, 2014, 32; Kilbride, 2016, 483, 486; Theide, 2017, section 2; Cunningham, 2010, 5-6; Kunda & Anderson-Wilk, 2011, 901-903; Kilbride, 2016, 483; Lucky & Harkema, 2018, 194). 
                        However, they have not recognized the fact that administrators or managers must also act in keeping with formal responsibilities to protect their organization and its members in a variety of ways. In addition to stewarding an organization’s good name, 
                        these include duties to protect the interests of the organization’s members, prevent its financial loss, and follow legal guidelines in order to avoid its prosecution or civil liability (Beaudin, 2015, passim; Demers, et al., 2017, 105-106; 
                        Blodgett & Carlson, passim; Joshi & Singh, 2017, passim; Stoneburner, et al., 2002, passim). Auburn University and NSCC administrators acted in keeping with these duties when they removed Decision Point! and Hawthorne in Salem, 
                        respectively, from the live web.</p>
                    <p>The record also shows how another aspect of technological change affected online materials’ sustainability. At UIUC research projects seeking to develop means for the assembly and management of very large data sets contributed to River Web’s undoing. 
                        Students tested new tools for extracting data from websites on River Web and eventually crashed it, causing the loss of its data. Economic historians and historians of technology have examined how technical innovation often undermines existing 
                        production methods and business models in the marketplace, a process they have identified as “creative destruction” (Schumpeter, 1942, passim; Swedberg, 2008, passim; Godin, 2008, passim). 
                        In this case technical innovation, or rather the pursuit of it, proved destructive in more than an abstract sense.</p>
                    <p>UIUC’s failure to recover River Web’s data also illustrates a common type of organizational experience that Hedstrom has not considered: failure to adhere to specific policies that help organizations to reach their larger goals. 
                        This type of failure may occur due to individual human beings’ mistakes, byzantine bureaucratic processes, general organizational dysfunction, or other unknown factors. The available evidence does not reveal 
                        how information technology professionals employed at a large research university renowned for its achievements in Computer Science failed to back up online materials, but regardless of its cause, 
                        this lapse prevented River Web team members from recovering the materials that they produced with NEH-EDD funds. Failures that occur without leaving a documentary trail
                        or individuals willing to discuss them often may prevent further documentation or analysis, but they remain regular events in organizations of all sizes. As such, research should acknowledge their occurrence and significance.</p>
                    <p>Smithies et al.’s 2019 examination of factors threatening the sustainability of legacy digital humanities websites noted security breaches at a number of institutions making materials available online by the use of unmaintained software applications. 
                        The authors then declined to examine these events and their causes in further detail “out of respect for [these organizations’] situation,” and went on to describe their largely successful practices in their own lab at King’s College, London. 
                        They hoped that a discussion of their solutions to common sustainability problems might “make it easier for other teams to share their experiences and request the resources needed to mitigate issues” 
                        (Smithies, et al., paragraph 9, FN 5, paragraph 10). The discussion went on to suggest that other teams might report sustainability failures rather successes, however. 
                        It proposed that digital humanists and associated technologists should not understand their struggles as embarrassments best concealed from administrators, funders, and colleagues. 
                        Rather they should perceive them as “research opportunities for developing enhanced methodologies” (Smithies, et al., paragraph 12). This article responds to that cue by providing faculty and staff members at four organizations with an opportunity 
                        to report on their experiences with website loss. Although it describes unhappy events that many individuals associated with each organization might regard as best forgotten, Smithies, et al.’s reasoning remains compelling. 
                        Recording and analyzing cases of legacy website failure provides information and insight that discussions of disasters averted simply cannot. The cases can indeed provide opportunities to develop enhanced methods, 
                        and organizations devoted to teaching, learning, and research should understand them from this perspective.</p>
                    <p>The evidence presented in the following histories of four NEH-EDD funded websites supports recent assertions, including that of Smithies and his co-authors, that work in the field of online digital humanities has reached an important juncture 
                        that requires a close evaluation of legacy websites’ future prospects. It shows that NEH-EDD funded materials produced in very different organizational contexts—including a 501c3 organization, a community college, and two large research universities—disappeared from the live web. 
                        A complex mix of factors produced this website loss over time periods ranging from 11 to 19 years. Although a familiar combination of technical and financial factors played a large role in each case, common forms of bureaucratic change, 
                        administrators’ responsibility to manage risk and avoid liability, different forms of technological innovation itself, and simple, seemingly inexplicable failure also contributed to website loss. Scholarship discussing a wide range of subjects, 
                        from those close at hand like digital preservation to more distant like network security, risk management, and the history of technology, has in several cases pointed the way to these factors. Before members of the digital humanities community 
                        decide how to respond to the precarious state of so many legacy websites, we should examine their histories in greater detail.</p>
                </div>
             <div>
                 <head>Part I: Network Security and Legacy Website Sustainability</head>
                 <head>A: Decision Point! (Auburn University)</head>
                 <head>I: Initial Success</head>
                 <p>In May 2001 John Saye, Professor of Curriculum and Teaching in Secondary Social Sciences at Auburn University, received an NEH-EDD award of $225,000. It supported the development of a website examining important issues and events in the United States’ civil rights movement. 
                     NEH-EDD funding allowed the project team to expand and refine an existing online resource called “Decision Point!”, which facilitated problem-centered instruction in United States history (National Endowment for the Humanities, 2001). 
                     The website placed high school students in Spring 1968 immediately following the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. It asked student teams to act as civil rights leaders, determining how they should continue the struggle 
                     for racial equality and justice in the United States. The website presented discussions of three general strategies that informed movement activism at that time: working within the legal system, nonviolent protest, and Black Power. 
                     It also included a database containing multimedia content documenting and discussing events related to the civil rights movement of the 1950s and 60s, such as period newspaper clippings, television footage and music, personal accounts, 
                     and interviews with movement participants. In addition to making these materials available in a searchable format, the site presented them thematically in three strands representing the primary change strategies. Each strand also included an original interpretive essay, 
                     an event timeline, and a menu of available materials organized by document type (Saye & Brush, 1999, 481; also see Saye & Brush, 2002). </p>
                 <p>Student teams performed research with the benefit of what the grant’s principal investigators described as an integrated electronic notebook. It contained a set of categorizing questions that a historian might use to organize evidence pertaining to an event, 
                     as well as an opportunity to record research activities in a journal format. Saye and collaborator Thomas Brush of Indiana University further described these additional materials as a set of scaffolding tools for collecting, analyzing, and evaluating historical 
                     evidence and offering conclusions. Using the website’s tools, student teams constructed persuasive presentations supporting their approach to continued civil rights activism in 1968 (Saye & Brush, 1999, 472-473; 481-482). Saye and Brush found that participating students 
                     responded to the website enthusiastically and achieved improved learning levels. In a 1999 publication the collaborators recounted their experience with the site and emphasized scaffolding materials’ great potential for supporting teachers using primary sources in history instruction. 
                     They went on to describe the website as an initial expression of an ongoing project seeking to build a sustainable model for multimedia-supported, problem-based social studies learning (Saye & Brush, 1999, 496-498).</p>
        
             </div>
             <div>
                 <head>II: Software Obsolescence and Project Takedown</head>
                 <p></p>
                 
             </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
           
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
