<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
         	<title type="article" xml:lang="en"><title rend="quotes">​​Whole Self to the World</title>: Creating Affective Worlds and Black Digital Intimacy in the Fandom of The Misadventures of <title rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> and <title rend="italic">Insecure</title></title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Brienne A.<dhq:family> Adams</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0883-6262</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Georgetown University</dhq:affiliation>
            	<email>ba644@georgetown.edu </email>
               <dhq:bio>
               	<p>Brienne A. Adams, is an Assistant Professor of African American Studies at Georgetown University. She earned a Ph.D. in American Studies from the University of Maryland. Her work utilizes Black feminisms, queer, and affect theories to examine Black fans of contemporary Black popular culture on social media platforms</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000639</idno>
         	<idno type="volume"
         		><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
         	<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-07-22">22 July 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):
                  CC-BY:
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
            	<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary<!--NEED KEYWORDS--></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Social Media</item>
                  <item>Fandom</item>
                  <item>Digital intimacy</item>
                  <item>Black feminism</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-07-29" who="BRG">updated to pass encoding validation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This article examines how Black fans utilize social media platforms to engage fandoms
               of contemporary Black popular cultural productions. Specifically, how Black digital
               intimacies are created through examining the interiority expressed in the cultural
               productions and their fandoms. Utilizing YouTube and Twitter fan comments from <title
                  rend="italic">The Mis-Adventures of Awkward Black Girl</title> [YouTube,
               2011-2012] and <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> [HBO, 2016-2021], this article
               proposes affirmative transformative fandom to examine the affective relationships
               fans have with their fan objects and fellow fans to explore their own intimate
               live</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><p>By examining interpersonal intimacy and interiority in cultural productions and
            digital fandoms, we see the demonstration of the pursuit of love, wholeness, and
            intimacy as labor that sustaining acts for and by Black communities.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction </head>
            <p>In an interview with <title rend="italic">Harper’s Bazaar</title>, Issa Rae, the
               creator of the web series <title rend="italic">The Misadventures of Awkward Black
                  Girl </title> and the television show <title rend="italic">Insecure </title> said:
                  <quote rend="inline">So much of Issa's [the character on the show] journey has
                  been about denying who she is, not being honest about her feelings, and just
                  really being obviously insecure about so much of her life. So, a happy ending to
                  me would just be Issa feeling happy and satisfied to give her <emph>whole self to
                     the world.</emph></quote>
               <ptr target="#betancourt2020"/>. Rae’s retrospective and foreshadowing pontification
               about the upcoming fifth and final season of her hit series, <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title>, exemplifies the journey fans found themselves on alongside Rae
               and in community with each other on social media platforms. <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title>, created by Issa Rae for HBO in 2016, is a comedy/comedy-drama
               that chronicles a thirty-year-old, Black heterosexual woman who, at beginning of the
               series, is dissatisfied with her career and love life. The show explores dating,
               family, friendship, sex, career issues, and race through <q>Issa Dee</q> as a
               character, which borrowed Rae’s first name as the protagonists’ name, and her best
               friend Molly’s relationship. <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> is loosely based
               on one of Rae’s earliest YouTube produced web series, <title rend="italic">The
                  Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl</title>, that premiered in 2011. <title
                  rend="italic">The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl</title> — also referenced in
               this article as <title rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> or <title
                  rend="italic">ABG</title> — features Issa acting as the character <q>J</q> with a
               similar premise. The protagonist <q>J</q> chronicles her career, friendships, and
               romantic life under the comedic guise of being awkward. Her awkwardness propels the
               comedy’s conflict and character development much like Issa’s insecurities does for
                  <title rend="italic">Insecure </title>'s plot.</p>
            <p>This article examines the online fandom of <title rend="italic">Awkward Black
                  Girl</title> and <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> to explore the affective
               relationships Black people have to their fandom objects, their own intimate lives,
               the creator’s intention, and the digital fandom expressed on social media. Following
               in the footsteps of televisions shows from the 1990s and early 2000s, such as <title
                  rend="italic">Living Single</title> and <title rend="italic">Girlfriends</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> continued the comedic expression of Black intimacy and
               interiority by focusing on friendships, romantic partnerships, and family
               relationships. Rae’s foray into producing the web series on her own on YouTube and
               her usage of fan engagement to continue producing and prop up its popularity that
               eventually turned into the iteration of <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> on HBO
               is a fascinating case study on digital creation, social media, and fandom that
               supports and propels shows into mainstream media.</p>
            <p>I focus on the intimate relationships characters have with each other and those
               developed by fans in social media spaces. Black familial and relationship studies
               emphasize the ways Black Americans forefront their intimate relationships as a
               foundational tenet and an affective motivating factor to continue to fight oppressive
               systems. Scholars of a journal special issue on Black Love state <quote rend="inline"
                  >…what sustained black Americans was love — communal, familial, and
                  carnal…</quote>
               <ptr target="#jelks2019"/>. Amidst all the turmoil and triumphs, relationships have
               sustained Black communities. Combined with Black feminisms, my research develops the
               affective mode to interrogate how Black communities have sustained themselves.
               Specifically, Black feminism grounds my affective theoretical approach through
               womanism’s assertion of love as a central tenet. Womanism’s definition of love is
                  <quote rend="inline">a woman who loves other women, sexually and/or nonsexually.
                  Sometimes loves individual men, sexually and/or nonsexually. Committed to survival
                  and wholeness of entire people, male and female</quote>
               <ptr target="#walker1983"/>. The emphasis on community, love, and sexuality within
               womanism’s description attends to how I am examining Black affect through intimacy
               and how Black communities have deep roots in love for self, others, and the community
               that continues in online spaces. It is the pursuit of wholeness as praxis — as
               sustaining and eventually thriving in Black communities’ personal lives. I assert
               that one way to trace this pursuit is in the active discussions about fandom. Fans
               have a specific understanding and relationship to their objects that center romantic,
               communal, and familial storylines. Rather than speculate and theorize about these
               processes through only examining the cultural productions themselves, we can turn to
               the words of fans as well as their reflections on the characters and their own lives
               as evidence of the affective struggles and triumphs in Black interpersonal
               relationships.</p>
            <p>Fandom studies is the lens by which Black feminisms and digital studies combine in my
               research. Fandom scholars have traditionally centered the affective and intimate
               through demonstrating fandom as inherently participatory. The two definitions of
               fandom, affirmative and transformative, are central to how I am conceptualizing
               digital participation and fandom engagement as well as how the cultural productions
               are informing how their fans are analyzing their interpersonal lives. Affirmative fandom describes fans that like, or affirm, the productions they center their fandom on.
               Transformative is defined as taking the interest and creating a new work inspired by
               the fandom. Fandom scholars, especially fandom scholars of color have evolved and taken up this question... ” should be “Fandom scholars, especially fandom scholars of color, have evolved and taken up the definitions and arguments of the field in various ways. I intervene through combining both
               definitions into an amalgamation that states that Black fans demonstrate affirmative
               transformative fandom in digital spaces. Further, fans shared their insights about
               the characters and storylines and the overlap with their own lives through witnessing
               the pain, joy, growth, setbacks, stagnation, and transitions explored in both shows
               through character arcs and narrative choices. Rae’s usage of the YouTube as a new
               media platform fueled by fan engagement spurred the popularity of the television
               series where the characters showcased their whole selves, and fans responded
               enthusiastically on social media to Rae’s creation of complicated characters that
               struggle with their inner worlds and how it affects their relationships. Centering
               the community that Black digital fandom spaces create, I engage Black studies,
               digital humanities, and fan studies to examine connections fans make to Rae’s media
               output and their own interiority and intimate lives amongst each other using the
               comments on YouTube and hashtags on Twitter.</p>
            <p>This article is driven by several interlocking questions: What does the digital
               fandom of the <title rend="italic">Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> reveal, complicate, and demonstrate about
               romance, friendship, and community? Further, how does the representation of these
               stories effect their fans interior lives? How does the expression of their interior
               lives on social media build community and challenge notions of hegemonic intimacy
               that is both expressed in the interpersonal sense and in online spaces? I posit that
               by examining interpersonal intimacy and interiority in cultural productions and
               digital fandoms, we see the demonstration of the pursuit of love, wholeness, and
               intimacy as labor that sustaining acts for and by Black communities. Within the
               quotidian acts of social media usage and the small moments of reflection they
               provoke, Black fans pursue much needed forms of rest and respite in these public
               communities and find ways to self-make to imagine a different world within their own
               relationships and interrogating processes taken to heal from generational trauma,
               patterns, and actions. Black fans contend with their familial and romantic lives
               through the expression and labor for themselves of simultaneous affective and
               transformative fandom in collective digital spaces. I examine how these interactions
               serve two capacities. First, they do the meaningful and important work of recovery
               and healing for Black fandom communities to examine how hegemonic narratives about
               the intimacies of friendship, family, and romantic relationships are reinscribed
               through popular media and are challenged in the storylines and expressive digital
               fandom. Secondly, pleasure and play in fandom communities continues to foster
               personhood, worldmaking, and reimagining for Black people in the face of the
               dehumanizing power structures that they navigate daily.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Black DH: Fandom and Intimacy</head>
            <p>Intimate partnerships are an extension of where we encounter and negotiate our
               interior selves and how they are expressed outwardly. Thus, our digital selves are an
               extension of these intimate negotiations and are a site to examine how our hegemonic
               ideals about our interpersonal relationships are reinscribed, challenged, and
               co-created with others in a public domain. Affect and queer theorist Lauren Berlant’s
               theoretical framing of intimacy as an intersection of interpersonal relationships
               that reverberate publicly situates my framework on Black relationships, the digital,
               and fandom. Berlant’s definition of intimacy is <quote rend="inline">an aspiration
                  for a narrative about something shared</quote> and that <quote rend="inline">the
                  inwardness of the intimate is met by a corresponding publicness</quote>
               <ptr target="#berlant1998"/>. Berlant’s assertion is that institutions that were
               supposed to teach us <quote rend="inline">democratic publicness</quote> — a la
               Habermas — evolved and were fostered into <quote rend="inline">collective experience
                  (s)</quote> like cinema and other entertainment forms where there is <quote
                  rend="inline">the desire for entertainment taken for pleasure</quote>
               <ptr target="#berlant1998"/>. Yet intimacy also operates outside of these
               institutional realms in everyday mundane practices — such as my argument of logging
               into social media — that reproduce, challenge, and produce the stories that hegemonic
               ideals encourage us to follow concerning our intimate lives. As Berlant asserts we
               impact each other in these public ways and thus, I theorize that it also effects our
               intimate lives directly: both interpersonally and with each other in public in online
               networks.</p>
            <p>Further, utilizing Berlant’s <quote rend="inline">inwardness</quote>, I turn to
               definitions from Black studies and Black feminist scholars of interiority to assist
               in forming my critical intervention about Black digital fandom practices. As <title
                  rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> and <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>
               center a Black female protagonist, I utilize Joan Morgan’s <quote rend="inline"
                  >politics of pleasure</quote> that is invested in <quote rend="inline"><emph>black
                     female interiority</emph></quote> as it is exemplified in the storylines and
               their fandoms <ptr target="#morgan2015"/>. Morgan frames pleasure in analyzing
               cultural texts through different interventions such as the advent of social media and
               digital discourse for the possibilities of expressing interiority. Morgan’s
               definition of interiority is <quote rend="inline">to excavate the broad range of
                  feelings, desires, hearing, (erotic and otherwise) that were once deemed
                  necessarily private by the <q>politics of silence</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#morgan2015"/>. Morgan grounds her argument in Black feminist Evelynn
               Hammonds’ <quote rend="inline">politics of articulation</quote> rather than the
               respectable <quote rend="inline">politics of silence</quote> thus, black female
               interiority provides a framework to examine Black women’s sexualities <ptr
                  target="#morgan2015"/>. <title rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">Insecure</title> do not shy away from this articulation of pleasure
               and sexuality as the characters routinely question and speculate about their desires
               and intimate partnerships whether they are familial, friendship, or romantic.
               Therefore, the usage of interiority in public digital spaces go together when
               discussing the plots of the cultural productions, fans engagement with them
               digitally, and specifically how they utilize them to explore their own interpersonal
               relationships.</p>
            <p>Queer and Black feminist theories of intimacy and interiority lend itself seamlessly
               to Black digital practices as they center intimate ways of knowing and resistance as
               scholars have demonstrated. Jessica Marie Johnson provides an anecdote for my
               questions by asserting that Black people use the digital in ways that are liberatory
               and revelatory. Johnson argues <quote rend="block">that black digital practice is the
                  interface by which black freedom struggles challenge reproduction of black death
                  and commodification, countering the presumed neutrality of the digital. Black
                  digital practice is the revelation that black subjects have …commodified
                  themselves and digitized and mediated their own black freedom ideas, in order to
                  hack their way into systems …thus living where they were <q>never meant to
                     survive</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#johnson2018"/>. Black fans are exemplary to the digital practice
               Johnson describes and that Andre Brock examines in, <title rend="italic">Distributed
                  Blackness: African American Cybercultures</title>. Brock outlines that <quote
                  rend="inline">political-economic analyses foreclose the sensual, the erotic, or
                  the deviant by arguing that they have no value in a rational worldview, but the
                  denial of their exchange value does not negate their existence. How does one value
                  love or anger?</quote>
               <ptr target="#brock2020"/>. Instead, Brock argues for libidinal economy that focuses
               on Black lived experience online. Especially, because <quote rend="inline">another
                  benefit is the acknowledgement and theorization of Black communal identity as a
                  meaning-making strategy</quote>
               <ptr target="#brock2020"/>. Black digital fandom is a meaning making strategy because
               it is also libidinal as it <quote rend="inline">offers a release from considerations
                  of Black digital practice as labor or commodity</quote>
               <ptr target="#brock2020"/>. Black fandoms are labor, but a labor of love for Black
               communities in terms of navigating their interpersonal relationships. Through putting
               Brock in conversation with Berlant, I argue that the libidinal economy of Black
               digital practice is then inherently intimate. Black digital practices that are fandom
               based is entertainment taken for pleasure and thus <quote rend="inline"
                  >pleasure-knowledge creates problems for the notional rationality with which
                  collective critical consciousness is supposed to proceed</quote>
               <ptr target="#berlant1998"/>. We can return to these places as they are produced
               relationally and <quote rend="inline">produce something, though frequently not
                  history in its ordinary memorable, or valorized sense, and not always
                     <q>something</q> of positive value</quote>
               <ptr target="#berlant1998"/>. Black digital fandom practices relationally produce
               hacking their way into their own systems and presenting their whole selves to the
               world in intimate ways through the analysis and expression of interiority.</p>
            <p>Within the field of fan studies, scholars often define two distinct modes of fandom
               production and engagement: the affirmative and transformative. In the introduction of
               the <title rend="italic">Fan Studies Reader</title>, Karen Hellekson and Kristina
               Busse offer a definition of the difference between affirmative fandom and
               transformative fandom. They explain, <quote rend="inline">affirmative fans tend to
                  collect, view, and play, to discuss, analyze, and critique. Transformative fans,
                  however, take a creative step to make the worlds and characters their own, be it
                  by telling stories, cosplaying the characters, creating artworks, or engaging in
                  any of the many other forms active fan participation can take </quote>
               <ptr target="#busse2014"/>. Hellekson and Busse emphasize that many academics focus
               on the transformative creations of fandom as they are new creations and sites for
               identity formation. I argue that Black fans demonstrate an amalgamation of both
               affirmative and transformative fandom as defined by the field to morph and become
                  <emph>affirmative transformative</emph> works of fandom expression. It is
               affirmative through casual engagement with fellow fans — or those that dislike the
               cultural productions or antifans — and content creators while also being
               transformative through the creativity of Black social media users and their
               identification with fandom objects. Black digital fandom reflects both. I argue for a
               simultaneous configuration of both because the ways representation, identity, and
               function operate for Black fans. Further, the communal aspects of fandom expressed
               comprise Black digital intimacies where affective interiority and transformative
               ideals through world making and affirming are enacted. Black fans affirm the cultural
               productions because of the representation they demonstrate but also transform them
               into something else through creative usage of hashtags, podcasts, and other modes of
               creative fandom. This also works interpersonally as the feel affirmed through the
               representations they see and express personal transformation as they encounter what
               they are seeing on screen and how it reflects interpersonally in their romantic,
               familial, and friend relationships.</p>
            <p>Black fandom scholars account for the ways that fan studies has typically not
               considered Black fandom practices. Wanzo, in her critical essay about fan studies
               genealogies and citational practices calls for an <quote rend="inline">identity
                  hermeneutics</quote> which places Black fan consumption, critique, and affective
               fandom in the center of any approach to Fan Studies <ptr target="#wanzo2015"/>. I
               continue in this tradition of building upon Black fan studies scholars and how the
               field has expanded its definitions of fan works. I am in conversation with scholars
               who discuss fandom and the intersection of Black digital humanities with scholarship
               from from Kristen Warner, Aymar Jean Christian &amp; Faithe Day, Sarah Florini, Ebony
               Elizabeth Thomas [2019], as well as many other scholars in the recent special issue
               of <title rend="italic">Transformative Works and Cultures</title> on Fans of Color
               that was edited by andré carrington and Abigail De Kosnik <ptr target="#warner2015"
                  /><ptr target="#day2017"/><ptr target="#florini2019"/><ptr target="#thomas2019"
                  /><ptr target="#carrington2019"/>. The amalgamation demonstrates the ways Black
               fans digitally practice fandom in ways outside of the intended or widely adapted
               usage. Black fandom practice at times connotes a different relationship to fandom for
               several reasons. This is in part due to a dearth of representation and/or at times
               harmful stereotypical depictions of Black people in media. Fandoms of the Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and Insecure are case studies for Black digital intimacies and affirmative transformative fandoms because of the dearth of Black representation at the time of
               their debut and the ways the show continued the comedic traditions of the Black shows
               that inspired Rae. Digital intimacy as a subfield borrows from heavily from Berlant
                  <ptr target="#rambukkana2020"/><ptr target="#berlant1998"/>. I am examining how
               Black digital intimacies work through centering fandom. To support my analysis of
               Black fandom fully, I preface Black feminist thought, Black digital studies, and
               queer analysis of intimacy. Berlant centers marginalized identities that have had to
               create new ways of being intimate by emphasizing that they have, and we must <quote
                  rend="inline">rethink intimacy</quote> and to do so is <quote rend="inline">to
                  appraise how we have been and how we live and how we might imagine lives that make
                  more sense than the ones so many are living</quote><ptr target="#berlant1998"/>.
               Or as Stuart Hall asserts that Black popular culture is where <quote rend="inline">we
                  discover and play with the identifications of ourselves, where we are imagined,
                  where we are represented, not only to the audiences out there who do not get the
                  message, but to ourselves for the first time</quote>
               <ptr target="#hall1992"/>. Through digital fandom practices we can see how Black fans
               speculate, reimagine, and world-make about their lives through sharing themselves
               with the world in intimate digital spaces.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Methodology</head>
            <p>I employ close reading to analyze the cultural productions and data I gathered from
               fans through YouTube and Twitter. I also use participant observation as a
               self-identified acafan, an academic who also has insider knowledge of their object of
               study because they are also a fan, and autoethnography as I account for my own
               affective reactions to the productions. I gathered social media posts from YouTube
               from the first episode of <title rend="italic">The Misadventures of Awkward Black
                  Girl</title> and I documented conversations in real time from select episodes of
                  <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>on Twitter.</p>
            <p>As a Fan Studies and an internet scholar, I am invested in the communities I study,
               thus I aim to be ethical in how I utilize and engage data. To maintain ethical
               transparency comments that affirm fandom about the show where there doesn’t seem to
               be any identifying attributes or revealing intimate details about their lives, I
               decided to forgo permission seeking. For the fandom expressions that utilize more
               personal thought about their relationship to the fandom object, I ask for permission
               to use those fandom expressions. These issues have been debated by fandom scholars
               and digital humanities scholars and my personal decisions are led by an ethics of
               care and what revealing these intimate issues will bring to the forefront for those
               discussing information. I aim for an ethics that centers Moya Bailey’s self-reflexive
               observations when conducting online and digital research <ptr target="#bailey2015"/>.
               Bailey explores the networks Black trans women create through Twitter. Bailey employs
               a feminist tactic of informed consent to combat the paternalistic IRB process, while
               considering the types of harm surveillance and exposure can bring to their lives. As
               I study affective fandoms that center on their interpersonal lives and information it
               is important that I consider if fans wish to have their comments shared.</p>
            <p>Further, the two platforms I utilize for this article, YouTube and Twitter, have
               different affordances and terms of use and privacy policies. That necessitates a
               different engagement with the data used for each platform. I utilize pseudonyms for
               the usernames on YouTube because the platform’s privacy policy requires it. YouTube’s
               Terms of Service states the following: <quote rend="inline">The following
                  restrictions apply to your use of the Service. You are not allowed to: 3. collect
                  or harvest any information that might identify a person (for example, usernames or
                  faces), unless permitted by that person or allowed under section (3) above</quote>
               <ptr target="#youtube"/>. Thus, in order to be in alignment with my ethical
               considerations and YouTube’s agreement, I utilize specific comments and code for
               usernames. YouTube is also under the umbrella of Google products where users must use
               their e-mails and that typically features a real name over a pseudo-name.</p>
            <p>Ethically, in addition to seeking permission I use high profile Twitter users that I
               define with 5k or more followers instead of smaller accounts with more casual usage.
               As I am studying “Black Twitter” and the popularity of these cultural productions, I
               carefully choose and curate the comments I analyze, and more popular tweeters reflect
               the breadth of thoughts Black Twitter encapsulates due to their networks that produce
               high engagement. The users who have public tweets with a higher follower count expect
               to have a larger audience with their tweets circulating more heavily, especially with
               the usage of hashtags related to the popular cultural productions I am examining.
               Users with smaller accounts might understand Twitter’s platform affordance of
                  <q>publicly available</q> but may not desire to have their tweets to circulate
               beyond an audience of 200 to 500 or less due to the small nature of their accounts.
               Further, I will not use pseudonyms for usernames on Twitter as the public nature of
               the authors I use are identifiable to those who are aware of Black Twitter — both
               social media users and researchers. I also will not use any tweets that identify
               confidential information as users are tweeting their responses to the cultural
               productions. Finally, the affordances of each platform inform my decisions. Twitter
               allows me to personally message users for permission as opposed to needing to add
               another comment to the public discourse to ask for permission from YouTube. YouTube’s
               commenting communities aren’t as conversational as Twitter as a primarily
               audio-visual platform versus Twitter’s primarily text-based platform.</p>
            <p>While YouTube’s policy for publishing comments requires anonymity, Twitter does not
               require the same. Twitter user privacy policy states the following: <quote
                  rend="inline">By publicly posting content, you are directing us to disclose that
                  information as broadly as possible, including through our APIs, and directing
                  those accessing the information through our APIs to do the same…But these
                  individuals and companies are not affiliated with Twitter, and their offerings may
                  not reflect updates you make on Twitter</quote>
               <ptr target="#twitter"/>. I will utilize direct quotes and twitter usernames for the
               purposes of this research. In terms of confidentiality, I will abide by Twitter's
               rules for researchers that outlines usage of tweets that are public — not under
               private accounts — and have not been deleted, and I will abide by both rules even as
               I ask for permission.</p>
         </div>
         	<div>
            <head><title rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> Fandom </head>
            <p>I begin by emphasizing the behavior and character construction Rae develops in both
               the web series and television show as an example of interiority she heralds as an
               essential part to the popularity and thus success of the show that began on YouTube
               and propelled the producer/actor/writer to mainstream media and HBO. Specifically,
               Black digital fan expression of affirming and identifying with this iteration of
                  <q>awkwardness</q> and then <q>insecure</q> interiority connote affirmative
               transformative fandoms through Black digital intimacies on social media platforms.
               Some examples of the interiority expressed in the shows include the main character
                  <q>J</q> narrating parts of the show, or Issa — the character on <title
                  rend="italic">Insecure</title> — talking to herself in the mirror and her mirrored
               self, talking back to her. <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> also includes many
               daydream flashbacks as aesthetic and to aid plot development for the 30-minute
               comedy. Fans responded to this expression of interiority with their own thus creating
               intimate digital spaces through affirmative transformative fandom expression. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>There are Other Awkward Black Girls</head>
            <p>While interiority and intimacy can connote many different types of emotion and
               affect, I want to focus on pleasure as aforementioned by Morgan due to <title
                  rend="italic">Awkward Black Girl</title>’s and <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> comedic aesthetic, genre, and expression of a different
               representation of Black women that was lacking in the entertainment landscape at the
               time. Ariane Cruz analyses <title rend="italic">ABG</title> before <title
                  rend="italic">Insecure’s</title> 2016 premiere. Cruz argues that Rae was
               successful in exploring Black female sexuality through her usage of <q>awkward</q> in
               relation to the character’s identity and specifically J’s sexuality. Cruz contends,
                  <quote rend="inline">the epithet of awkward mediates performances of Black female
                  racial and sexual authenticity on the show, unveiling the ways that black female
                  sexuality becomes authenticated in and through its ontological failure and
                  nonbelonging, however comic</quote>
               <ptr target="#cruz2015"/>. Cruz places <title rend="italic">Awkward Black
                  Girl</title> in relation to other dominant representations of heterosexual Black
               women in the media at the time. Rae represented a different take on Black women’s
               singleness and sexuality at the time by being awkward and not being a <q>wife</q> a
               la <title rend="italic">Basketball Wives</title>, <title rend="italic">Love &amp; Hip
                  Hop</title> [all on Vh1], and <title rend="italic">The Realhousewives of Atlanta
               </title>[Bravo] as depicted in many of the popular reality TV shows that were in
               their infancy at the time <ptr target="#cruz2015"/>. Cruz analysis of Rae’s
               exploration of sexuality focuses on the plot’s themes and construction of the web
               series as other scholars such as Carmel Ohman and Yael Levy have done for <title
                  rend="italic">Insecure </title>concerning the same interior subject <ptr
                  target="#ohman2020"/><ptr target="#levy2020"/>. I argue that understanding the
               behavior mediation of awkward and insecurity that <title rend="italic">ABG</title>
               and eventually <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> underscores alongside the fandom
               provides another analysis of the work these shows are doing for Black fans. Studying
               the series plot and aesthetic choices paired with fandom engagement demonstrates how
               a breadth of expressed emotions are received by fans — we can learn what fans learn
               from and ultimately do with their fandoms. </p>
            <p>Additionally, Rae took advantage of YouTube’s new media promise through their slogan
                  <quote rend="inline">Broadcast Yourself</quote> through passing some of the
               constraints and challenges that come from pursuing a greenlight from traditional
               media may have posed. Aymar Jean Christian’s book <title rend="italic">Open TV:
                  Innovation Beyond Hollywood and the Rise of Web Television</title> examines the
               ways in which web series become sites where producers and content creators can
               connect directly due to the digital nature of the comment section <ptr
                  target="#christian2018"/>. Christian’s argument is that web series allow for Black
               creators, who have been marginalized from the process of producing shows on
               mainstream television, to produce original content without the <quote rend="inline"
                  >single-story/cookie-cutter</quote> narrative mainstream producers perpetuate. By
               examining the digital ways fans interact and reflect on their fandom object,
               specifically focusing on the interiority expressed, I trace how digital community
               intimacy is built and how fans reflect interact with their fandom objects. YouTube
               prefaces audio-visual consumption due to its platform affordances and the commentary
               and interaction happens after an episode airs unless it is a live streaming event as
               opposed to Twitter where one can tweet simultaneously. Therefore, comment sections
               often reflect affirmative fandom which is the fandom that discusses and analyzes <ptr
                  target="#busse2014"/>. Analyzing representation alongside platform affordances,
               Christian continues, <quote rend="inline">She (Issa) created an original
                  representation and then experimented with distribution in ways that deviated from
                  and continued a tradition beginning with BET. <title rend="italic">Awkward Black
                     Girl</title> proposes to represent its community of fans — primarily but not
                  exclusively black women — in a way unseen on legacy television, and does so
                  convincingly</quote>
               <ptr target="#christian2018"/>. The web series allowed for Rae to <quote
                  rend="inline">push the boundaries of normative Black female representation</quote>
               <ptr target="#christian2018"/>. I argue that mainstream television has seen awkward
               Black girls in mainstream television before 2011. Characters such as Sinclair from
                  <title rend="italic">Living Single</title>, Lynn from <title rend="italic"
                  >Girlfriends</title>, Kim Parker from <title rend="italic">Moesha</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">The Parkers</title> can arguably be seen as source references
               for J’s character. However, to build upon Christian’s point, new media allowed Rae
               the opportunity to circumvent censorship of legacy media by expressing explicit
               sexuality, as Cruz analyses <ptr target="#christian2018"/><ptr target="#cruz2015"/>.
               To reiterate, the awkward mediation adds another layer of interiority and thus
               identification with fans while YouTube provides a platform for fans to comment.</p>
            <p>In the comment portion of <title rend="italic">ABG</title>’s first episode, “The Stop
               Sign” which was uploaded to YouTube on February 3, 2011, fans readily affirm the show
               and relate to Issa’s short pilot episode — only 3 minutes and 40 seconds — where she
               introduces us to her awkward relationships with her coworkers, ex-boyfriend, and
               ultimately herself. The episode introduces us to J’s world where she states that she
               is Black and awkward which are <quote rend="inline">the two worst things anyone can
                  be</quote>” <ptr target="#rae2011"/>. To sum the episode: J pretends to be in a
               music video when she’s by herself in the car, tries to avoid her co-worker at
               stop-signs as they both drive in their respective cars to work, shows a montage of
               her boyfriend breaking up with her, J’s subsequent sleeping with the co-worker she’s
               trying to avoid because of her heartbreak, and making up rap lyrics disparaging the
               ex-boyfriend as coping mechanisms. J narrates the episode with rhetorical questions
               to set up her awkward misadventures. J’s awkwardness and Rae’s scripting drew the
               audience in and resulted in fans affirming the series through their comments. As
               representation for a new audience in the landscape of Black media in the early 2010s,
               women identified with a representation that reflects their interiority and could
               express it to the creator and others on YouTube. Under the first episode, a
               commenting fan wrote, <quote rend="block">BAHAHAHAHAA my first time watching this
                  [yes, I live under a rock] and I am soooo happy to find another "awkward black
                  girl" like myself :,D don't feel so alone in this world happy dance I also shaved
                  my head to change my life's scenery, loved a guy named "D" [big mistake __], and
                  rap/sing while alone while trying SO hard not to have a nicki vibe XD lolz, <ref
                     target="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=%23sigh">#sigh</ref> what
                  i'm trying to say is: you're cool, and ima insta-fan :]</quote>
               <ptr target="#commentingABG2011"/>. The fan affirms every aspect of J’s character in
               the episode relating to being another awkward Black girl. The fan also includes
               reference to Nicki Minaj, a rapper known for her sexually explicit lyrics and
               branding representation as J’s character raps an original song for the show about a
               rapper’s sexual exploits. The fan also shaved her head to <quote rend="inline"
                  >change</quote> her <quote rend="inline">life’s scenery</quote>, and made a <quote
                  rend="inline">mistake</quote> loving a guy named D like J did in the episode.
               These other interior expressions of the fans’ life are both affirmative of the show,
               while being transformative to her life personally due to her relationship with the
               show and being <quote rend="inline">happy to find another <q>awkward black girl</q>
                  like myself</quote>. By commenting her pleasure with the show, she is invoking an
               affirmative transformative work and Black digital intimacy through naming herself a
               fan for Rae and others to see. It is affirmative by praising the show but also
               transformative that she can relate to and laugh about her interior and interpersonal
               relationships in the process.</p>
            <p>Generally, fans also expressed desire for the show to remain small to insulate it
               from changes that can happen on a larger production stage. One commenting fans
               discusses this aspect specifically: <quote rend="block">I've watched the whole
                  season, and I know this is selfish to say, but I don't want this show to be on TV,
                  I want it to be my little secret, and plus if it was TV it wouldn't be the same,
                  they would have to censor everything, but at the same time I would want this show
                  to make a lot of money, they deserve it, good script</quote>
               <ptr target="#commentingABG2011"/>. The fan affirms the series, recognizes the
               platform affordances, but also transformatively understands its impact on the
               industry, and to a certain extent, other fans through sharing. I also recognize this
               comment to express affective ownership of the show as they identified so closely and
               enjoyed the web series, while also wanting it to do well without losing authenticity.
               Black fans have had a contentious relationship to media forms regarding
               representation. Alfred L. Martin’s describes the political ways Black fans engage
               with their fandom objects. The four interlocking discourses Martin introduces are:
               must-see blackness, economic consumption, pedagogical properties, and understanding
               the machinations of the culture industries <ptr target="#martin2019"/>. The comment
               about the show not being censored but desiring it to make a lot of money collapses
               three of Martin’s assertions: the move to television and the potential economic boost
               underscores fan understanding the precarity of Black media such that it becomes
               must-see by knowing that money talks to produce more representations of Black media.
               The comment also prescribes Martin’s fourth way that Black fans engage through
               pedagogical properties which are the ways Black fans examine <quote rend="inline">how
                  fit fan objects are for learning and role modeling</quote> or <quote rend="inline"
                  >what can be learned from a particular fan object</quote> about how to move
               throughout the world as a Black person <ptr target="#martin2019"/>. Relatedly, to
               Martin’s exploration of Black fans I assert that the pedagogical properties for Black
               fans where pleasure and interiority allow them to learn more about their own
               interpersonal lives through transformative affective fandoms. Simply, what can fans
               learn about themselves with each other and from these cultural productions to
               world-build their own romantic, familial, and friend relationships?</p>
            <p>Another fan that commented on the show supports this the pedagogical effects of
               learning about oneself after watching a trailer for <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> on HBO in 2016 before its premiere. She claims, <quote
                  rend="block">Just saw the trailer for her new HBO show and had to come back and
                  reminisce. In high school, there was no show on television I could relate to. Then
                  a friend told me about this show and I was hooked instantly. I'm overjoyed Issa
                  made the bold choice to share with the world her incredible talents. And, in doing
                  that, she gave so many of us a show we could actually relate to and helped us
                  realize we weren't the only awkward black girl out there. So proud of Issa. I
                  can't wait for Insecure to air!</quote>
               <ptr target="#commentingABG2011"/>. She has learned that she is essentially not alone
               in her understanding of herself as she was represented in media. Notably, the
               comments I’ve chosen and their specific refrain of relating to the <q>awkward</q> is
               important as it created bonds both digitally and in their personal lives to the
               television show. They are learning from their interior lives that they are not alone
               in how they feel as <q>awkward back girls</q> even with their <q>awkward</q>
               sexualities that aren’t mired in the types of sexualities that were circulating
               widely in the media at the time. The digital intimacy Rae fostered for her fans to
               explore and world-build through continued with <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>.
               The popularity of the series garnered a built-in audience for <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> to build upon and shifted to other social media platforms,
               namely, Twitter and Black Twitter specifically.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>A Real Ass Conversation</head>
            <p>Once <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> premiered on HBO, Rae could push the
               boundaries of sexual expression to become more explicit and kept the affective
               interior plot device of being centered on one behavior from awkward to insecure. Cruz
               later acknowledges in the <title rend="italic">ABG</title> article concerns about the
               creative authenticity in the show as it transitioned in form and platform from
               YouTube to HBO <ptr target="#cruz2015"/>. Rae curated <title rend="italic"
                  >ABG</title> alongside Tracy Oliver as independent creators with full creative
               control as they didn’t have to answer to television executives about the direction of
               the series. While Cruz’s concerns were valid as the platform changed, they were
               expanded in an innovative way through the insecure mediation and pushing the
               boundaries of storytelling due to HBO’s established credibility in television.
               Specifically, with the move to HBO, Rae certainly pushed the sexual, language,
               aesthetics, and content boundaries even further, which may be an affordance of HBO as
               a platform that regularly pursues characters with blatant and expressed sexuality. As
               an innovative story arc, Rae flipped the romantic aspects of the show by depicting
               the woman cheating on her boyfriend, which is typically represented as a man cheating
               on a woman when heterosexual storylines are depicted. The audience is also privy to how issues in her relationship also reverberated in other areas of her life, such as her career and friendships. <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>’s characters are educated
               30-somethings that run in a tight circle with each other due to romantic,
               professional, and friendship connections in present day Los Angeles. As viewers, we
               can explore the main character’s motivations through the long arc of many of the
               ancillary characters and how they navigate their many insecurities with themselves,
               their relationships, and their careers.</p>
            <p>One evening on Twitter resulted in a flurry of conversation as a major turning point
               in the plot of <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>. The comments happened in
               response to a conversation between Lawrence, Issa’s ex, and his new romantic
               interest, Tasha, on the third episode of the second season <title rend="quotes">Hella
                  Open</title> where she calls him out on his actions, which inevitably ends their
               connection. The first season chronicled how Issa and Lawrence’s relationship devolved
               from what appeared to be Lawrence’s retreat into himself after losing his job and
               subsequently the loss of intimacy in their relationship. Instead of ending it, Issa
               cheated, and Lawrence enters a rebounding <q>friends with benefits</q> relationship
               with Tasha who he met at his bank. He told Tasha that he would return to help her
               with her family’s cookout and doesn’t return from leaving to drink with his new
               co-workers. Tasha calls out the ways his intentions, both in words and actions, don’t
               align and is evident when he attempts to apologize for his actions by citing that he
               wasn’t ready for a serious relationship. She calls out his lack of accountability by
               stating that he is <quote rend="inline">a fuck nigga…who is worse than fuck nigga.
                  You a fuck nigga who thinks he’s a good dude.</quote>
               <ptr target="#insecure2017"/>. Lawrence’s <q>good guy</q> credibility is questioned.
               I found myself engaging with the dialogue on my timeline as I follow many fans of the
               show and realized at this point that I wanted to study <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title> rather than remaining only a fan of the web series and at the
               time the new the show on HBO. The sympathy fans garnered for Lawrence being cheated
               on were placed under scrutiny because of his behavior with Tasha.</p>
            <p>I follow the author of one fan that tweeted a long thread after that episode. In it,
               @peoplesoracle writes about her views on relationships that was spurred by Lawrence’s
               behavior. She did not use the #InsecureHBO hashtag to make her comments visible to
               the fans and Twitter users that might click on the hashtag. This could be due to not
               wanting to engage in the dialogue about the show that centers hegemonic
               representations of relationships as she instead pushes the boundaries of these
               constructions with her comments or wanting the thread to stay within the confines of
               her followers. Black digital intimacy and knowledge of the timeline topics assisted
               me in knowing that she was indeed discussing <title rend="italic">Insecure</title> at
               the beginning of the thread without mentioning characters. The fan states that she
               wishes to <quote rend="inline">preach a sermon</quote> — which is a nod to Black
               oration and church culture — and discusses her views about the scene. In a thread
               with over 30 tweets, she discusses accountability and relationships needing core
               values as well as for a relationship to change you with the desire to change for the
               better <ptr target="#peoplesoracle2017"/>. She expounds upon relationship requiring
               skills and that Lawrence’s lack of self-reflection meant that he did not possess
               those skills by stating: <quote rend="inline">If being a <q>good guy</q> or <q>not
                     one of those chicks</q> means that you can get to stay exactly who you are,
                  then you can stay exactly by yourself</quote>
               <ptr target="#peoplesoracle2017"/>. At the end of the thread, she mentions how she
               wishes her future relationships to <quote rend="inline">aid me in becoming more in
                  alignment with my core values</quote>
               <ptr target="#peoplesoracle2017"/>. Bringing her thoughts back to Lawrence and
               reading a <q>real life</q> situation into Lawrence’s actions she states, <quote
                  rend="inline">So many say they want that. But like Lawrence, they act shocked and
                  appalled when it’s time to stand &amp; be accountable. He wasn’t sorry.
                  tuh.</quote>” <ptr target="#peoplesoracle2017"/>. She then drops the proverbial
               mic by tweeting <quote rend="inline">Love = accountability/fin</quote>
               <ptr target="#peoplesoracle2017"/>. This thread is an example of affirmative
               transformative fandom as she expresses her thoughts about the show, her thoughts
               about relationships, and refers to her own experience. Her tweets garnered a modest
               amount of engagement and several people responded with various affirmative memes to
               her comments about the show and relationships. Her interior life as expressed on
               Twitter exemplifies Black digital intimacies as others joined in by affirming her
               comments. It is also transformative as other fans possibly learned something new
               about themselves building upon Martin’s argument about the pedagogical aspects of
               Black fandom <ptr target="#martin2019"/>. They could reflect about their own
               relationships thus constitute world-building, rethinking, and reimagining their own
               intimate lives. The original fan also stated that she was considering putting the
               thread on her blog, which is another iteration of Black digital intimacies where she
               can engage another audience. The thread is an example of self-making and the
               affective usage of digital platforms that Black DH brings to the discipline of Black
               Studies, Fan Studies, and Digital Humanities.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of the fourth season Lawrence and Issa encounter each other enough
               through mutual friends and situations that keep them in each other’s orbits. They
               decided to meet up and have a conversation about the demise of their relationship as
               a way of closure. <title rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic"
                  >Insecuri</hi>tea</title> is an HBO sponsored podcast about <title
                  rend="italic">Insecure</title> by @crissles and @heyfranhey, two prominent podcast
               hosts with their own amassed followings due to their podcasts <title rend="italic"
                  >The Read</title> and <title rend="italic">The Friend Zone</title>, respectively.
               The recaps of the show are another place of intimacy where fans can immerse
               themselves further as a fan practice to produce self-making. By naming it <title
                  rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">Insecuri</title>tea</title>, Rae signals that
               the podcast is a Black fan space to further explore the real world and fictional
               implications of the show. <q>Spilling tea</q> is a Black American queer lexicon of
               providing the latest information and/or gossip about a person but has expanded to
               indicate a hot topic or other salacious information. Rae is directly marketing to her
               targeted audience, those who know Black idioms thus indicating that this show is for
               Black audiences.</p>
            <p>As an example, the episode <title rend="quotes">Lowkey Happy</title> aired on the
               Sunday after heightened protests due to news circulating around George Floyd’s death
               which defined the Summer of 2020 worldwide amidst Covid-19 pandemic <ptr
                  target="#insecure2020"/>. One of the hosts, @crissles, of <title rend="quotes"
                     ><title rend="italic">Insecuri</title>tea</title> primed the audience for the
               show’s distractive nature from the constant news cycle when she tweeted: <quote
                  rend="inline">if you need a break from reality you should *definitely* tune in to
                  Insecure tonight, trust me. #InsecureHOB #Insecuritea</quote>” <ptr
                     target="#crissles2020"/>. At the time of writing this article, the engagement on the tweet had 299 and over 1,300 likes as her followers anticipated her
               livetweeted thoughts about the show. A few minutes later during the episode,
               @crissles later commented about the dialogue on the show <quote rend="inline">a real
                  ass conversation only happens when both people are ready to put down their ego and
                  be vulnerable. #InsecureHBO #Insecuritea</quote>” <ptr target="#crissles2020"/>.
               This tweet garnered over 3,300 retweets and over 8,600 likes as it centered the more
               mature characterization the fans were seeing in the development of the characters.
               While much of the conflict and drama in the series consisted of the characters acting
               out of their insecurity, fans anticipated this episode as they saw the reconciliation
               of the main characters through relationship closure and them ending the show by
               engaging in sex after their conversation. While retweets and likes do not necessarily
               signpost agreement, they do demonstrate popularity and engagement with the sentiment
               and discourse surrounding the show. As a popular podcaster and the official show’s
               podcaster @crissles is also asserting and advertising her insider positionality to
               promote the show, the podcast, and continue to create community around both by using
               the hashtags. While the first tweet about the nature of the show is not affirmative
               transformative fandom, it does connote Black digital intimacy. Temporally, the show
               acted as a reprieve from the news cycle for Black Twitter users who <quote
                  rend="inline">come together as a family</quote> — an oft repeated phrase — for
               livetweeting Black cultural productions.</p>
            <p>Rae is aware of the effects of fandom and social media’s affordances and how it
               fosters fan engagement and growth from fans, thus fans can continue to engage with
               the content beyond the episodes. The podcast is corporately sponsored by HBO;
               however, the emphasis is on what the episode can do transformatively for audiences in
               the crisis of the protests and recognizing continuing police brutality. To that end
               @crissles realizes the cultural necessity of the moment and the digital intimacy that
               formed by Black Twitter users and fans of the show. The second tweet about the <quote
                  rend="inline">real ass conversation</quote> is affirmative transformative fandom
               in the same way @peoplesoracle’s thread is in that it is expressing commentary on a
               general observation about relationships <ptr target="#crissles2020"/>. Add in the
               specific analysis on the stagnation or growth of the characters interior lives while
               indicating hashtags to inform followers about the context of the tweets. It is
               affirmative in the sense that it supports the show's development and transformative in
               the way that one can reflect upon and think about their own egos and vulnerability
               when it comes to their interpersonal relationships. The interiority reflected upon is
               done publicly with other fans and we can learn a lot about the status of
               interpersonal relationships from these fandom exchanges as fans engage with each
               other.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>By focusing on Black digital intimacies in Black Digital Humanities we can delve into
               the ways in which culture can assist in identity development beyond hegemonic
               representations and center the quotidian. Another aspect of my research, and other
               Black digital humanists, contend that Black life is not always about recovering and
               responding to the injury of white supremacy, but that the mundane and quotidian
               aspects of life, like social media usage, should be considered as well. This is a
               project of Black DH as Kim Gallon writes, <quote rend="inline">Black studies as a
                  unique role to play in dismembering how we think about humanity and the digital
                  humanities by extension. A black epistemology will generate questions about the
                  relationship between the racialization of humanity and the digital as power,
                  ultimately fostering new inquiries and deeper understandings about the human
                  condition</quote>” <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>. Through studying
               digital fandom, epistemologies of interiority as expressed in cultural productions
               and fueled by Black digital intimacies opens a world of understanding about the human
               condition. As evidenced by @crissles stating that watching the show would be a break
               from the world in 2020. In a <title rend="italic">Cosmopolitan</title> article, Rae
               was asked about the intention of centering the mundane. The interviewer states <quote
                  rend="inline"><hi rend="italic">Insecure</hi> also proves that it’s OK to just
                  show the mundaneness of black lives — not everything needs to be about harrowing
                  black suffering, which can be overwhelming</quote>” <ptr target="#jerkins2017"/>.
               Rae replies, <quote rend="inline">It’s important to show the mundaneness because it
                  shows us as human, and we don’t get to have those moments of celebrating
                  ourselves. We have a very specific struggle even in the mundane, like with
                  microaggressions. But that doesn’t mean the world stops. We still keep moving.
                  We’re so trained to continue</quote>
               <ptr target="#jerkins2017"/>. Affirmative transformative usage of the digital and
               understanding of fandom practices centers how we continue and open ourselves up to
               the world to foster new connections online and in our personal lives. The small ways
               Black people experience joy and heal their intimate relationships drives my interest
               in this subject. I center Black intimacies because I believe by centering affect and
               how communities relate to each other and attempt to express joy, healing,
               forgiveness, and pleasure that the propensity for activism against oppression is
               strengthened. We go on.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crissles2020" label="@crissles 2020"> @crissles. (2020, May 31). <title
                  rend="italic">Twitter</title>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="peoplesoracle2017" label="@peoplesoracle 2017"> @peoplesoracle. (2017,
               August 6). <title rend="italic">Twitter</title>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bailey2015" label="Bailey 2015">Bailey, Moya (2015). <title rend="quotes"
                  >#transform(ing)DH writing and research: An autoethnography of digital humanities
                  and feminist ethics</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>. 9.2. <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="betancourt2020" label="Betancourt 2020">Betancourt, Bianca (2020). <title
                  rend="quotes">Issa Rae knows fans will be ‘mad’ following tonight’s insecure
                  season final</title>. <title rend="italic">harpersbazaar.com</title>. <ref
                  target="https://www.harpersbazaar.com/culture/film-tv/a32861295/issa-rae-insecure-season-finale-interview/"
                  >https://www.harpersbazaar.com/culture/film-tv/a32861295/issa-rae-insecure-season-finale-interview/</ref></bibl>



            <bibl xml:id="berlant1998" label="Berlant 1998">Berlant, Lauren (1998). <title
                  rend="quotes">Intimacy: A special issue</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical
                  Inquiry</title>. 24.2: 281–288.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="brock2020" label="Brock 2020">Brock, Andre 2020. <title rend="italic"
                  >Distributed Blackness: African American Cybercultures</title>. New York, NY: New
               York University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="busse2014" label="Busse and Hellekson 2014">Busse, K, &amp; Hellekson, K.
               (2014). <title rend="italic">The Fan Fiction Studies Reader</title> Iowa City:
               University of Iowa Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="carrington2019" sortKey="Carrington" label="carrington and De Kosnik 2019"> carrington, a. and
               De Kosnik, A. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Fans of color, fandoms of color</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Transformative Works and Cultures</title>. 29. <ref
                  target="https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/issue/view/52"
                  >https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/issue/view/52</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="christian2018" label="Christian 2018">Christian, Aymar Jean (2018). <title
                  rend="italic">Open TV: Innovation Beyond Hollywood and the Rise of Web
                  Television</title>. New York: New York University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="cruz2015" label="Cruz 2015">Cruz A. (2015). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Mis(Playing) blackness: Rendering Black female sexuality in <title rend="italic"
                     >The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl</title></title>. In T. Melancon &amp;
               J.M. Braxton (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Black Female Sexualities</title>. New
               Brunswick, New Jersey: Rutgers University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="commentingABG2011" label="Commenting ABG Fan #1, #2, #3">Commenting ABG
               Fan #1, #2, #3. (2011). <title rend="quotes">AWKWARD Black Girl | “The Stop Sign” (S.
                  1, Ep.1)</title>, <title rend="italic">YouTube</title> video. 3:40.<ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIVa9lxkbus"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIVa9lxkbus</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="day2017" label="Day and Christian 2017">Day, F. and Christian A.J. (2017).
                  <title rend="quotes">Locating Black queer TV: Fans, producers, and networked
                  publics on YouTube</title>. <title rend="italic">Transformative Works and
                  Cultures</title>. 24. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2017.0867"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2017.0867</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="florini2019" label="Florini 2019">Florini, F. (2019). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Enclaving and cultural resonance in Black <title rend="italic">Game of
                     Thrones</title> fandom</title>. <title rend="italic">Transformative Works and
                  Cultures</title>.29. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2019.1498"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2019.1498</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. (2016), <title rend="quotes"
                  >Making a case for the Black digital humanities</title>. In M. K. Gold &amp; L. F.
               Klein (Eds.). <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities.</title>
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="insecure2017" label="Insecure 2017"><title rend="italic">Insecure</title>.
               (2017). <title rend="quotes">Hella Open</title>. <title rend="italic">HBO</title>
               video. Season 2, episode 3.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="insecure2020" label="Insecure 2020"><title rend="italic">Insecure</title>.
               (2020). <title rend="quotes">Lowkey Happy</title>. <title rend="italic">HBO</title>
               video. Season 4, episode 8. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hall1992" label="Hall 1992">Hall, Stuart (1992). <title rend="quotes">What
                  is this ‘black’ in black popular culture?</title> Wallace, Michele, and Dia Center
               for the Arts (New York, N.Y.). <hi rend="italic">Black Popular Culture</hi>. Edited
               by Gina Dent, Bay Press, 1992.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="jelks2019" label="Jelks and Hardison 2019">Jelks, Randal Maurice, &amp;
               Hardison, Ayesha K. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Black love after E. Franklin
                  Frazier: An introduction</title>. <title rend="italic">Women, Gender, and
                  Families of Color</title>. 7:2: 108-12. <ref
                  target="doi:10.5406/womgenfamcol.7.2.0108"
               >doi:10.5406/womgenfamcol.7.2.0108</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="jerkins2017" label="Jerkins 2017">Jerkins, Morgan (2017, July 24). <title
                  rend="quotes">Issa Rae talks <title rend="italic">Insecure</title>, sex scenes,
                  and Black female friendship</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >cosmopolitan.com</title>. <ref
                  target="https://www.cosmopolitan.com/entertainment/tv/a10347648/issa-rae-insecure-season-2-interview/"
                  >https://www.cosmopolitan.com/entertainment/tv/a10347648/issa-rae-insecure-season-2-interview/</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson2018">Johnson, Jessica Marie. (2018). <title
                  rend="quotes">Markup bodies</title>. <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>.
               36.4: 57–79. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="levy2020" label="Levy 2020">Levy, Yael. (2020). <title rend="quotes">A
                  sexual subject: Black women’s sexuality in <title rend="italic"
                  >Insecure</title></title>. <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Studies</title>.
               21.7: 1209-1221.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="martin2019" label="Martin 2019">Martin, Alfred L. (2019). <title
                  rend="quotes">Fandom while Black: Misty Copeland, <title rend="italic">Black
                     Panther</title>, Tyler Perry and the Contours of US Black
                  fandoms</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of Cultural
                  Studies</title>. 22.6: 737–753.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="morgan2015" label="Morgan 2015">Morgan, Joan. (2015). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Why we get off: Moving towards a Black feminist politics of
                  pleasure</title>. <title rend="italic">The Black Scholar</title>. 45.4: 36–46. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ohman2020" label="Ohman 2020">Ohman, C. (2020). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Undisciplining the Black pussy: Pleasure, Black feminism, and sexuality in Issa
                  Rae's <title rend="italic">Insecure</title></title>. <title rend="italic">Black
                  Scholar</title>. 50.2: 5–15.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="rae2011" label="Rae 2011">[Rae 2011] Rae, Issa. (2011). <title
                  rend="italic">The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl.</title>
               <title rend="quotes">The Stop Sign</title>. <title rend="italic">YouTube</title>
               video. Season 1, Episode 1. Stable URL: <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIVa9lxkbus&amp;t=5s"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIVa9lxkbus&amp;t=5s</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rambukkana2020" label="Rambukkana and Wong 2020">Rambukkana, Nathan &amp;
               Wang, Keer (2020).
	       <title rend="quotes">Digital Intimacies</title>.
	       <title rend="italic">Oxford Bibliographies</title>.
	       <ref target="doi:10.1093/OBO/9780199756841-0250">doi:10.1093/OBO/9780199756841-0250</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="youtube" label="YouTube Terms of Service"><title rend="quotes">Terms of
                  Service</title>. <title rend="italic">YouTube</title> Stable URL: <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/static?template=terms"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/static?template=terms</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="thomas2019" label="Thomas 2019">Thomas, Ebondy Elizabeth (2019). <title
                  rend="italic">The Dark Fantastic: Race and the Imagination from Harry Potter to
                  The Hunger Games</title>. New York: New York University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="twitter" label="Twitter Privacy Policy"><title rend="quotes">Twitter
                  privacy policy</title>. <title rend="italic">Twitter</title>. <ref
                  target="https://twitter.com/en/privacy">https://twitter.com/en/privacy</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="walker1983" label="Walker 1983"> Walker Alice (1983). <title rend="italic"
                  >In Search of Our Mothers' Gardens: Womanist Prose</title>. 1st ed. San Diego:
               Harcourt Brace Jovanovich.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wanzo2015" label="Wanzo 2015">Wanzo, Rebecca.(2015). <title rend="quotes"
                  >African American acafandom and other strangers: New genealogies of fan
                  studies</title>. <title rend="italic">Transformative Works and Cultures</title>.
               20. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2015.0699"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3983/twc.2015.0699</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wanzo2011" label="Wanzo 2011">Wanzo Rebecca (2011). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Black love is not a fairytale</title>. <title rend="italic">Poroi</title>.
               7.2.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="warner2015" label="Warner 2015">Warner, Kristen J. (2015). <title
                  rend="quotes">ABC’s <title rend="italic">Scandal</title> and Black women’s
                  fandom</title>. In E. Levine (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Cupcakes, Pinterest, and
                  Ladyporn: Feminized Popular Culture in the Early Twenty-First Century</title>.
               University of Illinois Press.</bibl>


         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
