<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Review of <title rend="italic">Twitter and Tear
                  Gas</title></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Nanditha <dhq:family>Narayanamoorthy</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>nanditha@yorku.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy is a Doctoral Candidate in the Department of
                     Humanities at York University, Canada. Their research is focused on the
                     interrogation of digital communities in the Global South through the study of
                     digital protest movements. Nanditha is an active member of the York Centre for
                     Asian Research (YCAR) and The Canadian Society for Digital Humanities
                     (CSDH/SCHN) and is published in <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le Champ
                        Numérique</title> and <title rend="italic">The Journal of Social Media and
                        Society</title>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000535</idno>
            <idno type="volume">015</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2021-03-05">5 March 2021</date>
            <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2021-01-02" who="jmurel">created review fiel</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Zeynep Tufekci’s book <title rend="italic">Twitter and Tear Gas</title> (Yale University Press; 2017) speaks to
               high-profile, anti-authoritarian networked protests. She engages with street protests
               and online movements to bring new perspectives and dialogues on the need for
               reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces, and the trajectories of these
               social movements online. Her work contributes to scholarship in digital activism, and
               digital humanities in the context of networked movements.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Review of Zeynep Tufekci’s <title rend="italic">Twitter and Tear Gas</title> (2017)</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Zeynep Tufekci’s book <title rend="italic">Twitter and Tear Gas</title>, even within its
               title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and
               anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a <quote rend="inline"
                  >reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as
                  well</quote>
               <ptr target="#tufecki2017" loc="x"/>. Her study eloquently engages with street
               protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street
               in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to
               systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a
               reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social
               movements online.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Positionality</head>
            <p>As a social scientist, activist, programmer and faculty member in the Sociology
               Department at the University of North Carolina, Tufekci is uniquely positioned to
               underscore the metamorphosis that digital affordances have enabled in social
               mechanisms of protest. As a scholar of social movements and surveillance, Tufekci’s
               work explores digital protest at the interstices of technology, society, effects of
               big data on politics and the public sphere. With her background in Computer Science,
               she is able to offer a counter-discourse to Silicon Valley’s techno-utopianism, and
               her work disrupts the view that social media and tech companies have built over the
               years – that they are neutral, passive or even positive platforms affecting change in
               society. At this juncture, she locates the rise of Facebook, Twitter, and Google in
               relation to contemporary social movements. Her research could potentially be
               considered a repository of protest movements across the globe, and a comparativist
               analysis could engender the strengths they could draw from each other. Owing to
               versatility of her own disciplines, her research can be made available to a wide
               range of audiences and can function as a textbook or an academic resource within the
               university and beyond. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Attention over Information</head>
            <p>In Twitter and Tear Gas, Tufekci argues for both strengths and weaknesses;
               affordances and constraints of social media in organized digital protests, as she
               quotes historian Melvin Kranzberg from 1985, <quote rend="inline">Technology is
                  neither good nor bad; nor is it neutral</quote>
               <ptr target="#tufecki2017" loc="263"/>. Social media movements, in short, can both
               empower and keep protests from attaining their capacities. Her work speaks volumes on
               the technological affordances that accompany modern protest cultures to accomplish a
                  <q>coming together</q> of a large networked public in the overthrow of
               anti-authoritarian institutions and power structures. In tandem, Tufekci contends a
               fundamental fragility of leaderless networked movements that function ad hoc,
               providing flexibility to anyone who wishes to join and their debilitating lack of
               organization, authority and negotiation, when required. The ability to grow rapidly
               encompasses a lack of organization, a phenomenon she terms <q>tactical freeze</q> or
               an inability to enable tactical maneuvering. Moreover, as a techno-sociologist,
               Tufekci aptly identifies new media challenges of attention over information and new
               non-traditional forms of gatekeeping. According to the author, the new networked
               public sphere enables the amplification and abundance of false and unverified
               information <ptr target="#tufecki2017" loc="39"/> to <quote rend="inline">distract
                  the audience, dilute attention, and sow fear and doubt in their minds</quote>
               <ptr target="#tufecki2017" loc="228–229"/>. Tufekci highlights <quote rend="inline"
                  >the importance of attention as a key resource for social media movements,</quote>
               and underscores how <quote rend="inline">Facebook, Google and Twitter monetize
                  attention in ways that may or may not be conducive to the success of protest
                  movements online</quote>
               <ptr target="#tufecki2017" loc="270"/>. In short, our move to digital technologies
               has enabled a trend where attention is manufactured as part of an emerging economy,
               and social media choreographs it as a tool to control and manipulate the masses. The
               book deftly maneuvers between the success of attention building in online activism
               and its challenges in the form of algorithmic control through bully bots and
               censorship by denial of attention, implemented by governments or private companies
               that seek to distract and exhaust both user and participant from partaking in the
               movement. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Social Media Platforms</head>
            <p>Pragmatically, Tufekci explores the role of policies of larger social media platforms
               like Facebook, Google and Twitter that contribute aptly to the discussion on the
               softer biopolitics of algorithmic control. For example, Facebook’s real name policy
               that effectively disrupts protester experience and Twitter’s mention policy that
               generates attention across the platform are two mechanisms of algorithmic ebb and
               flow that create and disrupt success of protest movements online. Furthermore,
               protests, here, are an example of a signal that corresponds to one of several
               underlying capacities: narrative, disruptive and electoral capacities that are, in
               essence, muscles that need to be always prepared, and will enable a movement to scale
               enough to fight anti-authoritarian institutions.</p>
            <p>The non-chronological order of the discussions of power and fragility of protest
               movements online unnerves and oftentimes exhausts the reader. Nevertheless, there
               remains an effective freshness to the argument of technological non-neutrality that
               Tufekci constructs. She plays to her strengths as both a social scientist and
               ethnographer engaged in protest fieldwork across the world, and a programmer who
               studies algorithmic affordances, in the construction of a dialogue surrounding both
               online and offline protests. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>At the Intersection of Social Justice and Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>Tufekci’s project undertakes a broad investigation of digital activism, uncovers key
               players that influence the relationship between technology and contemporary social
               protest, and reflects on the power of attention over information in the age of New
               Media. Her work reconceptualizes social media movements in a new light, and applies
               rigorous empirical social science research to demonstrate the future of protest in
               digital media. She connects her discourse at the intersection of social justice,
               digital activism, and Digital Humanities. Although social science research in
               activism and Digital Humanities carries an important distinction, Digital Humanities
               scholar Roopika Risam argues that <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities methods can
                  be effective tools for calling attention to, and enabling social activism,
                  particularly for marginalized communities</title>
               <ptr target="#bagger2018"/>. According to Risam, <quote rend="inline">Digital
                  Humanities makes activism possible, offering hope for re-appropriating knowledge
                  production</quote>
               <ptr target="#bagger2018"/>. Digital humanists are poised to contribute to studies of
               social media activism through research, teaching, and community outreach and
               engagement. Digital Humanities envisions social media as a positive tool for
               transformative social change in digital activism, and for highlighting the scope and
               content of a humanistic inquiry. Although Tufekci’s <title rend="italic">Twitter and
                  Tear Gas</title> lacks the humanistic perspective in its study of protest
               movements online that other scholars in Digital Humanities like Elizabeth Losh <ptr
                  target="#losh2014"/>, Moya Bailey, Sarah Jackson, Brooke Foucault Welles <ptr
                  target="#bailey2019"/>
               <ptr target="#bailey2020"/>, and Nishant Shah <ptr target="#shah2015"/> tackle, it
               successfully builds a counter-narrative to techno-utopianism and left-leaning
               anti-authoritarianism in an effort to reframe knowledge production in the Humanities.
               Tufekci, in essence, grapples with critical questions in Digital Humanities about who
               creates, engages with, and controls digital spaces. This book is in a constant flux
               between the strengths and weaknesses of functioning and navigating within media
               spaces. It is an invaluable resource for anyone interested in how social activism
               constructs itself online and a must-read for all that have scholarly aims in the
               field of digital activism.</p>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bailey2019" label="Bailey et al. 2019">Bailey, M., Jackson, S., and
               Foucault Welles, B. <title rend="quotes">Women Tweet on Violence: From #YesAllWomen
                  to #MeToo,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Ada: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and Technology</title> 15
               (2019). <ref target="http://doi.org/10.5399/uo/ada.2019.15.6"
                  >http://doi.org/10.5399/uo/ada.2019.15.6</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bailey2020" label="Bailey et al. 2020">Bailey, M., Jackson, S., and
               Foucault Welles, B. <title rend="italic">#Hashtag Activism: Networks of Race and
                  Gender Justice</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA (2020). <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/10858.001.0001"
                  >https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/10858.001.0001</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bagger2018" label="Bagger 2018">Bagger, J. <title rend="quotes">Dr.
                  Roopika Risam: Calling Attention to Activism Through Digital Humanities.</title>
               Digital Humanities at Washington and Lee University (October 10, 2018). <ref
                  target="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2018/10/10/dr-roopika-risam-calling-attention-to-activism-through-digital-humanities/"
                  >https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2018/10/10/dr-roopika-risam-calling-attention-to-activism-through-digital-humanities/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="losh2014" label="Losh 2014">Losh, E. <title rend="quotes">Hashtag Feminism
                  and Twitter Activism in India,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Social Epistemology Review and Reply Collective</title> 3.12
               (2014): 10-22. <ref target="http://wp.me/p1Bfg0-1Kx">http://wp.me/p1Bfg0-1Kx</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shah2015" label="Shah et al. 2015">Shah, N., Sneha, P. P., and
               Chattopadhyay S. <title rend="italic">Digital Activism in Asia Reader</title>. Meson
               Press, Lüneburg, Germany (2015). <ref target="http://doi.org/10.14619/013"
                  >http://doi.org/10.14619/013</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tufecki2017" label="Tufekci 2017">Tufekci, Z. <title rend="italic">Twitter
                  and Tear Gas: The Power and Fragility of Networked Protest</title>. Yale
               University Press, New Haven, CT (2017). </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
