<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns=      "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc=   "http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq=  "http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:html= "http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:mml=  "http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf=  "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Designing for discovery: using web maps in the
               digital humanities</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Gethin <dhq:family>Rees</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3255-9584</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Department of Digital Humanities, King’s College
                  London</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Dr.gethin.rees@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Gethin Rees is lecturer in digital products and industries at the Department of
                     Digital Humanities, King’s College London. He was formerly lead curator for
                     digital maps at the British Library where he was also principal investigator of
                     Locating a National Collection, a foundational project in the Towards a
                     National Collection programme. From 2010-13 he was research associate in GIS on
                     the Mapping the Jewish Communities of the Byzantine Empire project, at the
                     Centre for Advanced Religious and Theological Study, Faculty of Divinity,
                     University of Cambridge.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000819</idno>
            <idno type="volume">019</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2025-11-14">14 November 2025</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml"
                     >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml"
                     >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp="#geospatial"/>
               <term corresp="#data_visualization"/>
               <term corresp="#graphic_design"/>
               <term corresp="#cultural_heritage"/>
               <term corresp="#information_retrieval"/>
               <term corresp="#tools"/>
               <term corresp="#web"/>
               <term corresp="#users"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>cartography</item>
                  <item>web maps</item>
                  <item>user experience</item>
                  <item>projection</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000819/000819.xml">GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Web map interfaces such as OpenStreetMap or Google Maps share a set of visual and
               interactive features that are widely used for navigation and discovering information.
               Associated software components such as Leaflet or Google Maps Embed API have become
               the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> standard for geographical visualisation in the
               digital humanities. This article examines how the needs of humanities researchers can
               inform the design of these web map components’ features. Visual analysis and
               discovery use cases for web maps are introduced based on the TaDiRAH taxonomy of
               digital research activities. Visual analysis offers researchers opportunities to gain
               geographical insights from patterns in humanities data. Yet visual features of web
               map components such as the Web Mercator projection and background mapping tiles are
               only appropriate for the analysis of certain regions and scales. A discovery use case
               is introduced with the aim of using the map to access research objects. The article
               argues that visual features such as vector representations and popups can be designed
               to guide the user towards accessing rich content beyond the map. This use case aligns
               with researchers’ experience of using web map components elsewhere and projects that
               wish to encourage usage of research objects. Web map components have expedited the
               process of creating visualisations. Yet their convenience has led to a lack of
               spatial literacy and critical reflection. The article argues that historical and
               wider usage should be considered when appropriating any form of visualisation.
               Examining the research process helps the design of visualisations to support use
               cases, guiding users in addressing the open-ended and complex questions of the
               humanities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>How can the needs of researchers inform the design of web maps in the digital
               humanities?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Web maps based on shared standards and common design principles are part of a suite of
            technologies developed since the late-twentieth century that <quote rend="inline">created new approaches to geographic information distribution and, most importantly,
               in the usability and ease of application development</quote>
            <ptr target="#haklay_2008"/>. Proprietary and open-source APIs, platforms and services
            provided by Google, Carto, Mapbox, OpenStreetMap and others have lowered the level of
            expertise required to create maps, opening up geospatial data to new audiences and uses.
            Web maps such as Leaflet or Google Maps Embed API are now a mainstay of digital
            humanities courses and research projects and have become the <hi rend="italic">de
               facto</hi> standard for geographical visualisation. Stuart Dunn notes that the launch
            of <quote rend="inline">web mapping platforms like OpenStreetMap (OSM) in 2004</quote>
            coincided with the <quote rend="inline">floruit</quote> of the <quote rend="inline">spatial turn</quote>
            <ptr target="#dunn_2019" loc="p. 5"/> and, alongside Geographical Information Systems
            (GIS), web maps have been key to the burgeoning interest in geography amongst digital
            humanists through the developing <quote rend="inline">Spatial Humanities</quote>
            <ptr target="#bodenhamer_2010"/>. In 2025, they represent the most commonly used form of
            visualisation amongst digital humanists employed by five of the eleven winners in the
               <title rend="quotes">DH Awards Best DH Visualization</title> category since 2012 <ptr target="#cummings_2022"/>. Yet, whilst the application of GIS in the digital
            humanities has been subject to decades of critical reflection <ptr target="#gregory_2007"/>, the use of web maps has received scant attention with a few
            notable exceptions <ptr target="#hepworth_2019"/>
            <ptr target="#luchetta_2017"/>
            <ptr target="#jessop_2006"/>. Indeed, web maps are commonly subsumed within the category
               <q>Web</q> or <q>DH</q> GIS <ptr target="#gieseking_2018"/>. In acknowledging the
            complexity of visualisation from a humanities perspective, recent scholarship has
            emphasised the need for <quote rend="inline">graphical forms… capable of expressing
               ambiguity, contradiction, nuance, change</quote>
            <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 3"/>. This article asks whether the web map
            component offers a constructive, effective, or appropriate method of visualising
            humanities data. To do so, it examines how such maps could be used in the humanities
            research process drawing on the TaDiRAH taxonomy of <quote rend="inline">digital
               research activities in the humanities</quote>
            <ptr target="#borek_2016"/> to outline discovery and visual analysis use cases.<note>
               TaDiRAH offers a formal classification of digital humanities research with the aim of
               helping scholars to find the tools and resources they are interested in.</note> This
            user-centred design approach draws on perspectives from cartography and visualisation
            research and is illustrated by the use of web maps in two collaborative projects that
            the author contributed to.</p>
         <div>
            <head>Definitions and scope</head>
            <p>The term <q>web map component</q> refers not to a single piece of software or service
               but rather to several software libraries that share core features. Maps, described
               variously as interactive, dynamic, or slippy, have become commonplace on the web
               since the 1990s. Coded in Javascript and displayed in web browsers, they consume
               geospatial data structured according to a set of standards set out by the Open
               Geospatial Consortium (OGC) <ptr target="#ogc_n.d."/>. Perhaps the seminal moment in
               the development of this technology was the release of Google Maps in 2005 <ptr target="#haklay_2008" loc="p. 2021"/>. However, in 2025, examples abound and
               include Leaflet, Open Layers, MapBoxGL, Maplibre and Google Maps Embed API. User
               studies demonstrate that the predominant use of these maps is to aid movement and
               understanding of the physical environment <ptr target="#rees_2022" loc="p. 7"/>.
               Tasks such as planning journeys and navigation fit within the revenue models of
               companies such as Google that are rooted in advertising locations for visits and
               gathering user data through GPS-enabled mobile apps <ptr target="#mcquire_2019" loc="p. 155"/>. These web map components have been used to make data available in
               bespoke applications that are created by developers for individual projects, or
               platform-based applications such as Carto or Google’s MyMaps, that are more widely
               used <ptr target="#carto_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#google_n.d."/>. The web map component is defined by some core features
               that exist in all software implementations and that constrain possible uses. Visual
               and interactive features sit within a rectilinear container that can be embedded into
               an HTML web page. </p>
            <p>Three visual features are considered core to the component namely tiles, vectors and
               projection. Tiles form the base or background images of the web map whilst vectors
               take the form of points, polylines, or polygons, commonly styled as markers or shapes
               that sit on top of tiles. Vectors’ underlying data consist of geometries, usually in
               the form of coordinates, and attributes, text, URLs, or other information attached to
               the coordinates. The final visual feature is projection, a cartographic method used
               to transform the curved surface of the earth so that it can be viewed on a flat,
               two-dimensional one such as a screen. Interactivity is possible through a
               circumscribed set of actions that facilitate two goals: update of the visual display
               and the retrieval and display of attribute data. The former is achieved through
               zooming and panning actions that adjust the position and focus of vectors and tiles
               on screen. Attribute data can be retrieved by clicking on a vector. Particular
               implementations of web map components may, of course, contain other features such as
               a title, north arrow, text search, or scale; however, these are not essential.
               Similarly, these components might be embedded within a broader web page that
               facilitates further interactions through filters, sliders or buttons.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>A view from a typical web map component: Leaflet displaying tiles from
                  OpenStreetMap. (Source <ref target="https://leafletjs.com/">https://leafletjs.com/</ref>) </head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Visual and interactive features are bound together in an iterative process that
               consists of three stages: <quote rend="inline">seeing the cartographic representation
                  (perception), interacting with the cartographic representation to change it (motor
                  skills), and thinking about the newly created cartographic representation
                  (cognition)</quote>
               <ptr target="#roth_2013" loc="p. 75"/>; see also <ptr target="#maceachren_1990"/>.
               The web map component’s <quote rend="inline">restricted, highly structured and
                  discrete environment</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 100"/> offers several advantages.
                  <q>Out-of-the-box</q> functionality allows developers to visualise geospatial data
               quickly and easily without having to write bespoke code for visualisation and present
               the results in a format that is familiar and intuitive to users. Yet, the design
               decisions available to the developer are constrained, and familiarity leads users to
               expectations about potential use. The question <quote rend="inline">how do people use
                  Google Maps in everyday life</quote>
               <ptr target="#gentzel_2021"/> is poorly understood despite the application being
               deeply embedded in people’s lives globally. This article takes this question as a
               starting point to examine the broader web map component and its use by expert
               humanities researchers specifically.</p>
            <p>The aforementioned out-of-the-box functionality has led maps to feature in many
               tutorials that urge digital humanists to visualise their data <ptr target="#humanities-design_2014"/>
               <ptr target="#programming-historian_n.d."/>. These tutorials pitch the component as a
               convenient method for digital humanists or developers to present data to other
               humanities researchers and as a tool for personal research based on the premise that
               visualisation stimulates geographical thinking and interpretation without the need to
               master complex GIS software. To name one example, the tutorial <title rend="quotes">Using JavaScript to Create Maps of Correspondence</title> presents a clear and
               easy-to-follow method of creating a map of historical data using Leaflet, encouraging
                  <quote rend="inline">us to think about space and geography in ways that challenge
                  historiographical assumptions</quote>
               <ptr target="#richmond_2017"/>. Whilst GIS provides powerful functionality in the
               form of complex queries or statistical and algorithmic analysis, the constrained
               functionality of the web map component makes it a technology of visual communication
                  <ptr target="#dunn_2019" loc="p. 80"/>
               <ptr target="#gregory_2007" loc="p. 639"/>. The ability to embed a map within web
               pages ranging from complex bespoke apps to simple blogs has led individuals, projects
               and organisations to draw on the component to support new ways of engaging with
               humanities data. This article argues that there has been a tendency to assume such
               presentation holds intrinsic value. A thorough investigation of how the component has
               been incorporated within digital humanities interfaces to date would undoubtedly have
               value but would emphasise the intentions of the developer. Instead, this article
               seeks to emphasise the user by examining the different possible ways that the web map
               component could be used in the humanities research process and the types of insights
               these uses might lead to. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Using web maps for visual analysis</head>
            <p>A substantial body of research has broken digital research in the humanities down
               into constituent primitives, <quote rend="inline">basic functions common to scholarly
                  activity across disciplines, over time, and independent of theoretical
                  orientation</quote>
               <ptr target="#unsworth_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#borek_2016"/>
               <ptr target="#gradmann_2015"/>. Such primitives are similar to the activities defined
               within the design perspective of Don Norman as a <quote rend="inline">collected set
                  of tasks, performed together towards a high-level goal</quote>
               <ptr target="#norman_2013" loc="p. 232"/>. The TaDiRAH taxonomy of <quote rend="inline">digital research activities in the humanities</quote> outlines a set
               of connected sub-activities that attempt to encapsulate the research process as a
               whole <ptr target="#borek_2016"/>. TaDiRAH defines interpretation –<quote
                  rend="inline">the activity of ascribing meaning to phenomena observed in
                  analysis</quote>
               <ptr target="#tadirah_n.d."/>– as absolutely fundamental to research. Analysis, the
               process of <quote rend="inline">extracting information from data</quote>, encompasses
               visualisation the <quote rend="inline">use of graphical forms analytically</quote> in
               order to <quote rend="inline">detect patterns, structures, or points of interest in
                  the underlying data</quote>
               <ptr target="#tadirah_n.d."/>. Such <q>visual analysis</q> could be considered the
               primary or even sole use of web maps in the digital humanities. However, this article
               argues that web maps can also assist researchers in <quote rend="inline">the activity
                  of seeking out objects of research, research results, or other information</quote>
               <ptr target="#tadirah_n.d."/>. Referred to as <q>discovery</q> in the TaDIRAH
               taxonomy, the activity is associated with tasks like querying, searching, or browsing
                  <ptr target="#gradmann_2015" loc="p. 24"/>. <q>Visual analysis</q> and
                  <q>discovery</q> are adopted as separate use-cases here as emphasising their
               differences offers a heuristic that can usefully inform the design of web maps.</p>
            <p>It might be assumed that the primary goal in using any map is to gain geographical
               insight, and a wealth of cartographic research has examined visual analysis of maps
               in terms of <quote rend="inline">map reading</quote> tasks or <quote rend="inline">communication models</quote>
               <ptr target="#battersby_2019" loc="Chapter 3"/>
               <ptr target="#maceachren_1990" loc="p. 70"/>. In defining visual analysis, the
               article draws on the distinction between elementary and synoptic tasks made by
               Natalia Andrienko and Gennady Andrienko <ptr target="#andrienko_2006"/>. In the
               digital humanities, a dataset is a model of a human phenomenon or behaviour that is
               derived from a research object or objects. Datasets model geographical
               characteristics of the phenomenon as coordinates. To offer insights, a map must offer
               a <quote rend="inline">general view</quote> of the phenomenon’s <quote rend="inline">principal parts</quote>
               <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 83"/>, communicating the shape or a summary of
               the data. Visual patterns based on variables such as association, differentiation,
               arrangement, or distribution approximate aspects of the phenomenon through
               two-dimensional patterns including clusters, trends, boundaries, or outliers <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 91"/>. Andrienko and Andrienko define the
               analysis of such patterns as a <quote rend="inline">synoptic task</quote>: one based
               on viewing a set of data simultaneously to gain an insight that goes beyond the sum
               of individual elements <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 85"/>. The generation of
               such an insight also rests on possessing contextual knowledge of the domain in
               question.</p>

            <dhq:example>
               <head>Example of a boundary geographical pattern. Visualisation of coordinates
                  assigned to research objects from several British Library collections as viewed in
                  Peripleo. Thanks to Victoria Morris for dataset. (Source: <ref target="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/BL/#/7.08/-1.6498/52.4824/mode=heatmap">https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/BL/#/7.08/-1.6498/52.4824/mode=heatmap</ref>)</head>
               <dhq:passThroughCode lang="xhtml" rend="block">
                  <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                     <iframe class="iframe-class" style="width: 100%; height: 700px;"
                        src="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/BL/#/5.48/-1.6010/52.0996/mode=heatmap"
                        frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"
                        allowtransparency="true">
                        <p>Your browser does not support iframes. Embedded document may be found at
                              <a
                              href="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/BL/#/7.08/-1.6498/52.4824/mode=heatmap"
                              >https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/BL/#/7.08/-1.6498/52.4824/mode=heatmap</a>
                        </p>
                     </iframe>
                  </div>
               </dhq:passThroughCode>
            </dhq:example>
            <p>The goal of visual analysis might vary from hypothesis testing to hypothesis
               generation just as the developer’s intention might vary from communicating a
               geographical argument to stimulating new geographical insights <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 2"/>
               <ptr target="#maceachren_1997"/>
               <ptr target="#rabinowitz_2013"/>. Or, humanists might take exception to the
               epistemological framework that draws such distinctions in the use of visualisations.
               Yet, in every case, the synoptic task that underlies visual analysis focuses on the
               visual features of the web map component –projection, vectors and tiles– whilst
               interactive features play a supporting role, helping the user to explore and find
               patterns in two visual dimensions. To illustrate this use-case, the article will draw
               on an interface developed by Fredrik Palm with the assistance of the author as part
               of the Mapping the Jewish Communities of the Byzantine empire project (MJCBE) funded
               by the European Research Council. Geography is critical to interpreting the history
               of these minority communities, and the visualisation of associated geospatial data
               was intended for visual analysis. The MJCBE interface embedded a web map component,
               in this case what was Google Maps API, within a set of interactive filters that
               existed outside the component. Point vectors that represent historical references to
               the Jewish communities were displayed on a map. The filters allowed the user to
               update the points displayed on the map through combinations of attribute data.
               Attributes that formed filters include place or toponym and date as well as known
               characteristics of the community like occupation, sect, or residential conditions.
               The filtering system was designed with the complexity and flexibility to support the
               display of many permutations of vectors and therefore to afford the generation of
               unexpected or new geographical patterns. Similarly, the vectors were styled to
               communicate uncertainty visually and to offer signifiers of issues with the
               underlying references. Thus, the intention was to stimulate insights into the history
               of the communities through geography. For example, the interface might offer insights
               into the relationship between these communities and their changing political and
               economic contexts within the wider Byzantine empire <ptr target="#rees_2018"/>. Yet
               the interface only displayed data that are directly related to the Jewish communities
               meaning users would have to draw on their wider knowledge in order to interpret
               visual patterns. Released in 2013, the interface was available when this article was
               submitted but has since become unavailable, it will serve as an example of this
               visual analysis use case throughout the article <ptr target="#panayotov_2013"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Web map component embedded within interactive functionality in the MJCBE
                  interface.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>In the discussion that follows, MJCBE is used to explore the visual analysis use
               case. However, MJCBE is representative of many other interfaces that employ web map
               components for visual analysis. Like MJCBE, such interfaces may or may not include
               complex interactive functionality outside the web map component. The focus here,
               however, is on the component and how the design of its features might support the
               visual analysis use case. Examples of interfaces that might be used for visual
               analysis include: <list type="unordered">
                  <item>The Map of Islamophobia Over Time: One of several maps that the Mapping
                     Islamophobia project has created. Here, the style of the vectors and absence of
                     popups suggests that the primary use is the visual analysis of changing
                     geographical patterns through time <ptr target="#elfenbein_n.d."/>.</item>
                  <item> The Mapping Past Societies project: Offers the ability to layer a wealth of
                     historical geospatial data for visual comparison and affords access to
                     attributes in a popup akin to GIS <ptr target="#harvard_n.d."/>.</item>
                  <item> Pauliceia 2.0: Focuses on mapping the history of the city of São Paulo
                     offering the ability to view, upload and download GIS data <ptr target="#pauliceia-2.0_n.d."/>.</item>
                  <item> Power of Attorney in Oaxaca, Mexico: Maps of legal documents in Mexico. The
                     accompanying text tells us that the resource <quote rend="inline">analyzes and
                        expresses the history of native people’s engagement with Mexico’s colonial
                        and post-independence legal systems by digitally mapping and visualizing
                        social networks and flows of knowledge and power created by legal procedures
                        and litigation.</quote> From this process <quote rend="inline">broad trends
                        emerge</quote>
                     <ptr target="#emory_n.d."/>. <note> Sincere thanks to John Levin for curating a
                        list of DH GIS projects and making these available on the Anterotesis blog
                           <ptr target="#levin_n.d."/>. Without this tremendous resource I would not
                        have been able to compile these examples or indeed write this article.
                     </note>
                  </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Some of these examples make the intention for visual analysis explicit in text
               accompanying the web map; for others, the use case can be inferred by using the
               interface. The developers of each of the examples that follow may not have explicitly
               intended them to be used for visual analysis, rather an examination of the
               affordances of their features by the author suggests they support this use case.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Designing for discovery</head>
            <p>The web map acts as a visual method of accessing digital research objects such as
               text, images, or sounds in the discovery use case. A suitable dataset must first,
               include coordinates that represent a geographical characteristic of each object, and
               second, offer access to rich representations of the objects usually taking the form
               of URLs pointing to objects hosted within the app or externally. An idealised
               discovery process consists of two stages. The first stage is interactive including
               zoom and pan to discover a single vector of interest. The user might have a
               predetermined idea of what they were looking for resulting in <quote rend="inline">instrumental and purposeful</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para. 7"/> behaviour or, alternatively, behaviour
               might encompass browsing or exploration. The location that a chosen vector represents
               may or may not be familiar to the user, meaning domain-specific knowledge is not
               essential. The second stage is interactive and based on the retrieval of attribute
               data: in practice, clicking on a vector to trigger a popup, so-called <quote rend="inline">details on demand</quote>
               <ptr target="#shneiderman_1996" loc="p. 336"/>. The resulting popup might include the
               research object itself or, more commonly, a hyperlink. The user might be interested
               in several research objects, in which case they would find their representative
               vectors sequentially, by clicking on a single vector at a time. The other vectors
               might help identify a vector of interest, but their relationships are not the focus
               of cognition. Discovery is therefore based on what Andrienko and Andrienko term
               elementary tasks. Elementary tasks examine <quote rend="inline">individual elements
                  of the data</quote>
               <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 60"/> and, in contrast to synoptic tasks, do
               not lead to an insight, interpretation, or developed understanding of the phenomenon
               that the data represents. Both visual analysis and discovery rely on the same set of
               visual and interactive features within the three-stage iterative process of
               perception, interaction, and cognition outlined earlier <ptr target="#roth_2013" loc="p. 76"/>. The key distinction between the use cases lies in the intended
               focus of cognition: For discovery, the focus is on research objects that can be
               accessed through the map whilst, in the case of visual analysis, the focus is on the
               visual features of the map. A map designed for discovery should act as a portal or
               gateway to research objects. As far as is possible the web map <quote rend="inline">doesn’t intervene as an explanation or argument</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay_2012" loc="p. 78"/>, although it is acknowledged that this ideal
               might be unachievable. Discovery is not simply information retrieval. Web maps do not
               demand queries, they present <quote rend="inline">navigable representations of large
                  digital collections; they invite exploration and support browsing, using overviews
                  to establish context</quote> and offer the potential for serendipitous discovery
                  <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para.46"/>. Yet, the extent to which they can
               present the <quote rend="inline">complexity and diversity of cultural collections,
                  and to privilege the process of interpretation</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para.46"/> and can be defined as <quote rend="inline">generous</quote> in Mitchell Whitelaw’s terms, is unclear.</p>
            <p>This discovery use case will be familiar to researchers from their use of web maps
               elsewhere, including tasks such as booking accommodation or buying property online.
               User studies show that Google Maps <quote rend="inline">are no longer used only as a
                     <q>map</q>, but also to obtain further information (including opening hours,
                  available goods, prices)</quote>
               <ptr target="#gentzel_2021" loc="p. 180"/>. Sixty percent of a representative sample
               of the UK public liked to have <quote rend="inline">practical information about
                  places (e.g. opening hours, pictures, reviews) available to them when using online
                  map interfaces</quote> making this the second most popular function after
               navigation <ptr target="#rees_2022" loc="p. 6"/>. Discovery aligns with the goals of
               cultural heritage organisations who are interested in driving traffic to web pages
               and in encouraging the use of a breadth of digital objects. However, as the examples
               outlined below demonstrate, the use case can also support digital humanities
               projects. Therefore, to illustrate the discovery use case, the article will draw on
               Peripleo, a web map interface developed by Rainer Simon with support from Stephen
               Gadd, Leif Isaksen, and the author as part of the Locating a National Collection
               project and funded by the UK’s Arts and Humanities Research Council <ptr
                  target="#simon_2022"/>. The interface was designed to help researchers and the
               wider public to discover web pages that represent the collections of the UK’s
               cultural heritage organisations. Developers are able to create their own instances of
               Peripleo based on Linked Data in the form of JSON-LD files.<note> Javascript Object
                  Notation Linked Data. A lightweight human-readable linked-data format for
                  exchanging data on the web.</note> The interface includes search and filtering
               functionality that updates vectors shown on the map and the colour of their
               representations. In creating this interface, the development team took design
               decisions that tailored its use for discovery, and these will be outlined in the
               remainder of this article. </p>

            <dhq:example>
               <head>Peripleo web maps interface displaying VisitPlus dataset from Locating a
                  National Collection (<ref target="https://britishlibrary.github.io/locating-a-national-collection/VisitPlus.html">https://britishlibrary.github.io/locating-a-national-collection/VisitPlus.html</ref>)
                  (Source: <ref target="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/visitplus/#/?/?/?/mode=points"/>) </head>
               <dhq:passThroughCode lang="xhtml" rend="block">
                  <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                     <iframe class="iframe-class" style="width: 100%; height: 700px;"
                        src="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/visitplus/#/?/?/?/mode=points"
                        frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"
                        allowtransparency="true">
                        <p>Your browser does not support iframes. Embedded document may be found at
                              <a
                              href="https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/visitplus/#/?/?/?/mode=points"
                              >https://britishlibrary.github.io/peripleo-lanc/visitplus/#/?/?/?/mode=points</a>
                        </p>
                     </iframe>
                  </div>
               </dhq:passThroughCode>
            </dhq:example>

            <p>Peripleo is representative of several interfaces that support the discovery use case.
               Whilst the text that accompanies these maps might not detail their intended purpose
               explicitly, as with the maps intended for visual analysis, potential use can be
               inferred from the design of features and their affordances. Examples include:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://booth.lse.ac.uk/">Charles Booth’s London</ref>: Connects
                  Booth’s maps of London with references to geography in pages from Booth’s notebook
                  made available in an International Image Interoperability Framework (iiif) viewer
                     <ptr target="#cbl_n.d."/>.</item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://mappingislamophobia.org/">Countering Islamaphobia maps</ref>:
                  The Mapping Islamaphobia website also makes this map available that offers
                  prominent links to journalism and other sources of information through simple
                  vector markers <ptr target="#elfenbein_n.d."/>.</item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://clevelandhistorical.org/">Cleveland Historical</ref>: Stories
                  related to locations in Cleveland available from map popups <ptr target="#center-for-public-history_n.d."/></item>
               <item><ref target="https://www.danskeherregaarde.dk/en/history/the-history-of-the-danish-manors">Danish Manors</ref>: Offers access to information on Danish Manors from a
                  simple map interface <ptr target="#dansk_n.d."/></item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://travellersmap.gr/public">Travellers maps</ref>: This <quote
                     rend="inline">modern map of traveling, which aims at promoting the <q>Hellenic
                        world</q></quote> acts as a gateway to multimedia resources <ptr
                     target="#alf_n.d."/></item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Interactive features</head>
            <p>Decisions taken in designing these features can provide signifiers that emphasise
               particular affordances. Such signifiers are particularly important as researchers do
               not necessarily have a use-case in mind. Digital humanities scholarship has argued
               that assuming users have a predetermined goal is unrealistic and counter-productive
                  <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para.7"/>
               <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 97"/>. Rather, users will initially enter into
               exploratory behaviour to understand how the map might be used in their research. In
               this exploratory phase, users will draw on their experiences of using similar
               interfaces elsewhere. However, the user should not be left <quote rend="inline">observing without any clear purpose, rambling through the data in the hope of
                  encountering something <q>interesting</q>, which might provide food for thought
                  and lead to a sudden <q>insight</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#andrienko_2006" loc="p. 148"/>. The developer should have an intended
               use for the map in mind: Good design communicates this potential use by providing
               signifiers to guide the user. </p>
            <p>The widespread use of web maps leads users to possess pre-existing knowledge of
               affordances. It is unnecessary to provide signifiers that panning, moving the
               geographical display of the map, is possible by clicking, holding and moving the
               mouse laterally or longitudinally. Similarly, users will know that turning the mouse
               wheel facilitates zooming in and out. However, the developer should always consider
               constraining the geographical area that can be panned whilst limiting the ability to
               zoom. The affordance that vectors offer to retrieve attribute data through a click is
               familiar to users from previous experience. Most would be unsurprised when their
               click triggers the appearance of a popup in the browser displaying text, a hyperlink,
               an image or a video. The motivation for retrieving attribute data differs based on
               use case. In visual analysis, attributes <quote rend="inline">point to evidence on
                  which the argument is based</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 127"/> such as dates, sources or people. Although
               they deepen understanding of the primary synoptic task, their retrieval is a
               secondary concern. For the discovery use case, the retrieval of attribute data such
               as URLs that represent research objects is the primary affordance.</p>
            <p>The developer has several opportunities to provide signifiers that guide the user.
               For example, vectors’ representations can be tailored to emphasise that they are
               clickable by providing a symbol of sufficient size and opacity or by employing tool
               tips. More complex vector designs such as heatmaps (see Example 1) or
                  choropleths<note> A thematic map that displays statistical information as
                  colours.</note> afford visual analysis but might obscure the ability to click and
               retrieve attributes. The use of tiles that are lighter in colour and that contain
               less detail can emphasise the ability to click on a vector. If the developer intends
               the map to be used for discovery, simple vector representations are preferable, as
               they guide the user away from visual analysis and towards the elementary task of
               finding an individual vector and clicking. For example, the Peripleo interface uses
               simple circles to emphasise the affordance of clicking. The form in which attribute
               data are displayed on retrieval should vary depending on use case. Where the
               attribute data are intended to support visual analysis, their popup display should
               not obscure the map and those attributes that are relevant to visual analysis can be
               emphasised. A concise popup, that can be closed easily, offers a simple route to
               return to the map view preventing the user from leaving the map entirely. In
               contrast, in the discovery use case, greater emphasis should be placed on the display
               of attribute data. For instance, a modal that displays attributes whilst deactivating
               other content on the page was used to good effect in Charles Booth’s London map when
               this paper was written <ptr target="#cbl_n.d."/>. The research object or the method
               of accessing the research object should be emphasised in the display. Hyperlinks that
               provide access to research objects should be prominent and housed within a button or
               other clear signifier. In the case of Booth’s map, the modal offers a prominent link
               to relevant pages from Booth’s notebook.</p>
            <p>Signifying the importance of these hyperlinks is the most important consideration
               when designing for discovery. Furthermore, previews that communicate properties of
               hyperlinked research objects such as media types like image, video or text should be
               considered <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para. 12"/>. Finally, as web analytics
               can capture relevant user interactions including statistics for the opening of popups
               and subsequent click-throughs to research objects, they offer clear metrics for the
               use of maps designed for discovery. For example, popups in the Peripleo interface
               provide prominent hyperlinks in the form of buttons alongside the ability to install
               web analytics. On the other hand, such metrics were not considered for the MJCBE
               interface where hyperlinks are less prominent and do not offer access to rich data or
               relevant research objects. In summary, the importance of retrieving attribute data
               varies between use cases. The ability to access attributes that represent research
               objects is critical to discovery. For visual analysis, the retrieval of attribute
               data only supports the synoptic task that focuses on the visual features of the map.
               With this key distinction established, the next section will examine the design of
               visual features and associated signifiers that the developer can use to guide the
               user.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Popup used in MJCBE interface.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p/>
            <figure>
               <head>Popup used in Peripleo displaying signifiers of hyperlinks designed for
                  discovery use case.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Visual features</head>
            <p>Of all the features of the web map component, the developer has the greatest control
               over vectors, coordinates displayed as markers and other shapes on the map. The
               vector data consumed by the web map component takes the point, polyline, and polygon
               forms that are known from GIS. The underlying geometry or coordinates are commonly
               encoded in WGS84: the most commonly used system for representing locations on the
               earth’s surface as latitude and longitude. These coordinates then sit within standard
               data structures designed to share geospatial data on the web that include formats
               such as GeoJSON, KML or the OGC’s Web Feature Service (WFS). For example, Peripleo is
               based on the Linked Places standard developed in association with the Pelagios
               Network. Some DH applications make the underlying datasets available for download,
               Pauleicia offers this ability providing opportunities for reuse <ptr
                  target="#pauliceia-2.0_n.d."/>. The coordinates and their associated attributes
               can be visualised in diverse ways.A vector dataset is created by modelling
               geographical characteristics of a research object or objects and metadata. Such
               characteristics include where the object was created, found or used, or some aspect
               of its content, broadly defined to include locations mentioned in text or depicted in
               art. Such geographical modelling is not self-evident or straightforward and the
               results subjective and partial <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 70"/>. Visual
               communication of the critical relationship between research object and geometry is
               difficult. The difficulties in using Euclidean geometry to represent place has been
               extensively discussed in scholarship on GIS and other technologies <ptr
                  target="#blaschke_2018"/>
               <ptr target="#dunn_2019" loc="p. 16"/>
               <ptr target="#gregory_2010" loc="p. 58"/>. The shortcomings of representing nuanced
               and complex humanities data within the simplistic demarcation of space that vector
               geometries provide should be a concern for the developer of a web map. However, the
               web map component offers significant flexibility to meet this challenge as most
               cartographic forms of representation can be rendered using standard technologies for
               rendering graphics in browsers including CSS, D3 or plugins <ptr target="#leaflet_n.d."/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Issues in defining place using vectors. A visualisation of crowd-sourced
                  neighbourhood mapping from the Boston Neighbourhood Consensus project created by
                  Bostonography. By Andy Woodruff (<ref target="https://andywoodruff.com">https://andywoodruff.com</ref>) and Tim Wallace (<ref target="https://www.nytimes.com/by/tim-wallace">https://www.nytimes.com/by/tim-wallace</ref>). (Source <ref target="https://bostonography.com/2017/official-unofficial-neighborhoods-2017">https://bostonography.com/2017/official-unofficial-neighborhoods-2017</ref>.
                  Used with the permission of the authors.)</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The representation of vectors should vary according to use case in terms of form and
               style. Web maps offer developers opportunities to configure symbol, shape, colour, or
               shade to represent attributes and support visual analysis. Users have experience of
               using particular styles for certain forms of visual analysis, for instance,
               choropleths in the case of electoral data. The division of a dataset into layers
               means vectors can be broken down into subsets where differences in representation
               might communicate relationships <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015" loc="para. 12"/>.
               Complexity of visual form might, however, obscure the affordance of clicking on a
               vector to retrieve attribute data. For example, the MJCBE interface styles vectors
               using opacity to help users understand spatial and temporal uncertainty in underlying
               data quickly <ptr target="#rees_2018"/>. As more transparent vector symbols represent
               greater uncertainty styling obscures the ability to click on a vector’s
               representation. On the other hand, the simple style of Peripleo markers is intended
               to guide the user away from making visual comparisons between markers and towards
               clicking. This article does not attempt to provide a comprehensive guide to these
               options and their application. Rather, it urges the developer to consider intended
               use when choosing vector representation and not employ the familiar
               inverted-drop-shaped pin popularised by Google <ptr target="#skopeliti_2019" loc="p. 11"/>. </p>
            <p>Whilst vectors should be the focus of any web map, tiles dominate the display space,
               setting the visual tone. Tiles provide an efficient and lightweight method of
               displaying and updating background maps in the browser based on zoom and pan
                  interactions.<note> Tiles are requested individually based on zoom and pan
                  interactions before being joined seamlessly in the browser. Traditionally made up
                  of geolocated PNG images in 2025 tiles more often take the form of packets of
                  vectors. They are typically served using an HTTP geospatial standard such as Web
                  Map Tile Service (WMTS) defined by the OGC <ptr target="#ogc_n.d."/>.</note>
               Rendered as seamless and interactive images they support the familiar, slippy web map
               format. Many users will be familiar with those made available by commercial providers
               such as Bing, Google, or MapTiler alongside open offerings like OpenStreetMap. These
               tiles are often designed to support uses of web maps in society today that include
               navigation and information retrieval and reflect the commercial interests of
               providers. The wealth of tiles made available has been extensively researched outside
               the digital humanities. These tiles are created for particular purposes, for example
               to generate commercial revenue through advertising. Tiles are complex and
               multi-layered datasets meaning their production process is not always readily
               apparent <ptr target="#jokar-arsanjani_2015"/>, and biases in design make them
               unsuitable for particular user needs <ptr target="#skopeliti_2019"/>. Some are not
               representative or equitable and suffer from deficiencies including the representation
               of national borders <ptr target="#soeller_2016"/> and poor coverage of the global
               south <ptr target="#gui_2016" loc="p. 13"/>. The use of many sets of tiles is
               therefore problematic from political and ethical perspectives. Those offered by
               commercial providers are by no means the only type of tile that can be displayed
               within web map components, rather, they represent a default setting. In particular,
               those projects that examine the global south or adopt a global perspective should
               consider the alternative options outlined below. </p>
            <p>Temporality is a critical consideration in the use of tiles in the digital humanities
               yet has been little discussed. Designed for use in today’s society, tiles generally
               depict current geography. Yet humanities research examines varied time periods making
               the use of many tiles anachronistic. Despite these concerns, such tiles are widely
               used in digital humanities projects: For example, more than 50 of 76 <quote
                  rend="inline">digital literary mapping projects</quote> used such <quote
                  rend="inline">online mapping services</quote>
               <ptr target="#luchetta_2017" loc="p. 8"/>. The Mapping Islamaphobia and Power of
               Attorney in Oaxaca, Mexico projects introduced earlier implement tiles from ESRI and
               Carto that depict modern topography which is mainly obscured by dark shading,
               anachronistic in the case of the Power of Attorney in Oaxaca, Mexico project. The
               MJCBE interface uses Google tiles derived from satellite imagery. Current topography
               was intended to act as a corollary for topography of the past yet, despite limits
               placed on zoom to avoid users’ engagement with large scales, the tiles are
               anachronistic.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Anachronistic use of tiles derived from satellite imagery to represent
                  Byzantine period topography in MJCBE interface.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpeg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>It is convenient to use tiles that display modern topography as they are packaged up
               as a service by commercial providers. The creation of tiles and the setup and
               maintenance of services is labour intensive, making bespoke implementations beyond
               the reach of many individual projects. Alternatives do exist such as tiles derived
               from individual digitised maps and made available through services like Allmaps <ptr target="#spann_n.d."/> or the Georeferencer <ptr target="#klokan_n.d."/> or as
               seamless map layers created by stitching a published series of maps together <ptr target="#fleet_2019"/>. Whilst undoubtedly useful, and often a significant
               improvement, such digitised maps also embody a specific worldview and power dynamic.
               Many such maps were originally created for navigation and economic planning, to name
               two examples, and are entangled with historical processes including conflict,
               colonialism, or empire building. A welcome alternative for an earlier period is
               provided by the Consortium of Ancient World Mappers who offer tiles with worldwide
               coverage of topography with water levels adjusted at different dates <ptr target="#horne_2022"/>. Peripleo offers an option within a JSON configuration file
               to configure the map instance to display selected tiles of choice. Those selected by
               default are provided by MapTiler, but guidance on adding the Consortium of Ancient
               World Mappers tiles is available in the form of some simple steps. The role and
               importance of tiles varies based on use case. Whilst vectors are the focus of visual
               analysis, tiles are also essential to recognising, interpreting, and deriving meaning
               from patterns. Therefore, the choice of tile is critical to guiding the user towards
               visual analysis. Tiles should be chosen to accentuate and to draw attention to
               markers, for example, by ensuring colours are complementary or that tiles are light
               in colour thus focusing attention on the markers. In the case of discovery, tiles are
               simply used for orientation, supporting the user to find, notice, or recognise a
               single vector. Familiarity with current geographical features like settlements might
               therefore be helpful and the anachronistic nature of many tilesets need not be
               detrimental to their use for discovery. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Projection</head>
            <p>Projection defines the display of vectors and their relationship to tiles making the
               choice of projection a critical consideration in designing any web map. A projection
               is a transformation of the three-dimensional earth onto a two-dimensional map. It is
               possible to use many different calculations to display or approximate the sphere that
               is the earth on a flat surface. That <quote rend="inline">map projections should be
                  selected based on their appropriateness for the user’s data, the geographic area
                  being mapped, and the types of measurements that a reader might need to
                  make</quote>
               <ptr target="#battersby_2014" loc="p. 98"/> is a firmly established cartographic
               principle. Yet, in the vast majority of cases, web map components are setup to use
               the default spherical, pseudo, or Web Mercator projection known by the code EPSG:3857
                  <ptr target="#klokan_2020c"/>. The deficiencies of the projection are
               well-documented in cartographic literature <ptr target="#monmonier_2004"/>. Despite
               this critique, the projection has gained prominence in the twenty-first century on
               the web. Components including Leaflet, MapBoxGL, and Open Layers offer the
               opportunity to select from a range of possible projections either using selectors,
               plugins or bespoke code <ptr target="#leaflet_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#mapbox_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#openlayers_n.d."/>. Yet these options are rarely used. Indeed, all of
               the projects introduced earlier are based on the Web Mercator projection.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Three forms of map projection. After: Comparison of cartography surface
                  development. By Cmglee (<ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Cmglee">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Cmglee</ref>). (Source: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Comparison_of_cartography_surface_development.svg">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Comparison_of_cartography_surface_development.svg</ref>
                  Used under <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:CC-BY-SA-4.0">CC-BY-SA-4.0</ref> license.)</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>All projections require compromise, and in selecting a projection the <quote rend="inline">cartographer must weigh distortion of area against the distortions
                  of angles, distances and directions</quote>
               <ptr target="#monmonier_2004" loc="p. 175"/>. Designed to facilitate the calculation
               of bearings, the Mercator projection preserves angles, making it <q>conformal.</q> A
               simplified version has become standard in web maps based on a spherical earth model
               and differing from modern Mercator implementations used elsewhere that adopt the most
               accurate earth model available <ptr target="#battersby_2014" loc="p. 87"/>.<note> The
                  earth is not a perfect sphere but rather is irregular. Advanced map projections
                  take this irregularity into account in their transformation.</note> The projection
               offers significant technical advantages as its uninterrupted, cylindrical form
               expedites the creation of tiles and makes panning straightforward. Furthermore, the
               projection’s conformality means the calculations required to plot coordinates are
               less complex, a desideratum for web services where computational resources have been
               at a premium historically <ptr target="#kessler_2017"/>. Yet these advantages are
               predicated on compromises elsewhere, and, in the case of Web Mercator, such
               compromises include distortions to area, shape, and distance. Such distortions also
               vary depending on latitude. Higher latitudes suffer from increased area and shape
               distortions meaning that, for example, polygons that are the same area in pixels but
               located at different latitudes do not represent the same geographical area <ptr target="#battersby_2014" loc="p. 98"/>. The relationship between pixels and
               distance varies according to latitude and is proportional only along the equator <ptr target="#kessler_2017"/>. For instance, it is a common misconception that a
               straight line or loxodrome represents the shortest distance between two points rather
               than a <quote rend="inline">great circle</quote>
               <ptr target="#monmonier_2004" loc="p. 7"/>. Moreover, the simplification of the
               earth’s shape that underpins Web Mercator leads to further errors with positions
               portrayed up to 50km from their correct position at high latitudes <ptr target="#battersby_2014" loc="p. 88"/>. Finally, whilst the projection’s
               cylindrical nature facilitates east-west panning, interruption at the poles prevents
               readers from considering trans-polar routes, those that cross the northern and
               southern edges of the map, when estimating distances between points <ptr target="#battersby_2019" loc="p. 98"/>. Thus, the use of web maps based on the
               Mercator projection for estimation tasks such as comparing and measuring can lead to
                  <quote rend="inline">incorrect assumptions about geographic distributions and
                  relationships</quote>
               <ptr target="#battersby_2014" loc="p. 91"/> as empirical studies have shown <ptr target="#lumley_2019"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Map of the world based on Mercator projection including indicatrices to
                  visualise local distortions to area. After: Mercator map of the world –
                  coastlines, graticule, and indicatrices. By Justin Kunimune (<ref
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Justinkunimune"
                     >https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Justinkunimune</ref>). (Source: <ref
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mercator_with_Tissot%27s_Indicatrices_of_Distortion.svg"
                     >https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mercator_with_Tissot%27s_Indicatrices_of_Distortion.svg</ref>.
                  Used under <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:CC-BY-SA-4.0"
                     >CC-BY-SA-4.0</ref> license.)</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The impact of such compromises varies depending on the dataset in question and the
               intended use case. The distortions to distance, area, and shape necessary to preserve
               angles can have a deleterious effect on performing the synoptic task that underpins
               visual analysis. Distortions to relationships between vectors and tiles affect maps
               of certain scales more than others. The projection is suited to <quote rend="inline">local geography over global comparison</quote>
               <ptr target="#monmonier_2004" loc="p. 180"/> and small-scale maps, those that depict
               larger geographical areas such as parts of continents, are particularly affected.
               Visual analysis of any map where the zoom level is less than four according to the
               standard scale used by Leaflet, Google Maps Embed API, and others, is particularly
               problematic, and, in such cases, alternatives such as those that preserve area, like
               Equal Earth <ptr target="#klokan_2020b"/>, or distance, like World Equidistant
               cylindrical <ptr target="#klokan_2009"/>, should be employed. The total latitude
               depicted on Mercator maps should be small and not include latitudes above around 60
               degrees. Any use of the component that includes a polar region would benefit from
               using a custom projection, for example, Antarctic Polar Stereographic <ptr target="#klokan_2020a"/>. In addition to considering the region to be depicted
               carefully, the map creator should set limits on pan and zoom, to ensure that only map
               views with minimum distortion are depicted. Vectors and tiles used in the MJCBE
               interface are projected using Web Mercator. Vectors depicted on the map lie between
               the latitudes of 44.8 and 24.9 meaning differences in areal distortion between these
               latitudes are within reasonable limits. Furthermore, the distribution of vectors in
               terms of both latitude and longitude facilitates relatively accurate estimation of
               distance. Web Mercator arguably has benefits for the discovery use case where the
               focus is on locating a particular vector of interest. Familiar to many users, the
               shape of landmasses and cardinal directions meet preconceptions for how a map should
               look. Such familiarity expedites the recognition of known geographical areas,
               fostering an un-intimidating experience <ptr target="#battersby_2019" loc="p. 91"/>.</p>
            <p>The concept of <q>distortion</q> may not sit comfortably with humanities researchers
               for whom representation is inherently subjective. Yet over and above the mechanistic
               considerations previously outlined, the resulting social and political biases
               embodied in the distortions of the Mercator projection and its history cannot be
               ignored. The inflation of particular landmasses such as western Europe at the expense
               of areas of Africa and Asia came under attack in critical cartographic discourse in
               the twentieth century. This was not only because such inflation renders maps
               unsuitable for particular purposes but also because the distortion replicates
               perceived Western cultural hegemony. In the later twentieth century, this
               reassessment was taken up as part of the wider post-colonial critique, leading to a
               significant decline in the projection’s use in print maps such as atlases <ptr target="#monmonier_2004" loc="p. 128"/>. Despite this welcome earlier change, the
               explosion in web mapping has led to a resurgence in the use of the Mercator
               projection, a trend that has been the subject of some critical discussion <ptr target="#battersby_2014"/>
               <ptr target="#kessler_2017"/>
               <ptr target="#lumley_2019"/>. </p>
            <p>Implementations of the web map component, including by the author of this article in
               co-designing both the Peripleo and MJCBE interfaces, have ignored decades of
               cartographic reflection on the projection’s political implications. The author has
               been unable to locate any projects in the digital humanities that use alternative
               projections within a web map component. Where alternatives projections have been
               implemented the maps used are either static or bespoke implementations based on the
               use of canvas or SVG elements with D3 for example. Examples of such maps include:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>The Spread of U.S. Slavery, 1790–1860 <ptr target="#mullen_2014"/>.</item>
               <item>The Atlantic slave trade in two minutes <ptr target="#kahn_2021"/>.</item>
               <item>Die politische Landkarte Europas Digitaler Atlas zur Geschichte Europas seit.
                  1500 Static maps <ptr target="#kunz_n.d."/>.</item>
               <item>SlaveVoyages static maps taken from <title rend="italic">Atlas of the
                     Transatlantic Slave Trade</title>
                  <ptr target="#eltis_2010"/>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>What might account for the lack of alternative projections in web map components?
               Platforms developed by technology companies including Google’s MyMaps or Carto offer
               a straightforward route to making interactive maps available by uploading a
               spreadsheet <ptr target="#carto_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#google_n.d."/>. These platforms account for many, if not the majority,
               of digital humanities projects but they do not offer straightforward alternatives to
               Web Mercator. Thus, there is often a requirement to write bespoke code to implement
               different projections and the appearance of some tiles within a web map component can
               deteriorate when reprojected at particular scales. Yet these barriers are by no means
               insurmountable as many of the web map components that are available in 2024 offer the
               ability to display maps in different projections <ptr target="#mapbox_n.d."/>
               <ptr target="#openlayers_n.d."/>. For example, Open Layers is open source and only
               requires minor changes in configuration to change the display projection. Although
               there are technical barriers, a lack of cartographic knowledge also prevents the use
               of alternatives. Calls for an ethical visualisation workflow have urged humanists and
               developers alike to consider <quote rend="inline">the larger contextual framing and
                  the story that it tells</quote> employing <quote rend="inline">a critical
                  perspective on the power of individual design elements</quote>
               <ptr target="#hepworth_2019" loc="para. 36–38"/>. The popularity of web maps arguably
               makes the Web Mercator projection the most widely used design element in digital
               humanities visualisation. If any community possesses the knowledge and critical
               skills to think beyond the confines of a default setting it should be digital
               humanists. In 2025, the barriers to implementing alternative projections are lower
               than ever before. Web maps developed in the digital humanities would be much improved
               by thinking through projections creatively.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Concluding remarks</head>
            <p>The user-centred approach adopted by this article has led to a set of recommendations
               for designing web maps to support the two use cases. Designing for the discovery use
               case supports finding and accessing research objects and draws on researchers’
               experience of using web maps elsewhere. Discovery aligns with the priorities of the
               creators of digital research objects including research projects and cultural
               heritage organisations who are interested in maximising the use of web pages through
               usage metrics and usability studies. Collections of research objects and the
               resulting datasets are palimpsests of decisions; their partial, subjective nature
               might not be suitable for collective interpretation. Designing for discovery can
               guide the user away from visual analysis and help projects and organisations to
               present a breadth of research objects. This article suggests that the implementation
               of web maps for visual analysis requires careful thought. The design of visual
               features such as vectors, tiles, and projection should be considered in relation to
               the dataset and aims of the project. These aims do appear to be unclear for many
               projects for which simply making a map available appears to be the main goal. The
               article’s perspective on visual analysis has been cultivated in response to the
               author’s work on MJCBE. Here, the web map component and associated interactive
               functionality were designed to support visual analysis. Yet use of the interface for
               this purpose has not proven straightforward and relies on significant background
               knowledge of the Byzantine empire. There have been few citations that record usage of
               the MJCBE interface for its intended purpose in the decade since release which raises
               the question of how to measure the success or effectiveness of web maps in the visual
               analysis use case. This article does not argue that every web map could be designed
               exclusively for visual analysis or discovery. Maps might serve both purposes or
               others such as the visualisation of a single narrative, journey, or marker or
               offering access to statistical information such as calculating routes in the past
                  <ptr target="#scheidel_2014"/>
               <ptr target="#seydi_2022"/>. Rather, considering both use cases in relation to
               modelling of data and an intended audience of users represents a useful exercise in
               planning and design. </p>
            <p>Future work, encompassing a systematic investigation of more projects that have used
               web map components could categorise implementations in terms of their data type,
               theme or subject, vector representation, and other characteristics leading to further
               definitions of use cases. The article has adopted a mechanistic or instrumentalist
               perspective focused on activities, tasks, and features – a perspective which might be
               considered to be at odds with recent digital humanities literature that persuasively
               argues for a reconsideration of the task-based or goal-oriented paradigm that has
               pervaded user experience or visualisation research <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 99"/>
               <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015"/>. Yet characteristics of the web map component itself
               justify the article’s perspective. Its intended and primary usage is mobility,
               planning and navigation within the physical environment. Researchers will bring
               learned behaviours of task-based use to any web map, and the discovery activity
               aligns with such experience of using web maps elsewhere. The article argues that if
               the component is used for visual analysis, the developer must consider the wider use
               of web maps, as <quote rend="inline">processes of knowing through interpretative work
                  … are also the expression of particular circumstances of production</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 45"/>. Whilst the article is titled <title rend="quotes">Designing for Discovery,</title> developing signifiers of the
               potential for visual analysis is just as important. The need for alternative methods
               of visualisation has been stressed over the last decade under the suggestion that
                  <quote rend="inline">data visualizations have depended on impoverished methods…
                  current practices of reductive graphs and standard charts have debased
                  interpretation, made it simplistic and literal. We know better and can do
                  more</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker_2020" loc="p. 68"/>. The web map component’s constrained set of
               features, two-dimensional visualisation and flat and tightly-defined data model call
               into question its suitability for many forms of open-ended, enjoyable or playful
               exploration. For example, possible user journeys are limited leading narrative or
               story maps to often rely on several different maps. </p>
            <p>Alternative methods of creating maps on the web offer greater flexibility. Bespoke
               maps based on Canvas or SVG are commonly used in fields such as data journalism and
               alternative forms suggested in the digital humanities include the space-time cube
                  <ptr target="#mayr_2018"/> or deep maps <ptr target="#bodenhamer_2021"/>. Yet
               these alternatives require greater effort and expertise to deploy. Whilst the web map
               component’s simplicity has led to its proliferation such simplicity also has
               disadvantages in terms of flexibility. The technology cannot be used to create the
               varied maps available in GIS or more flexible web technologies. Moreover, ease of
               deployment hampers thinking processes leading to a lack of spatial literacy or
               reasoning <ptr target="#dunn_2019" loc="p. 79"/>
               <ptr target="#mostern_2013" loc="para. 35"/>. The developer is completely separated
               from the inner workings of the component, <quote rend="inline">installing the user at
                  a level of abstraction far above whatever theoretical claims might lie
                  beneath</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay_2012" loc="p. 80"/>. This separation has stymied the process of
               critical thinking and experimentation for both user and creator that is valued in the
               digital humanities <ptr target="#hinrichs_2019" loc="p. 11"/>
               <ptr target="#hepworth_2019" loc="para. 41"/>. Tutorials based on the component
               emphasise skills related to web technologies which, whilst undoubtedly useful, are
               offered at the expense of cartographic knowledge or GIScience. Implementation has
               been driven by technology and not the open-ended and complex questions that
               humanities scholars ask. By looking beyond the web map component digital humanists
               have the means to transform the role of geography in the humanities research
               process.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>Thanks to members of the Locating a National Collection project team, especially
               Rainer Simon, Stephen Gadd and Leif Isaksen, and to the Arts and Humanities Research
               Council for funding the project and the development of Peripleo (Grant No.
               AH/T01119X/1). Thanks also to the Mapping the Jewish Communities of the Byzantine
               Empire project team, Nicholas de Lange, Alexander Panayotov and especially Fredrik
               Palm for productive discussions and to the European Research Council for their
               funding. The Pelagios Commons project generously supported the Web Maps-T hack event
               held in 2019 and conversations with the participants provided insights into many of
               the issues outlined here. Furthermore, the partners of the Pelagios Network have been
               a source of inspiration for several years now. Finally thanks to Victoria Morris at
               the British Library and Andy Woodruff and Tim Wallace from Bostonography for their
               kind permission to use their data and images.</p>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alf_n.d." label="Aikaterini Laskaridis Foundation n.d.">Aikaterini
               Laskaridis Foundation. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Travellers Maps.</title> Available
               at: <ref target="https://travellersmap.gr/public">https://travellersmap.gr/public</ref> (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andrienko_2006" label="Andrienko and Andrienko 2006">Andrienko, N. and
               Andrienko, G. (2006) <title rend="italic">Exploratory Analysis of Spatial and
                  Temporal Data: A Systematic Approach</title>. Berlin Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag.
               Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-31190-4">https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-31190-4</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="battersby_2014" label="Battersby et al. 2014">Battersby, S., Finn, M.,
               Usery, E. and Yamamoto, K. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Implications of Web Mercator
                  and its use in online mapping</title>, <title rend="italic">Cartographica: The
                  International Journal for Geographic Information and Geovisualization</title>, 49,
               pp. 85–101. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3138/carto.49.2.2313">https://doi.org/10.3138/carto.49.2.2313</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="battersby_2019" label="Battersby and Kessler 2019">Battersby, S. and
               Kessler, F.C. (2019) <title rend="italic">Working with Map Projections: A Guide to
                  Their Selection</title>. Boca Raton: CRC Press. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1201/9780203731413">https://doi.org/10.1201/9780203731413</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blaschke_2018" label="Blaschke et al. 2018">Blaschke, T., Merschdorf, H.,
               Cabrera-Barona, P., Gao, S., Papadakis, E. and Kovacs-Györi, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Place versus space: From points, lines and polygons in GIS to
                  place-based representations reflecting language and culture</title>, <title rend="italic">ISPRS International Journal of Geo-Information</title>, 7(11), pp.
               452–478. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi7110452">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi7110452</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodenhamer_2010" label="Bodenhamer, Corrigan, and Harris 2010">Bodenhamer,
               D.J., Corrigan, J. and Harris, T.M. (eds) (2010) <title rend="italic">The Spatial
                  Humanities: GIS and the Future of Humanities Scholarship</title>. Bloomington:
               Indiana University Press. Available at: <ref target="https://libcat.uchicago.edu/ipac20/ipac.jsp?uri=link=3100007~!11378488~!3100001~!3100002&amp;profile=ucpublic">https://libcat.uchicago.edu/ipac20/ipac.jsp?uri=link=3100007~!11378488~!3100001~!3100002&amp;profile=ucpublic</ref>
               (Accessed: 14 March 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodenhamer_2021" label="Bodenhamer, Corrigan, and Harris 2021">Bodenhamer,
               D.J., Corrigan, J. and Harris, T.M. (2021) <title rend="italic">Making Deep Maps:
                  Foundations, Approaches, and Methods</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borek_2016" label="Borek et al. 2016">Borek, L., Dombrowski, Q., Perkins,
               J. and Schöch, C. (2016) <title rend="quotes">TaDiRAH: A case study in pragmatic
                  classification</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>,
               10(1). Available at: <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/10/1/000235/000235.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/10/1/000235/000235.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carto_n.d." label="Carto n.d.">Carto (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Carto.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://carto.com">https://carto.com</ref> (Accessed: 14 October 2025).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="center-for-public-history_n.d." label="Center for Public History and Digital Humanities at Cleveland State                University n.d.">Center for Public History and Digital Humanities at
               Cleveland State University. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Cleveland Historical</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="https://clevelandhistorical.org/items/map">https://clevelandhistorical.org/items/map</ref> (Accessed: 9 October 2024) </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cbl_n.d." label="Charles Booth's London n.d." sortKey="Charles">
               <title rend="italic">Charles Booth’s London</title> (n.d.). Available at: <ref target="https://booth.lse.ac.uk/map">https://booth.lse.ac.uk/map</ref> (Accessed:
               3 February 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cummings_2022" label="Cummings 2022">Cummings, J. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Awards | Highlighting resources in digital
                  humanities</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://dhawards.org/">http://dhawards.org/</ref> (Accessed: 8 November 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dansk_n.d." label="Dansk Center for Herregårdsforskning n.d." sortKey="Dansk">Dansk Center for Herregårdsforskning. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Danish Manors.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://www.danskeherregaarde.dk/nutid/fovslet">https://www.danskeherregaarde.dk/nutid/fovslet</ref> (Accessed: 9 October
               2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker_2020" label="Drucker 2020">Drucker, J. (2020) <title rend="italic">Visualization and Interpretation: Humanistic Approaches to Display</title>.
               Cambridge, MA: The Massachusetts Institute of Technology Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunn_2019" label="Dunn 2019">Dunn, S. (2019) <title rend="italic">A
                  History of Place in the Digital Age</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elfenbein_n.d." label="Elfenbein n.d.">Elfenbein, C. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Mapping Islamophobia</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://mappingislamophobia.org">https://mappingislamophobia.org</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eltis_2010" label="Eltis and Richardson 2010">Eltis, D. and Richardson, D.
               (2010) <title rend="italic">SlaveVoyages. Maps from Atlas of the Transatlantic Slave
                  Trade</title> Available at: <ref target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/blog/tag/intro-maps">https://www.slavevoyages.org/blog/tag/intro-maps</ref> (Accessed: 9 October
               2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="emory_n.d." label="Emory University Digital Humanities Center n.d." sortKey="Emory">Emory University Digital Humanities Center. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Power of Attorney in Oaxaca, Mexico</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.powerofattorneynative.com/about/">https://www.powerofattorneynative.com/about/#</ref> (Accessed: 9 October
               2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fleet_2019" label="Fleet 2019">Fleet, C. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Creating, managing, and maximising the potential of large online georeferenced
                  map layers</title>, <title rend="italic">e Perimetron</title>, 14, pp.
               140–149.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gentzel_2021" label="Gentzel, Wimmer, and Schlagowski 2021">Gentzel, P.,
               Wimmer, J. and Schlagowski, R. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Doing Google Maps</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Culture &amp; Society</title>, 7(2), pp. 159–184.
               Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.14361/dcs-2021-070208">https://doi.org/10.14361/dcs-2021-070208</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gieseking_2018" label="Geiseking 2018">Gieseking, J.J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Where are we? The method of mapping with GIS in digital
                  humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 70(3), pp.
               641–648. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0047">https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0047</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="google_n.d." label="Google n.d.">Google (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Google
                  My Maps.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://mymaps.google.com">https://mymaps.google.com</ref> (Accessed: 14 October 2025). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gradmann_2015" label="Gradmann et al. 2015">Gradmann, S., Hennicke, S.,
               Tschumpel, G., Dill, K., Thoden, K., Pichler, A. and Morbidoni, C. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Beyond infrastructure! Modelling the scholarly domain</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/34625773.pdf">https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/34625773.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gregory_2010" label="Gregory 2010">Gregory, I.N. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Exploiting time and space: A challenge for GIS in the digital
                  humanities</title>, in D.J. Bodenhamer, J. Corrigan, and T.M. Harris (eds) <title rend="italic">The Spatial Humanities: GIS and the Future of Humanities
                  Scholarship.</title> Indiana: Indiana University Press, pp. 58–75.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gregory_2007" label="Gregory and Healey 2007">Gregory, I.N. and Healey,
               R.G. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Historical GIS: Structuring, mapping and analysing
                  geographies of the past</title>, <title rend="italic">Progress in Human
                  Geography</title>, 31(5), pp. 638–653. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0309132507081495">https://doi.org/10.1177/0309132507081495</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gui_2016" label="Gui et al. 2016">Gui, Z., Cao, J., Liu, X., Cheng, X. and
               Wu, H. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Global-scale resource survey and performance
                  monitoring of public OGC web map services</title>, <title rend="italic">ISPRS
                  International Journal of Geo-Information</title>, 5(6), pp. 88–112. Available at:
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi5060088">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi5060088</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="haklay_2008" label="Haklay, Singleton, and Parker 2008">Haklay, M.,
               Singleton, A. and Parker, C. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Web mapping 2.0: The
                  neogeography of the geoweb</title>, <title rend="italic">Geography
               Compass</title>, 2(6), pp. 2011–2039. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-8198.2008.00167.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-8198.2008.00167.x</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harvard_n.d." label="Harvard University n.d." sortKey="Harvard">Harvard
               University. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">The Mapping Past Societies project.</title>
               Available at: <ref target="https://darmc.harvard.edu">https://darmc.harvard.edu</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hepworth_2019" label="Hepworth and Church 2019">Hepworth, K. and Church,
               C. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Racism in the machine: Visualization ethics in digital
                  humanities projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, 12(4). Available at: <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hinrichs_2019" label="Hinrichs et al. 2019">Hinrichs, U., Forlini, S. and
               Moynihan, B. (2019) <title rend="quotes">In defense of sandcastles: Research thinking
                  through visualization in digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34(Supplement_1), pp. i80–i99. Available
               at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="horne_2022" label="Horne et al. 2022">Horne, R., Talbert, R., Becker, J.,
               Twele, R., Jo, A., Belanger, R., Hagemann, L., Lee, A., Bowen, J. and Butler, M.
               (2022) <title rend="italic">Consortium of Ancient World Mappers Map Tiles</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="http://cawm.lib.uiowa.edu/index.html">http://cawm.lib.uiowa.edu/index.html</ref> (Accessed: 15 December 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="humanities-design_2014" label="Humanities + Design, Stanford University 2014" sortKey="Humanities">Humanities
               + Design, Stanford University (2014) <title rend="italic">Palladio Home Page</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Palladio</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://hdlab.stanford.edu/Palladio">http://hdlab.stanford.edu/Palladio</ref> (Accessed: 16 January 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jessop_2006" label="Jessop 2006">Jessop, M. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Dynamic maps in humanities computing</title>, <title rend="italic">Human IT:
                  Journal for Information Technology Studies as a Human Science</title>, 8(3), pp.
               68–82.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jokar-arsanjani_2015" label="Jokar Arsanjani et al. 2015">Jokar Arsanjani,
               J., Zipf, A., Mooney, P. and Helbich, M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">An introduction
                  to OpenStreetMap in Geographic Information Science: Experiences, research, and
                  applications</title>, in J. Jokar Arsanjani, A. Zipf, P. Mooney, and M. Helbich
               (eds.) <title rend="italic">OpenStreetMap in GIScience: Experiences, Research, and
                  Applications</title>. Cham: Springer International Publishing, pp. 1–15. Available
               at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-14280-7_1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-14280-7_1</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kahn_2021" label="Kahn and Bouie 2021">Kahn, A. and Bouie, J. (2021)
                  <title rend="quotes">The Atlantic Slave Trade in two minutes</title>, <title rend="italic">Slate</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2021/09/atlantic-slave-trade-history-animated-interactive.html">https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2021/09/atlantic-slave-trade-history-animated-interactive.html</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kessler_2017" label="Kessler et al. 2017">Kessler, F.C., Battersby, S.E.,
               Finn, M.P. and Clarke, K.C. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Map projections and the
                  Internet</title>, in M. Lapaine and E.L. Usery (eds) <title rend="italic">Choosing
                  a Map Projection</title>. Cham: Springer International Publishing (Lecture Notes
               in Geoinformation and Cartography), pp. 117–148. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-51835-0_4">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-51835-0_4</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klokan_2009" label="Klokan Technologies 2009" sortKey="Klokana">Klokan
               Technologies (2009) <title rend="italic">WGS 84 / World Equidistant Cylindrical -
                  EPSG:4087</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://epsg.io/4087">https://epsg.io/4087</ref> (Accessed: 20 March 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klokan_2020a" label="Klokan 2020a" sortKey="Klokanb">Klokan Technologies
               (2020a) <title rend="italic">WGS 84 / Antarctic Polar Stereographic -
                  EPSG:3031</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://epsg.io/3031">https://epsg.io/3031</ref> (Accessed: 20 March 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klokan_2020b" label="Klokan 2020b" sortKey="Klokanc">Klokan Technologies
               (2020b) <title rend="italic">WGS 84 / Equal Earth Greenwich - EPSG:8857</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="https://epsg.io/8857">https://epsg.io/8857</ref>
               (Accessed: 20 March 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klokan_2020c" label="Klokan 2020c" sortKey="Klokand">Klokan Technologies
               (2020c) <title rend="italic">WGS 84 / Pseudo-Mercator - Spherical Mercator, Google
                  Maps, OpenStreetMap, Bing, ArcGIS, ESRI - EPSG:3857</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://epsg.io/3857">https://epsg.io/3857</ref> (Accessed: 20 March
               2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klokan_n.d." label="Klokan n.d." sortKey="Klokane">Klokan Technologies
               (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Georeferencer Home Page</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.georeferencer.com/">https://www.georeferencer.com/</ref>
               (Accessed: 16 January 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kunz_n.d." label="Kunz and Moeschl n.d.">Kunz, A. and Moeschl, R. (n.d.)
                  <title rend="italic">Die politische Landkarte Europas Digitaler Atlas zur
                  Geschichte Europas seit 1500</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.atlas-europa.de/t01/territorien-staaten/t01-territorien-staaten.htm">https://www.atlas-europa.de/t01/territorien-staaten/t01-territorien-staaten.htm</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leaflet_n.d." label="Leaflet n.d.">Leaflet (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Plugins for Leaflet, a JavaScript library for interactive maps</title>. Available
               at: <ref target="https://leafletjs.com/plugins.html">https://leafletjs.com/plugins.html</ref> (Accessed: 2 March 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="levin_n.d." label="Levin n.d.">Levin, J. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Anterotesis. DH GIS Projects.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://anterotesis.com/wordpress/mapping-resources/dh-gis-projects/">https://anterotesis.com/wordpress/mapping-resources/dh-gis-projects/</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luchetta_2017" label="Luchetta 2017">Luchetta, S. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Exploring the literary map: An analytical review of online literary
                  mapping projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Geography Compass</title>, 11(1),
               pp. 1–17. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/gec3.12303">https://doi.org/10.1111/gec3.12303</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lumley_2019" label="Lumley and Sieber 2019">Lumley, S. and Sieber, R.
               (2019) <title rend="quotes">Web maps for global data visualization: Does Mercator
                  matter?</title>, <title rend="italic">Spatial Knowledge and Information
                  Canada</title>, 7(1), pp. 1–6. Available at: <ref target="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2323/SKI-Canada-2019-7-1-5.pdf">https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2323/SKI-Canada-2019-7-1-5.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maceachren_1990" label="MacEachren and Ganter 1990" sortKey="Maceachrena">MacEachren, A. and Ganter, J. (1990) <title rend="quotes">A Pattern Identification
                  Approach to Cartographic Visualization</title>, <title rend="italic">Cartographica: The International Journal for Geographic Information and
                  Geovisualization</title>, 27, pp. 64–81. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3138/M226-1337-2387-3007">https://doi.org/10.3138/M226-1337-2387-3007</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maceachren_1997" label="MacEachren and Kraak 1997" sortKey="Maceachrenb">MacEachren, A.M. and Kraak, M.-J. (1997) <title rend="quotes">Exploratory
                  cartographic visualization: Advancing the agenda</title>, <title rend="italic">Computers &amp; Geosciences</title>, 23(4), pp. 335–343. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0098-3004(97)00018-6">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0098-3004(97)00018-6</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mapbox_n.d." label="Mapbox n.d.">Mapbox (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Projections | Mapbox GL JS</title>, <title rend="italic">Projections | Mapbox GL
                  JS</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://docs.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-js/guides/projections/">https://docs.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-js/guides/projections/</ref> (Accessed: 20
               March 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mayr_2018" label="Mayr and Windhager 2018">Mayr, E. and Windhager, F.
               (2018) <title rend="quotes">Once upon a spacetime: Visual storytelling in cognitive
                  and geotemporal information spaces</title>, <title rend="italic">ISPRS
                  International Journal of Geo-Information</title>, 7(3), pp. 96–114. Available at:
                  <ref target=" https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi7030096">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi7030096</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcquire_2019" label="McQuire 2019" sortKey="Mcquire">McQuire, S. (2019)
                  <title rend="quotes">One map to rule them all? Google Maps as digital technical
                  object</title>, <title rend="italic">Communication and the Public</title>, 4(2),
               pp. 150–165. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/2057047319850192">https://doi.org/10.1177/2057047319850192</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monmonier_2004" label="Monmonier 2004">Monmonier, M.S. (2004) <title rend="italic">Rhumb Lines and Map Wars: A Social History of the Mercator
                  Projection</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mostern_2013" label="Mostern and Gainor 2013">Mostern, R. and Gainor, E.
               (2013) <title rend="quotes">Traveling the Silk Road on a virtual globe: Pedagogy,
                  technology and evaluation for spatial history</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 7(2). Available at: <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/7/2/000116/000116.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/7/2/000116/000116.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mullen_2014" label="Mullen 2014">Mullen, L. (2014) <title rend="italic">The Spread of U.S. Slavery, 1790–1860.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://lincolnmullen.com/projects/slavery">https://lincolnmullen.com/projects/slavery</ref> (Accessed: 9 October
               2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="norman_2013" label="Norman 2013">Norman, D.A. (2013) <title rend="italic">The Design of Everyday Things</title>. Revised and expanded edition. New York,
               New York: Basic Books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ogc_n.d." label="OGC n.d." sortKey="Ogc">OGC (n.d.) <title rend="italic">OGC Standards | Open Geospatial Consortium</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.ogc.org/docs/is">https://www.ogc.org/docs/is</ref> (Accessed:
               7 January 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="openlayers_n.d." label="OpenLayers n.d." sortKey="Openlayers">OpenLayers.
               (n.d.) <title rend="italic">OpenLayers</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://openlayers.org/">https://openlayers.org/</ref> (Accessed: 9
               October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="panayotov_2013" label="Panayotov 2013">Panayotov, A., de Lange, N., Rees,
               G. and Palm, F. (2013) <title rend="italic">Mapping the Jewish Communities of the
                  Byzantine Empire</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://byzantinejewry.net/">http://byzantinejewry.net/</ref> (Accessed: 3 February 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pauliceia-2.0_n.d." label="Pauliceia 2.0. n.d." sortKey="Pauliceia">Pauliceia 2.0. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Plataforma Pauliceia 2.0: Mapeamento
                  Colaborativo da História de São Paulo</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://www.pauliceia.dpi.inpe.br/portal/home">http://www.pauliceia.dpi.inpe.br/portal/home</ref> (Accessed: 9 October
               2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="programming-historian_n.d." label="Programming Historian n.d." sortKey="Programming">Programming Historian (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Mapping
                  Lesson Directory</title>, <title rend="italic">Programming Historian</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="http://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/?topic=mapping">http://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/?topic=mapping</ref> (Accessed: 16
               January 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rabinowitz_2013" label="Rabinowitz 2013">Rabinowitz, A. (2013) <title rend="quotes">GeoDia: or, Navigating archaeological time and space in an American
                  college classroom</title>, in <title rend="italic">Archaeology in the Digital Era
                  Papers from the 40th Annual Conference of Computer Applications and Quantitative
                  Methods in Archaeology (CAA)</title>, Southampton, 26-29 March 2012 Amsterdam:
               Amsterdam University Press, pp. 259–268. Available at: <ref target="https://www.academia.edu/1801635/GeoDia_or_Navigating_archaeological_time_and_space_in_an_American_college_classroom">https://www.academia.edu/1801635/GeoDia_or_Navigating_archaeological_time_and_space_in_an_American_college_classroom</ref>
               (Accessed: 16 June 2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramsay_2012" label="Ramsay and Rockwell 2012">Ramsay, S. and Rockwell, G.
               (2012) <title rend="quotes">Developing things: Notes toward an epistemology of
                  building in the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                  digital humanities</title>, pp. 75–84. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctttv8hq.8"
                  >https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctttv8hq.8</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rees_2018" label="Rees et al. 2018" sortKey="Reesa">Rees, G., de Lange, N.
               and Panayotov, A. . (2018) <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Jewish communities of the
                  Byzantine Empire using GIS</title>, in <title rend="italic">Migration and Migrant
                  Identities in the Near East from Antiquity to the Middle Ages</title>. London:
               Routledge, pp. 104–121.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rees_2022" label="Rees et al. 2022" sortKey="Reesb">Rees, G., Hunt, A.,
               Vitale, V., Horgan, J. and Strachan, P. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Discovering the
                  local in national cultural heritage collections. How web maps can help the UK
                  public engage with their <q>own places</q></title>, <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp; Society</title>, 0(0), pp. 1–19. Available at:
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2113819">https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2113819</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="richmond_2017" label="Richmond and Tavenner 2017">Richmond, S.J. and
               Tavenner, T. (2017) <title rend="italic">Using JavaScript to Create Maps of
                  Correspondence</title>, <title rend="italic">Programming Historian</title>.
               Available at: <ref target="https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/using-javascript-to-create-maps">https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/using-javascript-to-create-maps</ref>
               (Accessed: 6 December 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roth_2013" label="Roth 2013">Roth, R. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Interactive maps: What we know and what we need to know</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Journal of Spatial Information Science</title>, 6, pp. 59–115.
               Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5311/JOSIS.2013.6.105"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5311/JOSIS.2013.6.105</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="scheidel_2014" label="Sheidel et al. 2014">Scheidel, W., Meeks, E. and
               Grossner, K. (2014) <title rend="italic">ORBIS: The Stanford Geospatial Network Model
                  of the Roman World</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://orbis.stanford.edu/">https://orbis.stanford.edu/</ref> (Accessed:
               9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="seydi_2022" label="Seydi and Romanov 2022">Seydi, M. and Romanov, M.
               (2022) <title rend="italic">al-Ṯurayyā Project: A Gazetteer and A Geospatial Model of
                  the Early Islamic World.</title> Available at: <ref target="https://althurayya.github.io/">https://althurayya.github.io/</ref>
               (Accessed: 9 October 2024).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shneiderman_1996" label="Shneiderman 1996">Shneiderman, B. (1996) <title rend="quotes">The eyes have it: A task by data type taxonomy for information
                  visualizations</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings 1996 IEEE symposium on
                  visual languages</title>. IEEE, pp. 336–343.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="simon_2022" label="Simon et al. 2022">Simon, R., Gadd, S., Rees, G. and
               Isaksen, L. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Peripleo</title>, <title rend="italic">Austrian Institute of Technology. </title>Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.23636/sd7c-k310">https://doi.org/10.23636/sd7c-k310</ref> (Accessed: 24 February 2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skopeliti_2019" label="Skopeliti and Stamou 2019">Skopeliti, A. and
               Stamou, L. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Online map services: Contemporary cartography
                  or a new cartographic culture?</title>, <title rend="italic">ISPRS International
                  Journal of Geo-Information</title>, 8(5), pp. 215–243. Available at: <ref target=" https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi8050215">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi8050215</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="soeller_2016" label="Soeller et al. 2016">Soeller, G., Karahalios, K.,
               Wilson, C. and Sandvig, C. (2016) <title rend="quotes">MapWatch: Detecting and
                  monitoring international border personalization on Online Maps</title>, in <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 25th international conference on world wide
                  web</title>, pp. 867–878. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2872427.2883016"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1145/2872427.2883016</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="spann_n.d." label="Spaan and Schoonman n.d.">Spaan, B. and Schoonman, J.
               (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Allmaps</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://allmaps.org/">https://allmaps.org/</ref> (Accessed: 16 January
               2023).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tadirah_n.d." label="TaDiRAH n.d." sortKey="Tadirah">TaDiRAH (n.d.) <title rend="italic">TaDiRAH: Taxonomy of Digital Research Activities in the
                  Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">GitHub</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH">https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH</ref> (Accessed: 8 July 2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth_n.d." label="Unsworth n.d.">Unsworth, J. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods do Humanities Researchers Have in
                  Common, And How Might Our Tools Reflect This</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://johnunsworth.name/Kings.5-00/primitives.html">http://johnunsworth.name/Kings.5-00/primitives.html</ref> (Accessed: 19 October
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitelaw_2015" label="Whitelaw 2015">Whitelaw, M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Generous interfaces for digital cultural collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9(1). Available at: <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html</ref></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
