<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Social Networks and Archival Context Project: A Case Study of
                    Emerging Cyberinfrastructure</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Tom J. <dhq:family>Lynch</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Computer Sciences Corporation</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>tlynch6@csc.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Tom J. Lynch is a Senior Application Designer at CSC, Computer Sciences
                            Corporation. Since 1997, his professional interests have included the
                            design and development of web-based software applications, data
                            modeling, and user-interface design. In 2012, he completed a Master of
                            Library and Information Science at the University of Illinois at
                            Urbana-Champaign where his research interests included data curation,
                            digital humanities, and text mining.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000184</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2014-10-09">9 October 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>For digital humanists planning to build tools for cyberinfrastructure several
                    variables ought to be defined for each project. Pay close attention to the
                    balance of traditional methods and new ways of conducting research. When
                    gathering resources to do the job, seek contributions of different domain
                    experts. Also, careful consideration of a tool’s intended scope will help refine
                    the required resources needed to complete a project. This case study illustrates
                    how one project, the Social Networks and Archival Context Project (SNAC), has
                    defined these variables. The process of building a new tool also benefits from
                    an awareness of older infrastructure that has come before it. SNAC illustrates
                    this awareness in the way it has taken advantage of previously existing
                    infrastructure, both cyber and not, by extending its purpose and building new
                    features on top of it.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A case study of the Social Networks and Archival Context Project</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>When speculating about the future of scholarship, it seems certain that research and
                teaching will continue to be affected by the evolution of traditional infrastructure
                into digital forms. This is as true for the humanities as it is for other
                disciplines and digital humanists in particular should have an important role to
                play in shaping the infrastructure for their domains. Digital humanists, who can
                both identify the needs of mainstream humanities scholars and suggest acceptable
                computational solutions to those needs <ptr target="#joula2008"/>, are essential
                participants in the development of a new digital cyberinfrastructure for humanities
                research. </p>
            <p>The American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) report on cyberinfrastructure
                defines cyberinfrastructure as <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#acls2006">the layer of information, expertise,
                        standards, policies, tools, and services that are shared broadly across
                        communities of inquiry but developed for specific scholarly purposes:
                        cyberinfrastructure is something more specific than the network itself, but
                        it is something more general than a tool or a resource developed for a
                        particular project, a range of projects, or, even more broadly, for a
                        particular discipline.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#acls2006"/>
                </cit>This definition leaves a lot of room to imagine the technological future of
                the humanities, allowing researchers and educators to decide for themselves the
                appropriate tools and services that will meet their needs. While the report states
                that cyberinfrastructure is something more general than a tool or resource, tools
                will be a necessary component. For digital humanists planning to build tools for
                cyberinfrastructure, it is helpful to pay close attention to the balance of
                traditional methods and new ways of conducting research, and to the contributions of
                different domain experts, when gathering resources to do the job. Careful
                consideration of a tool’s intended scope will also help refine the required
                resources needed to complete a project. The following case study will illustrate how
                one project has successfully balanced these variables and it may serve as a model
                for designing others. I will discuss each of these variables more, but I also want
                to introduce the idea of an infrastructure stack on top of which a successful
                cyberinfrastructure tool rests. The stack serves as a foundation for the new
                technology by linking it to the past. The sense of the word <q>stack</q> I use is
                the one that refers to a pile of objects, one on top of the other. In this case the
                stacked objects are abstract systems and technologies. The oldest technology rests
                at the bottom and newer technologies pile up to the top. If you remove one from the
                stack, the objects above it and supported by it could not exist without the missing
                foundation. To illustrate this concept and elaborate on the balancing act of tool
                design, I offer a case study of The Social Networks and Archival Context (SNAC)
                Project, which is an emerging example of cyberinfrastructure. SNAC serves this
                purpose by demonstrating the ability to balance many of the variables necessary for
                cyberinfrastructure and the project is built upon an easily definable infrastructure
                stack. I will begin this case study with a description of SNAC and its prototype
                user interface. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Introducing SNAC</head>
                <p>The SNAC project aims to provide scholars with improved access to distributed
                    historical records with new discovery tools. The heart of the project is a very
                    large (and still growing) dataset of archival creator descriptions expressed in
                    the international metadata standard Encoded Archival Context-Corporate Bodies,
                    Persons, and Families (EAC-CPF). The records describe people and corporate
                    bodies who are the creators of primary humanities resources that have been
                    collected into archives and libraries around the world. The descriptions contain
                    biographical data, lists of associated resources, and lists of associations with
                    other people. This curated set of data enables SNAC to build new discovery tools
                    for researchers. SNAC’s goal is to provide improved access to the resources that
                    document the lives, work, and events surrounding historical persons, and provide
                    unprecedented access to the biographical-historical contexts of the people
                    documented in the resources, including the social-professional networks within
                    which they lived and worked <ptr target="#IATHb"/>.</p>
                <p>SNAC’s emphasis on social networks is, of course, no accident. Social networks
                    are a hot topic. However, social networks have been around far longer than
                    Facebook. Simply put, a network is a set of relations between objects; a social
                    network the set of relations between people. Kadushin describes social networks
                    as having been <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#kadushin2012">at the core of human society
                            since we were hunters and gatherers. People were tied together through
                            their relations with one another and their dependence on one
                            another…Kinship and family relations are social networks. Neighbors,
                            villages, and cities are crisscrossed with networks of obligations and
                            relationships.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kadushin2012"/>
                    </cit> What is relatively new, Kadushin continues, are <cit><quote rend="inline"
                        source="#kadushin2012">systematic ways of talking about social networks, depicting
                        them, analyzing them, and showing how they are related to more formal social
                        arrangements such as organizations and governments.</quote><ptr target="#kadushin2012"/></cit></p>
                <p> From Facebook to Flickr, Twitter to Tumblr, the social networking concept is
                    embodied everywhere online through many widely used Web applications. Taking
                    advantage of the relationships captured in its dataset, SNAC has developed a
                    social network web application that has helped the project earn the nickname
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#seal2012">Facebook for the dead</quote>
                    <ptr target="#seal2012"/>. The comparison with the ubiquitous social networking
                    site is not without some utility. Social networking sites like Facebook enable
                    users to articulate and make visible their social networks <ptr
                        target="#boydellison2008"/>, which is the organizing principle for SNAC’s
                    data. Boyd and Ellison define social network sites as web-based services that
                    allow individuals to construct a profile within a bounded system, articulate a
                    list of other users with whom they share a connection, and view and traverse
                    their list of connections and those made by others within the system. In its own
                    way, SNAC provides these same features for historical figures. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>SNAC profile for J. Robert Oppenheimer</head>
                    <figDesc>Screenshot of SNAC profile for J. Robert Oppenheimer</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Figure 1 shows an example of a personal profile in the online SNAC prototype
                        (<ref target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/snac/search"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/snac/search</ref>), in this case the
                    one for J. Robert Oppenheimer. The profile contains descriptive metadata such as
                    life dates, occupations, subjects to which the person is related, alternative
                    forms of his or her name, and a biographical history. The central column
                    contains <q>Links to collections</q> and <q>Related names in SNAC,</q> where
                    lists of connections from the personal profile to archival collections, other
                    people, corporate bodies, and resources are articulated as well as providing
                    links to traverse the connections. For example, Oppenheimer is listed as the
                    creator of 38 collections housed at the Library of Congress and several
                    university libraries. Additionally, SNAC lists another 163 archival collections
                    in which Oppenheimer is referenced. For each of these collections SNAC provides
                    a link to its entry in WorldCat, the online catalog of the world’s largest
                    network of library content and services <ptr target="#worldcat"/>. In addition
                    to these external links, SNAC also links internally to the profiles of other
                    people, families, and organizations that share a connection to a given profile.
                    Oppenheimer, for example, is listed as having been associated with or
                    corresponded with 175 other people and 35 organizations, all of which have a
                    profile in SNAC. </p>
                <p> The profile pages, the links between them, and the lists of external related
                    resources are not created manually by experts. Another characteristic SNAC
                    shares with social networking sites is the bottom-up, rather than top-down,
                    approach to organizing its content. Individuals in the online community define
                    the content and structure of a typical social network site instead of
                    professional information providers <ptr target="#kolbitschmaurer2006"/>. SNAC
                    allows the properties of its data (such as the names, dates, correspondence
                    relationships, and creator attributions captured in the EAC-CPF records) to
                    self-organize the information presented in the system. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Project Variables</head>
                <p>Using SNAC as an example this case study will show what a software tool may look
                    like within humanities cyberinfrastructure and describe its relationship with
                    the other components listed in the definition of cyberinfrastructure from the
                    ACLS report quoted above (information, expertise, standards, etc.). Alongside
                    discussing SNAC specifically, I will address cyberinfrastructure more generally
                    by defining a set of variables to consider when approaching the design of a new
                    tool. When reviewing the existing literature about humanities
                    cyberinfrastructure a picture emerges that helps define these variables. Imagine
                    a three-dimensional graph where examples of cyberinfrastructure technology could
                    be plotted. The three axes of the graph represent the following opposing
                    extremes:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item>X: Created by humanists ← → Created by non-humanists</item>
                    <item>Y: Small boutique projects ← → General-purpose applications</item>
                    <item>Z: Traditional humanities infrastructure ← → Scientific
                        cyberinfrastructure</item>
                </list>
                <p>I will discuss each of these axes in turn through highlighting ideas from the
                    literature, as well as show how SNAC is a real-world example of how one project
                    has found its place on the graph by striking an appropriate balance for its
                    context on each axis. Plotting a multitude of projects on the axes imagined here
                    is beyond the scope of this article, but I do believe SNAC falls close to the
                    middle of the graph, hence its use as an illustrative example.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>A trio of variables that affect humanities cyberinfrastructure</head>
                    <figDesc>Screenshot of three variables affecting humanities
                        cyberinfrastructure</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.gif"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>X: Created by humanists ← → Created by non-humanists</head>
                    <p>Due to its complexity and necessarily broad range of required skills, the
                        development of cyberinfrastructure often requires collaboration between
                        humanists and non-humanists. First and foremost, scholars of the humanities
                        must lead the development of their own cyberinfrastructure, despite the fact
                        that tool development is not yet rewarded on par with more traditional
                        scholarly outputs <ptr target="#schreibmanhanlon2010"/>. They alone can
                        accomplish the intellectual task of modeling scholarship for new digital
                        environments <ptr target="#drucker2009"/>. They alone can judge its
                        usefulness and assure that the technology will serve their needs <ptr
                            target="#huntetal2011"/>. However, few individual humanities experts
                        (let alone any expert) will have the range of expertise required to build
                        cyberinfrastructure, so librarians, archivists, programmers, and computer
                        scientists will bring essential complementary skills to the task <ptr
                            target="#borgman2009"/>. Technology developers and humanities
                        researchers working alongside each other are likely to push both the
                        technical and the intellectual boundaries farther, yielding greater
                        innovation <ptr target="#collinsetal2012"/>. Casting the net even wider, the
                        ACLS report, which lists collaboration as a necessary characteristic of
                        cyberinfrastructure, calls for <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#acls2006">cooperation with librarians,
                                curators, and archivists; the involvement of experts in the
                                sciences, law, business, and entertainment; and active participation
                                from and endorsement by the general public</quote>
                            <ptr target="#acls2006"/>
                        </cit>. However, it should be noted that, while necessary, collaboration is
                        itself a challenge that requires careful resolution of methodological
                        differences and regular communication about each collaborators’ perspective
                            <ptr target="#chuketal2012"/>.</p>
                    <p>In the case of SNAC, its emphasis on social networks is conducive to
                        attracting collaborative partners. The study of social networks has been
                        identified as a cross-cutting agenda where the digital scholarship of
                        humanists, technology researchers, and others converge in a way that
                        encourages collaboration and, in particular, brings humanists to a seat at
                        the table where scholarly infrastructure decisions are being made <ptr
                            target="#borgman2009"/>. The social network is a topic that lends itself
                        to interesting collaborations among many different disciplines with a scope
                        not so narrow as to constrain research nor so expansive as to be meaningless
                            <ptr target="#friedlander2009"/>.</p>
                    <p>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities (IATH), University of
                        Virginia, leads the team developing SNAC. IATH is known for collaborative
                        research and technology development with the practical needs of humanities
                        scholars as its primary motivation. The list of other participating
                        institutions and individuals on SNAC’s project team and advisory board
                        suggests a wide range of disciplinary expertise is contributing to the
                        project, including historians, English scholars, librarians, archivists,
                        information technology developers, information scientists, computer
                        scientists, and more <ptr target="#IATHc"/>. The breadth of knowledge
                        required by the development of SNAC means no single discipline has all the
                        answers to the project’s research questions. Archivists, librarians, and
                        information scientists are needed for their expertise in existing
                        infrastructure surrounding primary resources, experience in information
                        organization, and their knowledge of new data standards. Computer scientists
                        and developers contribute by solving and implementing solutions for the
                        myriad of technical challenges encountered during the course of SNAC’s
                        development. Historians and English scholars contribute their knowledge of
                        humanities research methods and SNAC’s user community, helping shape the
                        public interface to the data and ensuring the new tools are designed to be
                        of practical value to scholars. For the sake of brevity, these examples are
                        probably oversimplified. The full picture of collaboration on SNAC is more
                        complicated, especially since its participants often wear multiple hats and
                        it is hard to encapsulate all the multidisciplinary challenges faced by SNAC
                        in a few short sentences. However, the team does appear to have a mix of
                        expertise well suited to the task of developing SNAC.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Y: Small boutique projects ← → General-purpose applications</head>
                    <p>Given the great need for teams of collaborators, it should be evident that
                        the scale of cyberinfrastructure research is large, the goals are many and
                        multi-faceted, and the aim is to serve a large audience. However, attempting
                        to do too much, to make a technology useful for everyone in the humanities,
                        risks the possibility of making it useful for nobody, because a tool with a
                        very broad audience in mind is unlikely to meet the requirements of
                        specialized fields <ptr target="#huntetal2011"/>. At the other end of the
                        scale, cyberinfrastructure of the past decade has led humanities researchers
                        to create smaller, isolated projects, the contents of which cannot be easily
                        combined for analysis without the development of a more robust
                        infrastructure to link them together <ptr target="#blackwellcrane2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#craneetal2009"/>. Creators of a cyberinfrastructure tool
                        should have a specific audience in mind and build features into a tool that
                        serves that audience well, but the tool should also be interoperable with
                        other systems to support some unimagined uses by unanticipated users. A
                        successful cyberinfrastructure of the future will likely consist of multiple
                        systems that exist to support the specialized needs of each discipline, yet
                        support the sharing of data between these systems <ptr
                            target="#huntetal2011"/>. </p>
                    <p>SNAC’s focus on social networks and creator description limits its scope by
                        reducing the types of data to be managed and the kinds of functionality
                        designers might build into the tool for analysis. However, it does not
                        restrict the size of the project. SNAC is poised to expand widely within a
                        certain band of information, specifically the description of primary
                        resource creators and the relations between them. SNAC has compiled over 2.6
                        million EAC-CPF records describing persons, families, and corporate bodies
                            <ptr target="#IATH2014"/> since the project began. In future phases of
                        development, nearly 4 million EAC-CPF records may be generated, creating an
                        unprecedented collection of data about the lives, work, and events
                        surrounding historic persons <ptr target="#IATHb"/>. </p>
                    <p>With its narrow, but deep, focus on creator description, SNAC intends to do a
                        handful of tasks extremely well and integrate itself into existing
                        infrastructure to offer researchers more functionality. The challenges
                        involved in creating, managing, and providing access to this massive amount
                        of data are a big enough task for one project, so SNAC will rely on others
                        to extend its functionality. For example, SNAC does not intend to collect
                        digitized primary resources or provide direct access to such resources, but
                        rather prefers to leverage existing cyberinfrastructure by providing links
                        to WorldCat (<ref target="http://www.worldcat.org/"
                            >http://www.worldcat.org/</ref>) and the online finding aids of archival
                        institutions to bring researchers closer to the resources they seek. Also,
                        SNAC has a specific audience in mind that is large, but certainly not
                        all-inclusive: anyone interested in historical research. SNAC will serve
                        this audience in a few ways: integrated access to distributed primary and
                        secondary resources about people and organizations; access to historical and
                        biographical descriptions; and access to the social networks of people of
                        historical interest <ptr target="#IATHb"/>. The emphasis on a small number
                        of functions for a targeted audience built atop a unique dataset of
                        unparalleled size strikes an appropriate balance on the Y-axis between
                        boutique projects and general-purpose applications.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Z: Traditional humanities infrastructure ← → Scientific
                        cyberinfrastructure</head>
                    <p>Humanities cyberinfrastructure should be a step forward for research
                        infrastructure otherwise there is no reason to build it. It should offer new
                        solutions to old problems or enable humanists to ask new questions.
                        Therefore, to build such systems there is a need to utilize methods and
                        technologies that go beyond the traditional tools of the humanities.
                        Traditional humanities infrastructure includes intellectual categories such
                        as literary genres and linguistic phenomena, material artifacts like books
                        and maps, buildings such as libraries and book stores, organizations
                        including universities and journals, business models such as subscriptions
                        and memberships, and social practices such as publication and peer review
                            <ptr target="#craneetal2009"/>. In the digital era, however, existing
                        infrastructure must not be used uncritically as the default model for new
                        infrastructure <ptr target="#svensson2011"/>. New infrastructure must go
                        beyond the capabilities of what already exists, otherwise it is merely
                        reinventing the wheel. Humanists may have something to learn from scientists
                        and engineers who have already defined, designed, and deployed much more in
                        the way of cyberinfrastructure, but this would leave the humanities in the
                        position of building on the technologies constructed for other disciplines
                            <ptr target="#borgman2009"/> and this approach should also not be
                        uncritically adopted <ptr target="#svensson2011"/>. A balance must be struck
                        with new technologies that push the boundaries of scholarly activities, yet
                        remain accessible and meet real needs. Humanities scholars will be unlikely
                        to engage with new technology for its own sake <ptr
                            target="#collinsjubb2012"/> and their adoption of any new technologies
                        will be highly influenced by existing research practices developed when
                        using traditional infrastructure <ptr target="#collinsetal2012"/>. </p>
                    <p>SNAC pushes the boundaries of traditional infrastructure through its use of
                        digital data. The creator description data that drives the project is a
                        standards-based, internally consistent dataset with high potential for
                        interoperability with other systems and purposes. Data of this sort (and the
                        tools that can use it) provide a desirable characteristic of
                        cyberinfrastructure: that access to the data should be seamless across
                        repositories <ptr target="#acls2006"/>. Having the potential for data
                        sharing and re-use baked into the initial design of the project is an
                        approach more readily found in scientific research. Also, the rigor with
                        which the data is curated opens the door for innovative approaches to
                        research and the tools that support it. This sort of data-centric approach
                        enables structures and relationships to emerge in the system that would
                        otherwise go unnoticed without a lucky combination of serendipity and
                        painstaking manual research by humans. For example, during the first phase
                        of research and development, the SNAC prototype included an experimental
                        radial graph feature that demonstrated the ability to visualize and explore
                        the relationships between people and organizations represented in the data.
                        See Figure 3. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Radial graph demo for J. Robert Oppenheimer</head>
                        <figDesc>radial graph</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p> The radial graph visualization initially puts the name of an individual at
                        the center of a circle of nodes (other names) to which he or she is related
                        in some way. The example in Figure 3 shows <q>Oppenheimer, J. Robert</q> as
                        the central node with lines extending out to the names of all the other
                        people and organizations he had been associated with in his lifetime. In
                        addition to the lines drawn between the central node in the network and all
                        the other surrounding nodes, relationships between the surrounding nodes in
                        the circle are also indicated with a line. The visualization enables further
                        exploration by responding to mouse clicks on any node in the graph by
                        redrawing the visualization to include the immediate social network of the
                        selected node. For an amusing example, from the graph in Figure 3, clicking
                        on the node for <q>Eliot, Thomas Stearns</q> opens his social network and
                        reveals that Oppenheimer, the father of the atomic bomb, was only two
                        degrees of separation from Groucho Marx<note>Thanks to Daniel V. Pitti
                            (Associate Director, Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                            Humanities) for demonstrating this social network example during a
                            personal conversation.</note> (see Figure 4). </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Extended network for J. Robert Oppenheimer via T. S. Eliot</head>
                        <figDesc>screenshot of extended network</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>While the current phase of SNAC development does not feature the radial
                        graph, the feature is archived at another location (<ref
                            target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/xtf/view?mode=RGraph&amp;docId=oppenheimer-j-robert-1904-1967-cr.xml"
                            >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/xtf/view?mode=RGraph&amp;docId=oppenheimer-j-robert-1904-1967-cr.xml</ref>).
                        It stands as an early experiment in what is possible with SNAC's data,
                        providing a hint of what is to come in future features such as a graph
                        visualization of social-document networks, visualizations of chronologies,
                        and geographic displays of collection locations <ptr target="#IATHf"/>.
                        SNAC’s web prototype and its visualization tools like the radial graph are
                        the public interface to (and a product of) a variety of innovative, yet
                        practical research agendas tackled by the SNAC project. The research never
                        sought to build and explore technologies just for the sake of creating new
                        technologies, nor did it adopt any existing technology without a plan to
                        apply its use to the current needs of SNAC’s target user group. SNAC
                        balances the utility of traditional methods that existing infrastructure
                        enable with the exciting, but unproven potential of new technologies. It
                        does so through the use of advanced technology to accelerate and extend
                        traditional methods in new ways. While researchers may have always wanted to
                        search for every occurrence of an individual’s name in the archives, it has
                        previously been impossible due to a lack of funding and time <ptr
                            target="#collinsjubb2012"/>. However, as some historians have already
                        observed, a year’s worth of work using the current infrastructure combined
                        with a great deal of serendipity and persistence can be replaced by the data
                        in a single SNAC record <ptr target="#IATHb"/>. Through this dramatic
                        reduction in time required to conduct research SNAC demonstrates the
                        benefits of a well-designed cyberinfrastructure tool.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Humanities Infrastructure Stack</head>
                    <p>To build upon existing infrastructure an understanding of its layered history
                        and the relationships between its various components may be beneficial. For
                        example, when trying to introduce a new public utility or a new mode of
                        transportation to a community, thorough knowledge of the existing layers of
                        infrastructure may reward planners with insights such as knowing the gaps in
                        existing service that a new one may fill, discovering ways to save
                        development effort for a new project by integrating with current
                        infrastructure, and understanding usage patterns that may help predict the
                        best places to initially roll out a new service. Look at the streetscape of
                        a typical city and you’ll see the layers, old and new. Sewers, sidewalks,
                        bike lanes, buses, and telephone poles line the streets. The poles are slung
                        with wires that carry electricity, telephone, cable TV, and the information
                        superhighway. The infrastructure that surrounds us is the result of an
                        iterative process of change and evolution over time. Humanities
                        cyberinfrastructure will be no different. </p>
                    <p>SNAC is not possible without the many layers of humanities infrastructure
                        that have come before it. SNAC is built on top of a long-standing
                        infrastructure stack that has served the scholarly community in a reciprocal
                        relationship, where it has been shaped and honed by scholarly use and in
                        turn has also shaped how scholars do their research. Any attempt to build
                        cyberinfrastructure ought to include a process of looking back while moving
                        forward. Which facets of prior infrastructure continue to be important
                        today? How can new technology be used to augment and extend those facets to
                        create a new layer of the infrastructure stack? Of course, some may ask, is
                        it even worth building? Certainly there are some who will have doubts about
                        the value of cyberinfrastructure and this points to the importance of the
                        Z-axis of the evaluation criteria. Cyberinfrastructure will not emerge
                        unless it is designed in a way that balances traditional research methods
                        along with the pursuit of advanced technology. One way to design technology
                        that respects the traditions of the past is to look back at the
                        infrastructure stack upon which the new technology is being built and not
                        neglect the scholarly activity it supports. If one can build a technology
                        that eliminates artificial or unnecessary restrictions on scholarly
                        activity, freeing scholars to do what they really want to do — read, write,
                        analyze, produce knowledge, and distribute it — then that technology will be
                        successful <ptr target="#joula2008"/>. What follows is a discussion of
                        several key pieces of the stack beneath SNAC.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Names</head>
                    <p>Arguably one of the earliest forms of infrastructure supporting information
                        for and about humans is the practice of naming people and their
                        organizations. The abstract appellation is a shorthand way of referencing a
                        whole person in narratives, news, rumors, documents, and data systems like
                        SNAC. Look back at Figures 3 and 4 in this article and notice the primacy of
                        names in SNAC's radial graph. Figure 5 shows a portion of the SNAC
                        prototype's home page where a searchable list of names provides access to
                        data contained in SNAC. The history of naming is long, but is perhaps most
                        significantly related to SNAC in the way personal names reflect the growing
                        complexity of society. For example, the legal and judicial systems of
                        expanding towns in medieval Europe needed to identify individuals clearly in
                        order to attach them to property, to tax and recruit them, and to prosecute
                        them, eventually leading to compulsory naming in the modern era for these
                        reasons <ptr target="#wilson1998"/>. All human organizations now have some
                        bureaucratic interest in names and the official records of many
                        institutions, from churches to governments to corporations and beyond, can
                        end up residing in the next level of the infrastructure stack, the archive. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Names are a primary access point in SNAC</head>
                        <figDesc>screenshot of index of names</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Archives</head>
                    <p>Archives are institutions that collect the unique records of corporations and
                        the papers of individuals and families, the unselfconscious by-products of
                        corporate bodies conducting business and people living their lives <ptr
                            target="#pitti1999"/>. Archives are part of our culture's memory
                        infrastructure, collecting material of legal and historical value. <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#borgman2009">Any record of human
                                experience can be a data source to a humanities scholar</quote>
                            <ptr target="#borgman2009"/>
                        </cit>. Historians list just about every conceivable type of material as
                        important to their work, including primary source material such as reports,
                        wills, deeds, diaries, letters, and so on, all materials to be found in the
                        archives <ptr target="#case1991"/>. What tool can a scholar use to find the
                        needles in the haystacks of archives? That would be the next level of the
                        infrastructure stack.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Finding Aids</head>
                    <p> A finding aid is a printed description of all the records left in an archive
                        with a common creator or source. A finding aid contains a description of the
                        creator, functions performed by the creator, and the records generated by
                        the creator through the performance of those functions <ptr
                            target="#pitti2006"/>. The finding aids provide context to archival
                        collections and detail their contents <ptr target="#dainesnimer2012"/>.
                        Reading through finding aids has been listed by some historians as the most
                        frequently used method for locating primary source material <ptr
                            target="#daltoncharnigo2004"/>. The archival descriptive principle that
                        organizes material based on its provenance (who created the collection)
                        causes personal and organizational names to be a key access point for
                        finding information in archives. Of course, this creator attribute of a
                        finding aid is not the only name. Deeper sections of the finding aid
                        describing the contents of a collection will also contain a wealth of names.
                        Experienced researchers often know the names of key people or organizations
                        connected to their topics of interest and pursue source material linked to
                        those names to provide context <ptr target="#duffjohnson2002"/>. Reading
                        finding aids and collecting names found therein is a method for building up
                        a list of leads to new sources. Finding aids have been an integral part of
                        humanities infrastructure, but for a long time the descriptive practice did
                        not conform to expectations of consistency one might expect from such a
                        system. Archivists initially developed specialized local practices for
                        describing their collections, believing their collections to be too unique
                        to employ standardized practices. However, over time, archivists came to
                        realize that although the contents of their collections are unique, the
                        properties, characteristics, and needs of these collections are not <ptr
                            target="#theimer2011"/>. This realization, combined with the energy
                        behind automating digital forms of description, led to the adoption of the
                        structured standard embodied in the next level of the infrastructure
                        stack.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoded Archival Description</head>
                    <p>The Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Document Type Definition (DTD) is a
                        standard for encoding archival finding aids using Extensible Markup Language
                        (XML) <ptr target="#loc2011a"/>. Development of the data standard began in
                        1993, currently exists in a version released in 2002, and has been adopted
                        by archives to enhance access to their collections by displaying the finding
                        aids online and enabling full text indexing for easier keyword searching
                            <ptr target="#pitti1999"/>. The schema is intended to represent
                        traditional print finding aids in machine-readable form and contains
                        elements to hold the same information one would find in those finding aids,
                        such as the creators, their functions, biographical information, and
                        descriptions of individual records in a creator’s collection <ptr
                            target="#pitti2006"/>. While EAD transformed archival description and
                        brought it into the digital age, the print conventions retained in the
                        presentations of online finding aids has been criticized as inappropriate
                        for the Web and archivists were urged to explore different ways of
                        presenting finding aid content online <ptr target="#dainesnimer2012"/>.
                        Archivists themselves increasingly recognize that the structure of the
                        traditional finding aid, which is embodied in EAD, is inflexible and
                        inefficient when dealing with complex, interrelated records <ptr
                            target="#pitti2004"/>. The next level up in the infrastructure stack,
                        the aforementioned EAC-CPF, provides the key to revolutionizing archival
                        description and online access. However, before I address that, there’s one
                        more part of the stack that bears mentioning. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Authorities</head>
                    <p>Before reaching the top of this mostly archival infrastructure stack a side
                        step to library infrastructure is necessary. An authority record is <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#loc2011b">a tool used by librarians to
                                establish forms of names (for persons, places, meetings, and
                                organizations), titles, and subjects used on bibliographic
                                records</quote>
                            <ptr target="#loc2011b"/>
                        </cit>. Of particular interest to SNAC are the collection of authorized
                        names (such as <q>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</q>) and the list of
                        cross-references that lead to the authorized names (such as <q>Snodgrass,
                            Quintus Curtius, 1835-1910</q> and <q>Clemens, Samuel Langhorne,
                            1835-1910</q>). For reasons that will be described shortly, SNAC relies
                        on authority files to flesh out the biographical descriptions of people and
                        organizations in its data. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoded Archival Content – Corporate bodies, Persons, and Families</head>
                    <p>Encoded Archival Content – Corporate bodies, Persons, and Families (EAC-CPF)
                        is the top of the infrastructure stack that supports SNAC. EAC-CPF Schema is
                        a standard for encoding contextual information about persons, corporate
                        bodies, and families related to archival materials using XML <ptr
                            target="#berlin"/>. EAC-CPF solves a problem inherent in traditional
                        finding aids and EAD, that is the difficulty of representing complex records
                        with a single document. Archival records are often of mixed provenance or
                        the records of the same provenance can be dispersed over numerous archives.
                        This situation causes unnecessary redundancy and duplication of effort <ptr
                            target="#pitti2004"/>. EAC-CPF solves this problem by enabling the
                        separation of creator description from record description. Maintaining a
                        unique, centralized creator record not only reduces redundancy and
                        duplication of effort, but also provides an efficient means of linking
                        creators to the functions and activities carried out by them, to the
                        dispersed records they created or to which they are related, and to other
                        related creators <ptr target="#pitti2006"/>. </p>
                    <p> As I mentioned before, one of SNAC’s primary objectives is the creation of a
                        large (and growing) collection of EAC-CPF records that power its prototype
                        access system. As its original National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH)
                        proposal describes, SNAC takes three steps to generate creator descriptions
                        in EAC-CPF <ptr target="#IATHa"/>. First, preliminary EAC-CPF records are
                        derived from name and biographical components of EAD. The structured nature
                        of the EAD records enables information to be migrated directly into the
                        EAC-CPF format through automated EXtensible Style Sheet Transformations
                        (XSLT). A less simple part of this first step is the extraction of names
                        from semi-structured and free form text fields that require natural language
                        processing techniques. </p>
                    <p> In the second step, duplicate EAC-CPF records that describe the same person,
                        family, or corporate body are automatically matched and merged into a single
                        record. This process presents a challenge for SNAC. It’s not unusual for
                        people and corporate bodies to use different names and leave records behind
                        under those various names. Additionally, the EAD records, while structured,
                        often contain text data created manually by humans. Consequently, names may
                        contain misspellings or the same name may be entered in a variety of ways,
                        such as <q>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910,</q>
                        <q>Twain, Mark,</q>
                        <q>Mark Twain,</q> or <q>M. Twain.</q> For more information on this step and
                        further technical details about the entire SNAC project, see Larson and
                        Janakiraman <ptr target="#larsonjanakiraman2011"/>. </p>
                    <p> The third step involves matching the set of EAC-CPF records against
                        authority records from the Library of Congress Name Authority File (LCNAF)
                        and the Getty Vocabulary Program Union List of Artists’ Names (ULAN). Doing
                        so will enable the project to set the authoritative form of a name as the
                        primary name in the EAC-CPF record as well as incorporating a list of
                        alternative forms. Also, biographical/historical data found in the ULAN
                        files will be added to the data in the EAC-CPF record to form a more
                        complete description of the person, family, or corporate body. </p>
                    <p> As of August 2014, SNAC has derived more than 2.6 million EAC-CPF records by
                        extracting data from 2.2 million WorldCat archival descriptions and nearly
                        300,000 British Library authority records. Future phases of development
                        expect to derive data from nearly 190,000 more descriptions of historical
                        collections from other government and academic archives and libraries <ptr
                            target="#IATH2014"/>. SNAC’s prototype access system and the radial
                        graph visualization tool are the current examples, but more may be
                        developed. Perhaps, in time, such tools will come to be considered as
                        essential to humanities research infrastructure as the earlier layers of the
                        stack that support them.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>This case study has discussed the development of cyberinfrastructure at the
                        level of building tools to enhance research. I used SNAC as an example
                        because it allowed me to illustrate several variables that ought to be
                        considered when designing a research tool for humanities
                        cyberinfrastructure: size and scope of the project, members of the project’s
                        team, and choice of technologies. SNAC aims to be a project of great size
                        focused on a narrow mission — creating a network of archival data. To meet
                        the specific research needs of its anticipated community of users SNAC will
                        leverage the power of its data to provide access to research materials
                        through integration with existing infrastructure. This goal could not be
                        achieved without a diverse group of collaborators, from technology
                        specialists to humanists, each representing the various domains of expertise
                        that contribute to the project. This variety of influence on SNAC’s design
                        contributes to decision-making that weighs the merits of traditional
                        infrastructure and advanced cyberinfrastructure. SNAC adopts and develops
                        technologies that best meet the needs of humanities researchers while
                        pushing the limits of what is possible. One key way designers of SNAC ensure
                        that the needs of current scholars are met is to heed the heritage of the
                        project’s infrastructure stack. The creators of SNAC have understood the
                        infrastructure of the past and present, identified what has served users
                        well and which aspects need improvement, and thought creatively about how to
                        augment existing services and solve current problems. Further examples of
                        new cyberinfrastructure are likely to evolve naturally from the layers of
                        existing infrastructure in this way as opportunities to build new layers are
                        realized in the future, just as the infrastructure layers of the past were
                        once new solutions to old research challenges. Research infrastructure both
                        reflects and inspires humanities thinking and methods. As old obstacles to
                        research crumble through the development of new infrastructure, new methods
                        evolve and generate new challenges to bedevil researchers. The developers of
                        infrastructure respond with technology and ingenuity, creating new services
                        to meet these challenges. The cycle continues to this day, where digital
                        technologies are inspiring new methods of research and new tools are being
                        designed to facilitate, enhance, and accelerate those methods while
                        eventually setting the stage for the next evolution in humanities thinking. </p>
                    <p>While I have discussed mainly tool building, cyberinfrastructure is much more
                        than that. Cyberinfrastructure is the digital manifestation of a research
                        culture. However, even while designing cyberinfrastructure at this grand
                        scale, some of the variables that contribute to the success of a single tool
                        may also contribute to successful shaping of a digital culture. SNAC can
                        serve as an illustrative example in this regard, too. To better serve the
                        entire research community SNAC intends to grow from the size of a research
                        project to a self-sustaining national program. The Institute for Museum and
                        Library Services (IMLS) has funded a project named Building a National
                        Archival Authorities Infrastructure to help meet this goal. A proper mix of
                        collaborators that represent the breadth of the project’s stakeholders is
                        essential to bring this plan to fruition. The IMLS funding will support a
                        meeting of leaders in the archive, library, museum, scholarly, and funding
                        communities to determine the requirements of building a sustainable National
                        Archival Authorities Cooperative (NAAC) <ptr target="#IATHd"/>. This
                        cooperative would go far beyond SNAC in scale, but share the same narrow
                        scope as SNAC. It intends to do a few things very well, but at a national
                        scale: provide integrated access to the records held in government,
                        business, and research archives across the United States as well as access
                        to the social networks of the people whose lives are documented in those
                        records. At this level of cyberinfrastructure building, researching new
                        technology plays less of a role than developing new policy recommendations
                        for the business, governing, and technical requirements for NAAC. However, a
                        great deal of emphasis is placed on the top of SNAC’s infrastructure stack,
                        the EAC-CPF standard <ptr target="#IATHe"/>. Writing about EAC-CPF several
                        years ago, Pitti predicted that this <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#pitti2004">standard for creator
                                description will facilitate building international, national,
                                regional, and institutional biographical and historical databases
                                that can serve as resources</quote>
                            <ptr target="#pitti2004"/>
                        </cit>. To that end, the IMLS funding will also support workshops and
                        scholarships to attend them in which EAC-CPF will be taught to increase
                        understanding and expertise in archival authority control. Broad adoption of
                        this standard by the archival community is a necessary component to building
                        the immense collection of data which tools like those developed in the SNAC
                        project require in order to become a major contribution to
                        cyberinfrastructure. </p>
                    <p>As progress continues with SNAC, NAAC, and other related research efforts, it
                        appears that tools like those discussed in this case study will continue to
                        grow and serve their intended community of scholars. In time, perhaps new
                        projects will emerge to fill gaps in other disciplines. As this happens, we
                        will get closer and closer to the goal set forth by the ACLS <ptr
                            target="#acls2006"/> report on cyberinfrastructure to create an
                        integrated digital representation of the cultural record, connect its
                        disparate parts and make the resulting whole more available to one and all,
                        over the network.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="acls2006" label="ACLS 2006"> American Council of Learned Societies
                    (ACLS), <title rend="italic">Our Cultural Commonwealth: The Final Report of the
                        American Council of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for
                        the Humanities and Social Sciences</title> (2006). <ref
                        target="http://www.acls.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/Programs/Our_Cultural_Commonwealth.pdf"
                        >
                        http://www.acls.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/Programs/Our_Cultural_Commonwealth.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed March 30, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blackwellcrane2009" label="Blackwell and Crane 2009"> Blackwell,
                    Christopher and Gregory Crane. <title rend="quotes">Conclusion:
                        Cyberinfrastructure, the Scaife Digital Library and Classics in a Digital
                        Age.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3 (2009). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000035/000035.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000035/000035.html</ref>. Accessed
                    March 29, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman2009" label="Borgman 2009"> Borgman, Christine L. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital Future is Now: A Call to Action for the
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3 (2009). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/4/000077/000077.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/4/000077/000077.html</ref>.
                    Accessed March 29, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boydellison2008" label="Boyd and Ellison 2008"> Boyd, Danah M. and
                    Nicole B. Ellison. <title rend="quotes">Social Network Sites: Definition,
                        History, and Scholarship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title>, 13
                    (2008): 210-230.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="case1991" label="Case 1991"> Case, Donald Owen. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Collection and Use of Information by Some American Historians: A Study
                        of Motives and Methods.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Library Quarterly</title>, 61 (1991): 61-82.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chuketal2012" label="Chuk et al. 2012"> Chuk, Eric, Rama Hoetzlein,
                    David Kim, and Julia Panko. <title rend="quotes">Creating socially networked
                        knowledge through interdisciplinary collaboration.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title>, 11 (2012):
                    93-108.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="collinsetal2012" label="Collins et al. 2012"> Collins, Ellen, Monica
                    E. Bulger, and Eric T. Meyer. <title rend="quotes">Discipline matters:
                        Technology use in the humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title>, 11 (2012):
                    76-92.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="collinsjubb2012" label="Collins and Jubb 2012"> Collins, Ellen, and
                    Michael Jubb. <title rend="quotes">How do Researchers in the Humanities Use
                        Information Resources?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Liber Quarterly</title>, 21 (2012): 176-187.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="craneetal2009" label="Crane et al. 2009"> Crane, Gregory, Brent
                    Seales, and Melissa Terras. <title rend="quotes">Cyberinfrastructure for
                        Classical Philology.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3 (2009). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000023/000023.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000023/000023.html</ref>. Accessed
                    March 29, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dainesnimer2012" label="Daines and Nimer 2012"> Daines III, J. Gordon,
                    and Cory L. Nimer. <title rend="quotes">Re-Imagining Archival Display: Creating
                        User-Friendly Finding Aids.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Archival Organization</title>, 9 (2012):
                    4-31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daltoncharnigo2004" label="Dalton and Charnigo 2004"> Dalton, Margaret
                    Stieg, and Laurie Charnigo. <title rend="quotes">Historians and Their
                        Information Sources.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">College and Research Libraries</title>, 65 (2004):
                    400-425.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009"> Drucker, Johanna. <title
                        rend="quotes">Blind Spots: Humanists must plan their digital future.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, (3 April
                    2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duffjohnson2002" label="Duff and Johnson 2002"> Duff, Wendy M. and
                    Catherine A. Johnson. <title rend="quotes">Accidentally Found on Purpose:
                        Information-Seeking Behavior of Historians in Archives.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Library Quarterly</title>, 72 (2002): 472-496.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="friedlander2009" label="Friedlander 2009"> Friedlander, Amy. <title
                        rend="quotes">Asking questions and building a research agenda for digital
                        scholarship.</title> In <title rend="italic">Working Together or Apart:
                        Promoting the Next Generation of Digital Scholarship</title>, Washington, DC
                    (2009), pp. 1-15.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huntetal2011" label="Hunt et al. 2011"> Hunt, Leta, Marilyn Lundberg,
                    and Bruce Zuckerman. <title rend="quotes">Getting beyond the common
                        denominator.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 26 (2011):
                    217-231.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHa" label="IATH n.d. a"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">NEH Proposal.</title> SNAC: The Social
                    Networks and Archival Context Project. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/NEH_proposal_narrative.pdf"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/NEH_proposal_narrative.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed April 15, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHb" label="IATH n.d. b"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">Mellon Proposal.</title> SNAC: The
                    Social Networks and Archival Context Project. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/Mellon2011_proposal_narrative.pdf"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/Mellon2011_proposal_narrative.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed April 29, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHc" label="IATH n.d. c"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">Project Team.</title> SNAC: The Social
                    Networks and Archival Context Project. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/staff.html"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/staff.html</ref>. Accessed
                    April 22, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHd" label="IATH n.d. d"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">Meetings.</title> Building a National
                    Archival Authorities Infrastructure. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/NAAC_meetings.html"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/NAAC_meetings.html</ref>.
                    Accessed January 29, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHe" label="IATH n.d. e"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">Introduction.</title> Building a
                    National Archival Authorities Infrastructure. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/NAAC_index.html"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/SNACI/NAAC_index.html</ref>.
                    Accessed February 5, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATHf" label="IATH n.d. f"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
                    Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">Forthcoming Features.</title> SNAC:
                    Social Networks and Archival Context. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/forthcoming_features.html"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/forthcoming_features.html</ref>.
                    Accessed August 13, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IATH2014" label="IATH 2014"> Institute for Advanced Technologies in
                    the Humanities (IATH). <title rend="quotes">News.</title> SNAC: The Social
                    Networks and Archival Context Project. <ref
                        target="http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/news.html"
                        >http://socialarchive.iath.virginia.edu/news.html</ref>. Accessed August 12,
                    2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="joula2008" label="Juola 2008"> Juola, Patrick. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Killer Applications in Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 23 (2008):
                    73-83.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kadushin2012" label="Kadushin 2012"> Kadushin, Charles. <title
                        rend="italic">Understanding Social Networks: Theories, Concepts, and
                        Findings</title>. Oxford University Press, New York (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kolbitschmaurer2006" label="Kolbitsch and Maurer 2006"> Kolbitsch,
                    Josef and Hermann Maurer. <title rend="quotes">The Transformation of the Web:
                        How Emerging Communities Shape the Information we Consume.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Universal Computer Science</title>, 12 (2006):
                    187-213.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="larsonjanakiraman2011" label="Larson and Janakiraman 2011"> Larson,
                    Ray R. and Krishna Janakiraman. <title rend="quotes">Connecting Archival
                        Collections: The Social Networks and Archival Context Project.</title> In
                    Stefan Gradmann, Francesca Borri, Carlo Meghini, and Heiko Schuldt (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Research and Advanced Technology for Digital
                    Libraries</title>, Springer Berlin/Heidelberg (2011), pp. 3-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loc2011a" label="Library of Congress 2011 a"> Library of Congress.
                        <title rend="quotes">Encoded Archival Description: Version 2002 Official
                        Site.</title> The Library of Congress (November 1, 2011). <ref
                        target="http://www.loc.gov/ead/">http://www.loc.gov/ead/</ref>. Accessed May
                    4, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loc2011b" label="Library of Congress 2011 b"> Library of Congress.
                        <title rend="quotes">Frequently Asked Questions.</title> Library of Congress
                    Authorities (October 4, 2011). <ref
                        target="http://authorities.loc.gov/help/auth-faq.htm"
                        >http://authorities.loc.gov/help/auth-faq.htm</ref>. Accessed May 5,
                    2012</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitti1999" label="Pitti 1999"> Pitti, Daniel V. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Encoded Archival Description: An Introduction and Overview.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title>, 5 (1999). <ref
                        target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/november99/11pitti.html"
                        >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/november99/11pitti.html</ref>. Accessed March 29,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitti2004" label="Pitti 2004"> Pitti, Daniel V. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Creator Description: Encoded Archival Context.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cataloging and Classification Quarterly</title>, 38 (2004):
                    201-226.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitti2006" label="Pitti 2006"> Pitti, Daniel V. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Technology and the Transformation of Archival Description.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Archival Organization</title>, 3 (2006):
                    9-22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibmanhanlon2010" label="Schreibman and Hanlon 2010"> Schreibman,
                    Susan and Ann M. Hanlon. <title rend="quotes">Determing Value for Digital
                        Humanities Tools: Report on a Survey of Tool Developers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 4 (2010). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000083/000083.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/2/000083/000083.html</ref>.
                    Accessed March 30, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="seal2012" label="Seal 2012"> Seal, Rob. <title rend="quotes"><title
                            rend="quotes">Social Network for the Dead</title> Set to Expand Due to
                        Mellon Grant.</title>
                    <title rend="quotes">UVA Today,</title> (19 April 2012). <ref
                        target="http://www.virginia.edu/uvatoday/newsRelease.php?id=18148"
                        >http://www.virginia.edu/uvatoday/newsRelease.php?id=18148</ref>. Accessed
                    April 22, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berlin" label="Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, n.d."> Staatsbibliothek zu
                    Berlin. <title rend="quotes">EAC-CPF Homepage</title> Encoded Archival Context
                    Corporate Bodies, Persons, and Families. <ref
                        target="http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/"
                        >http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/</ref>. Accessed May 5, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2011" label="Svensson 2011"> Svensson, Patrik. <title
                        rend="quotes">From Optical Fiber To Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 5 (2011). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html</ref>. Accessed
                    March 30, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="theimer2011" label="Theimer 2011"> Theimer, Kate. <title rend="quotes"
                        >What Is the Meaning of Archives 2.0?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title>, 74 (Spring/Summer
                    2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilson1998" label="Wilson 1998"> Wilson, Stephen. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Means of Naming: A social and cultural history of personal naming in
                        western Europe</title>. UCL Press, London (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="worldcat" label="WorldCat n.d."> WorldCat. <title rend="quotes">What
                        is WorldCat?</title> WorldCat. <ref
                        target="http://www.worldcat.org/whatis/default.jsp"
                        >http://www.worldcat.org/whatis/default.jsp</ref>. Accessed April 27,
                    2012.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
