<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Right Distance: The Researcher’s Key Role between Literary Criticism and Data Visualization in the <title rend="italic">Atlante Calvino</title> Project</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Virginia<dhq:family> Giustetto</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"> https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4145-7229 </idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Université de Genève</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>virginia.giustetto@unige.ch</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Virginia Giustetto is <title rend="italic">Chargée de cours</title> at the Faculty of Humanities of the Université de Genève. During her PhD, she joined the <title rend="italic">Atlante Calvino</title>. 
                            <title rend="italic">Literature and Visualization</title> DH project (<ref target="https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch">https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch</ref>), editing more specifically the itinerary of Space. Her doctoral dissertation, 
                            titled <title rend="italic">Tutto in uno spazio. Luoghi e ambientazioni nell'opera di Italo Calvino</title>, is forthcoming in 2025 with Carocci. 
                            Her research interests include Modern and Contemporary Italian Literature, Geoliterature, and Digital Humanities.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Margherita<dhq:family> Parigini</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0832-2202  </idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Université de Genève</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>margherita.parigini@unige.ch</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Margherita Parigini is <title rend="italic">maître-assistant</title> in Modern and Contemporary Italian Literature at the University of Geneva. During her PhD, she collaborated on the DH project <title rend="italic">Atlante Calvino</title>. 
                            <title rend="italic">Literature and Visualization</title> (<ref target="https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch">https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch</ref>), editing more specifically the itinerary of Doubt, and from which she drew the book <title rend="italic">Calvino nella nebbia</title>. 
                            <title rend="italic">Dubitare, esitare, cancellare</title> (Carocci, 2024). In her research, she is used to combine Data Visualization and literary criticism.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            	
            	<!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000784</idno>

            	
            	<!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date><!-- include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024 --></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
<!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                	
                	<!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp=""/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000784/000784.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
               
                <p>
                    Starting from the multidisciplinary project Atlante Calvino. Literature and Visualization (https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch/?lang=en), which combines literary criticism and data visualization, 
                    the paper reflects on the challenges in fusing the diverse methodologies applied by literary scholars (Unité d’italien, University of Geneva) and a team of designers (DensityDesign Lab, 
                    Polytechnic University of Milan). The paper describes the process that led from a research hypothesis of literary criticism, designed for Italo Calvino’s fictional work, to the creation 
                    of a series of visualizations: in particular, we will focus on the type of text analysis conducted for data collection. Questioning the most common distant reading approach, 
                    the Atlante Calvino project adopted a different kind of distance from the text, closer to the practices of scalable reading. The paper aims to reason about the acquisitions and 
                    limitations that characterize this method, assigning a new role to the researcher in the context of Digital Humanities.
                </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>xx</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
            <head></head>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>Distant reading is one of the boldest ventures that has animated the landscape of literary criticism studies in recent decades. This methodology, inaugurated by <name>Franco Moretti</name> (2000) 
                        
                        <note>In his article <title rend="italic">A Genealogy of Distant Reading</title>, Ted Underwood (2017) argues that Moretti did not actually <quote rend="inline">invent the idea of macroscopic literary inquiry. [...] Quantitative interpretation of literature is a story that 
                            stretches back through book history, sociology, and linguistics to a range of nineteenth-century experiments.</quote></note>
                        
                        and later applied to various problems in literary criticism, has sparked an intense and controversial debate over time (<ptr target="#anderson2008"/>; <ptr target="#herrmann2017"/>; <ptr target="#weitin2017"/>; <ptr target="#da2019"/>; <ptr target="#dobson2021"/>). 
                        Even Moretti himself has raised concerns, acknowledging that this practice often confirms results already acquired through traditional methodologies (<ptr target="#moretti2022"/>). 
                        However, when we consider its merits, the most important one may be that it pushes us to handle literary texts in an entirely new way
                        
                        <note>This statement is especially true when we look at the study group in Digital Humanities, which does not aim to computationally reproduce already tried-and-true practices, such as the philological edition of text. Our translation from Italian.</note>
                        
                        : we are dealing with a type of criticism that seeks a “defamiliarization, where the shift in perspective disrupts automatisms, scrapes away the patina of the obvious, 
                        and does not mechanically recognize phenomena but forces us to see them as if for the first time” (de Cristoforo and Ercolino, 2021, pp. 153-154).
                        
                        <note>3</note>
                    
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>The distant reading approach can be summarized in this way: through a series of computational techniques, a repeated analysis is conducted on a very high number of texts; this analysis leads to a set of information that, 
                        in order to be studied, is represented through visualizations. This description is obviously hasty and superficial, but it allows us to identify the two innovative aspects of this methodology: instead of the text being read by the critic, 
                        it is read by the machine; the critic, as a result, will no longer read the text, but visualizations. 
                        
                        <note>4</note>
                        
                        Our discourse, developed from the project Atlante Calvino, focuses on the visual aspect of the issue and at the same time intends to depart from the automatic dimension of reading.
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>The project Atlante Calvino. Literature and Visualization, funded by the SNSF at the University of Geneva (Switzerland), took place from 2017 to 2021. Directed by Francesca Serra, it aimed to investigate a series of critical issues related to Italo Calvino’s 
                        narrative work through data visualization techniques. There were two main motivations behind Serra’s decision to conceive the project: first, after having extensively worked on Calvino, to whom she had dedicated two monographs (Serra, 1996; Serra, 2006) and several papers, 
                        she noted the risk of fossilizing the image critics had of the author. Calvino, one of Italy’s most important intellectuals of the 20th century, had been accompanied over the years by an increasing bibliography dedicated to him, further expanded by the recent anniversary of his birth. 
                        
                        <note>5</note>
                        
                        However, many of these essays are often characterized by a sense of déjà vu: a reverberation effect that presents established interpretations and ideas without a real drive to question what is already known. Therefore, adopting a Digital Humanities approach to explore the work of such 
                        a well-studied author can be effective in viewing it from a new perspective and renewing the paths of interpretation.       
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>The second reason is that the Atlante Calvino project is an experimental field to develop a different practice of literary criticism combined with data visualization. On the one hand, we tried to prove that visual representations allow some literary issues to be addressed and resolved more effectively 
                        than through the traditional medium of critical writing itself. The other goal of the project was to enhance the qualitative aspects of the research as much as possible. It is well-known that literary studies, after encountering Digital Humanities, have mostly focused on numerical approaches, 
                        prioritizing quantitative aspects over interpretive ones.
                        
                        <note>6</note>
                        
                        With Atlante Calvino, we sought to find a boundary space where both components are in constant dialogue but where “counting” is not necessarily the unique strategy.
                        
                        <note>7</note>
                        
                        The project aimed not only to trace new paths for interpreting Calvino’s work but 
                        also to transform data visualization from a simple tool into a crucial node in the critical process, attempting to achieve the type of synergy increasingly desired in the current landscape of criticism (Hinrichs et al, 2019; Drucker, 2020; Windhager et al, 2019). This is done while avoiding the use of “visual design […] 
                        as a cosmetic retouch of important and complicated issues in an attempt to make them look simpler than they are” (Lupi, 2017).
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Both motivations introduce fundamental methodological differences compared to the type of research usually conducted with a distant reading approach. First, the project is dedicated to a single author and his narrative work, drastically reducing the scale of the analysis. Even 
                       more significant is the way the relationship between computational tools and the researcher is calibrated: in our case, the data collection is not automatically operated by a machine, but it is manually conducted by the scholar, text by text. 
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>To weave literary criticism with data visualization, two research teams participated in the project: a literary team from the University of Geneva, and the DensityDesign Lab from the Polytechnic University of Milan. 
                        
                        <note>8</note>
                        
                        After an intense three-year collaboration, an online platform was created (https://atlantecalvino.unige.ch/), which houses all the visualizations produced. However, the visualizations were not the only result achieved. As previously mentioned, these graphic artifacts were designed as glimpses into Calvino’s work, becoming cornerstones in strictly literary research that resulted in two doctoral theses. 
                        
                        <note>9</note>
                        
                        The process behind both outcomes is the real subject of this article.
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>This essay intends to focus on the type of text analysis conducted, with particular regard to the data collection during the intermediate phase, which led from the literary research question to the visualization.  
                    </p>
                   
                </div>
             <div>
                 <head>2. Objects</head>
                 <p>The literary corpus of Italo Calvino’s work 
                     
                     <note>10</note>
                     
                     seemed to fit particularly well with our research for three reasons. The first is extratextual and concerns the author. As mentioned, Calvino is one of the most well-known and translated 20th-century Italian writers whose influence has long transcended national boundaries, as has the critical interest in his work.
                     
                     <note>11</note>
                     
                     The second reason relates to the work itself: Italo Calvino is an extremely “varied and mutable” (Barenghi, 2007, p. 35) 
                     
                     <note>12</note>
                     
                     writer who, over his roughly forty years of activity, explored and experimented extensively in terms of form as well as content. 
                     
                    <note>13</note> 
                     
                     This heterogeneity, which sometimes leads one to feel as if dealing with not just one but many different authors, significantly influenced our choice. Lastly, a practical reason: the corpus of his works is broad but not unmanageable, homogeneous in terms of publication 
                     (Calvino published almost exclusively with the same publisher during his lifetime),
                     
                     <note>14</note>
                     
                     and well-defined. These characteristics made it particularly suitable for our research.
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>So, how many and what texts are we dealing with? If we choose to count each text as a unit (1 novel = 1 unit, 1 collection of n short stories = n units, 1 short story published in a magazine = 1 unit), we are talking about exactly 218 texts of varying lengths, with an average of 17,881 characters per unit, where the shortest ever makes 
                     986 characters and the longest 458,335 characters.
                     
                     <note>15</note>
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>As with many 20th-century authors, it is not always possible to define the exact type of work being examined. There are certainly novels and collections of short stories, but also cases where such terminology does not fully satisfy classification needs, such as long stories or short novels- terms that have been used interchangeably by critics for works 
                     published between the 1950s and 1960s. The difficulty of categorizing a text arose when, during the earliest phase of the project, we created the metadata of the corpus (title, type, length, year, place of first publication, etc.) (Figure 1). 
                     From this, after assigning each text an identifier (id), we developed a series of guide visualizations of the work.
                     
                     <note>16</note>
                     
                     Circumscribing and visually representing the boundaries of the corpus proved to be extremely important-not only to clarify which works 
                     to include in the textual analyses we were planning but also to gradually familiarize ourselves with the visual language upon which we would base our work.
                     
                     <!-- figure 1 -->
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>Defining the corpus was the starting point of our research, and the endpoint is the Atlante Calvino platform, which hosts a series of interactive visualizations organized into three different thematic “itineraries”: Doubt, considered one of the driving forces behind Calvino’s writing; Space, which allows for the exploration of the work through mapping all its narrative settings; 
                     and Form, which addresses the fundamental issue of plot. The research questions underpinning all subsequent investigations revolve around these three thematic cores, becoming increasingly sophisticated. The three itineraries are autonomous but deeply connected on a conceptual level (Figure 2). 
                     Each of them is composed of three “stages” corresponding to three visualizations: the first offers a concrete and tangible representation of the phenomenon (e.g., the settings of the work); the second seeks to highlight the underlying question (e.g., how do settings change over time?); 
                     the third investigates the abstract issue from which the phenomenon originates (e.g., the relationship with realism).
                     
                     <note>17</note>
                     <!-- figure 2 -->
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>Each visualization in the three itineraries presents the same interface. To illustrate the various possible interactions with the visualization, as well as the sections where the different information is located, we will use the second stage of the Space itinerary as an example, which we will return to later.
                   <!-- figure 3 -->  
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>At the center of Figure 3 appears the visualization, which can be interacted with through a series of simple operations: zooming in, selecting a specific element (which often reveals superficially hidden information, such as text labels), and using filters (e.g., chronological, title, etc.) that reduce the scope of action and highlight certain areas of interest. 
                     Textual sections located on the right-hand side of the window aid the correct reading of the visualization: the Explanation provides concise answers to the questions “What is it?” and “How does it work?” while also suggesting some possible “Reading tips”. The Key fulfills its traditional role of explaining the different symbols present in the visualization.
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>In addition to the three itineraries, the platform includes some informative sections (Team, Project, User guide, Capta, Publications) and the Compass section (see note 14).
                 </p>
             </div>
             
             <div>
                 <head>3. Process</head>
                 <div>
                     <head>3.1 The Space Itinerary as a Case Study</head>
                     <p>We would now like to focus on the process, namely the type of text analysis that allowed us to move from an initial research hypothesis to its realization in a visualization. To illustrate all the steps of this phase as exhaustively as possible, we have selected a case study highlighting a specific stage of the Atlante Calvino, 
                         which is part of the Space itinerary.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Space, primarily dealing with settings, as we will see, is a central theme in Calvino’s work, whose strong visual inclination is reflected in his considerable attention to “space, topology, and […] more generally to the surface of the world” (Belpoliti, 2006, p. XIV). Therefore, the starting point was investigating the ways, variations, and effects of this dimension on his work using Digital Humanities practices. 
                         Among other things, we believed that through the analysis of settings that form the backdrop of each work and their transformation over time, we could better understand certain nodes of Calvino’s complex relationship with realism. We also wanted to build on some insights from the dialogue between literary studies and geography, which began in the early 1990s (Tally, 2013; Peraldo, 2016) 
                         and has pointed to promising critical directions in the last two decades, which seemed to adapt particularly well to a digital approach. Specifically, there were two important references from which we started to frame the discourse: the literary maps worked on by Franco Moretti (1997) in his Atlante del romanzo europeo. 
                         1800-1900, and the digital project A Literary Atlas of Europe: Towards a Geography of Fiction, led by Barbara Piatti at the Zurich Institute of Cartography from 2006 to 2013.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>These are two very different works, created about fifteen years apart. Moretti’s research, completed at the end of the 1990s, is analog and not yet influenced by the concept of distant reading, either methodologically or instrumentally. However, the core thesis he advanced is crucial for our research: the idea that “geography is [...] an active, concrete force that leaves its traces on texts, plots, 
                         and systems of expectations” (Moretti, 1997, p. 5). 
                         
                         <note>18</note>
                         
                         Piatti’s cartographic model is more concerned with data classification, stemming from the question: “How adequately can fictional settings be mapped by means of newly designed tailor-made symbology?”. 
                         
                         <note>19</note>
                        
                        Despite the differences in approach and the approximately fifteen years separating the two studies, our research engages fruitfully with both. Our decision to begin investigating the spatial phenomenon of Calvino’s work by systematically analyzing all the settings 
                        
                        <note>20</note>
                        
                        stems from these two studies. 
                     </p>
                 </div>
                 <div>
                     <head>3.2 The Phases of the Process</head>
                     <p>The process we followed had two main phases: the initial hypothesis and the structuring and collection of data, as illustrated in the diagram (Figure 4).
                         
                         <!-- FIGURE 4 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Before describing these phases in detail, focusing on the unique aspects that characterized our work, it’s important to clarify: in the context of Digital Humanities, once the research question has been defined and initial critical hypotheses have been made, regardless of the
                         method adopted, the analysis will begin with the selection of a certain number of words (or, depending on the technique, some parts of it, like subwords), which will be used as data through a process of translation. This happens because in a text, “the only immediately accessible component is the words composing the 
                         ‘surface level’ of the discourse” (Ciotti, 2023, p. 92), 
                         
                         <note>21</note>
                         
                         and although this observation might seem obvious, it establishes a constraint with which researchers must immediately come to terms. 
                         
                         <note>22</note>
                         
                         For instance, if the analysis involves a stylometric technique, it is easy to see how a specific word might be used as a measurable value. But if the subject being measured is not a frequency but rather a more abstract concept, such as spatiality or doubt, the operations become more complex. On which words should the analysis be based?
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Let’s proceed in order: after deciding that our focus would be on the settings in text, 
                         
                         <note>23</note>
                         
                         it was important first to define clearly and consistently the concept of setting and then, in a second phase, to identify the categories from which to build the data structure.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>The definition of setting was particularly aided by the one proposed by Barbara Piatti’s team: “setting is the location where the action takes place – characters are present” (Reuschel and Hurni, 2011).
                         
                         <note>24</note>
                         
                         Here are three examples from three different Calvino’s texts published in 1947, 1957, and 1983:
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>
                         <!-- text passage -->
                         
                         <note>25</note>
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Although we cannot dwell in detail here on the hermeneutic nuances of this seemingly simple task, we will highlight some unique characteristics that became evident right from the start:
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <item>a. In some cases, the locations were geolocatable (e.g., the Jardin des Plantes in Paris), but in many other cases, they were unspecified locations (e.g., a vineyard) that could not be geolocated on a map.</item>
                            <item>b. Among the specific locations, some were existing places (e.g., Paris), while others were entirely fictional (e.g., Ombrosa).</item>
                            <item>c. In some cases, hierarchical relationships between two places could be identified (e.g., the villa at Ombrosa; the reptile house at the Jardin des Plantes in Paris), while in other cases, no such relationships existed.</item>
                        </list> 
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Considering these multiple possibilities and the logical consequences that would follow (for instance, the fact that cartographic language might not be suitable for fully representing all locations) 
                         was essential in defining the data structure. After consulting with experts from different fields, the data structure took the following form (Figure 5):
                            <!-- figure 5 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>For each word collected, we recorded the name (occurrence), any hierarchical relationships with other places mentioned (affiliation), the position of the word in the text (starts_at, ends_at), whether it was a terrestrial location 
                         
                         <note>26</note>
                         
                         (terrestrial), whether it was geolocatable (geolocation)
                         
                         <note>27</note>
                         
                         ,and whether it was fictional (invented). By cross-referencing these last three characteristics, it was possible to categorize the place (place category)
                         
                         <note>28</note>
                         
                         —a feature we immediately imagined would be central to the visual representation of our map. Finally, all the locations in a single text could be assigned a recurring theme (e.g., travel, war), if present, and any particular details could be marked in a note.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>The data collection phase was crucial in determining the final form of the visualization. Before starting, it was natural to discuss whether to partially or fully automate the data collection process. Several concerns quickly arose. Some were related to the specific nature of the data, others to contractual constraints, 
                         
                         <note>29</note>
                         
                         and still others to the available tools. The latter, in fact, mostly operate in English, resulting in imprecise or even ineffective outcomes when dealing with Italian texts. 
                         However, it was the nature of the data itself that presented the most significant issues. Some software can automatically recognize geographical references in a text, even in Italian, but this is not enough. A tool like GeoDict, 
                         
                         <note>30</note>
                         
                         for instance, can identify geographical references but cannot distinguish between spatial elements within a text (and, consequently, what is a setting and what is not). Moreover, software based on named entity recognition would 
                         not have been able to detect unspecified settings that are not geolocatable (e.g., a vineyard or a house) or automatically recognize a location that the author deliberately disguised with a coded name 
                         (e.g., the city of “***” in the story La speculazione edilizia), even though its real-world reference would have been easily deducible by the reader. These considerations highlighted how unsuitable 
                         automated data collection would have been for the type of analysis we were conducting.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>On the other hand, a fully manual data collection process, while feasible given the size of the corpus, seemed overly time-consuming. Ultimately, a middle-ground solution was found: a non-automated approach supported by a custom-built tool for textual mark-up, 
                         Explorer, which sped up the data collection process.
                         
                         <note>31</note>
                         
                         This solution, dependent on the interpretive choices made by the researcher, offered greater freedom in modeling the data, which, to paraphrase Giorgia Lupi (2017), introduced new ways of thinking and allowed us to better address complex issues through tailored solutions.
                     </p>
                 </div>
                 <div>
                     <head>3.3 Returnin to the Text</head>
                     <p>The data collection phase was essentially a translation operation, where the words of a text were used as computational elements, or data.
                         
                        <note>32</note> 
                         
                         It is worth noting what Valeria Burgio (2021, 59) has said about the term data: “Data does not exist in nature. The name is misleading because no one ‘gives’ data; rather, someone takes it, collects it-not because it grows on trees. Data is the result of an extraction from a reservoir of indistinct possibilities”. Our data, or as Johanna Drucker (2011) would say, our capta, are fundamentally “cultural artifacts contaminated by their historical and material contingencies” (Burgio, 2021, p. 60).
                         
                         <note>33</note>
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>The settings in the three examples mentioned earlier were classified as follows:
                         
                         <!-- figure 6 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Let’s focus on the last example, the reptile house at the Jardin des Plantes in Paris. Figure 7 depicts the visual translation of the data collected:
                         
                         <!-- figure 7 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>If we assume that “how a dataset is collected and the information included -and omitted- directly determines the course of its life” (Lupi, 2017), there are at least two considerations to be made. First, the fact that this and other visualizations produced for the 
                         Atlante Calvino always represent a subjective critical viewpoint, attributable to the person who directed the analysis with their choices. Secondly, in the data collection phase -and subsequently within the visualization- the original literary text seems to disappear. 
                         Some elements remain (e.g., place names), whose characteristics (e.g., place category) and internal relationships are highlighted, but the ability to grasp the text’s overall meaning, appreciating its nuances and intended ambiguities, is inevitably lost. Quite simply, the ability to read it is lost.
                         
                         <note>34</note>
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>This happens, as Martin Mueller aptly pointed out, because the kind of operation being carried out closely resembles the zoom tool we use when navigating Google Earth: “you can zoom in and out of things and discover that different properties of phenomena are revealed by looking at them from different distances” (Mueller, 2012). 
                         Martin Mueller’s idea, which led to the concept of scalable reading 
                         
                         <note>35</note>
                         
                         (English and Underwood, 2016; Herrmann, 2017; Fickers and Clavert, 2021), fits particularly well with our research, as the question underpinning his work is the same that initiated the Atlante Calvino: “how can literary scholars analyze texts, 
                         text segments or text corpora from different points of view, i.e., with quantitative and qualitative methods alike?” (Krautter, 2023, pp. 266-267).
                         
                         <!-- figure 8 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>For example, the visualization of settings 
                         
                         <note>36</note>
                         
                         allows one to visualize the entire literary geography of the writer in one go through a process of reduction (zoom out), which relates only the locations of the corpus, isolated from the rest of the text. On the other hand, by zooming in or selecting specific results, 
                         it is possible to delve deeper into the nature of these data, suggesting correspondences and potential critical directions, and prompting a return to the text to verify what has been discovered, either confirming or challenging already established critical hypotheses. The visualization, as Jérôme David affirms, is only “a ‘moment’ 
                         in the reasoning process” (de Cristofaro and Ercolino, 2021, p. 190)
                         
                         <note>37</note>
                         
                         ; it invites the viewer to return to the literary object through a movement of text-visualization-text, which is not confined to a single direction or a single instance (Figure 8). Although the text seems absent from the visualization, 
                         it remains a constant reference point to which we continually return during the different phases of the process. Moreover, the interactive nature of all the visualizations of the Atlante Calvino, which offer overall views but also suggest focused views on specific sections, 
                         inevitably leads to scalable reading, distancing itself significantly in terms of methodology from an exclusively distant approach.
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>Let’s examine one of the previously cited textual examples: the case of Paris. The French city appears as a setting not only in the story L’ordine degli squamati (1983, part of the collection Palomar) but also in various other texts by the author. After analyzing the specific case of the 1983 story, it might be interesting to simultaneously 
                         identify all instances of Paris in Calvino’s work (Figure 9).
                         
                         <!-- figure 9 -->
                     </p>
                     
                     <p>The overall analysis of this setting,
                         
                         <note>38</note>
                         
                         which appears 12 times between 1954 and 1983, raises a series of intriguing questions. Here are a few examples: Why does the presence of this setting increase starting from the 1970s? Is there a connection between the biographical places of the author -who lived permanently in Paris since 1967- and the literary settings? 
                         Do the selected texts tend to emphasize a realistic dimension or an invented one? How many and what kinds of places are contained within Paris? How is the city described? Do the characters in these stories move around the city, or do they remain essentially motionless? In many cases, to answer these questions, it is necessary to return to individual texts, 
                         or even specific paragraphs, while in others, the overall view itself guides the responses.
                     </p>
                 </div>
             </div>
             <div>
                 <head>4. Critical assessments</head>
                 <p>To consider the overall project, it is certainly helpful to attempt an evaluation of a research endeavor with such a marked experimental character.
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>A strong stance that influenced the project was the decision to avoid a series of established digital methods for textual analysis. In the Atlante Calvino, there is no trace of practices like topic modeling (Blei, 2012) or, more generally, of other techniques related to NLP (Nitsch, 2023). More than a rejection of these approaches, this choice was driven by the desire to 
                     create a genuine synergy between the practices of literary criticism and those of data visualization. And the first major step in this direction was the control over the data.
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>In each of the visualizations of the Atlante Calvino, the data is not selected by a machine but by a person: a scholar who examined the text, hypothesized a data collection structure 
                     compatible with their research question, and then patiently read and sampled the entire selected corpus, identifying page by page the words, phrases, and paragraphs relevant to the critical problem they wanted to investigate. Such an operation brings several limitations:
                     
                     <list type="simple">
                         <item>(a) The first is certainly practical. Manually generating a dataset takes a long time, nullifying one of the main advantages typically associated with Digital Humanities: the ability to conduct research on extremely large corpora in a short time through automation.</item>
                         <item>(b) Secondly, manual data collection can be seen as a disadvantage in terms of the reliability of the critical result: one of the peculiarities of most Digital Humanities studies is that they emphasize not only the conceptual but also the “technical” verifiability of the various stages of the research, thus guaranteeing the reproducibility of the method and- implicitly- the objectivity of the outcome </item>
                     </list>
                     <note>39</note>
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>However, both of these limitations offer positive outcomes. First, the slowdown caused by this careful data selection contributes to ensuring its quality. While a strong hermeneutic stance is not common practice in the Digital Humanities, shaping the dataset entirely based on the researcher’s skills opens the door to a new -and perhaps more mindful- way of using digital tools. Jérôme David argued that one of the most stimulating aspects of the Digital Humanities, 
                     as synthesized by de Cristofaro and Ercolino, is the effort to articulate as rigorously as possible the links in the chain of hermeneutic reasoning: “the fertility of this effort lies [indeed] in the ability to raise new problems upstream of any attempt at empirical verification through algorithms […], thus contributing to enriching the conceptual repertoire of literary studies” (de Cristofaro and Ercolino, 2021, pp. 185-186). 
                     
                     <note>40</note>
                     
                     Based on this interpretation, the Atlante Calvino creates an experimental ground where researchers are pushed to renew their role in the interplay between computational techniques and literary criticism expertise.
                     
                     <note>41</note>
                     
                     The researchers involved did not entrust the machine with the task of analyzing the text but analyzed the text themselves, focusing on the elements needed to create a visualization. By setting up data collection structures designed to answer a specific research question, it became possible to identify new ways of viewing Calvino’s literary work. 
                     
                     <note>42</note>
                     
                     Even the aura of objectivity often associated with results obtained through computational techniques -particularly during the initial phase of the Digital Humanities- is now being questioned within a broader discourse (Burgio, 2022; Bode, 2023), which tends to problematize the positivist approach, partly now outdated (Daston and Galison, 2007; Vidali, 2015). 
                     
                     <note>43</note>
                     
                     There is sometimes a sense that, rather than fully exploiting the potential of new technologies, the researcher wants to avoid their own role, delegating it to the machine. Or, at the very least, they entrust the machine with a greater responsibility than it might be fair to give.
                 </p>
                 <p>Moreover, manual data collection is a way of searching for things in the text that might otherwise go unnoticed. As Johanna Drucker has said, data is always acquired through a conscious selection and is never provided neutrally. This is even more true when dealing with the work of an author so studied that he risks being overshadowed by his critical reception. The Atlante Calvino aimed to set aside value judgments expressed on specific volumes or limited areas of the work, analyzing it as a whole. 
                     The result is an in-depth knowledge of the author’s oeuvre, challenging the adage Moretti postulated when he coined the term distant reading: “Reading ‘more’ is always a good thing but not the solution” (Moretti, 2000). 
                     In our case, it was the only solution. A solution that allowed us to minimize the amount of critical information that influences the reading of the text and determines its position in the literary canon.
                 </p>
                 
             </div>
             <div>
                 <head>5. Conclusion</head>
                 <p>Moretti provocatively reversed the traditional formula of close reading. If we were to describe this critical practice as a movement, we could imagine a person leaning closer to examine an object. Not because that object is not clearly visible, but because we are convinced that beyond appearances, something hidden lies waiting to be brought to light. In his article, Moretti inverted the direction of this movement: no longer approaching 
                     the object but stepping back until it disappears from view. What kind of knowledge could we access if we positioned ourselves so far from the text that we could no longer see it? “Distance, let me repeat, is a condition of knowledge: it allows you to focus on units that are much smaller or much larger than the text: devices, themes, tropes-or genres and systems” (Moretti, 2000).
                 </p>
                 <p>With the Atlante Calvino, we moved closer to the text, making it both the starting point and the destination of the analysis. The visualization is not an outcome in itself but a transitional phase, a critical tool to be handled to discover something new, after which we return to text.
                     
                     <note>44</note>
                     
                     Thus, a series of variable views follow one another: first, the entire corpus is analyzed microscopically (text analysis > database), 
                     then the focus shifts to a macroscopic scale thanks to a “graphic” version of the critical problem (database > visualization); from here, we return to the text, following the visual forms that we consider significant and capable of answering the questions we originally posed (visualization > enhanced analysis).
                 </p>
                 
                 <p>Perhaps what we have attempted to do is find a formula that places us at the right distance: far enough from the text to see something new through the visual trends (Moretti and Sobchuk, 2020), but still close enough to return to it.
                 </p>
             </div>
             <div>
                 <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                 <p>We would first like to emphasize the shared authorship of the article: both of us equally contributed to its conception, writing, and editing; only the figures are elaborated by Margherita Parigini.
                 </p>
                 <p>We would like to thank Francesca Serra, who conceived and directed the Atlante Calvino project, and our colleague Valeria Cavalloro, who edited the itinerary of Form.
                 </p>
                 <p>
                     We also thank the team at DensityDesign Lab: the founder Paolo Ciuccarelli, the scientific director Michele Mauri, the researchers Ángeles Briones, Tommaso Elli, and Beatrice Gobbo.
                 </p>
                 <p>The value of collaboration underpinned the project at every stage, contributing decisively to the final outcome of the research. This experience confirms the spirit of cooperation and constructive exchange that distinguishes the Digital Humanities. 
                 </p>
             </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="anderson2008" label="Anderson 2008">Anderson, C. (2008) <title rend="quotes">The End of Theory: The Data Deluge Makes the Scientific Method Obsolete.</title> WIRED. 23 June 2008. Available at: <ref target="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/pb-theory/">https://www.wired.com/2008/06/pb-theory/</ref>.
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="baranelli2007" label="Baranelli 2007">Baranelli, L. (2007) <title rend="italic">Bibliografia di Italo Calvino</title>. Pisa: Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa.
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="barenghi2007" label="Barenghi 2007">Barenghi, M. (2007) <title rend="italic">Italo Calvino, le linee e i margini</title>. Bologna: Il Mulino. 
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="belpoliti2006" label="Belpoliti 2006">Belpoliti, M. (2006) <title rend="italic">L’occhio di Calvino</title>. Torino: Einaudi.
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="benito_santos_sánchez2020" label="Benito-Santos and Sánchez 2020">Benito-Santos, A. and R.T. Sánchez (2020) <title rend="quotes">A data-driven introduction to authors, readings, and techniques in visualization for the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">IEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>, 40(3), pp. 45-57. 
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="bode2012" label="Bode 2012">Bode, K. (2012) <title rend="italic">Reading by numbers: Recalibrating the literary field</title>. London-New York: Anthem Press.
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="bode2023" label="Bode 2023">Bode, K. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Doing (computational) literary studies</title>, <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title>, 53(3), pp. 531-58. Available at: <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/898320">https://muse.jhu.edu/article/898320</ref>. 
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="burgio2021" label="Burgio 2021">Burgio, V. (2021) <title rend="italic">Rumore visivo. Semiotica e critica dell’infografica. </title>Sesto San Giovanni: Mimesis Edizioni</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="calvino1991" label="Calvino 1991, 1992, 1994">Calvino, I. (1991, 1992, 1994) <title rend="italic">Romanzi e racconti</title>. C. Milanini, M. Barenghi, and B. Falcetto (eds.). Milano: Mondadori. 3 voll.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="ciotti2023" label="ciotti2023">Ciotti, F. (2023) <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities. Metodi, strumenti, saperi</title>. Roma: Carocci.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="correll2019" label="Correll 2019">Correll, M. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Counting, collaborating, and coexisting: Visualization and the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Medium</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://mcorrell.medium.com/counting-collaborating-and-coexisting-visualization-and-the-digital-humanities-1bf157400d8">https://mcorrell.medium.com/counting-collaborating-and-coexisting-visualization-and-the-digital-humanities-1bf157400d8</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="decristofaro_erocolino2021" label="de Cristofaro and Erocolino 2021">de Cristofaro, F. and S. Erocolino (2021) <title rend="italic">Critica sperimentale. Franco Moretti e la letteratura</title>. Roma: Carocci.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="dastongalison2007" label="Daston and Galison 2007">Daston, L. and P. Galison (2007) <title rend="italic">Objectivity</title>. New York: Zone Book.</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="dignaziobhargava2016" label="D'Ignazio and Bhargava 2016">D'Ignazio, C. and R. Bhargava (2016) <title rend="quotes">DataBasic : Design Principles, Tools and Activities for Data Literacy Learners</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal of Community Informatics</title>, 12(3), pp. 83-107. Available at: <ref target="https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/databasic-design-principles-tools-and-activities-for-data-literacy-learners/">https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/databasic-design-principles-tools-and-activities-for-data-literacy-learners/</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="desrosières2010" label="Desrosières 2010">Desrosières, A. (2010) <title rend="italic">La politique des grands nombres. Histoire de la raison statistique</title>. Paris: La Découverte. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3917/dec.desro.2010.01">https://doi.org/10.3917/dec.desro.2010.01</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Humanities approaches to graphical display</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, 5(1). Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2020" label="Drucker 2020">Drucker, J. (2020) <title rend="italic">Visualization and interpretation: Humanistic approaches to display</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="dobson2021" label="Dobson 2021">Dobson, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Interpretable outputs: Criteria for machine learning in the humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, 15(2). Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/2/000555/000555.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/2/000555/000555.html</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="english_underwood2016" label="English and Underwood 2016">English, J.F. and T. Underwood (2016) <title rend="quotes">Shifting scales: Between literature and social science</title>, <title rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</title>, 77(3), pp. 277-295. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/00267929-3570612">https://doi.org/10.1215/00267929-3570612</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="elli2023" label="Elli 2023">Elli, R. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Supporting literary criticism with data visualization: Four design guidelines for facilitating interdisciplinary collaborations</title>, <title rend="italic">Convergências</title>, 16(32), pp. 152-63. 30 November 2023. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.53681/c1514225187514391s.32.215">https://doi.org/10.53681/c1514225187514391s.32.215</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="eve2019" label="Eve 2019">Eve, P.M. (2019) <title rend="italic">Close reading with computers</title>. Stanford: Stanford University Press.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="fabbrilatour1981" label="Fabbri and Latour 1981">Fabbri, P. and B. Latour (1981) <title rend="quotes">La rhétorique de la science. Pouvoir et devoir dans un article de science exacte</title>, <title rend="italic">Actes de la recherche en sciences sociales</title>, 16 (1), pp. 87-114. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.31468/cjsdwr.448">https://doi.org/10.31468/cjsdwr.448</ref>.</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="fickersclavert2021" label="Fickers and Clavert 2021">Fickers, A. and F. Clavert (2021) <title rend="quotes">On pyramids, prisms, and scalable reading</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital History</title>, 1(1). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/JDH-2021-1008?locatt=label:JDHFULL">https://doi.org/10.1515/JDH-2021-1008?locatt=label:JDHFULL</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="ketzan2021" label="Ketzan 2021">Ketzan, E. (2021) <title rend="italic">Thomas Pynchon and the digital humanities. Computational approaches to style</title>. New York: Bloomsbury.</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="krautter2023" label="Krautter 2023">Krautter, B. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The Scales of (Computational) Literary studies: Martin Mueller’s concept of scalable reading in theory and practice</title>, <title rend="italic">Zoomland. Exploring Scale in Digital History and Humanities</title>. F. Armaselu and A Fickers (eds). Berlin–Boston: De Gruyter Oldenbourg, pp. 261-86. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783111317779-011">https://doi.org/10.1515/9783111317779-011</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="giusjacke2022" label="Gius and Jacke 2022">Gious, E. and J. Jacke (2022) <title rend="quotes">Are computational literary studies structuralist?</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 7(4). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.46662">https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.46662</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="herrmann2017" label="Herrmann 2017">Herrmann, J.B. (2017) <title rend="quotes">In a test bed with Kafka. Introducing a mixed-method approach to digital stylistics</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, 11(4). Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/4/000341/000341.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/4/000341/000341.html</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="hinrichs_etal2019" label="Henrichs et al 2019">Henrichs, U. S. Forlini, and B. Moynihan (2019) <title rend="quotes">In defense of sandcastles: Research thinking through visualization in digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34(1), pp. 180-199. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="lupi2017" label="Lupi 2017">Lupi, G. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Data humanism: The revolutionary future of data visualization</title>, <title rend="italic">PrintMag</title>. Available at <ref target="https://www.printmag.com/article/data-humanism-future-of-data-visualization/">https://www.printmag.com/article/data-humanism-future-of-data-visualization/</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="manchia2020" label="Manchia 2020">Manchia, V. (2020) <title rend="italic">Il discorso dei dati. Note semiotiche sulla visualizzazione delle informazioni</title>. Milano: FrancoAngeli.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="moretti1997" label="Moretti 1997">Moretti, F. (1997) <title rend="italic">Atlante del romanzo europeo. 1800-1900</title>. Torino: Einaudi.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2000" label="Moretti 2000">Moretti, F. (2000) <title rend="quotes">Conjectures on world literature</title>, <title rend="italic">”, New Left Review</title>, 1.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, F. (2013) <title rend="italic">Distant Reading</title>. London-New York: Verso.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="morettisobchuk2020" label="Moretti and Sobchuk 2020">Moretti, F. and O. Sobchuk (2020) <title rend="quotes">Vedere e non vedere. Sulla visualizzazione dei dati nelle discipline umanistiche</title>, <title rend="italic">Ácoma</title>, 18, pp. 125-51.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2022" label="Moretti 2022">Moretti, F. (2022) <title rend="italic">Falso movimento. La svolta quantitativa nello studio della letteratura</title>. Milano: nottetempo.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="mueller2012" label="Mueller 2012">Mueller, M. (2012) <title rend="italic">Scalable reading</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://sites.northwestern.edu/scalablereading/scalable-reading/">https://sites.northwestern.edu/scalablereading/scalable-reading/</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="parigini2024" label="Parigini 2024">Parigini, M. (2024) <title rend="italic">Calvino nella nebbia. Dubitare, esitare, cancellare</title>. Roma: Carocci.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="peraldo2016" label="Peraldo 2016">Peraldo, E. (2016) <title rend="italic">), Literature and geography. The writing of space throughout history</title>. Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="pianzola_etal2020" label="Pianzola et al 2020">Pianzola, F., S. Rebora, and G. Lauer (2020) <title rend="quotes">Wattpad as a resource for literary studies. Quantitative and qualitative examples of the importance of digital social reading and readers’ comments in the margins</title>, <title rend="italic">PLoS ONE</title>, 15(1). Available at <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0226708">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0226708</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="piatti2008" label="Piatti 2008">Piatti, B. (2008) <title rend="italic">Die Geographie der Literatur. Schauplätze, Handlungsräume, Raumphantasien</title>. Göttingen: Wallstein.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="piper2020" label="Piper 2020">Piper, A. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Do we know what we are doing?</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 5(1). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.11826">https://doi.org/10.22148/001c.11826</ref>.</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="reuschelhurni2011" label="Reuschel and Hurni 2011">Reuschel, A. and L. Hurni (2011) <title rend="quotes">Mapping literature: Visualization of spatial uncertainty in fiction</title>, <title rend="italic">The Cartographic Journal</title>, 48(4), pp. 293-308.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="ries_etal2024" label="Reis et al 2024">Reis, T, K. van Dalen-Oskam, and F. Offert (2024) <title rend="quotes">Reproducibility and explainability in digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Int J Digit Humanities</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-023-00083-w">https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-023-00083-w</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="rosen2011" label="Rosen 2011">Rosen, J. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Combining close and distant, or, the unity of genre analysis: A response to Matthew Wilkens’s <title rend="italic">Contemporary fiction by the numbers</title></title>, <title rend="italic"></title>Post45. Available at: <ref target="https://post45.org/2011/12/combining-close-and-distant-or-the-utility-of-genre-analysis-a-response-to-matthew-wilkenss-contemporary-fiction-by-the-numbers/">https://post45.org/2011/12/combining-close-and-distant-or-the-utility-of-genre-analysis-a-response-to-matthew-wilkenss-contemporary-fiction-by-the-numbers/</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="rubini2023" label="Rubini 2023">Rubini, F. (2023) <title rend="italic">Italo Calvino nel mondo. Opere, lingue, paesi (1955-2020</title>. Roma: Carocci.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="serra1996" label="Serra 1996">Serra, F. (1996) <title rend="italic">Calvino e il pulviscolo del signor Palomar</title>. Firenze: Le lettere.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="serra2006" label="Serra 2006">Serra, F. (2006) <title rend="italic">Calvino</title>. Roma: Salerno.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="tally2013" label="Tally 2013">Tally, R.T. (2013) <title rend="italic">Spatiality</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="vidalineresini2015" label="Vidali and Neresini 2015">Vidali, P. and F. Neresini (2015) <title rend="italic">Il valore dell’incertezza</title>. Milano: Mimesis.</bibl>
           
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2017" label="Underwood 2017">Underwood, T. (2017) <title rend="quotes">A Genealogy of Distant Reading</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, 11(2). Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000317/000317.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000317/000317.html</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="weitin2017" label="Weitin 2017">Weitin, T. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Scalable reading</title>, <title rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und Linguistik</title>, 47(1), pp. 1-6.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="wilkens2011" label="Wilkins 2011">Wilkins, M. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Contemporary fiction by the numbers</title>, <title rend="italic">Post45</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://post45.org/2011/03/contemporary-fiction-by-the-numbers/">https://post45.org/2011/03/contemporary-fiction-by-the-numbers/</ref>.</bibl>
            
                <bibl xml:id="windhager_etal2019" label="Windhager et al 2019">Winghager, F. et al (2019) <title rend="quotes">Visualization of cultural heritage collection data: State of the art and future challenges</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, 25(6), pp. 2311-2330. Available at: <ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8352050">https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8352050</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
           
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
