<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
      xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
      xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
      <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                        <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Phenomenon of Interwar City
                              Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional
                              Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns
                              of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title>
                        <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                        <dhq:authorInfo>
                              <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                              <dhq:author_name>Eva <dhq:family>Hielscher</dhq:family>
                              </dhq:author_name>
                              <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
                              <email>eva.hielscher@gmx.de</email>
                              <dhq:bio>
                                    <p>Eva Hielscher is a film scholar, curator and moving image
                                          archivist. She worked for the Netherlands Institute for
                                          Sound and Vision, Eye Filmmuseum, Fotomuseum Winterthur,
                                          the University of Zurich and
                                          Friedrich-Wilhelm-Murnau-Foundation. She completed her PhD
                                          dissertation on experimental city films of the 1920s and
                                          1930s at Ghent University and is co-editor of <title
                                                rend="italic">The City Symphony Phenomenon</title>
                                          (Routledge, 2018) and <title rend="italic">Color
                                                Mania</title> (Lars Müller, 2019). Most recently,
                                          she has been working on an exhibition about the film and
                                          cinema history of Hamburg at the Altonaer Museum.</p>
                              </dhq:bio>
                        </dhq:authorInfo>
                  </titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                        <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000495</idno>
                        <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                        <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                        <date when="2020-12-20">20 December 2020</date>
                        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                              <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"
                              />
                        </availability>
                  </publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                        <p>This is the source</p>
                  </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                  <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                              <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                                          target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                                          >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                              </bibl>
                        </taxonomy>
                        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                              <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                        </taxonomy>
                  </classDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
            <profileDesc>
                  <langUsage>
                        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                        <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
                  </langUsage>
                  <textClass>
                        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                              <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                              <list type="simple">
                                    <item/>
                              </list>
                        </keywords>
                        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                              <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                              <list type="simple">
                                    <item/>
                              </list>
                        </keywords>
                  </textClass>
            </profileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                  <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
                  <change when="2020-09-11" who="jmurel">Created filed</change>
            </revisionDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
            <front>
                  <dhq:abstract>
                        <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
                        <p>The 1920s and 1930s saw the rise of the city symphony, a film phenomenon
                              of experimental-documentary city films that took the modern metropolis
                              as their protagonist and presented it in its multiple facets and
                              kaleidoscopic nature. While Ruttmann’s <title rend="italic"
                                    >Berlin</title>. <title rend="italic">Die Sinfonie der
                                    Grosstadt</title> (1927) and Vertov’s <title rend="italic"
                                    >Chelovek s kinoapparatom</title> (1929) gained canonical status
                              and exert a considerable influence on filmmaking to this very day, the
                              city symphony has remained a somewhat downplayed and neglected
                              phenomenon in film history. Indeed, besides the handful of well-known
                              titles, there have been more than eighty films made around the globe,
                              many of which fell into oblivion and have received little or no
                              scholarly attention at all. Moreover, even the canonical examples have
                              never systematically and structurally been analyzed in detail in a
                              comparative way. The result is the lack of a sophisticated and clear
                              definition of the city symphony, based on both the canonical films and
                              the greater city symphony corpus. My research sets in at this point,
                              addressing the conspicuous absence of an analysis of city symphony
                              characteristics. It does so by making use of a combined methodology of
                              traditional film analysis methods and digital tools. This article
                              reflects on the methodology applied and tools chosen and put into
                              practice to study and analyze the visual material of city symphonies,
                              which with their highly complex structure, dense imagery, and themes
                              as well as their experimental techniques and striking editing
                              patterns, are a perfect fit for a computational film analysis.
                              Particularly, the digital film/video annotation software ELAN, the
                              Cinemetrics method, a bar chart representation of shot lengths, and
                              the grid visualizations of multiple film frames created with ImageJ
                              play a role in this case study, which also broaches the aspect and
                              benefits of manual digital analysis.</p>
                  </dhq:abstract>
                  <dhq:teaser>
                        <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                        <p>Examines the the methodology and use of digital tooles such as ELAN,
                              Cinemetrics, and ImageJ in studying 1920/30s city symphony films</p>
                  </dhq:teaser>
            </front>
            <body>
                  <div>
                        <head>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History</head>
                        <p>This article is based on my PhD dissertation <title rend="italic"
                                    >Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and
                                    Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films</title>
                              (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for
                              the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be
                              considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods
                              chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies,
                              making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.
                              Particularly, the digital film/video annotation software ELAN, the
                              Cinemetrics method, a bar chart representation of shot lengths, and
                              the grid visualizations of multiple film frames created as image
                              montages with ImageJ play a role in this case study.</p>
                        <p>City symphonies are experimental-documentary city films of the 1920s and
                              1930s that take the modern metropolis as their protagonist and present
                              it in its multiple facets and kaleidoscopic nature. Often described as
                              cross-section or montage films (e.g. <ref target="#kracauer1947"
                                    >Kracauer, 1947</ref>; <ref target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann,
                                    1997</ref>; <ref target="#koeck2010">Koeck and Roberts,
                                    2010</ref>), they combine a great number of visual urban motifs
                              and themes with a highly complex editing structure. The most famous
                              examples are Walther Ruttmann’s <title rend="italic">Berlin. Die
                                    Sinfonie der Grosstadt</title> (<title rend="italic">Berlin,
                                    Symphony of a Great City</title>, 1927) and Dziga Vertov’s
                                    <title rend="italic">Chelovek s kinoapparatom</title> (<title
                                    rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, 1929). To this
                              day, these films exert a considerable influence on filmmaking and the
                              cinematic language in general. Recent city films such as <title
                                    rend="italic">London Symphony</title> (Alex Barrett, 2017),
                                    <title rend="italic">Symphony of Now</title> (Johannes Schaff,
                              2018), or Mark Cousins’s <title rend="italic">I am Belfast</title>
                              (2015) and <title rend="italic">Stockholm My Love</title> (2017) are
                              just the most obvious indications for this impact and popularity.</p>
                        <p>However, despite the ongoing (or reviving) influence on the production of
                              urban films and the canonical status of Ruttmann and Vertov’s films,
                              the city symphony has remained a somewhat downplayed and neglected
                              phenomenon in film history. While, on the one hand, in fact, it
                                    <emph>is</emph> considered as a crucial part of canonical film
                              history today and as a basis for the fast-growing scholarship on city
                              films in general (see e.g. <ref target="#bordwell2019">Bordwell and
                                    Thompson, 2019</ref>; <ref target="#nowell-smith1997"
                                    >Nowell-Smith, 1997</ref>; <ref target="#koeck2010">Koeck and
                                    Roberts, 2010</ref>; <ref target="#mazierska2003">Mazierska and
                                    Rascaroli, 2003</ref>), on the other hand, it has never really
                              been more than <quote rend="inline">a colorful footnote to film
                                    history</quote>
                              <ptr target="#kinik2008" loc="16"/>. Indeed, besides the handful of
                              well-known titles, which include also <title rend="italic"
                                    >Manhatta</title> (Paul Strand and Charles Sheeler, 1921) and
                                    <title rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> (<title
                                    rend="italic">Nothing But Time</title>, Alberto Cavalcanti,
                              1926), there have been more than eighty films made around the globe in
                              the interwar period.<note>For a comprehensive survey of interwar city
                                    symphony films, see <ref target="#jacobs2018">Jacobs, Kinik and
                                          Hielscher (2018)</ref>. In fact, apart from <ref
                                          target="#dahne2013">Dähne (2013)</ref>, this edited volume
                                    can be considered as the first book-length publication and
                                    overview on the topic.</note> Many of these films fell into
                              oblivion and have received little or no scholarly attention at all.
                              Hence, the city symphony phenomenon was much more complex, widespread
                              and diverse than generally assumed and acknowledged in film
                              historiography. Moreover, even the canonical examples have never
                              systematically and structurally been analyzed in detail in a
                              comparative way. While there have been studies on individual titles,
                              publications putting the city symphony in context of the broader field
                              of the city film, and a few attempts mentioning and discussing a group
                              of films together and highlighting <emph>some</emph> features (rough
                              descriptions and short characterizations), a comprehensive analysis
                              concerning shared visual and structural qualities and the central
                              characteristics of the city symphony has never been made.<note>This
                                    conclusion, though, should not deny the importance of key texts
                                    such as <ref target="#dahne2013">Dähne (2013)</ref> and <ref
                                          target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann (1997)</ref>, who made a
                                    start in changing this situation. This is also true for <ref
                                          target="#bollerey2014">Bollerey and Föhl
                                    (2014)</ref>.</note> The result is the lack of a sophisticated
                              and clear definition of the city symphony, based on both the canonical
                              films and the greater city symphony corpus, that is still missing
                              after decades of film studies. This blind spot is striking since it
                              does not concern obscure films from <term>the edge</term> of film
                              history, but a vast international phenomenon and films that were
                              highly celebrated at their time and – once more – whose popularity and
                              influence are recognizable to this very day.</p>
                        <p>What constitutes the city symphony looking at shared elements of the
                              canon films <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                    >Man with a Movie Camera</title>, <title rend="italic">Rien que
                                    les Heures</title> and <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title> as
                              well as the bigger corpus? What are the visual motifs, formal and
                              structural features of the city symphony? My research sets in at this
                              point, addressing the conspicuous absence of an analysis of city
                              symphony characteristics, as it delves deeper into the phenomenon by
                              examining the films themselves.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                        <head>A Perfect Fit: City Symphonies and Computational Analysis
                              Methods</head>
                        <p>With their highly complex structure, dense imagery and themes as well as
                              their experimental techniques and striking editing patterns, city
                              symphonies are a perfect fit for a computational film analysis, which
                              in segmentations and annotations allows to structurally, precisely and
                              in detail identify individual elements (such as motifs), break down
                              the complexity of these films into separate component parts, and makes
                              it possible to see how different aspects are linked to each other.
                              Moreover, city symphonies do not only share the fractured nature and
                              overwhelming, chaotic impressions with the modern city<note>They
                                    create these impressions by cinematic means.</note> – their very
                              subject matter – they also relate to the database logic of the
                              computer. According to <ref target="#manovich2001">Manovich
                                    (2001)</ref>, the database as a cultural form introduced the
                                    <quote rend="inline">correlate</quote> to the linearity and
                              cause-and-effect trajectory of the logic of the narrative and a new
                              way of structuring our experiences, presenting the world as a list of
                              items and refusing to order this list. Every item possesses the same
                              significance as any other. In addition, Manovich explicitly describes
                              Man with a Movie Camera as <quote rend="inline">perhaps the most
                                    important example of a database imagination in modern media
                                    art,</quote> which anticipated the database logic of digital
                              media in presenting an almost <quote rend="inline">linear printout
                                    [...] of a database</quote> and <quote rend="inline">a catalog
                                    of subjects that one could expect to find in a city of the
                                    1920s,</quote> supplemented with <quote rend="inline">the most
                                    amazing catalog of film techniques.</quote>
                              <ptr target="#manovich2001" loc="241"/><note><ref
                                          target="#manovich2013">Manovich (2013)</ref> also did
                                    pioneering work in visualizing Vertov’s films by digital means,
                                    as did <ref target="#heftberger2016">Heftberger (2016)</ref> and
                                    the project <title rend="quotes">Digital Formalism</title>. In
                                    fact, my methodology builds on both Manovich and Heftberger’s
                                    research. Another relevant study, to which I will return later,
                                    is <ref target="#olesen2017">Olesen (2017)</ref>.</note>
                              Similarly (and following Manovich’s ideas), Cowan integrates
                              Ruttmann’s <title rend="italic">Berlin</title> and the city symphony
                              form in general in the same tradition of the database logic as it
                              emphasizes <quote rend="inline">paradigmatic over syntagmatic
                                    relations, presenting the world as an inventory of possible
                                    choices rather than a causal chain of narrative events</quote>
                              <ptr target="#cowan2014" loc="60"/>. Moreover, apart from their form
                              underlining and embracing the database logic,<note>This happens, among
                                    others, through cross-sectional editing and thematic clustering.
                                    I will come back to this.</note> both <title rend="italic">Man
                                    with a Movie Camera</title> and Berlin were based on actual
                              databases documenting city life. Vertov, as we can see in his film,
                              arranged his film reels on shelves according to keywords, such as
                                    <q>city traffic,</q>
                              <q>factory,</q>
                              <q>machines,</q> and <q>market,</q> while Ruttmann used a card
                              catalogue system for organizing his footage (see Figure 1 and Figure
                              2). In this regard, a computational study of city symphonies also
                              comprises a self-reflexive moment as it shares its database logic with
                              its very subject of research and aims to build a catalogue or database
                              of city symphony features itself by looking at individual component
                              parts of the films as equal items.</p>
                        <figure>
                              <head>Vertov's film reels archive in <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                          Movie Camera</title></head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2001.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                              <head>Example of Ruttmann's <q>Kartothek</q> used for <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title>, published in <title
                                          rend="italic">Film-Kurier</title> (1926, September
                                    11)</head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2002.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Finally, city symphonies are a perfect case study for exploring the
                              possibilities and applications of computational methods for film
                              analysis as they allow for a variety of research questions, including
                              the issue of film style (editing patterns, experimental techniques
                              etc.), questions of content (motifs, themes), and specific aspects
                              concerning the representation of people and the city.</p>
                        <figure>
                              <head>Analysis scheme for the city symphonies research</head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2003.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <div>
                              <head>Film Analysis Step 1: ELAN</head>
                              <p>For the study of visual motifs and structural patterns of interwar
                                    city symphonies, I made use of the digital video annotation
                                    software ELAN.<note>I made use of ELAN 4.9.4. for Mac OS X. For
                                          the software and additional information see <ref
                                                target="https://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/elan/"
                                                >https://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/elan/</ref>
                                          (last consulted on November 29th 2018).</note> More
                                    precisely, ELAN formed the center and very fundament of the
                                    bottom-up analysis, based on which further analysis steps
                                    followed in terms of data evaluation and visualizations (see
                                    Figure 3).</p>
                              <p>Created by the Language Archive of the Max Planck Institute for
                                    Psycholinguistics in the Netherlands, ELAN was originally
                                    developed for a community of linguists and communication
                                    scholars. Nevertheless, this free and open-source tool can also
                                    be used in film studies and for visual and structural analysis,
                                    as it belongs to a group of professional video annotation
                                    programs that support manual annotation tasks, based on a tiered
                                    or layered timeline approach to segmentation and annotation. Put
                                    differently, a media stream can be divided into multiple
                                    segments grouped in categories. ELAN supports this via
                                    horizontal rows (or tiers) organized vertically under each
                                    other. Each tier corresponds to an annotation type or category
                                    the user can define herself according to specific needs and
                                    research questions. Within the individual tiers, segments can be
                                    defined and annotated, which appear in a horizontal, time-based
                                    distribution on the particular tier (see Figure 4).<note>In
                                          addition, it is possible to mark and define hierarchical
                                          relationships and dependencies between tiers and
                                          annotations, a feature I have not made use of in my study.
                                          In fact, this article discusses the way I used ELAN for my
                                          research endeavor, whereas there are more functionalities,
                                          including also the possibility to generate different
                                          queries or retrieve more complex annotation statistics.
                                          For a more general discussion of ELAN, see <ref
                                                target="#melgar2017">Melgar et al.
                                          (2017)</ref>.</note>
                              </p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>ELAN interface with tiers and annotations (example <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title>)</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2004.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>As single stand-alone platform, ELAN facilitates the analysis of
                                    visual material by providing the digital video file (the film),
                                    the timeline, segmentation, and annotations in one and the same
                                    platform, thereby directly linking these elements to each other
                                    so that jumping in the timeline (respectively a tier) brings one
                                    to the corresponding fragment and vice versa. What you see is
                                    directly where and what you segment and annotate. Moreover, it
                                    provides a visualization of the film, its timeline, and the
                                    segments and annotations, thus making visible in the same
                                    platform the film picture and a visualization of its
                                    analysis.</p>
                              <p>There are other digital video annotation tools, including Anvil,
                                    Advene, and Lignes de temps, which follow a comparable approach
                                    as ELAN and allow for similar analysis operations and
                                          options.<note>For the individual tools, see <ref
                                                target="http://www.anvil-software.org/"
                                                >http://www.anvil-software.org/</ref>, <ref
                                                target="https://www.advene.org/"
                                                >https://www.advene.org/</ref>, and <ref
                                                target="https://www.iri.centrepompidou.fr/outils/lignes-de-temps/"
                                                >https://www.iri.centrepompidou.fr/outils/lignes-de-temps/</ref>
                                          (last consulted on November 29th 2018). For a further
                                          elaboration of ELAN and other digital video annotation
                                          tools for film analysis, see <ref target="#melgar2017"
                                                >Melgar et al. (2017)</ref>.</note> However, a brief
                                    exercise with these four software programs demonstrated that
                                    ELAN was the most convenient and most suitable for my research
                                    endeavor. This concerned the media player with its playback rate
                                    possibilities, its media control panel, and viewing options as
                                    well as the handling and viewing possibilities of the timeline,
                                    tiers, and annotation sections. More precisely, ELAN facilitates
                                    to speed up the playback rate of the video up to 200% and slow
                                    it down to 10%. Moreover, the media control panel supports to
                                    jump ahead or back in the video (and the timeline) from one
                                    second down to one millisecond,<note>This depends on the zoom
                                          factor of the timeline viewer. When the zoom factor is at
                                          its maximum (1000), the control buttons, which enable to
                                          go to the next or the previous pixel, will make the video
                                          jump ahead or back one millisecond. Of course, jumping
                                          from frame to frame would be more accurate, which
                                          corresponds to jumping ahead or back 41.67 milliseconds
                                          (in case of a framerate of 24 frames per second).</note>
                                    while the video image can also be enlarged and presented in a
                                    separate window, unlocked from the control panel and annotation
                                    sections. In addition, the tiers can be zoomed in and out, which
                                    makes also the segmentation and annotation of extremely small or
                                    short segments in a detailed and precise way possible. Indeed,
                                    ELAN was also the most convenient of the four tested tools in
                                    the manner how it facilitates the creation of segments and the
                                    adding of annotations and comments in a very detailed way. As
                                    the focus of the analysis in my case lay both on the visual
                                    content and structural patterns of city symphonies, the latter
                                    for which montage plays a key role, a shot-based segmentation
                                    and annotation was the desired goal. In this regard, with its
                                    slow playback options of the video and zoom-in display of the
                                    timeline and tiers, ELAN allowed to identify and mark also
                                    extremely short takes of only a few (or even a single) frame(‑s)
                                    and analyze sections of extremely fast editing. In fact, city
                                    symphonies are often marked by such a fast and rhythmic editing,
                                    for which <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>’s opening sequence
                                    with a train approaching the city and <title rend="italic">Man
                                          with a Movie Camera</title>’s cross-cutting of telephone
                                    operators and a factory worker putting cigarettes into boxes are
                                    emblematic examples (see Figure 5 and Figure 6). ELAN’s option
                                    to set a shot change on the timeline linked to the picture
                                    (while the film is playing or pausing) in a very detailed and
                                    controlled way made it possible to create a shot-based
                                    segmentation also of these more challenging parts of city
                                    symphonies that one can go back to and replay at every point on
                                    the timeline as often as necessary.<note>This is also an
                                          advantage of ELAN’s computer-based analysis in contrast to
                                          an analogue film analysis. While an analysis of extremely
                                          fast editing is not impossible in an analogue way when
                                          working with the film material itself on a montage bench,
                                          or by using a VCR or DVD player (see <ref
                                                target="#kolaja1965">Kolaja and Foster, 1965</ref>),
                                          ELAN facilitates such an analysis in a feasible and
                                          time-saving way. This, of course, could be made even more
                                          time-efficient when shot changes would be detected
                                          automatically. In fact, some of the tools, including
                                          Linges de temps, provide such an automatic or
                                          semi-automatic segmentation. However, according to my
                                          knowledge, there is no satisfactory tool including a
                                          reliable and error-free automatic shot boundary detection
                                          at this moment. Lignes de temps, for example, fails when
                                          it comes to extremely short segments, as is often the case
                                          in experimental films. Moreover, there is the general
                                          issue of fades, since the software cannot detect these
                                          soft changes. In addition, there is a crucial benefit of
                                          manually segmenting, to which I will come later in more
                                          detail.</note>
                              </p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>ELAN screen shot of <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>'s
                                          opening train-ride sequence</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2005.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>ELAN screen shot of <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                                Camera</title>'s
                                          telephone-operators-and-cigarette-boxes sequence (reel
                                          4)</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2006.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>Moreover, its flexibility of defining multiple tiers according to
                                    one’s own research purposes, the option to use the same
                                    (self-defined) template of tiers as a blueprint for various
                                    films, the possibility of creating and using predefined
                                    vocabularies for individual tiers,<note> I used the option of
                                          predefined vocabularies especially for filmic techniques
                                          and shot distances.</note> and the combination of these
                                    aspects were advantages of ELAN. Another benefit is the tool’s
                                    search function, which allows to easily find a specific fragment
                                    – without scrolling, clicking, or reeling through the film – and
                                    get a list of all annotations, shots or segments including a
                                    particular search word. In this way, if a certain consistency is
                                    applied in the annotation process, one can, for instance, find
                                    all the shots containing a traffic policeman in <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title> in a single search request
                                    (see Figure 7). Finally, ELAN’s complete and detailed user
                                    manual, its support of various digital video file formats and
                                    codecs, its export options, and its computer system requirements
                                    as an actively supported and maintained tool contributed to the
                                    decision to work with this software.</p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>ELAN screen shot of search results for shots including a
                                          traffic policeman in <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title></head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2007.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>For the analysis of city symphonies, I manually segmented the four
                                    films <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                          >Man with a Movie Camera</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                          >Rien que les Heures</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                                          >Manhatta</title> and added descriptions, words, and
                                    keywords to the segments in a number of tiers focusing on motifs
                                    and visual elements, bigger thematic sequences, people, the
                                    cityscape, specific locations, and filmic techniques such as
                                    fades, multiple exposures, split screens, and fast motion (see
                                    Figure 4).<note>I also looked into camera angles, shot
                                          distances, camera and object movements. However, this was
                                          rather done in a selective way.</note> As mentioned above,
                                    segmenting in this case meant a very fine-grained segmentation
                                    at shot level as the basis for adding annotations to the
                                    individual tiers.<note><q>Shot</q> is understood here as the
                                          basic unit of the film, being characterized by a unity of
                                          time and space, a continuously exposed and uncut piece of
                                          film – a series of film frames without cuts.</note> Hence,
                                    I identified all shots and marked all shot changes,<note>Shot
                                          changes included hard cuts, dissolves, fade-ins and
                                          fade-outs.</note> and used the same self-defined tier
                                    template for segmenting and annotating all four films in order
                                    to make a structural and precise comparison of their data
                                          possible.<note>The digital video files used for the
                                          analysis (mpeg-4-films, codecs H.264, AAC, and QuickTime
                                          Text) had their origins in the following DVDs: <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >die Sinfonie der Großstadt</title> and <title
                                                rend="italic">Melodie der Welt</title>, Walther
                                          Ruttmann, 1927, 1929 (Edition Filmmuseum 39, 2008), <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, Dziga
                                          Vertov, 1929 (Image Entertainment, 1998), <title
                                                rend="italic">Masterworks of American Avant-Garde
                                                Experimental film</title> (1920-1970), including 2K
                                          restoration of <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title>, Paul
                                          Strand and Charles Sheeler, 1921 (Flicker Alley, 2015),
                                          and <title rend="italic">Avant-Garde 3: Experimental
                                                Cinema 1922-1954</title>, including <title
                                                rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> from the
                                          collection of the George Eastman House, Alberto
                                          Cavalcanti, 1926 (Kino International, 2009).
                                          Unfortunately, the Masters of Cinema/Eureka Blu-ray of
                                                <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>
                                          (2016) had not yet been released when I started my
                                          analysis, which presents the new Lobster Film/EYE
                                          Filmmuseum restoration from 2014, the uncut, most
                                          complete, and full-frame version of Vertov’s film. It
                                          needs to be said that the digital video files as well as
                                          their source DVDs differ from the original 35mm film
                                          material in terms of absolute frame accuracy. As silent
                                          films were shown at rates between 16 and 24 frames per
                                          second, these original rates have to be <q>transformed</q>
                                          to the DVD standard of 25 frames per second (European PAL
                                          format) respectively 30 frames per second (American NTSC
                                          format), otherwise the films look speeded up. This
                                          film-to-video transfer happens either by interpolating
                                          frames, selectively and consistently repeating frames to
                                          convert to the video frame rate, or (in the case of a DVD
                                          based on a progressive frame by frame digital scan) by
                                          flags in the DVD instructing the player to generate extra
                                          frames during playback. I won’t go into more detail here
                                          but underline that I am aware of the issue of frame
                                          (in‑)accuracy with regard to digital video files and that
                                          ideally, one would aim to use frame-accurate digital
                                          versions of the films. However, for the purpose of my
                                          analysis of city symphonies’ features, an absolute frame
                                          accuracy was not necessary. Therefore, I went with the
                                          “unclean” digital video files without aiming to eliminate
                                          the interpolated or doubled frames first – simply for
                                          pragmatic reasons. For a frame accurate process, see <ref
                                                target="#jacobs2016">Jacobs and Fyfe
                                          (2016)</ref>.</note>
                              </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                              <head>Film Analysis Step 2: Word and Shot Lists, Excel Sheets,
                                    Cinemetrics, and ImageJ</head>
                              <p>After the segmenting and annotating operation in ELAN, a
                                    time-consuming activity that took four weeks for the four canon
                                    films and required a high level of concentration to guarantee
                                    consistency and accuracy, further analysis steps followed.
                                    Basically, there were two tasks that required a couple of
                                    additional steps. The four data sets from ELAN (each
                                    corresponding to one of the films) had to be merged into one,
                                    allowing for a direct comparison and combined data evaluation.
                                    Following my research questions, I was interested in the
                                          <emph>shared</emph> features of the city symphony films
                                    rather than in detailed analyses of individual titles. Moreover,
                                    this data merging into a combined data set of city symphony
                                    films should happen according to the foci on visual motifs and
                                    structural patterns.<note>This double focus was also related to
                                          a further research sub-question: if the city symphony can
                                          be considered as a film genre or a film cycle. I
                                          approached this issue by using Altman’s semantic/syntactic
                                          approach to film genre (1984) as a heuristic tool for the
                                          analysis, which resulted in a split of the analysis and
                                          city symphony features into visual motifs (the city
                                          symphony semantics) and structural patterns (the city
                                          symphony syntax).</note> Consequently, the analysis should
                                    result in two lists: one for visual motifs, one for structural
                                    patterns. In this regard, annotations from the tier
                                          <q>imagery/visual shot elements</q> were used for the
                                    motif analysis, while the very segmentation, the tier <q>shot
                                          list,</q> as well as the tier <q>filmic techniques,</q>
                                    and the timeline visualization in ELAN formed the basis for the
                                    structural analysis (see Figure 3). Nevertheless, it needs to be
                                    said that both parts of the analysis, lists, and sections also
                                    stand in dialogue with each other and cannot be split that
                                    strictly. Indeed, it is also not desirable to do so as visual
                                    motifs and structural patterns, content and form are
                                          interrelated.<note>In the analysis scheme, this is
                                          represented by the orange double arrows (see Figure
                                          3).</note>
                              </p>

                              <div>
                                    <head>Motif Analysis</head>
                                    <p>For the analysis of visual motifs, I exported the tier on
                                          visual elements from ELAN. More precisely, ELAN provides
                                          an export option called <q>List of Words,</q> for which
                                          one can select a single or several tiers. The software
                                          compiles a wordlist in alphabetic order from all
                                          annotations in the selected tier(‑s) in a text file,
                                          optionally accompanied by the occurrences of the words. In
                                          this way, I was able to get an overview of all annotated
                                          visual shot elements of the four canon films.</p>
                                    <p>Moreover, the occurrences gave me an idea about important
                                          aspects. However, while an appearance of trams in at least
                                          68 shots in <title rend="italic">Berlin</title> hints at a
                                          rather important and recurring visual element, the amount
                                          of only one shot presenting a street cleaning vehicle does
                                          not necessarily lead to the opposite conclusion of a minor
                                          motif. In fact, theoretically, all trams could have been
                                          visible in the background of the frame, whereas the street
                                          cleaning vehicle in a single shot of three minutes could
                                          have been in the very center of attention. In this regard,
                                          the street cleaning vehicle would form an essential visual
                                          motif too, even though it occurs only in a single shot.
                                          This, of course, depends also on the way and detail of
                                          analysis and the guidelines the scholar defines and
                                          applies in the annotation process.<note>In fact, the more
                                                detailed the level of annotating, the more difficult
                                                it becomes to identify greater motifs. In this
                                                regard, elements such as cars, trams, taxis and
                                                trains can be combined under the common denominator
                                                of modern means of transportation.</note>
                                          Nevertheless, the example demonstrates that the
                                          occurrences exported from ELAN can be considered as
                                          indications in terms of importance rather than as absolute
                                          entities. Indeed, quantitative and qualitative aspects
                                          have to go together, since the trained eye and viewing
                                          experience of the film scholar can identify nuances and
                                          decide about emphases, thereby enriching, correcting, or
                                          verifying results from a strictly formal analysis of
                                          visual shot elements.<note>Moreover, the combination of
                                                the tier <q>imagery/visual shot elements</q> with
                                                other tiers, especially the row on shot distances,
                                                gives indications about the role of visual elements
                                                in the picture. Further aspects include shot length,
                                                position in the entire film, within a specific
                                                sequence etc.</note>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>Based on the exported word lists of the four canon films, I
                                          clustered the individual elements per film to motif groups
                                          and added a number of further aspects from the tiers
                                          relating to questions of people, elements of the cityscape
                                          (e.g. streetscape, industrial site, specific building or
                                          monument), and greater narrative sequences and themes,
                                          such as commute, morning routines or lunch break.
                                          Subsequently, these processed word lists were merged
                                          manually into a master list of visual motifs, indicating
                                          if a specific motif identified in this bottom-up approach
                                          could be found in one, several, or all four canon films as
                                          shared feature of city symphonies (see Figure 8).</p>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Excerpt of motifs list</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2008.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                              </div>
                              <div>
                                    <head>Structure Analysis</head>
                                    <p>The analysis of structural patterns and filmic (montage)
                                          techniques was more complex than the motif analysis as it
                                          required further sub-steps and introduced two additional
                                          computational analysis tools: Cinemetrics (or better: the
                                          Cinemetrics approach) and ImageJ in combination with the
                                          plug-in ImageMontage. Before explaining what these two
                                          analysis methods comprise, there is another step to
                                          mention, which forms the fundament for both of these
                                          methods.</p>
                                    <p>While for the motif analysis I exported alphabetic word lists
                                          from ELAN, for the structure analysis I exported shot
                                          lists with timecodes. In fact, when identifying shot
                                          boundaries on the timeline with the cursor during the
                                          segmentation process, ELAN notes the timecodes, which can
                                          be exported (via the <q>tab-delimited text</q> option and
                                          text files) into Excel spreadsheets as timecoded shot
                                                lists.<note> More precisely, this <q>tab-delimited
                                                  text</q> export option allows to select specific
                                                tiers and present them in the resulting text file in
                                                separate columns per tier, including (if selected)
                                                columns for start time, end time and duration of
                                                segments or shots. The data and columns can easily
                                                be transferred into Excel spreadsheets by copying
                                                and pasting.</note> Hence, the fine-grained
                                          segmentation on shot level was the basis for this export
                                          option and, subsequently, for a film rhythm and montage
                                          analysis both in the Cinemetrics tradition and with the
                                          software ImageJ. Both of these tools rely on timecodes and
                                          shot durations, supplemented, in the case of ImageJ, by a
                                          precise indication of frame numbers.</p>
                                    <p>Yuri Tsivian and Gunars Civjans (later joined by Daria
                                          Khitrova) launched Cinemetrics in 2005, a software that
                                          supports the measurement of films by counting the length,
                                          (type), and number of shots and presenting the results of
                                          these measurements in bar charts – as visual
                                          representation of the rhythm and editing patterns of
                                                films.<note> See <ref
                                                  target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv/index.php"
                                                  >http://www.cinemetrics.lv/index.php</ref> (last
                                                consulted on February 6th 2017). On the Cinemetrics
                                                tool and method, see also <ref
                                                  target="#heftberger2016">Heftberger (2016)</ref>
                                                and <ref target="#olesen2017">Olesen
                                                (2017)</ref>.</note> In these charts, the shots are
                                          arranged according to their succession in the film on the
                                          x-axis, while the height of the individual bars on the
                                          y-axis visualizes the duration of each shot (see Figure
                                          9). Such an analysis and representation of shot durations
                                          is especially valuable for city symphonies, since these
                                          films – as montage films – are concerned with both the
                                          tempo of the city and the rhythm of the films themselves,
                                          a rhythm created purely by visual means and by translating
                                          musical guidelines into the visual language of cinema.</p>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Cinemetrics shot length and film rhythm analysis of
                                                  <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                                  Camera</title></head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2009.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Shot length and rhythm analysis of <title
                                                  rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> in Excel
                                                (with ELAN data)</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2010.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <p>In this regard, I combined an analysis in the Cinemetrics
                                          tradition with data compiled in ELAN. The emphasis lies on
                                                <emph>tradition</emph> (or the Cinemetrics approach)
                                          since I did not use the very Cinemetrics software itself,
                                          but took the data exported from ELAN, the start times and
                                          durations of shots, to compile comparable bar charts of
                                          shot lengths in Excel (see Figure 10). The motivation to
                                          work with Excel and ELAN instead of Cinemetrics was to
                                          combine the analysis work in one tool and avoid segmenting
                                          and analyzing the same material multiple times in
                                          different programs. Moreover, Excel in combination with
                                          ELAN guaranteed a higher degree of accuracy, as shot
                                          changes can be identified more precisely in ELAN than with
                                          the Cinemetrics tool, and all four films were analyzed and
                                          measured exactly in the same way.<note>Apart from the
                                                analysis tool, the Cinemetrics website actually also
                                                provides a growing database of films measured and
                                                analyzed with the Cinemetrics software by scholars
                                                all over the world. This database comprises shot
                                                length analyses of <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                                  Movie Camera</title> and <title rend="italic"
                                                  >Berlin</title>. However, to guarantee
                                                comparability and accuracy, I used the data from all
                                                your films compiled in ELAN.</note> In fact, it
                                          needs to be said that ELAN itself in its timeline approach
                                          offers a representation of rhythm and shot lengths, too,
                                          as it displays shots (or segments) in their respective
                                          length horizontally next to each other, split by vertical
                                          lines representing shot changes (see Figure 5 and Figure
                                          6). However, the tool does not allow to zoom out as far as
                                          to see an entire act or even the whole film.<note>At
                                                least, this is the case in version 4.9.4. for Mac OS
                                                X.</note> The bar charts in Cinemetrics and Excel,
                                          on the other hand, support such a complete
                                          (over‑)view.</p>
                                    <p>In the end, film rhythm and editing do not only rely on shot
                                          length, but also relate to alternation between shot
                                          distances, movements within shots, camera movements, and
                                          the content of shots. As Vertov himself put it, montage is
                                                <quote rend="inline">the sum of various
                                                correlations,</quote> including <quote rend="inline"
                                                >the correlation of planes</quote> (shot distances),
                                                <quote rend="inline">the correlation of movement
                                                within the frame, the correlation of light and
                                                shadow,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">the
                                                correlation of recording speed</quote>
                                          <ptr target="#vertov1984" loc="90–1"/>.<note>He speaks
                                                about <quote rend="inline">the visual correlation of
                                                  shots,</quote>
                                                <quote rend="inline">the visual
                                                  <q>interval</q></quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >movement between shots</quote> that is montage.
                                                In fact, later he refers to the <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >montage battle.</quote></note> In this regard,
                                          ImageJ with the plug-in ImageMontage provides an analysis
                                          and visualization form that takes these elements into
                                          account and complements the graphical Cinemetrics analysis
                                          with a more figurative expression. More precisely, in its
                                          specific application developed by Manovich’s Software
                                          Studies Initiative,<note>Manovich developed the plug-in
                                                ImageMontage and the software extension ImagePlot
                                                for the open-source scientific visualization
                                                software ImageJ, which was originally introduced by
                                                the National Institute of Mental Health in the US.
                                                Following Olesen it <quote rend="inline">advanced
                                                  the combination of modern computation techniques
                                                  with microscopy and gained widespread success in a
                                                  broad range of disciplines in the natural
                                                  sciences</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#olesen2017" loc="168"/>. See also <ref
                                                  target="http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2014/03/how-to-visualize-4512-instagram-selfies.html"
                                                  >http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2014/03/how-to-visualize-4512-instagram-selfies.html</ref>
                                                (last consulted on July 20th 2018).</note> this
                                          software allows to combine a selection of individual film
                                          frames into a single image as a grid – as a montage of
                                          images. As Olesen explains: <cit><quote rend="block">As a
                                                  cinemetric tool, the ImageJ/ImagePlot software
                                                  developed within Cultural Analysis distinguishes
                                                  itself by processing films as image sets to create
                                                  visualisations, instead of extracting metadata to
                                                  produce reduced, statistical representations.
                                                  ImageJ breaks down video files into sequences of
                                                  separate images and seriates them according to
                                                  specific image features in various visualization
                                                  types. For example, the Montage visualisation type
                                                  orders frames onto a grid according to their
                                                  sequential order, in rows from left to right,
                                                  enabling a quick, comprehensive overview of
                                                  movements between shots.</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#olesen2017" loc="170"/></cit></p>
                                    <p>Indeed, by breaking down video files into separate still
                                          images, ImageJ recreates (more or less accurately) the
                                          individual frames of a film in digital form, comparable to
                                          their analogue equivalents on the film stip. Via a text
                                          file with a list of file names corresponding to individual
                                          images in the total number of images of a film, the
                                          ImageMontage plug-in allows to define a very specific
                                          selection of pictures to be compiled into such a montage
                                          visualization. For the analysis of city symphony
                                          structures, film rhythm, and editing patterns, I defined
                                          and produced three different types of image montages:
                                          Either a montage consisted of all individual frames of a
                                          shot or sequence (see Figure 11) or it represented a
                                          selection of frames from a specific scene or sequence:
                                          This selection presented one frame per second (see Figure
                                          12) or it displayed one frame per shot (see Figure 13 and
                                          Figure 14).<note>Normally the tenth frame was selected to
                                                avoid imprecisions in shot changes, fades etc. See
                                                also <ref target="#heftberger2016">Heftberger
                                                  (2016)</ref> and <ref target="#manovich2013"
                                                  >Manovich (2013)</ref> and their earlier analyses
                                                and visualizations of Vertov’s films.</note>
                                          Together, these three montage types, used depending on the
                                          length and complexity of the specific shot or sequence to
                                          analyze, facilitated a deeper and more nuanced study of
                                          film rhythm and different editing patterns by taking a
                                          look at the visual material of the films in a
                                                <emph>condensed</emph> or compact way.</p>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Image Montage of <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                                  Heures</title>'s newspaper sequence (all frames of
                                                the shots, 31'10''-31'26'')</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2011.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Image Montage of <title rend="italic"
                                                >Berlin</title>'s newspaper headlines,
                                                rollercoaster, merry-go-round and spiral sequence
                                                (one frame per second, 46'55''-47'34'')</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2012.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Image Montage of <title rend="italic"
                                                  >Manhatta</title>'s crowds in the city sequence
                                                (one frame per shot, 1'41''-2'59'')</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2013.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Image Montage of <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                                  Movie Camera</title>'s train ride sequence (one
                                                frame per shot, 10'16''-11'14'')</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2014.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                                    <p>To be able to produce these image montages and define
                                          specific frames to be included in the grids, it was
                                          essential to convert ELAN’s timecodes of shots and shot
                                          changes into frame numbers corresponding to the numbers of
                                          individual images in the film (or video file
                                          respectively). In fact, if ELAN would have had an option
                                          to define specific segments (or shots) not only in a time
                                          structure but also in frames,<note>With one second
                                                consisting of 24 frames or less (in the case of
                                                silent films).</note> this converting step could
                                          have been skipped. Either way, the importance of ELAN and
                                          segmentation as basic step once more becomes obvious
                                          here.</p>
                                    <p>Finally, for the analysis of structural patterns, the
                                          timeline representation and visualization in ELAN itself
                                          was essential as well. Above, I have already mentioned the
                                          visualization of film rhythm and editing in the horizontal
                                          timeline approach. Moreover, the timeline and annotation
                                          options in various tiers make it possible to see how
                                          different elements are linked to each other and to detect
                                          relations, recurring elements, and patterns. In addition,
                                          the tier <q>filmic techniques</q> contributed to the
                                          identification of structural patterns as it gave an
                                          overview of experimental techniques and shot changes per
                                          film.</p>
                                    <p>In the end, all these analysis steps together, from ELAN via
                                          Excel to Cinemetrics and ImageJ, made it possible to
                                          compile a master list of shared structural patterns of
                                                <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title>,
                                          and <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title> (see Figure 15).
                                          However, as it has become obvious from the various
                                          analysis steps, this list was created in a less
                                          straightforward way than the master list of visual motifs
                                          and required a higher degree of interpretation.</p>
                                    <figure>
                                          <head>Excerpt of structures list</head>
                                          <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2015.jpg"/>
                                    </figure>
                              </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                              <head>From the Canon to the Broader Corpus of City Symphonies</head>
                              <p>In a final analysis step, the two master lists of visual motifs and
                                    structural patterns were expanded to the broader corpus of city
                                    symphony films. Regarding this greater corpus, I used the
                                    overview of identified shared characteristics of <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic">Man
                                          with a Movie Camera</title>, <title rend="italic">Rien que
                                          les Heures</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                                          >Manhatta</title> to check, based on viewings, if and to
                                    what extent they could be found in these titles, too. This means
                                    that I did not start from a detailed in-depth close reading of
                                    each film in ELAN, as I did with the canon films, but used the
                                    canon features as a check list to analyze to what extent these
                                    features are applicable to a bigger group of films and thereby
                                    can be defined as characteristics for the interwar city symphony
                                    phenomenon in general.<note>The strong focus on the canon films
                                          as prototypical examples was particularly motivated within
                                          the greater objective of my dissertation: an examination
                                          and critical reflection of the city symphony
                                          historiography. Therefore, the analysis also takes
                                          historiography and the city symphony as the product it
                                          became throughout historiography as its center of focus:
                                          How can the city symphony be defined according to the
                                          construct it became in film historiography – and from
                                          there expanding to the greater corpus of these films,
                                          which have only marginally been mentioned in film history
                                          writings? Moreover, there was also a very pragmatic reason
                                          as the level of detail applied in the analysis of the
                                          canon films could not have been extended to a greater
                                          corpus of sixty to eighty-five titles.</note>
                              </p>
                        </div>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                        <head>City Symphony Features, Motifs, and Structures (Results 1)</head>
                        <p>Through the methodology described above, I could indeed identify an
                              extensive catalogue of shared visual motifs and structural patterns of
                              interwar city symphonies and their presentation of the modern
                                    city.<note>Moreover, by arriving at a list of visual motifs and
                                    structural patterns – or semantic and syntactic features –
                                    shared by a great number of films, I could also fortify the idea
                                    of considering the city symphony as a full-fledged film genre
                                    rather than a limited cycle. Obviously, not every feature is
                                    present in every film, but this is precisely an observation that
                                    can be made for every film that is considered in the context of
                                    a broader genre.</note>In fact, while, on the one hand, I could
                              underpin certain aspects emphasized in scholarship and film
                              historiography, on the other hand, I could also revise other elements
                              and mark them as misreadings or (over‑)hasty conclusions. Moreover, I
                              could also add new findings. The result is a much more nuanced,
                              detailed and sophisticated picture of the phenomenon of city
                              symphonies, of which this article includes just a small
                                    fraction.<note> For a complete overview and extensive discussion
                                    of city symphony features, see <ref target="#hielscher2018"
                                          >Hielscher (2018)</ref>. Since my analysis focused on
                                          <emph>shared</emph> features of the canon films and the
                                    broader corpus (thus the city symphony phenomenon as a whole),
                                    it excluded the comprehensive examination of individual films
                                    and the filmmaker’s individual projects. This means also that
                                    individual intellectual arguments remained in the background,
                                    even though they make part of these films.</note>
                        </p>

                        <div>
                              <head>Supporting Lights on Garbage-Minding, Crowds, and Rhythmic
                                    Montage</head>
                              <p>My analysis, for instance, confirmed the <quote rend="inline"
                                          >garbage-minding</quote> discussed by <ref
                                          target="#kracauer1960" loc="54">Kracauer (1960, p.
                                          54)</ref> in relation to <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title> and <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                          Heures</title>, and I could identify it as a general
                                    feature of city symphonies.<note> When discussing the revealing
                                          functions and capacity of the film medium to make things
                                          visible that are usually overseen, Kracauer refers to the
                                                <quote rend="inline">wealth of sewer grates,
                                                gutters, and streets littered with rubbish</quote>
                                          in <title rend="italic">Berlin</title> before turning to
                                          Cavalcanti, who <quote rend="inline">in his <title
                                                  rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> is
                                                hardly less garbage-minded</quote>
                                          <ptr target="#kracauer1960" loc="54"/>.</note> I could do
                                    so by detecting and analyzing the application of this motif in
                                    the canon films, which does not only concern the actual
                                    depiction of waste and dirt,<note><title rend="italic"
                                                >Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                                Movie Camera</title> and <title rend="italic">Rien
                                                que les Heures</title> all depict waste objects –
                                          quite often as atmospheric images. While <title
                                                rend="italic">Manhatta</title> forms rather an
                                          exception, Strand and Sheeler’s film also depicts smoke as
                                          waste product of heating and the maritime industry.</note>
                                    but also includes (and overlaps with) the elements of street
                                    cleaning and waste collection as city activities that are
                                    presented especially as morning routines (see Figure 16).
                                    Moreover, I could find similar shots and scenes in the bigger
                                    city symphony corpus. At least twenty other titles include a
                                    focus on waste.<note>Georges Lacombe even uses waste, waste
                                          collection and recycling as main theme and structuring
                                          element in <title rend="italic">La Zone</title>
                                          (1928).</note> The same is true for the depiction of
                                    street cleaning activities.</p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>Waste collection in <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>
                                          (top row) as well as street cleaning and <quote
                                                rend="inline">garbage-minding</quote> in <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title> (left), <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>
                                          (middle), and <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                                Heures</title> (right)</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2016.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>A second feature often associated with city symphonies in the
                                    literature I could support and strengthen by my analysis is the
                                    films’ focus on crowds (see e.g. <ref target="#barsom1973"
                                          >Barsam, 1973</ref>; <ref target="#weiss1995">Weiss,
                                          1995</ref>; <ref target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann,
                                          1997</ref>; <ref target="#dahne2013">Dähne, 2013</ref>).
                                    While the look at the greater city symphony corpus revealed that
                                    crowds play an important role in at least forty-four of the
                                    sixty-seven titles studied, the ELAN analysis of the canon films
                                    allowed to take a closer look at the construction of these
                                    crowds – thus how visual content and cinematic techniques create
                                    this motif together. In this regard, it is remarkable that there
                                    are not too many <q>real</q> crowd shots with masses of people.
                                    Instead, we can often speak of an accumulation technique, by
                                    with the impression of crowds is created visually through
                                    editing. In the case of <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>,
                                    seventy-two shots display more than fifty people, which is about
                                    6.5% of the entire film. The crowd-effect, however, arises
                                    significantly from the sum of street shots with a few people as
                                    well as smaller groups (see Figure 17).<note>I identified these
                                          groups in ELAN by ascribing each shot to one of the
                                          following categories: (1) a single person visible in the
                                          shot, (2) two people, (3) a small group of three to ten
                                          people, (4) a larger group of up to fifty people, (5) a
                                          crowd of more than fifty people.</note> Edited together,
                                    they form the city crowds and huge movements within the
                                    cityscape. The same is true for <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                          Movie Camera</title>, which contains fifty-six <q>real</q>
                                    crowd shots (3.3% of the entire film), while presenting 705
                                    shots with a single person (41.1% of the entire film). Put
                                    together by means of montage, these individuals merge into the
                                    urban crowd of the cinematically created new Soviet city, that
                                    combines the cityscapes of Moscow, Odessa, and Kiev.</p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>Example of crowd construction by accumulation in <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title> (one frame per
                                          shot)</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2017.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>In combination with the Cinemetrics approach and ImageJ, ELAN also
                                    allowed to underline the symphonic form and rhythmic montage of
                                    city symphonies, described, among others, by <ref
                                          target="#grierson1933">Grierson (1933)</ref>, <ref
                                          target="#rotha1936">Rotha (1936)</ref>, <ref
                                          target="#kracauer1947">Kracauer (1947)</ref>, <ref
                                          target="#jacobs1949">Jacobs (1949)</ref>, <ref
                                          target="#barsam1973">Barsam (1973)</ref>, <ref
                                          target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann (1997)</ref>, and <ref
                                          target="#dahne2013">Dähne (2013)</ref>. Indeed, the
                                    analysis of the canon films showed in detail how the
                                    well-calculated and -structured alternation of shot lengths and
                                    the varying duration of shots together with associative editing,
                                    analogous and contrasting montage, as well as cross-cutting
                                    strategies generate this rhythmic form (see Figures 5-6 and
                                    Figures 10-14). In addition, the visual elements of opening,
                                    closing, starting, stopping, arriving/entering, and leaving
                                    activities (motifs list) also greatly contribute to city
                                    symphonies’ rhythmic form and general pulse of the city. There
                                    are, for example, shots of opening doors, gates, blinds, and
                                    rolling shutters in <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                          Heures</title>, <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>,
                                          <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title>, and <title
                                          rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>,
                                    particularly presented in the morning. Moreover, there are
                                    scenes of people arriving at work, entering buildings, cafés,
                                    shops, elevators, telephone boxes, cars, busses, taxis, and
                                    various types of trains. The opposite activities of leaving and
                                    de-boarding are depicted in combination with the same elements
                                    and situations.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                              <head>The Myths of the Nature-Free Industrial City without
                                    Landmarks</head>
                              <p>I could also rectify certain aspects that had been introduced in
                                    the literature. For instance, intertitles and hired actors (or
                                    better: staged scenes) are not as unusual as often claimed (see
                                    e.g. <ref target="#jacobs1949">Jacobs, 1949</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#uricchio1982">Uricchio, 1982</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#urvey2011">Turvey, 2011</ref>).<note> These texts
                                          particularly refer to <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>
                                          and <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>
                                          regarding the deliberate avoidance of intertitles. In
                                          terms of the refusal of staged scenes and hired actors, it
                                          is especially Vertov’s film that is highlighted, while
                                          Ruttmann’s film is often criticized exactly for the
                                          integration of staged scenes, most prominently by <ref
                                                target="#kracauer1947">Kracauer (1947)</ref>.</note>
                                    Though, while these points could be supported especially through
                                    the look at the greater city symphony corpus, the aspect of
                                    natural elements in the city as a focus in city symphonies could
                                    be identified and revised particularly through the act of
                                          <emph>doing</emph> the ELAN analysis and studying the
                                    compiled (and exported) data with regard to <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                          Camera</title>, <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                          Heures</title>, and <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title>.
                                    More specifically, during the activity of marking shots and
                                    adding notes to the visual elements in these shots, I realized
                                    the recurrence of aspects such as clouds and sky, water and
                                    trees. A focus on these phenomena was further confirmed in the
                                    wordlists exported from ELAN and merged into the motifs master
                                    list. In addition, the step of checking the greater city
                                    symphony corpus also underlined the presence and focus on these
                                    natural elements in city symphonies. There are at least
                                    thirty-six titles depicting aspects such as clouds, water and
                                    trees in the city. Moreover, the detailed ELAN analysis of the
                                    canon films showed that these elements often function as
                                    atmospheric shots and images of transition or introduction.
                                    Clouds and water also work as indicators of the passing of time.
                                    While this might not be too surprising, the close reading of the
                                    films also stressed both the aspect of <term>urbanized</term>
                                    natural elements and the coexistence of natural and urban
                                    aspects in the city. Indeed, especially water appears in the
                                    city as civilized or <term>urbanized</term> water – in relation
                                    to street cleaning, wet streets, gutters and sewerage as well as
                                    in combination with water fountains and, in the case of <title
                                          rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, the
                                    waterfall of the Dneiper electricity power station (see Figure
                                    18). Here, a natural source is transformed into a modern and
                                    industrialized energy force (see also <ref target="#roberts2000"
                                          >Roberts, 2000</ref>). Moreover, natural elements exist
                                          <emph>in</emph> the city, such as trees that often appear
                                    in street scenes at the line between sidewalk and street,
                                    especially in Vertov and Ruttmann’s urban universes.<note>This
                                          modern urban street construction aspect belongs to the
                                          modern metropolitan streetscape in general since
                                          Haussmann’s restructuring of Paris.</note> In addition,
                                    natural elements exert an influence on urban structures and, in
                                    this way, make part of the urban environment, permeate urban
                                    structures, and become interwoven with the city. This is
                                    especially the case of wind, rain, and thunderstorm in <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic">Man
                                          with a Movie Camera</title>, and <title rend="italic">Rien
                                          que les Heures</title> (see Figure 19). Natural elements
                                    and organic forces are thus introduced to the city in these
                                    films, which show that the modern and industrialized city is
                                    anything but nature-free. This stands in contrast to <ref
                                          target="#horak1995">Horak (1995)</ref>, who states that
                                    the role of nature in city symphonies is basically limited to
                                    its role in leisure-time activities, especially in the European
                                          films.<note>More precisely, he opposes <title
                                                rend="italic">Manhatta</title> and the American film
                                          avant-garde of the 1920s and 1930s with their longing for
                                          the city’s (re‑)unification with nature to the European
                                          city films of that time, which, according to Horak proudly
                                          celebrate urbanism and the machine age and praise the
                                          urban environment <quote rend="inline">for its excitement,
                                                speed, and modernity, with few references to nature,
                                                beyond its role in leisure-time activities for
                                                Sunday picknickers</quote>
                                          <ptr target="#horak1995" loc="35"/></note> However, while
                                    natural elements, indeed, also appear in relation to sports and
                                    the recreation sector in many city symphonies, the ELAN analysis
                                    shows that they play a much more prominent and complex part –
                                    also (and especially) in the European films. They permeate the
                                    city just like the city permeates and <emph>urbanizes</emph>
                                    nature and coexist with urban structures.<note> This becomes
                                          even more obvious in city symphonies like <title
                                                rend="italic">Regen</title> (Joris Ivens and Mannus
                                          Franken, 1929) and <title rend="italic">Images
                                                d’Ostende</title> (Henri Storck, 1929).</note>
                              </p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head><term>Urbanized</term> Water in <title rend="italic">Rien
                                                que les Heures</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Manhatta</title>, <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                                Movie Camera</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                                                >Berlin</title></head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2018.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>Wind in <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, and
                                                <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                          Heures</title></head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2019.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>Another shortcoming resulting from literature and film
                                    historiography my analysis could revise is the assumption that
                                    city symphonies exclude landmarks and monuments. <ref
                                          target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann (1997)</ref>, for
                                    example, claims regarding <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>
                                    that the film makes no reference to actual places. Balázs also
                                    points into that direction as he describes <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title> as a non-touristic film <quote
                                          rend="inline">with little use as a guide to a stranger
                                          arriving in the city for the first time</quote> and sees
                                    both Ruttmann and Cavalcanti’s films as <quote rend="inline"
                                          >mental associations</quote> that have nothing to do with
                                    presenting reality or specific places <ptr target="#balazs2010"
                                          loc="162–163"/>. From discussions like these and the
                                    undeniable focus of city symphonies on everyday life (hence,
                                    they <emph>are</emph> non-touristic films),<note>Interestingly
                                          enough, this does not mean that they do not take tourism
                                          as a theme. All four canon films (as well as a handful of
                                          other titles) present hotels, guests and travelers. Also
                                          the famous arrival in the city, depicted in at least
                                          twenty-three films, can be seen in light of a touristic
                                          aspect.</note> the general assumption emerged that these
                                    films do not present landmarks, specific buildings, and
                                    monuments in favor of an abstract presentation of a generic
                                          cityscape.<note>The prologue of <title rend="italic">Rien
                                                que les Heures</title> might have also contributed
                                          to this assumption, in which Cavalcanti states in
                                          intertitles that all cities are the same, once we ignore
                                          their monuments, and that his film does not claim to
                                          synthesize any city as it is only a sequence of
                                          impressions of the passing of time. Moreover, the notion
                                          of the generic and unspecific makes sense also in light of
                                          city symphonies’ focus on streets and various means of
                                          transportation – places that <ref target="#auge1995">Augé
                                                (1995)</ref> would later call non-places without
                                          identity in the postmodern city. City symphonies
                                          anticipate these later non-lieux of post-modernity.
                                          Nevertheless, it should be added that there are also some
                                          rare remarks on urban specificity and recognizable urban
                                          and architectural constructions (see e.g. <ref
                                                target="#dahne2013">Dähne, 2013</ref> and <ref
                                                target="#macdonald2001">MacDonald,
                                          2001</ref>).</note> Nevertheless, while city symphonies
                                    also present numerous rather unspecific street scenes and city
                                    views, recognizable landmarks and monuments <emph>are</emph>
                                    included in quite a number of these films (at least in
                                    twenty-four titles). I could specifically mark and analyze these
                                    landmarks in ELAN regarding <title rend="italic">Berlin</title>,
                                          <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>,
                                          <title rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title>, and
                                          <title rend="italic">Manhatta</title>. In this context, it
                                    is remarkable that all four canon films do not only present
                                    recognizable constructions like the Woolworth Building, Brooklyn
                                    Bridge, or Trinity Church (<title rend="italic"
                                    >Manhatta</title>), the Place de la Concorde with the Luxor
                                    Obelisk and the contours of the Eiffel Tower in the background
                                          (<title rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title>), the
                                    Berliner Dom, the Berliner Funkturm, or the Rotes Rathaus
                                          (<title rend="italic">Berlin</title>), or the Bolshoi
                                    Theatre in Moscow (<title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                          Camera</title>),<note>In <title rend="italic"
                                                >Berlin</title> buildings receive a definition and
                                          recognition as city markers also via written signs and
                                          boards on their façades, such as the Gloria Palast at
                                          Kurfürstendamm, the Hotel Excelsior, or the Pschorr-Haus
                                          at Potsdamer Platz. Vertov’s film also includes a couple
                                          of textual signifiers, by which buildings become
                                          identifiable, like the Lenin Club building and the Club
                                          Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov (aka Lenin) at Odessa Station, the
                                          Kiev Proletarian Film Theatre the camera pans across, the
                                          All-Union newspaper building (the Izvestiya building), and
                                          the Bakhmetievsky district bus depot in Moscow. Going
                                          beyond buildings as specific markers in the city and
                                          taking a closer look at the street scenes in <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, it
                                          stands out that Vertov chose only five or six urban
                                          locations to which he returns repeatedly throughout his
                                          film – depicted in similar or (slightly) different camera
                                          positions. In this way, they become urban markers and
                                          specific locations too. One of these streets is Tverskaia
                                          Street in Moscow, the street with the Gorky banner
                                          spanning the street, which we see deserted in the morning
                                          and later with the traffic policeman doing his work.
                                          Nevertheless, the most recognizable location and landmark
                                          in <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>
                                          remains the Bolshoi Theatre, which Vertov makes visually
                                          collapse by a split screen shot in the climax of the film,
                                          according to Tsivian a <quote rend="inline">symbolic
                                                destruction</quote>
                                          <ptr target="#tsivian2004" loc="19"/> Though, he also
                                          presents it in the first minutes of his film as an urban
                                          signifier.</note> but they also do so in the very first
                                    minutes. This can also be seen in the light of introducing the
                                    cityscape. As a sort of <term>establishing shots</term>, these
                                    images function as structuring devices of introducing and
                                    establishing space. They anchor the generic and often anonymous
                                    streets and squares that follow in a concrete and identifiable
                                          place.<note>Nevertheless, even though Ruttmann,
                                          Cavalcanti, Vertov, Stand and Sheeler do include city
                                          markers and specific buildings, it needs to be said that
                                          they all exclude the most famous sights of their
                                          respective city/-ies at the time, including the
                                          Brandenburger Tor, the Statue of Liberty, the Louvre or
                                          Notre Dame de Paris, and Red Square with Kremlin, St.
                                          Basil Cathedral, and the Lenin’s Mausoleum. Indeed, it is
                                          not the touristic city the films focus on, but certain
                                          landmarks and monuments appear as part of the cities’
                                          everyday life.</note>
                              </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                              <head>Horizontal and Vertical City Explorations and Temporal
                                    Phasing</head>
                              <p>Closely linked to the identification and revision of certain
                                    aspects as shortcomings or myths, I could finally also find
                                    aspects that were not greatly paid attention to so far or even
                                    completely overlooked. For instance, by the close analysis of
                                    the canon films in ELAN in combination with the examination of
                                    the greater city symphony corpus, I could discover the
                                    prominence of harbors (and harbor cities)<note>Moreover, there
                                          is a great variation of cities thematized in city
                                          symphonies. While the literature generally speaks about
                                          metropolises such as New York, Paris, or Berlin, city
                                          symphonies of the extended corpus also focus on somewhat
                                          smaller, mid-sized cities, including Rotterdam, Porto, and
                                          Ostend. In addition, the greater city symphony corpus also
                                          demonstrates that Vertov’s concept to cinematically merge
                                          and spatially organize the visual material of several
                                          cities into a newly created filmic city, was not picked
                                          up. It was only once more realized in <title rend="italic"
                                                >Les Nuits Élecriques</title> (1929), in which
                                          Eugène Deslaw combines material of nocturnal Berlin and
                                          Paris.</note> and the extensive depiction of swimming as
                                    the most popular sports and leisure activity. Moreover, once
                                    again by the act of <emph>doing</emph> the analysis in ELAN as
                                    well as the resulting data and motifs list, I could identify an
                                    attention given to the depiction of wet streets (with their
                                    reflecting surfaces). I observed this first in <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title> (especially at night and in
                                    combination with electric lighting, neon signs, and vehicles’
                                    headlights), but could also detect wet street scenes in the
                                    other canon films and the extended city symphony corpus.<note>Of
                                          course, this feature was most elaborately deployed by
                                          Joris Ivens and Mannus Franken in <title rend="italic"
                                                >Regen</title> (1929) as the entire film is
                                          structured around the visual impacts a rain shower has on
                                          the city. Regarding the canon films, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Manhatta</title> is an exception as wet streets
                                          cannot be identified due to the film’s high camera angles,
                                          extreme long and panorama shots and great distance to the
                                          streets on ground level. Moreover, the depiction of wet
                                          (reflecting) streets is present in virtually all films of
                                          the genre that include street scenes at night.</note>
                                    Similarly, the focus on stairs came above water as well as their
                                    function to underline the verticality of the city – its above
                                    and below, including subways, streets, bridges, viaducts, and
                                    tall buildings.</p>
                              <p>Some of the most interesting findings also resulted from the
                                    in-depth exploration of the structuring patterns. Indeed, while
                                    generally the city in city symphonies is perceived as chaotic
                                    and overwhelming, there is a highly organized structure to
                                    create and emphasize this effect, among others through
                                    cross-sectional and rhythmic editing.<note>Montage forms such as
                                          rhythmic, fast, associative, metaphorical and
                                          cross-sectional editing as well as experimental techniques
                                          like unusual camera angles, extremely short takes,
                                          kaleidoscopic images, split screens, multiple exposures
                                          and manipulations of speed increase and
                                          cinematographically (re‑)create the intoxicating and
                                          overwhelming impressions in the modern city. They
                                          underline particularly the frenetic pace, highly
                                          fragmented nature and the contrasting features of urban
                                          modernity and modern urban life. In so doing, city
                                          symphonies can be considered as visualizations of the
                                          theories of <ref target="#benjamin1999">Benjamin
                                                (1999)</ref> and <ref target="#simmel1997">Simmel
                                                (1997)</ref> and their ideas about the modern urban
                                          shock experiences and the overstimulation of the
                                          senses.</note> However, to keep a balance with the
                                    turbulent and fragmented city impressions, city symphonies also
                                    apply a number of ordering strategies to structure the city
                                    experiences and keep things from becoming overly abstract.
                                    Literature has frequently (and often exclusively) referred to
                                    the day structure or dawn-to-dusk form (see e.g. <ref
                                          target="#grierson1933">Grierson, 1933</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#rotha1936">Rotha, 1936</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#noguez1985">Noguez, 1985</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#weihsmann1997">Weihsmann, 1997</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#macdonald2001">MacDonald, 2001</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#vogt2001">Vogt, 2001</ref>; <ref
                                          target="#dahne2013">Dähne, 2013</ref>), but, as my
                                    analysis demonstrates, the ordering strategies are much more
                                    substantial and include both temporal and spatial
                                    structures.</p>
                              <p>Regarding spatial structuring patterns, I want to focus here on the
                                    horizontal and vertical establishment of space and city
                                    explorations identified and analyzed in ELAN in all four canon
                                          films.<note>We can find those vertical and horizontal city
                                          explorations and establishments of space also in at least
                                          twenty other titles of the extended city symphony
                                          corpus.</note> The arrival-into-the-city subject is part
                                    of the horizontal explorations.<note>The city is spatially
                                          introduced by an arrival into that urban space. <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title> and <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>
                                          present arrivals into the city by train; <title
                                                rend="italic">Manhatta</title> starts with an
                                          arrival by a local ferry boat. <title rend="italic">Rien
                                                que les Heures</title> presents a rather conceptual
                                          and vertical arrival into the city as in the prologue
                                          Cavalcanti shows maps (and miniature monuments), from
                                          which he cuts to a shot of the Place de la Concorde on
                                          street level. Moreover, he switches from the idea of
                                          general city life in the prologue to the specific portrait
                                          of Montmartre in the main part. These arrivals into the
                                          city, which often stand at the beginning of the films, are
                                          also a pragmatic way of getting a film on a topic as huge
                                          as the metropolis started.</note> This is also true for
                                    rides through the city, that give the viewer an idea about the
                                    spatial dimensions of the city that unfolds in front of her
                                          eyes.<note> There are rides through the city especially in
                                                <title rend="italic">Berlin</title> and <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>, such
                                          as in the horse-carriage-ride-through-the-city-and-filming
                                          sequence in Vertov’s film and nocturnal taxi rides in
                                          Ruttmann’s Berlin portrait.</note> Moreover, <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                          >Manhatta</title>, <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                          Heures</title>, and <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                          Camera</title> also establish the city in a vertical
                                    perspective. Above, I have already mentioned the visual motif of
                                    stairs that underlines verticality. Moreover, in a sort of <hi
                                          rend="italic">zoom-in</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                                          >cut-down</hi> effect by means of montage, <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title> presents high angle panorama
                                    shots of the area around the Berliner Dom after the initial
                                    arrival into the city – with each shot presenting the city from
                                    a slightly closer and more tilted perspective. Subsequently,
                                    Ruttmann shows shots of lower angles looking up at the clock
                                    tower of the Rotes Rathaus, followed by ground level shots of
                                    deserted streets. These images provide a certain overview of the
                                    cityscape and add to a sense of orientation.<note>In this
                                          regard, they also go together the aforementioned
                                          recognizable landmarks and monuments, which, too, add to
                                          such a sense of spatial orientation.</note> Strand and
                                    Sheeler, too, present high-angle perspectives and panorama shots
                                    from a greater distance before they get closer to street level
                                    in shots of the Staten Island Ferry and crowds walking in the
                                    streets of lower Manhattan. The same is true for Cavalcanti, who
                                    first introduces the city by a high (and abstracted) perspective
                                    of maps before switching to the urban space of Paris and,
                                    subsequently, the borrow of Montmartre on ground level (see
                                    Figure 20). Vertov, in contrast, does not really make use of
                                    such a <term>cut-down</term> effect, but, nevertheless, visually
                                    hints at verticality throughout his film – from a coal mine
                                    underground to a bridge and factory chimneys reaching high in
                                    the air. Moreover, he exemplarily explores urban space
                                    vertically and horizontally in a sequence in reel three, in
                                    which he presents images of a wildly titling and panning camera
                                    showing streets, junctions, and squares intercut with images of
                                    a looking and blinking eye (see Figure 21). While this sequence
                                    reflects on human vision, it also demonstrates both the vertical
                                    and horizontal filmic depiction of the city. Moreover, Vertov
                                    elaborately makes use of extremely high and low camera angles as
                                    well as tilted shots, that further emphasize verticality. The
                                    ELAN analysis of shot distances, camera angles, perspectives,
                                    and montage techniques demonstrates that these cinematic devices
                                    are also part of the other canon films and their investigation
                                    and presentation of urban space.</p>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>Vertical city introductions in <title rend="italic">Rien
                                                que les Heures</title> (top), <title rend="italic"
                                                >Berlin</title> (middle), and <title rend="italic"
                                                >Manhatta</title> (bottom)</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2020.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <figure>
                                    <head>Eye-and-urban-panning-and-tilting sequence in <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title>,
                                          excerpt with all frames of the shots</head>
                                    <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2021.jpg"/>
                              </figure>
                              <p>Concerning temporal structuring patterns going beyond the
                                    well-known chronological day-structure,<note><title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Man with a Movie Camera</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> and <title
                                                rend="italic">Manhatta</title> show this linear
                                          structuring element, even though not all parts of the day
                                          are presented and made equally explicit in all four
                                          films.</note> the ELAN analysis particularly showed the
                                    aspect of the linear organization of events and activities into
                                    phases of before, during, and after (see Figure 22). To be
                                    clear, this is not the overall rule, but it is applied
                                    deliberately in a selective way and in combination with the
                                    chaotic and dizzying city impressions.<note><title rend="italic"
                                                >Manhatta</title> is an exception as it does not
                                          apply this temporal structuring element. Moreover, it
                                          needs to be said that <title rend="italic">Rien que les
                                                Heures</title> includes a certain linear narrative
                                          development as it shows several urban types and their
                                          doings in the course of one day presented in episodes with
                                          beginnings and endings, that happen one after the other.
                                          Though, it is an experimental and fragmented narrative
                                          structure as the different narrative threads constantly
                                          interrupted each other and the characters (and their
                                          stories) remain underdeveloped.</note> More precisely,
                                    there are two forms of this structuring technique. The first one
                                    refers to linear development (or <term>phasing</term>) within a
                                    single (continuing) scene, sequence, or section – thus by means
                                    of linear editing that ELAN accentuates in its timeline
                                    visualization. An example is the murder scene in <title
                                          rend="italic">Rien que les Heures</title> or the
                                    sports-races-and-matches episode in <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title>, which Ruttmann explicitly structures into
                                    shots presenting starting moments, followed by shots presenting
                                    the middle part of competitions, followed by shots presenting
                                    the final moment of a marathon with the winner crossing the
                                    finish line. In <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                          Camera</title> the ambulance-and-fire-brigade-operations
                                    episode is presented with an introductory, operational and an
                                          <term>extroductory</term> phase in one continuing
                                    sequence. The second form is the organization of events and
                                    activities into different phases stretched out over greater
                                    parts of the film. This is especiall used by Ruttmann and
                                    Vertov. For instance, they both present the beginning, during
                                    and end of work spread out over their films, combined with the
                                    activity cluster of machines at rest, starting to move, moving,
                                    stopping to move and at rest again.<note>Of course, this also
                                          emphasizes the chronological day structure and is also
                                          interwoven with the aforementioned numerous shots
                                          depicting acts of opening and closing, arriving and
                                          entering, leaving and de-boarding, and (re‑)starting and
                                          stopping.</note> Moreover, Ruttmann displays the before,
                                    during and after of a thunderstorm, interrupted by (and joined
                                    with) both a suicide and a fire-brigade-operation sequence.
                                    Vertov, too, presents the operations of the cameraman often in a
                                    preparatory, an executing and a concluding phase, as he shows
                                    him, intercut with other scenes, riding to the location of the
                                    film shoot, the actual act of filming and the departure from the
                                    location. These elements that are paused and picked up later –
                                    not seldomly to underline simultaneity – could be examined in
                                    detail especially through the non-linear analysis of keywords
                                    and individual component parts of the films that ELAN
                                    facilitates to disassemble and reassemble in a highly structured
                                    way.</p>
                        </div>

                        <figure>
                              <head>Temporal <term>Phasing</term> in <title rend="italic"
                                          >Berlin</title> (top), <title rend="italic">Man with a
                                          Movie Camera</title> (middle), and <title rend="italic"
                                          >Rien que les Heures</title> (bottom)</head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2022.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                              <head>Cross-sectional editing and thematic clustering in <title
                                          rend="italic">Berlin</title> (cleaning activities)</head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2023.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                              <head>Cross-sectional and associative editing in <title rend="italic"
                                          >Rien que les Heures</title> (men-sleeping-in-the-streets
                                    sequence, one frame per shot)</head>
                              <graphic url="resources/images/Figure%2024.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <div>
                              <head>Database and Narrative</head>
                              <p>The temporal structures – both the linear organization of
                                    activities and events into phases and the chronological day
                                    structure – introduce, to a certain degree, narrative aspects to
                                    city symphonies. More precisely, coming back to Manovich’s logic
                                    of the database versus the logic of the narrative, we can
                                    conclude from the analysis that city symphonies, in fact, relate
                                    to <emph>both</emph> of these logics, combining, merging, and
                                    interweaving a catalogue of (unordered) equal items with
                                    elements of linearity and a certain cause-and-effect trajectory.
                                    Indeed, in their wide, extensive, and diverse visual material
                                    and the accumulation of numerous urban impressions and phenomena
                                    organized in cross-sections, city symphonies anticipate the
                                    logic of the database. They collect and present an enormous
                                    catalogue of urban subjects and cross-sections of the modern
                                    city and modern urban life, which I have analyzed (and put into
                                    a database myself) in the motif analysis. Cross-sectional
                                    editing strategies and thematic clustering, which evoke
                                    simultaneity across space, make part of this database logic or
                                    aesthetic, too<note>Indeed, while film itself as a time-based
                                          medium presents pictures one after the other in
                                          chronological time, city symphonies employ strategies to
                                          evoke the idea of simultaneity resulting in cross-sections
                                          across space.</note> – hence the coming together of visual
                                    content and filmic techniques and structing patterns (see Figure
                                    23 and Figure 24). City symphonies present the modern city as an
                                    inventory. However, this is only one side since, as elaborated
                                    above, there is also the structuring of urban events and
                                    activities into phases, which introduces linearity and a certain
                                    chain of cause and effect, of before, during, and after.
                                    Moreover, the day structure also causes a chronological/linear
                                          development.<note>In addition, there are also
                                          mini-narratives that further underline the logic of the
                                          narrative. In <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                                                Camera</title>, for instance, there is the
                                          mini-thriller narrative of the cameraman getting stuck
                                          with his foot under the rails when the train is
                                          approaching or the story of the accident, the fire brigade
                                          and ambulance operations. An example from <title
                                                rend="italic">Berlin</title> is the mini-narrative
                                          of the female <term xml:lang="fr">flâneuses</term> in the
                                          streets (there is a sequence of similarly looking women),
                                          which turns into the story of a woman (a cocotte) and a
                                          man coupling.</note> Therefore, in their highly complex
                                    structuring and in their extensive urban material, city
                                    symphonies anticipate and reflect on the issue of database and
                                    narrative and play on tensions between a catalogue of motifs
                                    versus a structured history based on chronology and linearity.
                                    We can consider these films as both databases <emph>and</emph>
                                          narratives.<note>Manovich, in fact also points toward the
                                          interweaving of both logics as he describes <title
                                                rend="italic">Man with a Movie Camera</title> not
                                          only as a film anticipating the database logic but also as
                                          a work merging <quote rend="inline">database and narrative
                                                into a new form</quote>
                                          <ptr target="#manovich2001" loc="241–243"/>. Besides the
                                                <quote rend="inline">catalog of subjects that one
                                                could expect to find in a city of the 1920s –
                                                running trams, city beach, movie theatres, factories
                                                ...,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">the most
                                                amazing catalog of film techniques,</quote> there is
                                          also the narrative of modern urban life and the <quote
                                                rend="inline">gradual process of discovery,</quote>
                                          which, according to Manovich, <quote rend="inline">is
                                                film’s main narrative, and it is told through a
                                                catalog of discoveries.</quote> Similarly, other
                                          city symphonies also include a narrative – the story of
                                          the city and modern urban life in a day – while they also
                                          present a cross-sectional database of modern urban
                                          material of the era between the wars.</note> The ELAN
                                    analysis supports a study of both logics in the combination of
                                    its linear/chronological timeline approach and its data
                                    production, listing and cataloguing options. In this regard, the
                                    digital analysis tool itself also relates to both logics of the
                                    database and the narrative.</p>
                        </div>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                        <head>Reflections on Digital Tools, Research Transparency, and Manual
                              Digital Analysis (Results 2)</head>
                        <p>I would like to conclude this research report with a couple of reflecting
                              remarks that exceed the city symphony focus and underline some
                              benefits of digital tools like ELAN and Cinemetrics, that might have a
                              relevance for the entire field of film and media studies.</p>
                        <p>The first one concerns budget and research frameworks. My project did not
                              provide specific funding for the use of digital tools or a close
                              collaboration with software developers or IT engineers, who might have
                              come up with a different solution for my research endeavor. In fact,
                              the use of digital tools was not part of the initial research plan of
                              the umbrella project <title rend="quotes">City Symphonies: Urban
                                    Modernity, Film, and Avant Garde (1920-1940)</title>, funded by
                              the Special Research Funds of Ghent University, but came later by my
                              own initiative.<note>The fortunate encounters with other scholars from
                                    the field of media studies and information science, particularly
                                    L. Melgar and A. Heftberger, introduced me to various digital
                                    tools and inspired me to investigate benefits and options of
                                    applying those tools for my own research purposes.</note>
                              Therefore, the application of ELAN and the Cinemetrics approach in
                              combination with excel sheets and ImageJ can be considered as
                                    <emph>a</emph> best practice for getting my analysis done within
                              the available recourses and timeframe.<note>There are further
                                    interesting analysis methods and data evaluation/visualization
                                    types that could be very fruitful for a study of urban films.
                                    For example, in a cloud or network representation, relations
                                    between motifs could be highlighted or the manner specific
                                    features (re‑)appear in a number of films. Moreover, an online
                                    database project could be interesting, which would allow to
                                    provide access to findings and research results in an
                                    interactive and a rather non-linear way.</note> As I only used
                              free and open-source software (compatible with most computer operating
                              systems) as well as programs that were provided as part of the work
                              package for researchers at Ghent University,<note>I refer here
                                    especially to the MS-Office package, including Word and
                                    Excel.</note> this approach should be widely accessible and
                              might be interesting also for other scholars with little funding.
                              Moreover, with their variable, flexible, and open form, the tools I
                              used are applicable and customizable for a great variety of research
                              questions.</p>
                        <p>The second remark is about research transparency and visual
                              argumentation. ELAN allows for highly structured annotations,
                              segmentations and systematic annotation protocols, which can be
                              considered as externalizations of the observations that normally take
                              place inside the scholar’s mind during close analysis <ptr
                                    target="#melgar2017"/>. Moreover, they can easily be shared with
                              other researchers, who load them, together with the corresponding
                              video files, in their own ELAN version on their computer. In this way,
                              the analysis process and research, including various steps, collected
                              data, findings, and conclusions, become more transparent, retraceable,
                              and shareable. Moreover, the ELAN software and interface as well as
                              the Cinemetrics concept provide visualization methods that support
                              statements, which, with traditional film analysis methods, are harder
                              to underpin, generally only by written explanations. In fact, these
                              data visualizations become visual arguments themselves. This is also
                              true for the image montages made with ImageJ. The film or media
                              scholar receives new powerful tools to illustrate, underline, and
                              fortify findings and observations in a direct visual way.</p>
                        <p>The final comment concerns a significant benefit of using a tool such as
                              ELAN in a manual way, which might also make us rethink the notion of
                              digital analysis. From the methodology described in this article, the
                              impression might arise that I have mainly reproduced manual film
                              analysis practices in a digital environment: I noted shot changes and
                              added descriptions about visual and filmic aspects to this shot-based
                              protocol. While one could indeed question the advantage of ELAN
                              applied this way, there is the very activity of <emph>doing</emph>
                              ELAN – the very experience of segmenting and annotating – that leads
                              to an in-depth knowledge of the film and a level of
                                    <term>hands-on</term> research and learning that neither a
                              traditional film analysis nor a digital analysis with automatic shot
                              detection alone can provide.<note>No doubt, an automatic shot
                                    detection would be more time-efficient, but it would also
                                    eliminate this empirical aspect. As important part of the
                                    analysis, the experience of segmenting and annotating in ELAN
                                    and the pure viewing observations are indicated in the center of
                                    the analysis scheme, contributing to both sides of the study of
                                    motifs and structures (see Figure 3).</note> This is probably
                              most obvious for editing techniques and montage patterns, as the
                                    <q>ELAN experience</q> can, to a certain degree, be considered
                              as a recreation or reconstruction of the film editing process,
                              starting in reverse from the end product of the final film. In fact,
                              in its design, timeline approach, segmentation, and annotation
                              possibilities, ELAN resembles digital film and video editing
                              platforms, such as Final Cut Pro or Avid Media Composer.<note>
                                    Moreover, it also recalls the analogue film strip.</note> In
                              this regard, manually segmenting and annotating in ELAN on the level
                              of shots imitates or retraces the editing process (in digital form)
                              and, in so doing, provides an empirical way of analyzing a film in its
                              structures and motifs. We can speak of a reverse-engineering scholarly
                              experience. More precisely, it is an experience that – as a
                                    <term>hands-on</term> activity – includes both eyes and hands
                              (or better: fingers), which results in a more intimate interaction
                              with the material instead of <emph>just</emph> watching the film.
                              Simply speaking, by using your eyes and fingers in tandem, you get to
                              see things and observe connections and interrelations between various
                              elements you would not be able to see otherwise – or might easily
                              miss. In this article, I have discussed a couple of findings regarding
                              city symphonies that surfaced this way, such as the construction of
                              crowds out of individuals and small groups, the prominence of wet
                              streets and stairs, the interweaving of natural elements with urban
                              structures or the adroit horizontal and vertical city explorations.
                              Moreover, to be clear, the fingers aspect does not only concern the
                              reverse editing activity as detecting shot boundaries, but also the
                              descriptive part of adding keywords and describing shots that
                              contributes to the increased examination of the material and in-depth
                              knowledge of the films. This hands-on angle of using digital tools is
                              an underestimated aspect in digital humanities as <emph>digital</emph>
                              is increasingly understood as <emph>automatic</emph> as opposed to
                                    <emph>manual</emph>. Large bodies of automatically acquired data
                              became available and, as a result, the trend is distancing scholars
                              from their material. However, as I have shown, especially the manual
                              hands-on use of digital tools such as ELAN or Cinemetrics can be
                              extremely beneficial in giving film and media scholars (and students!)
                              an invaluable experience of more intimately interacting with their
                              material. This might also lead to a rethinking of the idea what
                              digital analysis is or can be. In the end, the manual fingers-eyes use
                              of ELAN can be considered digital in two respects and, if you will so,
                              in its purest way: It is digital because it produces numbers; it is
                              also digital, etymologically, because you do it <emph>with your
                                    fingers</emph>.<note>I am very grateful to [reviewer 1] for the
                                    description of the hands-on recreation of the editing process in
                                    ELAN as a reverse-engineering scholarly experience, the
                                    underrated aspect of manual digital analysis in digital
                                    humanities and for stressing and reminding me of the
                                    etymological relation of <emph>with your fingers</emph> and
                                          <emph>digital</emph>.</note>
                        </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="appendix">
                        <head>Appendix</head>
                        <list>
                              <head>Links to Tools:</head>
                              <item><label>Advene</label>
                                    <ref target="https://www.advene.org/"
                                          >https://www.advene.org/</ref> [last consulted on November
                                    29th 2018].</item>
                              <item><label>Anvil</label>
                                    <ref target="http://www.anvil-software.org/"
                                          >http://www.anvil-software.org/</ref> [last consulted on
                                    November 29th 2018].</item>
                              <item><label>Cinemetrics</label>
                                    <ref target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv/index.php"
                                          >http://www.cinemetrics.lv/index.php</ref> [last consulted
                                    on February 6th 2017].</item>
                              <item><label>ELAN</label>
                                    <ref target="https://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/elan/"
                                          >https://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/elan/</ref> [last
                                    consulted on November 29th 2018].</item>
                              <item><label>ImageJ and ImageMontage</label>
                                    <ref
                                          target="http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2014/03/how-to-visualize-4512-instagram-selfies.html"
                                          >http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2014/03/how-to-visualize-4512-instagram-selfies.html</ref>
                                    [last consulted on July 20th 2018].</item>
                              <item><label>Lignes de temps</label>
                                    <ref
                                          target="https://www.iri.centrepompidou.fr/outils/lignes-de-temps/"
                                          >https://www.iri.centrepompidou.fr/outils/lignes-de-temps/</ref>
                                    [last consulted on November 29th 2018].</item>
                        </list>
                  </div>
            </body>
            <back>
                  <listBibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="altman1984" label="Altman 1984">Altman, R. <title
                                    rend="quotes">A Semantic/Syntactic Approach to Film
                                    Genre</title>, <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> 23, 3
                              (1984): 6-18.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="auge1995" label="Augé 1995">Augé, M. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Non-places: Introduction to an Anthropology of
                                    Supermodernity</title>. Verso, London (1995).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="balazs2010" label="Balázs 2010">Balázs, B. <title
                                    rend="quotes">The Spirit of Film</title>. In E. Carter (ed),
                                    <title rend="italic">Béla Balázs: Early Film Theory. <q>Visible
                                          Man</q> and <q>The Spirit of Film</q></title>, Berghahn
                              Books, New York, Oxford (2010), pp. 91-230.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="barsam1973" label="Barsam 1973">Barsam, R. <title
                                    rend="italic">Nonfiction Film. A critical History</title>. E.P.
                              Dutton, New York (1973).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="benjamin1999" label="Benjamin 1999">Benjamin, W. <title
                                    rend="italic">The Arcades Project</title>. Harvard University
                              Press, Cambridge (1999).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bollerey2014" label="Bollerey and Föhl 2014">Bollerey, F. and
                              A. Föhl (eds). <title rend="italic">City Symphonies. Film Manifestos
                                    of Urban Experiences. Eselsohren</title>. Journal of History of
                              Art, Architecture and Urbanism, 1+2 (2014).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bordwell2019" label="Bordwell and Thompson 2019">Bordwell, D.
                              and K. Thompson. <title rend="italic">Film History. An
                                    Introduction</title>. Fourth Edition. McGraw-Hill, New York
                              (2019).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="cowan2014" label="Cowan 2014">Cowan, M. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Walter Ruttmann and the Cinema of Multiplicity. Avant-Garde,
                                    Advertising, Modernity</title>. Amsterdam University Press,
                              Amsterdam (2014).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="dahne2013" label="Dähne 2013">Dähne, C. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Die Stadtsinfonien der 1920er Jahre. Architektur zwischen Film,
                                    Fotografie und Literatur</title>. Transcript, Bielefeld
                              (2013).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="grierson1933" label="Grierson 1933">Grierson, J. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Documentary (2): Symphonics</title>, <title
                                    rend="italic">Cinema Quarterly</title> 1, 3 (1933):
                              135-139.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="heftberger2016" label="Heftberger 2016">Heftberger, A. <title
                                    rend="italic">Kollision der Kader. Dziga Vertovs Filme, die
                                    Visualisierung ihrer Strukturen und die Digital
                                    Humanities</title>. Edition Text + Kritik, Munich (2016).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="hielscher2018" label="Hielscher 2018">Hielscher, E. <title
                                    rend="italic">Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography,
                                    Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony
                                    Films</title>. Ph.D. thesis, Ghent University (2018).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="horak1995" label="Horak 1995">Horak, J. <title rend="quotes"
                                    >The First American Film Avant-Garde, 1919-1945</title>. In J.
                              Horak (ed), <title rend="italic">Lovers of Cinema: The First American
                                    Film Avant-Garde, 1919-1945</title>, University of Wisconsin
                              Press, Madison (1995), pp. 14-66.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="jacobs1949" label="Jacobs 1949">Jacobs, L. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Avant-Garde Production in America</title>. In R.
                              Manvell (ed), <title rend="italic">Experiment in the Film</title>,
                              Grey Walls Press, London (1949), pp. 113-152.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="jacobs2016" label="Jacobs and Fyfe 2016">Jacobs, L. and K.
                              Fyfe. <title rend="quotes">Digital Tools for Film Analysis: Small
                                    Data</title>. In C. Acland and E. Hoyt (eds), <title
                                    rend="italic">The Arclight Guidebook to Media History and the
                                    Digital Humanities</title>, REFRAME Books, Falmer (2016), pp.
                              250-251.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="jacobs2018" label="Jacobs et al. 2018">Jacobs, S., A. Kinik,
                              and E. Hielscher (eds). <title rend="italic">The City Symphony
                                    Phenomenon. Cinema, Art, and Urban Modernity between the
                                    Wars</title>. Routledge, New York (2018).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="kinik2008" label="Kinik 2008">Kinik, A. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Dynamic of the Metropolis: The City Film and the Spaces of
                                    Modernity</title>. Ph.D. thesis, McGill University
                              (2008).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="koeck2010" label="Koeck and Roberts 2010">Koeck, R. and L.
                              Roberts (eds). <title rend="italic">The City and the Moving Image.
                                    Urban Projections</title>. Palgrave MacMillan, Basingstoke, New
                              York (2010).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="kolaja1965" label="Kolaja and Foster 1965">Kolaja, J. and A.
                              Foster. <title rend="quotes"><q>Berlin, the Symphony of a City</q> as
                                    a Theme of Visual Rhythm</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                                    Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</title> 23, 3 (1965):
                              353-358.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="kracauer1947" label="Kracauer 1947">Kracauer, S. <title
                                    rend="italic">From Caligari to Hitler. A Psychological History
                                    of the German Film</title>. Princeton University Press,
                              Princeton (1947).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="kracauer1960" label="Kracauer 1960">Kracauer, S. <title
                                    rend="italic">Theory of Film. The Redemption of Physical
                                    Reality</title>. Oxford University Press, New York
                              (1960).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="macdonald2001" label="MacDonald 2001">MacDonald, S. <title
                                    rend="italic">The Garden in the Machine. A Field Guide to
                                    Independent Films about Place</title>. University of California
                              Press, Berkeley, Los Angeles, London (2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="manovich2001" label="Manovich 2001">Manovich, L. <title
                                    rend="italic">The Language of New Media</title>. MIT press,
                              Cambridge (2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="manovich2013" label="Manovich 2013">Manovich, L. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Visualizing Vertov</title>. Manovich.net (2013).
                              Available at: <ref
                                    target="http://manovich.net/content/04-projects/078-visualizing-vertov/74_article_2013_sm.pdf"
                                    >http://manovich.net/content/04-projects/078-visualizing-vertov/74_article_2013_sm.pdf</ref>
                              [last consulted June 5, 2018].</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="mazierska2003" label="Mazierska and Rascaroli 2003">Mazierska,
                              E. and L. Rascaroli. <title rend="italic">From Moscow to Madrid.
                                    Postmodern Cities, European Cinema</title>. Tauris, London, New
                              York (2003).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="melgar2017" label="Melgar et al. 2017">Melgar, L., E.
                              Hielscher, M. Koolen, C. Olesen, J. Noordegraaf, and J. Blom. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Film Analysis as Annotation: Exploring current
                                    Tools and their Affordances</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                                    Moving Image</title>, Special Issue: Digital Humanities and/in
                              Film Archives, 2 (2017): 40-70.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="noguez1985" label="Noguez 1985">Noguez, D. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Paris – Moscou – Paris. Paris et les symphonies de
                                    ville</title>. In P. Hillairet, C. Lebrat and P. Rollet (eds),
                                    <title rend="italic">Paris vu par le cinéma d’avant-garde
                                    1923-1983</title>, Paris Expermental, Paris (1985), pp.
                              31-37.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="nowell-smith1997" label="Nowell-Smith 1997">Nowell-Smith, G.
                              (ed). <title rend="italic">The Oxford History of World Cinema</title>.
                              Oxford University Press, London (1997).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="olesen2017" label="Olesen 2017">Olesen, C. <title
                                    rend="italic">Film History in the Making. Film Historiography,
                                    Digitised Archives and Digital Research Dispositifs</title>.
                              Ph.D. thesis, University of Amsterdam (2017).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="roberts2000" label="Roberts 2000">Roberts, G. <title
                                    rend="italic">The Man with the Movie Camera</title>. Tauris,
                              London, New York (2000).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="rotha1936" label="Rotha 1936">Rotha, P. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Documentary Film</title>. Faber and Faber, London
                              (1936).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="simmel1997" label="Simmel 1997">Simmel, G. <title
                                    rend="quotes">The Metropolis and Mental Life [1903]</title>. In
                              D. Frisby and M. Featherstone (eds), <title rend="italic">Simmel on
                                    Culture. Selected Writings</title>, Thousand Oaks, London
                              (1997), pp. 174-185.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="tsivian2004" label="Tsivian 2004">Tsivian, Y. <title
                                    rend="quotes">Dziga Vertov and His Time</title>. In Y. Tsivian
                              (ed), <title rend="italic">Lines of Resistance: Dziga Vertov and the
                                    Twenties, Le Giornate del cinema muto</title>, Gemona, Udine
                              (2004), pp. 1-28.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="turvey2011" label="Turvey 2011">Turvey, M. <title
                                    rend="quotes">City Symphony and Man with a Movie Camera</title>.
                              In M. Turvey, <title rend="italic">The Filming of Modern Life.
                                    European Avant-Garde Film of the 1920s</title>, MIT Press,
                              Cambridge/Massachusetts (2011), pp. 135-162.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="uricchio1982" label="Uricchio 1982">Uricchio, W. <title
                                    rend="italic">Ruttmann's <q>Berlin</q> and the City Film to
                                    1930</title>. PhD dissertation. New York University, New York
                              (1982).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="vertov1984" label="Vertov 1984">Vertov, D. <title
                                    rend="quotes">From Kino-Eye to Radio-Eye</title>. In A.
                              Michelson (ed), <title rend="italic">Kino-Eye: The Writings of Dziga
                                    Vertov</title>, University of California Press, Berkeley (1984),
                              pp. 85-92.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="vogt2001" label="Vogt 2001">Vogt, G. <title rend="italic">Die
                                    Stadt im Film. Deutsche Spielfilme 1900-2000</title>. Schüren,
                              Marburg (2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="weihsmann1997" label="Weihsmann 1997">Weihsmann, H. <title
                                    rend="quotes">The City in Twilight. Charting the Genre of the
                                          <q>City Film</q> 1900-1930</title>. In F. Penz and M.
                              Thomas (eds), <title rend="italic">Cinema and Architecture. Méliès,
                                    Mallet-Stevens, Multimedia</title>, BFI, London (1997), pp.
                              8-27.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="weiss1995" label="Weiss 1995">Weiss, P. <title rend="italic"
                                    >Avantgarde Film</title>. Suhrkamp, Frankfurt (1995).</bibl>

                  </listBibl>
            </back>
      </text>
</TEI>
