<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors--><!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/NNNNNN/NNNNNN.xml">GitHub
        	   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title rend="italic">Case Study: Annotating the Ambiguous Modality of
						must in Jane Austen’s Emma</title>
            </head>
            <p>Prof. Dr. Angelika Zirker (Eberhard Karls University Tübingen)
					&amp; Michael Göggelmann, MA (Eberhard Karls University Tübingen / University of
					Cologne)</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="mailto:angelika.zirker@uni-tuebingen.de">angelika.zirker@uni-tuebingen.de</ref>
            </p>
            <p>michael.goeggelmann@uni-tuebingen.de</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>1. Introduction</head>
            <p>In the following, we will present a case study based on student annotations from
					a class on “Digital Methods in Literary Studies” taught in the English Studies /
					English Literatures and Cultures programme at Tübingen University.<note> The class was taught in the summer term of
							2022 for advanced students. Altogether, nineteen students took part in
							this seminar, most of them being enrolled in the BA English and American
							studies, the MA English Literatures and Cultures and the BEd / MEd
							English; three of the students were enrolled in the BA/MA programme
							International Literatures.</note> The annotation task consisted in
					tagging the ambiguous modality of <hi rend="italic">must</hi> in Jane Austen’s
					novel <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> (1816). We will first show how the criteria
					for analysis were developed on the basis of a close reading of the novel; these
					evolved into annotation guidelines which were then translated into tag sets for
					two annotation tools: CATMA and CorefAnnotator. We will present the overall
					results of the annotation process, with a particular focus on the difficulties
					that emerged as well as (patterns of) mistakes and misconceptions across the
					groups and individual annotators. This approach will yield insights into
					challenges when annotating with a group in a teaching context as well as
					foreground conceptual difficulties when it comes to annotating complex phenomena
					in literary texts. </p>
            <p>The motivation for this case study in a student group was two-fold: the main aim
					consisted in introducing students to tools and methods of annotation that are
					applicable in literary analysis. This objective is intricately linked to the
					problem that literary analysis in general frequently relies very much on
					intuitions that are difficult to be tested and verified. Category-based
					approaches and methods from the Digital Humanities may help make the analysis of
					literary texts more plausible and empirically sound (see also
					Pagel/Reiter/Rösinger/Schulz 2020). It is the markup of texts through annotation
					in particular that requires phenomenon-based distinctions and clear definitions
					in order to arrive at (fine-grained) categories of analysis. The starting point
					is a particular reading experience and text observation that leads to a first
					hypothesis with regard to the text phenomenon or feature under discussion, from
					which categories of investigation are then developed. Once these analytical
					categories are applied in the annotation process, they (potentially) undergo a
					revision process that then feed into the next round of annotations and so forth
					(see Gius/Jacke 2017). </p>
            <p>The second aim is motivated by a textual phenomenon
					in Jane Austen’s novel <term>Emma</term>, namely the ambiguity of
					voice which is related to an ambiguity of attribution:<note>
							Parts of the literary background presented in what follows were
							presented at the conference “Ambiguity Matters”, organized by RTG 1808
							“Ambiguity: Production and Perception” at Tübingen University, in a
							joint paper by Michael Reid and Angelika Zirker on “Ambiguity of Voice:
							From Mr Knightley to the Green Knight”. </note> this means that,
					throughout the novel, it often remains unclear whose voice we are being
					presented with as readers, while there is a defined set of options, e.g. a
					narrator and a character in the fiction. This is to say that the attribution of
					voice is not merely underspecified or vague nor without clear referents (see
					more on this in subsection 2. below).<note> When we speak of
							voice, in itself a notoriously underspecified term, we refer to whoever
							speaks or to whom an utterance or thought is attributed in a fictional
							text. With this notion, we go slightly beyond what is customarily
							regarded as voice, i.e. the “persona […] behind […] the first-person
							narrator” (Abrams/Harpham 2015: 287), but rather think of it in terms of
							the origin(ator) of an utterance or thought, be it on the level of
							character or narration; in short, “the relationship between a
							character’s thoughts – his or her internal voice – and the voice of the
							narrator” (Davidson 2008: 237). This comparative openness is helpful
							particularly when it comes to ambiguity, e.g. on the level of character
							thoughts and speech. The concept of “voice,” especially in the context
							of ambiguity, has often been linked to Ducrot’s notion of polyphony
							(Ducrot 1984; see also Waltereit 2006: 63; and Bauer 2015:
						149).</note> This ambiguity is linked to the ambiguity of the modal <term>must</term>. The annotation
					of all instances of <term>must</term> in the text will hence not
					only reveal its overall distribution across the novel but, more specifically,
					indicate how the ambiguity of its modality interacts with ambiguities of voice.
					The expectation is that this approach will moreover yield results relating to
					how voice is ambiguous with regard to the narrator and particular characters,
					e.g. if the ambiguity of voice in the narrator cooccurs more frequently with a
					particular character than with others. As occurrences of <term>must</term> are also annotated in direct speech, it will moreover be possible
					to see if there are characters that use <term>must</term> more often
					than others (as well as in which ways). The results of the annotations will
					then, in turn, feed into the qualitative analysis and interpretation of the
					novel and its very peculiar narrative techniques. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Literary/Narratological Background: Ambiguous Voice in Jane Austen’s <title rend="italic">Emma</title>
            </head>
            <p>From early on in Jane Austen’s novel, the ambiguity of voice is made obvious: it
					is unclear who the originating voice of an utterance in the diegetic mode is,
					i.e. who a proposition can be attributed to. An example is provided in (1):</p>
            <list rend="numbered">
               <item>How was she to bear the change? — It was true that
							her friend was going only half a mile from them; but Emma was aware that
							great must be the difference between a Mrs. Weston, only half a mile
							from them, and a Miss Taylor in the house; and with all her advantages,
							natural and domestic, she was now in great danger of suffering from
							intellectual solitude. She dearly loved her father, but he was no
							companion for her. He could not meet her in conversation, rational or
							playful. (Austen 2012: 6)</item>
            </list>
            <p>The context is as follows: Emma, the protagonist of the novel, introduced as
					“handsome, clever and rich” (5) in its first sentence, has formed a bond of
					friendship with her governess Miss Taylor, who, after many years in the
					Woodhouse household, has married and moved house within the neighbourhood to
					live with her husband, Mr. Weston. In connection with the opening question of
					the paragraph – which may be asked by the narrator or be an instance of Free
					Indirect Discourse (FID)<note> Oberman refers to Cohn’s term “narrated
							monologue” (Oberman 2009: 109-10) in the context of <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> and considers the term to be “more specific” than FID
							(2n2); see also Pollack-Pelzner (2013: 766). Bray notes that, in the
							context of FID, “point of view can be hard to determine and ambiguous”
							(Bray 2007: 37). – According to Genette, the explanation is of course
							that this is a case of (uncertain) focalization. Interestingly, the
							distinction introduced by Genette between who speaks and who sees does
							not consider that there may be a difference of voice in FID, where the
							character’s language is used (Genette 1980: 186).</note> – it is
					unclear who thinks that “great must be the difference”: is this Emma or the
					omniscient narrator with access to her thoughts and feelings – or both?<note> See, e.g.,
							Oberman who writes: “In third-person narrated novels that dip in and out
							of the consciousnesses of multiple characters, there are usually moments
							when it is not easy to know for sure whether the voice we are hearing
							belongs to the narrator or to a character in the novel” (2009:
						1).</note> The question in this passage is an epistemic one and,
					depending on how we interpret it, we may arrive at different readings: If we
					attribute it to the narrator’s voice, Emma is objectively suffering from
					solitude. If we assume that we are presented with Emma’s thoughts, we learn that
					she regards herself as lonely. The effect based on the author’s strategy is
					clear: we as readers are supposed to pity her in any case, either because of her
					feeling or because of the state she factually finds herself in. </p>
            <p>These reflections on or by Emma are continued as follows in the opening chapter: </p>
            <list rend="numbered">
               <item>Her sister, though comparatively but little
							removed by matrimony, being settled in London, only sixteen miles off,
							was much beyond her daily reach; and many a long October and November
							evening must be struggled through at Hartfield, before Christmas brought
							the next visit […]. (Austen 2012: 6)</item>
            </list>
            <p>Again, it is unclear whether this is a narratorial statement or Emma’s thoughts
					that are being presented. If we look closely, however, we can see that there is
					a second ambiguity involved, potentially interacting with the ambiguity of
					voice: that of the modal verb <term>must</term>. Generally speaking,
						<term>must</term> may be epistemic, deontic or bouletic, i.e.
					express a fact, an obligation/necessity or a wish (see Fintel 2006). In this
					instance (2), <term>must</term> is epistemic as it is a fact that
					evenings are a struggle in the months of autumn with few visitors before
					Christmas; but it is also deontic as these evenings have to be struggled through
					by necessity. This reading is in line with her father having just been presented
					as being no companion to her; but to avoid interaction with him altogether is
					not an option either: he “made it <term>necessary</term> to be
					cheerful” (7; emphasis added), as the narrative continues to point out. </p>
            <p>Throughout the novel, the “narrative voice that dips in and out of her heroine’s
					thoughts, fusing Emma’s subjectivity (e.g. in the sense of her limited
					knowledge) to the narrator’s omniscience” (Oberman 2009: 2), a narrative device
					that has frequently been noted and commented on in the literature on Jane
						Austen.<note> What
							is particularly tricky: there may even be an added ambiguity as we do
							not always know whether the narrator is heterodiegetic or homodiegetic.
							Does the narrator “create” the characters (and, accordingly, is
							omniscient), or does the narrator “look” at them (on the basis of her
							limited knowledge)?</note> The concrete linguistic makeup behind
					this ambiguity of voice has been left widely unobserved, and our hypothesis is
					that it is intricately linked to the ambiguity of the modal <term>must</term>. Jane Austen regularly uses this ambiguity, and most famously so
					in the first sentence of her novel <term>Pride and Prejudice</term>: </p>
            <list rend="numbered">
               <item>It is a truth universally acknowledged, that a man
							in possession of a good fortune, must be in want of a wife. (Austen
							1998: 1)</item>
            </list>
            <p>In this instance, the modal <term>must</term> is ambiguous, too: a man in possession of a good fortune is
					generally in want of a wife, he is obliged to be so, and someone may wish this.
					The question is: whose thoughts are these? If we begin to disambiguate <term>must</term> here, we come up with different originating voices
					behind the utterance, with Mrs Bennet being its main originator as her most
					prominent objective in life is to see her five daughters married as much as the
					“communal voice” (Oberman 2009: 9) behind the “truth universally
					acknowledged”.</p>
            <p>To return to <term>Emma</term>.</p>
            <p>As there are altogether 571 occurrences of <term>must</term> in the novel,<note> The novel
							consists of altogether 160,310 words and is structured into three
							volumes, with 18 chapters in each, volumes one and two, and 19 chapters
							in volume three. </note> it makes sense to use annotation to learn
					more about these ambiguities and how they are distributed over the novel – as
					well as how they behave in relation to the various characters and the narrator’s
					voice. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Case Study</head>
            <p>The students in the class on digital methods were
					asked to annotate all instances of <term>must</term> in Jane
					Austen’s novel <term>Emma</term>, on the basis of annotation
					guidelines provided by their instructor. In what follows, the method will be
					introduced briefly (3.1), followed by an introduction of the annotation
					guidelines (3.2) and an analysis (4) of the annotations generated by the
					students over the course of term. </p>
            <div>
               <head>3.1 Method</head>
               <p>The analysis of the ambiguous modality of <term>must</term> in
						relation to the ambiguity of voice in Jane Austen’s novel is a particularly
						apt test case for the application of categories for text analysis.
						Annotation guidelines were developed from a close reading of the novel that
						were then translated into a tag set which covers all the text features
						resulting in the various ambiguities under discussion. </p>
               <p>The approach is interdisciplinary to begin with and thus exemplifies the
						complexity of categories in text analysis: in order to succinctly describe
						the phenomenon this case study is concerned with, linguistic knowhow is
						needed to conceptualize and use definitions; this approach supports a
						“precise and detailed analysis of a text, unaffected by arbitrary
						interpretations or conjectures” (Bauer/Beck et al. 2020: 1). This approach
						is not meant to reassert “somewhat simplistic binaries between (objective)
						analysis and (subjective) interpretations”, as one of the reviewers of this
						paper put it<note>
								We would like to thank the reviewer for pointing out this possible
								misunderstanding. </note>; the contrary is the case: with our
						category-based approach we want to go against the assumption that
						interpretations are “subjective”. In our understanding, a detailed analysis
						of the text leads to equally objective interpretations that are
							text-based.<note> For some more insight into this approach, see
								e.g. Bauer/Beck et al. 2020 and Bauer/Brockmann 2017.</note> The
						case study, based on the link between the ambiguity of modal verbs (a
						primarily linguistic issue) and of voice (related to narratology) and with
						the help of tools from Digital Humanities that allow for a quantitative
						analysis, accordingly had the pedagogical aim to exemplify how an informed
						analysis may feed into a text-based interpretation. The chosen
						operationalization can be amplified as well as transferred to other texts
						(prose fiction) and corpora. </p>
               <p>The use of both CATMA and CorefAnnotator was meant to introduce the group to
						two tools that are available open access and can be applied in teaching,
						e.g. in a school context, as many of the students are enrolled in the BEd or
						MEd programmes. We also wanted to find out if the use of a particular tool
						leads to particular mistakes or is more manageable for students so far
						unacquainted with digital methods. After a general introduction, students
						were free to choose the tool they wanted to work with. Six students chose
						CATMA, divided into two groups of three students each; 13 students worked
						with CorefAnnotator, divided into three groups of three students each and
						one group of four.<note> In hindsight, it
								may have been more sensible not to leave the choice of the tools to
								the students but form identical groups for each of the tools to make
								the analysis more comparable. At the same time, the group division
								as it stands has resulted in some intriguing insights as well (see
								below).</note> All groups were asked to annotate at least the
						first chapter to catch misconceptions in annotating early on in the process;
						each group was then asked to annotate a particular ‘package’ of chapters
						within the text:</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Annotated volumes and chapters per group and tool</head>
                  <graphic url=""/>
               </figure>
               <p>All members of the groups were supposed to annotate individually at
						first and to then sit down together to discuss their annotations within
						their work packages: this was to result in peer discussions to foster a
						process of understanding in the course of which the annotations would
						improve and require less discussion as the students went on annotating.
						Because of the uneven distribution of students over tools, work packages
						were designed in a way that at least two groups working with CorefAnnotator
						would (largely) overlap with the CATMA groups in the material they
						annotated, namely CATMA A with Coref A and B, as well as CATMA B with Coref
						C and D. The respective annotation groups were asked not only to discuss
						their individual annotations but agree on a group result to be submitted as
						their joint annotations for which there was consensus within the group.
						Unfortunately, this was only done by the groups working with CorefAnnotator:
						that the students working with CATMA (apparently) never went through this
						internal negotiation and discussion nor came up with annotations they had
						agreed on; this, however, only came to light at the end of term when further
						revisions were no longer possible (see below, subsection 4.). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.2 Annotation Guidelines</head>
               <p>The textual observations relating to ambiguity
						as described above (subsection 2.) were translated into annotation
						guidelines (see Appendix 1), with the task to tag and markup all instances
						of the modal verb <term>must</term> in the novel, based on the
						assumption that it may be used ambiguously. The “Preliminaries and
						Theoretical Background” in the annotation guidelines point to the ambiguous
						modality of <term>must</term>, including examples taken from
						linguistic literature on the topic (Fintel 2006); a literary example from
						Jane Austen’s novel <term>Pride and Prejudice</term> is also
						provided (see above, example (2)). The Annotation Guidelines proper were
						updated in the course of term, based on feedback from the students in their
						annotation process. They specified, for instance, that all instances of <term>must</term> in direct speech have to be annotated as well
						in order to learn more about the overall distribution of the modal verb in
						the novel as a whole (e.g. the question if it occurs particularly often in
						the speech of a particular character, but also to see clusters of the modal
						verb and identify chapters in which it is mentioned more frequently than in
						others etc.). For characters, the tags “speaker” and “focalizer” were hence
						introduced to specify the occurrence of <term>must</term>; as
						the notion of “focalization” is generally better known to students (in
						Germany) than “voice,” this term made its way into the annotation
							guidelines.<note> The notion of “voice” was not even addressed
								in more detail because of that. We still think, however, that it
								makes sense, on some level, to distinguish “voice”, as “an utterance
								or thought” (see above, n3) attributed to a character goes beyond
								Genette’s rather simplistic “who sees”, especially when it comes to
								ambiguities of voice between characters and the narrator (see also
								n11 on his matter). </note> By default, the “narrator” should
						always be tagged as “speaker”.<note> This follows the
								view, expressed, for example, by Margolin (2014), that “the term
								‘narrator’ designates the inner-textual (textually encoded)
								highest-level speech position from which the
								current narrative discourse as a whole originates” (para 1, emphasis
								added).</note> Students were then asked to follow these steps
						when annotating: </p>
               <list rend="numbered">
                  <item>Identify / search for all instances of <term>must</term>.</item>
                  <item>Read the context of each mention.</item>
                  <item>Identify who is speaking or thinking the sentence in which <term>must</term> occurs.</item>
                  <item>Annotate who the speaker or focalizer is by marking <term>must</term> and attributing a character as speaker or
							as focalizer. </item>
                  <item>If several options are possible for focalization (e.g. several
							characters), annotate all of them as in (iv). </item>
                  <item>Is <term>must</term> epistemic – deontic – bouletic? If
							several modalities apply, annotate <term>must</term>
							accordingly.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Another update of the guidelines consisted in
						the addition of an FAQs section (see below, Appendix 1), specifying issues
						that were addressed in discussions about the annotations. Overall, the
						approach was one of maximal annotation: if a student or a student group were
						uncertain as to the meaning of <term>must</term>, they were
						asked to annotate all possibilities rather than disambiguate the instance.
					</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. Analysis</head>
            <p>The overall aim was to learn more about how the ambiguous modal <term>must</term> “behaves” in the novel, i.e. if particular
					patterns can be identified, especially with regard to the ambiguity of voice. In
					the course of annotating, however, quite a number of challenges have cropped up
					as this analysis will show. A major problem was the wrong assumption by some
					students in the group that annotating a literary work makes reading the novel
					superfluous. Attributions hence become difficult as contexts within the text
					remain obscure; put in a more positive way: students have learned about the
					importance of context in the process.<note> There was a number of students who made this
							wrong assumption, especially in the CATMA groups – but this became
							obvious only fairly late in the term (although the reading of the novel
							had been marked as “mandatory” in the course description).</note> In
					a next step, a gold standard would have to be developed to compare the student
					annotations with, in order to identify all deviations. </p>
            <p>In our analysis of the annotations, we have been able to identify technical flaws
					(4.1) as well as conceptual difficulties (4.2). </p>
            <div>
               <head>4.1 Technical Flaws</head>
               <p>As we were interested in finding out whether the work with a particular tool
						led to specific mistakes, we compared technical flaws between the groups.
						Particular mistakes indeed cropped up only in the context of either of the
						tools and could lead, for instance, to a lower inter annotator agreement
							(IAA)<note> In our analysis we have therefore
								corrected careless mistakes as shown in Table 2.</note>:</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Technical flaws in annotations: a comparison of the tools</head>
                  <graphic url=""/>
               </figure>
               <p>While the exclusivity with which the errors
						occur for one of the tools suggests an explanation in the nature of the tool
						concerned, we cannot claim this with certainty in <term>all</term> cases, especially since some errors can rather be attributed
						to the respective users. This, for example, is apparent for the 224
						annotations of spaces following the annotated item in CATMA: a closer look
						reveals that the majority of these annotations were made by the same student
						– which, because of this regularity, must be interpreted less as an
						oversight induced by the tool than an intentional procedure. The complete
						absence of such errors for the CorefAnnotator, by contrast, can be easily
						explained: it offers a feature that is activated by default and ignores the
						annotation of spaces at the outer borders of annotated items. The same
						applies to non-annotated letters in words as a corresponding feature
						prevents the annotation of incomplete tokens. In our case, these features
						automatically protected the annotators of the CorefAnnotator groups from
						both accidental errors and intentional actions that turned out to be
							mistakes.<note> It should be
								noted, however, that, whenever these rules should hinder the
								annotation process (e.g. when only parts of a token are to be
								annotated), they can be switched off.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The errors that relate to tags, such as the forgotten annotation of a
						category, typos in the introduction of new tags for characters that added to
						the cast in the course of the narrative and alternative names for tags (e.g.
						“Mr. Knightley” or “Mr Knightley” or “John Knightley”), accumulate
						conspicuously with the CorefAnnotator, while CATMA shows almost no
						vulnerability to these types of error in almost inverse exclusivity. This
						accumulation of errors in tag names may be explained by an intentionally
						different configuration of the two tools: in CorefAnnotator tags could be
						added flexibly by the annotators themselves whereas all tags were fixed in
						CATMA beforehand; this configuration may always be an issue when it comes to
						using these tools in class: students must apparently be expected to generate
						mistakes at these points. The evaluations clearly show that – especially for
						inexperienced annotators – an annotation environment that is as restrictive
						as possible produces more reliable results. Formal aspects such as these
						should accordingly be integrated into the annotation guidelines.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>4.2 Misconceptions, Misreadings and Challenges</head>
               <p>It was agreed that, to get started and become aware of possible pitfalls and
						difficulties in annotating, all groups would annotate at least chapter one
						of the novel; in the case of the groups using CorefAnnotator, three of them
						annotated chapters one to three, while group D did not finally submit their
						annotations of chapter 1 (without giving a reason). The agreements and
						divergences across the groups yield insights into conceptual mistakes as
						well as (partly insurmountable) challenges while annotating; they, however,
						also point to complexities in the task itself that are revealing with regard
						to the nature of the phenomenon under consideration.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>4.2.1 The First Instance of must: Insights and Hypotheses</head>
                  <p>The comparison of the annotations for the
							first instance of <term>must</term> (see above, example (1))
							is revealing in respect of the annotating process within the groups. On
							the basis of this analysis, we eventually decided not to consider the
							results from the CATMA groups as we saw that the divergences here are
							mainly based on the wrong application of the annotation guidelines as
							well as partly inexplicable gaps in the annotations.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>�unable to handle picture
										here, no embed or linkAnnotatorsAnnotation
								CategoriesAnnotations for the first instance of must by the CATMA groups</head>
                     <graphic url=""/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>It becomes obvious that two students did not
							annotate <term>must</term> in this instance at all. We do
							not know if this was because of an oversight (despite the advice to use
							the search function) or for another reason. We can also see that the
							remaining students did not take the ambiguity of the figure uttering
							<term>must </term>into account: only
							student 3 from group B saw that. But then, all students ignored the
							default rule that the narrator is always given the role of “speaker”. </p>
                  <p>�<note>unable to handle picture of Windows format
									media/image1.emf</note>Annotators�<note>unable to handle picture of Windows format
									media/image1.emf</note>�<note>unable to handle picture here, no embed or
									link</note>A comparison of the annotations provided by
							those three CorefAnnotator groups that submitted their annotations for
							the first chapter and example (1), by contrast, helps develop a few
							hypotheses as to the difficulties in annotating the ambiguity of voice
							and <term>must</term> in the novel: </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotations for the first instance of must
								by the CorefAnnotator groups</head>
                     <graphic url=""/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>All groups agree in their attribution of the
							figures and roles of the instance of <term>must</term>: both
							Emma Woodhouse and the Narrator are possible originators of the
							utterance. The divergence sets in with the modality of must for each of
							them: groups A and B only attributed one modality to Emma and the
							Narrator but differed with regard to the attribution as either deontic
							or epistemic, whereas group C attributed both to each of the speakers.
							If we go back to the text passage, we can analyse this instance in more
							detail:</p>
                  <list rend="numbered">
                     <item>How was she to bear the change? — It was
									true that her friend was going only half a mile from them; but
									Emma was aware that great must be the difference between a Mrs.
									Weston, only half a mile from them, and a Miss Taylor in the
									house; and with all her advantages, natural and domestic, she
									was now in great danger of suffering from intellectual solitude.
									She dearly loved her father, but he was no companion for her. He
									could not meet her in conversation, rational or playful.
									(6)</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>We found earlier that the attribution leads to different readings: the
							narrator’s voice states that Emma is objectively suffering from
							solitude; in the case of a presentation of Emma’s thoughts, we learn
							that she regards herself as lonely. It is obvious that this is neither
							an expression of a wish (bouletic reading) nor of a necessity (deontic)
							but of a fact (epistemic). The deontic reading becomes possible,
							however, with regard to the greatness of the difference between the two
							identities of Miss Taylor and Mrs. Weston in their respective locations.
							From Emma’s perspective, this makes sense as a necessary outcome of the
							change, and the narrator could be ironical in presenting the change as
							such. This reading makes sense in the context of Emma’s introduction as
							a character:</p>
                  <list rend="numbered">
                     <item>The real evils indeed of Emma’s situation
									were the power of having rather too much her own way, and a
									disposition to think a little too well of herself; (Austen 2012:
									5)</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>In her view, any change of situation <term>must</term> be great, especially if she cannot have
							“her own way”; a fact that the narrator ironically takes into account as
							well. Against this background, one may assume that both readings of <term>must</term> go for both Emma and the narrator. The
							difficulty in arriving at this rather complicated interpretation is
							reflected in the varying disambiguations between groups A and B: their
							readings are merged by group C who identify an ambiguity for both Emma
							and the narrator. Based on this observation, we assume that the modality
							of <term>must</term> will prove to be the most difficult
							annotation task and lead to the greatest variety in annotations across
							the CorefAnnotator groups. As to the reasons for this difficulty, we can
							only speculate, but there are some indicators that it is extremely
							difficult for students to assume multiple meanings for the modal verb
							that is so much part of our everyday communication.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>4.2.2 Mistakes Exclusive to CATMA </head>
                  <p>Before altogether discarding the CATMA
							groups (see 4.2.1), we went on to compare all annotated instances of <term>must</term> for all groups who annotated identical
							chapters within volumes one and three with all actual instances in the
							novel (see Figures 1 and 2). The golden line represents all instances of
								<term>must</term> in all chapters and includes those
							that were annotated correctly; the individual diverging lines show the
							number of annotations that do not overlap with the instances. </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotated instances of
								must for Volume 1 The individual Students listed
										here were all in CATMA group A, hence Ca-A etc., and have
										been numbered randomly in the course of anonymisation. Graph
										2 refers to CATMA group B (Ca-B) who annotated volume 3 of
										the novel.</head>
                     <graphic url="media/image2.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->Line diagram showing the actually annotated
							instances of must per group and chapter of Volume 1 - and where these
							deviate from the actual number of instances per chapter.Line diagram showing the actually annotated
							instances of must per group and chapter of Volume 1 - and where these
							deviate from the actual number of instances per chapter.</figDesc>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->Line diagram showing the actually annotated instances
							of must per group and chapter of Volume 3 - and where these deviate from
							the actual number of instances per chapter.Line diagram showing the actually annotated instances
							of must per group and chapter of Volume 3 - and where these deviate from
							the actual number of instances per chapter.</figDesc>
                  <p>The annotated chapters of the novel contain altogether 323 mentions of
								<term>must</term>. Figure 1 shows that the
							CorefAnnotator groups<note> Whenever the
									diagrams refer to CorefAnnotator in general, the corresponding
									quantities include the numbers of those groups that were
									involved in the annotation of the chapters to be
								compared.</note> caught all instances of <term>must</term>, and so did student 2 in CATMA; student 1 in CATMA has
							one divergence, whereas student 3 has several. In Figure 2, the
							divergences are more striking: while, once again, the CorefAnnotator
							group annotated all instances of <term>must</term>, CATMA
							student 1 apparently stopped annotating altogether after chapters 6 and
							7, and so did student 3 after chapter 16. This was not communicated in
							any way, and it hence remains unclear whether the task simply appeared
							to be unmanageable for reasons of content or workload.<note> The latter was
									certainly an issue: although there were full sessions dedicated
									to annotating the text and there were no oral presentations that
									students had to prepare other than to present their results, the
									students found the class demanding and annotation time-consuming
									(beyond what is usually expected of them in terms of class
									work).</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Because of the divergences so far and an apparent tendency within the
							CATMA groups (see Table 3) not to annotate ambiguities, we in a next
							step compared the number of annotations per group and chapter within the
							first and third volumes. The golden line in Figure 3 once again shows
							the actual number of instances (as in Figures 1 and 2 above), and the
							individual bars indicate annotations of ambiguity as they exceed the
							number of instances of <term>must</term> in the text: the
							double annotations underlying this representation result from the
							ambiguity of “figure” rather than the ambiguity of modality, i.e.
							whenever it is unclear in the text whether a character or the narrator
							is the originator of an utterance, an annotation ensues for each of
							them. The divergences, once again, allow for a comparison between the
							groups. </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotations per instance of
								must for Volume 1</head>
                     <graphic url="media/image4.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->Bar chart showing for each chapter of Volume 1 how
							many annotations were made for each instance of <hi rend="italic">must</hi> by each group. A golden line running through the chart
							indicates how many annotations had actually to be made.Bar chart showing for each chapter of Volume 1 how
							many annotations were made for each instance of <hi rend="italic">must</hi> by each group. A golden line running through the chart
							indicates how many annotations had actually to be made.</figDesc>
                  <p>The graph shows that over the 156 mentions of <term>must</term> in the first volume of the novel, the CorefAnnotator
							group has 258 annotations whereas the students working with CATMA have
							190 (Student 1), 166 (Student 2) and 179 (Student 3). This means that
							they perceived a few ambiguities but far less altogether than the
							CorefAnnotator group whose annotations are based on in-group discussions
							and agreement.</p>
                  <p>The figure for Volume 3 presents a similar result: </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotations per instance of must for Volume 3</head>
                     <graphic url="media/image5.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->Bar chart showing for each chapter of Volume 3 how
							many annotations were made for each instance of <hi rend="italic">must</hi> by each group. A golden line running through the chart
							indicates how many annotations had actually to be made.Bar chart showing for each chapter of Volume 3 how
							many annotations were made for each instance of <hi rend="italic">must</hi> by each group. A golden line running through the chart
							indicates how many annotations had actually to be made.</figDesc>
                  <p>Over 167 instances of <term>must</term>, the CorefAnnotator
							group identified quite a number of ambiguities, with 243 annotations; as
							students 1 and 3 in the CATMA group stopped annotating at some point
							(see above), there are only 22 annotations for chapters six and seven by
							student 1 and 154 for student 3; student 2, however, has almost as many
							annotations as the CorefAnnotator group and overall appears to have
							worked much more reliably (at least on a quantitative basis). </p>
                  <p>The following figure summarizes the divergences between the annotations
							within the group who annotated with CATMA.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Distribution of annotations within CATMA groups for Volumes 1 and
								3</head>
                     <graphic url="media/image6.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->The bar chart shows the number of annotations made by
							each student within the CATMA groups.The bar chart shows the number of annotations made by
							each student within the CATMA groups.</figDesc>
                  <p>This graph shows once more the diverging number of annotations among the
							students in the CATMA groups over all annotated chapters: it makes
							evident that no negotiation has taken place within the groups with
							regard to individual annotations.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>4.2.3 Annotating the Ambiguity of Modality</head>
                  <p>To come back to the first instance of <term>must</term> in
							the novel (example (1)) and the annotations as compared in Table 2
							(CorefAnnotator group): overall, the ambiguity of figure and role did
							not lead to any disagreement between the groups; the major difficulty
							appeared to be the ambiguity of modality, an impression that came up in
							class discussions as well. It makes sense to test this hypothesis in
							light of the data and compare the annotations of the three groups who
							worked on chapters one to three as a warmup exercise. </p>
                  <p>In these opening chapters of the novel, <term>must</term> is
							mentioned 22 times.<note> To clarify the instances,
									especially for the following individual examples, we have
									counted and named them in the order of their appearance within
									those first three chapters of the novel.</note> We have
							calculated the pairwise agreement for the first annotation category
							“figure” for all instances of <term>must</term> in the first
							three chapters and added them up. The pairwise agreement for an instance
							is “3” if all groups agree on a “figure” (A agrees with B, B agrees with
							C, A agrees with C) and “1” if at least two of the three groups agree.
							We then investigated whether and to what extent the pairwise agreement
							decreases if it is checked for an instance where the three groups agree
							in “figure” <term>and</term> “role”, and in a final step in
							“figure”, “role” <term>and</term> “modality”.<note> While
									one might argue that there cannot be a difference between
									“figure” and “role,” in some of the annotations, wrong
									attributions could be found. One can also regard the split task
									between identifying a character and their respective role as a
									speaker or focalizer as a control task regarding the
									attentiveness of the annotators.</note> The maximum pairwise
							agreement for 22 instances accordingly is 66. The result confirms our
							assumption that the ambiguity of modality has been most difficult to
							annotate. </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Loss of total pairwise agreements of groups A-C per annotation
								step</head>
                     <graphic url="media/image7.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc><!--If this figDesc is invalid, move it into the nearest figure element-->The bar chart shows the change in pairwise agreement
							of the groups with the inclusion of annotation stepsThe bar chart shows the change in pairwise agreement
							of the groups with the inclusion of annotation steps</figDesc>
                  <p>The pairwise agreements for “figure” as well as “figure and role” are
							comparatively high. It is particularly noteworthy that the inclusion of
							the “role” annotation category (i.e. the identification of focalizer and
							speaker) did not result in any loss of agreement over all instances and
							groups; if there was agreement about the figure in the first place, it
							remained stable concerning its role as focalizer or speaker. Existing
							correlations between figures and roles were thus clearly recognised by
							the students: the narrator is, for example, <term>always</term> identified as “speaker”. The divergence, however, with
							regard to modality is striking: no inferences are possible, and no
							(conceptual) links appear to exist between a modality and a figure/role. </p>
                  <p>While the ambiguity of modality is most difficult to annotate, figure and
							role attributions are apparently (more) straightforward, potentially so
							because one can to some extent be derived from the other, and they
							require a lesser degree of interpretation. This finding is also
							confirmed when looking at the Fleiss Kappa values for inter annotator
							agreement (IAA) of each annotation category, especially since figure and
							role score significantly better with ĸ = 0,67 and ĸ = 0,5 than the
							category of modality, which is clearly inferior with ĸ = 0,16.<note>
									Following the widely used evaluation rankings by Landis/Koch
									(1977), the κ value for figure would qualify as “good
									agreement”, while role would still be considered a “moderate
									agreement”; unlike modality, which scores lowest possible as a
									“poor agreement”.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>At this point, it makes sense to have a
							closer look at some of the annotations to see what happens exactly
							between the groups with regard to the annotation of all categories. One
							of the following mentions of <term>must</term> also occurs
							in the first chapter, when Emma and her father discuss visiting the
							former governess at her new home:</p>
                  <list rend="numbered">
                     <item>“How often we shall be going to see them
									and they coming to see us! — We shall be always meeting! We must
									begin, we must go and pay our wedding-visit very soon.” (Austen
									2012: 7)</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>�<note>unable to handle picture here, no embed or
									link</note>AnnotatorsAnnotation CategoriesThe speaker of
							this utterance unanimously is Emma – there are no problems whatsoever at
							annotating this passage accordingly. </p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotations for instance 3 of must by the
								Coref groups</head>
                     <graphic url=""/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>A difficulty arises, however, once again when it comes to determining the
							modality of <term>must</term>; given the text and its
							context, one may argue that group C is correct here: Emma, first and
							foremost, voices an obligation, even a self-command, based on their
							social standing (a reading also considered by group A): they “must” make
							the visit because of that. She clearly also wishes to see her friend
							soon and as often as possible. To regard her statement as epistemic is
							more difficult as “begin” denotes a future event and hence cannot count
							as the perception of a known fact. </p>
                  <p>A third passage shows yet another difficulty in annotating <term>must</term>: in chapter two, the reader is introduced
							to the Westons in more detail and given some background information
							about Mr. Weston’s prior marriage:</p>
                  <list rend="numbered">
                     <item>It was now some time since Miss Taylor had
									begun to influence his schemes; […] He had made his fortune,
									bought his house, and obtained his wife; and was beginning a new
									period of existence with every probability of greater happiness
									than in any yet passed through. He had never been an unhappy
									man; his own temper had secured him from that, even in his first
									marriage; but his second must shew him how delightful a
									well-judging and truly amiable woman could be, […] (Austen 2012:
									13)</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>It is unclear whether this is merely the narrator reporting Mr. Weston’s
							thoughts and feelings – or whether we are presented with Mr. Weston’s
							view in his voice: both are possible and cannot be decided in favour of
							the one or the other reading. The students, however, very much diverged
							in their reading of this passage.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Annotations for instance 17 of must by the
								CorefAnnotator groups</head>
                     <graphic url=""/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The table shows that group B did not recognize the ambiguity of the
							figure here. The other groups diverge with regard to their
							interpretation of the modalities: they disagree between an epistemic
							reading of the narrator’s <term>must</term> in two cases,
							deontic and epistemic in one case, and they attribute Mr. Weston with
							deontic and either bouletic or epistemic.<note>
									Here an epistemic reading, though referring to a
										future event, works because it refers to a generally known
										fact (the assumption that second marriages are happier after
										a disappointing first one).</note> If we look at
							the text, the narrator may very well also be read as being deontic, but
							this only works in a meta-narrative reading with her being the law-giver
							of the narrative in her (slightly ironic) appreciation of Mr. Weston’s
							thoughts and prospects as well as expectations of married life – and
							wish him well in a bouletic reading. Mr. Weston himself probably wishes
							for a happy marriage as much as he counts it for a fact, given the
							qualities of his wife as he has come to know her, and thinks that he is
							somewhat entitled to it as he “had never been an unhappy man”. This
							analysis also foregrounds, once again, that to have read the novel and
							know about character dispositions is quite obviously indispensable for
							annotating such phenomena as ambiguity; it also shows that the mere
							linguistic analysis of the individual word must take into account the
							larger context, which results in an informed interpretation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5. Results and Conclusions</head>
            <p>The case study aimed, firstly, at exemplifying the process of developing criteria
					and categories for the study of literary texts that make the analysis more
					precise, and, secondly, at showing how methods from the Digital Humanities, i.e.
					annotation, may yield quantitative results that influence close readings and
					make an interpretation based on a precise analysis empirically valid. In the
					process, a third objective emerged: to try and test annotation as a teaching and
					learning tool in a group of advanced students.</p>
            <p>The annotation task has proved to generate more challenges than anticipated. This
					has to do, on the one hand, with technical issues; conceptual flaws, however,
					turned out to be even more frequent: the annotation of ambiguous modality, even
					the potential ambiguity of the originators of utterances within the fictional
					text, transpired to be partly unsurmountable challenges for the student groups.
					The annotations resulting from the work in the seminar are unfortunately not
					really of any use for further quantitative analysis: the complexity of the
					material makes the annotation by expert teams necessary. And yet, the
					divergencies between the annotations trigger a reflection on the ambiguity of
					the seemingly-clear-cut modalities and point to an ambiguity of ambiguity: it
					appears extremely difficult to decide in some of the cases which of the
					potential modalities are actualized in the context. We have also seen that
					ambiguous modalities may even result in irony and foreground metanarrative
					strategies.</p>
            <p>The analysis of the annotations thus has been quite revealing in several
					respects. In the context of digital annotation, they show that the annotation
					task is challenging: not only have students overlooked instances of <term>must</term> but they are also prone to careless mistakes, e.g.
					when direct speech remains undetected.<note> This has been
							the case for instance 35 of <hi rend="italic">must</hi>. In a dialogue
							between Mr. Knightley and Mrs. Weston in chapter 5 of the first volume,
							Mrs. Weston addresses Mr. Knightley, who answers: “Perhaps you think I
							am come on purpose to quarrel with you, knowing Weston to be out, and
							that you must still fight your own battle.” (27). One student in the
							CATMA group attributed the passage to Mrs. Weston as focalizer rather
							than Mr. Knightley as speaker, despite the quotation marks and the
							context of a dialogue. The reasoning behind this may be that s/he
							recognized Mrs. Weston as the originator of <hi rend="italic">must</hi>:
							“you think: ‘I must fight my own battle.’”</note> The negotiations
					within the groups that used CorefAnnotator led to overall more reliable results
					than those from the CATMA annotations that were submitted individually. The
					greatest challenge, however, consisted in wrong attributions: mistakes range
					from wrong attributions of figure and role to a tendency for disambiguation, in
					particular with regard to modalities. Roles were wrongly attributed whenever the
					annotation guidelines were ignored, i.e. when the narrator was given the
					function of focalizer although this was in fact excluded as an option by the
					annotation guidelines, with the narrator always counting as speaker by default. </p>
            <p>The expectation was that the annotations would yield quantitative results
					concerning the distribution of the ambiguous modality of <term>must</term> in relation to various characters in the novel, and, in
					particular, the ambiguity of voice. An analysis of the first chapter of the
					novel, for instance, has shown that <term>must</term> is mentioned
					16 times; and a close reading has revealed that it is used ambiguously almost
					every time and refers to at least two, sometimes all three modalities. This
					finding alone, i.e. the clustering of <term>must</term> in the
					opening chapter, may be regarded as productive with regard to reading the novel
					as a whole: it almost seems as if Jane Austen was trying to prime her readers
					and have them watch out for ambiguous modalities. Annotations with a higher IAA
					would make it possible to visualize the distribution of these ambiguities over
					direct speech and in relation to focalization. They could moreover show which
					characters use <term>must</term> most frequently in which
					communicative contexts, and whose usage of <term>must</term> merges
					particularly often with that of the narrator to result in ambiguous
					focalization. At the end of the day, the case study results in quite a number of
					insights when it comes to didactic and methodological pitfalls, and the clarity
					of annotation categories turns out to be no guarantor of their correct
					application. At the same time, annotation may create awareness of categories of
					analysis and, if pursued diligently, open new paths of literary analysis. </p>
            <p>With regard to best practice guidelines when it comes to annotating complex
					literary phenomena in the classroom, we suggest the following:</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
               <item>the working methods of students need to be checked regularly, and
						especially during the early stages of annotating, results need to be
						checked;</item>
               <item>the importance of working in a team and discussing individual annotations
						to achieve some IAA needs to be highlighted, particularly in groups that
						have so far been unacquainted with DH methods and annotation in
						particular;</item>
               <item>given the complexity of the phenomenon to be annotated in this case study,
						i.e. the ambiguity of the modal “must”, it would have made sense to start
						with simple introductory examples as a test study before moving on to the
						more complex data of Jane Austen’s novel;</item>
               <item>part of the learning process concerns the mere application of the
						annotation tool. The above-mentioned point, which aims to simplify the task,
						should create more freedom for students to get to grips with the tool
						itself, in order to then form routines in its application right from the
						start of the annotation work. This is especially true for more powerful but
						(depending on the task: necessarily) not so straightforward tools.</item>
               <item>explain that annotating individual instances of a text does not make
						reading it as a whole superfluous but that contextual knowledge of the plot
						and characters is vital to make decisions in the analysis and
							interpretation.<note> This has meanwhile been made obligatory in
								some DH classes – with very good results.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>If students simply lack the motivation or time to pursue a given task diligently,
					little is to be done, which is probably the only insurmountable problem we face
					in all teaching contexts. All other issues identified in the course of teaching
					the class and reflecting on it in this paper may be addressed and will, at least
					this is what we hope, lead to results that can be used for further research
					based on the acquired data.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Works Cited</head>
            <p>Austen, Jane. 2012. <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi>. Ed. George Justice. New York:
					Norton.</p>
            <p>Austen, Jane. 1998. <hi rend="italic">Pride and Prejudice</hi>. Ed. James
					Kinsley; intr. Isobel Armstrong. Oxford: OUP.</p>
            <p>Abrams, M. H.; Geoffrey Galt Harpham. 2015. <hi rend="italic">A Glossary of
						Literary Terms</hi>. Wadsworth: Cengage. </p>
            <p>Bauer, Matthias. 2015. “Ironie und Ambiguität: Annäherungen aus
					literaturwissenschaftlicher Sicht.” <hi rend="italic">Faktuales und fiktionales
						Erzählen.</hi> Ed. Nicole Falkenhayner, Monika Fludernik and Julia Steiner.
					Würzburg: Ergon, 2015. 139-58.</p>
            <p>Bauer, Matthias; Saskia Brockmann. 2017. “The Iconicity of Literary Analysis: The Case of Logical Form.” <hi rend="italic">Dimensions of Iconicity</hi>. Ed. Angelika Zirker, Matthias Bauer, Olga Fischer,
						and Christina Ljungberg. Amsterdam: Benjamins, 2017. 331-44.</p>
            <p>Bauer, Matthias; Sigrid Beck; Susanne Riecker; Saskia Brockmann; Angelika Zirker; Nadine Bade; Carmen Dörge; and Julia Braun. 2020. <hi rend="italic">Linguistics Meets Literature: More on
						the Grammar of Emily Dickinson</hi>. Berlin: de
						Gruyter. </p>
            <p>Bray, Joe. 2007. “The ‘dual voice’ of free indirect discourse: a reading experiment.” <hi rend="italic">Language and Literature </hi>16.1: 37-52.</p>
            <p>Cohn, Dorrit. 1978. <hi rend="italic">Transparent Minds: Narratives Modes for
						Presenting Consciousness in Fiction</hi>.
						Princeton: Princeton UP.</p>
            <p>Davidson, Jenny. 2008. “Austen’s voices.” <hi rend="italic">Swift’s Travels: Eighteenth-Century
						British Satire and Its Legacy</hi>. Ed. Nicholas
						Hudson and Aaron Santesso. Cambridge: CUP. 233-50.</p>
            <p>Ducrot, Oswald. 1984. “Esquisse d’une théorie polyphonique de l’énonciation.” <hi rend="italic">Le dire et le dit</hi>. Paris: Editions de Minuit. 171-233.</p>
            <p>Fintel, Kai von. 2006. “Modality and Language”. <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia of
						Philosophy</hi>. Ed. Donald M. Borchert. Detroit: MacMillan Reference. <ref target="http://mit.edu/fintel/www/modality.pdf">http://mit.edu/fintel/www/modality.pdf</ref>
            </p>
            <p>Genette, Gérard. [1972] 1980. <hi rend="italic">Narrative Discourse. An Essay in
						Method.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
            <p>Gius, Evelyn, and Janina Jacke. 2017. “The Hermeneutic Profit of Annotation. On preventing and fostering disagreement in literary text analysis.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and
						Arts
					Computing</hi> 11 (2): 233-54.</p>
            <p>Justice, George. 2012. Introduction. <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi>.
						By Jane Austen. New York: Norton. vii-xxxii.</p>
            <p>Landis, J. Richard, and Gary G. Koch. 1977. “The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data.” <hi rend="italic">Biometrics</hi> 33.1: 159-74 .</p>
            <p>Margolin, Uri. 2014. “Narrator.”
					<hi rend="italic">The Living Handbook of
						Narratology</hi>. <ref target="https://www-archiv.fdm.uni-hamburg.de/lhn/node/44.html">https://www-archiv.fdm.uni-hamburg.de/lhn/node/44.html</ref>. 23 Nov 2022.</p>
            <p>Pagel, Janis, Nils Reiter, Ina Rösiger and Sarah Schulz. 2020. “Annotation als flexibel einsetzbare Methode“. <hi rend="italic">Reflektierte algorithmische
						Textanalyse: Interdisziplinäre(s) Arbeiten in der CRETA-Werkstatt</hi>. Ed. Nils Reiter, Axel Pichler and Jonas Kuhn.
						Berlin/Boston: de Gruyter, 125-142.</p>
            <p>Pollack-Pelzner, Daniel. 2013. “Jane Austen, the Prose Shakespeare.” 
					<hi rend="italic">SEL</hi> 53.4: 763-92.</p>
            <p>Oberman, Rachel Provenzano. 2009. “Narrated Monologue in Jane Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth-Century
					Literature</hi> 64.1: 1-15.</p>
            <p>Waltereit, Richard. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Abtönung: Zur Pragmatik und
						historischen Semantik von Modalpartikeln und ihren funktionalen Äquivalenten
						in romanischen Sprachen</hi>. Tübingen:
						Niemeyer.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix 1</head>
            <p>The annotation task is to tag and markup all instances of the modal verb “must”
					in the novel, based on the assumption that it may be used ambiguously.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Preliminaries and Theoretical Background</head>
               <p>The ambiguous semantics of the modal verb has been pointed out, e.g., by
						Fintel (2006): “Modality is a category of linguistic meaning having to do
						with the expression of possibility and necessity” (1). </p>
               <p>Modal meaning can be distinguished as follows:</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>epistemic: relates to knowledge and “concerns what is possible or
							necessary given what is known and what the available evidence is”
							(Fintel 2006: 2)</item>
               </list>
               <p>e.g. I see people entering the restaurant where
						I am sitting with umbrellas: “It must be raining.”</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>deontic: relates to duty and “concerns what is possible, necessary,
							permissible, or obligatory, given a body of law or a set of moral
							principles or the like” (Fintel 2006: 2)</item>
               </list>
               <p>e.g. I read hospital regulations: “Visitors must
						leave by six pm.”</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>bouletic: relates to a wish and “concerns what is possible or
							necessary, given a person’s desires” (Fintel 2006: 2)</item>
               </list>
               <p>e.g. a stern father telling his daughter: “You
						must go to bed in ten minutes.”</p>
               <p>These modalities may ‘overlap’, in which case
						the modal verb becomes ambiguous. A prominent case of such an ambiguity is
						the first sentence of Jane Austen’s novel <term>Pride and
							Prejudice</term>: </p>
               <p>It is a truth
							universally acknowledged, that a man in possession of a good fortune,
							must be in want of a wife. (1)</p>
               <p>In this instance, the modal “must” is ambiguous: a man in possession of a
						good fortune is generally in want of a wife (epistemic), he is obliged to be
						so (deontic), and someone may wish this (bouletic). </p>
               <p>The question is: whose thoughts are these? If we begin to disambiguate “must”
						here, we come up with different originating voices behind the utterance,
						with Mrs Bennet being its main originator as her most prominent objective in
						life is to see her five daughters married as much as the “communal voice”
						(Oberman 9) behind the “truth universally acknowledged”. At the same time,
						it is the narrator who expresses the general fact; and a third instance,
						something like the general public, voices an obligation.</p>
               <p>The example shows that the ambiguity of must is related to an ambiguity of
						focalization: several originating instances can be identified, which means
						that two ambiguities are involved: on the lexical level and on the level of
						narrative transmission/focalization. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Annotation Guidelines</head>
               <p>The aim is to identify all instances of <term>must</term> and the
						respective meanings (see above). In order to learn more about its
						distribution over the novel, not only instances in the narrative
						transmission by the narrator and in possible focalizing passages will be
						identified but also those in direct speech; hence the distinction between
						the tag “speaker” and “focalizer” for characters. As the narrator is the
						default speaker in diegesis, there is no double tag for him/her but s/he is
						tagged as “speaker” by default. We also annotate all narrated instances of
						“must” as ambiguous and attribute a tag for narrator as well as for the
						character who is the most likely focalizer of the passage (see also below
						FAQ 2.).</p>
               <p>It makes sense to use the search function of the tool in order not to miss
						out on any instances of “must”.</p>
               <list rend="numbered">
                  <item>Identify / search for all instances of <term>must</term>.</item>
                  <item>Read the context of each mention.</item>
                  <item>Identify who is speaking or thinking the sentence in which <term>must</term> occurs.</item>
                  <item>Annotate who the speaker or focalizer is by marking “must” and
							attributing a character as speaker or as focalizer. </item>
                  <item>If several options are possible for focalization (e.g. several
							characters), annotate all of them as in (iv). </item>
                  <item>Is “must” epistemic – deontic – bouletic? If several modalities apply,
							annotate “must” accordingly.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>FAQs</head>
               <p>1. In par 92 (CoRef) – “ You like Mr. Elton, papa – I must look about for a
						wife for him” – “must” sounds deontic but Emma probably expresses a wish:
						how do we decide?</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>the point is not to decide in the sense of disambiguation but to
							identify possibilities: if both meanings are plausible, then both should
							be annotated in the context</item>
                  <item>it is vital to keep in mind that annotations should be based on what
							is offered in the text: the aim is not disambiguation but to mark the
							ambiguities</item>
               </list>
               <p>2. How do I know whether it’s the narrator or a focalizing character’s voice
						in passages of diegesis? See ex. in par 20: “but Emma was aware that great
						must be the difference…”?</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>the description “Emma was aware” shows that we have insight into her
							thoughts/consciousness, which means we may read this as a passage that
							focalizes her; at the same time, it is transmitted by the narrator and
							may be just his or her voice: again, we annotate both, as we do not
							strive for disambiguation </item>
                  <item>as many (if not almost all) narrated instances of “must” can be
							attributed to a focalizer because of their embedding in verbs like
							“know”, “felt”, “was aware” etc. or a possible instance of Free Indirect
							Discourse (see also in ch. 2, par 114: the paragraph beginning with Mr.
							Weston “He had only himself to please in his choice” could easily be
							read as FID, which can be seen in the possibility to add “He thought
							how…”.</item>
               </list>
               <p>3. Can “must” be epistemic if a character says it? See, for example, par 78:
						“It is impossible that Emma should not miss such a companion,” said Mr.
						Knightley. “We should not like her so well as we do, sir, if we could
						suppose it; but she knows how much the marriage is to Miss Taylor’s
						advantage; she knows how very acceptable it must be, at Miss Taylor’s time
						of life, to be settled in a home of her own…”</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>in this case, all three meanings should be tagged, as this must be
							Emma’s wish, her obligation as much as a fact</item>
                  <item>even though we assume a certain degree of subjectivity in a
							character’s statement, they may still express a fact</item>
                  <item>the case in the example is particularly complicated as Mr. Knightley
							is suggesting/assuming what Emma (should) think(s); yet, he is still a
							speaker, and we do not assume Emma to be a focalizer in an instance of
							direct speech</item>
               </list>
               <p>4. Can the narrator have a wish?</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>this is systematically interesting, and we do not assume an
							involvement of the narrator to a degree that such subjectivity is
							possible (in the example of <term>Emma</term>!)</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl/>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
