<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->A Keyword
					Analysis of <title rend="quotes">Climate Change</title> in Contemporary
					Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Matt <dhq:family>Morgenstern</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation/>
					<email>morgenst@purdue.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000672</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000672/000672.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
			<head></head>
			<p> The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest
				the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976,
				Williams’s book <title rend="italic">Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and
					Society</title> challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical
				analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse
				changes over time. As Williams notes, <quote rend="inline">When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak
				the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different
				immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often
				intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest</quote> <ptr target="#williams2014" loc="xxiii-xxiv"/>. Studying conceptual keywords in this view not only
				enables insights into semantic shifts but also reveals how historically
				contingent conditions embed themselves within such shifts. As such, composing
				keyword entries revealed to Williams that <quote rend="inline">words which seem to have been there
				for centuries, with continuous general meanings, have come in fact to express
				radically different or radically variable, yet sometimes hardly noticed,
				meanings and implications of meaning</quote> <ptr target="#williams2014" loc="xxix"/>. These insights have since
				generated a rich tradition of keyword analysis projects in the humanities,
				including but not limited to select critical theory books, the <title rend="quotes">Living Lexicon</title>
				series from the journal <title rend="italic">Environmental Humanities</title>, as well
				as the <title rend="italic">Keywords </title>series from New York University Press,
				which includes entries on disability, gender and sexuality, and environmental
				studies. </p>
			<p> Since Williams, scholars have relied on keywords in reading, writing, and
				teaching. For many today, a different kind of keyword engagement influences
				research methods. Keyword indexing in databases such as the Modern Language
				Association (MLA) International Bibliography facilitates access to published
				scholarship’s metadata. Selecting effective keywords on such databases enables
				the act of finding, citing, and responding to scholarship. Scholars interested
				in climate change, for instance, search databases for articles that effectively
				deal with the topic’s complexity, which, as Andrew Ross [<ref target="#ross2016">>2016</ref>] notes, connects
				to historical ramifications for scientific knowledge and planetary, geopolitical
				conflict <ptr target="#ross2016" loc="38-40"/>. However, it is important to note for not only contemporary
				literary studies but also the digital humanities that disjunctions in database
				indexing impede digital access to scholarship. In this article, I explore how
				select academic journals from contemporary literary studies exemplify this
				disjunction through the occurrence of <term>climate change</term> as a keyword. Applying
				the VOSviewer bibliometric analysis tool, I analyze thousands of unique
				citations in four academic journals representative of work in contemporary
				literary studies that I, as a scholar of the field, look to trendsetters. Large
				datasets of bibliographic data allow us to survey scholarship through their
				indexed citations and authorial networks <ptr target="#nolan2016"/> <ptr target="#friedman2017"/> <ptr target="#lei2019"/> <ptr target="#earhart2021"/> <ptr target="#sanderman2021"/>. Digital bibliometric analyses
				therefore enable scaled-up analyses of how keywords impact precise framing of
				and engagement with indexed research. </p>
			<p> The field of contemporary literary studies presents a valuable case study in how
				we categorize humanistic scholarship about climate change and related
				environmental issues because its scholarship reviews direct representations of
				climate change. Owing to established fields such as ecocriticism, the discipline
				enjoys many conferences, journal articles, and monographs dedicated to climate
				change <ptr target="#streeby2018"/> <ptr target="#deloughrey2019"/> <ptr target="#houser2020"/> <ptr target="#fiskio2021"/>, and
				scholarship will only proliferate in the coming years. Digital humanists will
				thus benefit from looking at the use of keywords in contemporary literary
				studies. The field reflects ongoing some of the more significant developments in
				humanities scholarship on myriad environmental issues, including but not limited
				to climate change. Deriving insights from a bibliometric analysis of
				contemporary literary studies will, in turn, suggest new possibilities for
				indexing scholarship to encourage engagement and access. While I go in more
				detail about the results below, this project’s central purpose is to identify
				how climate change occurs as an object of scholarly inquiry in the humanities
				through its use as a keyword in contemporary literary studies. </p></div>
			<div>
			<head>Corpus and Methods</head>
			<p>The following sections encompass a bibliometric analysis of four journals from
				contemporary literary studies: <title rend="italic">ISLE: Interdisciplinary Studies
					in Literature and Environment</title> (<title rend="italic">ISLE</title>); <title
					rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</title> (<title rend="italic">CL</title>); <title
					rend="italic">MFS Modern Fiction Studies</title> (<title rend="italic">MFS</title>);
				and <title rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association</title>
					(<title rend="italic">PMLA</title>). I analyze the <title rend="italic">ISLE
				</title>corpus as a reference case for the occurrence of <term>climate change</term> as a
				keyword in a journal explicitly interested in environmental issues. With this
				corpus as a basis, I compare the other three corpora as benchmarks of
				contemporary literary studies scholarship. In selecting journals for analysis, I
				gathered indexed citations from journals with approximately 500-750 results in
				the MLA International Bibliography. These results derive from filtering out
				non-English language results and citations that occur prior to 2000. The <title
					rend="italic">ISLE </title>corpus counts 665 unique citations; the <title
					rend="italic">CL </title>corpus counts 620; the <title rend="italic">MFS
				</title>corpus counts 763; and the <title rend="italic">PMLA </title>corpus counts 1,964.
				Though I considered journals such as <title rend="italic">Environmental Humanities
				</title>and <title rend="italic">Resilience: A Journal of Environmental
					Humanities</title> as supplemental reference cases to <title rend="italic"
					>ISLE</title>, they were excluded because their indexed citation count in the
				MLA International Bibliography was less than 500 at the time of data collection. </p>
			<p>Although the periodization of <q>contemporary literature</q> is highly contested
				<ptr target="#martin2019"/>, I define my scope as including literature published from 1985 to
				the present while limiting scholarship on said literature from 2000 to early
				2022. I adopt this timeline because I am most interested in scholarship that
				addresses recent representations of climate change that benefit from engagement
				(or lack thereof) with the past three decades of climate science. At the same
				time, I acknowledge that these journals — beside <title rend="italic">ISLE</title> — do
				not tally significant counts of <term>climate change</term> as a keyword because the topic
				was likely peripheral to their interests up until the last decade. However, I
				find them valuable test cases because they have since published on the topic
				and, thus, can be analyzed as a corpus with keyword connections that either do
				or do not reflect the topic’s many connections. With these variables in mind, I
				assembled each journal’s corpus, limiting their indexed citations in the MLA
				International Bibliography to English-language citations from 2000 to the
				present. <note> This corpus reflects the reviewed journal’s index counts as of
					January 24, 2022; it therefore does not include citations indexed after
					data gathering. The corpus is available for review on request.</note> I
				then exported the citations as research information system files to process with
				VOSviewer, a bibliometrics tool with modularity algorithms for visualizing
				author networks and keyword occurrence clusters <ptr target="#janvaneck"/>. I
				initially isolated keywords that occur at least ten times in the top fifty
				keywords across the run of journal articles and book reviews, removing keywords
				that convey period duration or generalist categories. <note> For each journal’s
					corpus, I removed select keywords that disproportionately impacted the
					visualizations. While select keywords do not occur in each corpus (unlike
						<title rend="italic">CL </title>and <title rend="italic">MFS</title>, <title
						rend="italic">PMLA</title>’s scope extends its range to medieval literary
					studies, which leads to keywords such as <q>1500-1599</q> and <q>1600-1699</q>), the
					listed keywords reappear frequently enough across corpora to justify
					exclusion: <q>400-1499,</q> <q>1100-middle English,</q> <q>1500-1599,</q> <q>1600-1699,</q>
					<q>1700-1799,</q> <q>1800-1899,</q> <q>1900-1999,</q> <q>2000-2009,</q> <q>english language
					literature,</q> <q>fiction,</q> <q>prose,</q> <q>short story,</q> and <q>film.</q> </note> I began
				with 10 keyword occurrences because that number suggests a keyword’s relative
				frequency in a corpus of at least 500 citations. If a <term>climate change</term> cluster
				did not emerge at ten keywords, I decreased the occurrence count to five and, if
				necessary, one keyword to find the climate change keyword cluster. I
				simultaneously increased the top count in permutations of 50, 100, and 1,000,
				while decreasing the occurrence count (if a cluster does not emerge in the top
				fifty, it will also emerge at subsequent scales). I followed these steps to
				determine the relative significance of <q>climate change</q> as a keyword in each
				reviewed corpus. </p>
			<p>While this article derives inspiration for bibliometric analyses elsewhere in
				literary studies <ptr target="#goldstone2014"/>, it also follows bibliometric
				analyses in applied environmental sciences that propose new avenues for research
				<ptr target="#haunschild2016"/> <ptr target="#zyoud2020"/> <ptr target="#xiao2021"/>. Reconciling differences between these projects will inform framings
				of climate change in digital humanities research and points to the utility of
				digital interventions in the environmental humanities. Survey approaches of
				contemporary literary studies, ecocriticism, and the environment humanities
				precede this project, as we see in select articles from Ursula K. Heise [<ref target="#heise2006a">2006a</ref>]
				[<ref target="#heise2006b">2006b</ref>] [<ref target="#heise2008">2008</ref>] [<ref target="#heise2013">2013</ref>]. But because digital humanities tools can analyze
				thousands of citations in databases, scaled-up bibliometric analyses can model
				approach for determining common terms of engagement between otherwise
				disconnected disciplines. As such, I focus on climate change as a keyword
				because keywords such as <q>climate malaise,</q> <q>climate fatigue,</q> and <q>climate
				perturbation</q> are not commonly recognized. The project also must rely on the
				keywords provided by the indexers of the MLA International Bibliography:
				<q>climate change</q> is the keyword because it is what appears on the database. I
				follow this determined condition because climate change is a discursive
				mainstay, a keyword in the truest sense of William’s work. For example, a brief
				search for publications with <q>Environment</q> in the Scopus database reveals the
				predominance of climate change as a keyword (both for authors and the database
				indexers) in pertinent research. Of 2,000 publications surveyed, selecting for
				at least 10 keyword occurrences, the keyword for climate change occurs in 188
				articles with 723 links to other pertinent topics such as <q>carbon,</q> <q>drought,</q>
				and <q>climate models</q> (Fig. 1). <note> As of October 21, 2022. </note>
			</p>
				
				<figure>
					<head>The node for <q>climate change</q> in the Scopus corpus demonstrates its
						proximity to numerous of topics important to not only the sciences but also the
						humanities.</head>
				</figure>
				
				
			
			<p>While not the leading keyword in the Scopus corpus (these being <q>article,</q>
				<q>controlled study,</q> and <q>nonhuman</q>), it is in the top 15, indicating its
				relative significance. As a keyword, then, climate change presents significant
				inroads for a variety of ecological issues with which literary studies, as well
				as the digital humanities, will benefit from informed engagement. </p>
			<p>When evaluating the corpora, I do not critique any author, journal, or publisher
				for how a given citation does or does not employ certain keywords. This is in
				part because the MLA International Bibliography’s keyword selection process is
				unclear. The Modern Language Association’s website for the database notes the
				number of indexers who cite publications and the thousands of <q>terms</q> they use
				for indexing <ptr target="#mla"/>, but
				does not mention if keywords derive from authors, journals, or other parties. I
				also do not know if the initial stage of keyword selection affects later
				indexing of pertinent metadata. I therefore survey this corpus of journal
				citations mindful of the many components that result in a keyword’s appearance
				in a scholarly database. The article’s conclusion considers how responding to
				these limitations may inspire more effective indexing practices for future
				digital environmental humanities (DEH) projects, in addition to future
				contemporary literary studies and digital humanities scholarship (not to say
				that the two are distinct). These DEH projects include not only analyses of
				emergent cultural forms <ptr target="#buckland2018"/> <ptr target="#joergensen2014"/> <ptr target="#musiol2021"/>, but also ongoing conversations about how the digital humanities
				will respond to climate change through its methods, tools, and critiques of
				extant technologies <ptr target="#nowviskie2015"/> <ptr target="#posthumus2018"/> <ptr target="#travis2022"/>. </p></div>
			<div>
				
			<head>Reference Case: ISLE</head>
			<p> Since its 1993 debut, <title rend="italic">ISLE: Interdisciplinary Studies in
					Literature and Environment </title>(hereafter <title rend="italic">ISLE</title>) has
				served as a hub for environmental scholarship in literary studies. As Patrick D.
				Murphy and Cheryll Glotfelty wrote in its first issue, <title rend="italic"
					>ISLE</title>’s founding <quote rend="inline">reflects the rapid growth of ecological criticism in
				the United States in recent years, which in turn reflects the steady increase in
				the production of environmental literature and nature writing over the past
				several decades and the attendant increased visibility of such writing in
				college literature courses</quote> <ptr target="#glotfelty1993" loc="1"/>. At the time of writing, 29 volumes of <title
					rend="italic">ISLE </title>have been published in as part of the Association
				for the Study of Literature and environment. The journal’s mission statement
				pinpoints its influence as a pillar for literary studies: <quote rend="inline">Celebrating the rich
				confluence of environmental humanities, ecocriticism, and environmental
				justice, ISLE welcomes submissions from authors creatively engaging these fields
				from a broad range of disciplines, geographies, and perspectives. ISLE invites
				scholarly articles and creative writing that interpret the environment in
				complex, imaginative, and generative ways</quote> <ptr target="#isle"/>. Owing to the journal’s long
				publication history and dedicated interest in the ways cultural texts grapple
				with environmental issues, and how these issues are explored through such genres
				as climate fiction and ecopoetics, <title rend="italic">ISLE </title>presents a
				fruitful archive for bibliometric analysis. I therefore refer to <title
					rend="italic">ISLE </title>as a <q>reference</q> case that generates an array of
				keywords for literary studies concerned with the environment may index
				scholarship concerned with climate change. </p>
			<p> The <title rend="italic">ISLE </title>corpus presents multiple occurrences of <q>climate
				change</q> as a keyword. The VOSviewer tool presents clusters that cohere around
				significant keyword occurrences at various scales. Links between clusters
				suggest the relative significance of keywords to other relevant topics of
				interest. An initial reading of the <title rend="italic">ISLE </title>corpus suggests
				the significance of keywords (referred to as <q>subject terms</q> in the MLA
				International Bibliography) such as <q>ecocritical approach,</q> <q>american
				literature,</q> and <q>nature</q> (Fig. 2), many of which characterize the initial
				stages of US ecocriticism. </p>
				
				<figure>
					<head>An Overlay Visualization of keywords in the <title rend="italic">ISLE
					</title>corpus. Nodes in darker shades of blue indicate older keywords, while nodes
						in brighter shades of yellow indicate newer keywords. The node between <q>climate
						change</q> and <q>ecocritical approach</q> is <q>environmental crisis.</q></head>
				</figure>
				<ptr target="#"/>
				
			<p>While these keyword clusters are the most frequent at a scale of 10 occurrences in
				the top 50, they are not the most recent. More recent clusters of significance
				include “postapocalyptic novel,” “environmental crisis,” and “climate change.”
				The “environmental crisis” keyword occurs 85 times, with 29 links to other
				clusters; the “climate change” keyword occurs 18 times with 13 links. As we can
				read “environmental crisis” in several ways, a discrepancy emerges between these
				two keywords in the <hi rend="italic">ISLE</hi> corpus. Does “environmental
				crisis” refer to climate change, a mass extinction event, or something else
				entirely? Does indexing “environmental crisis” preclude the mention of “climate
				change,” making the keywords mutually exclusive? </p>
			<p>Closer analysis of the <hi rend="italic">ISLE </hi>clusters hardly distinguishes
				the keywords. Scaling down from ten to five keyword occurrences produces
				“environmental crisis” and “climate change” nodes with more connections in the
				top 50: the former adds 23 links for a total of 52 connections while the latter
				gains three for a total of 16. The node for “environmental crisis” links with
				“meat,” “petroleum industry,” and “social justice.” The node for “climate
				change” does not link to any nodes not already connected to “environmental
				crisis,” suggesting that the conceptual keyword of “environmental crisis”
				includes but is not limited to “climate change.” Three <hi rend="italic"
					>ISLE</hi> articles in the corpus indexed with “climate change” are also
				indexed with “environmental crisis” [Schneider-Mayerson 2019] [Rosenthal 2020]
				[Dini 2021]. Our empirical knowledge of climate change daily evolves with
				applied modeling and research,<note> Though well-documented across the globe,
					reports from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) offer the
					most current scientific consensus on climate change. </note> and, whether
				in popular media coverage or in everyday conversation, we commonly do not
				associate the phrase “environmental crisis” with ecological catastrophe more
				than we do “climate change.” As a conceptual keyword, “climate change” is
				commonplace among environmental humanists, scientists, and policymakers alike.
				Its appeal as a keyword lies in its shared distribution between possibly
				disparate groups. At the same time, the conceptual keyword “environmental
				crisis” may lend itself to complexities that “climate change” does not present
				because the former touches on issues such as pollution, biodiversity loss, and
				changing ecosystems. These more specific problems and their local occurrences
				are not always direct effects of climate change. Consequently, indexing an
				article with the keyword “environmental crisis” may misrepresent its account of
				environmental issues that require further contextualization. </p>
			<p> It should not surprise us that “climate change” occurs significantly in the <hi
					rend="italic">ISLE </hi>corpus. Yet it is surprising that the
				“environmental crisis” cluster seemingly absorbs the “climate change” cluster in
				that the former attaches to topics discussed in concert with climate science.
				Though I argue that the distinction between “environmental crisis” and “climate
				change” remains significant, the <hi rend="italic">ISLE </hi>reference corpus
				presents a valuable example of wrestling with the two keywords as only two among
				many in its set. Now that we have seen a sampling of keywords from the <hi
					rend="italic">ISLE </hi>corpus, we can see how these keywords emerge, or do
				not emerge, in the other corpora that are not exclusively concerned with the
				environmental humanities. </p>
			<p>Test Cases: Contemporary Literature, MFS, and PMLA</p>
			<p> This section reviews the <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</hi> (<hi
					rend="italic">CL</hi>),<hi rend="italic"> MFS Modern Fiction Studies</hi>
					(<hi rend="italic">MFS</hi>), and <hi rend="italic">Publications of the
					Modern Language Association </hi>(<hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi>) corpora.
				While these journals have not historically foregrounded climate change as an
				object of inquiry, I look to their corpora to consider how their recent keywords
				reflect contemporary literary studies’ emergent interests in climate change.
				With the <hi rend="italic">ISLE </hi>keywords as a reference for work elsewhere
				in literary studies, I am interested in analyzing how journals indexed in the
				same database do, and do not, engage similar and dissimilar keywords. I begin
				with <hi rend="italic">CL</hi>, which publishes scholarly articles and book
				reviews. <hi rend="italic">CL</hi> published the “first articles on Thomas
				Pynchon and Susan Howe and the first interviews with Margaret Drabble and Don
				DeLillo; it also helped to introduce Kazuo Ishiguro, Eavan Boland, and J. M.
				Coetzee to American readers” [<hi rend="italic">Contemporary Literature
				</hi>n.d.]. As of late, <hi rend="italic">CL</hi> has also published
				eco-critical and environmental humanist scholarship. The most recent volume in
				the corpus includes articles that consider Black American conceptions of land
				use [Huehls 2020], post-apocalyptic environmental conditions in the novel <hi
					rend="italic">Red Plenty</hi> [Singer 2020], and a review of scholarship on
				the Anthropocene and cultural production in the Global South [Samuelson
				2020].</p>
			<p> In the <hi rend="italic">CL</hi> corpus, “climate change” as a keyword occurs
				infrequently. At 10 occurrences in the top 50, no “climate change” or
				“environmental crisis” clusters occur. Scaling the corpus down further by
				selecting for five keyword occurrences in the top one hundred produces
				“ecocriticism” and “environmental crisis” nodes quite distant from the network’s
				center (Fig. 3). Each cluster numbers six occurrences, indicating their relative
				insignificance in the corpus. </p>
			<p>FIG 3 HERE</p>
			<p>Figure 3. Node for “environmental crisis” in an Overlay Visualization of the <hi
					rend="italic">CL</hi> corpus. Note the node’s connection to “nature” and
				“ecocriticism” at the top of the graph. </p>
			<p>The occurrence of “environmental crisis” changes at subsequent scales. Selecting
				for one keyword in the top five hundred, “environmental crisis” occurs six times
				with eighteen links. Selecting for one keyword in the top seven
				hundred-and-fifty, the occurrence count of “environmental crisis” remains the
				same but adds new links. A cluster for “climate change” does not occur at any of
				these scales. We must scale down considerably to find a cluster: selecting for
				one keyword in the top one thousand registers a single occurrence of “climate
				change” with four cluster links.</p>
			<p> At first glance, these results corroborate the MLA International Bibliography’s
				listing of <hi rend="italic">CL</hi>’s citations: only one article in the last
				20 years has been indexed with “climate change” [Garrard 2009].<note> At the
					time of writing.</note> This does not mean the corpus does not include
				citations geared toward prominent environmental issues, as the “environmental
				crisis” keyword surfaces when scaling down. The six citations indexed with
				“environmental crisis” are not indexed with “climate change,” though they are
				indexed important topics such as “global warming,” “pesticide,” “poisoning,” and
				“violence.” In the corpus, these citations include both reviews [Didur 2012]
				[Irr 2018] [Bloomfield 2019] [Samuelson] and articles [Chisholm 2016] [Vázquez
				2017]. Because the “environmental crisis” cluster in the <hi rend="italic">CL
				</hi>corpus is attached to a constellation of topics, the corpus presents a
				notable discursive gap between the use of “environmental crisis” and “climate
				change.” If the latter is used seldomly, the former is used in reference to
				important topics that may, or may not, be discussed separately from climate
				change. </p>
			<p> I now turn my attention to the <hi rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpus. <hi
					rend="italic">MFS </hi>publishes articles and book reviews concerned with
				twentieth- and twenty-first century literature on a quarterly basis, with an
				emphasis on modernist, postmodernist, and contemporary fiction. A journal with a
				prestigious publishing record of nearly 60 years, <hi rend="italic">MFS</hi> is
				a benchmark publication for innovative debates and topics in contemporary
				literary studies. Of note to this article is the fact that <hi rend="italic">MFS
				</hi>has published multiple special issues concerned with climate change and
				related environmental issues. These special issues include “Modern Fiction and
				the Ecological: The Futures of Ecocriticism” (Fall 2009), “Anthropocene
				Fictions” (Winter 2018), and “Literature and Extraction” (Spring 2020); the
				first special issue in that list published prominent environmental humanist Rob
				Nixon’s [2009] early writing on “slow violence.” </p>
			<p> Compared to the <hi rend="italic">CL</hi> corpus, the occurrence of “climate
				change” as a keyword in the <hi rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpus differs greatly.
				The emergence of an “environmental crisis” node at the scale of 10 keyword
				occurrences in the top 50 suggests the cluster’s relative significance. However,
				no “climate change” cluster emerges. Scaling down to five keyword occurrences in
				the top fifty and top one hundred returns the same result. Scaling the corpus
				down to one keyword in the top five hundred produces a “climate change” cluster
				with three occurrences and fourteen links to other keywords (Fig. 4). Several
				clusters related to the environment occur at this scale, including “ecology,”
				“ecocritical approach,” “environmental movement,” “natural gas industry,”
				“petroleum industry,” and “plant imagery.” </p>
			<p>FIG 4 HERE</p>
			<p>Figure 4. Bottom center location of “climate change” as a keyword in an overlay
				visualization of the <hi rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpus. Note the node’s size
				compared to “environmental crisis” in a nearly vertical position. </p>
			<p>Different keyword connections for “climate change” and “environmental crisis”
				characterize their occurrence in the <hi rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpus. While
				the former keyword primarily occurs around geopolitical clusters such as “united
				states imperialism” and “afghanistan war (2000-2021),” the latter connects to
				“petroleum industry,” “nature,” and “ecocritical approach.” While I do not mean
				to focus on these two keywords throughout the essay, these distinctions are
				worth noting, as many of the “environmental crisis” connections are relevant to
				any literary studies account of “climate change.” Three citations appear that
				explicitly address climate change [Malewitz 2015] [Johns-Putra 2016] [Oh 2020];
				searching elsewhere in the corpus, citations with “environmental crisis”
				represent a range of important but different environmental issues. </p>
			<p>Databases such as the MLA International Bibliography operate with directed user
				engagement, and the difference between keyword selection may elide opportunities
				for accessible engagement. Regarding such engagement in the <hi rend="italic"
					>MFS </hi>corpus, we can turn to Caroline Levine’s article “The Long Lure
				of Anti-Instrumentality: Politics, Aesthetics, and Sustainability” as a
				synecdoche for the entire <hi rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpus. Levine’s article
				asks readers to revise conceptions of literature’s “anti-instrumentality” in the
				context of climate change’s emergence [2021, 227]. Levine situates this argument
				for literature’s instrumentality in the context of extant issues such as climate
				migration, resource allocation, ecological degradation, and climate denialism
				and pessimism (233-35, 238-40), Levine’s article provokes new ways of thinking
				about climate change and contemporary literary studies in scholarship and
				pedagogy. In the MLA International Bibliography, Levine’s article is indexed
				with three keywords: “themes and figures”; “aesthetics”; and “left-wing
					politics.”<note> At the time of writing. </note> Yet the term “climate” is
				used 18 times throughout the article, with 8 unique instances of “climate
				change.” Strikingly, climate change is absent from this list. While reading
				through journals may remain the best way to assess their scholarship, many
				contemporary scholars instead rely on Googling, library search portal browsing,
				and databases. Scholars’ targeted research practices help them get what they
				need when they need it (especially when increased teaching loads and immensely
				reduced funding opportunities undermine research capacities), and precise
				keyword selection makes the difference. In highlighting the indexing of Levine’s
				article, I do not aim to criticize any party for the absence of “climate change”
				as a keyword; we should still read, consider, and cite the article regardless of
				how it is indexed. Yet the absence of “climate change” as a keyword impedes our
				engagement with articles such as Levine’s that discuss it with significance. </p>
			<p> My final test case, the <hi rend="italic">PMLA </hi>corpus — which is
				significantly larger than either the <hi rend="italic">CL </hi>or <hi
					rend="italic">MFS </hi>corpora — publishes scholarship on a diverse range
				of fields and periods in literary studies, including contemporary literature.
				The journal’s active cultivation of novel approaches speaks to its importance,
				not only as the cornerstone publication of the Modern Language Association but
				also as a publication for established disciplinary conversations. As its website
				states, “The ideal  PMLA essay exemplifies the best of its kind, whatever the
				kind; addresses a significant problem; draws out clearly the implications of its
				findings; and engages the attention of its audience through a concise, readable
				presentation” [<hi rend="italic">PMLA </hi>n.d.]. <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi> is
				also a competitive site for submission: disciplinary journals may therefore not
				be as receptive to relatively new work, or even submissions from graduate
				students and junior scholars [Belcher 2019, 125]. However, <hi rend="italic"
					>PMLA</hi> has published work relevant to contemporary literary studies,
				the digital humanities [So 2017] [Underwood 2020], the environmental humanities,
				and even an early iteration of DEH referred to as the “ecological digital
				humanities” [Cohen and LeMenager 2015], even as much of the journal’s writing
				offers surveys of scholarship in their respective topics. </p>
			<p> Starting with 10 keyword occurrences in the top 50, no “environmental crisis” or
				“climate change” clusters emerge in the corpus. The notable absence of climate
				change is still visible when we scale for at five keywords in the top fifty and
				top one hundred. At each of these scales, zero clusters emerge for topics
				associated with environmental issues. A cluster for “climate change” appears if
				we select for one keyword occurrence in the top five hundred: the keyword occurs
				six times and links with twenty-six additional clusters (Fig. 5). </p>
			<p>FIG 5 HERE</p>
			<p>Figure 5. An Overlay Visualization of “climate change” as a keyword in the <hi
					rend="italic">PMLA </hi>corpus. The node (directly in the center) does not
				share significant associations with other clusters. </p>
			<p>Additional clusters associated with environmental issues emerge at this scale,
				including “nature,” “ecocriticism,” “landscape,” and even “anthropocene epoch.”
				In two unique citations, “climate change” is indexed with “nature”; in two other
				citations, with “weather” (also “seasons of the year” in one of those two); in
				another unique citation, with “environmental studies”; and, in a final unique
				citation, “pollution” and “industrialization” [Menely 2012] [Tait 2015]
				[Bronstein 2019] [Dimock 2018] [Dimock 2019] [Steer 2021]. In the <hi
					rend="italic">PMLA </hi>corpus, then, “climate change” as a keyword enjoys
				distinct cluster connections that speak to different yet interconnected topics.
				For example, we have Philip Steer’s [2021] recent article on nineteenth-century
				Britain, Australia, and the Anthropocene with “climate change” as a keyword.
				“Environmental crisis” occurs as a keyword twice, and neither citation is
				indexed with “climate change” or the above terms [Hsy 2016] [Malkmus 2017]. Is
				there a tradition of selecting “environmental crisis” in lieu of or as
				complement to “climate change” in <hi rend="italic">ISLE</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
					>CL</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">MFS</hi> but not in <hi rend="italic"
					>PMLA</hi>? This difference may account for the concerns of field- or
				period-based journals versus disciplinary journals. <hi rend="italic"
					>ISLE</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> CL</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">MFS</hi>
				publish scholarship with foci relevant to scholars; <hi rend="italic">PMLA
				</hi>publishes scholarship with a broad focus for multiple fields. Regardless of
				their differences, each corpus presents different accounts of “climate change”
				as a keyword. </p>
			<p>Conclusion: Keywords and DEH</p>
			<p> How fields such as contemporary literary studies and the digital humanities
				respond to climate change requires shared conceptual keywords that extend beyond
				disciplines. In the future, we may wish to derive inspiration for these terms
				from various keyword projects [Adamson, Gleason, and Pellow 2016]
				[Schneider-Mayerson and Bellamy 2019]. In addition, we may write a publicly
				available keyword selection guide for precise database indexing and engagement:
				Lauren Klein and Catherine D’Ignazio’s [2020] discussion of “datasheets” as a
				contextual tool for big datasets may serve as first step toward realizing this
				approach, encouraging what Johanna Drucker may refer to as a more “sustainable”
				digital humanities praxis [2021]. In this case, I suggest a specific lexicon for
				environmental issues and how they connect to climate change. Although some may
				say that all humanities work is in some way imbricated in climate change
				[McDougall, Ryan, and Reynolds 2022], I argue that only humanities work that
				explicitly addresses climate change should merit attention as climate humanities
				scholarship. For instance, an essay that addresses topics such as biodiversity,
				climate engineering, or climate fiction should be indexed with climate change
				only if the essay makes a significant connection between said topics and climate
				change. Such meaningful connections allow us to can avoid the nebulousness of
				“environmental crisis,” which I argue does not offer as many interdisciplinary
				inroads. This is not to overlook the fact that keyword indexing can be an
				imperfect practice; however, I hope my results show that it can be standardized
				for renowned publications interested in publishing on the topic. </p>
			<p>A systematic adoption of keywords, as Williams writes, grants us “a vocabulary to
				use, to find our own ways in, to change as we find it necessary to change it, as
				we go on making our own language and history” (xxxv-xxxvi). Whether one works in
				contemporary literary studies or the digital humanities (or both), following
				similarly determined examples of keyword selection will ensure continued
				collective meaning making in scholarly discourse. Students, scholars, and
				teachers interested in DEH will also benefit from deliberate indexing choices.
				As the DEH take on new, forms, effective indexing practices that precisely frame
				discussions of climate change in teaching, scholarship, and outward facing
				projects will enrich the field’s interdisciplinary significance. At the same
				time, because “climate change” is a phrase with meaning beyond academic
				indexing, it can be a keyword that encompasses diverse yet globally
				interconnected environmental issues; subsuming it within the “environmental
				crisis” hierarchy only dilutes the outward access to such scholarship. </p>
			<p>References</p>
			<p>Adamson, J., Gleason, W.A. and Pellow, D.N. (eds.). <hi rend="italic">Keywords for
					Environmental Studies</hi>. New York University Press, New York (2016).</p>
			<p>Belcher, W.L. <hi rend="italic">Writing Your Journal Article in Twelve Weeks,
					Second Edition: A Guide to Academic Publishing Success</hi>. University of
				Chicago Press, Chicago (2019). </p>
			<p>Bloomfield, M. “Beyond Nature Poetry: Ecopoetics for a New Era,” <hi rend="italic"
					>Contemporary Literature</hi>, 60 (2019): 132-37. </p>
			<p>Bronstein, M. “Taking the Future into Account: Today’s Novels for Tomorrow’s
				Readers,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language
					Association of America</hi>, 134 (2019): 121-36. </p>
			<p>Buckland, P.I., Dell’Unto, N. and Pálsson, G. “To tree, or not to tree? On the
				Empirical Basis for Having Past Landscapes to Experience,” <hi rend="italic"
					>Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, 12.3 (2018).</p>
			<p>Chisholm, D. “Juliana Spahr’s Ecopoetics: Ecologies and Politics of the Refrain,”
					<hi rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</hi>, 55 (2014): 118-47.</p>
			<p>Cohen, J. J. and LeMenager, S. “Introduction: Assembling the Ecological Digital
				Humanities,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language
					Association of America</hi>, 131.2 (2015): 340-46.</p>
			<p>
				<hi rend="italic">Contemporary Literature </hi>[n.d.],
				https://uwpress.wisc.edu/journals/journals/cl.html (accessed April 7, 2022).</p>
			<p>DeLoughrey, E.M. <hi rend="italic">Allegories of the Anthropocene</hi>. Duke
				University Press, Durham (2019).</p>
			<p>Didur, J. “Provincializing Ecocriticism,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary
					Literature</hi>, 53 (2012), 585-91. </p>
			<p>Dimock, W.C. “Editor’s Column: Climate Humanists,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA:
					Publications of the Modern Language Association of America</hi>, 133
				(2018): 9-18.</p>
			<p>Dimock, W.C. “Editor’s Column: Hanging with Chefs,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA:
					Publications of the Modern Language Association of America</hi>, 134
				(2019): 989-95.</p>
			<p>Dini, R. “‘Resurrected from Its Own Sewers’: Waste, Landscape, and the Environment
				in J. G. Ballard’s 1960s Climate Fiction,” <hi rend="italic">ISLE:
					Interdisciplinary Studies in Literature and Environment</hi>, 28 (2021):
				207-29. </p>
			<p>Drucker, J. “Sustainability and complexity: Knowledge and authority in the digital
				humanities,” Digital Scholarship in the Humanities, 36.2 (2021): ii86-ii94.</p>
			<p>Earhart, A.E., Risam, R. and Bruno, M. “Citational politics: Quantifying the
				influence of gender on citation in <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
					Humanities</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
					Humanities</hi>, 36.3 (2021): 581-94. </p>
			<p>Fiskio, J. <hi rend="italic">Climate Change, Literature, and Environmental
					Justice: Poetics of Dissent and Repair</hi>. Cambridge University Press,
				Cambridge (2021).</p>
			<p>Friedman, A. and Bernstein, J.H. “Measures of greatness: A Lotkaian approach to
				literary authors using OCLC WorldCat,” <hi rend="italic">Library &amp;
					Information Science Research</hi>, 39.3 (2017):180–188. </p>
			<p>Garrard, G. “Ian McEwan’s Next Novel and the Future of Ecocriticism,” <hi
					rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</hi>, 50.4 (2009): 695-720. </p>
			<p>Gerhardt, C. and Westerman, J. “Editors’ Note,” <hi rend="italic">ISLE:
					Interdisciplinary Studies in Literature and Environment</hi>, 28.3 (2021):
				815-16. </p>
			<p>Godin, B. “On the origins of bibliometrics,” <hi rend="italic"
				>Scientometrics</hi>, 68.1 (2006): 109-33.</p>
			<p>Goldstone, A. and Underwood, T. “The Quiet Transformations of Literary Studies:
				What Thirteen Thousand Scholars Could Tell Us,” <hi rend="italic">New Literary
					History</hi>, 45.3 (2014): 359-84.</p>
			<p>Gold, M. K. and Klein, L. F. “6. The Numbers Don’t Speak for Themselves” (2020).
					<hi rend="italic">Data Feminism</hi>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://data-feminism.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/czq9dfs5/release/3"
					>https://data-feminism.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/czq9dfs5/release/3</ref>
				(accessed April 7, 2022).</p>
			<p>Haunschild, R., Bornmann, L. and Marx, W. “Climate Change Research in View of
				Bibliometrics,” <hi rend="italic">PloS One</hi>, 11.7 (2016).</p>
			<p>Heise, U.K. “Greening English: Recent Introductions to Ecocriticism,” <hi
					rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</hi>, 47.2 (2006a): 289-98. </p>
			<p>Heise, U.K. “The Hitchhiker’s Guide to Ecocriticism,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA:
					Publications of the Modern Language Association of America</hi>, 121.2
				(2006b): 503-16. </p>
			<p>Heise, U.K. “Ecocriticism and the Transnational Turn in American Studies,” <hi
					rend="italic">American Literary History</hi>, 20.1-2 (2008): 381-404. </p>
			<p>Heise, U.K. “Globality, Difference, and the International Turn in Ecocriticism,”
					<hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association of
					America</hi>, 128.3 (2013): 636-43. </p>
			<p>Houser, H. <hi rend="italic">Infowhelm: Environmental Art and Literature in an Age
					of Data</hi>. Columbia University Press, New York (2020).</p>
			<p>Hsy, J. “Language Ecologies: Ethics, Community, and Digital Affect,” <hi
					rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association of
					America</hi>, 131 (2016): 373-80.</p>
			<p>Huehls, M. “The Radical Conservatism of Black Rural Literature,” <hi rend="italic"
					>Contemporary Literature</hi>, 61.4 (2020): 431-59.</p>
			<p>
				<hi rend="italic">ISLE: Interdisciplinary Studies in Literature and Environment
				</hi>(n.d.), <ref target="https://academic.oup.com/isle/pages/About"
					>https://academic.oup.com/isle/pages/About</ref> (accessed April 7,
				2022).</p>
			<p>Irr, C. “Contemporary Ecocriticism and the Weather,” <hi rend="italic"
					>Contemporary Literature</hi>, 59 (2018), 261-73. </p>
			<p>Jan van Eck, N. and Waltman, L. <hi rend="italic">VOSviewer</hi> (n.d.), <ref
					target="https://www.vosviewer.com/">https://www.vosviewer.com/</ref>
				(accessed April 11, 2022).</p>
			<p>Johns-Putra, A. “‘My Job Is to Take Care of You’: Climate Change, Humanity, and
				Cormac McCarthy’s <hi rend="italic">The Road</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">MFS Modern
					Fiction Studies</hi>, 62.3 (2016): 519-40. </p>
			<p>Jørgensen, F.A. “The Armchair Traveler’s Guide to Digital Environmental
				Humanities,” <hi rend="italic">Environmental Humanities</hi>, 4.1 (2014):
				95-112. </p>
			<p>Lei, L. and Liu, D. “Research Trends in Applied Linguistics from 2005 to 2016: A
				Bibliometric Analysis and Its Implications,” <hi rend="italic">Applied
					Linguistics</hi>, 40.3 (2019): 540-61.</p>
			<p>Levine, C. “The Long Lure of Anti-Instrumentality: Politics, Aesthetics, and
				Sustainability,” <hi rend="italic">MFS Modern Fiction Studies</hi>, 67.2 (2021):
				225-46. </p>
			<p>Malewitz, R. “Climate-Change Infrastructure and the Volatilizing of American
				Regionalism,” <hi rend="italic">MFS Modern Fiction Studies</hi>, 61.4 (2015):
				715-30.</p>
			<p>Malkmus, B. “‘Man in the Anthropocene’: Max Frisch’s Environmental History,” <hi
					rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association of
					America</hi>, 132 (2017): 71-85. </p>
			<p>Martin, T. <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Drift: Genre, Historicism, and the
					Problem of the Present</hi>. Columbia University Press, New York (2019). </p>
			<p>McDougall, R., Ryan, J.C., and Reynolds, P. (eds) <hi rend="italic">Postcolonial
					Literatures of Climate Change</hi>. Brill, Leiden, The Netherlands
				(2022). </p>
			<p>Menely, T. “‘The Present Obfuscation’: Cowper’s Task and the Time of Climate
				Change,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association
					of America,</hi> 127 (2012): 477-92. </p>
			<p>
				<hi rend="italic">Modern Language Association </hi>(n.d.), <ref
					target="https://www.mla.org/Publications/MLA-International-Bibliography/Frequently-Asked-Questions"
					>https://www.mla.org/Publications/MLA-International-Bibliography/Frequently-Asked-Questions</ref>
				(accessed April 11, 2022). </p>
			<p>Murphy, P.D. and Glotfelty, C.B. “Introduction,” <hi rend="italic">ISLE:
					Interdisciplinary Studies in Literature and Environment</hi>, 1.1 (1993):
				1-4.</p>
			<p>Musiol, H. “Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and
				Digital Humanities Prototyping,” <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities
					Quarterly</hi>, 15.2 (2021).</p>
			<p>Nixon, R. “Neoliberalism, Slow Violence, and the Environmental Picaresque,” <hi
					rend="italic">MFS Modern Fiction Studies</hi>, 55.4 (2009): 443-67. </p>
			<p>Nixon, R. <hi rend="italic">Slow Violence and the Environmentalism of the
					Poor</hi>. Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA (2013).</p>
			<p>Nolen, D.S., and Richardson, H.A. “The Search for Landmark Works in English
				Literary Studies: A Citation Analysis,” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of
					Academic Librarianship</hi>, 42.4 (2016): 453-58. </p>
			<p>Nowviskie, B. “Digital Humanities in the Anthropocene,” <hi rend="italic">Digital
					Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>, 30.1 (2015): i4-i15. </p>
			<p>Oh, R.S. “Making Time: Pacific Futures in Kiribati’s <hi rend="italic">Migration
					with Dignity</hi>, Kathy Jetñil-Kijiner’s <hi rend="italic">Iep
				Jaltok</hi>, and Keri Hulme’s <hi rend="italic">Stonefish</hi>,” <hi
					rend="italic">MFS Modern Fiction Studies</hi>, 66.4 (2020): 597-619.</p>
			<p>
				<hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi> (n.d.), <ref
					target="https://www.mla.org/Publications/Journals/PMLA/Submitting-Manuscripts-to-PMLA"
					>https://www.mla.org/Publications/Journals/PMLA/Submitting-Manuscripts-to-PMLA</ref>
				(accessed April 11, 2022).</p>
			<p>Posthumus, S., Sinclair, S. and Poplawski, V. “Digital and Environmental
				Humanities: Strong Networks, Innovative Tools, Interactive Objects,” <hi
					rend="italic">Resilience: A Journal of the Environmental Humanities</hi>,
				5.2 (2018): 156-71.</p>
			<p>Rosenthal, D.J. “Climate-Change Fiction and Poverty Studies: Kingsolver’s <hi
					rend="italic">Flight Behavior</hi>, Diaz’s “Monstro,” and Bacigalupi’s “The
				Tamarisk Hunter,”’ <hi rend="italic">ISLE: Interdisciplinary Studies in
					Literature and Environment</hi>, 27.2 (Spring 2020): 268-86. </p>
			<p>Ross, A. “Climate Change,” in Adamson, Gleason, and Pellow (2016): 37-41. </p>
			<p>Samuelson, M. “Thinking the Anthropocene South,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary
					Literature</hi>, 61.4 (2020): 537-49.</p>
			<p>Sanderman, E., Verhoeven, D. and Mandell, L. “The 21o3’N of separation of the
				Journal of Cultural Analytics: Mapping the first five years.” <hi rend="italic"
					>Journal of Cultural Analytics</hi>, September 21, 2021, <ref
					target="https://culturalanalytics.org/post/1144-the-21-3-n-of-separation-of-the-journal-of-cultural-analytics-mapping-the-first-five-years"
					>https://culturalanalytics.org/post/1144-the-21-3-n-of-separation-of-the-journal-of-cultural-analytics-mapping-the-first-five-years</ref>
				(accessed April 11, 2022).</p>
			<p>Schneider-Mayerson, M. “Whose Odds? The Absence of Climate Justice in American
				Climate Fiction Novels,” <hi rend="italic">ISLE: Interdisciplinary Studies in
					Literature and Environment</hi>, 26.4 (2019): 944-67. </p>
			<p>Schneider-Mayerson, M. and Bellamy, B.R. <hi rend="italic">An Ecotopian
					Lexicon</hi>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2019).</p>
			<p>Singer, M. “The Future that Failed: Speculation and Nostalgia in Francis
				Spufford’s <hi rend="italic">Red Plenty</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary
					Literature</hi>, 61.4 (2020): 483-504.</p>
			<p>So, R.J. “All Models Are Wrong.” <hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the
					Modern Language Association</hi>, 132 (2017): 668-73. </p>
			<p>Steer, P. “The Climates of the Victorian Novel: Seasonality, Weather, and Regional
				Fiction in Britain and Australia,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the
					Modern Language Association of America</hi>, 136.3 (2021): 370-85. </p>
			<p>Streeby, S. <hi rend="italic">Imagining the Future of Climate Change: World-Making
					through Science Fiction and Activism</hi>. University of California Press,
				Oakland (2018). </p>
			<p>Tait, P. “Love, Fear, and Climate Change: Emotions in Drama and Performance,” <hi
					rend="italic">PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association of
					America</hi>, 130 (2015): 1501-05. </p>
			<p>Travis, C., et al. (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Routledge Handbook of the Digital
					Environmental Humanities</hi>. Routledge, New York (2022). </p>
			<p>Underwood, T. “Machine Learning and Human Perspective.” <hi rend="italic">PMLA:
					Publications of the Modern Language Association</hi>, 135 (2020): 92-109. </p>
			<p>Vázquez, D.J. “Their Bones Kept Them Moving: Latinx Studies, Helena María
				Viramontes’s <hi rend="italic">Under the Feet of Jesus</hi>, and the
				Crosscurrents of Ecocriticism,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Literature</hi>,
				58 (2017): 361-91.</p>
			<p>Williams, R. <hi rend="italic">Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society</hi>.
				Oxford University Press, Oxford (2014).</p>
			<p>Xiao, Y. Wu, H., Wang, G. and Mei, H. “Mapping the Worldwide Trends on Energy
				Poverty Research: A Bibliometric Analysis (1999-2019),” <hi rend="italic"
					>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</hi>,
				18.4 (2021): 1764.</p>
			<p>Zyoud, S.H. and Fuchs-Hanusch, D. “Mapping of climate change research in the Arab
				world: a bibliometric analysis.” <hi rend="italic">Environmental Science and
					Pollution Research International</hi>, 27.3 (2020): 3523-40.</p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl/>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
