<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
	xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Exploring Combinatorial Methods to Produce Sonnets: An
					Overview of the Oupoco Project</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Frédérique <dhq:family>Mélanie-Becquet</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>LATTICE (CNRS &amp; ENS/PSL &amp; Univ. Sorbonne
						Nouvelle)</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>frederique.melanie@ens.psl.eu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Clément <dhq:family>Plancq</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>LATTICE (CNRS &amp; ENS/PSL &amp; Univ. Sorbonne
						Nouvelle)</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>clement.plancq@univ-tours.fr</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Claude <dhq:family>Grunspan</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>LATTICE (CNRS &amp; ENS/PSL &amp; Univ. Sorbonne
						Nouvelle)</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>grunspanclaude@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Mylène <dhq:family>Maignant</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>LATTICE (CNRS &amp; ENS/PSL &amp; Univ. Sorbonne
						Nouvelle)</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>maignant.mylene@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Matthieu <dhq:family>Raffard</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>Atelier Raffard-Roussel</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>raffard.roussel@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Fiammetta <dhq:family>Ghedini</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>RIVA Illustrations </dhq:affiliation>
					<!--<email/>-->
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Thierry <dhq:family>Poibeau</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>LATTICE (CNRS &amp; ENS/PSL &amp; Univ. Sorbonne
						Nouvelle)</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>thierry.poibeau@ens.psl.eu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000734<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language extent="original" ident="en"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
					<term corresp="#access"/>
					<term corresp="#corpora"/>
					<term corresp="#elit"/>
					<term corresp="#gender"/>
					<term corresp="#literary_studies"/>
					<term corresp="#materialisms"/>
					<term corresp="#nlp"/>
					<term corresp="#project_report"/>
					<term corresp="#users"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>poetry</item>
						<item>language generation</item>
						<item>natural language processing</item>
						<item>poetry generation</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000734/000734.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="original" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>In this paper, we describe Oupoco (l’Ouvroir de Poésie Combinatoire), a system producing
					new sonnets by recombining lines of poetry from existing sonnets, following an idea that
						<name>Queneau</name> described in his book <title rend="italic">Cent Mille Milliards
						de poèmes</title> (<title rend="italic">A Hundred Thousand Billion Poems</title>,
					1961). We first give the rationale of the project and review past experiments in poetry
					generation using combinatorial methods. We then demonstrate different outputs of our
					implementation (a Web site, a Twitter bot and a specifically developed device, called the
						<title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title>) based on a corpus of 19th
					century French poetry. We describe how this project was an opportunity to work with
					artists and reach a new audience through the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à
						poésie</title>, and also through a video clip that frequently served as an
					introduction to the project. Our goal is to revive people’s interest in poetry by giving
					access to automatically produced sonnets through original and entertaining channels and
					devices.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="section01">
				<head>1 Introduction: Combinatorial Literature, from <name>Queneau</name> to Oupoco</head>
				<p>The Oupoco project is a project exploring combinatorial methods to produce poetry by
					recombining existing lines of poetry. The starting point of the project was the book by
						<name>Raymond Queneau</name>, <title rend="italic">Cent Mille Milliards de
						poèmes</title> (<title rend="italic">A Hundred Thousand Billion Poems</title>, in
					English) <ptr target="#queneau1961"/>.</p>
				<p>This book is composed of ten sonnets, each line being printed on a separate strip of paper
						(<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>), allowing the reader, by freely combining the
					different lines, to potentially produce and read a hundred thousand billion different
					sonnets. This combinatorial approach (the main characteristic of the book) encourages the
					reader to play with the meanings of the lines, with the various language registers, or
					simply to have fun with the book. It is this stimulating relationship between poetry and
					constraints that we wanted to reproduce and that was the mainspring of our project.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure01">
					<head><title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Cent Mille Milliards de poèmes</title> by
							<name>Queneau</name>, both a book and an artistic creation</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>An open book with its pages cut along each line of text</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p><name>Queneau</name>’s book seems an ideal candidate to be transposed to a computer, since
					a machine can very easily combine lines and produce a comprehensive list of all the
					possible poems. However, <name>Queneau</name>’s work is still under copyright, which
					should normally prevent one from putting the sonnets contained in his book online,
					although numerous implementations can in fact be found on the Internet. Nevertheless, this
					is one of the reasons why, instead of working on <name>Queneau</name>’s poems, we decided
					to focus on freely available ones, which also helped develop more original and challenging
					research. Hence, an important part of the project consisted in constituting a collection
					of 19th century French sonnets.</p>
				<p>Beyond the availability of relevant collections of poetry, which facilitated the creation
					of our corpus, 19th century poetry also appeared as a fertile ground to reflect upon the
					sonnet and to work and play with various constraints. This means that the original poems
					first have to be analyzed so as to determine the rhyme, as well as other features (line
					length, topic of the sonnet, etc.). Our project thus deals with analysis, as much as with
					the generation of poetry. We will see that the project gave birth to various outputs,
					including artistic ones. Finally, we made several public demos, showing that such a
					project can have an impact on the general public as well as on children in school, in a
					learning perspective.</p>
				<p>The structure of the paper is as follows. We will first examine some past work and give our
					motivations for this project (<ref target="#section02">Section 2</ref>). We then describe
					the corpus (<ref target="#section03">Section 3</ref>), the approach for rhyme analysis
						(<ref target="#section04">Section 4</ref>), and the constraints on the generation
					process (<ref target="#section05">Section 5</ref>). We conclude the technical part of the
					paper with an evaluation of the sonnets thus generated (<ref target="#section06">Section
						6</ref>). We then describe our collaboration with artists, to produce the <title
						rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à Poésie</title>, and the Oupoco video clip (<ref
						target="#section07">Section 7</ref>). This led to different demonstrations and some
					outreach initiatives with the public (<ref target="#section08">Section 8</ref>). We
					conclude with a discussion on computers and creativity (<ref target="#section09">Section
						9</ref>).</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section02">
				<head>2 Computational Combinatorial Poetry, from <name>Queneau</name> to Oupoco</head>
				<p>In this section, we examine some past experiments to generate poetry with computers in the
					context of the <name>Oulipo</name>
					<note><name>Oulipo</name> (<title rend="quotes" xml:lang="fr">Ouvroir de littérature
							potentielle</title>; roughly translated: <q>workshop of potential literature</q>
						and stylized <name>Oulipo</name>) is a loose gathering of (mainly) French-speaking
						writers and mathematicians who seek to create works using constrained writing
						techniques. (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oulipo"
						>Wikipedia</ref>)</note>. We then describe the rationale behind our project, inspired
					by <name>Queneau</name> but also largely departing from <name>Oulipo</name>’s original
					ideas.</p>
				<div xml:id="section02.1">
					<head>2.1 Transposing <name>Queneau</name>’s Book to a Computer</head>
					<p>As mentioned in the introduction, there have been various attempts to transpose
							<name>Queneau</name>’s book to a computer. In fact, in 1961, immediately after the
						publication of the book, a first attempt was made by Dimitri Starynkevitch, a French
						computer scientist, working on a computer of the time (a CAB 500, to be precise,
						according to Bens (<ref target="#bens2005">2005</ref>); see <ref target="#figure02"
							>Figure 2</ref> and <ptr target="#starynkevitch1990"/>. Baillehache (<ref
							target="#baillehache2021">2021</ref>) reports <name>Oulipo</name>’s answer to
						Starynkevitch’s program: <cit><quote rend="inline">We wished that M. Starynkevitch
								would explain the method used; we hoped that the choice of the lines was not
								left to randomness</quote><ptr target="#bens2005" loc="79"/></cit>. As
						Baillehache explains, this answer <quote rend="inline" source="#baillehache2021"
							>reflects mistrust against randomness</quote>; moreover, it shows Oulipians’ lack
						of interest, in 1961, in the process that would make it possible to generate poetry
						indefinitely and automatically, which may seem surprising at first glance.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure02">
						<head>A picture of the CAB 500 computer (designed by the French company SEA, around
							1957, by Alice Recoque. <ptr target="#starynkevitch1990"/></head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpeg"/>
						<figDesc>A man sits at an old computer</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<p>It is indeed not entirely clear why <name>Queneau</name> and <name>Oulipo</name>
						reacted in this way. Baillehache (<ref target="#baillehache2021">2021</ref>), after
						Bloomfield and Campaignolle (<ref target="#bloomfield_etal2016">2016</ref>),
						attributed it to <name>Oulipo</name>'s aversion to randomness, seen as opposite to the
						idea of constraints that the group explored intensively in its literature.</p>
					<p>While this is possible, we also think that the main goal of <name>Queneau</name> was
						not just to produce an infinite number of poems generated randomly. The book, with its
						strips of paper, is in fact more than a book, it is also a piece of art and an object
						conceived as a device to be manipulated by people. The whole idea is to assemble lines
						of verse, look at the result, try other possibilities and produce silly, funny, or
						just unexpected poems. The transposition to a computer in 1961, and most of the
						implementations one can find online nowadays, do not allow this: they produce poems,
						one at a time, randomly, without any possible interaction with the end-user or the
						reader.</p>
					<p>Since the advent of the Web in the 1990s, many other implementations (transposing
							<name>Queneau</name>’s book and ideas online) have been proposed over the years.
						But there were many attempts even before that. Leonardo/Olats and Philippe Bootz (<ref
							target="#leonardo_etal2006">2006</ref>) give an interesting survey of what they
						call <term>combinatorial generative literature</term> (<term xml:lang="fr">littérature
							generative combinatoire</term>, in French). The authors report that Paul Braffort,
						from <name>Oulipo</name>, developed a computer version of the book in 1975, for an
						exhibition (Europalia) in Brussels. Tibor Papp, another enthusiast of computer
						literature, who worked with Bootz in the 1980s, also developed in 1988 an electronic
						version of the book (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>). Last but not least, a
						version was developed by Antoine Denize and Bernard Magné for the CD-ROM <title
							rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Machines à écrire</title>, in which the text is
						enhanced with graphic effects that were not part of <name>Queneau</name>’s original
						project (<ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). This CD-Rom, published by one of the
						most prestigious publishers in France (who is also the publisher of
							<name>Queneau</name>’s work), had a wider audience that the previous programs,
						which reached only a limited readership.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure03">
						<head>A screenshot of Tibor Papp’s implementation, in 1988 (reproduced from <ptr
								target="#leonardo_etal2006"/> thanks to the kind authorization of Philippe
							Bootz).</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
						<figDesc>Brightly colored lines of text display a rhyme structure</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure04">
						<head>Antoine Denize’s version, enhanced with graphic effects, for the CD-Rom <title
								rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Machines à écrire</title> for the French publisher
								<name>Gallimard</name>
							<ptr target="#denize_etal1999"/>, (reproduced from <ptr
								target="#leonardo_etal2006"/> thanks to the kind authorization of Philippe
							Bootz).</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
						<figDesc>Individual letters floating over a blurred portrait</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<p>In the 1990s, a natural move consisted in implementing versions on the Web. A memorable
						event occurred in 1997, when a French computer science student was summoned to court
						by a descendant of <name>Queneau</name>, because he had put online a version
						replicating <name>Queneau</name>’s book (thus breaching the copyright). The event
						attracted some attention, at least in France, as one of the first cases sending
						someone to court for a violation of literary property on the Internet<note>The
							decision of the court can be found online: <ref
								target="https://www.legalis.net/jurisprudences/tribunal-de-grande-instance-de-paris-ordonnance-de-refere-du-5-mai-1997/"
								>https://www.legalis.net/jurisprudences/tribunal-de-grande-instance-de-paris-ordonnance-de-refere-du-5-mai-1997/</ref></note>.
						In the end, the court sentence was mild (as the program had already been removed from
						the Internet). Since then, the magnitude of the problem of online piracy (the practice
						of downloading and distributing copyrighted works digitally without permission) has
						downgraded this episode to a mere incident. To the best of our knowledge, nobody else
						since then has encountered problems with online versions of <name>Queneau</name>’s
						book, even if they infringe copyright laws. Their readership is in any case extremely
						limited.</p>
					<p>While <name>Oulipo</name> members initially showed some interest in computers, this did
						not last for very long, as we have seen above. To revive this topic, a specific group,
						called <name>Alamo</name> (<foreign xml:lang="fr">Atelier de Littérature Assistée par
							la Mathématique et les Ordinateurs</foreign>), comprising members of the
							<name>Oulipo</name> but also (and mostly) academics and computer scientists
						interested in the connections between literature and computers, was created in 1982.
						While this group developed interesting ideas and pieces of software, it remained
						independent of the <name>Oulipo</name>, and in turn the <name>Oulipo</name> did not
						show a great interest in the activities of this group. Moreover, the rapid
						obsolescence of computer programs made their production hard to maintain and showcase.
						More recently, Natalie Berkman (<ref target="#berkman2017">2017</ref>, <ref
							target="#berkman2017">2022</ref>) tried to reproduce some of the early experiments
						of the <name>Oulipo</name> with computers and, more specifically, she tried to
						understand why the <name>Oulipo</name> quickly abandoned the idea of exploring this
						topic. Developing a program on a computer in the 1960s was complex (it involved
						preparing large sets of punch cards for example; it is no coincidence that the Alamo
						was created in 1982, with the advent of the personal computer). Moreover, it was not
						really possible at that time to represent the whole complexity of a language on a
						computer, and computers did not offer any real advantages compared to mathematical or
						formal models described on paper. As a result, in Berkman’s words (<ref
							target="#berkman2022">2022</ref>), the <name>Oulipo</name>’s members showed <quote
							rend="inline" source="#berkman2022">a clear preference for abstract mathematical
							thought — patterns and structure — rather than the procedural tendencies of
							applied mathematics</quote>. But let’s now come back to our own experiment.</p>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="section02.2">
					<head>2.2 Beyond <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Cent Mille Milliards de
						poèmes</title>, our own experiment</head>
					<p>In an interview with Georges Charbonnier (<ref target="#charbonnier1962">1962</ref>),
							<name>Queneau</name> explained that <term>potential literature</term> (<term
							xml:lang="fr">la littérature potentielle</term>) is <cit><quote rend="inline">the
								search for forms, [...] for new structures which can then be used by writers
								in whatever way they like</quote><ptr target="#charbonnier1962" loc="140"
							/></cit><note>In the original French: <quote rend="inline"
								source="#charbonnier1962" xml:lang="fr">la recherche de formes, [...] de
								structures nouvelles et qui, ensuite, pourront être utilisées par les
								écrivains de la façon qui leur plaira</quote></note>. Our own experiment here
						aims at reviving not only an interest in poetry but also aims at exploring new ways of
						writing, at a time when text is everywhere around us. For this, we also took
						inspiration from the notion of <term>uncreative writing</term>, as defined by Kenneth
						Goldsmith <ptr target="#goldsmith2011"/>
						<ptr target="#goldsmith2019"/>.</p>
					<p><title rend="italic">Uncreative Writing</title> challenges conventional notions of
						creativity and authorship in the realm of literature. Goldsmith's approach advocates
						for a departure from the traditional, romanticized image of the writer as a solitary
						genius crafting original, imaginative works. Instead, he promotes the idea that
						creativity can also be found in the act of appropriation and remixing, where writers
						repurpose existing texts, often without significant alteration, to create something
						new and thought-provoking. This notion blurs the lines between authorship, plagiarism,
						and creativity, emphasizing the power of the remix culture and the vast reservoir of
						existing texts as a source of inspiration. Uncreative Writing invites us to reconsider
						the boundaries of creativity in the digital age, where information is abundant and
						easily accessible, fostering a literary landscape that celebrates the art of
						recontextualization and the collaborative nature of language itself.</p>
					<p>Another important point, especially if we place ourselves in the continuation of the
							<name>Oulipo</name> tradition, is the role of randomness (or chance) in generating
						texts. In Jacques Bens' account of the early <name>Oulipo</name> meetings, there is
						extensive discussion on this topic, and <name>Queneau</name> believed that writers
						should always be conscious of the constraints they are using and leave nothing to
						chance. In this sense, <name>Oulipo</name> wanted to affirm its departure from other
						literary movements, first and foremost surrealism. Our project aligns with this idea,
						in a way: we focus on sonnets, and the goal is to respect as much as possible the
						constraints of this specific poetic form. However, the notion of chance should not be
						confused with the notion of <term>potential
							literature<!-- "literature" added by editor --></term> (<term xml:lang="fr">la
							littérature potentielle</term>): there is still an infinity of possible
						(potential) poems, even when taking into account all the constraints that apply <ptr
							target="#fournel1972"/>
						<ptr target="#oulipo1973"/>
						<ptr target="#oulipo1981"/>
						<ptr target="#oulipo2002"/>.</p>
					<p>Producing computational combinatorial poetry inspired by <name>Raymond Queneau</name>'s
							<title rend="italic">One Hundred Thousand Billion Poems</title> using publicly
						available poems opens up a large number of possibilities. By dissecting and
						reassembling publicly accessible verses through code, we can explore an infinity of
						poetic possibilities, taking into account constraints. Each line and word are placed
						in a new context, forging connections and juxtapositions that transcend the individual
						poems' original contexts. Through this experiment, we pay homage to
							<name>Queneau</name>'s legacy while showcasing the potential of technology to
						popularize poetry, enabling anyone to explore poetry and computational creativity.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section03">
				<head>3 The Corpus</head>
				<p>The first part of this research consisted in gathering a corpus of French sonnets from the
					19th and early 20th century. Although there are famous sonnets from the 16th and 17th
					century in French, we choose to focus mainly on the 19th century in order to build a more
					homogeneous corpus, both from a thematic and linguistic point of view (19th century French
					is more normalized than the language a few centuries before). We first used resources that
					were freely available on the Web, especially from the Gutenberg project and
					Wikisource.</p>
				<p>The <name><foreign xml:lang="fr">Bibliothèque nationale de France</foreign></name> (BnF)
					has an even larger collection of poems since it is in charge of legal deposit for France.
					A large proportion of these books has been digitized and is available on the Gallica
					website (maintained by the BnF). The BnF was thus able to select and extract a large
					number of poetry books, which included various collections, anthologies and essays (all
					the data are in the XML Alto format). We selected the books with an OCR quality score
					above 98%, and used the BnF API to collect metadata about the books.</p>
				<p>As these are complete books, not everything in them was relevant. Some books were simply
					irrelevant (e.g., critical essays that do not contain poetry), some parts had to be
					removed (preface, introduction, critical notes) and, even once we had reduced the text to
					poetry, we still needed to extract sonnets. In order to do this, several heuristics were
					used, thanks to Python scripts aiming at retrieving poems in the form: two quatrains
					followed by two tercets (the form of a sonnet). This heuristic (based simply on the
					analysis of space and empty lines between verses) proved quite robust and efficient, even
					if not perfect. Thanks to the resource provided by the BnF, we were able to considerably
					increase the number of sonnets in the database, with relatively few errors according to
					our estimation.</p>
				<p>As a result, the Oupoco Database is a collection of 4,872 French sonnets. 760 different
					authors are represented: 4,414 sonnets written by men (660 different authors), and 439
					sonnets written by women (107 authors), which leaves 19 sonnets to which we have not been
					able to assign an author. A specific license related to the source they come from is
					attached to all the sonnets, but all are freely available and can be reused for free
					(under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license), see <ref
						target="#table01">Table 1</ref>.</p>
				<table xml:id="table01">
					<head>Sources of the sonnets in the corpus</head>
					<row role="label">
						<cell>Source</cell>
						<cell>Number of Sonnets</cell>
						<cell>License/Comments</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="data">
						<cell>BnF</cell>
						<cell>3,979</cell>
						<cell>CC-BY-SA-NC</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="data">
						<cell>Wikisource</cell>
						<cell>772</cell>
						<cell>CC BY-SA 3.0</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="data">
						<cell>Web</cell>
						<cell>67</cell>
						<cell>Source (Blog) cited in the database</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="data">
						<cell>Books (anthology)</cell>
						<cell>37</cell>
						<cell>Manual collections of sonnets from different anthologies</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="data">
						<cell>Malherbe project</cell>
						<cell>7</cell>
						<cell>No explicit license (<ref target="https://git.unicaen.fr/malherbe/corpus"
								>https://git.unicaen.fr/malherbe/corpus</ref>) </cell>
					</row>
				</table>
				<p>This database can be used for various teaching and research purposes, especially in the
					following domains: literature studies, corpus linguistics, digital humanities, arts and
					technology. All major French poets from the 19th century are included in the database, but
					also some lesser known ones. Each sonnet is encoded in XML format along with the related
					metadata; a TEI version of the database is publicly available (for further explanation and
					access to the source files, see our data paper <ptr target="#melanie_etal2022"/> and the
					related Zenodo repository: <ref target="https://zenodo.org/deposit/5646940"
						>https://zenodo.org/deposit/5646940</ref>).</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section04">
				<head>4 Rhyme Analysis</head>
				<p>The OuPoCo project has nothing to do with the recent neural approach to poetry generation
						<ptr target="#ghazvininejad_etal2017"/>
					<ptr target="#vandecruys2020"/>, but it does require accessing a formal representation of
					rhymes (as proposed by Beaudouin in <ref target="#beaudouin2002">2002</ref><note>For more
						details, see <title rend="none">The Metrometer</title>, a tool developed to analyze
						French verse <ptr target="#beaudouin_etal1996"/> that is however, obsolete
						today.</note>). We will not detail here the (complex) rules of French versification,
					but two main difficulties need to be mentioned. First, as is widely known, pronunciation
					and spelling differ greatly in French, as in English. There is thus a need to first
					transform written texts into a phonetic transcription. Second, French has a specific and
					quite complex versification system, which is different (and far more complex) than simple
					phonetics. The second stage consists then in transforming the phonetic transcription into
					a representation that corresponds to French versification rules.</p>
				<p>In order to do this, the first step is to produce a phonetic transcription of the last word
					of each line. Phonetization (the process of transforming a word into a phonetic
					transcription) was done with eSpeak, a free software available on the Web (<ref
						target="http://espeak.sourceforge.net">http://espeak.sourceforge.net</ref>), that
					provided satisfactory results on our data. We analyze the whole verse and not only the
					last word of each line, so that a full rhythmic analysis is possible. However, the
					phonetic transcription provided by eSpeak is not enough.</p>
				<p>It is not enough because not everything that has the same sound in French can rhyme: this
					is, in a way, the beauty of poetry, and specific rules have to be defined to go from a
					phonetic transcription to a representation that corresponds to the rules of versification.
					Let’s take an example. The two words <foreign xml:lang="fr">aimé</foreign> and <foreign
						xml:lang="fr">aimée</foreign> have the same phonetic transcription, but do not rhyme,
					according to French versification rules (masculine and feminine words, in this case words
					that end with -é, as opposed to -ée, do not rhyme); there are also cases where the
					phonetic transcription is slightly different but the words actually rhyme (for example
					words ending with the sounds [e] and [ε]). All these cases are relatively frequent and
					must be handled appropriately.</p>
				<p>A series of rules written in Python had thus to be defined to obtain a proper analysis of
					rhyme derived from the phonetic transcription (especially of the last word of each line).
					These rules were manually defined and maintained, as there is no way they could be learnt
					directly from the data. Some of the rules can be easily derived from a treatise on French
					versification, but others are directly linked to the output of eSpeak, as we have to
					overwrite some phonetic distinctions produced by this software that are not relevant to
					analyze poetry.</p>
				<p>The sonnet generator uses this analysis to produce sonnets, with different possible
					structures, respecting the rules of French versification (the code and the resources used,
					especially the sonnet database, are open source and freely available for research, see:
						<ref target="https://github.com/clement-plancq/oupoco-api"
						>https://github.com/clement-plancq/oupoco-api</ref>).</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section05">
				<head>5 Constraints on the Generation Process</head>
				<p>In the footsteps of <name>Oulipo</name> and following the comments of <name>Queneau</name>
					who did not like the idea of purely random poetry generation, we chose to implement
					constraints to enable the reader to interact with the database, control the generation
					process in different ways, and discover 19th century French literature from a different
					and more playful angle.</p>
				<p>The first constraint corresponds to the different forms of sonnets that have been proposed
					in the course of history. Giacomo da Lentini, Petrarch, Marot, Peletier, Shakespeare and
					Spenser all proposed and initiated slightly different rhyming schemes (for example, Marot
					proposed the following structure: ABBA ABBA CCD EED, while Petrarch proposed several
					slightly different structures: ABBA ABBA CDE CDE / ABBA ABBA CDC DCD / ABBA ABBA CDE DCE,
					etc.). All these forms of sonnets are available and the user can choose any structure s/he
					prefers for generation.</p>
				<p>The second constraint enables the reader to generate random sonnets from texts within a
					chosen time framework. In other words, if the reader selects a period of twenty or thirty
					years that s/he wants to explore on the timeline, sonnets will be generated according to
					this time frame. This option makes it possible to have a quick overview of the productions
					of French sonnets over a period. Thanks to this option, it is for example possible to note
					that very few French sonnets were written at the beginning of the 19th century while their
					production tended to increase 20 years or so later.</p>
				<p>The third constraint deals with the authors themselves. The reader can select one or
					several poets as the source corpus to generate new sonnets. It is thus possible to explore
					the poems written by Baudelaire for instance, or to combine them with those written by
					Rimbaud or Verlaine.</p>
				<p>The fourth constraint is based on a semantic analysis of the original sonnets. Six main
					topics were identified (beauty, love, death, melancholy, nature, spirituality), later on
					reduced to five, as melancholy and death were hard to distinguish (beauty and love are
					also very close from a linguistic point of view, as well as death and spirituality, but
					they are nevertheless different enough to be annotated and recognized with sufficient
					accuracy). A sample of sonnets was annotated using these categories (50 sonnets per
					category) and a classifier was subsequently trained on the resulting manually annotated
					corpus. It is thus possible to generate sonnets on a specific topic. Note that the
					annotation operates at the sonnet level, whereas generation operates at the level of the
					individual line of verse. However, we assume that the theme gives a general flavor to the
					text, and that not every line has to be relevant from a thematic point of view</p>
				<p>This annotation is however highly subjective. Sometimes most of the poem is on a specific
					topic, while the last line gives a completely different perspective. See for example
						<title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Le dormeur du val</title>, by Rimbaud. This poem is
					highly bucolic, clearly about nature since it is about a man peacefully sleeping in a
					field — except that the last line completely changes the whole perspective, by revealing
					that the man is in fact a dead soldier. In cases like this, we chose to annotate the
					dominant topic (the one which covers most of the poem), <q>nature</q> in this case (but
						<q>death</q> would also have been relevant, and maybe more relevant if we take into
					account the deep meaning of the sonnet). All this reveals the subjectivity of any
					annotation. During the experiment, inter-annotator agreement was not high, but still
					acceptable and far beyond chance.</p>
				<p>In the end, all these constraints are available through a very simple interface on the
					project web site. <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> gives an overview of this
					interface. The more constraints one chooses, the fewer the potential sonnets generated
					(basically, each constraint restricts the possible choices and therefore the number of
					lines available for generation).</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure05">
					<head>The project’s web site interface (accessible at: <ref target="https://oupoco.org/fr"
							>https://oupoco.org/fr</ref>). On the right, a sonnet produced by the system; on
						the left, the panel with the different constraints that the user can
						manipulate.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>Menus with checkboxes and radio buttons; a sonnet</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>From a computational point of view, the approach is quite simple. However, it is difficult
					to control on the fly the number of sonnets that can be generated, depending on the number
					of constraints chosen by the end user. It is however important to keep track of this,
					otherwise the end user may frequently arrive at a dead end, with a number of constraints
					that prevents the possibility of generating new sonnets (a basic rule being that a line
					cannot rhyme with itself, and cannot be selected twice).</p>
				<p>Lastly, we wanted to take gender into account, and highlight female authors, who are
					underrepresented in most poetry anthologies. A special effort was made to identify sonnets
					by female authors, as the initial corpus (from Wikisource) contained mostly male authors.
					Finally, thanks to the data extracted from the BnF corpus and to intensive manual work, we
					were able to identify 439 sonnets written by 107 female authors (see <ref
						target="#section03">section 3</ref>). This was enough to produce a specific system
					highlighting the creativity of the female authors, most of whom had remained in the dark
					so far. The system is available on the Oupoco web site, in a specific tab<note><ref
							target="https://oupoco.org/fr/sonnet-feminin/index.html"
							>https://oupoco.org/fr/sonnet-feminin/index.html</ref> (last consulted,
						7/11/2022).</note>, see <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure06">
					<head>Female authors in Oupoco</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
					<figDesc>Word cloud of author names where females are grouped</figDesc>
				</figure>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section06">
				<head>6 Evaluation</head>
				<p>Poetry is, by nature, hard to evaluate. We did not perform a formal evaluation, as we were
					unable to provide meaningful evaluation criteria <ptr target="#gervas2013"/>. In our case,
					the first thing to be done was simply to examine some poems produced by the system, and
					assess their quality. Due to the nature of the generative process, the generated poems
					make more or less sense, and are more or less pleasant to read.</p>
				<p>We identified different causes that affect the quality of the text produced, mainly related
					to syntax. The most frequent issues are: a pronoun that cannot be linked to any other
					element in the sentence, or a segment that does not fit with the preceding part of the
					sentence. Both situations reveal in fact the same problem: one cannot obtain a coherent
					text simply by assembling smaller chunks of text obtained randomly. This was already one
					of the main problems of statistical machine translation (based on segments of text that
					the system had to assemble to form full sentences, see Poibeau (<ref target="#poibeau2017"
						>2017</ref>): because of the limitations of the approach, the resulting sentences were
					often slightly incorrect and grammatically odd. This has been largely solved with the
					modern neural approach, since it is now possible to encode full sentences directly
					(through vectors and deep learning approaches).</p>
				<p>But let’s come back to our system and examine a specific example. The following poem was
					fully automatically produced by our system <!--Editor's parenthetical addition-->(emphasis
					by <hi style="color:#AA0000">color difference</hi> added by the authors).</p>
				<lg>
					<lg>
						<l>Les vendangeurs lassés ayant rompu leurs lignes,</l>
						<l>La trirème d’argent blanchit le fleuve noir</l>
						<l>Sachant que notre cœur s’emporte et se résigne,</l>
						<l><hi style="color:#AA0000">Étranger tes sanglots</hi> dans le fatal mouchoir.</l>
					</lg>
					<lg>
						<l>C’est par un ciel pareil, tout blanc du vol des cygnes,</l>
						<l><hi style="color:#AA0000">L’éclair laisse, en fuyant</hi>, l’horizon triste et
							noir.</l>
						<l>Je hais le mouvement qui déplace les lignes,</l>
						<l>Et son verger fleuri n’est qu’un vaste encensoir.</l>
					</lg>
					<lg>
						<l>Mais, le corps étendu, n'oublions pas que l'âme,</l>
						<l><hi style="color:#AA0000">Ils</hi> me rendent aveugle au jour qui te proclame</l>
						<l>Si proche et déjà loin de celui que j’aimais.</l>
					</lg>
					<lg>
						<l>Haute théologie et solide morale,</l>
						<l>Et maintenant j’habite, hélas! et pour jamais,</l>
						<l><hi style="color:#AA0000">S’envole, tinte et meurt</hi> dans le ciel rose et
							pâle.</l>
					</lg>
				</lg>
				<p>Any native reader of French<!-- "of French" added by editor --> will be disturbed by things
					such as <word xml:lang="fr">ils</word> (<word>they</word>) in the third tercet, that
					cannot be related to anything in the surrounding text. In the first quatrain, <word
						xml:lang="fr">étranger</word> would fit as an apostrophe, but the rest of the line
						(…<word xml:lang="fr">tes sanglots</word>…) show that the noun cannot be interpreted
					as an apostrophe and, in fact, the whole line cannot be linked to what precedes. The same
					situation arises in the second quatrain (where <word xml:lang="fr">l’éclair laisse, en
						fuyant</word>… cannot be attached to the surrounding text), and again in the last
					tercet (<word xml:lang="fr">s’envole, tinte et meurt</word> needs a subject that cannot be
					found in the text).</p>
				<p>All these are clear examples that violate syntax and make the whole poem odd and clearly
					not the result of human inspiration. It is a pity because otherwise, from a semantic point
					of view, there are some signs of coherence in the fact that the same topics can be found
					in the different lines. For example, in the second quatrain, <word xml:lang="fr">le
						ciel</word> (<word>the sky</word>), <word xml:lang="fr">l’horizon</word> (<word>the
						horizon</word>), <word xml:lang="fr">les lignes</word> (<word>the lines</word>) all
					refer to the vast surroundings of the poet, whereas <word xml:lang="fr">vol des
						cygnes</word> (<word>flight of swans</word>), <word xml:lang="fr">l’éclair</word>
						(<word>lightning</word>) and <!--translated from author's original "et"-->
					<word xml:lang="fr">le verger</word> (<word>the orchard</word>) are clear allusions to
					nature. Even in the first quatrain, a link could be established between <word
						xml:lang="fr">les sanglots</word> (<word>sobs</word>), <word xml:lang="fr">le
						mouchoir</word> (<word>the handkerchief</word>), and <word xml:lang="fr">le fleuve
						noir</word> (<word>the black river</word>), and <word xml:lang="fr">notre cœur [qui]
						s’emporte et se résigne</word> (<word>our heart [that] gets carried away and is
						resigned</word>), all this being of course signs of sadness.</p>
				<p>We did not try to solve these issues, for example the syntactic incoherencies. Solving them
					would considerably complexify the system, which we wanted to keep as simple as possible.
					Note also that the more constraints there are, the more the number of available lines at
					each position is reduced. Lastly, working on these issues would involve implementing many
					heuristics without any clear scientific benefit (except that of producing better poems,
					which one could say is the main goal, though).</p>
				<p>The most obvious approach would be to move to neural poetry generation (a completely
					different approach), which we have explored but decided not to include in this system for
					the reasons given above: it would complexify the whole architecture and, for example,
					would require a GPU for training and for testing (as well as for the system in
					production). We considered that it was more interesting and more promising to explore
					neural poetry generation separately, as a new system and a new domain of research. We will
					not address this here as it is beyond the scope of this paper.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section07">
				<head>7 Collaboration with Artists</head>
				<p>From the beginning, Oupoco was not just an engineering or a research project. Because the
					project deals with poetry, and because its main objective is to interest people in it, it
					was important to go beyond a pure algorithm, and also to offer new ways to access
					poetry.</p>
				<p><name>Queneau</name> designed his book as an object, as a device that the reader can
					manipulate, with which the reader can interact and produce her/his own poetry. It was thus
					important to us to also materialize the project through an innovative device that would be
					both intriguing and appealing. In order to do this, we collaborated with two artists who
					belong to a collective called <name>Atelier Raffard-Roussel</name>. This is what they say
					themselves about this project and this collaboration:<note><foreign xml:lang="fr">Nous
							sommes intervenus dans le cadre [du projet oupoco] pour proposer une œuvre qui
							puisse donner à cette recherche une nouvelle forme de visibilité et de
							matérialité.Pour cela, nous avons réalisé un dispositif simple qui permet à un
							utilisateur de générer un poème automatiquement en tournant une manivelle. Par
							l’intermédiaire d’un petit écran périphérique, l’utilisateur est également informé
							de la quantité d’énergie électrique qu’il a été nécessaire de mobiliser pour
							générer ce nouveau poème. S’il le souhaite, il peut essayer de deviner le
							fonctionnement de la <title rend="italic">Boîte à Poésie</title> à travers les
							parois transparentes.Ce dispositif, à la fois mécanique et électronique, fait
							directement référence au Condensation Cube de Hans Haacke qui peut être considéré
							comme une œuvre jalon de l’art conceptuel américain, et qui est presque
							contemporain du livre de Raymond <name>Queneau</name> puisqu’elle a été réalisée
							en 1965. Il nous semble que l’on peut voir une grande similitude entre ces deux
							œuvres dans la mesure où chacune d’entre elles réagit pour ainsi dire aux
							conditions de leur exposition ; le Condensation Cube produit de la vapeur d’eau en
							fonction du taux d’hygrométrie du lieu dans lequel il est exposé et le livre de
								<name>Queneau</name> produit des poèmes en fonction de la chance et l’humeur
							du lecteur.Ce projet a été pour nous l’occasion de nous confronter à la
							réalisation d’un objet qui puisse être à la fois une machine et une œuvre d’art et
							de réfléchir aux enjeux écologiques qu’implique une telle pratique. Qu’est-ce qui
							relève de la machine dans les œuvres d’art et en retour qu’est-ce qui relève de la
							sculpture dans les machines qui nous entourent ? Comment rendre mieux visible
							l’impact environnemental qu’entraine la construction d’une machine ou d’une œuvre
							d’art?</foreign></note></p>
				<quote rend="block"><p> We intervened in [the Oupoco Project] to propose a work that could
						give this research a new form of visibility and materiality.</p>
					<p> To do this, we made a simple device that allows a user to generate a poem
						automatically by turning a crank. Via a small peripheral screen, the user is also
						informed of the amount of electrical energy that was required to generate this new
						poem. If they wish, they can try to guess how the <title rend="italic">Poetry
							Box</title> works through the transparent walls.</p>
					<p> This device, which is both mechanical and electronic, is a direct reference to Hans
						Haacke's <title rend="italic">Condensation Cube</title>, which can be considered a
						milestone work of American conceptual art, and which is almost contemporary with
							<name>Raymond Queneau</name>'s book, since it was made in 1965. It seems to us
						that there is a great similarity between these two works in that each of them reacts,
						so to speak, to the conditions of their exhibition; the <title rend="italic"
							>Condensation Cube</title> produces water vapour according to the humidity of the
						place in which it is exhibited and <name>Queneau</name>'s book produces poems
						according to the luck and mood of the reader.</p>
					<p> This project was an opportunity for us to tackle the creation of an object that could
						be both a machine and a work of art and to reflect on the ecological issues involved
						in such a practice. What is machine-like in works of art and what is sculpture-like in
						the machines that surround us? How can we make the environmental impact of building a
						machine or a work of art more visible?</p></quote>
				<p>The resulting device, the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title> (<title
						rend="italic">Poetry box</title>), is pictured on <ref target="#figure07">Figure
						7</ref>.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure07">
					<head>The <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title>, integrating the
						Oupoco sonnet generator, developed by <name>Atelier Raffard-Roussel</name>. See <ref
							target="http://www.raffard-roussel.com/fr/projets-boite-a-poesie/"
							>http://www.raffard-roussel.com/fr/projets-boite-a-poesie/</ref> for
						details.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
					<figDesc>A clear plastic box with an e-ink screen and visible circuits</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>The <title rend="italic">Poetry Box</title> is a very relevant tool to perform public
					demonstrations, as it is both portable and appealing. The object is also intriguing, since
					it is transparent and reveals the cables and computer cards (all Raspberry Pi components)
					it is made of. This proved to be a very efficient tool to engage the public with
					poetry.</p>
				<p>In addition to this portable device, we also developed a Twitter bot that posts a quatrain
					every 6 hours (<ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>).</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure08">
					<head>The Oupoco bot on Twitter</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>Screenshot of a twitter profile showing regular posts</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>We also released, in collaboration with Riva Illustration a short movie, which explains the
					project, the approach and the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à
							poésie</title><note><ref
							target="https://riva-illustrations.com/animations-oupoco/"
							>https://riva-illustrations.com/animations-oupoco/</ref> (last consulted
						7/11/2022).</note>. This short movie is an essential element in the dissemination of
					our work. It can be consulted online, at any time, without restrictions. It is available
					in English and in French. This short movie was awarded the prize for <q>the most
						entertaining video</q> during the IJCAI 2023 conference in Macao<note><ref
							target="https://ijcai-23.org/video-competition/"
							>https://ijcai-23.org/video-competition/</ref> (last consulted 9/10/2023).</note>
					(IJCAI, the 32nd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, is one of the
					most prestigious international conferences in Artificial intelligence).</p>
				<p>These different devices (web site, short movie, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à
						poésie</title>, Twitter bot, etc.) make it possible to propose different kinds of
					demonstrations, to different audiences, in different settings. They also proved useful to
					make the project more popular.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section08">
				<head>8 Demonstrations and engagement with the public</head>
				<p>At the crossroads between surrealism and absurdism, generated sonnets are generally quite
					funny and convey a dreamlike atmosphere. The themes specific to the Romantic period – such
					as love, whether it is magnified or lost, death or the fleetingness of time to name but a
					few – contribute to creating bizarre but intriguing poems. While most of them lack
					coherence, particularly with respect to the use of punctuation or pronouns, the syntactic
					confusions this creates can actually reinforce their poetic overtones. The Oupoco system
					is intended to be presented in front of an audience, to elicit reactions, as a means to
					make people rediscover poetry and literature.</p>
				<div xml:id="section08.1">
					<head>8.1 Demonstrations </head>
					<p>We gave several demonstrations of the Oupoco project, to different audiences. A number
						of these presentations occurred online, because of the Covid pandemic. Oupoco was
						mostly developed between 2018 and early 2020, so became available just at the
						beginning of the pandemic, which greatly impacted the number of demonstrations we were
						able to do. However, we seized the opportunities to present the project to researchers
						and librarians (for example thanks to meetings organized by the French national
						library, especially during the <title rend="quotes">Content Generative Models and
							GLAM</title> workshop organized by the AI4LAM network, on <q>artificial
							intelligence in, for and by libraries, archives and museums</q>, on 19/04/2022)
						and also to a wider audience through the participation in open days (at the Ecole
						normale supérieure and the University Paris Science et Lettres) and science festivals.
						Demonstrations for researchers were made using traditional presentations on a
						computer, but the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title> was the
						main support for open days and science festivals.</p>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="section08.2">
					<head>8.2 Reactions</head>
					<p>The main goal of the project, beyond the scientific challenge of automatically
						analyzing rhymes and detecting the main topic of a poem, was to interest people in
						poetry and literature in a non-academic way. Reactions were generally very positive
						and enthusiastic. We did not perform a comprehensive study, but we discuss here some
						of the observations we made during these demonstrations.</p>
					<p>Because the machine produces structurally impeccable sonnets, the experiencer is
						unconsciously encouraged to find coherence in them, simply because we are used to
						coherence in our everyday life and because incoherence is bewildering <ptr
							target="#reinhart1980"/>. The second observation we made (which follows on from
						the previous one to some extent), is a frequent need for the experiencer to go back to
						the original poem, to see where a given line comes from (on the Oupoco website,
							<q>tooltips</q> always allows the experiencer to go back to the original sonnet).
						This is encouraging as our main goal is to re-engage people with poetry (showing that
						poetry is interesting, and surprising).</p>
					<p>Other reactions were more surprising. Some children were fascinated by the <title
							rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title> and the cables inside the
						object. The fact that computers are made of electronic cards and cables is obvious to
						us, but computers remain abstract objects for children who have never seen <q>inside
							the box</q>. This experience was a way to explain to them that a computer
						manipulates information through electricity and that data and programs have to be
						physically stored somewhere, inside the machine.</p>
					<p>Last but not least, although we were not able to do many demonstrations in schools due
						to the pandemic, several people told us that the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr"
							>Boîte à poésie</title>, beyond engaging pupils and students with poetry, was also
						a very good way to raise their awareness of complex linguistic issues such as text
						coherence. The program frequently produces non optimal texts (with pronouns not
						referring to any antecedents or with erratic syntactic constructions, as shown in <ref
							target="#section06">Section 6</ref>). Since these texts are produced by a machine,
						there is no harm in using them to explain why they are problematic, and how they could
						be improved. The whole process also helps to show that a computer is not perfect in
						itself: it is just the result of what people (especially, programme designers) do with
						it.</p>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="section08.3">
					<head>8.3 Objections</head>
					<p>Even if most of the reactions about the website or about the <title rend="italic"
							xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title> were positive, we also had to face a few
						reservations, generally from teachers and professors of French literature. Their
						worries concerned the image all this gives of literature, and more specifically
						poetry. By assembling lines of verse selected from different poems (either randomly or
						with the light supervision of the reader) one may often produce meaningless texts.
						This could lead the reader to think that poetry can be anything, that even meaningless
						text or just a bunch of random words put together can be poetry. In brief, people
						could lose the sense of what real poetry is.</p>
					<p>While this has to be taken into account, our experience showed that people are well
						aware of what we propose through this system. Everybody immediately understood that
						the sonnets were generated automatically and that they do not have to make sense. In
						other words, they are not real poems and cannot be confused with poems written by
						humans. Conversely, as explained in the previous sections, people were often puzzled
						and wanted to know the source of a given line, and wanted to have a look at the
						original poem. So, far from being a distraction, the system was a way to reconcile
						people with poetry, although on a very limited and modest scale. We do not think our
						system will fundamentally change how people see poetry (a genre with a very limited
						number of readers nowadays, unfortunately), but it could at least arouse curiosity for
						this literary genre.</p>
					<p>In our opinion, the project is thus not a sacrilege with respect to venerated texts,
						but a way to make people experience and rediscover poetry.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section09">
				<head>9 Discussion</head>
				<p>Now that we have described the project in detail, it may be interesting to come back to the
					rationale behind this project. What have we explored, what have we learnt in the end,
					beyond developing a piece of software and some devices inspired by <name>Queneau</name>?
					How should we apprehend the poems created by the machine?</p>
				<p>As said in the beginning, one piece of inspiration was Kenneth Goldsmith’s book <title
						rend="italic">Uncreative writing</title> (<ref target="#goldsmith2011">2011</ref>).
					Goldsmith contends that the vast reservoir of pre-existing texts available in digital form
					allows people (especially writers) to engage with language in novel ways, emphasizing the
					value of recontextualization and reinterpretation over the creation of entirely new
					content. This approach challenges conventional ideas about what constitutes originality
					and innovation in the realm of writing and highlights the evolving relationship between
					humans and text. Goldsmith provocatively advocates for a shift towards a more "uncreative"
					approach to writing. He posits that human creativity can also be found in the act of
					appropriating and remixing existing texts, blurring the lines between authorship and
					readership. We partly wanted explore this idea through the Oupoco project.</p>
				<p>This may also remind the reader of Charles O. Hartman’s book, <title rend="italic">Virtual
						Muse: Experiments in Computer Poetry</title> (<ref target="#hartman1996">1996</ref>).
					In this book, Hartman explores technology and literature, showcasing the transformative
					potential of computers in redefining the very essence of poetry. Through meticulous
					analysis and experimentation, he demonstrates how algorithms and computational processes
					can be harnessed to generate innovative and unexpected poetic forms, challenging
					established norms and expanding the horizons of creative expression. More specifically,
					his first experiment was in a way a precursor of our own: a program named <title
						rend="quotes">RanLines</title> was designed to store a collection of 20 lines and
					subsequently to fetch one of these lines at random whenever the user pressed a key, so as
					to produce a kind of poem. Through this program, the author explores a <quote
						rend="inline" source="#hartman1996">simple sort of randomness</quote> that reminds him
					of the Greek oracles.</p>
				<p>What is even more interesting are Hartman’s reflections on the results he got. He observed
					that <cit><quote rend="inline">It’s hard to put together two words that don’t make some
							kind of sense to the willing reader</quote><ptr target="#hartman1996" loc="31"
						/></cit>. He also adds that: <quote rend="inline" source="#hartman1996">The more
						discrete and self-contained the syntax of the line (complete clause, complete
						prepositional phrase), the more easily it joins with lines before and after</quote>,
					which is also what we observed, and one of the limits of our experiments (when a
					linguistic element refers to other ones outside the line, coherence – or simple linguistic
					well formedness – is often lacking). But beyond this issue, we agree with Hartman that
					these experiments open new perspectives to the willing reader. As Hartman suggests, the
					reader’s imagination is challenged, as it is nearly always possible to find some meaning,
					draw some connexions and interpret combined verses. At the same time, our experiments
					showed that the application is also a strong incentive to rediscover poetry: very often,
					people are intrigued by a line and want to go back to the original poem.</p>
				<p>To conclude, we can say we have explored in a new manner the idea of potential literature,
					by producing new sonnets from a very well-defined set of constraints, following in this
					sense the program put forward by <name>Queneau</name> more than 60 years ago.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section10">
				<head>10 Conclusion</head>
				<p>The main interest of the Oupoco project is to present French poetry through a new and
					original setting. With our system, poetry is not just a literary genre, but a dynamic
					object that can be manipulated and experienced. For many people, poetry is seen at best as
					something related to school education, at worst as something boring and uninteresting from
					the past. Our new setting, in itself, makes it possible to show that playing with poetry
					can be fun. Our setting puts the notion of text coherence in perspective since the result
					of the generator can be more or less satisfactory from a semantic point of view <ptr
						target="#reinhart1980"/>. In the future, we plan to study the potential impact of our
					system in different (real world) contexts, especially in educational settings.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="appendix">
				<head>Acknowledgements</head>
				<p>This work received support from EUR Translitterae (Ecole universitaire de recherche,
					program <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="fr">Investissements d’avenir</title>
					ANR-10-IDEX-0001-02 PSL* and ANR-17-EURE-0025) and from the CNRS through the International
					Research Network Cyclades (Corpora and Computational Linguistics for Digital Humanities).
					This work was also supported in part by the French government under the management of the
					Agence Nationale de la Recherche as part of the <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="fr"
						>Investissements d’avenir</title> program, reference ANR19-P3IA-0001 (PRAIRIE 3IA
					Institute).</p>
			</div>
			<div type="appendix">
				<head>Author Roles</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item>Frédérique Mélanie-Becquet: conceptualization, data curation and supervision</item>
					<item>Clément Plancq: conceptualization and software development</item>
					<item>Claude Grunspan: data curation</item>
					<item>Mylène Maignant: conceptualization and data curation</item>
					<item>Matthieu Raffard: conception and development of the <title rend="italic">Poetry
							Box</title> (<title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title>)</item>
					<item>Mathilde Roussel: conception and development of the <title rend="italic">Poetry
							Box</title> (<title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Boîte à poésie</title>)</item>
					<item>Fiammetta Ghedini: conception and development of the Oupoco video clip</item>
					<item>Thierry Poibeau: conceptualization, funding acquisition, supervision and
						writing</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="baillehache2021" label="Baillehache 2021">Baillehache, J. (2021) <title
						rend="quotes">The Digital Reception of A Hundred Thousand Billion Poems</title>.
						<title rend="italic">Sens public</title>, pp. 1–13. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.7202/1089666ar"
					>https://doi.org/10.7202/1089666ar</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beaudouin2002" label="Beaudouin 2002">Beaudouin, V. (2002) <title rend="italic"
						>Mètre et rythmes du vers classique. Corneille et Racine</title>. Paris : Honoré
					Champion (Lettres numériques).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beaudouin_etal1996" label="Beaudouin and Yvon 1996">Beaudouin, V. and Yvon F.
					(1996) <title rend="quotes">The Metrometer: a Tool for Analysing French Verse</title>
					<title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 11(1), pp. 23–31.
					Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/11.1.23"
						>https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/11.1.23</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bens2005" label="Bens 2005">Bens, J. (2005) <title rend="italic">Genèse de
						l’Oulipo: 1960-1963. Circulaire du 28 août 1961</title>. Le Pré-Saint-Gervais: Le
					Castor Astral.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="berkman2017" label="Berkman 2017">Berkman, N. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
						>Digital Oulipo: Programming Potential Literature</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Digital Humanities Quaterly</title>, 11(3). Available at: <ref
						target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000325/000325.html"
						>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000325/000325.html</ref> (Accessed 27
					August 2023).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="berkman2022" label="Berkman 2022">Berkman, N. (2022) <title rend="italic">Oulipo
						and the Mathematics of Literature</title>. Bern: Peter Lang.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bloomfield_etal2016" label="Bloomfield and Campaignolle 2016">Bloomfield, C.,
					and Campaignolle, H. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Machines littéraires, machines numériques
						: l’Oulipo et l’informatique</title> in C. Reggiani and A. Schnaffner (eds.) <title
						rend="italic">Oulipo mode d’emploi</title>. Paris: Honoré Champion, pp. 319–36.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="charbonnier1962" label="Charbonnier 1962">Charbonnier, G. (1962) <title
						rend="italic">Entretiens avec Raymond Queneau</title>. Paris : Gallimard.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="denize_etal1999" label="Denize and Magné 1999">Denize, A. and Magné, B. (1999)
					Machine à écrire [CD-Rom]. Paris: Gallimard.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="derrida_etal1980" label="Derrida and Ronell 1980">Derrida, J. and Ronell, A.
					(1980) <title rend="quotes">On narrative: The law of genre</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Critical Inquiry</title>, 7(1), pp. 55–81.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fournel1972" label="Fournel 1972">Fournel, P. (1972) <title rend="italic">Clés
						pour la littérature potentielle</title>. Paris: Denoël.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gervas2013" label="Gervas 2013">Gervas, P. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
						>Computational modelling of poetry generation</title> in <title rend="italic"
						>Artificial Intelligence and Poetry Symposium</title>, AISB Convention, University of
					Exeter.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ghazvininejad_etal2017" label="Ghazvininejad et al 2017">Ghazvininejad M., Shi
					X., Priyadarshi J., and Knight K. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Hafez: an interactive
						poetry generation system</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of ACL 2017,
						System Demonstrations</title>. Vancouver: Canada, pp. 43–48.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="goldsmith2011" label="Goldsmith 2011">Goldsmith, K. (2011) <title rend="italic"
						>Uncreative Writing : Managing Language in the Digital Age</title>. Columbia
					University Press: New York.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="goldsmith2019" label="Goldsmith 2019">Goldsmith, K. (2019) <title rend="italic"
						>What Big Data Can’t Do: The Pleasure of the (Perverse) Text</title>. Available at:
						<ref target="https://savoirs.ens.fr/expose.php?id=3659"
						>https://savoirs.ens.fr/expose.php?id=3659</ref> (Accessed 27 August 2023).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hartman1996" label="Hartman 1996">Hartman C.O. (1996) <title rend="italic"
						>Virtual Muse: Experiments in Computer Poetry</title>. Middletown: Wesleyan University
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="leonardo_etal2006" label="Leonardo/Olats and Bootz 2006">Leonardo/Olats and
					Bootz, P. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Qu'est-ce que la littérature générative
						combinatoire?</title> In P. Bootz, <title rend="italic">Les Basiques : la littérature
						numérique</title>. Publication en ligne : <ref
						target="http://archive.olats.org/livresetudes/basiques/litteraturenumerique/10_basiquesLN.php"
						>http://archive.olats.org/livresetudes/basiques/litteraturenumerique/10_basiquesLN.php</ref>
					(consulté le 3/11/2022).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="melanie_etal2022" label="Mélanie-Becquet et al 2022">Mélanie-Becquet, F.,
					Grunspan, C., Maignant, M., Plancq, C., and Poibeau, T. (2022) <title rend="quotes">The
						Oupoco Database of French Sonnets from the 19th Century</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Journal of Open Humanities Data</title>, 8(0), pp. 1–5. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.5334/johd.89">https://doi.org/10.5334/johd.89</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="oulipo1973" label="Oulipo 1973">Oulipo. (1973) <title rend="italic">La
						littérature potentielle (Créations Re-créations Récréations)</title>. Paris:
					Gallimard.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="oulipo1981" label="Oulipo 1981">Oulipo. (1981) <title rend="italic">Atlas de
						littérature potentielle</title>. Paris: Gallimard.</bibl>
				<!-- check oulipo2002 about publisher? -->
				<bibl xml:id="oulipo2002" label="Oulipo 2002">Oulipo. (2002) <title rend="italic">Abrégé de
						littérature potentielle</title>. Paris: Éditions Mille et une nuits, n° 379.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="poibeau2017" label="Poibeau 2017">Poibeau, T. (2017) <title rend="italic"
						>Machine Translation</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="queneau1961" label="Queneau 1961">Queneau, R. (1961) <title rend="italic">Cent
						mille milliards de poèmes</title>. Paris: Gallimard.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="reinhart1980" label="Reinhart 1980">Reinhart, T. (1980) <title rend="quotes"
						>Conditions for text coherence</title>. <title rend="italic">Poetics Today</title>,
					1(4), pp. 161–180.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="starynkevitch1990" label="Starynkevitch 1990">Starynkevitch, D. (1990) <title
						rend="quotes">The SEA CAB 500 Computer</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Annals of
						the History of Computing</title>, 12(1), pp. 23-29. Available at: <ref
						target="10.1109/MAHC.1990.10008">10.1109/MAHC.1990.10008</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="vandecruys2020" label="Van de Cruys 2020" sortKey="Vandecruys">Van de Cruys, T.
					(2020) <title rend="quotes">Automatic poetry generation from prosaic text</title> in
						<title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for
						Computational Linguistics</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://aclanthology.org/2020.acl-main.223/"
						>https://aclanthology.org/2020.acl-main.223/</ref> (Accessed 10 October 2023).</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
