<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Disentangling Ownership in Digital Collecting Practices: Approaches From 
               Across Galleries, Libraries, Archives, and Museums</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Arran J. <dhq:family>Rees</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7155-5335</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leeds</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>arran@museumdata.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Arran Rees</name> is a Research Fellow in the School of Fine Art, History of Art and Cultural Studies at the 
                    <name>University of Leeds</name>, as well as the Museum Data Manager for the Museum Data Service. His research and 
                    practice is focused on action research, digital collecting, and collections management practices in museums. 
                    <name>Arran</name> has worked in and with museums like the <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name> and the 
                    <name>Museum of Cardiff</name> for over a decade, and he has recently been a part of a number of cultural heritage 
                    research projects, including the AHRC-funded Congruence Engine with the Science Museum Group and the Unlocking our 
                    Digital Past project at the <name>University of Loughborough</name>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Elizabeth <dhq:family>Stainforth</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2917-3522</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leeds</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>e.m.stainforth@leeds.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Elizabeth Stainforth</name> is a Lecturer in the School of Fine Art, History of Art and Cultural Studies at the 
                    <name>University of Leeds</name>. Her research explores digital heritage and memory cultures, and she is interested in 
                    theories of utopia for developing critical studies of history and heritage. She has published widely on this topic in 
                    journals including <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, <title rend="italic">Memory Studies</title>, the 
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, and the <title rend="italic">International Journal of Cultural 
                    Studies</title>. Her first book, <title rend="italic">Geopolitics of Digital Heritage</title> (CUP: 2024), is 
                    co-authored with <name>Natalia Grincheva</name>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000782</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#digitization"/>
               <term corresp="#glam"/>
               <term corresp="#cultural_heritage"/>
               <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
               <term corresp="#metadata"/>
               <term corresp="#social_media"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>ownership</item>
                  <item>digital collecting</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000782/000782.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
           <p>This article examines approaches to digital collecting across the institutional domains of museums, libraries, and archives 
              (MLAs) in order to scrutinize established norms regarding the ownership of collections. Challenges to collecting 
              institutions have been particularly apparent in the context of digital heritage, which encompasses a range of activities 
              including digitization, born-digital collecting, aggregation, and collecting from social media. Digital collections can 
              unsettle collections management processes that assume the retention and control of static holdings, due to their 
              reproducibility, proprietary frameworks, and complex rights issues. Using case studies drawn from across different MLAs, 
              the article identifies three modes of digital collecting: ownership-led, ambiguous ownership, and shared ownership. These 
              three modes demonstrate ways in which institutional ownership claims affect the status of digital collections. The article 
              argues for the need to practice approaches to ownership that offer more productive means of navigating the complexities of 
              digital collecting, thus preserving a fuller sense of what digital collections are.
           </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>Ownership is increasingly complex for digital artefacts in cultural heritage organisations. Here, <name>Rees</name> and 
              <name>Stainforth</name> attempt to disentangle those issues using social media collections as case studies.
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction </head>
            <p>In contemporary cultural heritage debates, the role of collecting institutions is increasingly contested, for a range of 
               different reasons. Writers such as <name>David C. Harvey</name>, <name>Rodney Harrison</name>, and <name>Laurajane 
               Smith</name> have characterized heritage as a practice and a cultural process in order to counter the historical privileging of material culture, and to highlight the relational aspects of cultural artefacts (Harvey 2001; Smith 2006; Harrison 2012). In the museum sector, too, Janet Marstine notes a turn towards processes and relationships, observing, “there is a focus on experience as the link binding people together through things” (2012: 45; see also Grewcock 2014). This idea resonates with how archives and libraries have tried to make collecting activities more people-centred and community-driven (Flinn et al 2009; Bastian and Alexander 2009) and with efforts to decolonize cultural heritage institutions (Lonetree 2012; D'Souza 2018; Hicks 2020). Terms like ethical stewardship (Geismar 2008; 2015; Marstine 2015; 2017), post-custodial archives (Ham 1981; Bearman 1991) and appropriate museology (Kreps 2008; 2015) try to account for these changes, all of which raise questions about institutional ownership and authority. Challenges to the norms of collecting institutions have been particularly apparent in the field of digital heritage, which encompasses a range of activities including digitization, born-digital collecting, aggregation and collecting from social media. This is because the issues presented by proprietary frameworks, digital preservation and rights management unsettle established collections management approaches, which tend to assume the retention and control of static holdings.</p>
            <p>Galleries, libraries, archives and museums (GLAMs) have been collecting digital material with varying degrees of success and commitment for more than twenty years, although museums have been relatively late to join “the fraternity of cultural institutions that are committed to ensuring that the digital legacy we create today is available to everyone tomorrow” (Cumiskey 2018). Over this period, innovations have occurred in GLAM collections management and preservation processes, and professional practice organizations like the Digital Preservation Coalition<note><ref target="https://www.dpconline.org/">https://www.dpconline.org/</ref> (Accessed: 02 January 2025)</note> and the BitCurator Consortium<note><ref target="https://bitcuratorconsortium.org/">https://bitcuratorconsortium.org/</ref> (Accessed: 02 January 2025)</note> have been established. During the last couple of years, large organizations like the Library of Congress have, in their latest Digital Collections Strategy, started to designate parts of their major collecting strands “e-preferred”, where the default will be “acquiring a digital instance of content instead of acquiring an analog version” (Library of Congress 2021: 4). In the UK, The National Archives (TNA) are taking a similar approach, actively working on their digital transfer processes as an increasing number of government records are being transferred to the archive in born-digital formats, in accordance with the Public Record Act's 20-year rule.<note> The 20 year rule was changed from the 30 year rule in 2013. This means the number of born-digital records due for transfer from government departments is increasing more rapidly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Born-digital objects in particular have presented a number of challenges to GLAMs interested in collecting and preserving them. Institutions have been slow to take account of digital objects' materiality (Cameron and Kenderdine 2007; Arvanitis and Zuanni 2021) and their boundlessness or fuzziness (Owens 2018; Flood and Hawes 2019), as well as their often multi-layered intellectual property rights, and personal data implications. In this article we focus on collecting social media to highlight the complexities of born-digital collecting, where the issues around materiality, boundlessness, and ownership can be drawn out and compared effectively.</p>
            <p>The act of born-digital collecting is both similar and different to physical collecting. The process of collecting inserts an item into an artificial context, where it takes on a new level of significance through being “selected” or “appraised” by the institution. This process has been referred to as one of “musealisation” (Mairesse et al 2010; Macdonald 2013), or “archivization” (Derrida 1995) in museum studies and archival studies respectively, and happens regardless of the composition of an item. However, born-digital material introduces complicating factors with regard to context, consisting of items that are both complexly woven into digital infrastructures and yet entirely replicable; they are therefore capable of existing both inside and outside of the institution at the same time. There have been attempts to differentiate between born-digital material that sits inside and outside of ”object” status by Niels Brügger, who suggests that we might understand born-digital objects as “reborn” after they have been incorporated into web archives (2016; see also Zuanni 2021 for an insightful discussion on museum objects). While this distinction is helpful, the challenges around a born-digital object's fuzziness and its ownership status remain.</p>
            <p>Understandably, accommodating born-digital material has demanded a shift in collecting practices in GLAMs and more digitally focused versions of collections management policies; the Spectrum 5.0 Digital Collecting toolkit for museums (2022) and Project Omega at TNA (2021) are concrete examples of this kind of work. The deeply entrenched politics of collecting that hinge on ownership are proving slower to change though. Nicole Meehan's (2020) work surveyed museum professionals' understandings of digital objects (both digitized and born-digital) and found that, in general, digital objects were valued lower than physical objects. Meehan's findings may help us to understand why, in many museums, there has been less impetus to respond to the logic of digital materiality, which unsettles the ownership principle of collections management. Libraries and archives have not tended to have that luxury, being forced to adapt their practices to accommodate born-digital material through legislation that requires them to receive, preserve and provide access to digital artefacts (legal deposit for libraries and electronic deposits as part of longstanding commitments to archive government and business documents in archives).  </p>
            <p>Following a number of years of experimentation with new approaches and models across the cultural sector, this article argues for the need to scrutinize digital collecting practices in order to better understand their distinct implications for ownership. Here, we identify three modes of digital collecting: ownership-led, ambiguous ownership and shared ownership. These are not necessarily unique to the context of digital media and are well-established within the histories of collecting institutions. However, digital collecting has amplified tensions around the politics, power and logic of ownership. Therefore, the aim in this article is two-fold: 1) to understand how the issue of institutional ownership affects the status of digital collections; 2) to suggest modes of ownership that offer more productive means of navigating the complexities of digital collecting, thus preserving a fuller sense of what digital collections are. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Digital collections management in GLAMs</head>
            <p>Digital collections management practices vary across the discrete institutional domains of GLAMs. Over the years, efforts to draw together scholarly and practical work in these fields has had different emphases. Digital heritage is a broad concept which has been rooted in dialogues dispersed over professional and media boundaries (Parry 2007; 2010; Lewi et al 2020). Fiona Cameron and Sarah Kenderdine were among the first to call for a “sustained interchange between digital cultural theory and heritage practices” and investigate how cultural heritage institutions use new and emerging digital media (2007: 2-3). A related area of inquiry concerns how GLAMs' systems can be designed to surface thematic links between media and content (Rayward 1997; Dempsey 2000; Cathro 2001; Kirchhoff 2008). Some researchers and practitioners have called for a focus on the network of relations in cultural collections, and the development of digital tools which allow complex interconnections to be made across institutional boundaries and different record types (Jones 2018; Dutia and Stack 2021; Boon 2023). </p>
            <p>The steps taken towards creating an expansive understanding of cultural institutions and their purpose have been linked to strategies for more adaptive and ethically appropriate museum work. Christina Kreps' concept of appropriate museology is important here. Kreps (2008) argues that museological practices dominant in the global minority are taken as standards for the rest of the world, disregarding forms of cultural heritage management that are local to other geographical regions. She suggests that more culturally and ethically appropriate forms of museology can emerge through acknowledging distinct cultural contexts and adapting established modes of museology to better suit local environments. Such approaches have reinforced arguments for shared ownership of collections (Marstine 2017) and the adoption of forms of guardianship over ownership (Geismar 2008; 2015). The CARE principles for Indigenous Data governance are also relevant here, as a framework which seeks to pay attention to knowledge protocols that are not fully accounted for within other global minority-led data guidelines such as the FAIR principles.<note> The CARE Principles for Indigenous Data Governance were built on the FAIR Data Principles that set out how digital data should be made Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable. The CARE Principles are designed to take into account the differing world views in indigenous societies. CARE principles include Collective Benefit, the Authority to control, Responsibility and Ethics. <ref target="https://www.gida-global.org/care">https://www.gida-global.org/care</ref> and <ref target="https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/">https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/</ref> (Accessed: 02 January 2025)</note> Ideas from appropriate museology and stewardship have also been applied in relation to the distinct cultural context of digital and online space (Kidd 2019; Rees 2021b), and are closely tied to outreach and more fluid approaches to the museum. Using Zygmunt Bauman's notion of Liquid Modernity, the concept of the Liquid Museum has been proposed as an ontology relevant to any circumstance a museum might have to deal with, removing distinctions between collections and audiences, and offering more operational freedom for museums to adapt according to societal changes (Van Oost 2012; Cameron 2013; Gonçalves 2019). </p>
            <p>In the realm of libraries and archives, there has been a comparable shift towards people-centred practices, specifically as they connect to memory, identity and social justice movements (Punzalen and Caswell 2016; McKemmish et al 2020). This shift is informed by Critical Librarianship and Archival Studies scholarship and the “explosion of efforts to examine the ways in which records and archives serve as tools for both oppression and liberation” (Caswell et al 2017). Work in the field has proposed a change in archival models from those based on legalistic understandings of individual rights, to cultivating radical empathy and a feminist ethics of care (Caswell and Cifor 2016). While libraries are oriented differently towards issues of rights and ownership, interventions in this area have started to recognize the role of library acquisitions in the uneven production of knowledge and the attendant need to centre social change (Gregory and Higgins 2013; Gibson et al 2017; Drabinski 2019). </p>
            <p>In their efforts to address uneven power and knowledge structures, many recent projects have been generating community-driven collections through the uncovering of racialized violence (Sutherland 2019), state injustice (Evans et al 2015; Jones and O'Neill 2014), or the digital capture of contemporary events that have not been well documented in the past, such as police brutality (Foster and Evans 2016; Williams and Drake 2017). These activities have built on established approaches, wherein the priority has been ensuring that people “retain their autonomy and independence in any relationship and participate in partnerships and project work very much on their own terms” (Flinn et al 2009: 80; see also Schwartz and Cook 2002; Bastian and Alexander 2009). Among critical archivists, widespread acknowledgement of the historical oppressions and exclusions of collections documentation has led to strategies for reconfiguring proprietary models of ownership through the post-custodial paradigm: the repositioning of collections from institutions into the communities of their creation or use (Ham 1981; Bearman 1991; Bastian 2002; Kelleher 2017). For Kimberly Christen, “post-custodialism moves away from the ownership model and the collection model, which is very much steeped in the colonial model” (2018). Alongside the idea of the post-custodial archive, commentators have foregrounded the potential of digital methods for dislodging custodianship from traditional collections management practices and leveraging the potential of digital technologies for resource-sharing (Ham 1981; Cook 2013; Light 2019).</p>
            <p>This brief survey of the literature highlights how different terminologies try to account for similar institutional challenges regarding the ownership of cultural collections. Within museology, archival, library and information studies there has been a sustained questioning of the status of the material record, and a concern with representing and negotiating multiple collections rights. These questions are not unique to, but increasingly overlap with, debates about ownership and digital collecting practices. For example, it has been argued that experimental approaches to digital collecting provide an opportunity to create the conditions of new knowledge and challenge oppressive archival logics (Agostinho 2019). The distinctive characteristics of digital objects have also prompted demands for more robust digital preservation strategies, involving how collections can be stored across multiple institutional sites (Lucky and Harkema 2018; Lyman and Besser 1998; Owens 2018). John Bell urges that “we need to be willing to let the things we preserve leave our institutional control when that is what's needed to sustain them […] whatever we can do to make preserved data portable between institutions will help it survive” (2018; see also Chan and Cope 2014). Lastly, there are ongoing calls to reformulate the tangible focus of intellectual property laws to accommodate digital culture (Lessig 2008; Perzanowski and Schultz 2016). These calls are echoed in cultural heritage institutions, where the stress on ownership in collections management and ethical frameworks has proven problematic for collecting new and emerging object types (Fouseki and Vacharopulou 2013; Rees 2021b).</p>
            <p>The next sections will introduce three modes of digital collecting – ownership-led, ambiguous ownership and shared ownership – in an effort to account for key issues of institutional ownership when collecting social media. The choice of case studies has been informed by the professional and academic work of the authors and each forms part of a larger research project spanning the period 2018-2020.  <note> In collaboration with the Collecting Social Photo research project (2017-2020) (see Rees 2021a) and as part of an Endeavour-funded postdoctoral fellowship (2018) (see chapter on Trove in Grincheva and Stainforth 2024).</note>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ownership-led collecting</head>
            <p>The dominance of the ownership-led model of collecting is an inheritance from the first formalized collecting institutions that understood the possession of material as the starting point for preserving them. This model has been codified by international frameworks like the International Council of Museums' (ICOM) and International Council of Archives' Code of Practice, and enshrined in more localized guidance like the UK Museum Association's Code of Ethics and the Collections Trust's Spectrum collections management standard. The language of ownership is deeply embedded in the politics of collecting institutions, with notions of acquiring, transferring, possessing, accessioning and permanence guiding discussions with any potential donor or seller. It is therefore unsurprising that ownership continues to be the default model for collecting, even as digital collecting gains more traction across GLAMs.</p>
            <p>The implications of digital culture's relation to ownership are beginning to be articulated through the work of scholars like Perzanowski and Schultz (2016), who explain that much of what we consider to be owned digitally is in fact just licensed for use. Even for digital items not necessarily governed by licence agreements, attempting to prove any form of tangible ownership over a digital file that can be copied and replicated an infinite number of times, to a degree that would enable a museum, library or archive to confidently request a transfer of title, is incredibly difficult (Arrigoni et al 2022; Rees 2021a). There are, of course, degrees of complexity in digital artefacts that make applying ownership-led models of collecting more or less achievable.</p>
            <p>However, when the digital artefact is complex, ownership-led models have still been applied and have run into complications. The Victoria and Albert museum (V&amp;A) has a comparatively long tradition of working with digitally produced objects and is the home of the UK's first digitally-produced art collection (V&amp;A 2023). Until relatively recently, the V&amp;A's digitally produced collections were still being collected physically and therefore being taken through a traditional acquisition process quite comfortably. Since the mid-2010s, the museum has been more actively collecting both born-digital and physical/digital hybrid items. A watershed moment came in 2017, when the V&amp;A collected a version of the Chinese social media platform WeChat after three years of discussions. The final object is made up of 173 individual items, comprising born-digital GIFs, designs on paper, and an APK file (the file type used by Android operating systems to package up individual files used to install and run apps). In collecting WeChat, the curators and collections managers at the V&amp;A were faced with balancing the need to formally own the object, as directed by the museum's acquisition policy, with the curatorial need to interpret and represent the design features of a social media platform. Here, we highlight two aspects of the ownership-led model used to acquire the V&amp;A's WeChat object. First, the language around ‘acquisition' and the challenges that this presented for a digital object; second, the impact the need to own the resulting object had on the make-up of that object. </p>
            <p>During conversations with the creators and owners of the WeChat application Tencent, the V&amp;A had to reconsider its use of the term “acquire”. Within the business sector, the idea of acquiring a product like WeChat would mean taking over ownership and management of the whole product, rather than owning a version, instance or copy of it, as was the case with the museum's collecting proposal (Rees 2021a). In an interview with Brendan Cormier and Esme Hawes, the curators responsible for collecting WeChat, they explained how the conversation with Tencent had to be re-framed to emphasize collecting as an act of preservation rather than taking formal ownership of the WeChat platform (Rees 2021a). Although it is possible there were some losses in translation, the misunderstanding over the term acquisition was also informed by the digital, downloadable nature of the object. As an item of use, WeChat is one of those digital products that Personowski and Schultz are referring to when they explain that the digital items we possess are not owned but licensed. The WeChat application that appears on a smartphone is licensed for our use and the transactional activities of downloading it, installing it, logging in and using it result in no change of ownership. In this context, conversations about the V&amp;A acquiring WeChat, a digital object that is a product distributed to millions of users, but does not have its ownership status altered, has larger implications than for a physical product where ownership status is routinely changed through transactions.</p>
            <p>The shape of the eventual collected WeChat object was affected by questions over what could formally be owned. The social element of a social media platform like WeChat is an important aspect of what makes it significant and worth collecting but reflecting this in the collected object was a challenge. Cormier and Hawes explained the ‘fuzzy' nature of ownership over individual user profiles on the platform, and the potential legal barriers to asking people to donate their profiles meant the resulting object was populated with ‘fake content' (Rees 2021a). WeChat, like many other social media platforms, has a complex rights agreement with users, whereby users retain a form of ownership over content they post to the platform through copyright but assign the platform far-researching licences to do whatever they want with the content. The object in the V&amp;A's collection is a staged copy of the WeChat application, something that was practically separable from the app that users download and use everyday. In order to use existing “transfer of title” documents, a new entity that could be “collected” and “owned” had to be created in collaboration between Tencent and the museum. Although it was a pragmatic solution to owning WeChat as per standard acquisition practices, the collected version, shaped by the need to use a traditional ownership-led approach, led to an artefact that could potentially be perceived as an inauthentic example of social media.</p>
            <p>This case from the V&amp;A illustrates some of the implications of trying to extend established ownership-driven approaches to collecting digital material. While libraries and archives have had alternative options to direct ownership, in the form of deposits (where ownership remains with the depositor, but preservation and access to the material is managed and negotiated by the institution), we still see approaches to digital collecting that default to ownership happening within the sector.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ambiguous ownership</head>
            <p>Ambiguous ownership encompasses a field of practices that elude clear parameters as far as ownership is concerned. Ambiguity often emerges as a result of grey areas in collecting practices, where a shared claim to collections is implied but never explicitly addressed. In order to explore these issues further, this section will focus on the field of large-scale digital heritage aggregation and highlight examples of ambiguous ownership that have arisen in the management of aggregators' collections data. </p>
            <p>Digital heritage aggregation is a relatively obscure concept and practice, and one that has not been given extensive critical attention (Grincheva and Stainforth 2024). Broadly speaking, aggregators are systems that collect, format and manage metadata from multiple providers, and offer federated access to that data via services like online portals and websites. Metadata refers to the descriptions of digital objects to facilitate their discovery online. A conceptual framework that informs the development of aggregation can be found in convergence theory, which foregrounds the blurring of traditional distinctions between cultural organizations in the digital age (Bearman and Trant 1998; Dempsey 2000; Cathro 2001; Kirchhoff et al 2008; Trant 2009; Marty 2014). The foundations of this theory have been traced back to the mid-1990s, when GLAMs started digitizing their content and making it available online, a practice which was seen to signal new opportunities for cross-institutional search and discovery (Rayward 1997). Practical examples of digital heritage aggregators include Digital Library of India, Digital NZ, Digital Public Library of America (DPLA), Europeana and the National Library of Australia's Trove. These systems draw together collections data from a range of sources, including both national and local GLAMs. For the end user, the point of entry to an aggregator tends to be a website with a collections search bar and/or a series of exhibitions links, themed according to various subject and format types. </p>
            <p>Most aggregators necessitate building on top of existing systems and have what could be described as an inter-institutional structure. As such, they offer an interesting if unconventional model for exploring ownership claims. This is because they do not store digital content and their collections data is not representative of a single institution; rather, they harvest digital object metadata, pointing to the institutional sites where the objects are held. Ostensibly, then, they deflect the problem of ownership from the outset, leaving intact prior institutional claims.<note> It is important to note that, although the question of ownership is put to one side, some aggregation initiatives such as Europeana, do require the GLAMs they partner with to subscribe to their open rights principles. All metadata published by Europeana are available free of restriction under the Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. <ref target="https://www.europeana.eu/en/rights/usage-guidelines-for-metadata">https://www.europeana.eu/en/rights/usage-guidelines-for-metadata</ref> (Accessed: 02 January 2025)</note> However, what could be described as ambiguously owned items have surfaced in heritage aggregation initiatives, not so much as a result of their knowledge discovery remit, but as a bi-product of their community-building efforts. These have frequently taken the form of participation activities such as crowdsourcing with digital and digitized collections (Ridge 2014). Ambiguous ownership pertains to data created by individual users, which is harvested by the system. </p>
            <p>One such example can be found in Click and Flick, an initiative launched by the National Library of Australia (NLA) in 2006. The project was a partnership between the NLA and Flickr, which sought to enable social photo-sharing from users (Hooton 2006). Click and Flick was an early instance of a cultural heritage institution crowdsourcing social photography collections, whereby thematic groups were created on the NLA's Flickr account for members of the public to upload and tag their images. Metadata and thumbnail images from the groups were then harvested on a weekly basis into the NLA's aggregator PictureAustralia. The motivation for the project was to “build a diverse collection of images of national significance produced by individual Australians” (Hooton 2007). These aims were met insofar as the project vastly expanded the contemporary image collection of PictureAustralia; after the first year, over 12,000 images had been harvested from the Flickr groups (Hooton 2007). While the promotion and uptake of the project was quite short-lived (2006-2008), photos did continue to be harvested by PictureAustralia and then by its successor Trove. These images are discoverable on Trove at the time of writing, and the Flickr account is still relatively active, with regular uploads of images from users.  </p>
            <p>The ambiguous status of the Flickr images in Trove is notable. They were harvested by the aggregator and are discoverable on the website, but they have not been accessioned by the NLA, meaning they are not in the official collections or subject to the institutional standards for image description. Without context or consistent descriptions, the extent to which the photos can be rendered meaningful is limited. They may retain meaning for the individuals who submitted them, but their social history value is questionable. A lack of context for the images also plays out in relation to Trove's interface, which operates via a search bar on the landing page. If the Flickr images appeared in a search results list, they would be difficult to trace back to the original Click and Flick project and the specific circumstances in which collecting took place. As Tim Sherratt (2016) observes, “There will always be priorities in digitisation programs. There will always be short-term funding opportunities related to specific initiatives or events […] these biases and distortions are not obvious to someone typing queries into a search box”. While the images were originally solicited by the NLA to build its contemporary photography collection, they were not subject to the institution's own collecting procedures. This issue invites reflection on the logic of aggregation as a system that blurs the boundaries between access and ownership. In surfacing crowdsourced content through the search, Trove appears to <hi rend="italic">hold</hi> user-generated images without needing to address the question of acquisition. The value of the images is therefore not grounded institutionally, which throws into doubt their status and ongoing relationship to the NLA.</p>
            <p>This discussion of aggregation shows how some of the ambiguities of ownership can play out in the context of crowdsourced digital collections. In Click and Flick, it is interesting to observe that the desire to foster a sense of participation in collections is what led to a lack of clarity about ownership. The issue appeared to stem from inattention to the question of how shared ownership of digital collections might work, with the result that it was avoided altogether.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Shared ownership</head>
            <p>Discourses on shared ownership and authority feature across a spectrum of GLAM work, from deciding what should and should not be displayed (Lagerkvist 2015), to developing accountability and performance frameworks for heritage management (Legget 2018). In particular, case studies from New Zealand demonstrate how Māori practices of care related to taonga are increasingly being incorporated into heritage management processes imposed through colonial institutions and frameworks (Ngata et al 2012; Horwood 2018; Geismar 2018). Digital data and systems, aligned with the CARE Principles, are also enabling data sovereignty and the right to control and interpret heritage materials, through tools like the Mukurtu content management system (Thorpe et al 2021). Ideas around shared ownership align well with the established work of post-custodial archival theory and Geismar's call for shared guardianship, which develops a more consultative relationship between collecting institutions and the original holders of the material (2008: 115). However, there are fewer examples of how formalized shared ownership models are being used in digital collections. Here, we understand shared ownership to be defined in terms of rights. It entails moving away from a singular and “indisputable” right to ownership, as outlined in documents such as ICOM's Code of Ethics (2017: 49), and towards the agreement of non-exclusive ownership rights between the sharing parties.  </p>
            <p>In researching this article, we have become more aware of how slippery the concept of shared ownership is. Working through the finer detail of case studies that initially appeared relevant, we came to realize that the practice of shared ownership is still, in a sense, ambiguous. Often, digital collections are being managed through licences and other forms of agreement that are <hi rend="italic">aligned with</hi>, rather than <hi rend="italic">constitutive of</hi>, a shared ownership approach. Moreover, some digital collecting projects we encountered assumed notions of sharing, either because of the reproducibility of digital objects, or because they relied on frameworks borrowed from social media. Such approaches diverge from how we have sought to define the shared ownership of digital collections, as an informed negotiation process. In this section, we try to navigate these tensions and interrogate claims to shared ownership through focusing on both socially and technologically grounded interventions.</p>
            <p>A research collaboration between one of the authors and the Stockholm County Museum (SCM) (Rees 2021a) was revealing of how shared ownership can be a slippery concept. In 2011, the Museum began working with Samtidsbild, an online collecting tool for digital photos. The system allows the public to contribute their own images to the Museum via a web application. Uploaded images and metadata are automatically accessioned into the photography collection and stored in a database (Boogh 2013). In an interview in 2019, Elisabeth Boogh, the Museum's curator of photography, claimed that SCM did not assert complete ownership over the photos and insisted the ownership was shared, in accordance with the terms and conditions users sign up to when uploading. Extra steps in the upload process address usage rights for the Museum, asking users to select a Creative Commons licence for each image (Rees 2021a). Boogh compared this to instances of images in the collection that had been digitized from analogue photographs before being returned to the holder, an approach often seen within post-custodial archiving.</p>
            <p>In late 2019, the Samtidsbild terms and conditions were very close to those of social media platforms like Twitter and Instagram, but they did not explicitly mention SCM's collection or shared ownership. Instead, they granted a “nonexclusive right of use to Stockholm County Museum to […] produce copies and in other ways make messages available to the public”. They also stated that “Stockholm County Museum has the right to place the publication on another's website, on social media or a search portal on the Internet”, and that “nothing in these sections restricts the User's right to use its content on its own” (Rees 2021a). In 2020, the terms and conditions were updated to include the sentence, “By submitting messages and personal data to Samtidsbild, they become part of Stockholm County Museum's cultural-historical archive and will be preserved and managed for future generations and for historical and scientific research purposes” (Rees 2021a). Here, we can see that assumptions about the nature of ownership had initially been derived from previous experiences of working with digital and digitized material, and later from images becoming part of the Museum's collection. It is important to note that Samtidsbild has been iteratively developed since 2011, very early for a museum to be thinking actively about digital-first collecting. Still, the terms and conditions did not directly assert a claim to shared ownership, with SCM only retaining a right to use through Creative Common licences and other stipulations. </p>
            <p>The case of SCM shows how models of shared ownership, especially in the realm of digital collecting, are still taking shape. Projects that collect from social media are at the forefront of attempts to grapple with the conditions and licensing issues this throws up. Documenting the Now (DocNow) is an interesting example because it has experimented with archiving born-digital social media content. DocNow's approach acknowledges the need for some traditional archival practices, as well as attending to ethical considerations that mean aspects of the archival process need to change to make them more appropriate for the social media environment. The project began in 2016, in response to the murder of Michael Brown, an unarmed black teenager, by a white police officer in Ferguson, Missouri (Galarza 2018). After initial discussions about what could be done to document the response to the killing, Bergis Jules and Ed Summers worked together to try and archive relevant Twitter hashtags and the DocNow project was born (Jules et al 2018). </p>
            <p>The project advocates for engaging with the ethics of collecting social media and rooting it in the core values of practitioners (Jules 2016). It has also highlighted issues such as lack of user awareness or informed consent about how social media platforms use and share data; the potential misuse of social media content; the heightened risk of harm for marginalized communities on social media; and the difficulty in applying traditional ethical archival practices to social media content (Jules et al 2018: 3). Some of the key recommendations to come out of DocNow centre on active engagement with the communities being documented. The aim is to foster relationships that go beyond what can be collected from the web freely, and to move traditional practices towards the practices that social media communities have themselves created (Jules et al 2018: 12). </p>
            <p>Although the context is different, it is possible to observe comparable practices in institutions like Aalborg City Archives (ACA) in Denmark. In an interview with one of the authors, the archivists discussed how ACA collects Instagram images. They explained that they cannot own Instagram users' photos, only ever have permission to use them (Rees 2021a). The Archive invites the users to sign formal archival documentation, donating possession of a copy of the digital file, and consulting on the most appropriate form of licence to use it. As with SCM, this does not constitute a formal shared ownership agreement, there is still a process by which the Archive becomes the tangible repository of the digital file that represents the image, with the donation form acting as a less ambiguous means of acknowledging ACA's rights over the photograph within their collection. In following and continuing to develop processes like those of SCM, DocNow and ACA, collecting institutions can take pragmatic steps towards negotiating shared ownership and guardianship approaches, while also reassessing the ethical appropriateness of their claims to total ownership over such material. </p>
            <p>Before concluding this section, it is worth mentioning one example of how digital collecting practices might change in relation to shared ownership in the future, specifically in the context of rapidly developing digital infrastructures such as blockchain. While it is beyond the scope of this article to explore in detail, Frances Liddell has carried out research on the potential of blockchain technology for digital collections in museums. She describes how digital tokens (also called non-fungible tokens or NFTs) are “singularized” through blockchain technology, which produces an immutable provenance and “builds in authenticity and exclusivity for any token exchanged within the blockchain network” (Liddell 2021: 221). Liddell studies the capacity of such networks to materialize value in digital versions of museum objects (cryptocollectibles), as a mode of shared guardianship and audience engagement. Her work also suggests that there may be unexplored uses of blockchain as a tool for helping to track and facilitate shared ownership of born-digital material. However, any application of this practice would need to be approached with caution, based on ongoing legal discussions about the grey areas concerning the actual “ownability” of NTF-works (Juhász and Sztermen 2024), and the degree to which GLAMs are computationally set up to take advantage of technology like blockchain.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>This article has explored digital collecting practices across the institutional boundaries of GLAMs to assess current perspectives and approaches, and the challenges that digital material presents to ownership. The ownership-led model of collecting was discussed in the first part of the article. The case study of the V&amp;A represents an instance of trying to apply traditional ownership and acquisition procedures to non-traditional material, which diminished the possibilities for preserving the dynamic and interactive elements of a social media object. Next, we identified what we termed ambiguous ownership, focusing on digital heritage aggregation. The Click and Flick case study shed light on how deflecting ownership claims can limit the scope for preserving digital objects and their associated contexts over time. Finally, we drew together several examples of digital collecting that loosely correspond with principles of shared ownership. As with the ownership-led model, shared ownership and stewardship approaches have been utilized in non-digital GLAM collections for a number of years. However, the very nature of digital material calls into question notions of control and authority over material objects traditionally associated with ownership. Digital collecting has, to some extent, shifted the balance of institutional models away from those that claim to own cultural heritage outright. </p>
            <p>As suggested at the beginning of the article, the issues that digital collecting raises for GLAMs in terms of ownership are taking place against a wider backdrop of practices and movements that are attempting to unsettle institutional authority and the indisputable right to own cultural heritage material. Some commentators have recognized the potential of digital media to change conversations around ownership and bring them more in line with “an increasingly digital environment and pluralistic society” (Light 2019). Yet a finding of this article is that digital collecting is not inherently more open, plural and oriented towards shared rights. Indeed, the discussion has shown that, in practice, there are ambiguities to shared ownership, especially when rights and licensing agreements are hidden in the terms and conditions. For digital collecting, then, as with any form of collecting, GLAMs must seek to negotiate rights and shared ownership claims in a clear and informed way.</p>
            <p>Ultimately, as GLAMs increase their digital holdings, so too increases the demand for more shared approaches to the collection of cultural heritage. This reality necessitates an institutional mentality shift. Trying to crack the code of shared, ethical ownership and guardianship is one way that GLAMs can start developing collaborative relationships with one another based on deeper understandings of their collections and their stakeholders. It is also a good starting place for creating new strategies for digital collecting as a core part of GLAMs' work.</p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="agostinho2019" label="Agostinho 2019">Agostinho, D. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Archival encounters: Rethinking 
             access and care in digital colonial archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 19(2), pp. 141-165.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="arrigoni_etal2022" label="Arrigoni et al. 2022">Arrigoni, G., Kane, N., McConnachie, S., and McKim, J. (2022) 
             <title rend="italic">Preserving and sharing born-digital and hybrid objects from and across the National Collection</title>. 
             London: Victoria and Albert Museum.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="arvanitis_etal2021" label="Arvanitis and Zuanni 2021">Arvanitis, K. and Zuanni, C. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Digital 
             (and) materiality in museums</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, 19(2), pp. 143-148.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bastian_etal2009" label="Bastian and Alexander 2009">Bastian, J.A. and Alexander, B. (eds.) (2009) 
             <title rend="italic">Community archives: The shaping of memory</title>. London: Facet Publishing.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bearman1991" label="Bearman 1991">Bearman, D. (1991) <title rend="quotes">An indefensible bastion: Archives as 
             repositories in the electronic age</title>, in Bearman, D. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Archival management of electronic 
             records</title>. Pittsburgh, PA: Archives &amp; Museum Informatics.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bearman_etal1998" label="Bearman and Trant 1998">Bearman, D. and Trant, J. (1998) <title rend="quotes">Unifying 
             our cultural memory: Could electronic environments bridge the historical accidents That fragment cultural collections?</title>, 
             in Dempsey, L., Criddle, S., and Heseltine, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Information landscapes for a learning society, 
             networking and the future of libraries</title>, vol. 3. London: Library Association. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://www.archimuse.com/papers/ukoln98paper/">http://www.archimuse.com/papers/ukoln98paper/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bell2018" label="Bell 2018">Bell, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Digital contexts: How communities self-archive 
             online</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.johnpbell.com/digital-contexts-how-communities-self-archive-online/">https://www.johnpbell.com/digital-contexts-how-communities-self-archive-online/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boogh2013" label="Boogh 2013">Boogh, E. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Samtidsbild/contemporary images – A method 
             of collecting vernacular photography in the digital age</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum</title>, 65, pp. 54-67.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boon2022" label="Boon 2022">Boon, T. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Origins and ambitions of the Congruence Engine 
             project”</title>, <title rend="italic">Science Museum Group Journal</title>, 18. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.15180/221801/001">https://doi.org/10.15180/221801/001</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bowker2005" label="Bowker 2005">Bowker, G.C. (2005) <title rend="italic">Memory practices in the sciences</title>. 
             Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brugger2016" label="Brügger 2016">Brügger, N. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Digital humanities in the 21st century: 
             Digital material as a driving force</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10(3). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000256/000256.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000256/000256.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cameron_etal2007" label="Cameron and Kenderdine 2007">Cameron, F. and Kenderdine, S. (eds.) (2007) 
             <title rend="italic">Theorizing digital cultural heritage: A critical discourse</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cameron2013" label="Cameron 2013">Cameron, F. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The liquid museum: New institutional 
             ontologies for a complex, uncertain world</title>, in Message, K. and Witcomb, A. (eds.) <title rend="italic">The international 
             handbook of museum studies</title>, vol. 1. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons, pp. 345-361.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="caswell_etal2016" label="Caswell and Cifor 2016">Caswell, M. and Cifor, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">From human 
             rights to feminist ethics: Radical empathy in the archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 81(1), pp. 23-43.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="caswell_etal2017" label="Caswell, Punzalan, and Sangwand 2017">Caswell, M., Punzalan, R., and Sangwand, T.K. (2017) 
             <title rend="quotes">Critical archival studies: An introduction</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library and 
             Information Studies</title>, 1(2). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i2.50">https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i2.50</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cathro2001" label="Cathro 2001">Cathro, W. (2001) <title rend="quotes">Smashing the silos: Towards convergence in 
             information management and resource discovery</title>, <title rend="italic">National Library of Australia Staff Papers</title>. 
             Canberra, Australia: National Library of Australia.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chan_etal2014" label="Chan and Cope 2014">Chan, S. and Cope, A. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Collecting the present: 
             Digital code and collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Museums and the Web</title>, 19.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="christen_etal2018" label="Christen et al. 2018">Christen, K., Davis, L., Griffith, Z., and Neely, J. (2018) 
             <title rend="quotes">Traditional knowledge and digital archives: An interview with Kim Christen</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">disClosure: A Journal of Social Theory</title>, 27(5). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.13023/disclosure.27.02">https://doi.org/10.13023/disclosure.27.02</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cook2013" label="Cook 2013">Cook, T. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Evidence, memory, identity, and community: 
             Four shifting archival paradigms</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 13, pp. 95-120.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cumiskey2018" label="Cumiskey 2018">Cumiskey, G. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Introduction to digital 
             preservation</title>, <title rend="italic">Museums and digital memory: From creation and curation to digital 
             preservation</title>. The British Museum.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="derrida1995" label="Derrida 1995">Derrida, J. (1995) <title rend="quotes">Archive fever: A Freudian 
             impression</title>, <title rend="italic">Diacritics</title>, 25(2), pp. 9-63.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dempsey2000" label="Dempsey 2000">Dempsey, L. (2000) <title rend="quotes">Scientific, industrial, and 
             cultural heritage: A shared approach</title>, <title rend="italic">Ariadne</title>, 22. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue/22/dempsey/">https://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue/22/dempsey/</ref> (Accessed: 
             2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="desvallees_etal2010" label="Desvallées and Mairesse 2010">Desvallées, A. and Mairesse, F. (2010) 
             <title rend="italic">Key concepts of museology</title>. Paris: Armand Colin-ICOM-ICOFOM.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="drabinski2019" label="Drabinski 2019">Drabinski, E. (2019) <title rend="quotes">What is critical about 
             critical librarianship?</title>, <title rend="italic">Art Libraries Journal</title>, 44(2), 49-57. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/alj.2019.3">https://doi.org/10.1017/alj.2019.3</ref> (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dsouza2018" label="D'Souza 2018">D'Souza, A. (2018) <title rend="italic">Whitewalling: Art, race and protest 
             in 3 acts</title>. New York: Badlands Unlimited.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dutia_etal2021" label="Dutia and Stack 2021">Dutia, K. and Stack, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Heritage connector: 
             A machine learning framework for building linked open data from museum collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Applied AI 
             Letters</title>, 2(2).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="evans_etal2015" label="Evans et al. 2015">Evans, J., McKemmish, S., Daniels, E., and McCarthy, G. (2015) 
             <title rend="quotes">Self-determination and archival autonomy: advocating activism</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival 
             Science</title>, 15, pp. 337-368.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="flinn_etal2009" label="Flinn, Stevens, and Shepherd 2009">Flinn, A., Stevens, M., and Shepherd, E. (2009) 
             <title rend="quotes">Whose memories, whose archives? Independent community archives, autonomy and the mainstream</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 9, pp. 71-86.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="foster_etal2016" label="Foster and Evans 2016">Foster, M.J. and Evans, M.R. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Libraries 
             creating sustainable services during community crisis: Documenting Ferguson</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Management</title>, 
             37(6/7), pp. 352-362.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fouseki_etal2013" label="Fouseki and Vacharopoulou 2013">Fouseki, K. and Vacharopoulou, K. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Digital 
             museum collections and social media: Ethical considerations of ownership and use</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Conservation 
             and Museum Studies</title>, 11(1), pp. 1-10.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="galarza2018" label="Galarza 2018">Galarza, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Documenting the now</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of American History</title>, 105(3), pp. 792-793.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="geismar2008" label="Geismar 2008">Geismar, H. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Cultural property, museums and the Pacific: 
             Reframing the debates</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Cultural Property</title>, 15(2), pp. 109-122.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="geismar2015" label="Geismar 2015">Geismar, H. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Anthropology and heritage regimes</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Anthropology</title>, 44(1), pp. 71-85.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="geismar2018" label="Geismar 2018">Geismar, H. (2018) <title rend="italic">Museum object lessons for the digital age</title>. 
             London: UCL Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gibson_etal2017" label="Gibson et al. 2017">Gibson, A.N. et al. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Libraries on the frontlines: 
             Neutrality and social justice</title>, <title rend="italic">Equality, Diversity and Inclusion: An International Journal</title>, 36(8), 
             pp. 751-766. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/EDI-11-2016-0100">https://doi.org/10.1108/EDI-11-2016-0100</ref> (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goncalves2019" label="Gonçalves 2019">Gonçalves, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The <quote rend="inline">liquid museum</quote>: 
             A relational museum that seeks to adapt to today's Society</title>, <title rend="italic">The Museum Review</title>, 4(1), pp. 1-8.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gregory_etal2013" label="Gregory and Higgins 2013">Gregory, L. and Higgins, S. (eds.) (2013) 
             <title rend="italic">Information literacy and social justice: Radical professional praxis</title>. Sacramento, CA: Library Juice Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="grewcock2013" label="Grewcock 2013">Grewcock, D. (2013) <title rend="italic">Doing museology differently</title>. London: 
             Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="grincheva_etal2024" label="Grincheva and Stainforth 2024">Grincheva, N. and Stainforth, E. (2024) 
             <title rend="italic">Geopolitics of digital heritage</title>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ham1981" label="Ham 1981">Ham, F.G. (1981) <title rend="quotes">Archival strategies for the post-custodial era</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">American Archivist</title>, 44(3), pp. 207-216.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawes_etal2018" label="Haes and Flood 2018">Hawes, A. and Flood, C. (2018) <title rend="italic">Curating and collecting digital 
             posters handbook</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://ccdgp.co.uk/colophon.html">https://ccdgp.co.uk/colophon.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hooton2006" label="Hooton 2006">Hooton, F. (2006) <title rend="quotes">PictureAustralia and the flickr effect</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">NLA Gateways</title>, 80. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://webarchive.nla.gov.au/awa/20060529045055/http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/11779/20060524-0000/www.nla.gov.au/pub/gateways/issues/80/story01.html">https://webarchive.nla.gov.au/awa/20060529045055/http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/11779/20060524-0000/www.nla.gov.au/pub/gateways/issues/80/story01.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hooton2007" label="Hooton 2007">Hooton, F. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Democratising history: Evaluating PictureAustralia's 
             flickr Pilot Project</title>, <title rend="italic">NLA Gateways</title>, 84. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://webarchive.nla.gov.au/awa/20070525063525/http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/11779/20070524-0000/www.nla.gov.au/pub/gateways/issues/84/story13.html">https://webarchive.nla.gov.au/awa/20070525063525/http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/11779/20070524-0000/www.nla.gov.au/pub/gateways/issues/84/story13.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hoorwood2018" label="Horwood 2018">Horwood, M. (2018) <title rend="italic">Sharing authority in the museum: Distributed 
             objects, reassembled relationships</title>. London: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hicks2020" label="Hicks 2020">Hicks, D. (2020) <title rend="italic">The brutish museums: The Benin bronzes, colonial violence 
             and cultural restitution</title>. London: Pluto Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="icom2017" label="ICOM 2017">International Code of Ethics for Museums (2017) <title rend="italic">ICOM code of ethics for 
             museums</title>. Paris: ICOM.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jones_etal2014" label="Jones and O'Neill 2014">Jones, M. and O'Neill, C. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Identity, records and 
             archival evidence: Exploring the needs of forgotten Australians and former child migrants</title>, <title rend="italic">Archives and 
             Records</title>, 35(2), pp. 110-125.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jones2018" label="Jones 2018">Jones, M. (2018) <title rend="italic">Artefacts, archives, and documentation in the relational 
             museum</title>. London: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="juhasz_etal2024" label="Juhász and Sztermen 2024">Juhász, Á., and Sztermen, O.L. (2024) <title rend="quotes">Transfering digital 
             artworks on online market platforms</title>, <title rend="italic">Public Governance, Administration and Finances Law Review</title>, 9(1). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.53116/pgaflr.7060">https://doi.org/10.53116/pgaflr.7060</ref> (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jules2016" label="Jules 2016">Jules, B. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Some thoughts on ethics and DocNow</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Documenting DocNow</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/some-thoughts-on-ethics-and-docnow-d19cfec427f2">https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/some-thoughts-on-ethics-and-docnow-d19cfec427f2</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jules_etal2018" label="Jules, Summers, and Mitchell 2018">Jules, B., Summers, E., and Mitchell, V.J. (2018) 
             <title rend="quotes">Ethical considerations for archiving social media content generated by contemporary social movements: Challenges, 
             opportunities, and recommendations</title>, <title rend="italic">DocNow</title>, 12. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf">https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf</ref> (Accessed: 
             2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kelleher2017" label="Kelleher 2017">Kelleher, C. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Archives without archives: (Re)locating and (re)defining 
             the archive through post-custodial praxis</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library and Information Studies</title>, 1(2). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i2.29">https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i2.29</ref> (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kidd2019" label="Kidd 2019">Kidd, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Digital media ethics and museum communication</title>, in 
             Drotner, K. et al (eds.) <title rend="italic">The Routledge handbook of museums, media and communication</title>. New York: Routledge, pp. 193-204.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kirchoff_etal2008" label="Kirchoff, Schwibenz, and Sieglerschmidt 2008">Kirchhoff, T., Schweibenz, W., and Sieglerschmidt, J. (2008) 
             <title rend="quotes">Archives, libraries, museums and the spell of ubiquitous knowledge</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 8(4), 
             pp. 251-266.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kreps2008" label="Kreps 2008">Kreps, C. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Appropriate museology in theory and practice</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Museum Management and Curatorship</title>, 23(1), pp. 23-41.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kreps2015" label="Kreps 2015">Kreps, C. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Appropriate museology and the <quote rend="inline">new museum 
             ethics</quote>: Honoring diversity</title>, <title rend="italic">Nordisk Museologi</title>, 2, pp. 4-16.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lagerkvist2015" label="Lagerkvist 2015">Lagerkvist, C. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Empowerment and anger: Learning how to share 
             ownership of the museum</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, 4(2), pp. 52-68.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="legget2018" label="Legget 2018">Legget, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Shared heritage, shared authority, shared accountability? 
             Co-generating museum performance criteria as a means of embedding <quote rend="inline">shared authority</quote></title>, 
             <title rend="italic">International Journal of Heritage Studies</title>, 24(7), pp. 723-742.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lessig2008" label="Lessig 2008">Lessig, L. (2008) <title rend="italic">Remix: Making art and commerce thrive in the hybrid economy</title>. 
             London: Penguin.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lewi_etal2020" label="Lewi et al. 2020">Lewi, H., Smith, W., Vom Lehn, D., and Cooke, S. (eds.) (2020) <title rend="italic">The 
             Routledge international handbook of new digital practices in galleries, libraries, archives, museums and heritage sites</title>. New York: 
             Routledge.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="loc2021" label="LOC 2021">Library of Congress (2021) <title rend="italic">Digital collections strategy overview 2022-2026</title>. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.loc.gov/acq/devpol/Digital%20Collections%20Strategy%20Overview_final.pdf">https://www.loc.gov/acq/devpol/Digital%20Collections%20Strategy%20Overview_final.pdf</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="liddell2021" label="Liddell 2021">Liddell, F. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Building shared guardianship through blockchain technology 
             and digital museum objects</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, 19(2), pp. 220-236.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="light2019" label="Light 2019">Light, M. (2019) <title rend="quotes">From responsible custody to responsible stewardship</title>, 
             in Weideman, C. and Caldera, M.A. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Society of American Archivists</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://digitalscholarship.unlv.edu/lib_articles/590">https://digitalscholarship.unlv.edu/lib_articles/590</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lonetree2012" label="Lonetree 2012">Lonetree, A. (2012) <title rend="italic">Decolonizing museums: Representing Native America 
             in national and tribal museums</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lucky_etal2018" label="Lucky and Harkema 2018">Lucky, S. and Harkema, C. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Back to basics: Supporting 
             digital humanities and community collaboration using the core strength of the academic library</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Library 
             Perspectives</title>, 34(3), pp. 188-199.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lyman_etal1998" label="Lyman and Besser 1998">Lyman, P. and Besser, H. (1998) <title rend="quotes">Defining the problem of our 
             vanishing memory: Background, current status, models for resolution</title>, in Parry, R. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Museums in the digital 
             age</title>. New York: Routledge, pp. 336-343.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="macdonald2013" label="Macdonald 2013">Macdonald, S. (2013) <title rend="italic">Memorylands: Heritage and identity in Europe 
             today</title>. London: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="marstine2012" label="Marstine 2012">Marstine, J. (2012) <title rend="quotes">The contingent nature of the new museum ethics</title>, 
             in Marstine, J. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Routledge companion to museum ethics</title>. London: Routledge, pp. 3-25.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="marstine_etal2015" label="Marstine, Dodd, and Jones 2015">Marstine, J., Dodd, J., and Jones, C. (2015) 
             <title rend="quotes">Reconceptualising museum ethics for the twenty-first century museum</title>, in McCarthy, C. (ed.) 
             <title rend="italic">Museum Practice</title>. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, pp. 69-96.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="marstine2017" label="Marstine 2017">Marstine, J. (2017) <title rend="italic">Critical practice: Artists, museums, 
             ethics</title>. New York, Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="marty2014" label="Marty 2014">Marty, P.F. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Digital convergence and the information profession 
             in cultural heritage organizations: Reconciling internal and external demands</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title>, 62(3), 
             pp. 613-627.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="meehan2020" label="Meehan2020">Meehan, N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Digital museum objects and memory: Postdigital 
             materiality, aura and value</title>, <title rend="italic">Curator: The Museum Journal</title>, pp. 1-17.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ngata_etal2012" label="Ngata, Ngata-Gibson, and Salmond 2012">Ngata, W., Ngata-Gibson, H., and Salmond, A. (2012) 
             <title rend="quotes">Te ataakura: Digital taonga and cultural innovation</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Material 
             Culture</title>, 17(3), pp. 229-244.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="owens2018" label="Owens 2018">Owens, T. (2018) <title rend="italic">The theory and craft of digital 
             preservation</title>. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="parry2007" label="Parry 2007">Parry, R. (2007) <title rend="italic">Recoding the museum: Digital heritage and 
             the technologies of change</title>. New York: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="parry2010" label="Parry 20120">Parry, R. (ed.) (2010) <title rend="italic">Museums in a digital age</title>. New York: 
             Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="perzanowski_etal2016a" label="Perzanowski and Schultz 2016">Perzanowski, A. and Schultz, J.M. (2016) 
             <title rend="italic">The end of ownership: Personal property in the digital economy</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="puzalan_etal2016b" label="Punzalan and Caswell 2016">Punzalan, R.L., and Caswell, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Critical 
             directions for archival approaches to social justice</title>, <title rend="italic">The Library Quarterly</title>, 86(1), pp. 25-42.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rayward1997" label="Rayward 1997">Rayward, W.B. (1997) <title rend="quotes">Electronic information and the functional 
             integration of libraries, museums, and archives</title>, in Higgs, E. (ed.) <title rend="italic">History and Electronic Artefacts</title>. 
             New York: Clarendon Press, pp. 207-225.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rees2021a" label="Rees 2021a">Rees, A.J. (2021a) <title rend="italic">Remixing museology: An approach to collecting social 
             media in museums</title>. PhD thesis. University of Leeds.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rees2021b" label="Rees 2021b">Rees, A.J. (2021b) <title rend="quotes">Collecting online memetic cultures: How tho</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, 19(2), pp. 199-219.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ridge2014" label="Ridge 2014">Ridge, M.M. (2014) <title rend="italic">Crowdsourcing our cultural heritage</title>. London: 
             Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sherratt2016" label="Sherratt 2016">Sherratt, T. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Hacking heritage: Power and participation in 
             digital cultural collections</title> <title rend="italic">2016 Digital GLAM symposium</title>, Melbourne, Australia, 15 July. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://discontents.com.au/hacking-heritage-power-and-participation-in-digital-cultural-collections/index.html">http://discontents.com.au/hacking-heritage-power-and-participation-in-digital-cultural-collections/index.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schwartz_etal2002" label="Schwartz and Cook 2002">Schwartz, J.M. and Cook, T. (2002) <title rend="quotes">Archives, records, 
             and power: The making of modern memory</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 2, pp. 1-19.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sutherland2019" label="Sutherland 2019">Sutherland, T. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The carceral archive: Documentary records, 
             narrative construction, and predictive risk assessment</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, 4(1). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22148/16.039">https://doi.org/10.22148/16.039</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="trant2009" label="Trant 2009">Trant, J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Emerging convergence? Thoughts on museums, archives, 
             libraries, and professional training</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum Management and Curatorship</title>, 24(4), pp. 369-387.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thorpe_etal2021" label="Thorpe et al. 2021">Thorpe, K., Christen K., Booker, L., and Galassi, M. (2021) 
             <title rend="quotes">Designing archival information systems through partnerships with Indigenous communities; Developing the Mukurtu Hubs 
             and Spoke model in Australia</title>, <title rend="italic">Australasian Journal of Information Systems</title>, 24, pp. 1-22. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10453/159542">http://hdl.handle.net/10453/159542</ref> (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="van-oost2012" label="Van Oost 2012">Van Oost, O. (2012) <title rend="italic">Living lab methodology in museum studies: 
             An exploration</title>. Roskilde, Denmark: Roskilde University.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="va2023" label="V &amp; A Museum 2023">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum (2023) <title rend="quotes">A history of collecting digital 
             objects at the V&amp;A</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.vam.ac.uk/articles/a-history-of-collecting-digital-objects-at-the-va">https://www.vam.ac.uk/articles/a-history-of-collecting-digital-objects-at-the-va</ref> 
             (Accessed: 2 January 2025).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="williams_etal2017" label="Williams and Drake 2017">Williams, S.M., and Drake, J. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Power to the people: 
             Documenting police violence in Cleveland</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library and Information Studies</title>, 1(2), pp. 1-27.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zuanni2021" label="Zuanni 2021">Zuanni, C. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Theorizing born digital objects: Museums and contemporary 
             materialities</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum and Society</title>, 19(2), pp. 184-198.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
