<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Manuscript Study in Digital Spaces: The State of
                    the Field and New Ways Forward</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Bridget <dhq:family>Almas</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>The Alpheios Project, Ltd.</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>balmas@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Bridget Almas is currently the lead software developer and architect for
                            The Alpheios Project, developing open source tools for the study and
                            enjoyment of classical languages. In her prior role at Tufts University,
                            Bridget was the technical lead on the Perseids Project and before that
                            the Perseus Digital Library. She has also acted in several leadership
                            roles in the Research Data Alliance and as a liaison between the
                            Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) and RDA. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Emad <dhq:family>Khazraee</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>School of Information, Kent State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>emad@kent.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Emad Khazraee is a sociotechnical information scientist and assistant
                            professor in the iSchool at Kent State University. He received his PhD
                            in Information Studies from the College of Computing and Informatics,
                            Drexel University (2014). His research is formed around the interplay
                            between social and technical phenomena. Currently, he is studying the
                            relationship between digital technologies, new media, and social
                            change.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Matthew Thomas
                        <dhq:family>Miller</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Roshan Institute for Persian Studies, University of Maryland
                        College Park</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mtmiller@umd.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Matthew Thomas Miller is Assistant Professor of Persian Literature and
                            Digital Humanities at the University of Maryland, College Park. He also
                            serves as the Associate Director of the Roshan Initiative in Persian
                            Digital Humanities (PersDig@UMD) and co-PI for the multi-institutional
                            Open Islamicate Texts Initiative (OpenITI) and the Persian Manuscript
                            Initiative (PMI). His research focuses on medieval Sufi literature, the
                            history of sexuality and the body, and digital humanities. He currently
                            is working on a book project, entitled <title rend="quotes">Embodying
                                the Beloved: Embodiment and Mystical Modes of Meaning Creation in
                                Medieval Persian Sufi Literature,</title> and a number of articles
                            on computational or <q>distant reading</q> approaches to Persian
                            literature and carnivalesque Sufi poetry.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Joshua <dhq:family>Westgard</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University Libraries, University of Maryland College
                        Park</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>westgard@umd.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Joshua Westgard is a Systems Librarian for Digital Programs and
                            Initiatives at the University of Maryland Libraries, in which capacity
                            he is primarily responsible for managing digital repository systems and
                            the preservation of digital assets. In addition to an MLS in Digital
                            Curation from the University of Maryland, he holds a Ph.D. in Medieval
                            European History from the University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, and
                            has published numerous articles on the manuscript transmission and
                            reception of the works of the Venerable Bede. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000374</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2018-07-03">03 July 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital workspaces</item>
                        <item>digital humanities</item>
                        <item>workflows</item>
                        <item>standards</item>
                        <item>data curation</item>
                        <item>pedagogy</item>
                        <item>crowdsourcing</item>
                        <item>data management</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In the last decade tremendous advances have been made in the tools and platforms
                    available for the digital study of manuscripts. Much work, however, remains to
                    be done in order to address the wide range of pedagogical, cataloging,
                    preservation, scholarly (individual and collaborative), and citizen science
                    (crowdsourcing) workflows and use cases in a user-friendly manner. This study
                    (1) summarizes the feedback of dozens of technologists, manuscript experts, and
                    curators obtained through survey data and workshop focus groups; (2) provides a
                        <soCalled>state of the field</soCalled> report which assesses the current
                    tools available and their limitations; and, (3) outlines principles to help
                    guide future development. The authors in particular emphasize the importance of
                    producing tool-independent data, fostering intellectual <soCalled>trading
                        zones</soCalled> between technologists, scholars, librarians, and curators,
                    utilizing a code base with an active community of users, and re-conceptualizing
                    tool-creation as a collaborative form of humanistic intellectual labor.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A study of the tools and platforms available for the digital study of
                    manuscripts.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>I. Introduction</head>
                <p>On 4 November 2016 the Roshan Institute for Persian Studies at the University of
                    Maryland (UMD), College Park hosted the <title rend="quotes">Manuscripts in the
                        Digital Age Workshop,</title> which was co-sponsored by Tufts University’s
                    Perseids Project, UMD’s Arts and Humanities Center for Synergy, UMD’s School of
                    Languages, Literatures, and Cultures (SLLC), and Kent State University’s School
                    of Library and Information Science. The two-day workshop was born out of a
                    concern that the existing digital infrastructure and tools for manuscript
                    studies are failing to address the wide range of workflows, use cases, and
                    research and pedagogical needs of scholars and curators in the field. Some of
                    these issues arise from technological barriers. For example, many of the best
                    solutions currently available require a level of technical knowledge that the
                    vast majority of scholars and curators do not possess, and some solutions even
                    require developer time to be properly set up (a financial hurdle that further
                    stymies utilization of these tools by many at smaller institutions). Other
                    problems, however, are the result of language-specific issues (e.g., poor
                    display of non-Latin script and right-to-left languages) and persistent gaps in
                    and atomization of functions and workflows. </p>
                <p>The organizers had four primary objectives for the workshop: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>to assess the current state of tools, services and infrastructure for
                            the creation and preservation of digital editions and annotation of
                            manuscripts, images, and related data objects;</item>
                        <item>to determine the extent to which those tools, services and
                            infrastructure that come closest to meeting the needs of our respective
                            projects can be reused and linked together;</item>
                        <item>to identify any apparent obstacles to their reuse and gaps in the
                            functionality that they provide; </item>
                        <item>to create a <soCalled>trading zone</soCalled><note> On the concept and
                                importance of <quote rend="inline" source="#x_galison1997">trading
                                    zones,</quote> please see: <ptr target="#galison1997"/>. Galison
                                suggests a model for cross-boundary collaboration through the
                                development of new shared cultures and languages. He argues that
                                different subcultures can collaborate and exchange knowledge at the
                                local level, without global agreement, by developing an
                                interlanguage that groups share and use to communicate.</note> to
                            foster dialogue between researchers, technologists, and librarians in
                            the university, gallery, library, archive, and museum (GLAM) contexts
                            regarding the functionality they would ideally like to see in an
                            integrated image workspace.</item>
                    </list> Building on the insights of the distinguished group of scholars,
                    curators, librarians, and technologists who participated in this two-day
                        workshop<note> In addition to the authors of the present work, the following
                        individuals were also in attendance: John Abrahams (John Hopkins
                        University), Alberto Campagnolo (Library of Congress), Hugh Cayless (Duke
                        University/Digital Latin Library), Elijah Cooke (Roshan Institute for
                        Persian Studies, University of Maryland), Hirad Dinavari (Library of
                        Congress), Doug Emery (Schoenberg Institute for Manuscript Studies,
                        University of Pennsylvania), Mahmood Gharavi (Columbia University), Ahmet T.
                        Karamustafa (Roshan Institute for Persian Studies, University of Maryland),
                        Fatemeh Keshavarz (Roshan Institute for Persian Studies, University of
                        Maryland), Ida Meftahi (Roshan Institute for Persian Studies, University of
                        Maryland), Patrick Murray-John (George Mason University/Omeka), Mark Patton
                        (Johns Hopkins University), Simon Rettig (Freer Gallery of Art and Arthur M.
                        Sackler Gallery), Raffaele Viglianti (Maryland Institute for Technology in
                        the Humanities, University of Maryland), Joan Weeks (Library of Congress),
                        and Jeffrey Witt (Loyola University Maryland). Daniel Gullo, Chad LaVigne,
                        and William Straub from the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library also joined
                        us for part of Friday afternoon to discuss the vHMML Reading Room.</note>,
                    this work first will provide a general overview of the state of the field and
                    then draft principles to help guide future development efforts. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>II. Problems and Desiderata</head>
                <div>
                    <head>General Overview</head>
                    <p> While there has been tremendous advancement in the development of digital
                        tools and platforms for the display and study of image data over the last
                        decade, there is still no end-to-end solution that meets the myriad needs of
                        scholars, curators, librarians, and students.<note> Henceforth, when we want
                            to collectively refer to <q>scholars, curators, librarians, and
                                students</q> we will use the term <q>users.</q> We will only use the
                            more specific terms <q>scholars,</q>
                            <q>curators,</q>
                            <q>librarians,</q> or <q>students</q> when we want to differentiate one
                            class of this broader category of <q>users</q> from the others.</note>
                        This is not a criticism of the pioneering efforts of the developers of the
                        existing tools and platforms. It is the result of the fact that there are an
                        incredible number of diverse use cases, each of which demands different
                        functionality and workflows. Users are also working with a wide variety of
                        different sized collections and linguistic traditions that are not all well
                        supported by current tools and platforms. </p>
                    <p>This has led to a proliferation of tools and platforms that are specific to a
                        particular collection or perform a discrete task (e.g., display, cataloging,
                        transcription) — or, in some of the more well-developed tools, a
                            <term>set</term> of discrete tasks — for the user. The tools and
                        platforms listed in <ref target="#table01">Table 1</ref> are just some of
                        the more popular tools and platforms that manuscript scholars report
                        utilizing in their research.</p>
                    <table xml:id="table01">
                        <head>Tools/Platforms used by scholars participated in the survery</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Tool/Platform</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Type</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>oXygen</cell>
                            <cell>Desktop software application</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Microsoft Access</cell>
                            <cell>Desktop software application</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>PDFExpert</cell>
                            <cell>Desktop software application</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>XMLMind</cell>
                            <cell>Desktop software application</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Kitodo</cell>
                            <cell>Software platform</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>IIIF (International Image Interoperability Framework)</cell>
                            <cell>API Specifications</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mirador</cell>
                            <cell>Web application</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Omeka</cell>
                            <cell>Web application (hosted or local installation)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>e-ktobe</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>OPenn</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>The Vatican Library Platform</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pinakes</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Perdita Project</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Brotherton Manuscripts</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>DEx: A Database of Dramatic Extracts</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Shelley-Godwin Archive</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Blake Archive</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>CELM: Catalogue of English Literary Manuscripts</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Camena</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>British Literary Manuscripts Online</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Gallica (Bibliothèque Nationale de France)</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>The New Testament Virtual Manuscript Room</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Coptic Old Testament Virtual Manuscript Room</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>vHMML</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Coptic Scriptorium</cell>
                            <cell>Online dataset/collection and tools </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>TAPAS</cell>
                            <cell>Online platform, repository and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Transkribus</cell>
                            <cell>Online platform plus installable tools </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Papyri.info</cell>
                            <cell>Online platform, dataset/collection and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Perseids</cell>
                            <cell>Online platform and tools</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>All of these platforms and tools have certain virtues and do certain tasks
                        well. Ultimately, however, their content, functionality, and workflows are
                        too often siloed/atomized so that the user must either learn numerous
                        different tools and platforms or have the technological skills necessary to
                        link them together or export and manipulate their data post-analysis. This
                        points to one of the biggest problems for users: none of the current tools
                        or platforms reproduces the scholarly, curatorial, or pedagogical workflow
                        in a single, integrated, digital space. As such, they are not always time
                        saving in the same way that other more widely adopted digital technologies
                        are.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements of Scholars, Curators, Librarians, and Technologists</head>
                    <p>Prior to the workshop we distributed a survey to colleagues in the Digital
                        Humanities, Classics, Middle Eastern/Islamic Studies, and library science
                        communities via the popular listservs associated with each.<note> For full
                            list of the survey questions, see Appendix I.</note> Twenty-seven
                        respondents completed the entire survey. Admittedly, this was not a
                        scientific or comprehensive survey, but its results are instructive and were
                        echoed by many of the participants in the workshop itself. Before delving
                        into the specific requirements of scholars, curators, and technologists,
                        there are a couple general insights that emerged from this survey. </p>
                    <p>First, the sizes of the manuscript collections with which users are working
                        vary widely. As can be seen in <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>, the
                        respondents to our survey are relatively evenly divided into the categories
                        of small (&lt; 100 mss), medium (100-999 mss), and large-scale (&gt; 1,000
                        mss) users. The diversity in collection size is not surprising given the
                        range of users — from scholars interested in studying a dozen manuscripts of
                        one work to librarians and curators at large institutions with thousands of
                        digital manuscripts — however, it should serve as a cautionary note for
                        those looking to develop a universal, end-to-end solution for the diverse
                        forms of manuscript study, display, and curation, which each have their own
                        use cases and requisite workflows.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>Response to survey question #9 regarding the approximate size of the
                            manuscript collections with which the respondent works.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Secondly, users do not feel they personally have the technical expertise or
                        access to technical staff required for installing and running tools or
                        platforms. Almost 83 percent of survey respondents indicated that they
                        prefer an online, fully hosted site that does not require them to seek
                        assistance from technical staff at their universities in order to install
                        and run. This is an important consideration for future development efforts,
                        especially those aiming to cultivate a large and active community of
                        users.</p>
                    <p>Beyond these general observations, there was a wide array of other specific
                        insights that emerged from both the survey responses and the workshop. Below
                        is a synthesis of the answers provided by both survey participants and
                        workshop attendees (we have elected not to publish the survey responses
                        verbatim due to privacy concerns). Our division of these responses into
                        requirements of scholars, curators/librarians, and technologists is purely
                        heuristic. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Response to survey question #17 regarding whether the respondent has
                            access to technical staff or services at his or her home institution
                            that could install and run the tools or prefer to use an online site
                            that his or her institution does not have to maintain.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements of scholars:</head>
                    <p><list type="unordered">
                            <item>A tool/workspace that aggregates previous scholarly comments on
                                manuscripts of particular texts and authors;</item>
                            <item>A collaborative space to draw on expertise of catalogers and
                                content specialists of different areas (e.g., manuscript experts,
                                textual scholars, art historians). As we heard repeatedly at the
                                workshop, <quote rend="inline" source="#x">no one can do it
                                    alone</quote>;</item>
                            <item>Collaborative scholarly workflows (e.g., functionality and
                                workflows that enable in digital space the scholarly workshop model
                                of multiple scholars working together on one manuscript) and similar
                                workflows for citizen science, knowledge-sourcing, or crowd-sourcing
                                initiatives; </item>
                            <item>Pedagogical workflows for use with students and <soCalled>citizen
                                    scientists</soCalled>;</item>
                            <item>Ability to access manuscript images from multiple digital
                                repositories and use digital tools on them (i.e., a client
                                application model);</item>
                            <item>Integration of text and image data — as one can see in <ref
                                    target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>, over 65 percent of
                                respondents indicated they need to be able to work with both
                                manuscript text and image data in their work;</item>
                        </list>
                        <figure xml:id="figure03">
                            <head>Response to survey question #10 regarding whether the manuscript
                                text, image, or both is the primary focus of the respondent in their
                                work.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p><list type="unordered">
                            <item>Ability to annotate text and image data. The ability to annotate
                                both types of data was reported as a requirement by 72 percent of
                                respondents (see <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>);</item>
                        </list>
                        <figure xml:id="figure04">
                            <head>Response to survey question #11 regarding what kind of annotation
                                support the respondent needs in their work.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p><list type="unordered">
                            <item>Educational materials/tutorials on how to setup and use new
                                digital tools and workspaces;</item>
                            <item>Institutional mechanisms and support for creating joint projects
                                with digital librarians and technologists;</item>
                            <item>A common gateway (because there are too many separate digital
                                manuscript collections with unconnected repositories that cannot be
                                universally searched), linking of similar texts in multiple
                                repositories, and information about the differences between those
                                copies;</item>
                            <item>Tools and workflows to create and publish digital scholarly
                                editions of works (e.g., digital critical editions, multi-text
                                editions), including peer-review mechanisms;</item>
                            <item>Better non-Latin script/right-to-left language support;</item>
                            <item>Support for multimedia archives;</item>
                            <item>Geographic tagging (for images of architecture, for example) to
                                enable visualizations of diachronic transformations of place,
                                buildings, etc.; </item>
                            <item>Linking of sound recordings to geographic spaces;</item>
                            <item>Ability to work, side by side, with multiple versions of the same
                                manuscript — a requirement reported by over 85 percent of survey
                                respondents (<ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>) — and ability
                                to annotate text variants and compare and classify large collections
                                of manuscripts into manuscript families.</item>
                        </list>
                        <figure xml:id="figure05">
                            <head>Response to survey question #12 regarding whether the respondent
                                works with multiple manuscripts of the same text in their
                                work.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements of curators and librarians:</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Cataloging workflows (both for lone cataloger and collaborative
                            cataloging projects);</item>
                        <item>User-friendly sharing;</item>
                        <item>Inclusion of conservation reports;</item>
                        <item>More attention to materiality of the object and structure of books
                            (e.g., bindings), including metadata on the whole object;</item>
                        <item>Mechanisms that allow for restricted user access (although many
                            collections are moving to open-access models, not all collections are
                            willing to make images completely open access: in the survey results a
                            sizable minority (37 percent) still reported that they need to restrict
                            access to their image or textual data due to licensing/copyright reasons
                            — see <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>);</item>
                    </list>
                    <figure xml:id="figure06">
                        <head>Response to survey question #14 regarding whether respondent needs to
                            restrict access to the images or textual content of their manuscripts
                            for licensing/copyright reasons.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Tools that can be used by local teams (especially in poor or conflict
                            areas) that are computationally light and standards-compliant (thus
                            helping to facilitate collaboration with wider scholarly communities); </item>
                        <item>Standards for dealing with multiple manuscripts in a single
                            codex;</item>
                        <item>Digital reunification of dispersed codices;</item>
                        <item>Digital repatriation of objects removed from their country of
                            origin;</item>
                        <item>Expanded metadata for features such as type of paper, color of ink,
                            type of leather;</item>
                        <item>Inclusion of preservation metadata;</item>
                        <item>Better support for dealing with alternative (i.e., non-traditional
                            manuscript) image data, such as wedding certificates, audio visual
                            materials, textiles, and 3D objects.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements of technologists:</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Interoperability;</item>
                        <item>Standards compliance;</item>
                        <item>Persistent identifiers and permanent citation of manuscript data — a
                            critical need, which over 92 percent of survey respondents indicated was
                            required for their work (see <ref target="#figure07">Figure
                            7</ref>);</item>
                    </list>
                    <figure xml:id="figure07">
                        <head>Response to survey question #13 regarding whether enabling citation of
                            manuscript data (text or image) is important for the respondent’s
                            work.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Named entity recognition;</item>
                        <item>Ability to display documents together with known metadata;</item>
                        <item>Ability to add and correct existing metadata;</item>
                        <item>Stable edition numbers for texts published online (i.e.,
                            versioning);</item>
                        <item>Version control (i.e., detailed tracking of textual changes through
                            time);</item>
                        <item>Citation via tag or git commit hash;</item>
                        <item>Support for reading in multiple directions;</item>
                        <item>Usability of tools/platforms in low bandwidth locations;</item>
                        <item>Rejection of digital repository silo models;</item>
                        <item>Controlled vocabularies that are built into
                            cataloging/metadata;</item>
                        <item>Ability to export data in multiple standard formats, especially TEI
                            XML;</item>
                        <item>Online hosted solution (preferable) or downloadable out-of-the-box
                            program, since most users report that they do not have the requisite
                            technical knowledge to setup tools/platforms and they do not have in
                            house support from technologists to do it for them (see <ref
                                target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>).</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Tool-Specific Issues</head>
                    <p>Much hard work has been devoted over the past decade to building digital
                        infrastructure and tools for manuscript display and study. The tools and
                        platforms we reviewed represent some of the best of the field currently.
                        There are, however, user requirements that are still not being met. </p>
                    <p>We recognized from the outset that each of the tools selected for review in
                        the workshop was designed with its own use case in mind, and coding for
                        general purpose and reuse very likely was not explicitly in scope for many,
                        or even any, of them. The goals and guidelines we used for the evaluations
                        (presented in full in Appendix II) were developed with the aim of helping us
                        surface some key characteristics that would help us better understand the
                        potential of each tool as a starting point for further work. In particular,
                        we tried to answer these questions for each tool:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>What use cases and workflows is it <emph>intended to</emph>
                            support?</item>
                        <item>What additional use cases and workflows is it <emph>capable of</emph>
                            supporting?</item>
                        <item>Could gaps in functionality be filled by combining it with another
                            tool?</item>
                        <item>Could gaps in functionality be filled by extending it with new
                            development?</item>
                        <item>What skills are necessary to be able to use it effectively?</item>
                        <item>What skills are necessary to be able to extend it with new
                            functionality?</item>
                        <item>How well does it support data management best practices?</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Our review in the workshop — reproduced in summary form below — was not
                        comprehensive; it focused on the principal uses and characteristics of each
                        tool, to the extent we were able to discern them in the very limited time we
                        had available to us. In preparation for the workshop we had each tool
                        pre-installed in a virtual environment that workshop participants then used
                        collectively to evaluate the tools. It is important to note that preparing a
                        fully optimized configuration of each tool was not possible, so while our
                        results are certainly of value in identifying some important features and
                        gaps and in prioritizing what should happen next, they should only be
                        considered as a jumping off point and not taken as fully informed analyses
                        or judgments of any of these tools and platforms. While some tools we
                        analyzed have a well-documented code base, in this study we did not do a
                        thorough inspection of the code and documentation of each platform. Future
                        studies will need to investigate these platforms in this regard, considering
                        specific workflows and use cases to evaluate the extensibility of each
                        platform and to discuss development strategies and necessary next steps.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Scriptorium</title> was designed specifically for the
                        task of annotation and transcription of manuscript images. Preservation and
                        curation are not among its intended use cases. It supports import of images
                        via externally referenced IIIF manifests <ptr target="#IIIF2017"/>. It uses
                        custom metadata fields to describe manuscripts, and its metadata is limited
                        to the text — i.e., physical manuscript details, such as bindings, are not
                        included. Curation of metadata is not supported. The user interface was
                        designed specifically for scholarly and pedagogical workflows. Collaborative
                        features are in place, although not fully fleshed out. The code relies on
                        the Meteor javascript framework <ptr target="#meteor2017"/> and was not
                        developed with the intent of being reused for other purposes. Both of these
                        factors have implications for the long-term sustainability of the codebase.
                        Of all the tools we surveyed, Scriptorium’s user interface had the most
                        appeal to the scholars in the group. The user interface design is a
                        candidate for reuse, even if the underlying code itself might not be.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Omeka</title> was the most mature and well supported of
                        the platforms we looked at, with a large community of open source developers
                        contributing plugins and enhancements to the code base. It was also the most
                        general purpose. It is primarily intended for display and publication of
                        modest collections of digital materials. Support for real-time collaboration
                        or pedagogical workflows is not inherent in the platform, although there may
                        be plugins to provide some of this functionality. Omeka does offer excellent
                        support for metadata standards, providing built-in templates using Dublin
                        Core but allowing for easy extension with other controlled vocabularies. It
                        also has good data management support, offering the ability to supply your
                        own persistent identifiers (of any format, including Handles, URNs, DOIs,
                        etc.) for collection items, not restricting you to database specific node
                        identifiers. An existing IIIF plugin is not well integrated, but a current
                        effort to develop new support for IIIF, led by University of Toronto <ptr
                            target="#uot2017"/> is focused specifically on working with manuscripts.
                        The Toronto work supports import of images via IIIF Manifest URLs and treats
                        IIIF annotations on those images as items in an Omeka collection. There is
                        not currently native support for working extensively with manuscript text,
                        outside of annotations on images, and this would need to be added for many
                        use cases. The use of PHP and Javascript as the primary programming
                        languages, and the level of documentation and support available for
                        developers makes it a strong candidate for extension and reuse. It should be
                        noted, though, that Omeka is not intended for long term preservation of
                        data. Omeka is also available as a hosted online platform through a
                        subscription model at <ref target="omeka.net">omeka.net</ref>. Opportunities
                        for project-specific customizations are limited in the hosted version,
                        though, and depend upon the plan chosen.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Getty Scholar’s Workspace</title> is a set of extensions
                        to the Drupal Content Management System <ptr target="#drupal2017"/> which
                        aims to provide a research environment for art historians. It adds tools to
                        Drupal for creating bibliographies, grouping and comparing images, and for
                        creating transcriptions, essays and annotations. It has some support for
                        collaboration, based upon Drupal’s role-based permissions, but no
                        pedagogical workflows. Standards supported include Dublin Core for
                        taxonomies, but IIIF was not supported. Digital publication is explicitly
                        excluded from the scope of the application, although it does support export
                        of data in JSON, XML or CSV, which could then be used to create a static
                        website from the data via the Getty Publication’s static web resource
                        generator. By leveraging the underlying flexibility and configurability of
                        Drupal, together with the Getty tools, it is possible to create a fairly
                        sophisticated digital publication adhering to good data citation practices
                        (such as assigning external Persistent Identifiers to the data items and
                        providing citation guidance to users), but the toolset itself does not
                        provide any guidance on how to do this. In our exploration, for example, we
                        could not easily determine exactly how the collection of tools was
                        configured and used to produce the demonstration site, <title rend="quotes"
                            >Pietro Mellini’s Inventory in Verse, 1681.</title>
                        <ptr target="#gri2016"/> PHP programming skills would be needed to customize
                        the toolset for specific use cases. There is good user documentation
                        provided on the installation and use of the workspace’s features, and a
                        Docker image to get up and running easily, so it does have some potential
                        for reuse. We could envision, for example, building themes which provide
                        preset defaults for data management, organization and eventual publication.
                        There are already other existing plugins that provide IIIF support to
                        Drupal, so these could potentially be added to a Getty workspace
                        installation to round out the image support. The primary advantage over
                        Omeka might be that Drupal, serving such a wide multidisciplinary user base,
                        has a large number of plugins available, ranging from the very general to
                        the very specific, but this could also be a drawback for less technical
                        users because taking advantage of them can require significant programming
                        expertise. Resources such as <title rend="italic">Drupal for
                            Humanists</title>
                        <ptr target="#drupal2017"/> could prove useful here.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">vHMML</title> is a virtual reading room and cataloging
                        environment designed specifically for the Hill Museum and Manuscript
                        Library, with modules for display of reference material, images and other
                        digital resources. It supports a cataloging workflow and metadata standard
                        that is specific to its core use case. It supports IIIF for image viewing
                        and annotation, via the Mirador viewer and the OpenSeaDragon library. The
                        core application itself is written in Java and deployed on Tomcat with a
                        MySQL database, and uses Elastic Search for indexed searching. It uses
                        w3id.org to provide stable links to the resources published on it. It does
                        not include support for collaborative scholarly or pedagogical workflows.
                        The code, while available in an open source GitHub repository, is not
                        currently intended to be collaboratively maintained or developed. It is,
                        however, available for forking and repurposing, and the technologies used
                        are fairly standard. One important thing to evaluate when looking at the
                        code with an eye towards reuse would be the extent to which the
                        vHMML-specific workflows, data formats, and use cases are tightly coupled to
                        the design of the code. If they are baked into the design, it would likely
                        not be worth the effort to try to reuse, but if done generally it might be
                        possible.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Collective Access</title> is a web-based suite of
                        applications that provides a framework for management, description, and
                        discovery of complex physical and digital collections. It is designed as a
                        collection management system with a front end that can be used for public
                        exhibitions. Archives and museums are the intended users of the system,
                        especially ones who need to support both physical and digital collections.
                        Creating and publishing collection catalogs and exhibitions are its core use
                        cases. It is clear that archivists and librarians are the primary intended
                        consumers of the tool and it is not designed for the casual user who does
                        not have an understanding of metadata and cataloguing activities. It does
                        support a wide variety of metadata standards preconfigured in the
                        installation, such as Dublin Core, EAD (Encoding Archival Description), VRA
                        Core (Visual Resources Association metadata standard), and CDWA-Lite
                        (Categories for the Description of Works of Art). The metadata scheme is
                        also easily extendable through the user interface (UI). The system provides
                        control over the exposure of different metadata elements to the end user. A
                        series of controlled vocabularies such as LCSH (Library of Congress Subject
                        Headings) and Getty vocabularies are already integrated into the system. It
                        provides a full tracking system for collections such as insurance valuation,
                        location tracking, and provenance. Extensive logs for changes to each
                        object/collection are also accessible through UI. Collective Access comes
                        with a series of built-in workflows for batch import, export, and editing.
                        There is no support for real-time collaboration or pedagogical workflows in
                        the platform; however, there may be plugins to provide some of this
                        functionality. The platform also provides granular levels of search such as
                        objects, collections, events, and exhibitions. Collective access can use
                        different viewers for access to media. Its default media viewer can allow
                        access to still images, audio, video, and multi-page documents in PDF
                        format. It has a built-in annotation tool for single images and audio/video
                        but not for multipage documents. At the time of our workshop, the
                        development team was in the process of modularizing the viewer and adding
                        support for IIIF image server and multi-page document viewers such as
                        Mirador and Universal Viewer <ptr target="#digirati2017"/>. The code is
                        written in PHP and there is both user and developer documentation available
                        on the project wiki, as well as consulting services offered by the
                        Collective Access development team. The use of PHP as the primary
                        programming language, and the level of documentation and support available
                        for developers make it a strong candidate for extension and reuse.
                        Collective Access is also available as a hosted online platform through a
                        subscription model at <ref target="collectiveaccess.org"
                            >collectiveaccess.org</ref>. Along with Omeka, these are the only
                        options of the tools we looked at which are publicly offered via this model.
                        The heavy focus on the physical collection and cataloguing use case, and the
                        complexity of the interface, led us to the initial conclusion that it was
                        not a likely candidate for reuse for the manuscripts-centered use cases. It
                        can, however, be used by archivists interested in managing their physical
                        and digital collections through a single platform.</p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Mirador</title> is a client-side javascript image viewer
                        designed around and for the IIIF standard. It can run as an embedded library
                        in an HTML page, and is designed to be integrated into larger applications.
                        It was used in a number of the platforms discussed above. There is technical
                        documentation available, but using and deploying it does require minimal
                        competence with Javascript and HTML. It is an obvious candidate for reuse.
                        When combined with an IIIF image server and an annotation server it could
                        provide a complete environment for image display and annotation, but it does
                        not aim to cover any other use cases (e.g. such as transcription or
                        cataloging). <ref target="#table02">Tables 2-3</ref> provide a summary of
                        the comparison of the platforms.</p>
                    <table xml:id="table02">
                        <head>Summary comparison of platforms (part 1)</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Platform/</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="bold">Tool</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Main functionality</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Curation and preservation workflows</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Support external IIIF manifests</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Metadata extensibility</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Collaborative workspace features</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Code base and framework for development</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Scriptorium</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Annotation and transcription of manuscripts</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>No; Idiosyncratic schema</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>JavaScript; Meteor Framework</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Omeka</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Display and publication of digital collections</cell>
                            <cell>Some functionalities</cell>
                            <cell>In development</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>PHP and JavaScript</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Getty Scholar’s Workspace</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Research environment for art historian</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>No (but a Drupal plugin exists)</cell>
                            <cell>Only Dublin Core</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Developed as extensions to Drupal; PHP</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">vHMML</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Virtual reading room and cataloging environment</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>No; Idiosyncratic schema</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>Java</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Collective Access</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Physical and digital collection management</cell>
                            <cell>Some functionalities</cell>
                            <cell>In development</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>PHP</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Mirador</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Client-side image viewer</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>JavaScript</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <table xml:id="table03">
                        <head>Summary comparison of platforms (part 2)</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Platform/</hi><lb/>
                                <hi rend="bold">Tool</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">User Experience for working on manuscripts</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Quality of documentation</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Open source</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Development community</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Extensibility</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Manuscript annotation support</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Scriptorium</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>Poor</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Small team; limited to the project</cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Omeka</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Large active community</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>No</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Getty Scholar’s Workspace</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Limited</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Small team; Not active</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Yes (some features implemented)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">vHMML</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>Poor</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Small team; limited to the project</cell>
                            <cell>Somewhat</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Collective Access</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>Limited</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Active community</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Only for single images</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Mirador</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>NA</cell>
                            <cell>Good</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Active community</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                            <cell>Yes</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>III. Observations and Recommendations for the Field</head>
                <p>The technology and standards needed to support digital manuscript studies and
                    publication are in place. While we may still be lacking some standardization
                    around highly specific metadata, standards such as IIIF for images, TEI (Text
                    Encoding Initiative) for text, Dublin Core for metadata, and the newly approved
                    W3C Web Annotation Data Model <ptr target="#w3c2017"/> cover a large majority of
                    needs. While freely available tools and services for open source development,
                    such as GitHub and various cloud infrastructures, have removed some
                    infrastructure barriers and reduced the overhead required for development and
                    deployment, the depth and diversity of scholarly and pedagogical workflows, the
                    fast pace of technological change, and the shortage of software development
                    expertise are challenges that still need to be overcome. A one-size-fits-all
                    solution for digital manuscript studies remains difficult to envision, but
                    modular infrastructures which allow for tools to be combined in different ways
                    are possible and show a great deal of potential.</p>
                <p> The following are our concluding insights and recommendations for future
                    development efforts.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Insights</head>
                    <p><list type="ordered">
                            <item>There is a diversity of workflows that need to be addressed. <list
                                    type="unordered">
                                    <item>There are different workflows needed for pedagogical,
                                        cataloging, preservation, individual scholarly,
                                        collaborative scholarly, and citizen science (crowdsourcing)
                                        work. Therefore, some tools may use a shared base platform
                                        (e.g., Omeka or Drupal) and add different workflows as
                                        modules or plugins for the base platform. This approach
                                        makes it easier to reuse and repurpose existing
                                        platforms.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>The tool’s code base and level of community involvement is
                                critical for sustainability and expansion. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>The code base significantly impacts future usability of
                                        tool. For example, high quality code base reduces the
                                        overall cost of recruiting new contributors.</item>
                                    <item>An active community of users and developers is critical in
                                        sustaining a tool. It is worth studying the best practices
                                        on this point.</item>
                                    <item>Following development best practices, such as producing
                                        comprehensive unit tests and developer documentation, is
                                        essential to reuse.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>There are no developer-free, end-to-end solutions for scholars and
                                students of manuscripts. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>There are no end-to-end solutions that are
                                        developer-free.</item>
                                    <item>The field still lacks basic infrastructure, guidance and
                                        sustainable solutions for individual scholars and small
                                        institutions to manage and preserve their manuscript images
                                        and data.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>Iteration is inescapable. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>There is no one tool or platform that is going to be the
                                        panacea, so we need to think in terms of iterative
                                        development and collaborative development building upon
                                        existing tools and platforms.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>Tool/platform creation is a collaborative form of intellectual
                                labor. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>We need to bring scholars, curators, and librarians
                                        together with technologists to create new tools and
                                        platforms and work to reconceptualize this collaborative
                                        work as a form of intellectual labor that is recognized by
                                        university administration as such in existing hiring,
                                        promotion, and tenure review processes.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Recommendations</head>
                    <p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>Data curation and tool creation should be treated as separate
                                projects. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>We need to think about and plan for data separately from
                                        its manifestation in a particular tool. For example, high
                                        resolution images can be stored and preserved in an image
                                        repository while tools that aim to facilitate collaborative
                                        work on manuscripts can use IIIF manifestation of those
                                        images without the need to store and preserve original
                                        images.</item>
                                    <item>We need to plan for enabling persistent identification and
                                        citations, in order to have clearly defined connection
                                        points and use APIs that can outlast the tools.</item>
                                    <item>Data must be easy to export and transform.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>We need to create more <quote rend="inline"
                                    source="#x_galison1997">trading zones</quote>
                                <ptr target="#galison1997"/> for technologists, librarians,
                                curators, and scholars of manuscripts. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>We need to establish communities and spaces (i.e., <quote
                                            rend="inline" source="#x">trading zones</quote>)
                                        composed of technologists, librarians, and scholars and
                                        develop <quote rend="inline" source="#x"
                                            >interlanguages</quote> that facilitate collaboration.
                                        In the course of our workshop round tables with users, for
                                        example, it became clear that there are a number of types of
                                        functionality that users want but are unable to find in
                                        existing solutions and have not even been thought about
                                        before. Developers of such platforms will benefit from such
                                        trading zones through learning about the needs of their
                                        intended community of users, and thereby improve the overall
                                        design and functionality of the platform.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>We need to better document the workflows and use cases our tools
                                are meant to address. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>Workflows and ideal use cases need to be identified and
                                        documented for each tool (in the workshop it became clear
                                        that even experts in the field were not always able to
                                        easily ascertain the workflows and use cases that a
                                        particular tool aimed to support). Well-documented workflows
                                        and use cases make extension and repurposing of the tools
                                        easier.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>Avoid starting from scratch. <list type="unordered">
                                    <item>Since there is no platform which satisfies the wide-ranges
                                        of needs and workflows, it might be tempting to think about
                                        building a platform from scratch. We believe it is better to
                                        resist such temptations. There are many platforms (e.g.,
                                        Omeka and Drupal) which can serve as the base infrastructure
                                        for development of tools. Designers and developers can use
                                        those platforms and add modules and plugins to extend their
                                        functionalities to serve particular workflows and use
                                        cases.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>These insights and recommendations emerged from a collective effort of
                        scholars, curators, and technologists to survey the state of digital tools
                        available for manuscript study and curation. Through such <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#x">trading zones</quote> we can come to a better
                        understanding of the different emerging needs of these communities and
                        increase their awareness about the status of digital infrastructure and the
                        existing and emerging technologies. Such attempts can reduce redundancies
                        and increase technological convergence. We hope these observations and
                        recommendations encourage further collaboration between these communities
                        and foster efforts aimed at co-creating shared extensible
                        infrastructure.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix I: Survey Information</head>
                <list type="simple">
                    <head>Survey Questions</head>
                    <item>Q1 - If you currently study manuscripts, do you employ any digital tools
                        or platforms? </item>
                    <item>Q2 - If you currently study manuscripts, but do not employ any digital
                        tools or platforms, why do you not make use of any of the existing tools and
                        platforms?</item>
                    <item>Q3 - If you currently do use platforms or tools when studying manuscripts,
                        which ones do you use?</item>
                    <item>Q4 - Why do you use the platform you mentioned in the question
                        above?</item>
                    <item>Q5 - Which tools or platforms would you point to as the best in the field
                        currently?</item>
                    <item>Q6 - What features and functionality of these tools or platforms are most
                        important to you?</item>
                    <item>Q7 - What features and functionality of these tools and platforms would
                        you like to see improved and how?</item>
                    <item>Q8 - What features or functionality would you like to see in a manuscript
                        workspace that you do not currently see in any of the existing tools
                        platforms?</item>
                    <item>Q9 - What are the approximate sizes of the collections of manuscripts that
                        you typically work with in your capacity as a scholar or curator? <list
                            type="unordered">
                            <item>Less than 100</item>
                            <item>More than 100, but less than 500</item>
                            <item>More than 500, but less than 1000</item>
                            <item>More than 1000, but less than 5000</item>
                            <item>More than 5000</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Q10 - Which of the following options are the primary focus of your
                        digitization effort? <list>
                            <item>Manuscript images</item>
                            <item>Text itself</item>
                            <item>Both</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Q11 - Do you need to support annotation? <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Annotation of images</item>
                            <item>Annotation of text</item>
                            <item>Both</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Q12 - Are you working with multiple manuscripts of the same text?</item>
                    <item>Q13 - Is enabling citation of your manuscript data (text or image)
                        important for you?</item>
                    <item>Q14 - Do you need to restrict access to images or textual content for
                        licensing/copyright reasons?</item>
                    <item>Q15 - Are there particular file formats (for example, TEI XML) that are
                        required for storing the output of your research? Please provide the file
                        formats.</item>
                    <item>Q17 - Do you have technical staff or services at your home institution
                        that could install and run the tools for you, or do you prefer to use an
                        online site that your institution does not have to maintain? <list>
                            <item>I prefer my home institution install and run the tools</item>
                            <item>I prefer to use an online site that my institution does not have
                                to maintain</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Survey Distributed to the Following Scholarly Listservs:</head>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:arabiclitscholars@utlists.utexas.edu"><title
                                rend="italic">ArabicLitScholars</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:adabiyat@lists.uchicago.edu"><title rend="italic"
                                >Adabiyat</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:islamaar@lists.psu.edu"><title rend="italic"
                                >IslamAAR</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:digitalclassicist@jiscmail.ac.uk"><title rend="italic"
                                >Digital Classicist</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:dh@groupes.renater.fr"><title rend="italic">French
                                DH</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:Institute@lists.uvic.ca"><title rend="italic">The
                                Digital Humanities Summer Institute</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:DC-CULTURAL-TG@jiscmail.ac.uk"><title rend="italic"
                                >Dublin Core Metadata Data Initiative - Cultural Heritage Task
                                Group</title></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="mailto:listserv@societyforiranianstudies.org"><title
                                rend="italic">Association for Iranian Studies</title></ref></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix II: Goals for Tool Evaluations</head>
                <p>Our basic goals for the workshop are to evaluate a selection of platforms for use
                    in digital manuscript studies. The use cases are diverse and the platforms we’ve
                    selected to review each have different objectives and core constituencies.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Primary Objectives</head>
                    <p>The primary objective for the technical portion of the workshop was to obtain
                        answers to the following questions for each tool or platform:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>What use cases and workflows is it <emph>intended to</emph>
                            support?</item>
                        <item>What additional use cases and workflows is it <emph>capable of</emph>
                            supporting?</item>
                        <item>Could gaps in functionality be filled by combining it with another
                            tool?</item>
                        <item>Could gaps in functionality be filled by extending it with new
                            development?</item>
                        <item>What skills are necessary to be able to use it effectively?</item>
                        <item>What skills are necessary to be able to extend it with new
                            functionality?</item>
                        <item>How well does it support data management best practices? (Consider
                            features such as persistent identification of resources, versioning,
                            data import/export, data transformations, standard data formats,
                            ontologies, etc.)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Below were some suggested questions for deeper investigation into each of
                        these topics. These were intended to be a jumping off point only.
                        Participants were encouraged to explore other questions and topics as
                        appropriate for their use cases. </p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Use Cases and Workflows</head>
                        <item>Which of these high-level use cases does it support with regard to
                            digital manuscript content: <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. Creation</item>
                                <item>b. Curation</item>
                                <item>c. Publication</item>
                                <item>d. Preservation</item>
                                <item>e. Collaboration</item>
                                <item>f. Pedagogy</item>
                                <item>g. Analysis</item>
                                <item>h. Other</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Which of these content types does it support: <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. Metadata</item>
                                <item>b. Text</item>
                                <item>c. Images</item>
                                <item>d. Annotations</item>
                                <item>e. Other</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head>Data Management</head>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Persistent Identifiers</hi>
                            <list type="ordered">
                                <item>Does it provide stable identifiers to your data
                                    objects?</item>
                                <item>What type? (URLs, DOIs, Handles, ARKs, Database Identifiers, etc.)</item>
                                <item>Are they globally unique or unique only to the instance of the
                                    tool/platform?</item>
                                <item>What means does it provide to make these identifiers
                                    persistent and resolvable outside the context of the
                                    tool/platform?</item>
                                <item>At what level of granularity are they available? (The object,
                                    a fragment of an object, annotations on an object, etc.)</item>
                                <item>Can you supply your own PIDs for your data objects in addition
                                    to or instead of those assigned by the platform?</item>
                                <item>Does it support versioning of identifiers?</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Other Data Management Topics</head>
                        <item>Are there any restrictions on what is considered a data object?</item>
                        <item>Does it offer a means to provide formalized, machine-actionable
                            descriptions of the data objects?</item>
                        <item>Does it support versioning of data?</item>
                        <item>Can you export your data?</item>
                        <item>Does it provide an API for access to its data?</item>
                        <item>What data type formats does it support?</item>
                        <item>Can you add/define your own data types and formats?</item>
                        <item>What support does it provide for publishing your data as linked
                            data?</item>
                        <item>What support does it provide for ingesting or referencing external
                            linked data sources?</item>
                        <item>Can you group your data into collections?</item>
                        <item>Can you have multiple collections of different data types?</item>
                        <item>Can you define relationships between items across collections?</item>
                        <item>What cataloging functionality does it provide?</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Metadata</head>
                        <item>Does it support OAI/PMH? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. For export?</item>
                                <item>b. For ingest/harvesting?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>What metadata vocabularies does it support? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. Can you define or supply your own vocabulary?</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Text</head>
                        <item>What text formats does it support? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. Plain Text, HTML, HOCR, Markdown, XML, PDF, etc.?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Is there an interface to upload textual content? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. From the file system?</item>
                                <item>b. From urls?</item>
                                <item>c. Does it support batch mode?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Does it provide support for linking text to other objects (images,
                            external sites, annotations, etc.)?</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Images</head>
                        <item>What image formats does it support? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. JPG, PNG, TIFF, etc.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Does it support a IIIF API endpoint?</item>
                        <item>Is there an interface to upload images? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. From the file system?</item>
                                <item>b. From urls?</item>
                                <item>c. Does it support batch mode?</item>
                                <item>d. Does it support 3D visualization features?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Does it provide support for linking images to other objects (texts,
                            external sites, annotations, etc.)?</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Annotation</head>
                        <item>Can you create annotations? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. On text?</item>
                                <item>b. On images?</item>
                                <item>c. On pdfs?</item>
                                <item>d. On other?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>How are annotations stored? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. Are they assigned identifiers distinct from the items they
                                    are attached to?</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Collaboration</head>
                        <item>Does it support collaboration on a shared object?</item>
                        <item>Does it support real time collaboration (multiple users working on the
                            same object at the same time)?</item>
                        <item>Does it provide a user model?</item>
                        <item>What authentication options are offered? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. OAuth2 and Social Identity Providers?</item>
                                <item>b. Shibboleth?</item>
                                <item>c. Username/password?</item>
                                <item>d. Other?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Does it support group features?</item>
                        <item>Does it support user roles? <list type="simple">
                                <item>a. At what level of granularity? <list type="unordered">
                                        <item>Individual objects?</item>
                                        <item>Application wide?</item>
                                        <item>Project?</item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Extensibility</head>
                        <item>Does it support plugins for new functionality?</item>
                        <item>Does it provide documentation for how to extend?</item>
                        <item>Does it provide APIs for application integration?</item>
                        <item>What programming language(s) are required to extend it? <list
                                type="simple">
                            <item>a. What skill level is required to extend it?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Does it support custom themes/stylesheets for presentation?</item>
                        <item>Does it support mobile devices?</item>
                        <item>Is there an active developer community?</item>
                        <item>Is the code documented?</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <head>Usability</head>
                        <item>How easy is to use?</item>
                        <item>Is there user help/documentation?</item>
                        <item>Are there tutorials?</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="digirati2017" label="Digirati 2017">Digirati. <title rend="quotes"
                        >UV.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017, <ref
                        target="http://universalviewer.io/">http://universalviewer.io/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drupal2017" label="Drupal 2017">Drupal. <title rend="quotes">Drupal
                        for Humanists.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="http://drupal.forhumanists.org/"
                        >http://drupal.forhumanists.org/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drupalassociation2017" label="Drupal Association 2017">Drupal
                    Association. <title rend="quotes">Drupal.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.drupal.org/">https://www.drupal.org/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galison1997" label="Galison 1997">Galison, Peter. <title rend="italic"
                        >Image and Logic: A Material Culture of Microphysics</title>. Chicago:
                    University of Chicago Press, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gri2016" label="Getty Research Institute 2016">Getty Research
                    Institute, <title rend="quotes">Pietro Mellini’s Inventory in Verse,
                        1681.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="http://www.getty.edu/research/mellini/"
                        >http://www.getty.edu/research/mellini/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IIIF2017" label="IIIF 2017">IIIF, <title rend="quotes">International
                        Image Interoperability Framework.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="http://iiif.io/">http://iiif.io/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meteor2017" label="Meteor 2017">Meteor. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Fastest Way to Build Javascript Apps.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.meteor.com/">https://www.meteor.com/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="uot2017" label="University of Toronto 2017">University of Toronto.
                        <title rend="quotes">Digital Tools for Manuscript Study.</title> Accessed
                    March 29, 2017. <ref target="https://digitaltoolsmss.library.utoronto.ca/"
                        >https://digitaltoolsmss.library.utoronto.ca/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="w3c2017" label="W3C 2017">W3C. <title rend="quotes">Web Annotation
                        Data Model.</title> Accessed March 29, 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model/</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
