<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Simple but Beautiful:
               A Case Study on the ZHI Project of Traditional Craftsmanship</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jing <dhq:family>Chen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>School of Art, Nanjing University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cjchen@nju.edu.cn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jing Chen, PhD, is an associate professor at the School of Art, Nanjing University, a founding member of the Center for Digital Humanities at the Institute for Advanced Studies in the Humanities and Social Sciences, Nanjing University, and a part-time researcher at the Center for Contemporary Chinese Cultural Studies, Shanghai University. From 2012 to 2014, she was a post-doctoral researcher at the Chao Center for Asian Studies at Rice University, USA. Her main research interests are cultural and media studies, digital humanities, digital art and digitization of intangible cultural heritage.
                     </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mengqi <dhq:family>Li</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Shanghai Traditionow Culture Development Corp</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>limengqi_manchi@qq.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mengqi Li is a researcher at Shanghai Traditionow Culture Development Corp. Her research focuses on using digital technologies for the dissemination and transformation of intangible cultural heritage.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Wensi <dhq:family>Lin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Shanghai Museum, China</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>linwensi@shanghai-museum.org</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>I'm an exhibition planner of the Shanghai Museum, China. I also work for the research and education of Chinese intangible cultural heritage at university Nanjing. My research topic focuses on the digital protection and knowledge production of Chinese traditional colors.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Yinzhou <dhq:family>Zhao</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Art Institute of Nanjing University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>1604031883@qq.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Yinzhou Zhao graduated from the Art Institute of Nanjing University and is currently a cultural civil servant.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mengyue <dhq:family>Zhang</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Nanjing University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>1064443545@qq.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mengyue Zhang graduated from Nanjing University and is currently working in the Nanjing University Alumni Association.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Han <dhq:family>Chen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Nanjing Art Institute</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>fotochen@126.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Han Chen graduated from Nanjing Art Institute and is currently a photographer.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Qiang <dhq:family>Hu</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>N/A</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alex@tapbetter.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Qiang Hu is a full-stack development engineer. He is an advertising professional and front-end technology expert. He worked in Renren and Sohu, led the front-end technology development team, and trained a number of technical managers in first-tier Internet companies. He is mainly engaged in project technical design, development, operation and maintenance.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Yongqing <dhq:family>Xie</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Nanjing Art Institute</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>583256317@qq.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Yongqing Xie graduated from Nanjing Art Institute, is a graphic designer and freelancer, and is currently the head of Hangzhou Text Story Cultural Creative Co.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000592</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
      	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
      		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000592/000592.xml">GitHub
      	</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This essay offers a case study of the ZHI project, a digital craftsmanship project
               showcasing the beauty of traditional craftsmanship at three levels: knowing, making, and
               intelligence. The project began with a Designer Residency Program and was developed to
               answer three crucial questions: (1) How could we bridge the gap between enthusiastic
               outsiders and little-known creators of intangible cultural heritage? (2) How could we
               help students understand and participate in craftwork? and (3) How could we facilitate
               sustainable knowledge production about intangible cultural heritage among the audiences,
               students, and craftsmen so everyone benefits and contributes? The ZHI project uses
               minimal computing strategies to encourage craftspeople to pass their skills and
               knowledge onto others, particularly younger generations, through digitization and online
               exhibitions that use minimal computing practices. The project provides user-friendly,
               accessible information to researchers and craftspeople who do not possess expensive
               digital equipment or high-level technical skills. This offers them opportunities to
               virtually present their craft and research, share knowledge, and tell their own stories
               to audiences unfamiliar with craftsmanship. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This essay offers a case study of the ZHI project, a digital craftsmanship project
               showcasing the beauty of traditional craftsmanship at three levels: knowing, making, and
               intelligence.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
         
         <p>In 2003, UNESCO established their Lists of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH), <quote rend="inline">to
            ensure better visibility of the intangible cultural heritage and awareness of its
            significance, and to encourage dialogue which respects cultural diversity</quote> <ptr target="#unesco2011"/>. Subsequently, the Chinese government launched a national campaign to promote the
            recognition, discovery, and conservation of ICH. As a result, 42 types of ICH in China
            have been added to the UNESCO list and China is the country with the highest number of
            ICH elements on the list as of December 2020.<note> See <title rend="italic">
                  <foreign xml:lang="zh">中国入选联合国教科文组织非物质文化遗产名录（名册）项目 - 中国非物质文化遗产网·中国非物质文化遗产数字博物馆</foreign></title>,
               2020年10月10日, available at <ref target="http://www.ihchina.cn/chinadirectory.html">http://www.ihchina.cn/chinadirectory.html</ref>. </note> The
            national and local governments in China consider the conservation and promotion of ICH
            to be crucial to enhancing national identity, amplifying cultural heritage, raising
            consciousness about the need to protect cultural heritage, and promoting Chinese culture
            both domestically and internationally. </p>
         <p>High-performance technology was promoted as an important method for the conservation and
            distribution of ICH. Many IT companies are used to working with museums to digitize ICH.
            While it is important to promote ICH to broad audiences, high-performance technology
            requires technical skills and equipment that bear high costs. Moreover, it is crucial to
            work directly with craftspeople to better understand the goals and outcomes of
            conservation. Our work on ZHI: A Digital Project of Traditional Craftsmanship, developed
            by graduate students at Nanjing University’s School of Arts, offers an alternative that
            incorporates minimal computing technologies and direct collaboration with creators of
            ICH. </p>
         <p>The project began with our Designer Residency Program, developed in 2017 to bring
            together designers, craftspeople, non-governmental organization (NGO) workers, and
            administrators from cultural institutions. As we visited local studios and interviewed
            designers and craftspeople, we sought to understand the obstacles to digitally
            preserving and transmitting knowledge about craftsmanship in Nanjing. What became clear
            is that it was impractical to launch a multi-year training program to share Nanjing’s
            ICH with amateurs or hobbyists. Seeking alternatives, we interviewed designers,
            craftspeople, students, and potential audiences interested in learning more about
            craftsmanship. We further explored digital technologies that would be user-friendly and
            economical for preserving ICH. </p>
         <p>This research led to even more questions: How could we bridge the gap between
            enthusiastic consumers and the little-known creators of ICH? How could we create
            opportunities for students to learn about and contribute to craftwork? How could we
            facilitate a sustainable process of knowledge production about ICH among the audiences,
            students, and craftsmen so everyone benefited and had opportunities to contribute? </p>
         <p>To answer these questions, we developed ZHI, a digital craftsmanship project.<note> In
               Chinese, one pronunciation with different tones can correspond to different words,
               and sometimes one tone can represent many words. <q>Zhī</q> means knowing (知),
            intelligence (<foreign xml:lang="zh">智</foreign> ), and making (<foreign xml:lang="zh">制</foreign>). </note> As indicated in the name, this project
            establishes a model of knowing and making to strengthen knowledge production on
            craftsmanship in the digital era. ZHI is dedicated to showcasing the beauty of
            traditional craftsmanship at three levels — knowing, making, and intelligence — and
            providing sources of imagination and cultural roots for contemporary hobbyists. As a shareable network supported by the community, it aims to provide a user-friendly, knowledge-based, and accessible website for craftspeople who do not possess expensive digital equipment and experienced skills to virtually present their craft or research, share their knowledge, and tell their stories to audiences who may only know a little about the craftsmanship.</p></div>
        <div>
            <head>Making-as-knowing and Technological Needs for ICH</head>
         
         <p>According to UNESCO’s 2003 Convention, ICH connotes the <quote rend="inline">practices, representations,
            expressions, knowledge, and know-how, transmitted from generation to generation within
            communities, created and transformed continuously by them, depending on the environment
            and their interaction with nature and history</quote> <ptr target="#unesco2011" loc="4"/>. Its importance lies in
            the way it <quote rend="inline">adapts permanently to the present and constitutes cultural capital that can
            be a powerful driver for development. Food security, health, education, sustainable use
            of natural resources — intangible cultural heritage is a wealth of knowledge to be used
            in many aspects of life</quote> <ptr target="#unesco2011" loc="4"/>. Rather than emphasizing historical value,
            unique places, or material objects, ICH focuses on the <q>living</q> status of heritage in
            the communities — ensuring it can be known, learned, and transmitted from
            generation-to-generation and thus remain alive — as well as the human spirit that lies in
            communities and provides a sense of identity that promotes broader cultural and social
            effects. Starting from the understanding of ICH as <q>living heritage,</q> we adopted three
            key concepts to develop a sustainable model to help practitioners share the knowledge
            and skills of ICH. From the process of making and producing digital twins of ICH,
            supported technically by the strategies of <q>minimal computing</q> — that is, using
            accessible technologies — we designed a flexible website to showcase the knowledges,
            communities, and aesthetic values of ICH. </p>
         <p>In the case of the ZHI project, digitization of craftsmanship is not simply duplicating
            products, but a process of making <q>digital twins,</q> a term used by Michael Grieves to
            describe <quote rend="inline">a virtual representation of what has been produced</quote> in his project for his
            Product Lifestyle Management Development Consortium. Grieves suggests one could,
            <quote rend="inline">Compare a Digital Twin to its engineering design to better understand what was produced
               versus what was designed, tightening the loop between design and execution</quote> <ptr target="#grieves2015"/>. 
            By adopting and applying the term <q>digital twins</q> to cultural heritage,
            Pierre-André Jouan and Pierre Hallot indicate that implementing digital twins for the
            management and preservation of cultural heritage assets would assist with data
            collection and management for cultural heritage, which will in turn provide initial and
            long-term support for the conservation of cultural heritage. This all relies on the
            value attributed to the form of cultural heritage, while evaluation of that value itself
            depends on data preservation <ptr target="#jouan2019"/>. In this sense, the ZHI project
            considers digitization, data collection, and analysis as a process of making digital
            twins of craftsmanship. This process requires knowledge about material, the skill of
            making, the emotion and time required, and the use of proper equipment. The outcomes —
            physical product and digital content — are interdependent and complement each other.
            Under the principle of making-as-knowing, digitization, data collection, and analysis
            provide an epistemological approach to the knowledge of craftsmanship and its virtual
            representations. </p>
         <p>Emphasizing the principle of living heritage, we take the sustainable production of
            knowledge as the core of the ZHI project to encourage craftspeople to pass their skills
            and knowledge onto others, particularly younger generations, through digitization and
            online exhibition. During this process, we discovered that while craftspeople know how
            to make things by drawing on their skills, it is difficult for them to convert the
            knowledge that they learned from their practical experiences into what Ulrich Lehmann
            calls a systematic <q>knowledge shape.</q> Lehman notes this difficulty:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">If making is knowing, it doesn’t follow that all makers <q>know</q> their crafts. They might
            know how to produce an effective, economical, or detailed result. But this does not mean
            that they can change completely, reverse, or deconstruct their techne in such a way as
            to challenge established thinking about this craft.</quote> <ptr target="#lehmann2012" loc="151"/></cit>
         <p>Lehmann reminds us that Plato and Aristotle’s metaphorical expression of the distinction
            between <q>knowledge</q> and <q>techne</q> universalized and empowered making processes, such as
            weaving and clothes-making. These are epistemological processes of knowledge production
            that go <quote rend="inline">beyond material creation, and thus constitute[s] conceptual knowledge</quote> <ptr target="#lehmann2012" loc="151"/>. 
            Following Lehmann, epistemology is not just about the conditions of
            knowledge origins, its structures, and limits, but more importantly the creation,
            distribution, and consumption processes. Lehmann’s study of pleated fabrics in the
            context of fashion illustrates his argument, but his analysis is largely analog,
            not digital. Yet, he raises crucial questions that are pertinent to our digital work: </p>
         <p><quote rend="block">If making is knowing, can its conditional base be separated and evaluated
            independently?.... Are craft techniques, the communal structures of craftspeople, the
            sociability of crafting, and the consumption of crafted forms to be seen as conditional
            for the generation of knowing? <ptr target="#lehmann2012" loc="151–160"/> </quote></p>
         <p>Extending these questions to the digital realm, is digital technology conditional for
            the making-knowing process of craftsmanship now? Does the digital making process also
            produce knowing/knowledge for the new generation? </p>
         <p>Yes, we think so. Our work is inspired by projects like the Making and Knowing Project,
            a <quote rend="inline">research and pedagogical initiative in the Center for Science and Society at Columbia
            University that explores the intersections between artistic making and scientific
            knowing,</quote> where craftspeople represent their skills and knowledge through their own
            voices and stories <ptr target="#making2021"/>. While our project emphasizes the
            role of digital technology in the conservation of cultural heritage, the Making and
            Knowing Project provides a research-driven model of pedagogy by creating an open-access
            digital critical edition of an anonymous French manuscript through text- and
            object-based research and hands-on reconstruction. Students not only reconstruct 16th-
            and 17th-century culinary recipes but also collect data and record the acquisition
            process through field notes; this illuminates the making-as-knowing process as students
            undertake working processes similar to those of artists or craftspeople. What they have
            explored and examined, as presented on the project’s website, fills the missing spots in
            the historical documents: students have decoded and brought tacit components of
            knowledge back to the surface from the deeply encoded texts in the 16th and 17th
            centuries through their digital representations and the work of remediation. The
            students’ digital engagements transform tacit knowledge of the early modern period into
            comprehensible common knowledge, bringing insights from the early modern period to
            contemporary audiences. </p>
         <p>Inspired by the <q>making as knowing</q> principle and the Making and Knowing Project, the
            ZHI project invited the craftspeople to work with the undergraduate and graduate
            students. During the collaboration process, craftspeople learned to use language that
            young people understand to explain the tacit knowledge behind the texts and objects.
            Students also needed to learn how to use texts, images, and videos — the digital content
            that represents not only the material craft product but also the knowledge and emotions
            of craftspeople — to demonstrate the value of crafts to users in virtual environments.
            This is a making process of both material media and translations of knowledge across
            different languages systems.</p>
         <p>Strategies of minimal computing undergird this work on the ZHI project because it fits
            our needs and provides a framework for theorizing our practices. In <title rend="quotes">The User, the
            Learner and the Machines We Make,</title> Alex Gil asks the question, <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote> to
            open a discussion of necessity-based technical practices, articulating a concern about
            <quote rend="inline">how to produce, disseminate, and preserve digital scholarship ourselves, without the
            help we can’t get, even as we fight to build the infrastructures we need at the
            intersection of and beyond our libraries and schools</quote> <ptr target="#gil2015"/>. We fully agree with
            Gil’s argument that the orientations of digital knowledge production should be towards
            the <quote rend="inline">ease of use, ease of creation</quote> <ptr target="#gil2015"/>. Because ZHI is a student-based research
            project with little grant funding, ensuring the sustainability and affordability of both
            labor and technology was the first, perhaps most important, concern for the project.</p>
         <p>In contrast, the digital heritage community in China trends towards fetishizing
            technology. The more <q>advanced</q> and expensive digital technologies or devices are, the
            more popular they are. Recently, virtual reality and augmented reality (VR/AR) have
            become popular in the national digital heritage community. However, not all types of
            cultural heritage or ICH are suitable for VR/AR, even though VR/AR have been strongly
            recommended and supported by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism. Are they necessary for
            the ZHI project? No. The required terminal display equipment and the cost of modeling 3D
            content, as well as easily outdated operating environments, are unaffordable luxuries
            for individual craftspeople and students. Even with the possibility of grant funding,
            the question remains about who could continue maintaining content and customized
            technologies for VR/AR when the funding runs out. Rather than following the VR/AR trend,
            we considered the purpose of using technologies, focusing on the question of <quote rend="inline">what we
            need.</quote> We further considered which technologies would allow ZHI project participants to
            engage in the hands-on making-as-knowing process with digital technologies, rather than
            outsourcing the making process and turning our technologies into a figurative “black
            box” for craftspeople and students. With the strategic framework of minimal computing,
            the ZHI project maximizes the use of only the most necessary technologies and the most
            effective ways to expose the most important, but often neglected, aspects of ICH: the
            beauty of handcrafts and the wisdom of craftspeople. </p></div>
        <div>
            <head>Simple but Beautiful as a Core Approach</head>
         
         <p>Inspired by the concepts listed above, the ZHI team examined three types of traditional
            craftsmanship in Nanjing: Yunjin brocade, gold foil forging, and velvet flower making.
            In addition to originating in Nanjing, all three are closely related to the silk
            industry. Due to existing market needs, especially for gold foil, craftspeople are still
            living within self-identified communities. To preserve ICH, craftspeople need to
            collaborate with researchers to digitally conserve and promote the crafts. The ZHI
            project helps facilitate such collaborations. </p>
         <p>Our team consists of graduate and undergraduate students from different disciplines and
            our approach combines the study of documents and images with fieldwork and collaboration
            with craftspeople. The first stage of the project focused on identifying challenges to
            the preservation of intangible cultural heritage through fieldwork. Through our
            international Designers-in-Residency program, we worked closely with designers,
            craftspeople, NGO workers, and administrators of cultural institutions. We visited local
            studios and interviewed designers and craftspeople, discussing the obstacles of digital
            preservation for Nanjing’s ICH. </p>
         <p>Through our visits and interviews, we identified two challenges. First, craftspeople do
            not have a systematic digital record of their products, skills, tools, and stories,
            since they are not part of the museum system. As a result, the value of their work has
            not been recognized by cultural heritage authorities. Some organizations, such as
            television stations, interview craftspeople but not all of these organizations give
            copies of images, audio, videos, and texts back to the craftspeople. Additionally,
            craftspeople do not have their own physical or virtual archives to preserve their work,
            documents, and ephemera. </p>
         <p>Second, it is almost impossible to help designers from different cultural contexts
            understand an artifact with a 2000-year-old history of complicated techniques, complex
            meanings behind colors and patterns, or that these groups of people spend their whole lives
            weaving a textile or making a fan. They can respect it but not understand it. This
            happens with students too, even when they share the same cultural contexts as these
            craftspeople. Students love these beautiful artifacts and enthusiastically want to know
            more about them, but they do not know how to acquire that knowledge. Not all students
            are from the local area, so some are unfamiliar with the culture. But, more importantly,
            as a younger generation, they do not have first-hand knowledge and experience of
            traditional craftsmanship — just surface knowledge from books, museums, tourist stores,
            and TV shows, which are carefully illustrated, elucidated, encoded, and programmed by
            authoritative researchers, professionals, and product designers. Students seldom have a
            chance to have hands-on experiences with the making process that is needed to acquire
            the deep, tacit knowledge of craftsmanship and craftspeople themselves.</p>
         <p>Based on the insights from the first stage of our project, in the second stage we chose
            to establish a digital website to virtually represent craftsmanship to general audiences
            and create an archive for craftspeople to digitally preserve their works, processes, and
            stories. We also adopted a research-driven pedagogical model; the process of developing
            the website engaged students in making-as-knowing, as they worked with the craftspeople
            to select, digitize, design, and interpret content, with the help of collaborators, such
            as researchers, photographers, and programmers. </p>
         <p>The ZHI project carefully chose four ways to collect data: (1) taking photos, (2) making
            short video clips, (3) searching for free copyright images, and (4) conducting oral
            history interviews (see Figure 1). Most of the filming is done on students’ phones, and
            they can edit them on their laptops with video editing software. We ask them to strictly
            follow our protocols of data collection, which have been designed and customized by us,
            so the filming and editing work is also part of the scientific investigation process and
            includes consent of the craftspeople (see Figures 2 and 3). For example, students have
            to clearly understand the name and purpose of every step in the development of a craft,
            as well as additional considerations, such as why we should take a photo of silk yarn
            from a particular perspective — because the reflection of silk yarn in a different light
            will affect color representation. Students also have to understand why particular
            patterns have to be arranged next to another one — because royal rules in ancient China
            dictated the whole pattern for clothes. All of this detailed information about ICH has
            to be included alongside the photos, videos, and interactive games they create.</p>
           
           
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the interview page, <title rend="quotes">记忆之场: 云锦.</title><title
                 rend="italic"> ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>, <ref
                    target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/yjheritage/"
                    >https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/yjheritage/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of a website page</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of <title rend="quotes">The tricks of the Yunjin Brocade</title> page,
                 <title rend="quotes">手口相授: 云锦.</title> <title rend="italic">ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>, <ref
                    target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/yjkoujue/"
                    >https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/yjkoujue/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of a webpage</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the homepage’s silkflower video banner,
                 featuring the theme <title rend="quotes">Teach by oral instructions and hands-on examples,</title> <title
                    rend="italic">ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台,</title> <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/"
                       >https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of a banner on a video</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <p>Since the content is lightweight, we designed an HTML5/PHP-based, highly flexible
              website for images, videos, texts, and interactive games with a freelance developer.<note>
                 <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="zh">ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</foreign></title>, October 10, 2020,
                 <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/</ref>. </note> All of the modules are image-based and
              can be edited as needed (see Figures 4 and 5). For example, we designed an interactive
              coloring game of Yunjin brocade to illustrate the rules and principles of </p>
           <p>color selection and matching in brocade making. All elements of the game are image-based
              and can be replaced and changed accordingly so the game can be extended to different
              patterns with different color palettes. For now, we use a line drawing named <title
                 rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="zh">翠蓝地加金缠枝莲花牡丹妆花</foreign> </title>from the book <title rend="italic">Yunjin Patterns
                 </title>(1959), drawn by Chen Zhifo, a very famous artist and educator of the last century,
              and a color palette digitized by us from the physical color card of a craftsman, Wang
              Jisheng, who has been working on silk dyes for decades. Users can easily interact with
              the pattern to make their own design and then download the image as a calendar page to
              their computer (see Figures 6, 7, and 8).</p>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the content management system for
                 Coloring Yunjin Brocade: The Color Schemes of Yunjin; <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>, <ref target="artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/manage">artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/manage</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
              <figDesc>Screenshot of a content management system backend</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the content management system for
                 Coloring Yunjin Brocade: Design Rules about Yunjin Color; <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>, <ref target="artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/manage">artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/manage</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image5.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of a content management system backend</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the game page for Coloring Yunjin Brocade, where users choose
                 one color palette for each flower, <title rend="quotes">云锦配色小游戏.</title> <title rend="italic">ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台,</title>
                 <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image6.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of the coloring yunjin brocade game</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of game page for Coloring Yunjin Brocade,
                 where users choose color palettes for flowers, <title rend="quotes">云锦配色小游戏.</title> <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台,</title> <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image7.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of coloring yunjin brocade game</figDesc>
           </figure>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of Coloring Yunjin Brocade, where users can
                 download their work as a calendar page, <title rend="quotes">小游戏.</title> <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台,</title> <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/game/brocade/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image8.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of page where users can download the coloring yunjin brocade game</figDesc>
           </figure>
           

        
         <p>Simple does not mean inelegant. On the contrary, we want to make the website simple but
            beautiful. By studying the materials, tools, making process, and products, and talking with
            craftspeople, we developed our <q>3S principle</q> as we found that the <emph
               >scales</emph>, <emph>scene</emph>, and <emph>scenario</emph> are
            very important for virtual representation. This principle begins with the idea that
            beauty is based on understanding, not intuition alone. For example, to present a
            pattern, an image should present a minimal unit of pattern with an explanation of the
            meaning of each element, rather than showing a photo with just a title. In this sense,
               <emph>scale</emph> is crucial for understanding (see Figure 9). Second,
            beauty emerges in context. Craftsmanship is rooted in history, so we have to go back to
            the <emph>scene</emph> of history to understand it. While craftsmanship may
            have seemed to have disappeared from daily life, we can trace it in some <emph>scenes</emph> of contemporary culture, such as paintings or TV soap
            dramas (see Figure 10). Finally, beauty is constructed by narratives. Beauty is complex
            but we can select specific <emph>scenarios</emph> and the most tangible and
            touching moments for storytelling (see Figure 11).</p>
           
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of a minimal unit of a wave pattern with the
                 meaning explained in Yunjin Brocade; <title rend="quotes">帝王之气: 云锦.</title> <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台,</title> <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/animaltism/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/brocade/animaltism/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image9.png"/>
              <figDesc>Screenshot of a webpage with the coloring yunjin brocade game</figDesc>
           </figure>
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot showing use of the silk flower as a
                 headdress in history and contemporary usage, <title rend="quotes">日常之光: 绒花.</title> <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>,
                 <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/velvet-flowers/rhusage/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/velvet-flowers/rhusage/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image10.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of page where floral headdresses are shown</figDesc>
           </figure>
           <figure>
              <head>Screenshot of the gold foil video banner featuring the
                 theme, <q>As then as a cicada’s wings,</q> <title rend="quotes">薄如蝉翼: 金箔</title>. <title rend="italic"
                    >ZHI艺：非物质文化遗产虚拟展示平台</title>,
                 <ref target="https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/gold-foil/craftsmanship/">https://artlab.nju.edu.cn/heritage/gold-foil/craftsmanship/</ref>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/images/image11.png"/>
              <figDesc>screenshot of a webpage banner</figDesc>
           </figure>
        </div>
         <div>
            <head>Insights from the ZHI Project</head>
       
         <p>Since the launch of the ZHI website, we have received compliments and feedback from
            craftspeople and researchers alike. Reflecting on our process, we can summarize the
            lessons we learned. First, developing a sharable knowledge network is essential. We are
            fortunate to have many collaborators working with us on the ZHI project, including
            craftspeople, dyeing experts, scholars, designers, and museum curators. They examine our
            workflow, protocol, and principles, and give students seminars and workshops on dyeing
            and color analysis. The students work very closely with craftspeople to record and
            annotate all the photos of procedure and craft works. During this process, tacit
            knowledge is circulated among this collaborative community and students’ experiences
            merge into knowledge production and become a new branch of the digital twin of
            craftsmanship. Consequently, three students from the team decided to work in cultural
            heritage fields after they graduated — another outcome of this project.</p>
         <p>Next, based on the principle of mutually beneficial sharing, all photos, video, and oral
            history texts taken by us from the local studios and craftspeople are given back to them
            as documents. Meanwhile, all materials are authorized by craftspeople and local museums
            and presented on our website as <emph>their</emph> own archives, so it is not
            necessary for them to establish another one. Our team routinely visits their studios to
            help them digitize and record their newly made craft works. </p>
         <p>Further, establishing data collection specifications from the beginning and following
            them throughout the research and technical processes is crucial to sustainability and
            scalability. Minimal computing shaped our decision to set a variety of rules before the
            <q>actual work</q> began and to undertake both data collection and our technical work
            carefully. For example, the students record all of the scientific data as they learn
            about dyeing and, in turn, all images of craftsmanship on the website are also
            color-managed so that accurate and effective color analysis can be performed.</p>
         <p>Our hope is that the ZHI project offers a model for others working to present ICH
            digitally in an economic and aesthetic way. While ZHI tries to decode the knowledge of
            craftsmanship and present the beauty of craftsmanship with minimal computing, several
            concerns arose with the launch of the website, chiefly sustainability and permanence.
            The construction of the website was largely supported by Nanjing University, Nanjing Art
            Foundation, and established partnerships with craftspeople, but the operation and
            maintenance of the website requires continued investment in human and financial
            resources. At the same time, we have started to promote the ZHI model to the community
            of elders as well as to middle school students. Through these new developments, we aim
            to develop a new operational model to promote ICH in the broader community.</p></div>
         
         
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>This essay is supported by the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities of Nanjing University (Grant No. 011514370105) and the National Social Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 21BA026).</p>
         </div>
     
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2015" label="Gil 2015"> Gil, Alex. <title rend="quotes">The User, the Learner, and the Machines We Make.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Minimal Computing: A Working Group of GO::DH, </title>May 21, 2015.
               <ref target="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/">https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grieves2015" label="Grieves 2015"> Grieves, Michael. <title rend="quotes">Digital Twin: Manufacturing Excellence through Virtual
               Factory Replication.</title> White paper<title rend="italic">, </title>Florida Institute of
               Technology, 2015, 1-7.
               <ref target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275211047_Digital_Twin_Manufacturing_Excellence_through_Virtual_Factory_Replication">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275211047_Digital_Twin_Manufacturing_Excellence_through_Virtual_Factory_Replication</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jouan2019" label="Jouan and Hallot 2019"> Jouan, Pierre, and Pierre Hallot. <title rend="quotes">Digital Twin: A HBIM-Based
               Methodology to Support Preventive Conservation of Historic Assets Through Heritage
               Significance Awareness.</title> <title rend="italic">The International Archives of the
                  Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences</title>, 609–615.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5194/isprs-archives-xlii-2-w15-609-2019">https://doi.org/10.5194/isprs-archives-xlii-2-w15-609-2019</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lehmann2012" label="Lehmann 2012"> Lehmann, Ulrich. <title rend="quotes">Making as Knowing: Epistemology and Technique in
               Craft.</title><title rend="italic"> The Journal of Modern Craft</title> vol. 5.2 (2012): 149–164.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2752/174967812x13346796877950">https://doi.org/10.2752/174967812x13346796877950</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="making2021" label="The Making and Knowing Project 2021">  <title rend="quotes">About.</title> <title rend="italic">The Making and Knowing
               Projec</title>t. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.makingandknowing.org/about-the-project/"
                  >https://www.makingandknowing.org/about-the-project/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unesco2011" label="UNESCO 2011"> UNESCO. <title rend="italic">Convention for the Safeguarding of the
               Intangible Culture Heritage, </title>2011. <ref target="https://ich.unesco.org/doc/src/15164-EN.pdf">https://ich.unesco.org/doc/src/15164-EN.pdf</ref>.
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
