<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Tracking the telepathic sublime as a phenomenon
                    in a digital humanities archive<!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Isabel <dhq:family>Pedersen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Ontario Institute of Technology</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>isabel.pedersen@uoit.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Isabel Pedersen, PhD, Associate Professor, Faculty of Social Science and
                            Humanities, University of Ontario Institute of Technology</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Quinn <dhq:family>DuPont</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Washington</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>qdupont@uw.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Quinn DuPont, PhD, Center For Digital Cultures, Fellow, Leuphana
                            University</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000344<!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --></idno>
                <idno type="volume">011<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">4<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date when="2017-12-22">22 December 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital humanities archiving</item>
                        <item>archival practice</item>
                        <item>wearable technology</item>
                        <item>rhetoric</item>
                        <item>technoculture</item>
                        <item>digital futures</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-11-20">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This paper discusses a digital humanities collection called <title rend="quotes">Contemporary Telepathics</title> housed within a larger archive, <title rend="italic">The Fabric of Digital Life</title>. We argue that through a
                    variety of multimedia representations, the rhetoric of contemporary telepathic
                    devices invokes sublime predictive visions that become instantiated in popular
                    media, news organizations, and disclosures of technology advancement. We discuss
                    the theoretical grounds for a collection of technological forecasts, at a time
                    when they are largely considered ephemera. We also discuss how tracking the
                        <term>telepathic sublime</term> as a dynamically evolving popular
                    communication phenomenon requires a unique, humanities-based metadata scheme and
                    archival practice.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Authors discuss the theoretical grounds for a collection of technological
                    forecasts.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>This paper explores a phenomenon that we term the <term>telepathic sublime</term> and
                it proposes a way to classify and display it through an archived digital collection.
                As digital participants, people are assailed with predictions of how we will
                    <emph>work</emph>, <emph>live</emph> or <emph>be</emph> in the future. For
                instance, self-driving cars are proposed as technical feats, but the excitement lies
                in neo-futurist speculations that everyday lives will transform due to their use. In
                this vein, we are concerned with how the rhetoric surrounding contemporary
                telepathic devices evinces predictive visions that filter into popular media, news
                organizations, popular film, and public opinion through a variety of multimedia
                representations. We emphasize that it is characterized by descriptions that point to
                the sublime. We argue that tracking the <term>telepathic sublime</term> as a
                dynamically evolving rhetorical phenomenon requires a unique, humanities-based
                metadata scheme and archival practice. We use the term <soCalled>tracking</soCalled>
                to highlight the ways in which the archive follows discourse through the lifecycle
                of invention. In characterizing and tracking the telepathic sublime, we argue that
                technologic advancement ought not to be separated from the euphoria associated with
                it. The contribution we make in this article and the associated archive is to
                explore the notion of telepathic sublime: name it as a concept, digitally collect,
                co-locate and track it, display it aesthetically, and reveal how it influences
                scientific advancements and attitudes over time.</p>
            <p>Surrogates of the telepathic sublime are collected, co-located, and archived for
                study within the <title rend="quotes">Contemporary Telepathics</title> (1999 to
                2016) collection,<note> The collection is available at the following URL: <ref target="http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/facet/collection_facet/id/7/view/images/key/e7ea7a9363bf62768d1a37a4a0c78efa">http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/facet/collection_facet/id/7/view/images/key/e7ea7a9363bf62768d1a37a4a0c78efa</ref>.</note>
                a set of contemporary digital artifacts housed within a larger digital humanities
                archive called the <title rend="italic">Fabric of Digital Life</title> at <ref target="http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com">www.fabricofdigitallife.com</ref>
                (referred to as <title rend="italic">Fabric</title>). <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> tracks the emergence of present day personal digital
                technologies, inventions, and predictions (or <soCalled>forecasts</soCalled>) of
                futuristic innovations, most of which are popularized visions of the future.<note>
                    Where available, references to rhetorical depictions of telepathic devices will
                    include URLs to the <title rend="italic">Fabric of Digital Life</title> archive,
                    rather than the original artifact.</note> It focuses on platforms of
                human-computer interaction, mobile, wearable, and implanted technology as they
                undergo the processes of emergence in society.</p>
            <p>We define <term>telepathy</term> (from <soCalled>telepathics</soCalled>) as direct
                communication of thoughts from one person’s mind to another person’s mind without
                using words, signals, gestures, or other traditional forms of communication. We use
                the Contemporary Telepathics collection to cluster related digital technologies that
                    <emph>appear</emph> to work telepathically. <term>Digital telepathy</term> is
                defined as direct communication of thoughts from one person’s mind to a computer (or
                computer-like device) or another person through a digital medium rather than
                traditional (linguistic) media. A related concept is <term>digital
                    telekinesis,</term> defined as movement of digital or material objects by the
                mind, and augmented by a computing device. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Archiving the telepathic sublime</head>
                <p>In 2000, researchers at Duke University affixed monkeys with experimental head
                    caps to measure the brain’s <soCalled>raw electrical activity</soCalled> to see
                    if <soCalled>action potential</soCalled> could be sent along a wire to a nearby
                    box <ptr target="#nicolelis2008"/>. Called a <soCalled>Harvey box</soCalled>
                    after its inventor Harvey Wiggins, the container amplified signals to
                    distinguish between the monkey’s myriad thoughts. More than just a mind reading
                    device, researchers hoped to use the signals to remotely control a robotic arm
                    six hundred miles away. The inventors recount their own amazement with the
                    experiment: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nicolelis2008">We will always remember our sense of awe as we
                            eavesdropped on the processes by which the primate brain generates a
                            thought</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nicolelis2008"/>
                    </cit>. They hoped to create a device for telekinesis.</p>
                <p>The article discussing the experiment in telekinesis appeared in a 2008 <title rend="italic">Scientific American Reports</title> magazine under the cover
                    headline <title rend="quotes">Your Future with Robots,</title> which also
                    included articles by futurists like Bill Gates, Hans Moravec and Ray Kurzweil.
                    The discussion of the experiment within a broader thematic of the technological
                    future fulfilled two purposes. First, it recounted a feat of technology in the
                    creation of a brain-machine interface to serve as a historical record of the
                    advancement. Second, it also expressed the speculative potential for the future
                    of the technology as a forecast meant to garner excitement in its readership.
                    This latter point, about the speculative potential and predictions of telepathic
                    technologies, has a surprisingly long history. For example, Giambattista della
                    Porta (1535-1615) claimed to harness subtle forms of magnetism through various
                    contraptions to <q>express all the sentiments of your mind</q> to a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#devries2012">friend who is distant</quote>
                        <ptr target="#devries2012" loc="103"/>
                    </cit>. Where della Porta drew on the field of cryptography for his
                    technological explanations, William Benjamin Carpenter (1813-1885) later argued
                    that a <soCalled>nerve-force</soCalled> could extend <q>from a distance, so as
                        to bring the Brain of one person into direct dynamical communication with
                        that of another,</q> drawing on the new technology of telegraphy <ptr target="#puglionesi2017"/>. Today, this kind of technological solutioneering
                    is likely to arise in popular news broadcasts, research articles, start-up
                    company concept videos, films, social media exchange, and military documents.
                    Indeed, Dan Kaplan argues in a recent <title rend="italic">Techcrunch</title>
                    article called <title rend="quotes">Digital Telepathy Is The Future Of The Human
                        Species</title> that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kaplan2014">the prospect of digital telepathy will eventually stop
                            being a prospect we can only attempt to imagine and start being a
                            reality that some of us live</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kaplan2014"/>
                    </cit>. Fascination with the invention of digital telepathy and similar
                    technology continues with the same enthusiasm and grandeur as it did in the
                    past.</p>
                <p>The Contemporary Telepathics collection we discuss here deliberately archives
                    this aspect of prediction, forecast, and possibility by foregrounding
                    representations that celebrate <emph>imagination</emph> as means and motivator
                    for innovation, through texts that are usually considered ephemera. By using the
                    word <term>telepathics</term>, rather than <term>telepathy</term>, we draw on
                    the polyvalent meanings bound up in the word. <term>Telepathic</term> means
                    relating to the characteristic of telepathy (e.g., mind-reading technology), but
                    it also means a person who has the ability to read minds (e.g., she is a
                        <term>telepathic</term>). As discussed below, the <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive is devoted to personal technology, so,
                    appropriately, the word <term>telepathic</term> implies identity or selfhood
                    within the larger ontological space of the archive’s themes.</p>
                <p>The metaphor behind the archive’s name, Fabric of Digital Life, references a
                    famous prediction made in 1991 by Mark Weiser, Chief Scientist at Xerox PARC: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#weiser1991">The most profound technologies are those that
                            disappear. They weave themselves into the <emph>fabric of everyday
                                life</emph> until they are indistinguishable from it</quote>
                        <ptr target="#weiser1991"/>
                    </cit> [emphasis added]. As a slogan, the <q>fabric of everyday life</q> offers a way to reflect
                    on Weiser’s bold claim. Weiser’s dream of technological disappearance is itself
                    indebted to previous socio-technical scholars: he cites Martin Heidegger and
                    Hans Georg Gadamer directly. However, the design of <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> is also inspired by the writings of media, rhetoric, and
                    communications scholars Marshall McLuhan, Jean Baudrillard, Walter Benjamin, and
                    Kenneth Burke, which underpin our analysis of the telepathic sublime. The <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive reflects the writings of these scholars
                    to frame and contemplate how media shape attitudes, innovations, technologies,
                    and culture.</p>
                <p>The <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive sits in relation to other similar
                    examples of experimental technology innovation archives. For example, <hi rend="italic">Engineering at Home</hi> (<ref target="http://engineeringathome.org/">http://engineeringathome.org/</ref>)
                    is an archived collection of hacked, reworked, and rewired
                        <soCalled>rehabilitation engineering</soCalled> technology. The manifesto at
                        <title rend="italic">Engineering at Home</title> states, <q>We want to
                        recover a nuanced understanding of engineering’s history of invention that
                        includes craft, assembly, and appropriation–right alongside advances in
                        material sciences and innovative technique.</q>
                    <title rend="italic">Fabric </title>also seeks to reveal advancements and
                    technological appropriations. It archives the cultural valorization of so-called
                    high tech innovation in order to contextualize it as a humanities phenomenon.
                        <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> authorizes this approach in order to
                    disclose dominant industry values and the popular journalism that circulates
                    around innovation — which also oftentimes informs and misinforms — thereby driving
                    it forward. </p>
                <p>The <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive, and the Contemporary Telepathics
                    collection in particular, have been designed in dialogue with current digital
                    humanities work on digital futures studies, and those that reflect on what
                        <soCalled>the digital</soCalled> has come to signify. Mauro Carassai and
                    Elisabet Takehana, in introducing a <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> special issue devoted to the <title rend="quotes">Futures
                        of Digital Studies,</title> foreground the notion of <emph>the
                        digital</emph> as a <soCalled>digital condition</soCalled>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#carassai2011">As a condition, rather than as a technological
                            prosthesis, the digital seems to function more and more as a true
                            reality principle…. In these essays we see, more generally, an explicit
                            awareness that life, subjects, culture, art, and technological
                            production might mirror their digital technologies.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carassai2011"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Or, consider Jentry Sayer’s more recent analysis, in which he points out that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sayers2016">that a majority of the 2012 [Digital Humanities]
                            Debates volume is anchored in discussions about the future</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sayers2016"/>
                    </cit>. Accepting Carassai, Takehana, and Sayer’s propositions concerning the
                    digital and its futures, we again point to Kaplan’s speculations concerning
                    digital telepathy. Echoing a certain strain of Digital Humanities analysis,
                    Kaplan argues that digital telepathy will stop being the stuff of imagination
                    and will <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kaplan2014">start being a reality that some of us live</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kaplan2014"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>We see one function of our archived collections as a counterpart or complement to
                    the argument that the digital condition ought to be viewed as a lived reality.
                    For example, Brian Greenspan argues that locative media, and their implied
                    futures, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#greenspan2011">operationalize the spatial tension between
                            conventionally sedentary modes of literary engagement and new modalities
                            of mobility, a tension that is constitutive of our present
                            mediality</quote>
                        <ptr target="#greenspan2011"/>
                    </cit>. He concludes that locative narratives will encourage <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#greenspan2011">more embodied, dynamic, collective and multiply
                            contextualized applications</quote>
                        <ptr target="#greenspan2011"/>
                    </cit>. Similarly, critical interrogations of Digital Humanities that highlight
                    race, sex, globalization, and other embodied or lived experiences help recognize
                    the lived reality of the digital <ptr target="#liu2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#wernimont2013"/>. For our purposes, the archived collections
                    contained within <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> offer a means to chart how
                    future imaginings unfold, overlap, conceal, inform, and celebrate the digital,
                    contributing to the cultural horizon of digital futures. <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> offers collections as tools for co-locating, displaying, and
                    indexing cultural representations in novel ways to reflect this kind of
                    scholarship. In short, <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> contributes to the
                    tracking of such a shift and its unfolding.</p>
                <p>In designing the archive we also considered the ways that networked technologies
                    enable new discourses. For example, John Unsworth lists a series of
                        <soCalled>scholarly primitives,</soCalled> including what he calls
                        <soCalled>networked digital</soCalled> systems of scholarship <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/>. Unsworth argues that a discoverable, annotated,
                    and curated archive drawn from a selection of representative artifacts (across
                    myriad discourses) is a basis for the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth2000">tool-building enterprise in humanities
                            computing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/>
                    </cit>. Similarly, the
                    <title rend="italic">Fabric </title>archive demonstrates ways
                    that technology can form new critical discourses, as a <soCalled>networked
                        model</soCalled> of scholarship that expands, contests, and enables new
                    kinds of readers, collaborators, and participants <ptr target="#dupont2016"/>. </p>
                <p>Finally, the goals for <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> are influenced by
                    Johanna Drucker’s <title rend="italic">SpecLab,</title> where Drucker and her
                    collaborators pushed the bounds of artistic, critical, and practical forms of
                    scholarship. Drucker distinguished her goals with <title rend="italic">SpecLab</title> from the digital humanities more generally in describing
                        <title rend="italic">SpecLab</title> as moving beyond <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">the instrumental, well-formed, and increasingly
                            standardized business of digital humanities</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="19"/>
                    </cit>. Instead, she argued that <title rend="italic">SpecLab</title> used
                        <soCalled>digital metatexts</soCalled> to create
                        <soCalled>aesthesis</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="19"/>. According to Drucker, digital metatext is
                    not merely a commentary on a set of texts (as might be envisioned within a
                        <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> digital humanities project). Instead,
                    digital metatexts contain features and functions that enable analysis, search,
                    selection, and display, which (alongside their metadata schemes) are capable of
                    structuring and grouping elements <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="11"/>. Through
                    these discursive instruments, metatexts <q>bring the object of their inquiry
                        into being</q> while developing a sense of aesthesis — the partial, situated,
                    and subjective knowledges that are as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">ideological... as epistemological</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="xiii"/>
                    </cit>. The goal of <title rend="italic">SpecLab</title>, therefore, is to
                    challenge <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">the authority of… systematic rationality by questioning
                            its founding assumptions, particularly its totalizing concepts of
                            knowledge</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="xiii"/>
                    </cit>. Likewise, our Contemporary Telepathics collection lays bare a phenomenon
                    unfolding in public discourse. We make the telepathic sublime salient by
                    bringing the object of inquiry <soCalled>into being</soCalled> through the
                    metadata scheme and the public display of the work. </p>
                <p>The remainder of this article is organized in two parts. First, we discuss how
                    future visions of technology are rhetorically formulated by drawing on existing
                    theoretical statements. Second, we contextualize how the Contemporary
                    Telepathics collection reifies rhetorical figures that instantiate the
                    telepathic sublime through new kinds of classificatory practices and structures
                    in the archive.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Technological forecasting and the digital sublime</head>
                <p>Many of the artifacts in the Contemporary Telepathics collection promise,
                    predict, or forecast a time when it will be normal to move objects with only a
                    mind or to make choices just by thinking of them (e.g., <title rend="italic">Turn on the lights</title>, <title rend="italic">Play some Mozart on my
                        sound system</title>, <title rend="italic">Call the police</title>). These
                    forecasts usually involve hyped speculation about the future. Moreover, many of
                    the innovations are discussed <emph>as if</emph> they will emerge and be
                    adopted, even though many will not. Nonetheless, the cultural work (and
                    ephemera) that they instigate is significant. <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> deliberately preserves and tracks this kind of rhetoric.</p>
                <p>Many writers have looked at the rhetorical strategies associated with forecasting
                    the future, the technological sublime, and technocultural myths. According to
                    Daniel Bell, in <title rend="italic">The Coming of Post-Industrial Society: A
                        Venture in Social Forecasting </title>(1976), forecasting is a critical part
                    of the <soCalled>post-industrial</soCalled> society. Forecasts typically involve
                    concrete facts and constraints about the world, but they are often framed
                    axiomatically, and in some cases are buttressed by statistical extrapolations.
                    For example, engineers often forecast industrial design in aluminum with
                    predictive assessments. Statements concerning maximum compositional strength of
                    aluminum will dictate design decisions and visions about how something will end
                    up looking — that is, how thin and light the end result can be. The compositional
                    strength of aluminum is therefore a constraint, which is then coordinated with
                    axioms of design (how it <emph>will</emph> look), alongside existing scientific
                    and market knowledge and sometimes mathematical modelling. Taken together, these
                    aspects become a form of predictive and persuasive reasoning. Once the
                    predictive and persuasive reasoning stabilizes, the forecast will often take the
                    rhetorical form of scientific fact. </p>
                <p>Carolyn Miller (1994), identifies the rhetoric of forecasting in technological
                    discourse, grounding her claims on the term <soCalled>Kairos</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#miller1994" loc="82"/>. Miller defines <q>the phenomenon of
                        ‘technological forecasting’</q> as a unique discourse <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#miller1994">in which the characterization and construction of
                            moments in the present are crucial to the projection of the
                            future</quote>
                        <ptr target="#miller1994" loc="82"/>
                    </cit>. Kairos, then, is an active rhetorical process whereby forecasts leverage
                    the inventor or rhetor’s will, as acts of opportunism. A rhetor will <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#miller1994">look for the particular opportunity in a given moment,
                            to find — or construct — an opening in the here and now, in order to achieve
                            something there and then</quote>
                        <ptr target="#miller1994" loc="83"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>Consider, also, the rhetoric of forecasting taken up by Isabel Pedersen (2013),
                    who argues in the context of the recent emergence of personal digital devices
                    that the desire for human digital enhancement is driven by hype and predictive
                    discourses, which frame future inventions as assumed inevitabilities. Pedersen
                    uses Kenneth Burke’s <soCalled>Terms for Order</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#burke1950" loc="189"/> as a model to explain how predictive
                    discourses require rhetorics of inevitability. She makes the point that such
                    predictive discourses are grounded on a rhetorical construction of imminence–an
                        <soCalled>ultimate order</soCalled>–which makes them appear logical,
                    necessary, and unretractable <ptr target="#pedersen2013" loc="27"/>. Pedersen
                    describes the <q>imminence</q> of the rhetoric of technological forecasting as
                    such: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#pedersen2013">[They] exhibit a progression across the rhetorical triad
                            in the language that informs them. They signal fantastical thoughts and
                            ambitions, which generate rhetorical <soCalled>What if?</soCalled>
                            momentum. However, to counter utopian visions, all of these technologies
                            undergo emergence through scientists who both leverage fantasy and
                            dismiss it while justifying the technology, often under the guise of
                            dehumanizing language. Most powerfully, though, the technology often
                            mysteriously appears as inevitable, as utterly imminent.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pedersen2013" loc="25"/>
                    </cit> In this formulation, utopic claims about inventions are utilized by
                    scientists, and then grounded by the assumption of imminence for their
                    emergence.</p>
                <p>Shock and amazement are other instrumental rhetorical strategies that help
                    constitute the allure of new technologies, together resulting in the feeling of
                    sublime. Throughout history, discussions surrounding telepathic devices have
                    usually been met with feelings of enthusiastic amazement combined with shock. In
                    fact, this response is typical of the initial emergence of most modern
                    technologies, which is why these technologies have been described as sublime.
                    Emily Rohrbach describes the sublime as a propensity to imagine the present in
                    its relation to futurity <ptr target="#rohrbach2016"/>. Historically, and most
                    famously articulated by Edmund Burke and Immanuel Kant, the sublime is an
                    aesthetic experience related to but ultimately distinct from feelings of beauty.
                    Unlike beauty, the sublime so fully fills the mind (usually with terror or awe),
                    that other feelings and reasoning are excluded. The classic case of sublime is
                    found in the work of the Victorian painter Joseph Turner, whose dramatic
                    shipwrecks were the typical subjects of sublimity, evoking transcendent
                        terror.<note> The word <soCalled>sublime</soCalled> has a long history of
                        theorization and scholarly attention in the humanities, and specifically
                        across the visual arts. We use the term to characterize the sense of intense
                        inspiration framed in representations that promote these technologies, which
                        claim to alter human cognition and thinking as a subjective practice. The
                        emphasis lies in how sublime constructions facilitate this shift in digital
                        conditions, discussed earlier.</note> However, as James Carey and John
                    Quirk, Leo Marx, David Nye, and Vincent Mosco have identified, it is modern
                    technologies and not natural landscapes like Turner’s that are typically
                    associated with feelings of the sublime today <ptr target="#carey1970"/>
                    <ptr target="#marx2000"/>
                    <ptr target="#nye1996"/>
                    <ptr target="#mosco2004"/>
                    <ptr target="#mosco2014"/>. </p>
                <p>Mosco traces the lineage of technological, electric, and scientific sublimes to
                    describe a new <emph>digital</emph> sublime, which is the tendency for digital
                    technologies <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mosco2014">to take up a transcendent role in the world beyond the
                            banality of its role in everyday life</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mosco2014" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. According to Mosco, the sublime so fully fills the mind with its object
                    that it can entertain no other <ptr target="#mosco2004" loc="23"/>. The digital
                    sublime functions through myth, in the sense that digital technologies
                        (<soCalled>cyberspace</soCalled> first among them) are oriented towards this
                    common belief, which therefore guides social determinations and justifications.
                    In other words, the sublime informs how manifold inventions are perceived and
                    taken up in society, and therefore, how such inventions work to subsequently
                    shape attitudes toward future inventions. The digital sublime informs future
                    digital conditions.</p>
                <p>An extreme version of Mosco’s digital sublime is described by Anne C. McCarthy
                    (2017), which she calls the <soCalled>Red Bull sublime.</soCalled> Referencing
                    the popular energy drink and media company, the Red Bull sublime fully rejects
                    the ideology of nature as other, or as a distinct site of sublime experience.
                    The Red Bull sublime is in essence a digital sublime, as it takes advantage of
                    social media sharing and digital distribution to <emph>pull</emph> viewers into
                    sublime experiences. These sublime experiences are usually already-mediated
                    feats of daredevil action, both natural and technical, made possible by wing
                    suits, so as to fly down mountain canyons, and high-tech balloons to jump from
                    space <ptr target="#mccarthy2017"/>.</p>
                <p>The role of myth in the digital sublime is especially important for turning the
                    common practices of speculation and forecasting into <soCalled>facts.</soCalled>
                    Barthes, for example, argues that the <q>depoliticized speech</q> of myth
                    produces an important naturalizing effect, writing, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#barthes1972">myth has the task of giving an historical intention a
                            natural justification, and making contingency appear eternal</quote>
                        <ptr target="#barthes1972" loc="142"/>
                    </cit>. Just as Bell believed forecasting was an important agent in the
                    post-industrial society, Barthes believed that the mythic process of making
                    contingency appear eternal was a reflection of bourgeois (or capitalist)
                    ideology. This process is seen most clearly when inventions are developed,
                    commercialized, and adopted, then subsequently, change in response to the latent
                    circulation of commercial myths. Once myth becomes ossified and stable these
                    commitments become history, or <soCalled>facts.</soCalled> Myth progresses not
                    through true or false claims, but instead, as a transformation from productive
                    and predictive desires, on the one hand, and ossified and stable commitments, on
                    the other. Finally, productive and predictive myths project a view of the world,
                    which entails the collective beliefs of its community. </p>
                <p>As our examples of telepathic technology will make clear (below), predictions of
                    the future often start as mythic, which over time stabilize into fact. Facts,
                    just because they are stabilized, do not lack efficacy, rather, they are myths
                    turned invisible, and usually become powerful through this reconfiguration.
                    Electricity offers an example of this dynamic of myth, and the subsequent
                    increase in causal power. Mosco writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mosco2004">electricity achieved its real power when it left
                            mythology and entered banality</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mosco2004" loc="19–20"/>
                    </cit>. Of course, facts can be overturned and changed, but this takes
                    considerable effort. The infrastructures and institutions built up around facts
                    are slow to change or fade, and true innovation, as Latour <ptr target="#latour1999"/> often describes, requires putting your reputation on
                    the line, and fighting against the structuring forces already in place. In the
                    end, when a myth has accreted sufficient “rationality” it becomes fact, just as
                    forecasting transforms into science and the scientific sublime.</p>
                <p>The following section describes the design and development choices of <title rend="italic">Fabric</title>, and how it attempts to capture and trace the
                    movement of the telepathic sublime through forecasting and sublimity in the
                    Contemporary Telepathics collection.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Fabric of Digital Life Artifacts and Archival Representations</head>
                <p><title rend="italic">Fabric</title> is an open-access digital humanities archive
                    that collects and classifies the rhetoric surrounding the emergence of platforms
                    of human-computer interaction, or personal technologies, through digital
                    multimedia objects, publically available at <ref target="http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com">fabricofdigitallife.com</ref>
                    (see Figure 1) <ptr target="#pedersenbaarbe2013"/>. The concept of personal
                    technology is here understood as broadly as possible, which includes
                    technologies that are worn on the body, but also those that are ingested,
                    implanted or embedded. Wearable technologies usually augment embodied actions,
                    but they also sometimes replace body parts, such as limbs or eyes, pointing to
                    the terms <soCalled>embedded</soCalled> and bionic, which sit on the fringe of
                    this collection, with some entries characterizing it. At the time of writing,
                        <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> contains over two thousand digital
                    artifacts about personal technology (and is constantly growing), ranging from
                    images, film clips, academic research articles, video marketing materials, and
                    collected ephemera. The archive is implemented on the CollectiveAccess platform,
                    an open-source content management and description system developed commercially
                    by Whirl-i-Gig.<note> The process to choose a suitable content management system
                        for the archive involved input from software developers, students,
                        librarians and online discussion. We also considered Omeka (<ref target="https://omeka.org/">https://omeka.org/</ref>) and DSpace (<ref target="http://www.dspace.org/">http://www.dspace.org/</ref>).
                        Currently, we hire developers at Whirl-i-gig to customize the
                        CollectiveAccess platform for Fabric, while students archive
                        materials.</note></p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Fabric of Digital Life</title> home screen</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>As each artifact is entered into the archive, it is classified and described
                    using a customized schema. Most of the categories draw on the original Dublin
                    Core set of metadata elements. However, early on in the development of the
                    archive, the decision was made to customize a few of the standard Dublin Core
                    elements, to better reflect the specialized nature of the technologies being
                    archived, and to implicitly make an argument about the ways that such objects,
                    and the archival practices that surround them, are to be understood. In addition
                    to metadata attached to each artifact, the archive also features a number of
                    collections of artifacts, organized by curators with the goal to highlight
                    certain technologies, to explore research themes, or to disclose ideologies
                    embedded in the texts (e.g., transhumanism or surveillance culture). Visitors
                    access <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> through a web frontend that enables
                    searching, browsing, and ways to variously compare artifacts. Other more
                    specialized research tools include user-specified virtual
                        <soCalled>briefcases</soCalled> for saving collections, object viewers, and
                    the ability to automatically create timelines of objects.</p>
                <div>
                    <head> Artifacts</head>
                    <p>As discussed above, for the purposes of this article we are concerned with
                        the telepathic sublime in the Contemporary Telepathics collection, a
                        phenomenon about the response of awe, terror, or amazement over
                        technological inventions that augment or replace the power, distance, or
                        effect of existing human capacities. These sentiments tap into an
                        individual’s or culture’s experience of the future — that is, using telepathic
                        devices often feels <emph>futuristic</emph>. </p>
                    <p>Perhaps most pragmatically, the archive also collects and tracks digital
                        materials related to an invention through its various stages of development
                        and public promotion or public response. As such, the archive follows
                        discourses over time by tracking cross-references and keyword designations.
                        One design intent for the archive is to reflect how an artefact is
                        positioned according to a function or human motivation. Discourses about
                        telepathic devices (and more broadly, <soCalled>wearables</soCalled>),
                        concentrate on how these devices will be used <emph>for</emph>
                        something — they have a <soCalled>for-ness</soCalled> — rather than just being
                            <emph>about</emph> something (<soCalled>aboutness</soCalled>). <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> distinguishes itself from technology
                        indexes such as the ACM Computing Classification System in this regard,
                        which implicitly focus on <soCalled>aboutness.</soCalled><note> See <ref target="https://www.acm.org/publications/class-2012">https://www.acm.org/publications/class-2012</ref>.</note> Instead,
                        it sets out to problematize this orientation, strategically tracking how
                        wearables can be understood in terms of their social <emph>use</emph>. As a
                        result, the effect can sometimes blur optimal pathways for searching,
                        browsing, and information retrieval. </p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Fabric</title> has multiple entry points that facilitate
                        browsing through categories, images, timelines, and index terms, as well as
                        full-text and keyword search. One of the ways users view the archive is by
                        entering through a specific <term>Collection</term>; each collection is a
                        curated set of documents that have been specifically selected by curators.
                        Each focus on a particular topic, theme, or argument. At the time of
                        writing, the Contemporary Telepathics collection holds 62 artifacts across
                        14 different media types ranging from 1999 to 2017. </p>
                    <p>There are also other collections, which reveal different rhetorical
                        motivations and arguments. In one such collection, the goal is to reveal how
                        commercial exoskeletons are developed by military industrial complex
                        producers in close partnership with global Hollywood film franchises (e.g.,
                        Iron Man).<note> See: <ref target="http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/key/ecc7411b22d8481e480b6140ebe83778/facet/collection_facet/id/4/view/images">http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/key/ecc7411b22d8481e480b6140ebe83778/facet/collection_facet/id/4/view/images</ref>.</note>
                        In this collection, video game play has also been archived to reveal how
                        fictional exoskeletons influence real world innovation, and vice versa.
                        Another collection concentrates on the evolving story of inventor/filmmaker
                        Rob Spence and his journey to create a digital prosthetic eye for
                            himself.<note> See: <ref target="http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/key/ecc7411b22d8481e480b6140ebe83778/facet/collection_facet/id/9/view/images">http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/key/ecc7411b22d8481e480b6140ebe83778/facet/collection_facet/id/9/view/images</ref>.</note>
                        His persona, sometimes the subject of a CNN clip, other times a portrayal of
                        himself trying to improve his life after a childhood gun accident, is
                        especially compelling when collected under a single banner. Ultimately, each
                        collection performs a specific task and offers a curatorial argument, set
                        out by the curator (or a number of curators) responsible for its
                        construction.</p>
                    <p>Collections are dynamic and grow over time with new artifacts added as the
                        arguments evolve, as classification adapts, and as contributors and curators
                        come and go on the project. This design prefigures what Miguel Escobar
                        Varela describes as the transience of archives: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#varela2016">[t]raditional archivists could assert that digital
                                archives are not really built to endure the passage of time and
                                constitute a repository for future historical research</quote>
                            <ptr target="#varela2016"/>
                        </cit>. Addressing this challenge, Takhteyev and DuPont point to the spirit
                        of <soCalled>remix</soCalled> in suggesting that collection and preservation
                        are <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#takhteyev2013">living, ongoing practice[s]</quote>
                            <ptr target="#takhteyev2013" loc="362"/>
                        </cit>. We embrace this state of flux and try to overcome the challenges
                        wrought by the passage of time by inviting new people to the archiving team,
                        who then create new archival practices and advocate for new ideas. Varela
                        argues that digital archives should be considered performance in part
                        because <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#varela2016">[o]ften the archives are not impersonal, but highly
                                modified by the interests of the participants</quote>
                            <ptr target="#varela2016"/>
                        </cit>. As such, since its inception in 2012, the archive includes
                        contributions by more than thirty people, even before it was opened for
                        public display.</p>
                    <p>Viewed as a timeline (see Figure 2), comparisons between different media and
                        sometimes heteroclite artifacts are possible. The earliest artifact in the
                        collection is a scene from the film The Matrix (1999), depicting the
                        character Neo learning about telekinesis.<note> See: <ref target="http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/view/timeline/key/769590c77f0f06a1af0831e5877373fd">http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Browse/objects/view/timeline/key/769590c77f0f06a1af0831e5877373fd</ref>.</note>
                        This film clip was included when one of the authors discovered a blog
                        article that directly referred to the film when describing a technological
                        innovation. This serendipitous discovery offers a powerful rhetorical
                        explanation about how a technology might eventually evolve — a forecast.
                        Therefore, multimedia representations such as films form an important part
                        of the discourse and analytical terrain. </p>
                    <p>Taken together, the artifacts displayed in the collection enable a visitor to
                        track the telepathic sublime, which is a keyword. One recent item in the
                        collection is a 2016 article that discusses the same university group who
                        used monkeys wearing brain interfaces back in 2000 <ptr target="#olewitz2016"/>. It reports on implanting a monkey with a chip
                        to move wheelchairs through the powers of telekinesis. In the 2016 article,
                        the final sentence concludes, <q>[w]e hope to begin trying this on humans
                            soon</q> — pointing to a vision of the future, and exhibiting the mythic
                            <soCalled>hope</soCalled> of telepathic sublime, which is never
                        questioned, but simply assumed <ptr target="#olewitz2016"/>. In tracking the
                        telepathic sublime through the metadata schema and collected artifacts, the
                        classificatory approach focuses attention on particular technologies’
                            <soCalled>for-ness,</soCalled> rather than as static and inert
                        technologies. Indeed, since it is often the case that the machinery of
                        telepathic devices becomes obsolete so quickly, tracking motive or intent
                        becomes a foundational critical practice.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Timeline view of Contemporary Telepathics Collection, September
                            2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Moving from monkey to <soCalled>human,</soCalled> the <title rend="quotes">Mind Control Your TV</title> artifact (Figure 3) illustrates the unique
                        archival practices necessary to document the technology as well as the
                        complex rhetorical motivators bound up in this collection, and how they
                        evolve over time.<note> See: <ref target="http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Detail/objects/1089">http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Detail/objects/1089</ref>.</note>
                        The item, a video clip, promotes the idea of using a wireless wearable
                        technology to select television shows to watch, simply through the power of
                        thought <ptr target="#alred2015"/>. In the video, human participants (or
                        maybe actors) wear a headset that reads brainwave fluctuations, which, with
                        suitable control and training of the mind, allows one to telepathically
                        change TV channels. The video is a 4-minute segment from a BBC blog, which
                        discusses how the BBC collaborated with the company <soCalled>This
                            Place</soCalled> to create the technology prototype for TV viewers <ptr target="#alred2015"/>. As such, the video combines executives and
                        developers passionately celebrating their innovative mind-control technology
                        and BBC insiders reacting with shock and awe over how television will evolve
                        in the future. To open the clip, Head of Business Development, BBC Digital,
                        Cyrus Saihan says: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block" source="#alred2015">What we have developed here is a very experimental
                                proof-of-concept that hopefully gives an idea as to how audiences of
                                the future might be able to control devices, such as TVs, just using
                                their brainwaves. So, seeing colleagues using it first-hand has been
                                an interesting experience.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#alred2015"/>
                        </cit>The video reports on future promises as much as it does on current
                        developments. While This Place wants to <emph>sell</emph> its technological
                        abilities (e.g., writing software code, re-engineering of consumer devices,
                        etc.), the BBC wants to appear future-focused and on the cusp of emergent
                        ideas. On the whole, the technology itself is clunky, with awkward
                        brain-computer interaction (BCI) headsets and slow interactions as the
                        television receives the signal. However, the point of the video is not to
                        market a product, rather, the point is to position the BBC as forecasting a
                        future for its consumers. The video is compelling to watch because the
                        participants are awestruck when describing their desire to achieve
                        telekinetics. The visual rhetorical markers from participants, such as
                        excited expressions, gleeful remarks, and the sense that one has witnessed
                        magic, aligns well with the heritage of telepathic invention disclosures.
                        One person in the video says: <q>[t]his is telekinesis… I am literally
                            controlling it with my mind,</q> as if he witnessed phenomena deemed
                        extraordinary <ptr target="#alred2015"/>.</p>
                    <p>Like most web content, the BBC broadcasted this video on multiple media
                        outlets (which the archive tracks), and included a complementary blog story
                        that was written to further explain the original video <ptr target="#saihan2015"/>.<note> See also: <ref target="http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Detail/objects/1768">http://www.fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Detail/objects/1768</ref>.</note>
                        Saihan writes: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block" source="#saihan2015">A subject popular in works of fiction is the ability
                                to control things just by using your mind. The idea of being able to
                                simply think about something and then magically make it happen has
                                fascinated people for many years. Whether it’s using ‘the Force’ in
                                Star Wars, spoon bending on stage or The Matrix, controlling objects
                                simply with your brain has a unique appeal and could open up a whole
                                world of possibilities. So when we learnt that new technologies were
                                now available in the market that allowed you to control electronic
                                devices by measuring the brain’s electrical activity, we wanted to
                                experiment with the technology to see what types of audience
                                experiences this might result in.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#saihan2015"/>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p>This sublime language glorifies and romanticizes telekinesis, but it also
                        argues for the utility of telekinesis, a fantasy-turned-utility rhetoric.
                        Rhetorical allusions to <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> and <title rend="italic">The Matrix</title> ground the fantasy within a familiar
                        context (blockbuster film franchises), but they also make the argument
                        open-ended and seemingly otherworldly — <soCalled>a whole world of
                            possibilities,</soCalled> writes Saihan. Strikingly, this combination
                        makes telekinesis sound reasonable. Audiences are swayed not only with the
                        shock and awe of seeing this invention work, they are also swayed by the
                        familiarity of film culture contextualizing it. <title rend="italic">Fabric
                            of Digital Life</title> archives these kinds of allusions as
                        cross-references to films through specially-designed metadata that makes
                        such connections and allusions clear.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Mind Control Your TV, archived in Fabric of Digital Life,
                                <soCalled>Location on the body</soCalled> and
                                <soCalled>Augmenting</soCalled> categories</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Archival Representations</head>
                    <p>The <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive uses its metadata scheme
                        tactically. Highlighting our interest in rhetorical framings, one goal of
                        the archive is to make salient each artifact’s persuasive intent. For
                        example: what is the artifact <emph>for</emph>? What is it doing in terms of
                        changing attitudes? Is there an audience shaped by the genre? Or, returning
                        to a point made earlier, how might the artifact inform the digital as a
                        cultural condition <ptr target="#carassai2011"/>?</p>
                    <p>Similarly, Melanie Feinberg has argued that classification as communication
                        frees system designers from charges of bias <ptr target="#feinberg2008"/>.
                        In <title rend="italic">Fabric,</title> each artifact is designated a
                        classification with one persuasive intent: <emph>academic, advertisement,
                            art, entertainment, or information</emph>. Therefore, by its very
                        nature, <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> is designed to
                            <emph>preserve</emph> bias, feature it, and display its connection to
                        scientific advancement. </p>
                    <p>Another goal of the archive is to track how a technology and its persuasive
                        intent emerges over time. News of a single piece of technology may go
                        through several stages, each with an intentional and rhetorical shift
                        according to the genre and content producer. For example, a brain interface
                        may transform from its representation in an academic conference paper
                            (<emph>academic</emph>), to a news broadcast celebrating an innovative
                        R&amp;D discovery (<emph>information</emph>), to a commercial product
                            (<emph>advertisement</emph>), and finally, to a novel that interrogates
                        its dystopic implications (<emph>art</emph>). According to Diana Taylor,
                        this process of tracking across media and temporal stages is <q>what makes
                            an object archival</q> in the sense that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2003">it is selected, classified, and presented for
                                analysis</quote>
                            <ptr target="#taylor2003" loc="19"/>
                        </cit>. In this hypothetical example, these shifts in media would be
                        captured in <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> by each artifact’s metadata:
                        shifting classification from <emph>academic</emph>,
                        <emph>information</emph>, <emph>advertisement</emph>, to <emph>art</emph>. </p>
                    <p>Similarly, <title rend="italic">Fabric </title>tracks how technology is
                        carried near, on, or in a body, which is recorded in the metadata schema.
                        The metadata category <soCalled>location on the body</soCalled> lets a user
                        select a body part in order to find associated technologies, ideas, or
                        products. For example, one can select <emph>wrist</emph> to reveal all
                        wrist-worn wearables, and then compare how artifacts and their
                        representations change over time. In the Contemporary Telepathics
                        collection, nearly all items are associated with <emph>brain</emph>, but
                        several are also indexed with another body part. For example, inventor Kevin
                        Warwick achieves telekinesis with an arm implant, and so the artifacts
                        describing his work also include <emph>arm</emph> in their metadata. To help
                        facilitate high-level comparisons, <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> also
                        includes a body analytics visualization.<note> See <ref target="http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Analytics/Index">http://fabricofdigitallife.com/index.php/Analytics/Index</ref>.</note>
                        In this way, <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> enables multi-dimensional
                        and multi-temporal exploration.</p>
                    <p>One of the more experimental metadata categories of the archive is the
                            <soCalled>augmenting</soCalled> field. It is meant to serve as an
                        experiential classification. All artifacts are archived according to an
                        action associated with human activities, which may be physical (e.g.,
                        moving, placing, killing), cognitive (e.g., thinking, choosing) or
                        existential (e.g., living, adoring, reminiscing).<note> We acknowledge that
                            most actions defy this triadic reduction. Killing might be physical,
                            cognitive, or existential. However, considering this complexity helps
                            the archival practice. If we consider inventions as an aspect of lived
                            experience, this field helps us identify technical innovation in a
                            manner that reveals its purpose in terms of society or persons. </note>
                        Manifesting the archive’s experimental and unorthodox approach, the
                        grammatical structure is always a gerund, as gerunds better suggest activity
                        and <soCalled>for-ness</soCalled> (see Table 1). </p>
                    <p>In requiring archivists to capture the ways that wearables augment a body,
                        the archivist must imagine what the technology is augmenting for a
                        seemingly, essentialized, pre-technologic human. This formulation
                        deliberately requires the archivist to cast a narrative about the implied
                        subject of an artifact, that is: if technology were <emph>not</emph>
                        available, how would the implied action be performed? Or, what would it be
                        replaced with, if at all? For example, surveillance technologies augment
                            <emph>watching</emph>, eldercare devices augment <emph>caring</emph> (or
                        perhaps <emph>ignoring</emph>), and military exoskeletons might augment
                            <emph>killing</emph> or <emph>protecting</emph>. Interestingly, new
                        archivists often misidentify this category by choosing technologic
                        activities (e.g., <soCalled>heart-monitoring</soCalled> instead of
                            <soCalled>living</soCalled> or <soCalled>healing</soCalled>). Resolving
                        this mistake requires a tacit exploration of posthuman identity through the
                        acts prescribed by these technologies. The archivist must therefore ask,
                            <q>can we imagine activities without machines?</q> The archival goal is
                        to explore how personal technologies augment constructions of human identity
                        and human action, and to understand how they adapt to a technological
                        world.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Augmenting keywords from Contemporary Telepathics collection</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>acting, being, choosing, communicating, concentrating, connecting,
                                controlling, desiring, evolving, existing, experiencing, feeling,
                                fighting, finding, flying, focusing, gaming, gazing, healing,
                                hearing, imagining, interacting, knowing, living, looking,
                                manipulating, moving, playing, recognizing, reconnecting,
                                remembering, scanning, searching, sending, seeing, sensing, sharing,
                                socializing, storing, thinking, touching, treating, understanding,
                                viewing, walking, wanting, watching, working</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Most new technology is popularized as a commercial product through mass media
                    that dictate the ebb and flow of business trends. As such, devices, costs, and
                    market-share dominate the moment — the implied present. By erasing history, this
                    inclination also valorizes the future — a mythic facade that justifies technology
                    through forecasting (because the future demands it). While the machinery that
                    fulfills this forecast may become woefully obsolete in the future, the idea and
                    the desire might not. The rhetorical framing continues and evolves, and
                    therefore is tracked by the <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> archive.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Fabric</title> is a growing digital humanities archive that
                    exposes the rhetoric of personal technologies (through acts of emergence,
                    forecasting, and myth-making), which invites visitors to explore artifacts
                    across multiple media at different times and locations. <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> has been designed on humanistic principles <ptr target="#drucker2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/> to provide unusual and interesting foils to the
                    ways technology is often displayed, explored, and preserved. Fictional artifacts
                    appear alongside seemingly real ones, inviting comparison without privileging
                    either representation as more valid than the other. The metadata categories
                    focusing on embodied dimensions (<soCalled>location on the body</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>augmenting</soCalled>) deliberately attempt to problematize
                    typical formulations that privilege commercial information over an experiential
                    one.</p>
                <p>We described the Contemporary Telepathics collection and argued for its
                    analytical and exploratory utility. We did so because telepathic capabilities
                    are not yet fully realized as commercial products — in fact, they are partly
                    fictional and constituted by what we term the telepathic sublime. We argued for
                    the necessity of a metadata schema oriented towards tracking this kind of
                    complex phenomenon, which enables us to better preserve and experience the
                    sublime feelings associated with the technology. Our classification schema is
                    deliberately persuasive in that it maintains the archival bias felt and realized
                    as the sublime, rather than seeking objectivity. In this way, <title rend="italic">Fabric</title> displays its artifacts in a manner intended to be exploratory
                    and investigative.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>We want to acknowledge Dr. Andrew Iliadis for his extensive work on metadata
                    development, interface design, and curator editorship for FABRIC. We thank many
                    of the archivists over the years who archived material in the collection
                    including Sharon Caldwell, Tameka Bailey, Samantha Reid, Jeremiah Baarbé​, and
                    Douglas Trueman. We thank Dave DeCamp and the anonymous journal reviewers who
                    made this paper much stronger through suggestions and comments. We thank the
                    Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC) for supporting
                    this research. This research was undertaken, in part, thanks to the Canada
                    Research Chairs program.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alred2015" label="Alred et al. 2015">Aldred B, Mildon T, Plunkett R,
                    and Saihan C (2015) <title rend="quotes">Mind Control Your TV</title> video
                        <title rend="italic">British Broadcasting Corporation</title>. Available
                    from: <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/internet/entries/cd1e4242-3dd2-4e48-8556-8a5ecec6b056">http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/internet/entries/cd1e4242-3dd2-4e48-8556-8a5ecec6b056</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barthes1972" label="Barthes 1972">Barthes R (1972) <title rend="italic">Mythologies</title>. New York: The Noonday Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bell1976" label="Bell 1976">Bell D (1976) <title rend="italic">The
                        Coming of Post-Industrial Society: A Venture in Social Forecasting</title>.
                    New York, NY: Basic Books.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burke1950" label="Burke 1950">Burke K ([1950] 1969) <title rend="italic">A Rhetoric of Motives</title>. London: University of
                    California Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carey1970" label="Carey and Quirk 1970">Carey JW and Quirk JT (1970)
                        <title rend="quotes">The Mythos of the Electronic Revolution.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The American Scholar</title> 39(3): 395–424.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carassai2011" label="Carassai and Takehana 2011">Carassai M and
                    Takehana E (2011) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Futures of Digital
                        Studies</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5:3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="devries2012" label="De Vries 2012">De Vries IO (2012) <title rend="italic">Tantalisingly Close an Archaeology of Communication Desires in
                        Discourses of Mobile Wireless Media</title>. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009">Drucker J (2009) <title rend="italic">SpecLab: Digital Aesthetics and Projects in Speculative
                        Computing.</title> Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2012" label="Drucker 2012">Drucker J (2012) <title rend="quotes">Humanistic Theory and Digital Scholarship.</title> In: Gold MK
                    (ed.), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>,
                    Minneapolis: University Of Minnesota Press. Available from: <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/34">http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/34</ref> (accessed 22 September
                    2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dupont2016" label="DuPont and Cattapan 2016">DuPont Q and Cattapan A
                    (2016) <title rend="quotes">Moving Forward, Looking Back: Taking Canadian
                        Feminist Histories Online.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Atlantis: Critical Studies in Gender, Culture, and Social
                        Justice</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://journals.msvu.ca/index.php/atlantis/issue/archive">http://journals.msvu.ca/index.php/atlantis/issue/archive</ref> (accessed 15
                    June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="feinberg2008" label="Feinberg 2008">Feinberg M (2008) <title rend="italic">Classification as Communication: Properties and
                    Design</title>. PhD, Seattle, WA: University of Washington.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greenspan2011" label="Greenspan 2011">Greenspan B (2011) <title rend="quotes">The New Place of Reading: Locative Media and the Future of
                        Narrative</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5(3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kaplan2014" label="Kaplan 2014">Kaplan, Dan. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Digital Telepathy Is The Future Of The Human Species</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Techcrunch</title>. Available from <ref target="https://techcrunch.com/2014/09/24/digital-telepathy-is-the-future-of-the-human-species/">https://techcrunch.com/2014/09/24/digital-telepathy-is-the-future-of-the-human-species/</ref>
                    (accessed 7 June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour1999" label="Latour 1999">Latour B (1999) <title rend="italic">Pandora’s Hope: Essays on the Reality of Science Studies</title>. 1st ed.
                    Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2013" label="Liu 2013">Liu A (2013) <title rend="quotes">The
                        Meaning of the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publications of the Modern Language Association of
                        America</title> 128(2): 409-423.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccarthy2017" label="McCarthy 2017">McCarthy AC (2017) <title rend="quotes">Reading the Red Bull Sublime.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publications of the Modern Language Association of
                        America</title> 132(3): 543-557.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marx2000" label="Marx 2000">Marx L (2000) <title rend="italic">The
                        Machine in the Garden: Technology and the Pastoral Ideal in America</title>.
                    New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="miller1994" label="Miller 1994">Miller C (1994) <title rend="quotes">Opportunity, Opportunism, and Progress: Kairos in the Rhetoric of
                        Technology.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Argumentation</title> 8(1): 81–96.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mosco2004" label="Mosco 2004">Mosco V (2004) <title rend="italic">The
                        Digital Sublime: Myth, Power, and Cyberspace</title>. Cambridge MA: MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mosco2014" label="Mosco 2014">Mosco V (2014) <title rend="italic">To
                        the Cloud: Big Data in a Turbulent World</title>. Boulder CO:
                    Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nicolelis2008" label="Nicolelis and Chapin 2008">Nicolelis M and
                    Chapin J (2008) <title rend="quotes">Controlling Robots with the Mind.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scientific American Reports</title>. Available from: <ref target="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/controlling-robots-with-the-mind/">https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/controlling-robots-with-the-mind/</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nye1996" label="Nye 1996">Nye DE (1996) <title rend="italic">American
                        Technological Sublime</title>. Cambridge MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olewitz2016" label="Olewitz 2016">Olewitz C (2016) <title rend="quotes">Thanks To A Brain Implant, These Monkeys Can Control
                        Wheelchairs with Their Minds.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Trends</title>. Available from: <ref target="https://www.digitaltrends.com/cool-tech/monkeys-control-wheelchairs-with-minds/">https://www.digitaltrends.com/cool-tech/monkeys-control-wheelchairs-with-minds/
                    </ref>(accessed June 15, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pedersen2013" label="Pedersen 2013">Pedersen I (2013) <title rend="italic">Ready to Wear: A Rhetoric of Wearable Computers and
                        Reality-shifting Media</title>. Anderson, SC: Parlor Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pedersenbaarbe2013" label="Pedersen and Baarbé 2013">Pedersen I and
                    Baarbé J, (2013) <title rend="quotes">Archiving the 'Fabric of Digital
                        Life',</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality
                        - Arts, Media, and Humanities</title> (ISMAR-AMH), Adelaide, SA, 2013, pp.
                    1-6.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="puglionesi2017" label="Puglionesi 2017">Puglionesi A (2017) <title rend="quotes">Lofty Only In Sound: Crossed Wires and Community in
                        19th-Century Dreams</title>. <title rend="italic">The Public Domain
                        Review</title>. Available from: <ref target="https://publicdomainreview.org/2017/04/05/lofty-only-in-sound-crossed-wires-and-community-in-19th-century-dreams/">https://publicdomainreview.org/2017/04/05/lofty-only-in-sound-crossed-wires-and-community-in-19th-century-dreams/</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rohrbach2016" label="Rohrbach 2016">Rohrbach E (2016) <title rend="italic">Modernity's Mist: British Romanticism and the Poetics of
                        Anticipation.</title> New York, NY: Fordham University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="saihan2015" label="Saihan 2015">Saihan C (2015) <title rend="quotes">Mind control your TV.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">BBC Internet Blog</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/internet/entries/cd1e4242-3dd2-4e48-8556-8a5ecec6b056">http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/internet/entries/cd1e4242-3dd2-4e48-8556-8a5ecec6b056</ref>
                    (accessed 22 September 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2016" label="Sayers 2016">Sayers J (2016) <title rend="quotes">Dropping The Digital.</title> In: Gold MK and Klein LF (eds.), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, Minneapolis:
                    University Of Minnesota Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="takhteyev2013" label="Takhteyev and DuPont 2013">Takhteyev Y and
                    DuPont Q (2013) <title rend="quotes">Retrocomputing as Preservation and
                        Remix.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Library Hi Tech</title> 31(2). Available from: <ref target="http://www.emeraldinsight.com/doi/full/10.1108/07378831311329103">http://www.emeraldinsight.com/doi/full/10.1108/07378831311329103</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2003" label="Taylor 2003">Taylor D (2003) <title rend="italic">The Archive and the Repertoire.</title> Durham, NC: Duke University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unsworth2000" label="Unsworth 2000">Unsworth J (2000) <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods Do Humanities Researchers
                        Have in Common, and How Might Our Tools Reflect This.</title> In: <title rend="italic">Symposium on Humanities Computing: Formal Methods,
                        Experimental Practice</title>, King’s College, London. Available from: <ref target="http://people.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html">http://people.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html</ref>
                    (accessed 22 September 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weiser1991" label="Weiser 1991">Weiser M (1991) <title rend="quotes">The Computer for the 21st Century.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scientific American Ubicomp Paper</title>. 94-105.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013" label="Wernimont 2013">Wernimont J (2013) <title rend="quotes">Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions In Digital
                        Literary Archives.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7(1). Available from:
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="varela2016" label="Varela 2016">Varela ME (2016) <title rend="quotes">The Archive as Repertoire: Transience and Sustainability in Digital
                        Archives. </title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 10(4). Available from:
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000269/000269.html</ref>
                    (accessed 15 June 2017).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>