<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Towards a National Data Architecture for Cultural Collections: Designing the Australian Cultural Data 
               Engine</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Rachel <dhq:family>Fensham</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0339-4848</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Melbourne; Australian Cultural Data Engine</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rachel.fensham@unimelb.edu.au</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Rachel Fensham</name> is Professor of Dance and Theatre Studies at the <name>University of Melbourne</name> and former Lead 
                     Chief Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Tyne Daile <dhq:family>Sumner</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1717-7147</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Australian National University; Australian Cultural Data Engine</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Tyne Daile Sumner</name> is an ARC DECRA Fellow at the <name>Australian National University</name> and former Cultural Data 
                     Research Fellow for the Australian Cultural Data Engine. 
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Nat <dhq:family>Cutter</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3699-0881</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Melbourne; Australian Cultural Data Engine</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Nat Cutter</name> is the Mary Lugton Postdoctoral Fellow and Assistant Lecturer in History at the <name>University of 
                     Melbourne</name>, and former Research Coordinator and Cultural Data Research Fellow for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>George <dhq:family>Buchanan</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9044-6644</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>RMIT University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>George Buchanan</name> is Associate Professor and Deputy Dean (Research) in Computing Technologies at <name>RMIT 
                     University</name> and a Chief Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Rui <dhq:family>Liu</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5631-8702</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Melbourne</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Rui Liu</name> is a PhD student in Human-Computer Interaction at the <name>University of Melbourne</name> and an affiliated 
                     researcher for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Justin <dhq:family>Munoz</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5339-2904</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Justin Munoz</name> is an independent scholar and former data scientist for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>James <dhq:family>Smithies</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4801-0366</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Australian National University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>James Smithies</name> is Professor of Digital Humanities at the <name>Australian National University</name> and a Chief 
                     Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ivy <dhq:family>Zheng</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-7028-9980</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Newcastle</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Ivy Zheng</name> is an independent scholar and former data engineer for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Carlin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8902-0918</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>RMIT University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>David Carlin</name> is Professor of Creative Writing at <name>RMIT University</name> and a Chief Investigator for the 
                     Australian Cultural Data Engine. 
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Erik <dhq:family>Champion</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5362-6176</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of South Australia</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Erik Champion</name> is an Enterprise Fellow at the <name>University of South Australia</name> and a Chief Investigator for 
                     the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Hugh <dhq:family>Craig</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9336-1678</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Newcastle</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Hugh Craig</name> is Emeritus Professor at the <name>University of Newcastle</name> and a Chief Investigator for the 
                     Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Scott <dhq:family>East</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7367-7707</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of New South Wales</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Scott East</name> is a Lecturer of Art and Design at the <name>University of New South Wales</name> and a Chief Investigator 
                     for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Chris <dhq:family>Hay</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8507-3556</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Flinders University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Chris Hay</name> is Professor of Drama at <name>Flinders University</name> and a Chief Investigator for the Australian 
                     Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Lisa M. <dhq:family>Given</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1840-6175</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>RMIT University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Lisa M. Given</name> is Director of the Social Change Enabling Impact Platform, Professor of Information Sciences at 
                     <name>RMIT University</name>, and a Chief Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>John <dhq:family>Macarthur</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8787-1305</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Queensland</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>John Macarthur</name> is Professor in Architecture at the <name>University of Queensland</name> and a Chief Investigator for 
                     the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>McMeekin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6445-1183</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Curtin University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>David McMeekin</name> is Senior Lecturer in Software Engineering at <name>Curtin University</name> and a Chief Investigator 
                     for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Joanna <dhq:family>Mendelssohn</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7562-668X</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Melbourne</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Joanna Mendelssohn</name> is an Honorary Associate Professor at the <name>University of Melbourne</name> and a Chief 
                     Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Deborah <dhq:family>van der Plaat</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5379-9395</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Queensland</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Deborah van der Plaat</name> is a Senior Lecturer in Architecture at the <name>University of Queensland</name> and a Chief 
                     Investigator for the Australian Cultural Data Engine.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000678</idno>
            <idno type="volume">018</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2024-04-26">26 April 2024</date>
            <dhq:articleType>case study</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#databases"/>
               <term corresp="#info_architecture"/>
               <term corresp="#project_report"/>
               <term corresp="#data_analytics"/>
               <term corresp="#visual_art"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000678/000678.xml">GitHub
                   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article summarises the aims, methods, information architecture, outputs, and innovations of the Australian Cultural Data Engine 
               (ACD-Engine), a project that harnesses leading cultural databases to build bridges to research, industry, and government. The project 
               investigates digital heritage collections, data ontologies, and interoperability, building an information architecture to enhance the 
               open sharing of Australian cultural data. Working with a cross-disciplinary team, the ACD-Engine establishes conceptual and technical 
               frameworks for better understanding the platforms and uses of cultural data across a range of national and international contexts. This 
               new cyber-infrastructure advances cultural data aggregation and interoperability whilst prioritising data quality and domain 
               distinctiveness to answer new research questions across disciplines. As such, the ACD-Engine provides a novel approach to data 
               management and data modelling in the arts and humanities that has significant implications for digital collections, digital humanities, 
               and data analytics.
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>Cultural databases are complicated beasts: rich in their contents and yet often idiosyncratic, siloed, and precarious. This article outlines 
              an innovative workflow and information architecture designed to harness the interoperability of digital resources/records for cultural 
              analytics research without obliterating distinctive domain knowledges.
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The Australian Cultural Data Engine (ACD-Engine) is a multidisciplinary project that harnesses leading Australian cultural databases to 
               analyse cultural production, artistic networks, and the socio-economic implications and uses of arts and cultural data in the Australian 
               context and internationally. Commencing in August 2021, the project received two years' funding through the Australian Research Council 
               (ARC) Linkage, Equipment, Infrastructure and Facilities (LIEF) program. Based at the <name>University of Melbourne</name>, the 
               ACD-Engine gathered a collaborative team of humanities and social science researchers, data scientists, data engineers, and data 
               visualisation specialists from the <name>University of Melbourne</name>, the <name>University of Queensland</name>, the 
               <name>University of New South Wales</name>, <name>Swinburne University of Technology</name>, <name>Curtin University</name>, 
               <name>RMIT University</name>, the <name>University of Newcastle</name>, <name>Flinders University</name>, and 
               <name>King's College London</name>.
            </p>
            <p>The core ACD-Engine team in <name>Melbourne</name> worked closely with institutional partners and domain experts from diverse cultural 
               data backgrounds (architecture, design, performing arts, and visual arts) to foster improved data analytics and cross-disciplinary data 
               sharing within the Australian arts and cultural sector. In line with approaches emerging in <name>Europe</name> and the <name>UK</name>, 
               as well as other research and data-intensive contexts in <name>Australia</name>, we investigated the data quality and data ontologies 
               that inform <name>Australia</name>'s cultural data landscape. To coordinate an interoperable model for linking, interpreting, and using 
               heterogeneous digital heritage data, the project team built a Research Software Engineering (RSE) capacity that could interrogate the 
               potential of more robust, larger-scale understandings of arts and cultural data in future. The ACD-Engine has also examined how data 
               analytics can provide meaningful insights to issues of national significance including employment, heritage, and cultural policy.
            </p>
            <p>This article contributes to a growing genre of scholarship about collaborative research design within the digital humanities, including 
               <ptr target="#ahnert_et_al_2023"/> <ptr target="#mcgillivray_et_al_2020"/>. Writing from a cross-disciplinary perspective, in this 
               article we describe the project's objectives, design, and multi-stage approach to the extraction, aggregation, and analysis of a wide 
               range of cultural data. Reporting on the organisation of research design and activity has been standard practice in government and the 
               commercial sector for decades and helps to establish standardised and stable frameworks for research 
               <ptr target="#desfray_raymond_2014"/>. Continuing this developing best practice, we outline our project's aims and objectives, 
               contextualise these among some major national and international cultural data aggregation projects, and explain how we assembled our 
               team. It was essential to establish principles for open data sharing among our project partners, so this process is also explained. As 
               the central outcome of the project, we then provide a detailed overview of the ACD-Engine Architecture Construction Workflow that has 
               resulted in the ACD-Engine information architecture prototype, as a significant contribution towards a national data architecture for 
               Australian artistic and cultural collections. Developing from our work in data exploration and enrichment, we outline some cultural data 
               outputs emerging from the ACD-Engine that illustrate how the discrete datasets developed by the project offer productive applications in 
               humanities research, creative industries, and cultural policy. Finally, we summarise the project's key outcomes and suggest possible 
               future directions for the generation, interoperability, and application of Australian cultural data that might build upon the 
               ACD-Engine's work.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Aims and Work Programs</head>
            <p>Arts and cultural data accumulate in the catalogues of collecting institutions (e.g., museums, art galleries, and member organisations), 
               bespoke disciplinary datasets (e.g., biographical indexes or catalogues), curated digital repositories and archives (e.g., specialist 
               libraries or websites), and in a range of smaller scale heritage, community, and creative industry organisations 
               <ptr target="#whitelaw_2015"/>. It also exists in government reporting, census and statistical modelling of culture, and online digital 
               platforms providing links to cultural events. These disparate systems represent a <q>cyber-infrastructure</q> of humanities knowledges 
               and expertise, but researchers and policymakers often lack the data literacies that would enable this abundance of cultural data to 
               substantively contribute to global social and policy transformations <ptr target="#smithies_2017"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The ACD-Engine emerged from recognition of the fragmented nature of cultural data collections and the different computational models 
               upon which they have been built, as well as the distinctiveness, sensitivities, and vulnerabilities of specialist data repositories. In 
               response to this, the project's central aims were:
            </p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>Improve the quality of existing Australian cultural data across a range of partner databases and cultural disciplines;
                </item>
                <item>Support an expansion in the accessibility, use, and interoperability of cultural data in research, industry, and government 
                  contexts; and
                </item>
                <item>Demonstrate how new insights into arts and cultural production can emerge by improving cultural data interoperability across 
                  platforms, systems, and regions.
                </item>
              </list>
            <p>To achieve these aims, we established the following overlapping programs of work. These programs generally moved from processes 
               concerned with data integration and design to questions of capability, analysis, access, and public impact, but each program was 
               iterative and informed the others as the ACD-Engine project developed.
            </p>
            <div>
              <head>Program A: Project Design</head>
                <p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Establish an approach for effectively working with cultural data across multi-disciplinary teams from diverse disciplines, 
                      backgrounds, and skill-sets;
                    </item>
                    <item>Shape a flexible and diverse humanities-trained workforce with data science skills, who can manage the social and ethical 
                      considerations of cultural data; and
                    </item>
                    <item>Develop a shared understanding of the process of cultural data sharing, which honours the labour of content creators as well 
                      as those transforming, enriching, and analysing data.
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Program B: Data Exploration and Transformation</head>
                <p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Using a range of scraping and data wrangling methods, transform existing cultural collections into datasets for immediate 
                      use in computational contexts;
                    </item>
                    <item>Identify and resolve inconsistencies, redundancies, errors, and gaps in the data;
                    </item>
                    <item>Liaise closely with subject matter experts to augment and refine datasets in accordance with industry knowledge, cultural 
                      histories, and personal experience;
                    </item>
                    <item>Develop conceptual frameworks for the creation of qualitative subsets for use in comparative analysis; and 
                    </item>
                    <item>Explore new adjacent data sources to complement existing datasets for innovative analytics.</item>
                  </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Program C: Information Architecture Development</head>
                <p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Investigate and interrogate named entities and ontologies within cultural data collections;
                    </item>
                    <item>Engage with existing standards in the digital humanities to develop a prototype information architecture for cultural data; 
                    </item>
                    <item>Interconnect different cultural data collections without dissolving their distinctive discipline-specific and ontological 
                      structures.
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Program D: Analysis and Impact</head>
              <p>
                <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Design innovative models for revealing patterns in Australian arts production, cultural consumption, and tangible and 
                    intangible cultural heritage;
                  </item>
                  <item>Create new resources for policy formation, cultural production, and research infrastructure development; and
                  </item>
                  <item>Extend access to cultural data to facilitate new cross-collection, cross-disciplinary, and cross-institutional research.
                  </item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program A.1: Project Context</head>
            <div>
              <head>Cultural Data Aggregation in <name>North America</name>, <name>Europe</name>, and the <name>United Kingdom</name></head>
                <p>National and international efforts to aggregate humanities databases are reshaping concepts of heritage, creativity, and cultural 
                   inclusion in the global sphere <ptr target="#bettivia_stainforth_2017"/> <ptr target="#smithies_et_al_2023"/>. However, as 
                   <name>Lisa M. Given</name>, <name>Sarah Polkinghorne</name> and <name>Joann Cattlin</name> point out, <quote rend="inline">while 
                   cultural data initiatives are growing in number, globally, they lack a cohesive, sustainable, and healthy ecosystem to enable 
                   collaboration and sharing across related contexts</quote> <ptr target="#given_polkinghorne_cattlin_2023"/>. Several international 
                   models for the expansion and interoperability of cultural data warrant consideration. The DARIAH-DE repository is a digital archive 
                   for the long-term preservation of humanities and cultural research data, aggregated across various services and applications 
                   (<ref target="https://repository.de.dariah.eu/search/">https://repository.de.dariah.eu/search/</ref>). Europeana PRO makes millions 
                   of cultural data assets from European galleries, libraries, archives, and museums available for searching and downloading 
                   (<ref target="https://pro.europeana.eu/page/datasets">https://pro.europeana.eu/page/datasets</ref>). Similarly, the Digital 
                   Repository of Ireland (<ref target="https://dri.ie/about-us/">https://dri.ie/about-us/</ref>) was launched in 2015 to facilitate 
                   the <quote rend="inline">preservation, curation, and dissemination of <name>Ireland</name>'s humanities, social sciences, and 
                   cultural heritage data</quote>. In 2020, the <name>United Kingdom</name> launched Towards a National Collection (TaNC), an £18.9 
                   million, five-year program of investment aimed at <quote rend="inline">creating a unified virtual national collection</quote> of the 
                   <name>UK</name>'s museums, libraries, galleries, and archives, <quote rend="inline">dissolving barriers between different 
                   collections</quote>, and <quote rend="inline">opening UK heritage to the world</quote> <ptr target="#ukri_2022"/>.
                </p>
                <p>Most of these platforms have elected either to combine data into a single unified search engine or to provide a collection of 
                   external links. However, seeking to develop best practices for data sharing and data flows, some international aggregation projects 
                   and research groups, such as DHARPA (<ref target="https://dharpa.org/">https://dharpa.org/</ref>), have begun to grapple with how 
                   to productively interconnect diverse data sources without flattening the distinctiveness of domain-specific collection ontologies. 
                   Another dimension to data aggregation and interoperability is the export and generation of cultural heritage datasets, which until 
                   recently has been dominated by the Open Archives Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting 
                   (<ref target="https://www.openarchives.org/pmh/">https://www.openarchives.org/pmh/</ref>), discussed in the section <q>Program B: 
                   Technical Design and Methods</q> below.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Cultural Data Aggregation and Interoperability in Australia</head>
                <p>In <name>Australia</name>, the most important digital aggregator of cultural data is Trove, the <name>National Library of 
                   Australia</name> (<name>NLA</name>)'s search engine, which over the past several decades has evolved into a powerful platform 
                   offering access to the <name>NLA</name>'s own collections, as well as other registered collections. While not specifically designed 
                   as research cyber-infrastructure, Trove has nevertheless attracted a wide local and international user base, ranging from 
                   professional researchers to the general public <ptr target="#stainforth_2019"/>. Under its <q>People and Organisations</q> portal 
                   (<ref target="https://trove.nla.gov.au/help/categories/people-and-organisations-category">https://trove.nla.gov.au/help/categories/people-and-organisations-category</ref>), 
                   Trove currently links to several cultural collections associated with the ACD-Engine, and NLA software developers as well as 
                   independent digital humanities experts have produced a range of tools that enable the searching and downloading of curated research 
                   datasets.<note>A key innovator in this space is <name>Tim Sherratt</name>, whose GLAM Workbench 
                   (<ref target="https://glam-workbench.net/">https://glam-workbench.net/</ref>) and Trove Data Guide 
                   (<ref target="https://wragge.github.io/trove-data-guide/home.html">https://wragge.github.io/trove-data-guide/home.html</ref>, 
                   in-progress at the time of writing) have been transformative for researchers in this space.</note> Historically, however, it has 
                   suffered from inadequate resourcing to maintain and renovate core infrastructure and develop research capability 
                   <ptr target="#jones_verhoeven_2022"/>.<note>Completed in September 2023, the <q>Trove Enhancements</q> project managed by the 
                   Australian Research Data Commons improved the Trove pages for researchers and updated the public Trove API to provide better support 
                   for Australian HASS researchers 
                   (<ref target="https://ardc.edu.au/project/trove-researcher-platform-for-advanced-research/">https://ardc.edu.au/project/trove-researcher-platform-for-advanced-research/</ref>). 
                   Trove development remains tied to fixed-term, outcome-focused projects, and ongoing funding is not assured.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Another important project has been the Humanities Networked Infrastructure (HuNI, 
                   <ref target="https://huni.net.au/#/search">https://huni.net.au/</ref>), a platform developed as part of the Australian government's 
                   National e-Research Collaboration Tools and Researchers programme. The design framework of HuNI recognises humanities data as 
                   consisting of <quote rend="inline">the various annotations, tags, links, associations, ratings, reviews, and comments produced 
                   during the humanities research process, together with the semantic <quote rend="inline">entities</quote> to which these annotations 
                   refer: concepts, persons, places, and events</quote> <ptr target="#burrows_2011"/>. HuNI's data-centred workflow, in a similar way 
                   to Trove, focuses on a <quote rend="inline">discovery environment</quote> that enables browsing and searching across disparate data 
                   sources, though it does not house the data itself <ptr target="#burrows_2013"/> <ptr target="#burrows_verhoeven_2016"/>. 
                   <name>Australia</name> also has a major centralised data repository, the Australian Data Archive (ADA). The ADA provides a central 
                   searchable catalogue of more than 5,000 social science datasets. It holds data from surveys, opinion polls, and censuses from 
                   <name>Australia</name> and the <name>Asia</name>-Pacific region 
                   (<ref target="https://ada.edu.au/about-ada/">https://ada.edu.au/about-ada/</ref>). However, the ADA hosts very little material on 
                   arts and culture, and its uncurated, user-submitted datasets are not necessarily immediately suitable for computational analysis. A 
                   more encouraging development in the Australian cultural data landscape has been the formation of an Indigenous Data Network in 2018 
                   (<ref target="https://mspgh.unimelb.edu.au/centres-institutes/onemda/research-group/indigenous-data-network">https://mspgh.unimelb.edu.au/centres-institutes/onemda/research-group/indigenous-data-network</ref>), 
                   and, more recently, national investment in a HASS and Indigenous Research Data Commons within the Australian Research Data Commons 
                   (ARDC). These projects justly champion the importance of Aboriginal and Torres Straits Islander custodianship of rich cultural 
                   traditions as they are expressed in data and housed in cultural collections.
                </p>
                <p>In <name>Australia</name>, as much as in <name>Europe</name>, <name>North America</name>, and the <name>United Kingdom</name>, the 
                   demand for quality data and online access to data-rich sources of information has grown exponentially, with more stakeholders 
                   entering the field each year. As such, the cultural data landscape in <name>Australia</name> is broad, yet fragmented, and has been 
                   supported for decades by fixed-term national investment grants made to individual humanities, arts, and social sciences (HASS)-based 
                   digital tools, platforms, working groups, and labs (such as the ARDC's HASS Community Data Lab,: 
                   <ref target="https://ardc.edu.au/project/hass-community-data-lab/">https://ardc.edu.au/project/hass-community-data-lab/</ref>). As 
                   <name>Mike Jones</name> and <name>Alana Piper</name> point out, the <quote rend="inline">funding models set up for traditional 
                   projects normally rely on them having a clear end date for financial support, after which digital resource may not even be accessible, 
                   let alone updated</quote> <ptr target="#jones_piper_2023"/>. Moreover, many individual research collections and digital databases 
                   have been built using bespoke technical approaches (often outsourced to private companies), which have led to institution-specific 
                   issues relating to design, access, maintenance, and use of data. Inevitably, the diversity of cultural data collections reflects 
                   different histories of data collection, management, curation, and maintenance, and can lead to intergenerational and sometimes 
                   competitive misalignments of the potentiality in cultural data. Similarly, and in spite of national and international calls for open 
                   data policies (see e.g., <ref target="https://inke.ca/">https://inke.ca/</ref>), the economic, cultural, and social data managed by 
                   governments is often limited by idiosyncratic data structures, short-term political support, or survey parameters (e.g., 
                   <ref target="https://www.arts.gov.au/cultural-data-online">https://www.arts.gov.au/cultural-data-online</ref>).
                </p>
                <p>Nonetheless, the appetite for accessing, connecting, and telling stories with Australian cultural data in the creative industries 
                   continues apace, as evidenced by a reinvigorated national cultural policy, REVIVE, announced in 2023 
                   <ptr target="#australian_government_2023"/>. Researchers across the humanities are also increasingly interested in the research 
                   possibilities to be realised by using structured cultural data and large digital collections. However, as Ahnert et al. rightly 
                   point out in their analysis of collaborative historical work using big data, relatively little research considers 
                   <quote rend="inline">the practical steps in getting hold of such data, and the restrictions with which it may come</quote> 
                   <ptr target="#ahnert_et_al_2023"/>.
                </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program A.2: Project Structure and Team</head>
            <p>Rather than trying to <q>solve</q> national collections in a single effort, we took a targeted, bottom-up approach to examine the larger 
               problem space in a way that did not centre on acquiring more data, developing more tools, or building another aggregation platform. 
               Instead, the project undertook a detailed exploration of heterogeneous cultural data collections, each with unique histories and 
               infrastructures. We thus began with the same broad intent as the <q>Foundation</q> TaNC projects 
               (<ref target="https://www.nationalcollection.org.uk/Foundation-Projects">https://www.nationalcollection.org.uk/Foundation-Projects</ref>), 
               which sought to interconnect selected collections in vast, historic institutions, including the <name>National Archives</name>, 
               the <name>National Gallery</name>, the <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name>, the <name>British Library</name>, and the 
               <name>Tate Gallery</name>. The ACD-Engine benefitted from the agility afforded by working with smaller, discipline-based databases with 
               fewer institutional or historical barriers to cooperation (e.g., those committed to an open API). In so doing, the project focused on 
               assembling discrete, cleaned, augmented, and merged datasets that could become usable in a variety of computational contexts and yet 
               retain each collection's disciplinary distinctiveness and place within the national cultural data ecosystem 
               <ptr target="#zheng_munoz_2023a"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The ACD-Engine is, distinctively, a cyber-infrastructure that strategically built upon pre-existing projects, investments, and data 
               models without erasing their unique affordances, histories, and investments. Centring on a skilled research software engineering and 
               digital humanities team at the <name>University of Melbourne</name>, which experimented with innovative technical methods and 
               theoretical interrogation, we established a multi-institutional network of discipline experts and digital humanities practitioners 
               across <name>Australia</name> and the <name>UK</name>.<note>In addition to our partners, we have also engaged with a range of 
               stakeholders in the sector including the <name>Victorian Centre for Data Insights</name>, the P<name>owerhouse Museum</name>, the 
               <name>National Association for the Visual Arts</name>, the <name>National Museum of Australia</name>, the <name>National Gallery of 
               Australia</name>, the <name>Centre for Artificial Intelligence and Digital Ethics</name>, the <name>Robin Boyd Foundation</name>, and 
               <title rend="italic">Art + Australia</title> magazine.</note> Harnessing this new capacity at the intersection of computation and 
               cultural interpretation, we sought to enhance the contribution and impact of cultural data through focused interdisciplinary projects 
               and themes.<note>These objectives align with those of the TaNC scheme in the <name>UK</name> and projects such as the <name>British 
               Library</name>'s <q>Living with Machines</q> project 
               (<ref target="https://www.bl.uk/projects/living-with-machines">https://www.bl.uk/projects/living-with-machines</ref>).</note>
            </p>
            <p>The following diagram explains how the contributing data sources were transformed through the ACD-Engine into new resources for a range 
               of users and beneficiaries.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
              <head>The ACD-Engine's institutional structure (October 2023). Our five partner databases (AusStage, the Circus Oz Living Archive, DAAO, 
                DAQA, and the <name>Curtin University Library</name>) appear on the left-hand side, flanked by our technical and advisory partners, the 
                Swinburne Data Co-Op, <name>RMIT</name>'s Social Change Enabling Impact Platform, the <name>University of Newcastle</name>'s 
                Time-Layered Cultural Map, and the King's Digital Lab. The ACD-Engine core team <q>ingested</q> these databases, working in partnership 
                with internal <name>Melbourne</name> platforms, before distributing the results to our Partner Institutions and national Cultural Data 
                Organisations. In turn, this data would reach a range of Australian Users and Beneficiaries across the HASS Research Community, 
                Government, Arts and Cultural Sector, and the public.</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>In terms of personnel, the ACD-Engine was comprised of a core team at the <name>University of Melbourne</name> and collaborators at 
               institutions around Australia, summarised as follows:
            </p>
            <div>
              <head><name>Melbourne</name> Team</head>
                <p>The interdisciplinary <name>Melbourne</name> team, in consultation with project partners, undertook the day-to-day work of the 
                   ACD-Engine project as outlined in the project workflow below. The team comprised the following six part-time posts, totalling 
                   approximately three full-time positions.
                </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Two lead researchers (in ARC parlance, Chief Investigators or CIs; professorial level, expertise in digital humanities, 
                      theatre studies, and information systems)</item>
                    <item>One cultural data research fellow (postdoctoral level, expertise in digital humanities and literary studies)</item>
                    <item>One project manager/cultural data research fellow (postdoctoral level, expertise in digital humanities and historical 
                      studies)</item>
                    <item>One data scientist and visualisation specialist (PhD/postdoctoral level)</item>
                    <item>One data engineer (graduate student level)</item>
                  </list>
                <p>In additional, we benefited from the expertise of students affiliated to, but not funded by the project:
                </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>One doctoral student in open linked data (graduate student level)</item>
                    <item>Three short-term student interns (undergraduate/graduate student level)</item>
                  </list>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Project Partners (Cultural Data)</head>
                <p>Cultural researchers from our project partners were involved in the ACD-Engine's reflexive exploration, transformation, and analysis 
                   of the cultural data extracted from their databases. Each chief investigator was tasked to the project at either half a day or one 
                   day per week, with research assistants on short-term part-time contracts. They provided five primary sources of cultural data across 
                   five different artistic fields, many of which developed from ARC investment in research and/or database construction, as follows:
                </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>AusStage: The Australian Live Performance Database 
                      (<ref target="https://www.ausstage.edu.au/">https://www.ausstage.edu.au/</ref>). Funded by seven ARC LIEF grants, 
                      AusStage centres on events of live performance (more than 133,000 at the time of writing), linked to the 
                      contributors, works, venues, and organisations involved. AusStage is now one of the largest databases of performing 
                      arts in the world. AusStage is headquartered at <name>Flinders University</name>, which provided one chief 
                      investigator to the ACD-Engine project as well as local support staff.
                    </item>
                    <item>Circus Oz Living Archive 
                      (<ref target="https://circusozlivingarchive.com/">https://circusozlivingarchive.com/</ref>). Funded initially by an ARC LIEF 
                      grant, it houses archival footage from decades of Circus Oz performances, densely tagged to delineate acts, skills, 
                      and performers. Each event is also indexed through AusStage. The Circus Oz Living Archive originated at 
                      <name>RMIT</name>, which provided one chief investigator.
                    </item>
                    <item>Digital Archive of Queensland Architecture (DAQA) 
                      (<ref target="https://qldarch.net/">https://qldarch.net/</ref>). Developing from an ARC Discovery Project on modernist 
                      architecture, this database centres on oral histories, connected with pages for architects, architectural firms, building 
                      projects, and published articles. DAQA is headquartered at the <name>University of Queensland</name>, which provided 
                      two chief investigators and hosted one research assistant.</item>
                    <item>Design and Art Australia Online (DAAO) 
                      (<ref target="https://www.daao.org.au/">https://www.daao.org.au/</ref>). Initially designed as a digital repository for several 
                      print-based biographical dictionaries of Australian artists, the DAAO has been funded by several ARC LIEF grants. 
                      The database centres on more than 17,000 artist biographies,<note>For a full report on the data scope of each database, see 
                      <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_DataReport.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_DataReport.html</ref>.</note> 
                      with associated artistic works, events, recognitions, art collections, and groups such as awarding bodies, galleries, and artist 
                      collectives. DAAO is hosted by the <name>University of New South Wales</name>, which provided two chief 
                      investigators and hosted one research assistant.</item>
                    <item>The Summerhayes Collection at the <name>Curtin University Library</name> 
                      (<ref target="https://www.curtin.edu.au/library/collections/special-collections/architecture/">https://www.curtin.edu.au/library/collections/special-collections/architecture/</ref>). 
                      This archival collection includes mainly architectural drawings from the West Australian Summerhayes architectural 
                      firm, described with library metadata. <name>Curtin University</name> provided two chief investigators and hosted one research 
                      assistant.</item>
                  </list>
                <p>Each database presented distinctive opportunities to interrogate prior assumptions about data entry, coding protocols, and 
                   relationality. Taken together, they provided a manageable volume of data for an integrated information architecture to emerge. This 
                   under-the-hood approach, secured by the generous commitment of partners to the exploration of their existing databases, facilitated 
                   an iterative knowledge-sharing approach between data engineers, subject domain experts, and digital humanities scholars.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>Project Partners (Analysis and Policy) and Advisory Board </head>
                <p>Our partner institutions also included teams at <name>Swinburne University</name>'s Data Co-Op (one chief investigator), 
                   specialising in government data analysis, and the Time-Layered Cultural Map of Australia (TLC Map) 
                   (<ref target="https://tlcmap.org/">https://tlcmap.org/</ref>, see <ptr target="#arthur_et_al_2020"/>, one chief investigator), which 
                   provided a platform for geospatial analysis and detailed interrogation of demographic contexts. Researchers from the Social Change 
                   Impact Enabling Platform at <name>RMIT University</name> and the King's Digital Lab and Department of Digital Humanities at 
                   <name>King's College London</name> (one chief investigator each, along with supporting local staff), provided 
                   understanding of and alignment with national and global infrastructure priorities, as well as connections to user groups in 
                   <name>Australia</name> and the <name>UK</name>. The ACD-Engine was also supported by an international advisory board comprised of 
                   researchers and infrastructure specialists from the <name>University of Melbourne</name>, <name>Flinders University</name>, the 
                   <name>National University of Singapore</name>, the <name>University of Ghent</name>, and the Victorian government's Centre for Data 
                   Insights, which met approximately three times a year across the project to provide strategic advice and oversight.
                </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program A.3: Open Data Sharing</head>
            <p>With its emphasis on the active construction and investigation of a shared cultural data framework or model, this project sits 
               alongside major initiatives that support open data in research. Before beginning technical work, we needed to agree on how to share data 
               between the project partners and the ACD-Engine central team as well as how to attribute authorship to individual and co-authored 
               datasets and data-informed publications. A central concern was achieving a balance between energising new research by working across 
               multiple data sources and making raw data available for wider users, while also honouring the intellectual labour embedded in and the 
               ongoing development of each partner database. Each partner database was built on unique data that had been collected by domain experts 
               and, as such, carried within it their labour, both conceptual and quotidian (who among us has not dedicated extraordinary amounts of 
               time to transcribing, annotating, and generating metadata!). Conversely, since each database was at least partially funded by national 
               research agencies and often supplemented by volunteer contributors, the data was in a sense already public and designed to be shared 
               with arts and humanities researchers as well as the public at large. Therefore, much like other data aggregation and interdisciplinary 
               projects, the ACD-Engine faced both the potentials and pitfalls of sharing data <ptr target="#smithies_millar_thomson_2015"/> 
               <ptr target="#millar_et_al_2018"/>.
            </p>
            <p>With these concerns in mind, we sought to develop a data-sharing agreement that outlined a pipeline for recognition of contributors to 
               ACD-Engine datasets and collaborative papers, as well as a model for citation of data sources, that would adhere to recently released 
               recommendations from the Australian Research Council for authorship of collaborative publications. After surveying the existing 
               literature and participating in an Australian Research Data Commons laboratory on this topic, it became clear that most projects share 
               general principles, but there was no well-established data sharing policy standard that would meet our needs. Our final data sharing 
               policy, one component of which is represented in the visual summary below, has enabled us to rapidly determine responsibilities for work 
               outputs and to appropriately assign authorship and acknowledge additional contributors.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
              <head>Extract from ACD-Engine Data Sharing Agreement Diagram pertaining to datasets.</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Following these paths in an open data landscape, the work of different kinds of contributors is made explicit, including work by 
               volunteers who undertake substantial amounts of data entry, software engineers who clean and sort data into usable subsets, and those 
               who provide domain expertise in the organisation of a data output. This method of distributed attribution for the collective authors of 
               an open data artefact will inevitably shape the national arts and humanities research environment, facilitating greater recognition of 
               the intellectual work undertaken at different stages of cultural data projects by diverse contributors (for the full data sharing 
               agreement, see 
              <ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/policy-ethics-governance">https://www.acd-engine.org/policy-ethics-governance</ref>).
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program B: Technical Design and Methods</head>
            <p>To combine and harmonize data from multiple sources, formats, and structures into a single, unified framework, the ACD-Engine was 
               informed by the long-standing technical data warehousing approach pursued in many fields of the sciences 
               (see <ref target="https://www.ibm.com/topics/etl">https://www.ibm.com/topics/etl</ref>). For the humanities in <name>Australia</name>, 
               this approach is relatively nascent, with the possible exception of PARADISEC 
               (<ref target="https://www.paradisec.org.au/">https://www.paradisec.org.au/</ref>), a consortium of language collections with a platform 
               that warehouses a wide range of data inputs and outputs and provides tools to analyse across their content.
            </p>
            <p>Work to enable the interoperability of digital collections in the arts and humanities is long-standing, initially based in the domain of 
               digital libraries. The OAI-PMH protocol, one of the most widely deployed technologies for digital library interoperability aimed to 
               provide a very simple method for harvesting data from primarily digital libraries, but it has several key shortcomings 
               <ptr target="#van_de_sompel_et_al_2004"/>. As <name>Carl Lagoze</name> points out, OAI-PMH is <quote rend="inline">based on the premise 
               that discovery occurs within the boundaries of the digital library</quote>, thus <quote rend="inline">relying on a technology distinct 
               from that in the mainstream web architecture</quote>. OAI-PMH also presupposes that <quote rend="inline">structured metadata</quote> are 
               <quote rend="inline">necessary and fundamental to a digital library environment, and that the Dublin Core vocabulary is the key to 
               <quote rend="inline">semantic</quote> interoperability</quote> <ptr target="#lagoze_2010" loc="216"/>. The tangible effect of these 
               limitations is the prioritization of simplicity and efficiency at the cost of functionality and robustness, as well as limited ability 
               to implement feedback mechanisms to correct unusable or poor-quality data.
            </p>
            <p>Two core aims of the ACD-Engine were to improve the quality of cultural data and better support the interoperability of cultural data 
               across new disciplinary bridges and in new contexts outside the traditional institutional repository domain. Our technique diverges from 
               OAI-PMH in several ways. First, our approach is dynamic real-time access, working in real time rather than on harvested, static data, 
               using a method similar to the more sophisticated Z39.50 protocol <ptr target="#lynch_1997"/>. Second, the access module for each 
               collection normalises the format of data items, which again OAI-PMH does not require but Z39.50 does. Neither difference, however, 
               addresses the problems of data quality that pervade many collections accessible via OAI-PMH <ptr target="#warwick_et_al_2009"/>. The 
               ACD-Engine's current access modules can be set to discount incomplete (meta-)data, and we anticipate that future iterations of the 
               ACD-Engine platform will provide feedback mechanisms for data quality, in line with emerging best practice in digital library 
               infrastructures.
            </p>
            <p>Our approach to data management, while not unique, is pioneering in its application to Australian artistic and cultural data. 
               Furthermore, our approach provides an exemplar for undertaking future projects in this field:
            </p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item><hi rend="bold">Extracting</hi> encoded digital data from a range of separate, heterogeneous sources using APIs and various forms 
                  of web scraping in collaboration with project partners;</item>
                <item><hi rend="bold">Identifying</hi> and <hi rend="bold">resolving</hi> inconsistencies, redundancies, errors, and gaps in the data, 
                  specifically where a datapoint definition (attribute) has specific meanings in one dataset that are incompatible with a like unit in 
                  another dataset, or where significant limitations exist in the coverage of available data;</item>
                <item>Structuring the data into a uniform architecture adapting recognised metadata schema relevant to the arts and humanities without 
                  flattening disciplinary distinctiveness;</item>
                <item><hi rend="bold">Augmenting</hi>, <hi rend="bold">expanding</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">enriching</hi> the data through a variety of 
                  methods including manual data entry (conducted by project partners and research assistants), data warehousing, and ETL (extract, 
                  transform, load) tools; and</item>
                <item>Transforming the data into machine-readable datasets that can be easily understood and deployed by end users.</item>
              </list>
            <p>We spent much of the first year of the project intensively investigating the contents and structures of our partner databases to 
               understand how their distinctive data attributes could be usefully extracted, processed, and enhanced by an integrated model. Working 
               across multiple, heterogeneous data sources, we faced the challenges of bespoke and discipline-specific metadata, varying levels of 
               accessibility, and distinct knowledge transfer capabilities, including custom-made and obsolete websites, APIs, and database backend 
               structures. We tackled these problems, to use <name>Tim Sherratt</name>'s terminology, by <quote rend="inline">digging down through 
               layers of technology, descriptive practice, and institutional history, to understand what is delivered so conveniently through our 
               browsers</quote> <ptr target="#sherratt_2019"/>. Respectful questioning of the relative weight to be given to a specific datapoint, or 
               how to identify the relationships between diverse concepts across multiple artistic disciplines, required close interrogation of the 
               databases as knowledge domains that have been shaped by the affordances of their specific information architecture, as well as detailed 
               consultation with discipline experts. Only through this exhaustive, iterative process, scrutinising data science methods in their 
               application to artistic research and vice versa, could we develop the depth of understanding necessary to build a robust and 
               intellectually sophisticated integrative architecture. Seeking to guide our diverse team through this process of investigation and 
               consultation, we gradually developed an easy-to-understand data integration workflow diagram (Figure 3).
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
              <head>ACD-Engine Architecture Construction Workflow.</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>As the project progressed, we added and trained skilled software engineers and data scientists to the team and hosted several research 
               students and interns who each helped to refine the technical competency of the model. Some members of the team investigated existing 
               data ontologies for Open-Linked Data to align the data attributes selected for the ACD-Engine with best practice models in the arts and 
               humanities <ptr target="#liu_mckay_buchanan_2023"/> <ptr target="#sumner_et_al_2023"/>. Others designed the components of the 
               ACD-Engine's architecture for cultural data (ACDEA) featuring core entities and key attributes <ptr target="#zheng_munoz_2023c"/>.  The 
               Data Transformation stage involved creating an aggregated data dictionary that explained the attributes and values for each data source, 
               as well as a data mapping plan that outlined how the information from different sources combined into the ACDEA.<note>For the full data 
               map, see 
               <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_Overview.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_Overview.html</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having extracted data from our partner databases, the ACD-Engine team then enriched selected subsets of the data. First, we asked the 
               discipline experts on our research team to enter new data for selected key attributes that had not been captured in the original 
               databases but would facilitate more robust analyses across the ACD-Engine unified datasets. In some cases, as much as 90% of a single 
               attribute was missing from a dataset. For instance, while career commencement dates and birth dates were commonly available in the 
               <q>People</q> entity, very few career end dates or death dates were listed.
            </p>
            <p>We also cleaned the data by identifying and correcting errors and inconsistencies. For example, due to the nature of integrating data 
               from multiple sources, similar records with minor variations often appeared in multiple places. It was crucial to identify and handle 
               duplicated records appropriately to avoid skewing analysis results. We used artificial intelligence and machine learning to accomplish 
               these tasks, but for the most part undertook deduplication with a mix of simple automation and manual correction. Future development of 
               AI in this space would be fruitful, particularly when working with larger volumes of data. Through this process, our data science team 
               shared insights with our data partners and experts, who engaged in a generative back-and-forth process around definitions, gaps, 
               opportunities, and limitations.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program C: ACD-Engine Architecture</head>
            <p>Qualitative data modelling is now indispensable to the creation of federated digital humanities databases 
               <ptr target="#rankin_gordon_potter_2009"/>. As we have shown, building the ACDEA required a close interrogation of the data models and 
               entities (or, in non-digital language, cultural concepts) that shaped the different cultural databases. A key finding was the extent to 
               which each database was structured around a meaningful yet discrete entity<note>Or, to use a humanities term, a disciplinary construct: a 
               definable object, actor, or location around which a relational database can be constructed.</note>: AusStage around events, DAAO around 
               artist biographies, DAQA around oral history interviews, and so on. Each database contained a wealth of front-facing data on people and
               organisations — indeed, both DAAO and AusStage contribute to the <q>People and Organisations</q> sub-platform in Trove, which also draws in 
               other collections such as the Australian Women's Register and the Encyclopaedia of Australian Science — but the level of information 
               and detail among these entities was markedly different across each database. We also found, on the other hand, that the public-facing 
               structure of each database to a degree obscured the richness of data entities and relationships that existed embedded in their systems. 
               DAQA, for instance, has front-end browse capacities for <quote rend="inline">Architects</quote> (people), 
               <quote rend="inline">Firms</quote> (organisations) and <quote rend="inline">Projects</quote> (works), but also contained substantial 
               information that aligned with the events and places that appeared in the front ends of DAAO and AusStage.
            </p>
            <p>A key aim for the ACDEA, therefore, was to ensure the people, organisations, works, and events entities across the databases were 
               interoperable, which necessitated a fixed, consistent set of minimum attributes. For the person entity, for example, which invites 
               biographical analysis, we recommend a minimum of first and last name, as well as date and place of birth and death. Inevitably, as 
               mentioned above, many of the people listed in our partner databases did not have all of these basic attributes; as appropriate, we 
               supplemented selected entries where new information was available (the <q>top 500</q> or <q>top 100</q>), and/or based our analyses on 
               the most complete entries <ptr target="#cutter_fensham_sumner_2023"/>. Similarly, the interrogation of arts organisations and their 
               histories required the collection of changing organisational names, establishment dates, and locations — again, assembling a baseline 
               of accurate data points was essential for comparative extraction and analysis. Each entity inevitably generated a range of connections 
               to other entities, which required their own set of attributes. Ultimately, we established standardised definitions and attributes for 
               eight entities: Person, Organisation, Work, Recognition, Place, Resource, and Relationship. Each unified ACDEA entity corresponded to 
               an entry atributed to a somewhat different name in our source datasets.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure04">
              <head>A simplified visualisation of the ACDEA, showing how differing entity titles are translated into our harmonised data structure. 
                White rectangles indicate that the database does not explicitly recognise the entity in question, but that information on this entity 
                is nonetheless available within. Circus Oz and Summerhayes are also italicised, being the only organisations in their respective 
                datasets.</head>   
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>   
            <div>
              <head>ACDEA Construction Principles</head>
                <p>We constructed the ACDEA based on the following principles <ptr target="#liu_mckay_buchanan_2023"/>:
                </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item><hi rend="bold">Refer to the Most Comprehensive Existing Data Models</hi>: For each entity's basic metadata requirements, we 
                      looked to the database with most comprehensive orientation towards that entity. For example, to construct its own 
                      <quote rend="inline">Person</quote> entity, ACDEA refers to the <quote rend="inline">person</quote> data model from 
                      DAAO, which is a person-oriented data collection, whereas AusStage has a comprehensive approach to 
                      <quote rend="inline">Event</quote> entity collection.</item>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">Keep Differences &amp; Unify Commonalities</hi>: Seeking then to integrate the central entity model with 
                      similar entities in the other datasets, ACDEA follows the principle of keeping differences between the data models that are 
                      significant and add value to the data, while integrating similar data attributes and unifying common elements to ensure 
                      consistency and usability. This approach helps to capture the unique characteristics of each data source and ensure that ACDEA 
                      includes all relevant information.</item>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">Fuzzy Mapping</hi>: This method involved mapping data attributes from each data source to a common attribute 
                      in the unified data model, even if they were not an exact match.<note>For a different context of interest, see 
                      <ref target="https://github.com/Living-with-machines/DeezyMatch">https://github.com/Living-with-machines/DeezyMatch</ref>.</note> 
                      For instance, the DAAO has an attribute called <quote rend="inline">other occupations</quote> and AusStage has an attribute 
                      called <quote rend="inline">(contributor) functions</quote>. These attributes can both be mapped to the 
                      <quote rend="inline">person</quote> entity in ACDEA, and a common attribute called  <quote rend="inline">career</quote>. Reading 
                      across these multiple elements of career allows ACDEA to capture as much information as possible while still maintaining 
                      consistency and usability.</item>
                  </list>
                <p>While remaining open to the inclusion of diverse or novel attributes, this model provided us with a view of the range and complexity 
                   of data from cultural databases across multiple disciplines, without diminishing the significance of each entity in disciplinary 
                   histories. Each of the terms we use for these entities, we argue, has a firm basis in existing cultural research methodologies and 
                   an intuitive, difficult-to-dispute accessibility. We arrived at these terms following extensive debates about the meaning of various 
                   concepts (for the results of one discussion, see <ptr target="#cutter_fensham_sumner_2023"/>). Simultaneously, this data ontology 
                   facilitates the potential future integration of datasets from other sources or search engines of specific interest to a research 
                   project, whether they might be from urban design, music, or the art market. Each entity in ACDEA contains three essential 
                   identifying metadata:
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Record data, including the original (database) ID, URL, associated entity name, timestamps, and other important details. This 
                    metadata is crucial in maintaining the integrity and traceability of the data back to its original source.</item>
                  <item>Content details of the record type, provided as description.</item>
                  <item>Related records which refer to the one-dimensional connections to other records within the same entity. This feature provides 
                    easier access to the relationship network of a particular record.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>ACDEA Entity Definitions</head>
                <p>To facilitate use of ACDEA, each entity has been described in a data dictionary <ptr target="#zheng_munoz_2023b"/> and detailed 
                   visualisation <ptr target="#zheng_munoz_2023c"/><note>For a general discussion of data dictionaries, see 
                   <ptr target="#data_dictionary_n.d."/>.</note> with a simplified version provided in the table below:
                </p>
                <table>
                  <head/>
                    <row role="label">
                      <cell role="label">Entities</cell>
                      <cell role="label">Attributes</cell>
                      <cell role="label">Description</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Person</hi>, representing individuals who are relevant to cultural data</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Names</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">All versions of the individual's name, including display name, primary name, and alternative names</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Summary</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The biography/descriptive summary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Gender</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Male, female, non-binary, unknown</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Birth</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The date and place of birth</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Death</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The date and place of death</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Roles</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The roles an individual has held for an extended period of time, as defined by entry records</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Career</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Features of an individual's career (e.g., persons and organisations worked for/with, career start/end date)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Residences</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The places an individual has resided and the time period of their residence</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Nationality</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Identifying markers of nation</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Languages</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Identifying language groups</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Related entities</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">To link to all other entities in the architecture</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">National Library Archive ID</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The ID assigned by the <name>National Library of Australia</name> to an individual</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Organization</hi>, representing organizations that are relevant to the cultural data</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Names</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">All versions of the organization's name, including display name, primary name, and alternative names.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Description</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The biography/descriptive summary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Types</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The type of the organization</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Long Term Roles</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The roles that the organization has held for an extended period of time</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Locations</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The places where the organisation has been located</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Operation</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The features of the operation of the organisation, including periods and coverage</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Event</hi>, representing cultural events</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Title</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Description</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The brief description of the event</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Types</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">the type/genre of the events</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Time &amp; Place</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The specific date and location where the event took place</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Work</hi>, representing cultural works such as books, architecture, performance, art, etc.</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Titles</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">All titles of the work, including the primary title and alternative titles</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Summary</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The summary of the work</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Medium</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Unique to visual art and design</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Time &amp; Place</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The specific date and location where the work was created</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Recognition</hi>, representing awards or recognition received by individuals or organizations</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Title</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Title of the award</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Summary</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Descriptive summary of the award or recognition</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Types</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The types of the recognition</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Time &amp; Place</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The specific date and location where the recognition was granted</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Place</hi>, representing the geographic locations or facilities where the cultural events take 
                        place</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Names</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">All names of the location, including the primary name and alternative names</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Address</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The standardized physical address of the location, including country, state, suburb, street, and postcode</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Geo-Coordinates</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The geographic coordinates (latitude and longitude) of the locations</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Type</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The type of venue or building situated in a location</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Start &amp; End Date (Optional)</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The start and end date of a location, which is optional information for tracking the changes of a location with the 
                         type <q>venue</q> over time</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Resource</hi>, representing resources that are relevant to the cultural data, such as books, images, 
                         paintings, oral histories, video and audio files. The description details refer to the metadata schema used in the 
                         <name>National Library of Australia</name> and are more typically bibliographic</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Titles</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">All titles of the resource, including the primary title and alternative titles</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Description</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Descriptive summary of the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Type</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The type or genre of the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Authoring</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The author or creator of the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Source</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The source of the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Date</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The associated dates of the resource, such as created date, published date, etc.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Acquisition</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The method or process used to acquire the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Right</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The rights associated with the resource, such as copyright or licensing information</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Format</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The format information of the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Identifier</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Rhe identifiers associated with the resource</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"><hi rend="bold">Relationship</hi>, representing the relationships between the various entities within the cultural data. 
                         The semantic structure plays a crucial role in establishing connections and dependencies between the other entities</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Subject</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The entity that initiates the relationship</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Object</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The entity that is related to the subject</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Predicate</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The type of relationship that exists between the subject and the object</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                      <cell style="width: 33%"/>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">Time</cell>
                      <cell style="width: 33%">The time period during which the relationship between the subject and the object existed</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Some of the attributes listed above represent discrete attributes, while others (such as <quote rend="inline">career</quote> under 
                   <quote rend="inline">person</quote>) provide an entry point to further nested data attributes. In addition, the bottom-up 
                   construction of the ACDEA ensures that all relevant attributes from the originating data sources are included (even though some 
                   attributes do not map across all datasets) without losing sight of larger questions of scale, sustainability, and interoperability 
                   with other national and international collections.
                </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Program D: Data Enrichment and Project Outputs</head>
            <p>Developing from our work in data exploration and enrichment, the ACD-Engine set out to interrogate and test the interoperability of a 
               range of cultural databases for use of cultural data in new analytic contexts. These included but were not limited to scholarly 
               research, data analytics and public interest, statistical experimentation, and national infrastructure strategy and policy.
            </p>
            <p>In order to demonstrate the value of data analytics and speak to live debates in cultural scholarship that would engage researchers, we 
               began our analytical program by investigating four themes: Working in the Arts: Women, Careers, and Creativity; Cultural Hotspots and 
               Local Scenes; Cultural Diffusion and Arts Diplomacy; and Environmental Politics and the Arts. Each theme aligned with the high-level 
               entities of our information architecture for the purposes of data extraction and analysis: for instance, questions about gender and 
               careers were to be answered through interrogation of the <quote rend="inline">People</quote> entity of the ACDEA.  The first two themes 
               in particular became fruitful sites for data experimentation, guided by specific research questions raised by our domain experts. The 
               core team of data scientists transformed data throughout this process by producing data <q>experiments</q> that examined the robustness 
               of specific data attributes within each dataset and showcasing them to research partners, who provided feedback and drove further 
               investigation.
            </p>
            <div>
              <head>Key Project Outputs</head>
                <p>The results are showcased in a number of tangible, open-access outputs, including but not limited to:
                </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>The ACD-Engine Cultural Data Workbook. This public-facing Jupyter notebook <ptr target="#zheng_munoz_2023a"/>, freely 
                      available through GitHub, provides new users in research, industry, and government with the framework to re-examine our data 
                      outputs and to identify further information required to use ACD-Engine data effectively. It also showcases a range of bespoke 
                      analytics on ACD-Engine datasets 
                      (<ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/about.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/about.html</ref>), a 
                      prototype geotemporal map of our datasets 
                      (<ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_ACDE_Map.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_ACDE_Map.html</ref>), 
                      intersections with IMDB and AustLit 
                      (<ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_ExternalDatasets.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_ExternalDatasets.html</ref>), 
                      and an exploration of <name>Melbourne</name>'s evolving music scenes using setlist.fm, Discogs, and Spotify data 
                      (<ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_TLC_Workshop.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_TLC_Workshop.html</ref>).</item>
                    <item>Seven ACD-Engine Unified Datasets (Event, Organisation, Person, Place, Recognition, Resource, Work) using data from 
                      AusStage, Circus Oz, DAAO, DAQA, and the Summerhayes Collection) 
                      (<ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets">https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets</ref>).</item>
                    <item>Six Data Dictionaries (ACD-Engine Unified, AusStage, Circus Oz, DAAO, DAQA, and Summerhayes Collection) explaining the data 
                      structures and column meanings for all metadata fields across each data source 
                      (<ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets">https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets</ref>).</item>
                    <item><title rend="quotes">ACD-Engine Data Entry Guidelines</title>, a basic guide to effectively and consistently entering data 
                      into cultural databases 
                      (<ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/policy-ethics-governance">https://www.acd-engine.org/policy-ethics-governance</ref>).</item>
                    <item><title rend="quotes">Mapping Cultural Data: The Basics</title>, a simple, easy-to-use guide to mapping cultural data 
                      (<ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/resources">https://www.acd-engine.org/resources</ref>).</item>
                    <item><title rend="quotes">Australian Cultural Data in Trove, VIAF and Wikidata</title>, a prototype tool developed in 
                      collaboration with historian and hacker <name>Tim Sherratt</name>, which highlights the extensive and largely unexplored 
                      connections between Australian cultural databases and global data aggregators 
                      (see <ref target="https://github.com/wragge/acd-engine">https://github.com/wragge/acd-engine</ref> and 
                      <ref target="https://acde-links-yajhxrvxsa-ts.a.run.app/acde-links">https://acde-links-yajhxrvxsa-ts.a.run.app/acde-links</ref>).</item>
                  </list>
              </div>
              <div>
                <head>Partner-Specific Outputs and New Research Directions</head>
                  <p>In the process, we undertook investigations into each partner database, leading to a number of new insights and directions for 
                     future research. Each data partner explains some of their key findings below:
                  </p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                      <item>DAAO/<name>University of New South Wales</name>
                        <list type="unordered">
                          <item>Interfacing with data scientists around the material captured by DAAO included undertaking new research to supplement 
                            information for 500 top artists (<title rend="quotes">DAAO 500</title>; see 
                            <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAAO500.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAAO500.html</ref>) 
                            and helped us understand the DAAO's strengths and limitations. One application has been a statistical exploration of 
                            gendered name changes and their impact on historical visibility of women and non-binary artists 
                            <ptr target="#sumner_et_al_2023"/> <ptr target="#cutter_fensham_sumner_2023"/>.</item>
                          <item>An analysis of data on visual arts events captured in DAAO enabled key features and trends in Australian cultural 
                            institutions to be identified quantitatively (e.g., the boom in cultural institutions, such as experimental art spaces, in 
                            the late 1980s) and analysed against known historic trends.</item>
                          <item>Looking across all the ACD-Engine's datasets helped us understand the interconnections (and duplications) of 
                            practitioners across different fields, offering insight into the well-known but little-analysed <q>portfolio career</q> in 
                            the arts. For example, <name>Elaine Haxton</name>, <name>Margaret Olley</name>, <name>Sidney Nolan</name>, 
                            <name>Frank Hinder</name>, and <name>George Gittoes</name> all worked in theatre (mainly stage design) as well as the 
                            visual arts, while <name>Sally Morgan</name> is both a visual artist and a writer. We intend to investigate these 
                            connections, as well as the <quote rend="inline">other occupations</quote> field in DAAO, to consider new research 
                            questions. For example, what is the cultural impact of artists/actors/performers working as schoolteachers?</item>
                        </list>
                      </item>
                      <item>AusStage/<name>Flinders University</name> and Circus Oz Living Archive/<name>RMIT University</name>
                        <list type="unordered">
                          <item>Collaborating on the <title rend="quotes">Data Dictionary</title> allowed the AusStage team to reconsider its data 
                            ontology, in particular redefining the category of <quote rend="inline">Event</quote> to standardise its use and to 
                            recognise that a single performance at one venue is different from a season. Factoring in duration and significance allows 
                            for future interoperability with other databases that hold <quote rend="inline">Event</quote> data.</item>
                          <item>Tracing gendered career pathways through the dataset 
                            (see <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_AusStage.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_AusStage.html</ref>) 
                            revealed data transcription errors in the gender field of <quote rend="inline">Contributor</quote> (in ACDEA, 
                            <quote rend="inline">Person</quote>) records, compounded by a default to <quote rend="inline">Male</quote> when adding a 
                            new <quote rend="inline">Contributor</quote>. The AusStage team developed a new gender policy, including a new 
                            <quote rend="inline">Non-Binary</quote> category that can be used in defined circumstances and a gender field that defaults 
                            to <quote rend="inline">Unknown</quote>.</item>
                          <item>We prepared an <title rend="quotes">AusStage 250</title> (a dataset of 250 top performing arts practitioners analogous 
                            to the <title rend="quotes">DAAO 500</title>), which was enriched with basic biographical data, including dates and places 
                            of birth and death, as well as person attributes not ordinarily captured in the AusStage database. This process focussed 
                            attention on how community data entry shapes what is recorded in cultural databases. Some of the best documented 
                            <quote rend="inline">Contributors</quote> were recognised not because of their general significance, but because particular 
                            AusStage authors were interested in supplementing their entries.</item>
                          <item>We also undertook a focused investigation of the Circus Living Archive and enriched AusStage data relating to 
                            Circus Oz, some results of which can be found here: 
                            <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_CircusOz.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_CircusOz.html</ref>.</item>
                        </list>
                      </item>
                      <item>DAQA/<name>University of Queensland</name>
                        <list type="unordered">
                          <item>While recording the achievements of women architects was an aim of the original DAQA research project, the original 
                            database lacked gender metadata. By adding this attribute, a key facet of <quote rend="inline">People</quote> profiles 
                            across the other ACD-Engine datasets, we were able to investigate the proportions of women practicing architecture in 
                            <name>Queensland</name>, which firms employed women, and when and where historical shifts in participation and employment 
                            occurred. This also allowed us to consider the relationship to gender balance in the visual arts and design through 
                            comparisons with DAAO.</item>
                          <item>ACDEA enabled uses of DAQA that had not been envisaged in its design 
                            (see <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAQA_Part1.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAQA_Part1.html</ref> and 
                            <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAQA_Part2.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Analysis_DAQA_Part2.html</ref>). 
                            While DAQA recorded the names of architectural firms (in ACDEA, <quote rend="inline">Organisations</quote>) and their predecessors, 
                            the ACD-Engine's work enabled us to visually model and analyse the multiple progenitors and successors of key firms. By examining the 
                            top five longest lineages of firms in <name>Queensland</name> we gained a new understanding of the social and commercial structures of 
                            architectural cultures throughout the twentieth century.</item>
                        </list>
                      </item>
                      <item>Summerhayes Collection/<name>Curtin University</name>
                        <list type="unordered">
                          <item>The team at <name>Curtin</name> generated a 360-degree panorama tour of the <name>Subiaco Hotel</name> in <name>Perth</name>, 
                            Western <name>Australia</name>, in order to investigate the potential of open linked data and panoramic tours to enhance the localised 
                            and contextual comprehension, virtual exploration, and spatial perception of architectural heritage locations. The 
                            <name>Subiaco Hotel</name> was chosen because the Summerhayes architecture collection documents its architectural history and repeated 
                            renovation by the <name>Summerhayes</name> family firm, and because it is linked with other architectural datasets that were being 
                            integrated into the ACDEA.</item>
                          <item>This project revealed that when flexible, robust, and relational metadata is produced, exploration of datasets across national 
                            collections becomes feasible. By creating linked open datasets of varying media, the 360-panorama can enrich cultural heritage 
                            datasets. This allows for researchers as well as visitors to experience immersive, content-rich panoramic tours 
                            <ptr target="#rahaman_champion_mcmeekin_2023"/>.</item>
                        </list>
                      </item>
                      <item>Time-Layered Cultural Map/<name>University of Newcastle</name>
                        <list type="unordered">
                          <item>Funding from the ACD-Engine allowed us to build a new function in TLCMap to combine map layers in a single map while preserving 
                            the structure of the components. With this new capability, TLCMap users can create a <quote rend="inline">Multilayer</quote> and see 
                            how patterns in a new layer fit with patterns in existing layers, or they can divide a new layer into multiple components to see how 
                            categories interact. One example of this functionality is a timeline map of Aboriginal Protection and Welfare Board sites in NSW 
                            overlaid with a historical map of railway stations, which reveals a correlation between the development of rail transport and the 
                            treatment of Aboriginal people in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.</item>
                          <item>TLCMap also benefited from engagement with the ACD-Engine through a deeper understanding of data models. Individual 
                            <quote rend="inline">Person</quote> entries were difficult to map on TLCMap since they require recognition of why place of 
                            birth or death — the most common mappable attributes — might be significant in artistic career paths, as a component of a 
                            larger cultural phenomenon with more self-evident geolocations. TLCMap now benefits from access to the ACD-Engine's unified 
                            data structure (ACDEA) and datasets, with unlimited potential for map layers to be created from the newly curated data, and 
                            also from the lived experience of structuring rich but loose cultural and historical materials on secure foundations and 
                            sound principles.</item>
                        </list>
                      </item>
                    </list>
                  <p>As this showcase highlights, with the capability of the ACD-Engine's robust datasets and outputs now readily available, members of 
                     the project team have begun to explore a range of novel use-cases for data analysis, particularly where data interrogation might 
                     be placed alongside scholarly and topical debates, or interfaced with other smaller datasets that invite new understandings of 
                     digital cultural heritage. Further applications might include:
                  </p>
                  <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Open linked data annotation of digital models (e.g., reconciling entities with national and international data repositories 
                      such as Trove, Wikidata, International Standard Name Identifier, or the Virtual International Authority File<note>For a 
                      proof-of-concept tool showcasing some potential connections between entities in our databases with Trove, Wikidata, and the 
                      Virtual International Authority File, built in collaboration with <name>Tim Sherratt</name>, see 
                      <ref target="https://github.com/wragge/acd-engine">https://github.com/wragge/acd-engine</ref>.</note>)</item>
                    <item>Bulk data fetching across different data sources</item>
                    <item>Multilayer spatial visualisation</item>
                    <item>Text-mining functionalities</item>
                    <item>Multilayer network analysis</item>
                    <item>Extension of data queries to national and international collections</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>We further anticipate that the datasets will now be used in data analytics pedagogy in the digital humanities, information 
                     science, and digital collections. Data scientists and graduate researchers could also experiment with the data coding and models 
                     in their own research.
                  </p>
              </div>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Key Project Innovations</head>
              <p>In summary, the ACD-Engine has made a distinctive and timely contribution to a complex and evolving national data ecosystem. In the 
                 two years designated for the project, a diverse range of intellectual, technical, and infrastructural advancements were made which 
                 addressed our original project aims. These include but are not limited to:
              </p>
              <p>Aim 1: Improve the quality of existing cultural data in <name>Australia</name> across a range of partner databases and cultural 
                 disciplines.
              </p>
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>Undertook unprecedented and comprehensive investigation of databases: collecting histories, shortcomings, funding histories, and 
                  workforce constraints;</item>
                <item>Definitively established the coding logics, disciplinarity distinctives, and sensitivities and vulnerabilities of specialist 
                  collections as well as their software capabilities;</item>
                <item>Mapped and synthesised data ontologies critical to specific categories of cultural data across a range of fields, including 
                  history, cultural studies, literature, and art and design history; and</item>
                <item>Undertook systematic analyses of core categories of cultural data and documentation, identified the challenges for interpretation 
                  of cultural data, such as changing social norms (e.g., naming conventions, gender differences, career pathways, and organisational 
                  locations), and promoted solutions for localised aggregation methods.</item>
              </list>
              <p>Aim 2: Support an expansion in the accessibility, use, and interoperability of cultural data in research, industry, and government 
                contexts.</p>
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>Built a sophisticated and integrated Research Software Engineering (RSE) team for wrangling, structuring, and interrogating large 
                  scale datasets;</item>
                <item>Produced an interoperable data model (ACDEA) for linking and interpreting arts and cultural data between different systems and 
                  platforms;</item>
                <item>Tested the suitability of ACDEA for interoperability with international cyber-infrastructures;</item>
                <item>Delivered robust, cultural datasets suitable for re-use and further testing with a range of research tools and platforms; 
                  and</item>
                <item>Produced dynamic visualisations and critical case studies exploring key research questions in arts and culture.</item>
              </list>
              <p>Aim 3: Demonstrate how new insights into arts and cultural production can emerge by improving cultural data interoperability across 
                 platforms, systems, and regions.
              </p>
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>Developed a novel policy framework for data-sharing, in line with open access principles, for the attribution of data-led 
                  research in the humanities; and</item>
                <item>Promoted innovative and multidisciplinary ways of working across cultural collections, including topical analysis featured in 
                  public media outlets.<note>Several public-facing outputs of the Engine's work in this space include 
                  <ptr target="#sumner_fensham_2023"/> and <ptr target="#sumner_munoz_2023"/>. The ACD-Engine also contributed to a topical analysis 
                  of <name>Australia</name>'s prestigious Archibald Prize in collaboration with the <title rend="italic">Guardian</title> data 
                  journalism team <ptr target="#nicholas_touma_2023"/>.</note>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>These ACD-Engine outcomes lay significant groundwork for the future development of a national data architecture for Australian 
                 cultural collections. The prototype information architecture, knowledge base, and RSE capabilities developed by the ACD-Engine pave 
                 the way for future work on Australian cultural data, including record unification (harmonising duplicated records, predicates in 
                 relationships, and place records across multiple data sources), identifying more implicit data, integrating Australian cultural data 
                 with more data sources, and consideration of persistent identifiers for <quote rend="inline">Person</quote> records across national 
                 collections.
              </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Discussion and Conclusion</head>
              <p>National cultural collections continue to grow in significance as investment at government and inter-governmental levels extends  
                 expectations of greater utilisation of public resources. Greater integration should not, however, diminish the important role that 
                 distinctive databases and curated collections have to their source communities and disciplinary experts. Given the volume and 
                 complexity of cultural data in national collections, dissolving barriers between one collection and another, as this project has 
                 identified, requires careful understanding of how cultural data might be organised beyond each collection.
              </p>
              <p>If the goal of national collections involves expanding and enhancing (trans)-national data resources, we would assert that more 
                 priority should be given to developing robust information architectures. As we have found, cultural data sharing and interoperability 
                 is rich terrain for the digital humanities and will be more so as new cyber-infrastructures, including artificial intelligence, 
                 transform the ways we engage with, reflect upon, and utilise cultural data. If we are to grow research impact and public engagement, 
                 national collection projects ought to strenuously pursue best-practice data-sharing approaches, particularly responsible attribution, 
                 documentation, and data contextualisation by collection owners <ptr target="#loukissas_2019"/> <ptr target="#lee_2023"/> 
                 <ptr target="#alkemade_et_al_2023"/>. Without so doing, we risk developing an array of increasingly disparate data structures and 
                 infrastructures that will inhibit both disciplinary and interdisciplinary research. The intensive (and unavoidably expensive) 
                 investment of human labour and expertise is critical in this process to safeguard database quality and disciplinary distinctiveness 
                 against the oversimplification too often wrought by external metadata structures, especially as they are increasingly implemented by 
                 machines.
              </p>
              <p>In this context, the challenges we face for future research in this space are principally structural. Research infrastructure for the 
                 Australian arts and humanities is maturing, but national and university-based funding remains largely tied to short-term projects like 
                 the ACD-Engine, rather than medium- or long-term workforce and infrastructure development. As longer term strategies slowly emerge, 
                 researchers (particularly those early in their careers) will continue to repeatedly enter and exit the field as they pursue employment 
                 and funding, making it difficult to build a consistent approach to infrastructure development for cultural data research. The 
                 ACD-Engine's exploratory work has already seeded new investment and opportunities for further research collaboration that recognises 
                 the central role of data curation and aggregation in cultural collections to further re-use, as well as knowledge exchange across 
                 industries, universities, and governments.
              </p>
              <p>Considering the future use of the ACD-Engine within the Australian and international cultural data landscape, a number of possible 
                 scenarios present themselves. Though the ACDEA is based around text and metadata, the process through which it was developed could be 
                 fruitfully applied to other digitalised media (images, film, audio recordings, digital modelling). The ACD-Engine's federated model, 
                 in which nodes of disciplinary expertise and data collections interface with a central hub of data science, information science, and 
                 digital humanities experts, could facilitate ongoing partnerships across disciplines to further demonstrate the utility and analytical 
                 power of working across multiple collections in historical analysis of cultural production. Future funding applications might focus on 
                 the testing and application of software tools (artificial intelligence, machine learning, 3D/4D modelling, immersive VR) in the 
                 enhancement and analysis of Australian cultural data, or on new collaborative projects between researchers, industries, and 
                 governments to explore the quality of insights available from cultural data. At the same time, we hope that funders will invest in 
                 maintaining and improving <name>Australia</name>'s ecosystem of cultural databases, many of which rest principally on the 
                 custodianship of individual researchers and the current goodwill of university- or community-based hosting providers. This project 
                 shows the potential of these databases, the necessity of human labour to extract and interpret it, and how much may be lost should 
                 these databases disappear.
              </p>
              <p>In this critical moment where automation is rapidly pervading the arts and cultural space, we both welcome the utopian possibilities 
                 and caution against a dystopian erosion of the contexts, histories, and community values embedded in digital cultural heritage. The 
                 ACD-Engine represents a pragmatic, stress-tested, and feasible model for comparative data extraction and attribution towards future 
                 cultural and critical enquiry.
              </p>
          </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ahnert_et_al_2023" label="Ahnert et al. 2023">Ahnert, R. et al. (2023) <title rend="italic">Collaborative historical research 
             in the age of big data</title>. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="alkemade_et_al_2023" label="Alkemade et al. 2023">Alkemade, H. et al. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Datasheets for digital 
             cultural heritage datasets</title>, <title rend="italic">Zenodo</title>, 25 September. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8375034">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8375034</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="arthur_2014" label="Arthur 2014">Arthur, P.L. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Biographical dictionaries in the digital era</title>, 
             in Arthur, P.L. and Bode, K. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Advancing digital humanities: Research, methods, theory</title>. New York: 
             Palgrave Macmillan, pp. 83-92.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="arthur_et_al_2020" label="Arthur et al. 2020">Arthur, P.L. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Time-layered cultural map of 
             Australia</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the fifth annual digital humanities in the Nordic countries conference, 
             2020</title>. Riga, Latvia, 21-23 October. CEUR, pp. 184-191. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/11541.2/143150">https://hdl.handle.net/11541.2/143150</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="australian_government_2023" label="Australian Government 2023">Australian Government Department of Infrastructure, Transport, 
             Regional Development, Communications and the Arts (2023) <title rend="italic">National cultural policy: Revive: A place for every story, 
             a story for every place</title>. 9 February. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.arts.gov.au/publications/national-cultural-policy-revive-place-every-story-story-every-place">https://www.arts.gov.au/publications/national-cultural-policy-revive-place-every-story-story-every-place</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bettivia_stainforth_2017" label="Bettivia and Stainforth 2017">Bettivia, R.S. and Stainforth, E. (2017) 
             <title rend="quotes">All and each: A socio-technical review of the Europeana project</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 
             Quarterly</title>, 11(3).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="borgman_2007" label="Borgman 2007">Borgman, C. (2007) <title rend="italic">Scholarship in the digital age: Information, 
             infrastructure, and the internet</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burrows_2011" label="Burrows 2011">Burrows, T. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Sharing humanities data for e-research: Conceptual 
             and technical issues</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the sustainable data from digital research conference, 2011</title>. 
             Melbourne, Australia, 12-14 December. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://ses.library.usyd.edu.au/handle/2123/7938">https://ses.library.usyd.edu.au/handle/2123/7938</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burrows_2013" label="Burrows 2013">Burrows, T. (2013) <title rend="quotes">A data-centred <q>virtual laboratory</q> for the 
             humanities: Designing the Australian Networked Infrastructure (HuNI) service</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic 
             Computing</title>, 28(4), pp. 576-581. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt064">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt064</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burrows_verhoeven_2016" label="Burrows and Verhoeven 2016">Burrows, T. and Verhoeven, D. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Aggregating 
             data for social linking in the humanities and creative arts: The Humanities Networked Infrastructure (HuNI)</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ninth annual metadata and semantics research conference, 2015</title>. Manchester, England, 
             9-11 September. Springer Link, pp. 109-119. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24129-6_36">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24129-6_36</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cathro_collier_2020" label="Cathro and Collier 2020">Cathro, W. and Collier, S. (2020) <title rend="quotes"><q>Developing</q> 
             <title rend="italic">Trove</title>: The policy and technical challenges</title>, <title rend="italic">eLucidate</title>, 7(3), pp. 3-14. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.vala.org.au/vala2010/papers2010/VALA2010_127_Cathro_Final.pdf">https://www.vala.org.au/vala2010/papers2010/VALA2010_127_Cathro_Final.pdf</ref>.
.          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cutter_fensham_sumner_2023" label="Cutter, Fensham, and Sumner 2023">Cutter, N., Fensham, R., and Sumner, T.D. (2023) 
             <title rend="quotes">The slipperiness of name: Gender and biography in Australian cultural databases</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Gender &amp; History</title>, 2023. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1468-0424.12699">https://doi.org/10.1111/1468-0424.12699</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="data_dictionary_n.d." label="Data Dictionary, n.d."><title rend="quotes">Data Dictionary</title> (n.d.) 
            <title rend="italic">Science Direct</title>. Available at: 
            <ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/computer-science/data-dictionary">https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/computer-science/data-dictionary</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="desfray_raymond_2014" label="Desfray and Raymond 2014">Desfray, P. and Raymond, G. (2014) <title rend="italic">Modeling 
             enterprise architecture with TOGAF: A practical guide using UML and BPMN</title>. Cambridge, MA: Morgan Kaufmann.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="given_polkinghorne_cattlin_2023" label="Given, Polkinghorne, and Cattlin 2023">Given, L. M., Polkinghorne, S., and Cattlin, J. 
             (2023) <title rend="quotes">Structural elements and spheres of expertise: Creating a healthy ecosystem for cultural data 
             initiatives</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</title>, 2023. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24849">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24849</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hunter_et_al_2012" label="Hunter et al. 2012">Hunter, J. et al. (2012) <title rend="quotes">A Web 3.0 approach to building an 
             online digital archive of architectural practice in post-war Queensland</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the international 
             council on archives conference, 2012</title>. Brisbane, Australia, 20-24 August. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://ica2012.ica.org/files/pdf/Full%20papers%20upload/ica12Final00326.pdf">http://ica2012.ica.org/files/pdf/Full%20papers%20upload/ica12Final00326.pdf</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jones_piper_2023" label="Jones and Piper 2023">Jones, M. and Piper, A. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Digital history: State of the 
             field review essay</title>, <title rend="italic">Australian Historical Studies</title>, 55(1), pp. 178-203. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1031461X.2023.2267586">https://doi.org/10.1080/1031461X.2023.2267586</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jones_verhoeven_2022" label="Jones and Verhoeven 2022">Jones, M. and Verhoeven, D. (2022) <title rend="quotes"> Trove's 
             funding runs out in July 2023 – and the National Library is threatening to pull the plug. It's time for a radical overhauls</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">The Conversation</title>, 23 December. 
             <ref target="https://theconversation.com/troves-funding-runs-out-in-july-2023-and-the-national-library-is-threatening-to-pull-the-plug-its-time-for-a-radical-overhaul-197025">https://theconversation.com/troves-funding-runs-out-in-july-2023-and-the-national-library-is-threatening-to-pull-the-plug-its-time-for-a-radical-overhaul-197025</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lagoze_2010" label="Lagoze 2010">Lagoze, C.J. (2010) <title rend="italic">Lost identity: The assimilation of digital libraries 
             into the Web</title>. PhD thesis. Cornell University. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://carllagoze.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/carllagoze.pdf">https://carllagoze.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/carllagoze.pdf</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lee_2023" label="Lee 2023">Lee, B.C.G. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The <q>collections as ML data</q> checklist for machine 
             learning and cultural heritage</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information Science &amp; Technology</title>, 
             2023. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24765">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24765</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="liu_mckay_buchanan_2023" label="Liu, McKay, and Buchanan 2023">Liu, R., McKay, D., and Buchanan, G. 
             <title rend="quotes">Person-oriented ontologies analysis for digital humanities collections from a metadata crosswalk perspective</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 86th annual meeting of the association for information science &amp; technology, 2023</title>. 
             London, England, 27-31 October. RMIT University, pp. 255-266. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://researchrepository.rmit.edu.au/esploro/outputs/conferenceProceeding/Person-Oriented-Ontologies-Analysis-for-Digital-Humanities/9922290625501341">https://researchrepository.rmit.edu.au/esploro/outputs/conferenceProceeding/Person-Oriented-Ontologies-Analysis-for-Digital-Humanities/9922290625501341</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="loukissas_2019" label="Loukissas 2019">Loukissas, Y.A. (2019) <title rend="italic">All data are local: Thinking critically in a 
             data-driven society</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lynch_1997" label="Lynch 1997">Lynch, C.A. (1997) <title rend="quotes">The Z39.50 information retrieval standard</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title>, 3(4).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcgillivray_et_al_2020" label="McGillivray et al. 2020">McGillivray, B. et al. (2020) <title rend="italic">The challenges and 
             prospects of the intersection of humanities and data science: A white paper from the Alan Turing Institute</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.12732164">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.12732164</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="millar_et_al_2018" label="Millar et al. 2018">Millar, P. et al. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The challenge, the project, and the 
             politics: Lessons from six years of the UC CEISMIC Canterbury Earthquakes Digital Archive</title>, in Bouterey, S. adnd Marceau, L.E. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Crisis and disaster in Japan and New Zealand: Actors, victims, and ramifications</title>. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 
             pp. 159-179.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nicholas_touma_2023" label="Nicholas and Touma 2023">Nicholas, J. and Touma, R. (2023) <title rend="quotes">How to win the 
             Archibald prize: What 100 years of data tells us</title>, <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 5 May. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2023/may/05/how-to-win-the-archibald-prize-what-100-years-of-data-tells-us">https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2023/may/05/how-to-win-the-archibald-prize-what-100-years-of-data-tells-us</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rahaman_champion_mcmeekin_2023" label="Rahaman, Champion, and McMeekin 2023">Rahaman, H., Champion, E., and McMeekin, D. (2023) 
             <title rend="quotes">Outside inn: Exploring the heritage of a historic hotel through 360-panoramas</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Heritage</title>, 6(5), pp. 4380-4410. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/heritage6050232">https://doi.org/10.3390/heritage6050232</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rankin_gordon_potter_2009" label="Rankin, Gordon, and Potter 2009">Rankin, R., Gordon, M., and Potter, R. (2009) 
            <title rend="quotes">Implementing a federated data archive with asynchronous data query, gathering and analysis capabilities</title>, 
            <title rend="italic">AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</title>, 33(SM33B-1570).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ryan_et_al_2022" label="Ryan et al. 2022">Ryan, T. et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Codebooks</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Australian Cultural Data Engine</title>, June-November. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets">https://www.acd-engine.org/datasets</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sherratt_2019" label="Sherratt 2019">Sherratt, T. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Hacking heritage: Understanding the limits of 
             online access</title>, in Lewi, H. et al. (eds.) <title rend="italic">The Routledge international handbook of new digital practices in 
             galleries, libraries, archives, museums and heritage sites</title>. New York: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="smithies_2017" label="Smithies 2017">Smithies, J. (2017) <title rend="italic">The digital humanities and the digital 
             modern</title>. New York: Springer.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="smithies_et_al_2023" label="Smithies et al. 2023">Smithies, J. et al. (2023) <title rend="quotes">MaDiH (مديح): A transnational 
             approach to building digital cultural heritage capacity</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title>, 
             15(4), pp. 1-14. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3513261">https://doi.org/10.1145/3513261</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="smithies_millar_thomson_2015" label="Smithies, Millar, and Thomson 2015">Smithies, J., Millar, P., and Thomson, C. (2015) 
             <title rend="quotes">Open principles, open data: The design principles and architecture of the UC CEISMIC Canterbury Earthquakes Digital 
             Archive</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Japanese Association for Digital Humanities</title>, 1(1), pp. 10-36. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://ir.canterbury.ac.nz/items/1add02b2-49f2-49b7-8c22-261fa35f7d7d">https://ir.canterbury.ac.nz/items/1add02b2-49f2-49b7-8c22-261fa35f7d7d</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="stainforth_2019" label="Stainforth 2019">Stainforth, E. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Disruptive forms, persistent values: 
             Negotiating digital heritage and <q>the memory of the world</q></title>, in Carter, T. et al. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Creating 
             heritage: Unrecognised pasts and rejected futures</title>. New York: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sumner_fensham_2023" label="Sumner and Fensham 2023">Sumner, T.D. and Fensham, R. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The hidden stories 
             in Australian cultural data</title>, <title rend="italic">Pursuit</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://pursuit.unimelb.edu.au/articles/the-hidden-stories-in-australia-s-cultural-data">https://pursuit.unimelb.edu.au/articles/the-hidden-stories-in-australia-s-cultural-data</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sumner_munoz_2023" label="Sumner and Munoz 2023">Sumner, T.D. and Munoz, J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Gendered labour in the 
             Australian arts</title>, <title rend="italic">Pursuit</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://pursuit.unimelb.edu.au/articles/gendered-labour-in-the-australian-arts">https://pursuit.unimelb.edu.au/articles/gendered-labour-in-the-australian-arts</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sumner_et_al_2023" label="Sumner et al. 2023">Sumner, T.D. et al. (2023) <title rend="quotes">What's in a name? A cross-section 
             of biography, gender &amp; metadata in the <title rend="italic">Design &amp; Art Australia Online</title> database</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the twentieth international conference on Dublin Core and metadata applications, 2022</title>. 
             Virtual, 3-7 October. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://rest.neptune-prod.its.unimelb.edu.au/server/api/core/bitstreams/9cb75031-a202-4e98-9e7b-15ab8a5c6924/content">https://rest.neptune-prod.its.unimelb.edu.au/server/api/core/bitstreams/9cb75031-a202-4e98-9e7b-15ab8a5c6924/content</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ukri_2022" label="UKRI 2022">UK Research and Innovation (2022) <title rend="italic">Towards a national collection: Opening UK 
            heritage to the world</title>. Available at: 
            <ref target="https://www.librarydevelopment.group.shef.ac.uk/referencing/harvard.html">https://www.librarydevelopment.group.shef.ac.uk/referencing/harvard.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="van_de_sompel_et_al_2004" label="van de Sompel et al. 2004">van de Sompel, H. et al. (2004) <title rend="quotes">Resource 
             harvesting within the OAI-PMH framework</title>, <title rend="italic">D-lib Magazine</title>, 10(12). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.dlib.org/dlib/december04/vandesompel/12vandesompel.html">https://www.dlib.org/dlib/december04/vandesompel/12vandesompel.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="warwick_et_al_2009" label="Warwick et al. 2009">Warwick, C. et al. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Documentation and the users of 
             digital resources in the humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 65(1), pp. 33-57. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/00220410910926112">https://doi.org/10.1108/00220410910926112</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="whitelaw_2015" label="Whitelaw 2015">Whitelaw, M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Generous interfaces for digital cultural 
             collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9(1). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zheng_munoz_2023a" label="Zheng and Munoz 2023a">Zheng, I. and Munoz, J. (2023a) <title rend="quotes">Australian Cultural Data 
             Engine workbook</title>, GitHub. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/about.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/about.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zheng_munoz_2023b" label="Zheng and Munoz 2023b">Zheng, I. and Munoz, J. (2023b) <title rend="quotes">ACD-ENgine unified data 
             dictionary</title>, <title rend="italic">Australian Cultural Data Engine</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://acd-engine.org/datasets">https://acd-engine.org/datasets</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zheng_munoz_2023c" label="Zheng and Munoz 2023c">Zheng, I. and Munoz, J. (2023c) <title rend="quotes">Overview of the Australian 
             Cultural Data Engine architecture</title>, <title rend="italic">Australian Cultural Data Engine</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_Overview.html">https://acd-engine.github.io/jupyterbook/Integration_ACDEA_Overview.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>