<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Response to
						<title rend="quotes">The circus we deserve? A front row look at the
						organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital
						Humanities</title></title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>The Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations <dhq:family></dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation/>
					<email>email: adho@adho.org</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>The Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) is an umbrella organization whose goals are to promote and support digital research and teaching across arts and humanities disciplines, drawing together humanists engaged in digital and computer-assisted research, teaching, creation, dissemination, and beyond, in all areas reflected by its diverse membership. For more information, please visit <ref target="https://adho.org/">https://adho.org/</ref></p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000664</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000664/000664.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>The annual, international Digital Humanities conference is what originally
					brought ADHO (the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations) together.
					Many see it as a cornerstone of our collective identity which enables
					collaboration, networking, and the international dissemination of
					scholarship in the field. This response to <title rend="quotes">The circus we deserve? A front
					row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the
					Digital Humanities</title> by Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega,
					Melissa Terras, Deb Verhoeven and Glen Layne-Worthey engages with its call
					for ADHO to improve its processes and practices surrounding the DH
					conference by describing the work that has been done to date, and
					initiatives ADHO is now undertaking. </p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			
				<div>
					<head>Executive Summary </head>
					<p>We thank <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> for the opportunity to respond to this article, which is of
						vital importance to the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations
							(ADHO).<note>This response from ADHO was drafted by current ADHO
							Constituent Organisations Board (COB) President Susan Brown with
							COB members Quinn Dombrowski and COB President-Elect Christof
							Schöch. The draft was revised in consultation Diane Jakacki and
							Michael Sinatra as past and current chairs of the
							Conference Coordination Committee, by the COB as a whole, and by
							the members of the ADHO Executive Board. The response has been
							approved by the Constituent Organisations Board and the Executive
							Board.</note> The annual conference is what originally brought
						ADHO together, and many see it as a cornerstone of our collective
						identity which enables collaboration, networking, and the
						international dissemination of scholarship in the field.</p>
					<p>Many thanks to Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega, Melissa
						Terras, Deb Verhoeven, and Glen Layne-Worthey for taking the time to
						formulate their analysis and offer these insights and recommendations,
						drawing on their extensive service to ADHO, in particular as Program
						Chairs for several conferences between 2014 and 2020. ADHO has long
						grappled with the significant issues associated with <quote rend="inline">representation,
						diversity, multilingualism, and labor</quote> <ptr target="#estill2022" loc="Abstract"/> at the
						ADHO conferences, and we appreciate this contribution to the ongoing
						efforts to address them, particularly with respect to advancing
						equity, diversity, and inclusion. On behalf of the ADHO Constituent
						Organisations Board (COB), the Executive Board (EB), and the
						Conference Coordinating Committee (CCC),<note> The Constituent
							Organisations Board (COB) is composed of one representative from
							each of the Constituent Organisations (COs) and a liaison to the
							Special Interest Groups (SIGs). Its role is to establish and
							develop vision, strategy, and policy for ADHO. The Executive
							Board (EB) is appointed by the COB, and its role is to enact the
							decisions made by the COB, to administer the day-to-day running
							of the organization, and to ensure that ADHO abides by all
							applicable laws. The Conference Coordinating Committee is
							appointed by the COB and is responsible for developing, improving
							and maintaining the ADHO conference protocol and accompanying
							guidelines, and coordinating the annual conference. Individuals
							in these bodies change from year to year. The names of current
							officers can be accessed on the ADHO site at <ref
								target="https://adho.org/leadership/governance-structure/"
								>https://adho.org/leadership/governance-structure/</ref>.
							Article co-author Glen Layne-Worthey serves as current Chair of
							the ADHO Executive Board, and therefore occupied a dual role
							throughout the writing, editing, and early reception of this
							article. He notes that he did his best to operate with integrity
							and transparency in both roles, but he acknowledges occasional
							conflicts of interest, miscommunications, and unwelcome
							interventions on his part during the process.</note> we welcome the spur to greater transparency about the measures being taken by ADHO to address these problems, the opportunity to discuss some of the fundamental concerns raised here, and the contribution by the article to <quote rend="inline">an ongoing conversation that welcomes new voices and encourages
						reflection on our scholarly and community practices</quote> <ptr target="#estill2022" loc="§16"/>.</p>
					<p>In our response we take up the authors’ call for ADHO to improve its
						processes and practices surrounding the conference by describing the
						work that has been done to date, and initiatives we are now
						undertaking. The long ramp-up to each conference,<note> Due to the
							size and complexity of the conference, the call for bids and the
							selection of conference venues is made years in advance. For
							instance, the call for bids for DH2025 from the Conference
							Coordinating Committee has to go out by January 2023, and will be
							governed by the policy in place at the time the bid is announced,
							and any subsequent changes would have to be voluntarily adopted
							by the organizers. Financial planning is supposed to begin 30
							months prior to the conference. There will thus be at least a
							2.5-year lag in manifesting new policy related to the
							conference.</note> over the course of three years, has a time-warp effect as far
						as both policy and practices are concerned: there is a significant gap
						between the approval of new procedures and their effects. Major
						organizational changes and conference policy changes that provide the
						context for this response and the further work we hope to undertake
						are described in detail in the Appendix, respectively. </p>
					<p>We know and readily acknowledge that neither ADHO’s structures nor we
						who work within them are perfect, and that there will be failures and
						inconsistencies as there have been in the past. But we do hope to
						learn from them with humility, as well as to learn from other
						organizations similar in structure to ADHO such as <ref
							target="https://www.ifla.org/">IFLA (International Federation of
							Library Associations and Institutions)</ref>. This response
						certainly cannot address all of the concerns raised in the article,
						nor can it define a complete roadmap for the future; rather, we hope
						that it can be another element in a continuing process of dialogue and
						improvement. Based on the discussions spurred by this article as well
						as ADHO’s ongoing internal review processes, ADHO plans to undertake
						the following work, as described in greater depth in this
						response:</p>
					<list rend="bulleted">
						<item>Encouraging Constituent Organizations (COs) – i.e., the entities
							responsible for decision-making within ADHO – to negotiate those
							decisions in a manner that is reflective of the diversity across
							many potential axes (e.g. gender, ethnicity, language,
							institutional affiliation, etc.) within their
							organizations.</item>
						<item>Look to the recently-formed ADHO Intersectional Identities Task
							Force (IITF) as a resource and guide in navigating the
							sometimes-conflicting needs and priorities of Constituent
							Organizations as we continue to shape ADHO’s policies and
							practices.</item>
						<item>Undertake an ad-hoc ADHO Identity project to support a more
							open, clear discussion of how COs understand what ADHO is and
							does, and what we should prioritize, to which the role and
							purpose of the conference will undoubtedly be central. Unspoken
							differences in these perspectives have underpinned past
							conflicts, and being clearer about these issues will make it
							easier to identify a set of agreed-upon values that can serve as
							a guide when navigating decision-making.</item>
						<item>Work to develop new policies on data gathering, analytics, and
							data sharing related to the conference, beyond publishing
							abstracts, while at the same time fostering the community of
							additional volunteers needed to realize this policy when
							finalized.</item>
						<item>Re-evaluate ADHO’s reliance on volunteers for practically all of
							its work, both conference-related and otherwise, working with the
							new cohort of CO treasurers to reimagine how we distribute ADHO’s
							limited funding in a way that balances differences in cultural
							practices related to payment with the organization’s needs, in a
							manner that reflects a shared vision and values.</item>
						<item>Work with the IITF to re-evaluate a number of specific
							challenges related to the conference, including expanding the
								<ref target="https://adho.org/conference/code-of-conduct/"
									>Code of Conduct</ref> and introducing a conflict resolution process, and reviewing how multilingualism is addressed throughout the entire conference process while also broadening the policy on languages.</item>
					</list>
					<p>We recognize that much work remains to be done in reimagining the
						conference to better serve the DH community, and we are grateful to
						<title rend="italic">DHQ</title> to have this opportunity to share the work that has been done in
						recent years to begin addressing many of the issues raised in the
						article, even if the impact has not been felt yet. </p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Detailed Response<note> The larger context of how these matters
							relate to ADHO’s governance, which has been overhauled over the
							period covered by the article, and how the conference is managed,
							is outlined in the Appendix.</note>
					</head>
				
				<div>
					<head>Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, Representation, Multilingualism, and
						Accessibility</head>
					<p>ADHO is keen to address the lack of diversity evident in major missteps
						like the gender imbalance in the allocation of the 2014 bursaries as
						well as on the stage for the 2015 opening ceremonies, the latter of
						which took the shape they did despite gender parity (five women and
						four men) among <ref
							target="https://adho.org/leadership/past-officers/">CO
							representatives on the Steering Committee at the time</ref>.<note> Past Constituent Organisation
							representatives and ADHO officers are listed on the <ref
								target="https://adho.org/leadership/past-officers/">ADHO
								website</ref>.</note> Changes in policy and structure at the
						ADHO level can help to offset privilege and balance representation
						across multiple axes including gender, language, race, and
						nationality. A certain amount can and will be achieved through
						top-down change, such as by mandating diversity in local conference
						organizing committee membership and in choices of keynotes, but real
						transformation will require a culture change effected by an
						increasingly diverse complement of volunteers flowing into ADHO from
						the COs. </p>
					<p>ADHO is, fundamentally, an organization of organizations. Representation
						within ADHO is crucially and entirely dependent on its COs. Whom do
						the COs nominate for positions within ADHO? Do CO representatives
						express their own opinions on behalf of their organization, or do they
						engage their members on important issues and bring to ADHO a more
						nuanced, broadly-based view? The diversity of opinions within
						individual COs can be challenging in larger organizations; the
						decision of <ref target="https://dig-hum.de/">Digital Humanities im
							deutschsprachigen Raum (DHd)</ref> to apply to become an ADHO
						CO as an organization separate from EADH is one approach to addressing
						the situation, but other resolutions are possible. The nature of ADHO
						in its current instantiation – as an umbrella organization of
						organizations – has had a significant effect on its funding, its
						staffing, and its mission. Beyond the <ref
							target="https://adho.org/conference/">conference</ref>, <ref
							target="https://adho.org/awards/">awards</ref>, and <ref
							target="https://adho.org/leadership/infrastructure-committee/"
							>infrastructural services</ref>, there is little that <q>ADHO</q>
						itself does, other than through actions taken by COs. Improving
						representation in ADHO must, therefore, start with the COs – and such
						a shift in representation would have an impact on the organization at
						several levels and in many ways.</p>
					<p>ADHO’s Multi-Lingualism and Multi-Culturalism Committee (MLMC) could, in
						principle, be another mechanism for supporting representation at the
						ADHO level, but, once again, the historical requirements for its
						constitution (one member per CO) have impacted its priorities. It has
						historically focused more on the multilingual aspect of its name than
						the multicultural one, and despite frequent and passionate advocacy
						about linguistic matters, its most consistent visible contribution has
						been managing the translation of the CFP into the official languages
						of ADHO.<note> We recognize that the gap between the list of the
							official languages of ADHO and the languages used by members of
							ADHO’s COs has been growing larger for some time. Whether and how
							to address this gap is a matter that the COB will consider this
							year along with a review of how multilingualism is addressed in
							the Conference protocol; promotion of multilingualism is also a
							priority for the Intersectional Inclusion Task Force discussed
							more below. See <ref target="https://adho.org/inclusion/"
								>https://adho.org/inclusion/</ref>.</note> Efforts to expand
						the remit of the MLMC, in particular along the multicultural axis,
						have encountered friction on account of exactly that same
						multiculturalism. Diversity means different things to different people
						in different places at different times; there is no one size that fits
						all. As a result, ADHO’s recent public statements on political matters
						– the <ref
							target="https://adho.org/2020/07/14/adho-statement-on-black-lives-matter-structural-racism-and-establishment-violence/"
							>Statement on Black Lives Matter, Structural Racism, and
							Establishment Violence</ref>, and the <ref
							target="https://adho.org/2022/03/03/adho-statement-on-the-invasion-of-ukraine/"
							>Statement on the Invasion of Ukraine</ref> – took considerable
						time to finalize and receive approval because the COB had to negotiate
						significant regional and organizational differences, as well as
						reflect on ADHO’s own relationship to the matters the statements
						addressed. In the process, both statements changed markedly from their
						initial drafts, and the results may seem less satisfying to some than
						similar statements emitted by individual organizations with more
						convergent perspectives, yet the process of negotiation allowed the
						international DH community to take a joint public stand on these
						matters. There have been in the past conflicts around diversity that
						have had very unhappy outcomes, yet diversity has been established,
						including through use of the word in the conference themes for DH2012
						and DH2022 as well as community conferences, as a persistent priority
						within the DH community for more than a decade now, and continues to
						be pursued through other initiatives.</p>
					<p>Recognizing that the need for thoughtful consideration of diversity,
						equity, and inclusion go beyond the remit of any extant organizational
						structure, in 2021 ADHO put out a call for volunteers to serve on an
						anti-racist, anti-discriminatory task force, formed in 2022 as the
						Intersectional Inclusion Task Force (IITF).<note> See <ref
								target="https://adho.org/2021/12/02/call-for-volunteers-for-adho-anti-racism-task-force/"
								>https://adho.org/2021/12/02/call-for-volunteers-for-adho-anti-racism-task-force/</ref>;
								<ref
								target="https://adho.org/leadership/intersectional-inclusion-task-force/"
								>https://adho.org/leadership/intersectional-inclusion-task-force/</ref>
						</note> The group’s mandate is to advise and assist, with a focus on
						the impact of ADHO’s policies and activities on individuals, in
						organizational change to ensure that its governing bodies, events, and
						publications fully reflect the diversity of its Constitutent
						Organization members. IITF is also advising ADHO as we work to combat
						the inequalities and all forms of discrimination that exclude groups
						or individuals from academic endeavors. The IITF is composed both of
						individuals with a history of ADHO engagement and members of the
						broader digital humanities community. The IITF liaison has an open
						invitation to EB and COB meetings in a non-voting role. The work of
						the recently-formed ad-hoc ADHO Identity Project<note> See <ref
								target="https://adho.org/2022/10/20/a-new-adho-year-a-renewing-adho/"
								>https://adho.org/2022/10/20/a-new-adho-year-a-renewing-adho/</ref>.
						</note> will inform the work of the IITF by providing context of a
						shared understanding of what ADHO is and whom we serve. </p>
					<p>In this same spirit, we believe that for ADHO to <quote rend="inline">rethink the point of
						the conference through the perspective of diversity, equity, inclusion
						and decolonization</quote> <ptr target="#estill2022" loc="§5"/> as suggested by the article, we must first
						find common ground among the COs about the nature, priorities, and
						values of ADHO, and how the conference manifests (or should manifest)
						those priorities and values. Ideally, this common ground should draw
						from perspectives beyond exclusively those of the CO representatives,
						but ADHO has little leverage to ensure that COs engage with their
						members on these topics, beyond counting on their goodwill and buy-in
						and providing the necessary time for them to do so. Where the article
						lays out a set of dichotomies for the conference – <quote rend="inline">justice rather
						than merit, equity rather than innovation, polyvocality rather than
						canons, differences rather than standards, and inclusion rather than
						gatekeeping</quote> <ptr target="#estill2022" loc="§5"/> – we believe that framing these issues as binary
						choices whereby ADHO must pick a side is more likely to contribute to
						disagreements than foster a productive dialogue that is sensitive to
						the differences in cultures and priorities among the COs. We expect,
						however, that finding a common ground in articulating the nature,
						priorities, and values of ADHO will provide guidance to us for
						reevaluating many aspects of the conference and the organization
						overall, from refining criteria for accepting papers, to the choice of
						keynotes, to how much funding to allocate for labor vs. bursaries vs.
						awards.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Transparency, open decision-making, (data-driven)
						accountability</head>
					<p>Many of the article’s suggestions for things such as accessibility
						audits or a study of the labor associated with the conferences are
						excellent. Indeed, the labor implications associated with greater
						transparency are one of the greatest challenges faced by ADHO as an
						organization led and run by volunteers. Relatedly, the <ref
							target="https://adho.org/conference/conference-protocol/">Conference Protocol</ref> reflects attempts to clarify gray areas
						of responsibility, in an endeavor to reduce the labor involved in
						negotiating those guidelines individually, year after year. This attempt to
						reduce labor in one way has had the consequence of increasing it in
						another way, through the need to read, understand, and follow a set of
						protocols of considerable complexity.</p>
					<p>Some suggestions, for instance the development and implementation of a preservation policy, have been
						recognized as highly desirable for years. Significant progress has
						been made with respect to the book of abstracts, with abstracts being
						indexed from 2006 onwards in the <ref
							target="https://doi.org/10.34666/k1de-j489">Index of Digital
							Humanities Conferences</ref> (a <q>labour of love</q> seed-funded by
						ADHO but <ref
							target="https://dh-abstracts.library.virginia.edu/pages/team/"
							>built entirely by volunteers</ref>). Other aspects are more
						challenging and, given the financial realities of ADHO, they are
						unlikely to be realized without significant volunteer engagement.
						There is interest among members of the COB to develop policies on data
						gathering and analytics; on public sharing of reports, going forward;
						and on data management, beyond the published abstracts, related to the
						conference. This is another area that requires negotiation across
						different sets of cultural expectations and practices, in addition to
						legal matters, since privacy regimes and intellectual property
						considerations vary across the world and are difficult to solve after
						the fact for legacy data. While it may be possible to agree on a new
						set of practices for conferences moving forward (and note here, again,
						a possible significant lag time for changes to become visible),
						retroactively applying those practices to previous years’ data would require additional labor. Even once a new set of policies
						are in place, if they represent more work on top of what is already
						done (e.g. through preparing the book of abstracts), we will need to
						consider where the labor comes from to implement those policies year
						after year. It is likely to involve ongoing data stewardship
						responsibilities to handle issues such as takedown requests,
						name-change requests, and similar needs.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Labor, volunteerism, engagement</head>
					<p>As the article highlights, one of the most intractable issues here is
						the amount of volunteer labor, over a significant period of time,
						involved in producing the conference – a timeframe considerably longer
						than what is involved in offering a more local or regional conference.
						There has been awareness of this for some time and an attempt to deal
						with it in the current protocol particularly with regard to PC chairs
						and CCC chairs. Attempts to ensure people taking on these roles are
						aware of the workload and confirm that they have institutional support only go so far, informing volunteers of the  conference’s heavy demands on time, but not doing much to mitigate them. ADHO’s requirement that the organizers must have institutional support does limit those who can take
						on the role, but seems like the only ethical stance given the demands
						of the conference.</p>
					<p>Looking toward other large organizations – including
						organizations-of-organizations like the International Federation of
						Library Associations (IFLA) – we see more paid staff and the use of
						professional organizers to reduce the volunteer burden in running the
						organization and putting together the conference. This is made
						possible through (sometimes considerably) higher fees both for
						membership and conference registration. While DH2019 was criticized
						for its high registration fees (€375 for ADHO members), <ref
							target="https://2019.ifla.org/congress-registration-information/registration-fees-and-payment-methods/"
							>IFLA’s fees were significantly higher (at €605 for IFLA
						members)</ref>. </p>
					<p>The alternative to higher fees is other sources of income, and the
						revenue from paid subscriptions to <title rend="italic">Digital
							Scholarship in the Humanities (DSH)</title> – which has been
						practically the sole source of ADHO’s funding and annual financial
						distribution to its COs – is in no way guaranteed to continue to be
						stable going into the future. This is the reason why ADHO has
						incorporated a “service fee” into its financial model to prepare for
						the possibility that COs may need to contribute funding to ADHO if the
						organization’s expenses outstrip the income from <title rend="italic"
							>DSH</title>. This, in turn, will lead to a legitimate desire for
						greater CO oversight on ADHO expenses. If the result of that oversight
						is to lead to anything other than cutting ADHO costs to the absolute
						minimum, the COs need to have a shared understanding about ADHO’s
						purpose, goals, priorities, and values. We hope that the ad-hoc ADHO
						Identity Project will guide the organization to such an understanding
						before ADHO’s costs exceed journal revenue. Here, too, however, we
						anticipate a tension between respecting differences in cultural
						practice and the desire to reduce volunteerism (with its concomitant
						limits on diversity in participation) as some CO members come from
						academic cultures that are not comfortable with, or make it legally
						impossible, to accept remuneration outside of their university salary.
						The current model, where only a few ADHO positions are remunerated
						(Communications Fellows, website translators, the IITF members receive
						very modest stipends, and a systems administrator is paid by the
						hour), raises concerns from multiple camps. It will be revisited by
						the COB in the upcoming year, now that we have formally established a
						cohort of CO treasurers who can help shape these discussions.</p>
					<p>Some aspects of conference organization are inherently more rewarding
						than others. Shaping conversations within the field, bringing together
						a community, and cultivating both the current and the next generations
						of scholars should be invigorating and satisfying on some level.
						However, academic service is a gendered activity within and beyond
						ADHO and is pervasively devalued, a challenge further intensified when
						those performing service are women. ADHO is very limited in what it
						can do to change the culture around service where it matters most for
						people: within their disciplines, fields, and institutions. Nonetheless, if
						the net impact on the organizers of so many instantiations of the ADHO
						conference is the degree of dissatisfaction and alienation described
						by the authors of the article, then ADHO must both take responsibility
						and take action, at the level where its organizational and financial
						decisions will have consequences for future organizers.</p>
					<p>Although we recognize that the focus of the article is on systemic
						practices and policies, we want to also acknowledge the personal,
						often gendered, experiences of bullying, harassment, and denigration
						mentioned in it that have contributed to the sense of alienation,
						burnout, and of negative personal and professional impacts from involvement in the organization of the conference.
						Such oppressive behaviors are completely unacceptable. While the
						article highlights the downsides of ADHO’s organizational tendency to
						address problems by adding more policies, the lack of
						conflict-resolution and appeals mechanisms within ADHO’s expansive
						policies is an oversight that must be addressed promptly. We aim to
						develop and implement such a policy as soon as possible. We also aim
						to broaden the code of conduct, in consultation with the IITF, and to
						include a conflict resolution mechanism.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Negotiating difference going forward</head>
					<p>As an increasingly global organization dedicated to the promotion of DH
						across different cultures – ever more widespread geopolitical local
						cultures and quite diverse academic cultures – ADHO faces the
						challenge and the exciting prospect of negotiating among diverse
						perspectives to establish priorities and advance initiatives. As the
						article illustrates, the process of change within ADHO has been a slow
						and an uneven one, in part because of considerations like governance
						structures and available volunteer time, but in part also because of
						the recognition that there is not one single right position on every
						matter nor a single position that will satisfy every CO, or every
						member of the DH community, equally. </p>
					<p>For instance, the question of multilingualism is a very vexed one on
						which there are very strongly held, divergent views as to the right
						course. Some believe passionately that ADHO conferences should have
						substantial multilingual components; others feel that the present
						policy, which allows for paper proposals and presentation in English,
						French, Spanish, Italian and German, introduces a hierarchy, in privileging these over other languages, that is more problematic than a
						monolingual conference, given the increasing availability of
						conferences in these languages. </p>
					<p>These and other views are reasoned and principled perspectives emerging
						from different intellectual frameworks, local contexts, and cultural
						histories. When ADHO is confronted with such controversial matters,
						time and care are required to negotiate among real, legitimate
						differences amongst COs and to seek ways forward that, while in some
						cases not equally acceptable to all, are acceptable enough that the
						Alliance can continue. These discussions are slowed further if
						COs take the time to engage their membership, rather than reflecting
						the voice of only the CO’s representative to ADHO. Since those members
						may someday also step into the role of CO representative, taking time
						to build a broader consensus in the community is essential. </p>
					<p>Dialogue and careful listening, as well as sound governance structures,
						solid processes, and checks against abusive behavior, are all required
						to negotiate differences respectfully within a global alliance of
						diverse organizations. Although in ADHO’s current financial situation
						these require people to come forward and invest substantial time and
						care, the need to negotiate difference is in itself a sign of
						increasing diversity. The COB, EB, and other officers are working to
						make ADHO a space in which diversity and other aims can be advanced
						for the DH community globally, and we are working together to better
						articulate those aims and our values. Aware that ADHO’s policies and
						processes are far from perfect, we hope to learn how to do better from
						the COs, from the broader DH community, and from other organizations
						similar in structure to ADHO, in order to continue to offer our
						communities the benefits of the conference while minimizing negative
						effects on volunteers. </p>
					<p>We are deeply grateful to those past and present who have stepped
						forward to give generously of their time to ADHO as an organization,
						and, in particular, to the co-authors of this article who have shared
						their insights into the important challenges and opportunities for
						improvement in the conference that their particular experiences have
						afforded. We are also thankful to those who have stepped forward and
						shared the positive experiences they have had working for a DH
						conference and the ways that work has contributed to their
						professional growth. We are committed to taking steps from our
						positions within ADHO to ensure that the conference better serves the
						global DH community, and that ADHO does right by those who are willing
						and able to volunteer as organizers.</p>
					<p>In closing, we extend to the reader an invitation to reframe their
						conception of ADHO as a distant <q>them</q> that produces and adheres to a
						complex set of rules and processes, and instead think of it as a
						revolving cast of <q>us,</q> since many individuals have held multiple <ref
							target="https://adho.org/leadership/past-officers">roles in ADHO
							over the years</ref>.
						There is very little of ADHO that exists as a separate bureaucracy –
						rather, ADHO is an attempt to coordinate and collaborate across the
						cultural and linguistic gaps that separate COs, which are themselves
						made up of regional, linguistic, or structural groups of <q>us.</q> ADHO
						can and will strive to become a more transparent, inviting, and
						rewarding space in which to collaborate with others in shaping the
						international DH community, but ultimately it can only do better if
						COs engage in making it better. COs can only engage with ADHO if
						people in their communities advocate for that involvement, and can
						offer the time to make it happen. On one hand, it would be vastly more
						straightforward if ADHO were a clear group of <q>them</q> that could be
						lobbied for change. At the same time, however slow the process for
						getting there, the form ADHO takes in the future is in the hands of
						the people who get involved and who together imagine and implement the
						international DH organization they would like to see.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Appendix: Background and Context</head>
				<div>
					<head>Organizational changes</head>
					<p>Originally conceived as a partnership between the North America-based
						ACH and the European EADH (at the time ALLC) to host an international
						conference, ADHO has grown rapidly in recent years, from 2 to 11
						Constituent Organizations between 2005 and 2022, with several more
						applications pending. An organizational structure appropriate for two
						large sub-organizations is poorly suited to serve over five times that
						number. Beginning with the decision in 2013 to undertake a strategic
						review of our structure and governance, ADHO undertook a complete
						organizational restructuring, the final implementation details for
						which are scheduled to be completed by the end of 2022.<note> See <ref
								target="https://change.adho.org/"
								>https://change.adho.org/</ref>. </note> Working through the
						implications of that restructuring – everything from arranging bank
						access to establishing a non-profit in the Netherlands and revising
						representation, voting, and financial protocols – has been a major
						concern of those who served on ADHO’s Steering Committee, and many
						volunteers from beyond it, over the last decade. While significant
						attempts have been made by the CCC to address procedural matters
						through revision of the protocol, most recently in 2022, overall these
						issues have taken a back seat to the organizational changes. In 2019,
						the reorganization created the parallel structures of the
						policy-making COB and the EB, which carries out the day-to-day running
						of ADHO, a division of responsibilities that makes it easier for the
						COB to direct its attention to the big-picture challenges, priorities,
						and future directions for ADHO, confident that the EB is handling the
						operational work of the organization.</p>
					<p>The near-completion of the reorganization and the clarification of roles
						and responsibilities within ADHO have created space for the ADHO COB
						to reflect on the issues with the conference as raised by this
						article, as well as other fundamental questions about ADHO, including
						who the organization is for, what we do, how we engage with COs and
						their members, and what ADHO’s values and priorities are. Even more
						broadly, ADHO’s role in running the international conference,
						sponsoring journals, and adjudicating awards comes with an implicit
						but ill-defined responsibility to the DH community made up of
						individuals within the COs, as well as those with no CO affiliation.
						As a step towards establishing and articulating a shared understanding
						of how ADHO should answer these fundamental questions, as of fall 2022
						we have established an ADHO ad-hoc Identity Project that will begin by
						interviewing CO representatives about their perspectives on what ADHO
						is, what we should be doing, and how effectively the systems
						established by the reorganization distribute power throughout the
						Constituent Organisations. </p></div>
				<div>
					<head>Conference Organization: Local Organizers, Program Committee, and the
						Conference Coordinating Committee</head>
					<p>As noted in the Background section (§17-§20) of the article, one of the
						most challenging aspects of organizing the conference results from the
						extensive policies governing it. The <ref
							target="https://adho.org/leadership/conference-coordinating-committee-ccc/"
							>Conference Coordinating Committee (CCC)</ref> maintains these
						policies and oversees their implementation in specific instances of
						the conference. The Local Organizers are responsible for hosting,
						logistical management, and finances, and the Program Committee (PC)
						for the academic program. After conference bids have been prepared by
						the prospective LOs and then refined in consultation with the CCC, the
						COB (formerly the Steering Committee) selects the host institution and
						hence the LO committee prior to the formation of the PC. The host CO
						is usually<note> The need to select a CO in the case of Mexico
							resulted from the fact that, at the time the PC was formed, RedHD
							had not yet been admitted as a CO; in this case a number of ad
							hoc decisions were made that required subsequent
							correction.</note> determined by the geographic location of the
						conference rather than assigned, and historically the LOs are
						determined through the bidding process, with a separate process for
						selecting the Chairs for the PC, which is composed of representatives
						from all COs. This practice not only results in “gray areas” of
						responsibility, as noted, but also overlaps that indeed make essential
						“Cooperation, communication, and goodwill” (§19) and increase the
						potential for conflict if the LOs and the PC chairs do not work well
						together, as has sometimes been the case. The LO/PC division of
						responsibilities lies at the root of a number of recurrent problems
						flagged in the article. To address this issue, ADHO is
						currently redefining the process for nominating PC chairs to better
						include the perspective of the LOs, in order to more effectively
						promote coordination and compatibility from the earliest stages of
						planning. </p>
					<p>The coordination of roles and responsibilities associated with the
						conference has been, as the article notes, rendered very challenging
						by the fact that historically the Local Organizers (LOs), the Program
						Committee (PC), and the CCC all ran in parallel with some
						cross-representation. Recognition of the need to bridge the gap
						between different activities has led to multiple changes including
						deliberate overlapping and historical continuity in the composition of
						the groups.<note> From the current protocol: The CCC email list also
							includes (in ex officio capacity) the EB Chair, the EB
							Secretariat, the Communications Officer, the chairs of the
							Multi-Lingualism &amp; Multi-Culturalism and Awards Committees,
							and the SIG Liaison.</note> Until 2019-20, the CCC was composed
						of representatives from each CO plus a chair appointed by the COB, and
						it operated quite independently from the PC and LOs. However, to
						address concerns raised by past conferences, since 2021 it has been
						transformed to a smaller, more streamlined group made up of a Chair
						and Chair-Elect, with an Incoming Chair-Elect to ensure further
						continuity, with each person spending one year in each role over a
						three-year period. The <ref
							target="https://adho.org/conference/conference-protocol/">current
							conference protocol</ref> reflects these changes.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="estill2022" label="Estill et al. 2022">Estill, Laura, Melissa Terras, Elika Ortega, Deb Verhoeven, and Glen Layne-Worthey. <title rend="quotes">The circus we deserve? A front row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital Humanities.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> (2022).</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
