<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Modernism and
                    Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sean <dhq:family>Weidman</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Pennsylvania State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>seangweidman@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sean Weidman (seangweidman@gmail.com) holds a PhD from the Pennsylvania
                            State University, where he is currently an Instructor of English. Some
                            of his other work on modernist literature and modern culture can be
                            found in <title rend="italic">English Literary History,
                                Modernism/modernity</title>, and <title rend="italic">Digital
                                Scholarship in the Humanities</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Aaren <dhq:family>Pastor</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Pennsylvania State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>aaren.pastor@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Aaren Pastor (aaren.pastor@gmail.com) is a dual title PhD candidate in
                            English and Women’s, Gender, and Sexuality Studies at the Pennsylvania
                            State University, whose research reflects commitments to feminist
                            theory, a politics of difference, and gender and sexuality studies
                            within the realms of literature and culture.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000566</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->015</idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->4</idno>
                <date when="2021-11-12">12 November 2021</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
            <change when="2022-08-02" who="BRG">resolved malformed xml tags</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
                <p>Virginia Woolf writes in her novel <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> that <quote rend="inline">it is clothes that wear us and
                    not we them; we may make them take to mould of arm or breast, but they mould our
                    hearts, our brains, our tongues to their liking.</quote> Her observation remains vital
                    to the author’s longstanding, feminist critique of essentializing discourses,
                    but it also gives recourse to the ways our computational methods of studying
                    literature and its history sometimes <quote rend="inline">mould […] to their liking</quote> their objects.
                    When studying style and gender, digital humanists have tended to use
                    computational methods to trace embedded, hidden linguistic structures, showing
                    how they can contain, conceal, and condition the gendered lives of social groups
                    and cultural milieus. In this essay, we present a stylometric case study — Woolf’s
                    <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> — that reminds us why, when dealing with gender in modern literature,
                    computational critics must pay particular care when addressing and generalizing
                    from modernism’s experimental styles. We outline the limitations of our own and
                    prior approaches to questions of gender and literary style, and we ask whether
                    flawed stylometric analyses can acquaint us with ways that modernism’s stylistic
                    innovations productively haunt the conclusions of digital literary
                    criticism.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                <p> We outline the limitations of our own and prior approaches to questions of
                    gender and literary style, and we eventually consider how even a structurally
                    flawed stylometric analysis can acquaint us to new ways that modernism and its
                    stylistic innovations haunt certain kinds of digital literary criticism.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head/>
                    <epigraph>
                        <cit>
                            <quote rend="block">
                                <emph>
                                    Presumably<lb/>
                                	(once upon a time)<lb/>
                                	you thought MODERNIST STYLE was<lb/>
                                	worthy of your<lb/>
                                	ATTENTION and CURIOSITY.<lb/><lb/>
                                </emph>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Manifesto of Modernist Digital
                                        Humanities</title> Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna
                                    Ross, Katie Tanigawa <ptr target="#christie2014"/>
                            </quote>
                        </cit>
                    </epigraph>
                

                <p>When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of
                    the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, the <term>digital turn</term> did
                    not make the cut <ptr target="#mao2008"/>. In fact, only very recently have
                    accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to
                    reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize
                    new digital technologies applied to modernism. Jessica Pressman’s <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title> and Shawna Ross and James
                    O’Sullivan’s edited collection <title rend="italic">Reading Modernism with
                        Machines</title> necessitate special note in this regard, as each study in
                    its own way accounts for how a digital modernism, or a digital approach to
                    modernism, is <quote rend="inline">aligned with strategies of the avant-garde:
                        it challenges traditional expectations about what art is and does [and]
                        illuminates and interrogates the cultural infrastructures, technological
                        networks, and critical practices that support and enable these
                        judgments</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="10"/>
                    <ptr target="#ross2016"/>. Stephen Ross and Jentery Sayers trace as much in
                        <title rend="quotes">Modernism Meets Digital Humanities,</title> and Gabriel
                    Hankins argues similarly that through the <q>weak program</q> of digital
                    methods applied to modernism, critics can activate a variety of subtler points
                    of contact that better model how diffuse modernisms share aesthetic territory
                        <ptr target="#ross2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#hankins2018b" loc="582"/>. Elsewhere, Hankins goes so far as to
                    say that the <quote rend="inline">new modernist studies is now always already
                        digital,</quote> and though Ama Bemma Adwetewa-Badu reminds us that <quote
                        rend="inline">digital tools cannot do the critical and analytical work that
                        we do,</quote> she adds that <quote rend="inline">neither can we do the work
                        that they do,</quote> that is, the work necessitated by a messy and data-filled literary
                    world <ptr target="#hankins2018a"/>
                    <ptr target="#adwetewabadu2020"/>. Look no further for corroboration than Laura
                    McGrath et al.’s <title rend="quotes">Measuring of Modernist Novelty,</title> an
                    essay that operationalizes modernist <q>newness</q> to measure evolutions of
                    novelty in 20th-century fiction <ptr target="#mcgrath2018"/>. Other digital
                    forays in the past half-decade, as detailed expansively by J. Matthew Huculak,
                    represent substantial collections, recoveries, expansions, and innovations of
                    modernist archivism <ptr target="#huculak2018"/>. Cue in Amanda Golden and
                    Cassandra Laity’s co-edited issue of <title rend="italic">Feminist Modernist
                        Studies </title>on modernist, feminist digital humanities <ptr
                        target="#golden2018"/>, and the digital turn of modernist criticism seems
                    fully upon us, furnishing the New Modernist Studies with accounts that
                    illustrate how the critical debates of modernism are newly accessible, and newly
                    accessible to critique, through digital methods.</p>
                <p> Even so, computational approaches to analyzing modernist texts (e.g. text
                    analysis, stylometry, computational stylistics, network analysis, and topic
                    modeling) so far account for a relatively scarce subset of modernism’s new
                    digital surge. By far the most active scholars at the intersection of text
                    analysis and modernist studies have been Hoyt Long and Richard Jean So, whose
                    work on modernism at the Chicago Text Lab has spanned a wide range of modernist
                    topics: they’ve analyzed the poetic publication networks of high modernism,
                    provided a multifaceted analysis of the English-language haiku, and studied the
                    movement of stream of consciousness as literary technique <ptr
                        target="#long2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#long2016a"/>
                    <ptr target="#long2016b"/>. Other scattered exceptions exist too,<note> One
                        might just as easily scan this essay’s bibliography for other examples, but
                        among them: McGrath et al. (2018); Ross and O’Sullivan (2016); Jeffrey
                        Drouin, <title rend="quotes">Close- And Distant-Reading Modernism: Network
                            Analysis, Text Mining, and Teaching <title rend="italic">The Little
                                Review</title></title> (2014); Sean Weidman and James O’Sullivan,
                            <title rend="quotes">The limits of distinctive words: Re-evaluating
                            literature’s gender marker debate</title> (2018).</note> but their work
                    makes up the bulk of that subset of digital literary criticism that attempts to
                    measure, model, and interpret the styles of modernism computationally.</p>
                <p> Several practical reasons have shouldered much of the blame for this lack of
                    critical diversity. Although new and compelling intellectual paradigms have
                    attempted temporal and spatial refigurings of modernism through its complex
                    global and planetary shifts <ptr target="#hayot2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#wollaeger2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#stanford2015"/> , the dominant critical views of modernist work
                    still converge in the early 20th century.<note> In fact, David James and Urmila
                        Seshagiri recently bolstered that organizing logic, arguing how <quote
                            rend="inline">[r]etaining modernism across deep time can dehistoricize
                            it as a movement but repoliticize it as a global practice, a practice
                            that serves instrumental ends in the context of cultural circumstances
                            with which modernist writing has yet to be associated</quote>
                        <ptr target="#james2014" loc="90"/>.</note> Computational literary criticism
                    requires an accessible textual archive, and since the preferred periodization of
                    modernism has gone largely unchanged, large portions of modernist corpora have
                    long been under copyright until only very recently — and most works, at least
                    widely, may remain so for the better part of the next decades.<note> Peter B.
                        Hirtle of Cornell University Library hosts a <q>Copyright Information
                            Center</q> page that’s kept updated for the complex copyright terms of
                        public domain in the US. See Hirtle’s article, <title rend="quotes">When Is
                            1923 Going to Arrive and Other Complications of the U.S. Public
                            Domain</title> (2012), for an explanation of why published works after
                        1923 have remained out of the public domain. As of 1 January, 2019, a
                        variety of US-published works from 1923 have entered the public domain, and
                        each subsequent year will see a correlative year’s worth of once-copyrighted
                        works do the same. An exception must be made, however, for Matthew Huculak
                        and Claire Battershill’s <ref target="http://openmods.uvic.ca/">
                            <title rend="italic">Open Modernisms</title>
                        </ref> project, which as of this writing represents an online archive of
                        nearly 500 modernist works in various genres (see also Claire Battershill et
                        al.’s <title rend="italic">Making The Modernist Archives Publishing
                            Project</title> (2017)). Otherwise, in the past half-decade, the
                        HathiTrust Research Center is the only digital collection that offers access
                        to sets of post-1923 texts for scholars doing computational research, and it
                        comes with several restrictions.</note> Unsurprisingly, easy access to
                    reliable digital materials has been a strong determiner of the topic matter of
                    computational literary study, which often seeks to analyze bodies of work
                    macroanalytically or, in the now notorious Morettian variation, <q>from a
                        distance.</q> These limits have held particular sway in the realm of
                    stylometry, a broad approach to studying textual style that aims, usually, to
                    analyze a large corpus of literature by counting certain words (or other
                    linguistic elements like grammatical structures, punctuation, etc.), averaging
                    the measurements out into a unique <q>signature,</q> and then comparing that
                    stylistic composite to other texts, authors, periods, and so on. Applied to
                    literature, these countings have helped scholars make claims about style as a
                    measurable form as it exposes certain conditions, contexts, and forms of
                    representation, both inside and outside of narratives; through style, that is,
                    critics have argued that they can digitally identify, measure, and compare the
                    flows and workings of social and cultural mechanisms — like productions and
                    representations of gender, race, class, or nationality — as they slip into
                    linguistic tendency. </p>
                <p> If we put aside the material limitations of modernist literature’s computational
                    study, we find that deeper conceptual concerns have also tended to restrict it,
                    especially with regard to modernist stylometry and its relationship to gender
                    (and other identity categories). Modernist social life was as much governed by
                    the sociopolitical affordances of feminism’s first wave as anything else, and
                    its consequences ripple powerfully through much of modernist literature. Coupled
                    with the dicta of avant-garde modernist aesthetics — which, for the sake of
                    space, we might vulgarly boil down to newness and experimentation — this access
                    to new material conditions, sociopolitical spaces, forms of representation, and
                    modes of being-in-the-everyday also released a well-documented
                        <emph>stylistic</emph> first wave for many writers. Gertrude Stein, Virginia
                    Woolf, H.D., Djuna Barnes, Mina Loy, and Jean Rhys, among a multitude of others,
                    unwound the concertinaed styles of their literary predecessors to produce, if we
                    might borrow from Cary Nelson, a literature <quote rend="inline">generically
                        undecidable, sometimes feminist and lesbian, wholly unassignable to a
                        humanizing persona, and more purely and powerfully devoted to an exploration
                        of how language works</quote> than much of the literature that preceded it
                        <ptr target="#nelson1989" loc="179"/>.</p>
                <p> Our aim in this essay is to consider the conceptual impediments to studying that
                    undecidability of gender stylometrically, as an influencer (or correlative
                    feature) of modernist literary style.<note> We should clarify that our use of
                        the term <term>style</term> diverges from other variants used by modernist
                        literary scholars (e.g. Rebecca Walkowitz), which tend to invoke the term
                        loosely and synonymously with <term>form,</term> insofar as each denotes a
                        literary pattern traceable through (for example) close reading. In the realm
                        of stylometry, a notion of literary style is technical and tied to word use,
                        and the term stands in for the aggregate of a set of formal, observable
                        textual features. Our underlying assumption is that word preference can be
                        measured by first counting words, both within individual texts and
                        comparatively within a group of texts, and that those counts will be unique
                        along different axes (e.g. different from writer to writer; genre to genre;
                        etc.). By extension, those counts tell us something about the content and
                            <term>style</term> of a text/writer relative to other texts. For a
                        terrific account of the interdisciplinary use of the term among textual
                        studies fields, see Herrmann et al. (2015).</note> We first locate where
                    some of those difficulties are borne out in computational literary criticism
                    broadly and, in particular, call attention to the way stylistic markers that
                    have been taken as proxies for forms of gendered experience can prove unreliable
                    in modernist contexts. Virginia Woolf’s famous meditation in <title
                        rend="italic">A Room of One’s Own </title>on androgyny and its creative
                    potential might be invoked here: stylometric scholarship has not yet contended
                    with how extensively the experiments of modernist style, full of gender
                    explorations and polysemous difficulty, complicate the tidiness and
                    differentiability sometimes required of text analysis. Such a claim is certainly
                    not new in the realm of computational literary criticism generally, and as the
                    next section details, many digital practitioners have already studied just how
                    deeply our notions of gender undermine computational designs. It is simply to
                    this mounting critical stack that we add a new stylometric case featuring a
                    small corpus of modernist fiction, in an effort to show both the limits and
                    potentials of its stylometric study.<note> And this line probably owes a great
                        critical debt to those recent critiques of computational literary study
                        proffered by Katherine Bode (2017) and Nan Z. Da (2019) — though, our study tends toward slightly
                        more optimism: in the end, while we suggest stylometric critique needs to be
                        wary of drawing firm conclusions about modern life via modernist fiction, we
                        nevertheless think stylometry has much to offer the study of
                        modernism.</note>
                </p>
                <p> Using <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando</title> as a featured example, we argue that the story of gender
                    and modernism as seen through stylometry reveals a shared limit of its models —
                    of identity and computation — to provide trustworthy exemplars.
                    We then briefly consider some ways that the
                    stylistic uniqueness of Woolf’s novel might help us understand modernism more
                    completely. After all, if the full cultural stakes of modernism remain unearthed
                        <ptr target="#james2014"/>, if the legacies of modernism continue to haunt
                    our aesthetic forms, and if gender is one site of particularly fruitful
                    aesthetic experimentation, then stylometry may help further uncover the
                    stylistic innovations and cultural remnants that constitute the topos of
                    modernist influence. And since modernist texts, at least in the US, are
                    beginning to shed their copyright shackles, the proto-framing for a modernist
                    stylometry is perhaps already overdue.</p>
                <p> The digital turn has provided an innovative set of tools for reading,
                    encountering, and thinking through modernist texts, as singular materials to
                    linger with but also to scrutinize through their forms of digital manufacture.
                    We hope to show that stylometric analysis of someone like Woolf in particular,
                    and perhaps many modernist writers in general, links critics to new ways of
                    seeing the designs of gender, the stylistic transitions of which require
                    stylometrists to contend carefully with the complexity and multiplicity of
                    modernist literature and its shifting orientations.<note> In this we uphold Losh
                        et al.’s call for a <quote rend="inline">genuinely messy, heterogeneous, and
                            contentious pluralism</quote> as the underlying ethic of our digital
                        methods, a critical approach that may also productively join — or
                        productively digitize — the political investments of our data, its
                        structures, and our own methods of analyzing and contextualizing modernism
                            <ptr target="#losh2016" loc="98"/>.</note> Such a view has the benefit
                    of reiterating two important points: first that modernism’s collection of
                    digital movements (vis-à-vis Pressman) occasioned an understanding of linguistic
                    styles as flexible, experimental technologies that could hide and reveal, invoke
                    and manufacture identity categories at the proverbial touch of a pen or click of
                    a typewriter; and second that our computational methods themselves complicate
                    the study of modernist representation by rewriting literary data into new and
                    ongoing digital dialectics. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> A Critical History of Gender, Literature, and Quantitative Formalism</head>

                <p>Some framing is in order before we outline our modernist experiment, regarding
                    first how we employ the concept of gender in relation to modernist literature,
                    and second what digital humanists have tended to glean from the computational
                    study of literary style and gender (using tools and methods at least adjacent to
                    stylometry). After, we consider how treating Woolf’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando </title>as a case study of gender and modernist style may help
                    scholars rethink their applications of stylometric critique.</p>
                <p> If we start with an understanding of gender as a medley of sociopolitical
                    conventions and laws discursively assigned to bodies and constructed and policed
                    accordingly (a là Judith Butler),
                    to imagine we might reliably evaluate gender computationally seems,
                    conceptually, at least somewhat confused. Gayle Rubin’s sex-gender system, that
                        <quote rend="inline">set of arrangements by which society transforms
                        biological sexuality into products of human activity</quote>
                    <ptr target="#rubin1975" loc="159"/>, has long-since clarified that gendered
                    identities are sets of internalized, performative scripts reified through
                    various legal, political, scientific, and cultural processes. This is an
                    essential clarification for stylometric analysis, which purports to measure
                    these discursive influences as they bleed through language. If it is only
                    through socializing discourses that a body becomes vested with the idea of an
                    essential sex/gender, stylometry only detects the un-isolated impressions of
                    that social and cultural influence as they mix with a mess of other discursive
                        powers.<note> For Bode, this manner of viewing texts often ends in <quote
                            rend="inline">dismiss[ing] the documentary record’s multiplicity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bode2017" loc="92"/>.</note>
                </p>
                <p> In spite of these conceptual limitations, a variety of digital humanists have
                    undertaken the intricate work of studying gender and style throughout literary
                    history and at various scales. A first and landmark example is John Burrows’s
                    1986 study of Jane Austen’s novels, which simply used Austen’s varied frequency
                    of function words (pronouns, prepositions, articles, conjunctions, and other
                    non-content words) to identify character dialogue patterns, narrative
                    subtleties, thematic transformations, tonal ebbs and flows in characterization,
                    directions and forces of speech, and so on, formal features that (he notes)
                    regularly fall along typical 19th-century gender lines <ptr
                        target="#burrows1986"/>.<note> Burrows popularized the field of literary
                        computational stylistics with his book, and his was one of the first to
                        recognize the scales of semantic meaning within patterns of function word
                        usage; although he doesn’t really study gender in Austen explicitly,
                        literary stylometrists continue to build on his principles.</note> Many have
                    since built from Burrows’s pioneering study and, among the more recent attempts
                    to unravel gender’s impact on literary style, Matthew Jockers’s work on
                    19th-century fiction in <title rend="italic">Macroanalysis</title> is likely the
                    most well-known. Chief among Jockers’s conclusions is that gender is the
                        <emph>least</emph> influential determiner on literary style in the 19th
                    century when compared to other categories of stylistic difference — e.g. author,
                    genre, (decade-long) period, textual variations (punctuation, pronoun usage,
                    etc.) <ptr target="#jockers2013" loc="96–8"/>. In a narrower study of
                    19th-century fiction, one framed more closely by the period’s sociohistorical
                    contexts, Jockers and Gabi Kirilloff looked at the depiction and action (via
                    pronoun and verb combinations like <emph>she walked</emph> or <emph>he
                        dressed</emph>) of male and female characters; they observed that men and
                    women were narrated with different vocabularies according to 19th-century norms,
                    and that 19th-century novelists had difficulty masking their own gender when
                    they wrote characters of another <ptr target="#jockers2016"/>.<note> Refer also
                        to Jan Rybicki (2016) and Mark Algee-Hewitt (2015) for two more essays
                        utilizing similar methods to reach similar ends.</note> In fact, Kirilloff
                    and Jockers published an addendum to that study recently, pairing close reading
                    of several of its outliers with those verb-usage lists, concluding that <quote
                        rend="inline">[t]hough the characters in these novels behave in
                            <soCalled>unconventional</soCalled> ways, all three struggle to mitigate
                        traditional and emerging social values,</quote> a dialectic they found
                        <quote rend="inline">reflected not only at the level of plot but at the
                        level of the sentence, and in fact, at the level of individual words</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kirilloff2018" loc="842"/>.</p>
                <p> Although the above examples concern gender as it emerges in literature to
                    reflect certain cultural norms and social circumstances, critics have also
                    studied gender computationally in relation to its contemporary production, to
                    its politics of reception, and to the literary marketplace; and each approach
                    productively ties the stylistic into its socioeconomic imprints. Ted Underwood,
                    David Bamman, and Sabrina Lee find that gender divisions between characters in
                    fiction are becoming less distinguishable (i.e. men and women characters are
                    being described and speaking/acting more similarly), but that the proportion of
                    fiction written by women, and the proportion of women characters, dropped
                    dramatically from 1800-1960. Hence <quote rend="inline">while gender roles were
                        becoming more flexible,</quote> Underwood et al. argue that the story of
                    women writing literature is <quote rend="inline">a story of steady
                        decline,</quote> and that between 1850 and 1960, <quote rend="inline"
                        >fiction itself became more attentive to men,</quote> such that women as
                    characters were becoming less prominent, even in books by women <ptr
                        target="#underwood2018"/>. Jonathan Y. Cheng, meanwhile, takes physical
                    descriptions as an entryway to studying gender and gendered embodiment over the
                    last 150 years of English-language fiction; he uncovers that physical
                    descriptions of characters has increased over time, but that for women’s
                    characterization, specifically, bodily descriptions remain curiously central,
                    even as literary depictions of men and women become less binary <ptr
                        target="#cheng2020" loc="28–9"/>. In a strictly contemporary account, after
                    canvassing thousands of reviews from the <title rend="italic">New York Times
                        Book Review</title>, Andrew Piper and Richard Jean So discovered that
                    reviewers still talk about women’s books and men’s books in stereotypically
                    antithetical terms, <quote rend="inline">reproduc[ing] the public/private split
                        bequeathed to us from the nineteenth century</quote>
                    <ptr target="#piper2016"/>. For Piper and So, their findings indicate that the
                    damaging discourses around gender are still being subtly reproduced in the
                    public apparatuses that surround literature.<note> Although not limited to
                        modern literature, this claim is made even clearer and more forcefully by
                        Earhart et al. (2020) in their recent account of gender and scholarly
                        citational practices.</note> Their results were expanded upon by Eve Kraicer
                    and Piper, who found similarly — and through a diverse and thorough assortment
                    of computational models — that the representations of women in much of
                    contemporary fiction mirrors their marginalized and decentralized positions in
                    the literary marketplace <ptr target="#kraicer2019"/>. Matthew J. Lavin achieves
                    something similar in his more located study of gender, reception, and the
                    descriptive styles of <title rend="italic">NYT </title>book reviews between 1905
                    and 1925; and, contrary to Underwood et al., Lavin finds that although women were in fact
                    writing <emph>more</emph> fiction than men, that diverse work was still
                    being discussed and reviewed within a reductive, domestic, private/public
                    vocabulary <ptr target="#lavin2020"/>.</p>
                <p> The computational analyses we cover above largely discuss gender and literary
                    production in the 19th-century or our contemporary period, and we draw attention
                    to them not only to detail the range of current quantitative formalist work on
                    gender and literature, but also to point to the critical gap that exists where a
                    related digital modernist criticism could be, given that these studies have
                    provided few insights about modernism.<note> In fact, aside from Lavin’s essay
                        about modern reviewing, we can think of only two studies that employ some
                        form of quantitative formalist approach to modernist work and even vaguely
                        relate it to gender. Stephen Ramsay’s <title rend="italic">Reading Machines
                        </title>opens with a chapter that analyzes Virginia Woolf’s <title
                            rend="italic">The Waves </title>in relation to its feminist criticism,
                        and David Hoover’s later <title rend="quotes">Argument, Evidence, and the
                            Limits of Digital Literary Studies</title> positions itself directly
                        opposite Ramsay’s earlier study by rereading <title rend="italic">The Waves
                        </title>with different computational methods <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#hoover2016"/>. Among other thematically adjacent studies: see
                        González et al. (2019) for an account of gender, stylometry, and
                            <emph>modernismo</emph>; and outside of modernism’s computational
                        literary study, see Churchill et al. (2018) regarding their work on Mina
                        Loy, style, and UX design and their interactive digital project of feminist
                        modernist design (which builds on D’Ignazio and Klein’s (2016) foundational
                        feminist visualizations essay). </note> While the above is by no means a
                    comprehensive list,<note> Among other, longer accounts, Katherine Bode’s <title
                            rend="italic">A World of Fiction: Digital Collections and the Future of
                            Literary History </title>(2018) and Ted Underwood’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Distant Horizons: Digital Evidence and Literary Change </title>(2019)
                        also each contain a section on gender and (mainly) 19th-century
                        literature.</note> as a largely current critical sampling, these studies
                    showcase both the standard story of gender and style leading up to or following
                    the <term>fin de siècle</term> and how scholars have approached that story,
                    which is most often by examining the stylistic indications of a period’s
                    culturally and socially produced gender binary, and then determining how those
                    categorizations reveal new aspects of gendered subjectivity. In fact, this is
                    probably a fair way to summarize the basic project of most computational studies
                    of literary style and gender, the majority of which unearth, organize, and
                    interpret linguistic traces through gender’s various social and cultural
                    histories, its modes of material production, and its narrativized
                    representations. Yet as these scholars realize, utilizing digital methods to
                    approach gender as a defining mechanism governing literary reception, critique,
                    and re/production introduces as many problems as insights, especially when the
                    results of digital literary analyses are placed within the same social and
                    historical contexts from which the corpuses are pulled. </p>
                <p> The first impulse of computational critics is often to test the already-reified
                    categories around us, gender notwithstanding. But that approach can tend toward
                    troublesome precarity — troublesome not merely from a computational standpoint
                    either, per Johanna Drucker, who makes the following observation about the
                    hazards of studying gender digitally in her meta-analysis of computational
                    modeling:</p>
                <p><quote rend="block">The markers of gender identity may be not in the corpus but in the biographical
                    details, expressed or suppressed, of authors. Looking at stylistic features and
                    asking how they come to represent or construct conventions of gender as an
                    effect of textual practice would lead in directions other than those that
                    presume to sort according to gender as a given category. <ptr
                        target="#drucker2017" loc="632"/></quote> </p>
                <p>So, as we harness computational methods for the textual analysis of gender, we
                    cannot neglect the urgency of self-reflexivity, which must illuminate how the
                    parameters of our textual data, as well as our own interpretive contexts,
                    already construct the pseudo-essentialized elements of gender in our digital
                    practices. Miriam Posner and Lauren Klein helpfully reimagine data in an
                    analogous way, <quote rend="inline">as much an orientation toward one’s sources
                        as it is a primary category of knowledge</quote>
                    <ptr target="#posner2017" loc="2"/>. Such a view, the scholars point out, yields
                    DH methods more materially, socially, culturally oriented, attendant to the
                    non-digital conditionings of the digital, the discourses of which are often
                    grounded in dialectics of visibility and invisibility.</p>
                <p> Take, though, a statement from some of the scholars participating in that
                    digital praxis — for example, Underwood et al. in their <title rend="italic"
                        >Cultural Analytics </title>piece — who often explain these shared
                    limitations differently: </p>
                <p>
                    <quote rend="block">This essay considers both the gender positions ascribed to
                        authors as biographical personages, and the signs of gender they used in
                        producing characters. In both cases, we understand gender as a conventional
                        role that people were expected to assume in order to become legible in a
                        social context. Authors and characters have been coded according to a
                        tripartite scheme (feminine / masculine / other or unknown), because that
                        scheme organized most public representation of gender in the period we are
                        studying. Gender can certainly be more complex than these categories
                        suggest, and flexible ontologies can be designed to illuminate the
                        complexity. But this essay is inquiring about the history of conventional
                        roles, not about the truth of personal identity, or the underlying processes
                        that produce gendered behavior. <ptr target="#underwood2018" loc="2"/></quote> 
                </p>
                <p>The message here begins to echo Drucker’s, in that it is in the author’s
                    biographical details and situated experiences, which leech into the text as
                    stylistic attributes, that the idiosyncrasies of the author’s personal style
                    become the clothing that outfits a novel’s gendered position. But where Drucker
                    implies that gender can operate as other than a given category, Underwood et al.
                    must admit to retaining a tripartite structure for sorting gender, even though
                    they make very clear that such a schema will fail to encapsulate gender’s
                    complex, messy, performative capacities. In most computational analyses of
                    literary style and gender this is an inevitable rhetorical move that, as Kraicer
                    and Piper explain, historicizes the results and <quote rend="inline">allows us
                        to make explicit the otherwise latent ways in which gender is being
                        mobilized and hierarchized within novels</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kraicer2019" loc="26"/>. After all, a first lesson of
                    computational literary studies is that discourse predetermines data — depending
                    on the tools we implement and the discourses we possess, data can always be made
                    to appear a certain way. As they track some of those ways in their <title
                        rend="italic">Cultural Analytics </title>
                    <title rend="quotes">Identity Issue</title> introduction, Susan Brown and Laura
                    Mandell develop an exhaustive history of conceptualizing gender, outlining the
                    importance of such historicizing for digital projects, which must balance
                    quantitative methodologies with that same reflexive process that asks how our
                    methodological designs direct our analyses. <quote rend="inline">Historicizing
                        helps to destabilize identities,</quote> Brown and Mandell maintain, <quote
                        rend="inline">and cultural analytics can make visible a kind of history that
                        we have never seen before</quote>
                    <ptr target="#brown2018" loc="13"/>. </p>
                <p> Perhaps, though, the kind of historicizing typical textual analysis does serves
                    to stabilize more than <emph>de</emph>stabilize. Underwood et al. say, for
                    instance (to keep with our arbitrary, cherry-picked example), that their essay
                    does not delve into <quote rend="inline">the underlying processes that produce
                        gendered behavior.</quote> But the assumption that such processes can be
                    ignored when studying literary history seems suspect — because language, we
                    know, is one such process, one that governs many others; and as Drucker reminds
                    us, if you want to model gender you must produce (or reproduce) the underlying
                    structures of gender. At some point, the current confines of stylometric
                    analysis require that data be sorted into comparable categories, which means whether one gender, 
                    two gender, three gender, four, comparing categories or columns of gender identification 
                    remains much easier than comparing gender spectra. Does
                    adding a third, non-binary category — or a fourth, or a fifth — unlock or
                    ameliorate the hindered politics of representation at the heart of designing
                    computational analyses around those historical notions of gender? As Pamela
                    Caughie et al. emphasize in their work on feminist ontologies, the answer is:
                        <emph>of course not</emph>
                    <ptr target="#caughie2018"/>. And yet, to label some identity as historically
                    extant when it wasn’t <emph>also</emph> introduces a set of problems, and as
                    Underwood and company note, to imagine there was more social space for
                    expressions of gender fluidity than there actually was does us little good when
                    analyzing textual traces that we aim to tie back into historically grounded
                    claims about social realities. </p>
                <p> This is the uncertain impasse at which stylometric gender analysis has, so far,
                    found a rather comfortable home. Underwood is right, as he aptly remarks
                    elsewhere, that <quote rend="inline">nothing about this [binary] method compels
                        us to stop at two perspectives</quote>
                    <ptr target="#underwood2020" loc="96"/>; but is the best we can really expect of
                    such critique its regular revelation that <quote rend="inline">the very act of
                        modelling carries with it the seeds of a constructionist recognition that a
                        phenomenon could [or will soon] be modelled differently</quote>
                    <ptr target="#brown2018" loc="17"/>?<note> Richard Jean So contends similarly
                        that errors help us realign models to the unseen peripheries of data, and
                        echoes Brown and Mandell’s sentiment through the oft-quoted adage of famed
                        statistician George E.P. Box: <quote rend="inline">All models are wrong, but
                            some are useful</quote>
                        <ptr target="#so2017" loc="669"/>. Andrew Piper makes a comparable remark
                        when he considers that <quote rend="inline">[m]odeling puts computation not
                            on the outside of what is known but as part of the process
                            itself,</quote> a reflexive process toward the contingency of knowledge
                        he terms <term>the New Recursivity</term>
                        <ptr target="#piper2016"/>. Piper also argues convincingly that every aspect
                        of the modeling process, especially those required by its implementation on
                        particular data selections, necessitates reduction — and that in its
                        ubiquity reductiveness can actually be generative <ptr target="#piper2017"
                            loc="654"/>. </note> That leaves us with a set of untenably limited
                    critical positions and several vital, unaddressed questions. Does the clumsiness
                    of quantitative formalism actually force us to decide whether to (a)
                    anachronistically apply new understandings of gender to contexts that cannot
                    hold them, or (b) hand-wash our responsibility to witness and recover different
                    kinds of gendered being, whenever they occurred? In the context of stylometry
                    specifically, how can we responsibly do (a) while avoiding (b)? How can we avoid
                    reproducing normative investigations of identity categories like gender through
                    models of distant reading, given that those models function in systemic and
                    epistemological hierarchies of power that were not designed with plurality in
                        mind?<note> A case in point about this own study, which began many years ago
                        (and before the resources of HathiTrust were widely accessible): our corpus
                        of women authors is almost entirely hand-scanned and OCRed, because the
                        continued gender inequality of the literary marketplace, which Piper and So
                        have studied, also occupies the realm of text digitization. Riddell and
                        Bassett (2020) have measured this gender inequity, finding (in a corpus from
                        the 1830s to the present day) that novels by women have been digitized at
                        substantially lower rates than novels by men. For a more detailed account on
                        the many levels of infrastructural relevance women writers require to be
                        studied by digital methods, see Laura Mandell’s <title rend="quotes"
                            >Gendering Digital Literary History: What Counts for Digital
                            Humanities</title> (2016), then see Roopika Risam’s <title rend="quotes"
                            >Navigating the Global Digital Humanities: Insights from Black
                            Feminism</title> (2016) for a take on the complexity of foregrounding
                        racial and multicultural diversity while doing so.</note>
                </p>
                <p> In short, we not only lack a spectrum-based computational model for categorizing
                    and operationalizing gender stylistically, but — for scholars of modernism — we
                    also lack a critical vocabulary to address how our digital methods at once allow
                    and prevent us from analyzing those <quote rend="inline">thick textures of
                        history</quote> that the New Modernist Studies promised <ptr
                        target="#mao2008" loc="745"/>. This is a hinge, too, of Nan Z. Da’s argument
                    against computational literary studies: that computational approaches to texts
                    (stylometry among them) are frequently ill-applied to data not suited for its
                    methods, and that its results are either incorrect, overstated, or unoriginal
                    [Da 2019]. So, how might we develop a situated stylometry as <quote
                        rend="inline">a digital strategy that <emph>can</emph> inform</quote> our
                    computational and interpretative methods <ptr target="#christie2014"/>? How can
                    we put at our service digital methods that, according to Drucker, only act as a
                    kind of filter through which we pull existing social structures and hierarchies,
                    like normative or binary ideas about gender? Can we avoid treating their
                    computational products as purified or more extant forms of pre-constructed
                    inequity, and instead allow our processes of modeling to deconstruct themselves,
                    to produce findings resistant to the systems that arrange them? </p>
                <p> In addition to underscoring the urgency of revising our methods to better fit gender’s 
                    actualities, we hope to demonstrate shortly — against recent critiques of computational 
                    literary scholarship — that even flawed stylometric models can teach us new things about 
                    modernism. In the following section, we posit that studying Woolf from within the binary 
                    she saw beyond is itself an approach that helps us to reconstruct her project of imaginative 
                    self-fashioning. Treating <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> as an important edge-case for modernism’s digital-critical
                    scaffolding, our investigation aims to recover one of Woolf’s stylistic innovations and, 
                    in doing so, to rethink a few of stylometry’s prevailing critical assumptions. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Anglophone Modernism and Woolf’s <title rend="italic">Orlando</title></head>
                <p>As with any digital literary analysis, taking the stylometric baton into
                    modernism began with an inevitably insufficient selection (and rejection) of
                    texts to analyze, and the narrow variety we collected here is representative of
                    three, semi-arbitrary governing features: first, each author needed to have
                    written at least three works of fiction (or collections of short stories);<note>
                        While our analyses included the default standardization of all texts with
                        z-scores (such that variations in a term like <q>novel-length</q> no longer
                        come into play) and might have analyzed works of intentionally disparate
                        lengths, we wanted to ensure our corpus maintained a cohesive genre; the
                        phrase <q>novel-length fiction</q> is one common compromise. </note> second,
                    those texts needed to be published between 1900 and 1940;<note> Give or take a
                        year or two — we cheated, for example, to fit in Conrad’s <title
                            rend="italic">Heart of Darkness </title>(1899).</note> and third, those
                    works needed to be written in English. Bearing in mind the lessons of Jockers’s
                        <title rend="italic">Macroanalysis</title>, by narrowing our scope so
                    dramatically we tried our best to isolate gender and its stylistic pressures
                    from other well-known influencers of style like genre, period, translation, and
                    so on. We thus settled on 15 male and 15 female Anglo-modernists (Tables 1-2),
                    and chose three to five works from each, for a total of 141 texts (68 female, 73
                        male).<note> For the sake of space, the full text list isn’t included here,
                        but it is of course available upon request. </note>
                </p>

                <figure>
                    <head/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
                    <figDesc>image of two charts, one for female authors and one for male
                        authors</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p> If the process of forming a modernist corpus begets a state-of-the-field
                    question about the current archive of modernism, this study’s selection of
                    authors succeeds only in capturing a small, Anglophone, transatlantic subsection
                    of the diverse, global engagements with and reactions to the political, social,
                    and cultural investments of modernity. It is representative, that is, of only
                    one, precarious, incomplete variant of modernism — a small sample that allows us
                    to make clear claims about one subsection of modernist work. Archives, digital
                    or otherwise, summarize and sometimes disguise significant acts of scholarship,
                    and our own corpus operates with an agenda that erases as much as it attempts to
                    combat its erasures. The resulting selections are meant only to represent one
                    specific stylistic case — a rather <q>traditional</q> canon of Anglophone
                    modernist fiction<note> We would be remiss if we didn’t mention Evans and
                        Wilkens (2018) as a recent computational study that adds to the mounting
                        rationales <emph>against </emph>such a canon. The authors argue convincingly
                        that, when modeling British fiction as a whole (and not just its canonical
                        works), the modernist period produced narrative attentions to international
                        locales that greatly outnumbered national ones. Most modern British fiction,
                        that is, spent more time discussing international milieus than not, which
                        reaffirms concerns about the representative validity of something like an
                        orthodox canon of British modern fiction.</note> — among the many stylistic
                    cases of modernist literature, and we hope readers will forgive the
                    indiscretions of our modernist assemblage, knowing that this list of authors
                    could have taken any number of reasonable forms.<note> Hence conventional
                        caveats apply: our corpus may indeed produce a narrative driven by
                        ease-of-access or proximity over actual representativeness; a larger, more
                        diverse, more global (in short, a <q>different</q>) corpus may have provided
                        different results; and the claims we hope to make about gender and modernist
                        style thus can’t reliably be extrapolated to modernist literature’s other
                        flavors without further analysis. We admit this is a substantial, but so far
                        largely unavoidable, limitation of studying the literary canon of a period
                        still heavily under material and economic wraps. It’s reason, too, to be
                        skeptical of the midrange scale of our study, which ends by looking at one
                        text and one author and is thus not nearly as macroanalytic as most
                        stylometric studies of literature. (It should be said that Marks
                        Algee-Hewitt and McGurl explore this and other rationales of corpus-making
                        in the Stanford Literary Lab’s<title rend="italic"> Pamphlet 8</title>,
                            <title rend="quotes">Between Canon and Corpus: Six Perspectives on
                            20th-Century Novels,</title> 2-8.)</note>
                </p>
                <p> After just outlining some of the many problems of doing so, the irony of
                    organizing our study around normative gender categories has not eluded us.
                    Mandell announces that this very move is her topic of inquiry in the opening
                    chapter of a recent <title rend="italic">Debates in the DH</title> volume:
                        <quote rend="inline">in some quantitative cultural analyses, the category of
                        gender has been biologized, binarized, and essentialized in a trend that I
                        call <term>stereotyping</term></quote>; and if literary data has <quote
                        rend="inline">been collected, sorted, and even produced according to the
                        categories M/F,</quote> then it will find statistically significant
                    differences whether or not those differences are significant <ptr
                        target="#mandell2019"/>. An algorithm trained on constructed differences of
                    data (i.e. assigned authorial gender) does not sort through the world it
                    purports to represent, after all, but generates a new world through the measures
                    of difference with which we provide it. Bearing that considerable problem in
                    mind, and building on the foundations set by the many computational studies of
                    19th-century literature, our interest is not in asking if or where gender is
                    marked in fiction, but whether and how it <q>gives-to-see</q> the literary
                    styles and structures of modernist fiction. Because we rely on gender as a
                    historical category, we can learn about its in/stability and trans/formation
                    from the ways it is invoked, signaled, modified, or tailored textually, around
                    specific cultural contexts and social meanings and in relation to other texts.
                    As traditional, binary conceptions of gender began to be understood as
                    culturally, socially, politically, and legally affixed to bodies, modernist
                    authors might also have affixed them to — or unfixed them from — their texts at
                    a macro level, and we want to track the unique structural styling of gender in
                    those texts. </p>
                <p> Like most, our methods for doing so stylometrically rely on the production of a
                    table of word frequencies, from which stylistic similarity (based on statistical
                    distance) can be measured. Traditionally, the most influential words in these
                    tables are those function words, English’s grammatical glue (articles,
                    prepositions, pronouns, etc.), because it turns out that each author — and,
                    though to a lesser degree, each period, genre, and gender — uses each of those
                    words at a remarkably consistent rate in their own work, and at a unique rate
                    when compared to others.<note> Though, there are indeed more nuanced measures of
                        stylistic distance that weight function and content words in different ways.
                        Regardless, this general technique is often called the <term>bag of
                            words</term> approach, and while it is popular in text analysis it also
                        has its drawbacks. Its most basic model treats every word in each text in
                        the same way, regardless of that word’s (a) syntactic or semantic contexts
                        and (b) relation to the narrative or literary forms — thus, every novel
                        merely becomes a countable bag of words. The approach makes measuring
                        stylistic difference simple and effective, but in doing so it erases the
                        context of all other literary elements in a work, which makes <q>reading</q>
                        the resulting wordlists a precarious task. Take the exchange in <hi
                            rend="italic">Orlando</hi> between the newly acquainted Shelmerdine and
                        Orlando as a brief example — and take first a jumbled approximation of what
                        our machine sees, in the spirit of <term>big-data</term> experimentalism:
                            <q>a</q> (2), <q>cried</q> (2), <q>[a]re</q> (2), <q>you</q> (2),
                            <q>he</q> (1), <q>man</q> (1), <q>Orlando</q> (1), <q>she</q> (1),
                            <q>Shel</q> (1), <q>woman</q> (1). What’s happened in this sequence, now
                        that we’ve merely counted words and glossed over all context? Maybe a man
                        and a woman were crying together, but who really knows? The flattening
                        perils of decontextualized computational analysis are indeed laid bare. Now,
                        here’s the moment as it appears in the actual narrative: <quote
                            rend="inline">‘You’re a woman, Shel!’ she cried. ‘You’re a man,
                            Orlando!’ he cried.</quote> Even in a short, two-sentence example,
                        Woolf’s tremendous gender-/word-play and its meaning for the speakers, who
                        have fallen for one another (and soon marry) in part because of their gender
                        non-conforming androgyny, is entirely lost if one merely rushed to count
                        one’s computational chickens.</note> Stylometrists can then measure the
                    statistical distances between the styles of individual texts, authors, or other
                    groups (e.g. based on gender) to detect broad trends.<note> Although we don’t
                        engage with it here, Underwood and So have raised a few conceptual concerns
                        with this approach, asking recently whether statistical distance and
                        stylistic distance are comparable measures of relation at all <ptr
                            target="#underwood2021"/>.</note> This research has tended to take the
                    form of sorting and examining diverse most-frequent-word (MFW) lists made up of
                    other types of content words (nouns, verbs, adjectives, etc.) to locate
                    stylistic quirks or generate topics for close-reading. For instance, one group
                    of authors might prefer one term, set of terms, or set of topics over another —
                    or, they might not — and by contextualizing and interpreting the divergences or
                    convergences, critics can theorize what circumstances (generic, historical,
                    social) might contribute to similarity or difference. However, in this study, we
                    want to be particularly sensitive to the interpretive dangers in close-reading
                    individualized wordlists (either for authors or their texts) because of how our
                    digital design treats gender as a two-body problem. Fearing, that is, the equal
                    likelihood of finding gender-specific stylistic trends and replicating
                    essentializing discourses in our interpretations, we decided to take a less
                    orthodox path by staying <term>macro</term> and running a series of broader,
                    supervised machine-learning analyses on our modernist corpus.<note> A basic note
                        may be necessary regarding the difference between supervised and
                        unsupervised machine learning techniques (though, there are other techniques
                        that borrow from both types). Supervised techniques tend to require the
                        input of pre-classified data to <q>learn from,</q> so that the algorithm can
                        track and then predict future patterns from similarly classified data (e.g.
                        one might train a road sign classification machine on thousands of different
                        stop sign images, and then feed it other random images and ask it to output
                        whether or not they feature stop signs). Unsupervised machine learning,
                        conversely, tends to model the distribution or configuration of input data
                        (e.g. providing a large, unsorted data set of road sign images and some
                        metric of sorting them might provide correlations, groupings, or trends to
                        help identify or separate those images). For further reading on this
                        difference, and for the other variations of these methods, see
                        Shalev-Shwartz and Ben-David (2014), 4-6.</note>
                </p>
                <p> So, we trained our machine on the two groups of modernist texts (female, male),
                    asking it, in effect, to develop an average style for each group based on the
                    frequencies with which its authors used common words.<note> Our stylistic
                        analysis was done entirely through Eder et al.’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Stylo</title> package in the statistical computing program, R <ptr
                            target="#eder2016b"/>. Although we’ve chosen a supervised analysis, its
                        methodological limitations are significant. The benefit of unsupervised
                        learning (e.g. PCA) is that the machine doesn’t know how many groups of data
                        we think we’re studying, so we can’t privilege a group split just because we
                        think there is one; the difficulty becomes identifying what features,
                        exactly, constitute the groupings output by the machine. Inversely, the
                        downside of a supervised analysis is that we organize the data in two
                        pre-conceived groups and ask that each text be assigned to one group or the
                        other. The benefit is that we at least think we have an idea of where
                        machine-located differences are coming from — i.e. in this case, we isolate
                        our groups based on gender. Both methods put us in an at least somewhat
                        compromised position when drawing conclusions about gender and its stylistic
                        features.</note> We then gave it sequences of random groupings of six
                    different texts (three male, three female), which it had to correctly place in
                    the corresponding author’s associated sex. By random chance, the
                    machine will assign any text to its correct group 50% of the time — with two
                    possible groups in our analysis, the algorithm has the equivalent of a digital
                    coin toss — which means that anything consistently or considerably more accurate
                    suggests there may be measurable stylistic differences between the two groups.
                    Among hundreds of classifying runs, misattributions occurred on average about
                    10% of the time; the classifier accurately determined the assigned gender of a
                    text’s author in around 90% of cases, which supports the notion that even given
                    the experiments of modernism, the period’s sex-gender binary seems to remain a
                    strong determiner of style.<note> One digital interpretation of the stylistic
                        distinctiveness between the genders in modernism has been advanced elsewhere
                            <ptr target="#weidman2018"/> . Again, as Mandell notes, this measure of
                            <soCalled>textual gender</soCalled> alone is not terribly interesting;
                        traditional social and cultural gender signaling is perfectly expected in
                        literary work and, in this case, we also constructed our data to produce a
                        split along that line of pre-sorted difference <ptr target="#mandell2019"/>.
                    </note> We utilized a series of different test conditions to ensure our results
                    weren’t skewed with any one set of parameters,<note> We forced the machine, for
                        example, to cull words that didn’t appear in most or all of the texts (to
                        prevent particularly uncommon themes, narrative locations, or character
                        names to artificially amplify differences); we used different MFW counts
                        (50, 100, 200, … 1000) to see if a more robust set of word frequencies would
                        change our findings; we employed a variety of sampling methods, from
                        analyzing each text in its entirety to including only one or two random,
                        bag-of-word samples; and we even swapped between statistical distance
                        measures, seeing similar results from Burrows’s Delta and the Wurzburg
                        Cosine — though we talk more in footnotes 28 and 34 about why we limited
                        this particular adjustment. </note> and though our tests turned up fleeting
                    misattributions — among other examples, the machine assigned a random sample
                    from Hemingway’s <title rend="italic">For Whom the Bell Tolls </title>to the
                    female group, and it ascribed several samples from Radclyffe Hall’s <title
                        rend="italic">Well of Loneliness </title>to the male set<note> This finding
                        about Hall is especially intriguing; though we haven’t space to discuss the
                        novel here, Hall’s protagonist, the <q>sexual invert</q> Stephen
                        Gordon, is narrated through much of the same language as Woolf’s in <title
                            rend="italic">Orlando</title>, a comparison that certainly warrants
                        further study.</note> — we produced one misattribution that was both more
                    frequent and more consistent than the rest: Virginia Woolf’s 1928 novel, <title
                        rend="italic">Orlando: A Biography</title>. </p>
                <p> Common stylometric practice says to zoom in here and discern why <title
                        rend="italic">Orlando </title>is an outlier — and options abound for doing
                    so: we might, for example, compare individual wordlists of each gender grouping,
                    or of the text itself, or of the words preferred or avoided by one gender
                    grouping/text over another. Again, however, our interest is in staying macro.
                    Having already separated the novels into male and female groups, the wordlists only and unsurprisingly provide the same
                    stylistic snapshot that has been traced extensively
                    elsewhere (as our previous section details). We know that even as standard uses
                    sometimes lead to surprising ends, male and female authors normally reproduce
                    socially, culturally, historically consistent accounts of gender in their
                    writing, often through predictable and stereotypically gendered
                    characterizations, vocabularies, narrative actions, identifiers, and
                        locales.<note> Many of the studies from Jockers and Underwood, for example,
                        discern as much in their 19th-century and contemporary corpuses, and
                        alongside at least one other aforementioned piece <ptr target="#cheng2020"
                        />, one of our prior essays confirms those findings in modernist fiction
                            <ptr target="#weidman2018"/>.</note> Relocating the gender difference we
                    structured our study around is not so interesting to us. What we want to
                    ascertain, separately, is whether we can deploy stylometric methods without
                    double-reading gendered cultural meaning into a list of semantic differences
                    like verb constructions or function words. What if we apply stylometry to zoom out to
                    the level of a whole text rather than its list of words? What does gender
                    play look like within our small modernist corpus if we treat it as, for
                    instance, an element of narrative structuring?</p>
                <p> Instead of studying how male and female authors diverged in word choice or
                    grammatical preference, then, we decided to look at the overarching structure of
                    that difference in our consistent outlier, <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>.
                    To do so, we ran a more specific classification Eder calls a <term>Rolling
                        NSC.</term><note> For a detailed explanation of the <term>nearest shrunken
                            centroid</term> (NSC) method of classification, see Jockers and Witten
                        (2010). For a specific description of the technical features of NSC as
                        applied in <title rend="italic">Stylo</title>, see Eder (2016). As a
                        stylometric classifier that finds an averaged stylistic profile, NSC
                        provides certain benefits over a standard variant like Burrows’s Delta in
                        Eder’s rolling method, which tries to pinpoint moments of stylistic
                            <q>takeover</q> in a single text after being trained on one more groups
                        of texts <ptr target="#eder2016a" loc="459–63"/>. With Delta, each text in
                        each training group is treated distinctly and is not consolidated into a
                        stylistic profile (i.e. <title rend="italic">Orlando </title>is measured
                        against <emph>each</emph> training sample/text, ranking the
                            <soCalled>styles</soCalled> that are closest to the test text); NSC,
                        however, produces composites against which we can compare our test text
                        (i.e. <title rend="italic">Orlando </title> against the averaged style of
                        all female texts or all male texts). For our study, where we want to isolate
                        the gender binary as a two-class problem, NSC is a natural fit. </note> This
                    method also requires that we train the machine on our two gender groups, but
                    rather than supply it with a random selection of texts to assign, we ask it to
                    analyze slices of one particular text — in this case, <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando</title> — and then assign each slice to its stylistically closest
                    group/gender. To make matters more interesting, we isolated our test author, so
                    that none of Woolf’s other works appeared in the training sample or contributed
                    to the averaged style of the female set; if she had a particularly strong author
                    signal (and she does), this process would prevent her unique style from
                    overpowering the average gendered style that results from the amalgam of her
                    contemporaries’ works.<note> This control turned out to matter little — when we
                        reintroduced her remaining texts to the training set and re-ran the
                        analysis, the results were nearly identical. </note> For sake of reference,
                    we did the same analysis on a number of other randomly selected texts and, as is
                    to be expected with a ~90% attribution rate, most slices of most novels were
                    correctly assigned to their author’s corresponding gender (Figures 1-2).<note>
                        Although we analyzed each text at 50-1000 MFWs with culling from 0-50% and
                        received remarkably negligible variation in our results, for exact
                        reproducibility’s sake, each NSC classification image we included here was
                        produced at 500 MFWs and 0% culling.</note> In other words, most modernist
                    authors in our corpus write more like the other modernists of their sex, and do so
                    consistently and for the entirety of each novel, which appears to be the stylistic 
                    norm in literature regardless of period. </p>


                <figure>
                    <head>James Joyce’s <title rend="italic">Portrait of the Artist as a Young
                            Man</title> as seen through the <title rend="quotes"
                            >rolling.classify</title> function of <title rend="italic"
                        >Stylo</title>; the green line is actually made up of many thinner segments,
                        5000-word slices of the novel, each of which overlaps by 4500 words, and all
                        of which were classified as <q>male</q> in style.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
                    <figDesc>Image of a bar graph</figDesc>
                </figure>


                <figure>
                    <head>Jean Rhys’s <title rend="italic">Quartet</title> as seen through the
                            <title rend="quotes">rolling.classify</title> function of <title
                            rend="italic">Stylo</title>; the red line is similarly made up of
                        5000-word slices of the novel, each of which overlaps by 4500 words, and all
                        of which were classified as <q>female</q> in style.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
                    <figDesc>Image of a bar graph</figDesc>
                </figure>


                <p> But <title rend="italic">Orlando </title>presents an atypical case — and to an
                    extraordinary degree (Figure 3). About 32,000 words into the novel, the
                    seemingly misclassified <q>male</q> style of Virginia Woolf abruptly changes,
                    and the algorithm attributes the remainder of the novel’s style to the correctly
                    assigned sex. More extraordinary, even, is what takes place narratively at the
                    stylistic switch. The barely visible vertical dotted line marked
                    '<emph>a</emph>' in Figure 3, which lines up almost perfectly with the moment of
                    stylistic gender reassignment, if you will, comes just after our protagonist
                    Orlando is awakened in dramatic fashion from a weeklong slumber, and as those
                    around him make a startling discovery:</p>
                <p>
                    <quote rend="block">
                        <p> We are, therefore, now left entirely alone in the room with the sleeping
                            Orlando and the trumpeters. The trumpeters, ranging themselves side by
                            side in order, blow one terrific blast — </p>
                        <p> ‘THE TRUTH!’</p>
                        <p> at which Orlando woke.</p>
                        <p> He stretched himself. He rose. He stood upright in complete nakedness
                            before us, and while the trumpets pealed Truth! Truth! Truth! we have no
                            choice left but confess — he was a woman.</p>
                        <ptr target="#woolf1928" loc="87"/>
                    </quote>
                    
                </p>



                <figure>
                    <head>Virginia Woolf’s <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>. The slices (and
                        500-word incremental changes) are more visible here, and their overlap shows
                        the sudden stylistic transition — from stylistically <q>male</q> to
                            <q>female</q> — about a third of the way through the novel. The smaller
                        peaks/valleys represent the model’s less-certain detection of each gender’s
                        style.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
                    <figDesc>Image of a bar graph</figDesc>
                </figure>


                <p> As she narrates a sex change in her story, Woolf actively styles a gender
                    signature to match that of her character, a creative feat no other author — of
                        <emph>any</emph> period — has managed, as far as we know. It’s difficult to
                    explain just how unusual this is, in part because our subsection of modernist
                    fiction doesn’t speak for all of modernism (let alone all of fiction), but in
                    larger part because we’ve just never seen anything like this before. If our
                    analysis isolated a descriptive, content-based lexicon (nouns, verbs, adverbs,
                    adjectives), something like this result would be expected, at least to a degree.
                    Several of the studies we outlined in the last section confirm that regardless
                    of an author’s gender, talented writers are capable of imitating aspects of
                    another gender in their writing (preferred behaviors, contexts, spaces, styles
                    of speaking, etc.), a fact likely truer still for a writer as accomplished as
                    Woolf. In our analyses, however, which again ranged from 50 to 500 MFW, the
                    words we used to measure literary style are largely just those functional,
                    non-descriptive terms void of explicit narrative context. This means that Woolf
                    didn’t simply change the <emph>what</emph>, the content her male-turned-female
                    protagonist was thinking, saying, or doing — she fundamentally changed the
                        <emph>how</emph>, the grammar and syntax that holds that content
                        together.<note> Burrows’s aforementioned 1986 study, among other
                        contemporary versions — e.g. Pennebaker’s <title rend="italic">The Secret
                            Life of Pronouns </title>(2011) — was among the first to explore just
                        how important function words were to the close analysis of literary style.
                        Remarkable, then, that Woolf seems to have divined and manipulated this
                        reality half-a-century earlier and without the benefit of computational
                        analysis.</note> Perhaps how this came to pass, as <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando</title>’s narrator relates, matters little: <quote rend="inline">It
                        is enough for us to state the simple fact; Orlando was a man till the age of
                        thirty; when he became a woman and has remained so ever since</quote>
                    <ptr target="#woolf1928" loc="88"/>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><title rend="italic">Orlando</title> at the Limits of Modernist
                    Stylometry</head>

                <p>If we turn to the literary criticism on <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>, the
                    impressiveness of this stylistic manipulation would seem inevitable given the
                    theoretical projects the novel is said to carry out. <quote rend="inline">Long
                        before university Gender Studies departments came into existence,</quote>
                    writes Anne Delaplace, <quote rend="inline">Woolf had already reflected on the
                        dissonance between social and sexual identity</quote> in <title
                        rend="italic">Orlando</title>, which retains echoes of the
                        <quote rend="inline">intermix[ing]</quote> of genders from the exploration of androgyny in
                        <title rend="italic">A Room of One’s Own</title>
                    <ptr target="#delaplace2011" loc="39"/>. Indeed, <quote rend="inline">in every
                        human being,</quote> says <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>’s narrator,
                        <quote rend="inline">a vacillation from one sex to the other takes place,
                        and often it is only the clothes that keep the male or female likeness,
                        while underneath the sex is the very opposite of what it is above</quote>
                    <ptr target="#woolf1928" loc="121"/>. For Pamela Caughie, the novel provides
                    nothing less than the archetypal <quote rend="inline">model of modernist life
                        writing in the era of transsexualism,</quote> a unique, modernist
                        <quote rend="inline">transgenre</quote> that <quote rend="inline">radically refigures the
                        narrative of transsexualism</quote>
                    <ptr target="#caughie2013" loc="502–4"/>.<note> Several related essays warrant a
                        brief mention here: Brenda Helt’s <title rend="quotes">Passionate Debates on
                            ‘Odious Subjects’: Bisexuality and Woolf’s Opposition to Theories of
                            Androgyny and Sexual Identity</title> (2010) provides an argument for
                        using bisexuality to describe Woolf’s depictions of desire; Jessica Berman’s
                            <title rend="quotes">Is the Trans in Transnational the Trans in
                            Transgender</title> (2017) offers a discussion of how Orlando’s
                        transnational roaming contributes to Woolf’s critique of imperial
                        masculinity via Orlando’s seamless gender transition; and Madelyn Detloff’s
                            <title rend="quotes">Camp Orlando (or) Orlando</title> (2016) provides
                        an account of the camp sensibilities and reparative work of <title
                            rend="italic">Orlando</title>.</note> These literary critics identify
                    clearly the power of Woolf’s novel as it derives from close readings of context
                    and narrative, producing feminist modes of representation for non-normative
                    sexuality and genders through its play of literary genre — in Caughie’s case,
                    the biography, mock or not. Elsa Högberg and Amy Bromley even consider <title
                        rend="italic">Orlando </title>the novel that inaugurated Woolf’s theory of
                    sentence morphology, the way Woolf playfully reshapes formal and generic
                    sentence structures to mark a <quote rend="inline">modernist rewriting of
                        biography and gender, and the orthodox ways in which they tend to shape life
                        and the body</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hogberg2018" loc="2"/>.</p>
                <p> Keeping with these accounts, we simply want to make one vital addendum: that the
                    novel’s power — as proto-gender study or as transgenre — emerges from Woolf’s
                    style. Again, while not every novel in our analysis was always assigned so
                    tidily to one gender or another, no text separated as consistently or in such a
                    structured manner as <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> — on cue, as it were,
                    with the gender transition in its narrative. That level of stylistic control
                    raises new questions about the scales of gender performativity, or rather
                    focuses them down to the level of the line, the choice of one (seemingly
                    insignificant) function word over the other, which complicates readings of
                        <title rend="italic">Orlando </title>as a tale of cross-dressing, in which
                    clothes make the (wo)man without regard for the discursive power wielded in the
                    creation of <q>men</q> and <q>women.</q> Woolf, it seems, did not merely change
                    the descriptions and clothes of her protagonist and so change the gender; she
                    altered the very stylistic nuances that characterized Orlando when she was a
                    woman from when he was a man. Hers isn’t just a narrative exploration of
                    transition either, in the vein of Dr. Matthew O’Connor in Djuna Barnes’s <title
                        rend="italic">Nightwood</title> or Leopold Bloom in James Joyce’s <title
                        rend="italic">Ulysses</title>.<note> We steal both examples directly from
                        Emma Heaney’s magnificent book, <title rend="italic">The New Woman: Literary
                            Modernism, Queer Theory, and the Trans Feminine Allegory</title> (2017).
                        In fact, Heaney’s exploration of the history and production of trans
                        femininity provides an important clarification to our study’s finding,
                        detaching Woolf from a legacy of modernist trans feminism <ptr
                            target="#heaney2017" loc="302 (note 11)"/>.</note> That her writing
                    diverges so thoroughly from the stylistic doxa of her contemporaries suggests to
                    us that, as Woolf celebrates the new possibilities of being gendered and
                    representing genderedness, she delivers a linguistic paradigm of that futurity.
                    In <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>, Woolf not only cultivates a sustained,
                    pluralist theory of gender transition, but she also practices the linguistic
                    applications of its modern futures, a multifaceted engagement that perhaps no
                    other author had actualized before.</p>
                <p> In this our study deviates from the findings of several aforementioned accounts
                    of gender and literary style (e.g. the work of Jockers and Kirilloff (2016) on
                    gender in 19th-century fiction), which tend to suggest gender-disciplinary
                    social norms had significant and, by extension, inextricable effects on
                    literature’s stylistic structures. Most stylometric studies that isolate gender
                    within a corpus of literature treat it similarly, as a governing stylistic force
                    that manifests in formal semantic preferences or syntactic characteristics. In
                    the case of Anglo-modernist fiction, though, staying out of the wordlists forces
                    a change in perspective.<note> We understand, of course, that we still depend on
                        averaged literary styles (via a bag-of-word list of most frequent terms) in
                        this study, and we do not call that essential stylometric practice into
                        question. What we’re after here, rather, is a reimagining of how eschewing
                        the inexact close-readings that tend to follow computational measures of
                        style can actually help us accomplish something critically important.
                        Deciphering averaged stylistic differences — or, what’s more probable,
                        incidentally lodging our pre-held assumptions into stylistic peculiarities —
                        does not expand or contextualize our conclusions as much as it forecloses
                        their messiness in almost-assuredly biased explainers. By restraining that
                        stylometric impulse, we hope to let the text’s relation to the corpus
                        (rather than specific terminological connections/disparities) do the
                        critical work for us. We want to venture an observation here, one helped
                        along by Adam Kilgarriff’s influential essay, <title rend="quotes">Language
                            is never, ever, ever, random</title> (2005) and its adjacent, clarifying
                        distinction between <soCalled>randomness</soCalled> and
                            <soCalled>arbitrariness</soCalled> in interpretations of linguistic
                        phenomena in literary corpora. That linguistic structures appear nonrandom
                        or predictable in their relation does not make that relation meaningful —
                        just as syntax can colonize meaning, narrative structures can demand certain
                        forms, patterns, and distributions of linguistic content, which detaches
                        judgments about their meaning from their possible literary-historical or
                        sociocultural arbitrariness. Having used a specific corpus organization and
                        specific modeling tools, all of which were designed to treat gender as a
                        bimodal stylistic question, we think finding in <title rend="italic">Orlando
                        </title>a nonrandom and narratively nonarbitrary gender flip is more than a
                        linguistic oddity. </note> Perhaps the period’s history of gender and
                    literary style is more than a sum of linguistic tendencies, or more than
                    gender’s socially, culturally, politically enforced written marking. In her
                    innovative styling of gender transition, Woolf shows that this history is also
                    an account of gender’s <emph>un</emph>marking and <emph>un</emph>disciplining.
                    Perhaps all that Woolf intuited is that gender needn’t have been as influential
                    on literary style as we think it must have been; or, perhaps Woolf saw that our
                    ideas about gender do not so much influence literary style as literary style
                    influences our ideas about gender. If <title rend="italic">Orlando
                    </title>declares gender as merely the newest formal territory on which writers
                    could experiment with identity, then it uncovers for us Woolf’s broader way of
                    modern seeing, which could understand gender not as an imminent, immutable,
                    uniform stylistic determiner, but as a flexible literary landscape — or, what
                    comes to the same thing, as a social text, a style.<note> Following Rachael
                        Scarborough King’s delineation of form and genre, we might even call the
                        literary style of gender a <emph>genre</emph>, an organizing metanarrative,
                            <quote rend="inline">a collection whose members are assembled and whose
                            boundaries are always permeable</quote>
                        <ptr target="#king2021" loc="262"/>. </note>
                </p>
                <p> Taking a step back, and stealing from the punchy clarity of Stephen Ramsay, we
                    want to repeat a key clarification: <quote rend="inline">We are not trying to
                        solve Woolf</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ramsay2011" loc="15"/>. We instead want to use <title
                        rend="italic">Orlando </title>to wonder whether the current registers of
                    stylometry and computational stylistics stymie some of the radical potentials of
                    modernist style. Because we constructed this stylometric study around a
                    constricting binary gender logic, it can only tell us so much about that binary
                    or what constitutes its differences, especially with tools applied as narrowly
                    as we apply them here (e.g. on a relatively small modernist corpus, and then on
                    a single modernist text relative to that corpus). Stylometric methods, like
                    other forms of quantitative formalism, can’t exactly be employed in pursuit of
                    such a task, particularly when our assumptions need to be levied in service of
                    cultural and social conclusions to make them critically relevant. Most studies of gender
                    and literary style have tended to assume that if a linguistic difference can be computationally
                    tracked along gender lines, that difference must divulge something about gender’s lived differences
                    or material history. But we are not convinced this is
                    always true. Sometimes the only thing stylistic difference informs is our
                    understanding of failed historical representation, or a history of
                        <emph>un</emph>lived difference, or (in our case) gender’s otherwise hidden
                    potentials. Despite writing from within a descriptive system that inhibits
                    gender identity’s expression and possible futures — and despite being studied
                    from within the same — Woolf still teaches us about the ways gender/ing could be
                    deployed, inverted, and resisted, a didactic function that materializes even
                    through, even as, the digital recording of a broken and insufficient gender
                    binary.</p>
                <p> Our brief analysis of <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> should suggest that
                    stylometry even applied narrowly can still teach us a great deal about, say, the
                    depth of modernism’s <emph>avant garde</emph> or about the limitations of
                    studying style as a consistent and formal indicator of real-world messiness.
                    After all, it’s through our study’s significant structural limitations that we
                    see the extent to which modernists could make their styles fit (or an ill fit
                    for) its categories — see, that is, how Woolf fashioned gender in, out, and
                    around the binary trying to contain it. So what other realignments might Woolf’s
                    modernist experiment afford within the genealogy of gender and computational
                    literary studies? Two observations seem essential: the first, a minor point
                    about exemplarity, will lead us to the second, a broader claim about the limits of 
                    studying modern(ist) sociocultural forms through stylometric analysis. </p>
                <p> Christy Burns asserts that <quote rend="inline">in <title rend="italic">Orlando
                        </title>Woolf has already […] anticipated our attempts to clothe her
                    writings in our own desires,</quote> for the very reason that <quote
                        rend="inline">the curious residue of language […] both invites and resists
                        our insistent refigurations, our attempts to make Woolf conform to our
                        societal demands</quote> 
                    <ptr target="#burns1994" loc="359"/>. In this unique anticipatory capacity
                    Woolf’s novel comes to represent an exceptional case in our corpus of modernist
                    fiction, both through its multi-century generic scope and through its stylistic
                    flexibility. Its uniqueness thus poses an interpretive problem: How can we draw
                    general conclusions about Anglophone modernism, or about gender and modernist
                    literature, from a text so different from the rest, a novel that singularly
                    rejects what we thought we knew about the relationship between gender identities
                    and literary style?<note> This is a problem Piper (2020) has recently aimed to
                        tackle at much greater length and with much greater care than we do
                        here.</note>
                </p>
                <p> According to Ben Etherington and Sean Pryor, by focusing on such exceptional
                    cases scholars <quote rend="inline">can actively resist the falsifications and
                        exclusions performed by the abstract generalisations of history, theory, and
                        society at large</quote>
                    <ptr target="#etherington2019" loc="7"/>. Stylometry notwithstanding,
                    computational methods of analyzing literature attempt to discern a set of
                    generalities that can cater to the macroanalytic at the cost of particulars,
                    outliers or exceptions that sometimes require culling or discarding. But if
                    Woolf’s unprecedented literary experimentalism is what makes her an exemplary
                    modernist — which is the case made by Burns and many other modernist critics —
                    perhaps <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>’s exceptionalism is what makes it
                    an ideal text from which to generalize. If, in numerous cases of Anglophone
                    modernism, the experimentally exceptional <emph>is</emph> the general,<note> As
                        Pryor notes elsewhere, <quote rend="inline">the category of modernism was
                            developed through attention to exemplars</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pryor2019" loc="37"/>. </note> then the discovery of new forms
                    of difference in that literature, like <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>’s
                    stylistic play, requires that the very category of <q>general</q> be
                    productively expanded to include even its most remarkable outliers. And when the
                    general example produces an updated interpretive scale or model, then it also
                    produces an updated politics of historical interpretation consistent with that
                    model, a politics that scholars like Burns would insist Woolf not only refuses
                    but remakes.<note> Etherington and Pryor also clarify this point: <quote
                            rend="inline">because exemplarity conditions the production of
                            knowledge, helping to construct the very object of inquiry, it is also a
                            political problem</quote>
                        <ptr target="#etherington2019" loc="5"/>.</note> Another way to say this is
                    that, as Woolf invents a new means by which gender could be individually styled
                    and proven as style, she shows that our general, normative understanding of the
                    conditions and capabilities of fiction for representing gendered life is
                    incomplete and in need of expansion. Literary critics have known about this
                    capacity of Woolf for a long time, of course, but this stylometric view of
                        <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> demonstrates just how acutely she
                    played with gender as itself a type of literary style. There is no solving Woolf
                    here, as Ramsay says, because Woolf fundamentally changes the stylistic
                    equation, widening modernism’s scope of the representatively possible.</p>
                <p> To our second point, then, and contrary to what most digital humanists have
                    found by studying the literature of the 19th century, Woolf proves again that
                    modernist literature generated denaturalizing and atypical movements of gender
                        <emph>as</emph> and <emph>through</emph>, and not merely <emph>in</emph>,
                    its styles. Modernists, we know, were among the first generations of writers
                    fundamentally influenced by the reality that unconscious forces construct
                        us,<note> This is a claim that has long since entered modernist criticism's common
                        vocabulary, but see, among other examples: Maud Ellman, <title rend="italic"
                            >Nets of Modernism: Henry James, Virginia Woolf, James Joyce, and
                            Sigmund Freud</title> (2010); Matt Ffytch, <title rend="quotes">The
                            Modernist Road to the Unconscious</title> (2012); and, for a classic
                        account of this impact on modern culture generally, Michael North, <title
                            rend="italic">Reading 1922: A Return to the Scene of the Modern</title>
                        (1999).</note> and it’s essential to remember that their words are thus not
                    simply markers of hidden sociocultural powers and discourses, but that they
                    instead represent — for one of the first times in modern literary history —
                    active, ongoing, deliberate engagements with those discourses as they knew they
                    were appearing in their literature. Hopefully it’s clear how our point about
                    exemplarity is a stepping-stone to this. When we arrive in modernism, a period
                    in which authors, figures, writers, and thinkers were quite explicitly styling
                    gender and its cultural markers, tracing a gender signal in writing and
                    attaching its features to latent cultural realities is no longer quite as
                    defensible by the logic used in stylometric studies of 19th-century literature.
                    As Woolf herself says elsewhere, theirs was already <quote rend="inline">an age
                        clearly when we are not fast anchored where we are; things are moving round
                        us; we are moving ourselves</quote>
                    <ptr target="#woolf2009" loc="74"/>.</p>
                <p> Simply put, what we imagine to be the latent, stylistic territory of stylometry
                    (and other computational methods invested in written style) cannot be trusted to
                    have been latent at all in modernism. Woolf’s experiment reminds us that the
                    fundamental assumption of traditional stylometry is notoriously unreliable:
                    namely, that authors and specified groups have distinct, independent, hidden
                    markers of style we can compare and from which we can glean social and cultural
                    insight — about, for instance, the intentional or accidental written production
                    of gender. Earlier we argued that modernism hasn’t been studied digitally for
                    two reasons, but this would offer a third: treating modern style as a proxy for
                    (or reflection of) the linguistic features of modern identity can neither be
                    done dependably nor without presuming to already know, and thus arrange a study
                    around, where identity begins and ends for literary stylists. Scholars
                    leveraging stylometric methods to analyze modernist literature must contend with
                    modernism’s unique self-awareness in this regard — the ways stylistic
                    experimentation may limit the conclusions that can be drawn from modernist
                    language about the conditions of modern life. <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando</title>’s remarkable stylistic play gives us reason to pause, in
                    other words, reason to question stylometry’s ability to contextualize gender and
                    modernism in the same breath. </p>
                <p> We do not mean to suggest that stylometry is fundamentally an ill-fitted tool
                    for studying modernism and gender, or even modern identity writ large. We simply
                    want to point out that modernism, perhaps more so than other aesthetic movements
                    or literary periods, necessitates a critical mutuality that requires from its
                    scholars an upfront and explicit negotiation between object and method, accident
                    and intention, style and styling. As interpretive constraints, these tensions
                    might even address why there isn’t much serious stylometric work on modernism —
                    and perhaps why there should be. If we want the future of modernity’s digital
                    literary study to have any kind of educational end, and if we indeed think that
                    stylometry can spill forth new insights about (or models of) the
                    representational histories of social experience (vis-à-vis linguistic style),
                    then a crucial part of such projects must be to gauge how the limitations of our
                    tools might help us to study differently the sociocultural traces of modern
                    identity and its stylistic waves. Maybe Woolf isn’t the first or only author to
                    make the necessity of this reorientation so evident, but <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando</title> certainly illustrates the extents to which, when applied to
                    and in modernism, both our literary data and our digital-critical methods must
                    become more than <quote rend="inline">mere containers</quote> of language’s
                    curious residues <ptr target="#posner2017" loc="4"/>
                    <ptr target="#burns1994" loc="359"/>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>

        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adwetewabadu2020" label="Adwetewa 2020"> Adwetewa-Badu, Ama Bemma.
                        <title rend="quotes">Poetry from Afar: Distant Reading, Global Poetics, and
                        the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Modernism/modernity Print Plus</title> 5, no. 1
                    (2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="algeehewitt2015a" label="Algee-Hewitt 2015"> Algee-Hewitt, Mark.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Performance of Character: Digital Models for
                        Gendered Speech in Romantic period Literature.</title> Lecture at Simon
                    Fraser University, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="algeehewitt2015b" label="Algee-Hewitt and McGurl 2015"> Algee-Hewitt,
                    Mark and Mark McGurl. <title rend="quotes">Between Canon and Corpus: Six
                        Perspectives on 20th-Century Novels.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary Lab: Pamphlet 8</title> (2015): 1-27.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="battershill2017" label="Battershill et al. 2017"> Battershill, Claire,
                    Helen Southworth, Alice Staveley, Michael Widner, Elizabeth Willson Gordon, and
                    Nicola Wilson. <title rend="italic">Scholarly Adventures in Digital Humanities:
                        Making The Modernist Archives Publishing Project</title>. Routledge,
                    2017.</bibl>
               
                <bibl xml:id="bode2018" label="Bode 2018"> Bode, Katherine. <title rend="italic">A
                        World of Fiction: Digital Collections and the Future of Literary
                        History</title>. U of Michigan P, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bode2017" label="Bode 2017"> Bode, Katherine. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Equivalence of ‘Close’ and “Distant’ Reading; or, Toward a New Object for
                        Data-Rich Literary History.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</title> 78, no. 1 (2017):
                    77-106.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2018" label="Brown and Mandell 2018"> Brown, Susan, and Laura
                    Mandell. <title rend="quotes">The Identity Issue: An Introduction.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics </title>(Feb. 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrows1986" label="Burrows 1986"> Burrows, John F. <title
                        rend="italic">Computation into Criticism: A Study of Jane Austen’s Novels
                        and an Experiment in Method</title>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1986.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burns1994" label="Burns 1994"> Burns, Christy L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Re-Dressing Feminist Identities: Tensions between Essential and Constructed
                        Selves in Virginia Woolf’s <title rend="italic">Orlando</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Twentieth Century Literature</title> 40, no. 3 (1994): 342-
                    64.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="butler1990" label="Butler 1990"> Butler, Judith.<title rend="italic"
                        >Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity</title>. Routledge,
                    1990.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="butler1993" label="Butler 1993"> Butler, Judith. <title rend="italic"
                        >Bodies That Matter: On the Discursive Limits of “Sex.</title> Routledge,
                    1993.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caughie2013" label="Caughie 2013"> Caughie, Pamela L. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Temporality of Modernist Life Writing in the Era of
                        Transsexualism: Virginia Woolf’s <title rend="italic">Orlando</title> and
                        Einar Wegener’s <title rend="italic">Man Into Woman</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modern Fiction Studies</title> 59, no. 3 (2013):
                    501-25.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caughie2018" label="Caughie et al. 2018"> Caughie, Pamela L., Emily
                    Datskou,&amp; Rebecca Parker. <title rend="quotes">Storm clouds on the horizon:
                        feminist ontologies and the problem of gender.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feminist Modernist Studies </title>1, no. 3 (2018):
                    230-42.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cheng2020" label="Cheng 2020"> Cheng, Jonathan Y. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Fleshing Out Models of Gender in English-Language Novels
                        (1850-2000).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics </title>(Jan. 2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="christie2014" label="Christie et al. 2014"> Christie, Alex, et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities.</title>
                    Humanities Commons, 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="churchill2018" label="Churchill et al. 2018"> Churchill, Suzanne W.,
                    Linda A. Kinnahan, and Susan Rosenbaum. <title rend="quotes">Feminist designs:
                        modernist digital humanities and<title rend="italic">Mina Loy: Navigating
                            the Avant-Garde</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feminist Modernist Studies</title> 1, no. 3 (2018):
                    243-56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="da2019" label="Da 2019"> Da, Nan Z. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Computational Case against Computational Literary Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry </title> 45, no. 3 (2019): 601-39.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="delaplace2011" label="Delaplace 2011"> Delaplace, Anne. <title
                        rend="quotes">Transcending Gender: Virginia Woolf and Marcel Proust, Orlando
                        and Albertine.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Virginia Woolf Bulletin</title> 37 (2011): 37-41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dignazio2016" label="D'Ignazio and Klein 2016"> D’Ignazio, Catherine,
                    and Lauren F. Klein. <title rend="quotes">Feminist Data Visualization.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE VIS4DH Conference</title>, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drouin2014" label="Drouin 2014"> Drouin, Jeffrey. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Close- And Distant-Reading Modernism: Network Analysis, Text Mining, and
                        Teaching <title rend="italic">The Little Review</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Journal of Modern Periodical Studies</title> 5, no. 1
                    (2014): 110-35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2017" label="Drucker 2017"> Drucker, Johanna. <title
                        rend="quotes">Why Distant Reading Isn’t.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 132, no. 3 (2017): 628-35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="earhart2020" label="Earhart et al. 2020"> Earhart, Amy E., Roopika
                    Risam, and Matthew Bruno. <title rend="quotes">Citational politics: Quantifying
                        the influence of gender on citation in <title rend="italic">Digital
                            Scholarship in the Humanities.</title></title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>. Preprint, 3
                    August 2020.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eder2016a" label="Eder 2016"> Eder, Maciej. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Rolling stylometry.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 31, no. 3
                    (2016): 457- 69.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eder2016b" label="Eder et al. 2016"> Eder, Maciej, Jan Rybicki, and
                    Mike Kestemont. <title rend="quotes">Stylometry with R: A Package for
                        Computational Text Analysis.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">R Journal</title> 8, no. 1 (2016): 107-21.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etherington2019" label="Etherington and Pryor 2019"> Etherington, Ben,
                    and Sean Pryor. <title rend="quotes">Historical poetics and the problem of
                        exemplarity.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Quarterly</title>61, no. 1 (2019): 3-17.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="evans2018" label="Evan and Wilkens 2018"> Evans, Elizabeth F., and
                    Matthew Wilkens. <title rend="quotes">Nation, Ethnicity, and the Geography of
                        British Fiction, 1880-1940.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (Jul. 2018).</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="golden2018" label="Golden and Laity 2018"> Golden, Amanda, and
                    Cassandra Laity, <title rend="quotes">Feminist Modernist Digital
                        Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Feminist Modernist Studies</title>
                    1, no. 3 (2018), 205-210.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gonzalez2019" label="Gonzalez et al. 2019"> González, José Eduardo,
                    Montserrat-Fuente Camacho, and Marcus Barbosa. <title rend="quotes">Detecting
                        Modernismo’s Fingerprint: A Digital Humanities Approach to the Turn of the
                        Century Spanish American Novel.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Review: Literature and Arts of the Americas</title> 51, no.
                    2 (2019): 195-204.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hankins2018a" label="Hankins 2018 a"> Hankins, Gabriel. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Weak Powers of Digital Modernist Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modernism/Modernity</title> 25, no. 3 (2018):
                    569-585.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hankins2018b" label="Hankins 2018 b"> Hankins, Gabriel. <title
                        rend="quotes">We Are All Digital Modernists Now.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modernism/Modernity Print Plus</title> 3, no. 2
                    (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayot2016" label="Hayot and Walkowitz 2016"> Hayot, Eric, and Rebecca
                    L. Walkowitz, eds. <title rend="quotes">A New Vocabulary for Global
                        Modernism</title>. Columbia UP, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heaney2017" label="Heaney 2017"> Heaney, Emma. <title rend="italic"
                        >The New Woman: Literary Modernism, Queer Theory, and the Trans Feminine
                        Allegory</title>. Northwestern UP, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="herrmann2015" label="Herrmann et al. 2015"> Herrmann, J. Berenike,
                    Karina van Dalen-Oskam, Christof Schöch. <title rend="quotes">Revisiting Style,
                        a Key Concept in Literary Studies,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Literary Theory</title> 9, no. 1 (2015):
                    25-52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hirtle2018" label="Hirtle 2018"> Hirtle, Peter B. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Coypright Information Center.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cornell University Library</title>. Jan. 10, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hirtle2012" label="Hirtle 2012"> Hirtle, Peter B. <title rend="quotes"
                        >When Is 1923 Going to Arrive and Other Complications of the U.S. Public
                        Domain.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Searcher</title> 20, no. 6 (2012): 22-8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hogberg2018" label="Högberg and Bromley 2018"> Högberg, Elsa and Amy
                    Bromley. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Sentencing Orlando.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sentencing Orlando: Virginia Woolf and the Morphology of
                        the Modernist Sentence</title>, edited by Elsa Högberg and Amy Bromley.
                    Edinburgh UP, 2018, 1-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hoover2016" label="Hoover 2016"> Hoover, David L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Argument, Evidence, and the Limits of Digital Literary Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">In Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> 2016, edited
                    by Lauren F. Klein and Matthew K. Gold. U of Minnesota P, 2016, 230-50.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huculak2018" label="Huculak 2018"> Huculak,J. Matthew. <title
                        rend="quotes">What Is a Modernist Archive?,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modernism/Modernity Print Plus</title> (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="james2014" label="James and Seshagiri 2014"> James, David, and Urmila
                    Seshagiri. <title rend="quotes">Metamodernism: Narratives of Continuity and
                        Revolution,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 129, no. 1 (2014): 87-100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2013" label="Jockers 2013"> Jockers, Matthew. <title
                        rend="italic">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>. U
                    of Illinois Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2010" label="Jockers and Witten 2010"> Jockers, Matthew L. and
                    Daniela M. Witten. <title rend="quotes">A Comparative Study of Machine Learning
                        Methods for Authorship Attribution.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing </title>25, no. 2 (2010):
                    215-23.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2016" label="Jockers and Kirilloff 2016"> Jockers, Matthew, and
                    Gabi Kirilloff. <title rend="quotes"> “Understanding Gender and Character Agency
                        in the 19th Century Novel.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (Dec. 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kilafarriff2005" label="Kilgarriff 2005"> Kilgarriff, Adam. <title
                        rend="quotes">Language is never, ever, ever, random.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Corpus Linguistics and Linguistic Theory</title> 1, no. 2
                    (2005): 263-76.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="king2021" label="King 2021"> King, Rachael Scarborough. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Scale of Genre.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title>, vol. 52, no. 2 (2021):
                    261-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirilloff2018" label="Kirilloff et al. 2018"> Kirilloff, Gabi, Peter
                    J. Capuano, Julius Fredrick, and Matthew L. Jockers. <title rend="quotes">From a
                        distance ‘You might mistake her for a man’: A closer reading of gender and
                        character action in <title rend="italic">Jane Eyre, The Law and the
                            Lady,</title>and <title rend="italic">A Brilliant Woman</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 33, no. 4
                    (2018): 821-44.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kraicer2019" label="Kraicer and Piper 2019"> Kraicer, Eve, and Andrew
                    Piper. <title rend="quotes">Social Characters: The Hierarchy of Gender in Contemporary
                    English-Language Fiction,</title> <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (Jan. 2019).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lavin2020" label="Lavin 2020"> Lavin, Matthew J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Gender Dynamics and Critical Reception: A Study of Early 20th-century Book
                        Reviews from <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics </title>(Jan. 2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="long2013" label="Long and So 2013"> Long, Hoyt, and Richard Jean So.
                        <title rend="quotes">Network Analysis and the Sociology of
                        Modernism,</title> boundary 2 40, no. 2 (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="long2016a" label="Long and So 2016 a"> Long, Hoyt, and Richard Jean
                    So. <title rend="quotes">Literary Pattern Recognition: Modernism between Close
                        Reading and Machine Learning.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 42, no. 2 (2016): 235-67.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="long2016b" label="Long and So 2016 b"> Long, Hoyt, and Richard Jean
                    So. <title rend="quotes">Turbulent Flow: A Computational Model of World
                        Literature.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</title> 77, no. 3 (2016):
                    345-67.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="losh2016" label="Losh et al. 2016"> Losh, Elizabeth, Jacqueline
                    Wernimont, Laura Wexler, and Hong-An Wu. <title rend="quotes">Putting the Human
                        Back into the Digital Humanities: Feminism, Generosity, and Mess.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> 2016, edited
                    by Lauren F. Klein and Matthew K. Gold. U of Minnesota P, 2016, 92-103.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mandell2016" label="Mandell 2016"> Mandell, Laura C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Gendering Digital Literary History: What Counts for Digital
                        Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 2nd ed, edited by Susan Schreibman, Ray Siemens, and John
                    Unsworth. Wiley-Blackwell, 2016, 511-23.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mandell2019" label="Mandell 2019"> Mandell, Laura C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Gender and Cultural Analytics: Finding or Making
                        Stereotypes?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>2019, edited by
                    Matthew K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein. UP of Minnesota, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mao2008" label="Mao and Walkowitz 2008"> Mao, Douglas, and Rebecca
                    Walkowitz. <title rend="quotes">The New Modernist Studies,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 123, no. 3 (2008): 737-48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgrath2018" label="McGrath et al. 2018"> McGrath, Laura B., Devin
                    Higgins, and Arend Hintze. <title rend="quotes">Measuring Modernist
                        Novelty.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title>(Nov. 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nelson1989" label="Nelson 1986"> Nelson, Cary. <title rend="italic"
                        >Repression and Recovery: Modern American Poetry and the Politics of
                        Cultural Memory, 1910-1945</title>. U of Wisconsin P, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="north1999" label="North 1999"> North, Michael. <title rend="italic"
                        >Reading 1922: A Return to the Scene of the Modern. </title>Oxford UP,
                    1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2020" label="Piper 2020"> Piper, Andrew. <title rend="italic">Can
                        We Be Wrong? The Problem of Textual Evidence in a Time of Data.
                    </title>Elements in Digital Literary Studies, edited by Katherine Bode, Adam
                    Hammond, and Gabriel Hankins. Cambridge UP, 2020.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2016" label="Piper 2016"> Piper, Andrew.<title rend="quotes"
                        >There Will Be Numbers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (May 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2017" label="Piper 2017"> Piper, Andrew.<title rend="quotes"
                        >Think Small: On Literary Modeling.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 132, no. 3 (2017): 651-8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piperso2016" label="Piper and So 2016"> Piper, Andrew, and Richard
                    Jean So. <title rend="quotes">Women Write About Family, Men Write About
                        War.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Republic</title>, Apr. 8, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2017" label="Posner et al. 2017"> Posner, Miriam and Lauren F.
                    Klein. <title rend="quotes">Editor’s Introduction: Data as Media.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Histories</title> 3, no. 3 (2017):
                    1-8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pressman2014" label="Pressman 2014"> Pressman, Jessica. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making It New in New Media. </title>Oxford
                    UP, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pryor2019" label="Pryor 2011"> Pryor, Sean. <title rend="quotes">A
                        poetics of occasion in Hope Mirrlees’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Paris</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Quarterly</title> 61, no. 1 (2019): 37-53.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011"> Ramsay, Stephen. <title rend="italic"
                        >Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism. </title>U of Illinois P,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="riddell2020" label="Riddell and Barrett 2020">Riddell, Allen and Troy
                    J. Barrett. <title rend="quotes">What Library Digitization Leaves Out:
                        Predicting the Availability of Digital Surrogates of English Novels.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">arXiv:2009.00513 [cs.DL]</title>. Preprint, 1 September
                    2020.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2016" label="Risam 2016"> Risam, Roopika. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Navigating the Global Digital Humanities: Insights from Black
                        Feminism.</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> 2016, edited by Lauren F. Klein and Matthew K. Gold. U of
                    Minnesota P, 2016, 359-67.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2014" label="Ross and Sayers 2014"> Ross, Stephen, and Jentery
                    Sayers. <title rend="quotes">Modernism Meets Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literature Compass </title>11, no. 9 (2014):
                    625-633.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2016" label="Ross and O'Sullivan 2016"> Ross, Shawna, and James
                    O’Sullivan, eds. <title rend="italic">Reading Modernism with Machines: Digital
                        Humanities and Modernist Literature.</title>Palgrave Macmillan, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rubin1975" label="Rubin 1975"> Rubin, Gayle. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Traffic in Women: Notes on the ‘Political Economy’ of Sex.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Toward an Anthropology of Women</title>, edited by Rayna R.
                    Reiter. Monthly Review Press, 1975, 157-210.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rybicki2016" label="Rybicki 2016"> Rybicki, Jan. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><title rend="italic">Vive la différence</title>: Tracing the
                        (authorial) gender signal by multivariate analysis of word
                        frequencies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 31, no. 4
                    (2016): 746-61.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shalevshwartz2014" label="Shalev-Schwartz and Ben-David 2014"
                    >Shalev-Shwartz, Shai, and Shai Ben-David. <title rend="italic">Understanding
                        Machine Learning: From Theory to Algorithms</title>. Cambridge UP,
                    2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="so2017" label="So 2017"> So, Richard Jean. <title rend="quotes">All
                        Models Are Wrong.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 132, no. 3 (2017): 668-73.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stanford2015" label="Stanford 2015"> Stanford Friedman, Susan. <title
                        rend="italic">Planetary Modernisms: Provocations on Modernity Across Time.
                    </title>Columbia UP, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2021" label="Underwood and So 2021">Underwood, Ted and Richard Jean So, <title rend="quotes">Can We Map Culture?</title> <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (June 2021).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2019" label="Underwood 2019"> Underwood, Ted. <title
                        rend="italic">Distant Horizons: Digital Evidence and Literary
                    Change</title>. U Chicago P, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2020" label="Underwood 2020"> Underwood, Ted. <title
                        rend="quotes">Machine Learning and Human Perspective.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 135, no. 1 (2020): 92-109.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2018" label="Underwood et al. 2018"> Underwood, Ted, David
                    Bamman, and Sabrina Lee. <title rend="quotes">The Transformation of Gender in
                        English-Language Fiction.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Analytics</title> (Feb. 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weidman2018" label="Weidman and O'Sullivan 2018"> Weidman, Sean G.,
                    and James O’Sullivan. <title rend="quotes">The limits of distinctive words:
                        Re-evaluating literature’s gender marker debate,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 33, no. 2
                    (2018): 374-90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="woolf1928" label="Woolf 1992"> Woolf, Virginia. <title rend="italic"
                        >Orlando: A Biography. </title> (1928). Vintage, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="woolf2009" label="Woolf 2009"> Woolf, Virginia. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Poetry, Fiction and the Future.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Selected Essays. </title>Oxford UP, 2009, 74-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wollaeger2012" label="Wollaeger 2012"> Wollaeger, Mark, and Matt
                    Eatough, eds. <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Global
                        Modernisms</title>. Oxford UP, 2012.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
