<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">From the Rock Wall to Wikipedia: Sites of
                    Digital Connection and Repair in the Community-Engaged Classroom</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Carly <dhq:family>Schnitzler</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation> Johns Hopkins Univeristy </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>cschnit1@jh.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Alexandra <dhq:family>Odom</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    
                    <dhq:affiliation>UNC-Chapel Hill </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>alexodom@live.unc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Courtney <dhq:family>Rivard</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    
                    <dhq:affiliation>UNC-Chapel Hill </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>crivard@email.unc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Rolando <dhq:family>Rodriguez</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    
                    <dhq:affiliation>UNC-Chapel Hill </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>rolando.rodriguez@unc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Katherine <dhq:family>tein</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    
                    <dhq:affiliation>UNC-Chapel Hill </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>katherine.stein@unc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Kathryn <dhq:family>Wall</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    
                    <dhq:affiliation> The Marian Cheek Jackson Center for Saving and Making History </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kathryn@jacksoncenter.info</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000855</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">020</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2026-03-01">2026 March 1</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#cultural_heritage"/>
                    <term corresp="#oral_history"/>
                    <term corresp="#pedagogy"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <term>Wikipedia</term>
                    <term>Community-building pedagogy</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist"
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000855/000855.xml"
                    >GitHub</ref>.</change>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change>DHQ</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In the Spring of 2023, we collaborated on the development of a project for ENGL 114: The Rhetorics of Data, that tasked students with exploring the relationship between knowledge production and data through a collaborative Wikipedia project with the Marian Cheek Jackson Center for Saving and Making History, a nonprofit organization that preserves and celebrates the history of Chapel Hill and Carrboro's Black communities. To amplify the Jackson’s Center ongoing oral history work digitally, the organization’s public history leaders came together with a team at UNC-Chapel Hill to create a public digital humanities project for undergraduates that would offer students the opportunity to gain needed digital and data literacy skills by meaningfully contributing to the local community. In this case study, we outline: (1) the formation of this collaborative, reciprocal partnership that aids in the mission of the Jackson Center, (2) the power and intrinsic inequities in Wikipedia, and (3) the critical data literacies students develop through such a public humanities project. Ultimately, we argue that Wikipedia can serve as a bridge between community partners and classrooms of higher-ed institutions by centering community histories in accordance with the mission of community organizations to achieve key pedagogical goals, including the development of critical data literacy skills.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>PLACEHOLEDER</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head/>
                <p>As we sat reviewing Wikipedia pages in the St. Joseph CME Church’s basement next
                    to the Marion Cheek Jackson Center, Mr. William Gattis, a lifelong resident of
                    the Tin Top neighborhood in Chapel Hill, North Carolina, gave us some tough but
                    fair feedback. He explained, <quote rend="inline">this page is beautifully
                        written, but it glosses over the violence that we lived through. It is too
                        simple and plain.</quote> With this statement, Mr. Gattis pointed to much of
                    the problem with how Wikipedia and Wikidata often describe events in the past,
                    which are used to shape search engine results and AI-generated overviews. This
                    is a problem that we all were working together to address. He also demonstrated
                    that we had more work to do in our collaboration between the Marion Cheek
                    Jackson Center, students in Dr. Rivard’s course on the rhetoric of data at
                    University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (UNC-CH), and the Digital Literacy and
                    Communications (DLC) lab. </p>
                <p>Mr. Gattis was referencing our recently created Wikipedia page for the
                    Pottersfield neighborhood in Chapel Hill, NC. The goal of the page was to
                    describe the neighborhood that sits just north of UNC-Chapel’s campus and
                    constitutes part of the university’s history that many students and contemporary
                    residents in Chapel Hill know little about. The version of the page Mr. Gattis
                    commented on described the neighborhood’s history, beginning with its origins in
                    the nineteenth century as a labor settlement for enslaved persons working for
                    the University of North Carolina. It detailed the evolution of the neighborhood
                    throughout the Civil Rights Era as many of its residents played pivotal roles in
                    local and, in some instances, even national movements. The page included details
                    about recent efforts to preserve the community’s history with memorial plaques,
                    guided tours, and oral histories. It concluded with a description of how the
                    current community members were diligently working to preserve this history. </p>
                <p>This meeting, held March 2025, consisted of faculty, undergraduate, and graduate
                    students from UNC-Chapel Hill, Jackson Center staff, and key members of the
                    Jackson’s Center Community Review Board of which Mr. Gattis was a central
                    member. For the most part, the community members in attendance agreed that the
                    information on the Wikipedia page was factually correct. The people, places, and
                    dates were accurate. Where the page fell short was in contextualizing the
                    motivations and larger implications behind significant moments in the
                    neighborhood’s history — it did not attend to the difficult, inequitable, and
                    often violent structures of power that wrapped around each date on the neatly
                    articulated timeline. As Patricia Jackson (Community Review Board member and St.
                    Joseph CME’s secretary) stated, <quote rend="inline">This Pottersfield [on the
                        Wikipedia page] is glamorous. The Pottersfield that we knew was thrown away
                        property that nobody else wanted, that nothing else could happen on and they
                        said, <quote rend="inline">Ok, you could use this area.</quote></quote>
                </p>
                <p>As she made her remarks, others in the room nodded along. Mr. Gattis added:
                <quote rend="block">Actually it wasn’t so much <quote rend="inline">you could use,</quote> but <quote rend="inline">this is where
                    you are relegated to, because we have established Chapel Hill, white Chapel
                    Hill, as being between Boundary Street and Merritt Mill Road. This is our
                    territory. Now, we are going to relegate you all to the Northside of
                    Pottersfield area, to Tin Top, to Pine Knolls, to South Lane and Windy Hill area
                    because this is the worst areas in the town and we aren’t going to be there but
                    we don’t mind you all being there.</quote></quote>
                As the conversation continued, it quickly became clear that the pages we compiled
                    needed significant revision to meet our original mission of the project: forging
                    a reciprocal and equitable partnership between students and faculty at UNC,
                    Jackson Center staff, and community members to amplify community knowledge of
                    local histories through the development of Wikipedia and Wikidata pages
                    representing important historical sites in the Chapel Hill area. Wikipedia’s
                    knowledge structures and sourcing guidelines make it difficult to include the
                    type of context and motivations outlined by Mr. Gattis and Mrs. Jackson. These
                    guidelines require <quote rend="inline">notable</quote> topics, neutral
                    language, <quote rend="inline">reliable</quote> secondary sources, and prohibit
                    original research [reliable-sources, n.d.]. Together these criteria often fail
                    to acknowledge histories of marginalized communities deemed not <quote
                        rend="inline">notable</quote> because underrepresented groups lack the
                    secondary sources Wikipedia considers legitimate <ptr target="#silva-scott_2023"/>. The result
                    is that Wikipedia, despite its democratic ideals, reproduces many of the same
                    knowledge hierarchies and historical erasures that have always privileged
                    dominant groups while silencing minority voices <ptr target="#tripodi_2021"/> [silva-scott,
                    2023]. </p>
                <p>To disrupt these structural issues of inequity in Wikipedia, we developed a
                    multi-step workflow that centers community knowledge and builds digital
                    literacies for students and community members. The process consists of six
                    steps: </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Site selection by Jackson Center staff and community members </item>
                    <item>Research and drafting by an undergraduate students from a course on the
                        rhetoric of data (ENGL 114) in consultation with DLC staff to meet
                        Wikipedia’s secondary-source guidelines</item>
                    <item>Collaboration with Jackson Center staff to publish oral history excerpts
                        on their website — a workaround we invented since Wikipedia prohibits oral
                        history as a primary source but allows quotes from oral histories on web
                        pages </item>
                    <item>Revision and refinement of content </item>
                    <item>Publication of pages by ENGL 114 students along with an accompanying
                        portfolio to meet course requirements </item>
                    <item>Ongoing page revision and long-term oversight by the DLC in collaboration
                        with community members. </item>
                </list>
                <p>This paper uses our collaborative workflow as a case study to show how community
                    expertise and university resources can work together to intervene in Wikipedia’s
                    increasingly powerful knowledge structures. In so doing, we demonstrate how
                    Wikipedia can serve as an important site for public digital humanities projects.
                    We begin by outlining our partnership, then discuss issues in Wikipedia and
                    Wikidata, and end with a more detailed description of our methods of
                    intervention.</p>
                <div>
                    <head/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Crafting a Collaborative, Reciprocal Partnership </head>
                <p>This partnership began in early 2022 when a mutual colleague connected Dr.
                    Courtney Rivard (Director of the DLC lab and instructor of ENGL 114: Rhetoric of
                    Data) with Dr. Kathryn Wall (Co-Director of Public History at the Jackson
                    Center). Rivard was interested in creating a public digital humanities project
                    for her rhetoric course in the Department of English &amp; Comparative
                    Literature, which also filled a core requirement in the university’s newly
                    created data science minor. She also wanted to include students in the DLC Lab
                    that she directed. The DLC serves as a hub for innovation in the humanities with
                    a focus on digital humanities, critical games studies, digital literacy, and
                    communications [<hi rend="italic">Digital Literacy and Communications Lab</hi>].
                    Wall was hoping to connect with UNC-CH’s students to further the mission of the
                    Jackson Center. The Jackson Center is dedicated to honoring, renewing, and
                    building community in historically Black neighborhoods in the Northside of
                    Chapel Hill, Carrboro, and southern Orange County. The center’s aim is <quote
                        rend="inline">to engage the power of civil rights history; the struggles and
                        strengths of generations of long-term residents; the insights of all who
                        work, live, play, serve, and worship in Northside neighborhoods; and
                        partnership across multiple lines of difference to make community-driven
                        change</quote> [<hi rend="italic">Our Vision and Mission</hi>]. Part of this
                    mission to preserve local history includes an oral history project, <title
                        rend="italic">From the Rock Wall: Living Histories of Black Chapel
                        Hill/Carrboro. </title>The Jackson Center has been dedicated to telling
                    these stories in a way that centers the voice, perspective, and agency of
                    community members and community histories. As community member and former
                    Carrboro-Chapel Hill NAACP president Eugene Farrar notes, <quote rend="inline"
                        >The only way our history can get told right is that we have to tell
                        it</quote> [ <hi rend="italic">Eugene Farrar</hi>].</p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">From the Rock Wall</title> contains so much important
                    history, though like most oral history projects, browsing its contents is a
                    challenge as faceted searching of the transcripts is not currently possible <ptr target="#ma-van-kleeck_2023"/>. To address this issue, the Jackson Center established a <title
                        rend="quotes">Places</title> page on their website to highlight key oral
                    histories attached to important sites around Chapel Hill, but it lacked
                    significant web traffic. Wall suggested that Rivard’s students could help make
                    these places and their linked oral histories available to a wider audience. To
                    support the development of this course project, Rivard and Wall brought together
                    a team that would ensure a reciprocal, sustainable, and non-extractive
                    partnership that meaningfully benefited and involved the community as experts
                    and collaborators. In particular, this meant acknowledging the university’s long
                    history of one-sided partnerships that benefit the institution rather than the
                    local community, as well as making sustained and consistent steps to work
                    alongside community members to build a relationship of trust
                    <ptr target="#sanders-thompson-hood_2016"/>. The initial team formed in 2022 consisted of Anna
                    Spencer (Co-Director of Public History at the Jackson Center), Dr. Carly
                    Schnitzler (former graduate student and DLC Digital Humanities Director),
                    Katherine Stein (graduate student and DLC Public Humanities Co-Director), Dr.
                    Alexandra Odom (former graduate student and DLC Public Humanities Co-Director),
                    and Rolando Rodriguez (Humanities Data Librarian). As the collaboration grew,
                    three additional team members joined the project in 2024: Kyle Cunningham
                    (graduate student and current DLC Digital Humanities Director), Sage Clausen,
                    and Sarah Davey (undergraduate student interns). What began as a
                    community-oriented course project designed to give undergraduate students a more
                    ethically informed understanding of the community in which they lived soon
                    evolved into a years-long collaboration between university research lab,
                    non-profit organization, and community members.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Why Wikipedia?</head>
                <p>We selected Wikipedia as the platform that could best increase circulation of the
                    Jackson Center’s resources and build students’ digital and data literacy skills,
                    given its central position in knowledge circulation and the scarcity of Chapel
                    Hill’s Black history on the site. Not only is Wikipedia increasingly the first
                    site that many go to for basic research, but the semantic and linking structure
                    of Wikipedia gives it a privileged position in search engine results, often
                    appearing in knowledge boxes and AI summaries that searchers see first <ptr target="#iliadis_2023"/>. As a result, Wikipedia serves as a <quote rend="inline">high-traffic
                        gateway to the broader Web ecosystem</quote> through its content <ptr target="#piccardi_2021" loc="249"/>. Now, as AI continues to mediate and consolidate digital knowledge
                    circulation, Wikipedia has an even more prominent role in search ecosystems, for
                    two primary reasons: 1) Wikipedia is among the largest sources of training data
                    for commercial LLMs and 2) Wikipedia is a common source in AI summaries or
                    overviews on popular LLMs and search engines<note>From a 2025 study from
                        Profound, a company that <quote rend="inline">helps brands gain visibility
                            in AI-generated answers,</quote> Wikipedia accounts for 47.9% of
                        ChatGPT’s top 10 sources and 5.7% of Google’s top 10 sources for AI
                        Overviews <ptr target="#lafferty_2025"/>.</note> <ptr target="#deckelmann_2023"/> <ptr target="#lafferty_2025"/>. A
                    2025 Pew study found that Google users who encounter an AI overview or summary
                    are almost half as likely to click on a traditional search result link, compared
                    to those who do not see an AI summary — down from 15% to 8% <ptr target="#chapekis-lieb_2025"/>. Wikipedia is central to digital knowledge production and circulation,
                    both as a consolidated source and as an infrastructural node. Therefore, we
                    reasoned that creating pages dedicated to central locations in African American
                    history in Chapel Hill would make these histories more visible and hopefully
                    drive more traffic to the Jackson’s Center website. </p>
                <p>Wikipedia has been used successfully in classrooms for years to expand digital
                    literacies <ptr target="#ball_2019"/>, conduct mixed-methods research (i.e., network analysis,
                    interviews, participant reflections) <ptr target="#littlejohn_2021"/> <ptr target="#kennedy_2017"/>, explore
                    and make public university archival materials <ptr target="#vetter_2014"/>, consider editorial
                    authority and collaborative knowledge creation <ptr target="#lockett_2019"/> <ptr target="#estill_2017"/>,
                    and expand knowledge in a digital commons to be more diverse and inclusive
                    <ptr target="#gordon_2015"/> <ptr target="#el-khatib_2020"/>. Outside of the classroom, community
                    organizations have hosted editathons to advance the visibility of particular
                    communities both in the articles appearing on Wikipedia and as editors on the
                    platform, <note>See Silva and Scott’s Wikipedia editing project focused on the
                        digital literacies of Black girls, hosted after-school in a Pittsburgh high
                        school <ptr target="#silva-scott_2023"/>.</note> thereby broadening the scope of content
                    and addressing key issues of equity <ptr target="#silva-scott_2023"/>. Developing such digital
                    literacies aligned with learning objectives for ENGL 114 and community
                    enrichment activities for the Jackson Center. </p>
                <p>Despite these affordances, prior work on Wikipedia by some members of the
                        group<note>See also <title rend="quotes"><q>Flagged for Deletion</q>:
                            Wikipedia, the Federal Writers’ Project, and First-Year
                            Composition</title> <ptr target="#rivard_2022"/>.</note> made us well aware of major
                    problems within and surrounding the platform that we would need to address.
                    These problems included: 1) editorial power dynamics and representation; 2)
                    rigidity around source notability and verifiability; and 3) missing data
                    infrastructures on Wikidata. </p>
                <p>Despite its democratic ethos of providing <quote rend="inline">free access to
                        knowledge</quote> in the world where <quote rend="inline">anyone can
                        edit</quote> [<hi rend="italic">Wikimedia projects</hi>], it is well
                    documented that 80% of Wikipedia’s content is created <quote rend="inline">by
                        white men from Europe and North America</quote> and is in need of
                    significant diversification <ptr target="#duncan_2020" loc="156"/>. These inequities are reinforced
                    by factors like the time required for unpaid editing work, language barriers,
                    technical literacy requirements, and a community culture that can be unwelcoming
                    to newcomers, particularly those from underrepresented groups <ptr target="#lockett_2019"/>
                    <ptr target="#duncan_2020"/> <ptr target="#tripodi_2021"/>. For example, in a study of gender inequity in
                    Wikipedia, Francesca Tripodi demonstrates that <quote rend="inline">women are
                        reluctant to edit [Wikipedia] because the interface is not readily
                        accessible and the <soCalled>pipeline</soCalled> for participation is effectively
                        broken</quote> <ptr target="#tripodi_2021" loc="1689"/>. Jim Brown argues that participation in
                    Wikipedia and its overall ethos is impacted by <quote rend="inline">rules,
                        regulations, and assumptions about identity and authority,</quote> which are
                    reinforced through software and data structures <ptr target="#brown_2015" loc="109"/>. </p>
                <p>The central rules and regulations that impact participation and the knowledge
                    accrued in Wikipedia involve its concept of notability and the type of sources
                    that it deems reliable. Wikipedia describes <soCalled>Places</soCalled> as a
                    test used by editors to decide whether a given topic warrants its own article,
                    which is determined by having <quote rend="inline">verifiable, objective evidence
                        that the subject has received significant attention from independent sources
                        to support a claim of notability. No subject is automatically or inherently
                        notable merely because it exists: the evidence must show the topic has
                        gained significant independent coverage or recognition</quote> [<hi
                        rend="italic">Reliable Sources</hi>].</p>
                <p>Such evidence is provided by sources that Wikipedia guidelines explain must be
                    written from a neutral point of view, attributed to a reliable published source,
                    and cannot include original research [<hi rend="italic">Reliable Sources</hi>].
                    In other words, all evidence must consist of secondary sources. Importantly,
                    oral histories, like the ones collected by the Jackson Center, would not be
                    considered reliable sources. </p>
                <p>Scholars of gender, race, and sexuality recognize the limitations these
                    guidelines present when Wikipedia editors seek to contribute to or create pages
                    on the platform about minority communities. Because underrepresented groups are
                    less likely to be present in the kind of secondary sources Wikipedia deems
                    acceptable, their histories are less likely to pass the notability test, thus
                    creating significant absences on Wikipedia <ptr target="#silva-scott_2023"/> <ptr target="#tripodi_2021"/>.
                    Moreover, the arbitration of this concept of notability usually revolves around
                    a narrow interpretation of Wikipedia policy that has been formed over the years
                    by users who have spent extensive time editing Wikipedia and have moved up the
                    ranks of administration status as one can get more administrative privileges
                    only through more substantive edits on Wikipedia <ptr target="#lockett_2019"/>. Gauthier and
                    Sawchuk explain the impact of these decisions: </p>
                <quote rend="block">Wikipedia is a large-scale information infrastructure, a classification system
                    made of its own standards, categories, technologies, and the phenomenological
                    experience of its users. Indeed, classification allows a segmentation of the
                    world and is based on compromises ranging from epistemology to data entry. In
                    this sense, classification work is political. Aspects of the work get deleted
                    and made invisible, which means that voices are suppressed, and it produces a
                    mainstream, universal narrative on a topic. Wikipedia’s guidelines have become
                    hard to change and to interpret differently. The result is that the
                    classification of the world operated by its entries becomes rigid and maintains
                    an epistemology that delegitimizes some topics and points of view
                    <ptr target="#gauthier-sawchuk_2017" loc="395"/>.</quote>
                <p>Wikipedia’s centrality within digital knowledge circulation heightens the
                    significance of these inequities, a status that is largely driven by
                    Wikidata.</p>
                <p>Wikidata began in 2012 as the central storage for the structured data of all
                    Wikimedia projects including Wikipedia [<hi rend="italic">Wikimedia
                        Projects</hi>]. Wikidata constitutes a public repository of linked open data
                    through the creation of semantic web connected not just by hyperlinks and
                    documents, but also through structured data that links entities and relations
                    <ptr target="#sigalov-nachmias_2023"/>. It can be read and edited by both humans and machines
                    and provides the data necessary for Wikipedia’s infoboxes and as well as Google
                    to optimize its search capabilities <ptr target="#minhaj-urs_2021"/>. Each item in Wikidata is
                    given a unique identifier and is composed of a label (the item’s common name), a
                    description, and any possible aliases. The description details the item’s key
                    characteristics through a statement that consists of a property and a value.
                    Properties define how one thing relates to another on Wikidata in the form of a
                    semantic triple (subject, predicate, object — or in Wikidata parlance, item,
                    property, value). For example, <quote rend="inline">for a person, you can add a
                        property to specify where they were educated, by specifying a value for a
                        school. For buildings, you can assign geographic coordinates properties by
                        specifying longitude and latitude values</quote> [ <hi rend="italic"
                        >Introduction</hi>]. Such linked semantic data <quote rend="inline">aims to
                        eventually represent everything in the universe in a way computers can
                        understand</quote> <ptr target="#simonite_2019"/></p>
                <p>Because of its highly structured nature, Wikidata now constitutes one of the
                    largest <quote rend="inline">free and open <soCalled>Big Data</soCalled> knowledge bases</quote> in
                    the world <ptr target="#sigalov-nachmias_2023" loc="286"/>. This <quote rend="inline">means that one
                        can query it and receive relevant and accurate answers, especially compared
                        with traditional search engines…[making] it fertile ground for learning and
                        research opportunities</quote> <ptr target="#sigalov-nachmias_2023" loc="286"/>. Using the
                    query service provided by the Wikidata platform, which provides a user-friendly
                    way to run a SPARQL (database) query, one can answer questions that are not
                    possible on traditional search engines such as Google, for example, <quote rend="inline">where are
                    the birthplaces of women physicists in history</quote> <ptr target="#mcandrew_2017"/>. Of course, to
                    answer such a question requires there to be sufficient and accurate data drawn
                    from Wikipedia pages and corresponding Wikidata entries. At the time of this
                    writing, there are more than 120 million data items in Wikidata with 34,000
                    users. Despite its significance and rapid growth, there remain many gaps in data
                    that often reproduce existing inequities around race, gender, and class <ptr target="#ripoll_2025"/>.</p>
                <p>The way that data is structured has far-reaching significance. Ford and Iliadis
                    argue, <quote rend="inline">The ways that Wikidata classifies phenomena have a
                        ripple effect on how media, such as search engines and virtual assistants
                        retrieve and directly convey facts, answers, meanings, and knowledge</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ford-iliadis_2023" loc="2"/>. These classification systems that reduce complex
                    information on Wikipedia into barebone semantic triples effectively erase the
                        <quote rend="inline">narratives, detailed historical backgrounds, academic
                        references, news stories, and in-depth descriptions of individuals’
                        lives…What remains is a database of interconnected facts that can be
                        queried, providing individuals with quick answers, concise knowledge, and
                        limited data specific to their inquiries</quote> <ptr target="#ford-iliadis_2023" loc="6"/>. </p>
                <p>It is because of the immense power that Wikidata and Wikipedia now play in the
                    information infrastructure that shapes our world that they mark important
                    terrain for the field of digital humanities to explore, especially projects that
                    are pedagogical and community focused. Students and community members can, as
                    Melanie Kill writes, <quote rend="inline">learn a great deal about effective [and
                        perhaps ineffective] collaboration in practical and real world terms, and
                        reflect on the diversity of contemporary knowledge-making methods and
                        practices, by participating in existing public digital humanities projects
                        like Wikipedia</quote> <ptr target="#kill_2012"/>. Moreover, Wikidata is now becoming a
                    focal point in many DH projects interested in data annotation, <quote
                        rend="inline">metadata curation, modelling, and Named Entity Recognition
                        (NER)</quote> <ptr target="#zhao_2023" loc="869"/>.</p>
                <p>To take advantage of the affordances of Wikipedia and address issues of absence
                    and equity within its structures, team members crafted an assignment for
                    Rivard’s Rhetoric of Data course (ENGL 114) that was supported by the DLC lab
                    after the class ended in which each Wikipedia page was presented for review to
                    the Jackson’s Center Community Review Board; their feedback was then
                    incorporated into the pages, and the DLC lab continues to monitor the pages.
                    Future iterations of ENGL 114 have also followed this workflow and made use of
                    this support structure. The following sections explain this workflow in more
                    detail, noting problems and successes that emerged in the process, most
                    significantly how to attend to the problem that oral histories are not
                    considered reliable sources. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Assignment Structure</head>
                <p>First taught in Spring 2022, English 114: The Rhetoric of Data fulfilled
                    requirements in both the English department’s Writing, Editing, and Digital
                    Publishing concentration and UNC’s Data Science Minor. The course examined
                    rhetoric, digital media, information, and data while requiring students to
                    evaluate how data shapes power structures and impacts lived realities. In
                    creating the Wikipedia project, we aimed to fulfill these course goals, while
                    helping students learn about the important sites in Chapel Hill history by
                    supporting the work of the Jackson Center. The assignment consisted of putting
                    students into groups with defined roles in which they created Wikipedia and
                    Wikidata sites on a historical site of the Jackson Center’s choosing, and then
                    individually created a portfolio that showcased their work on the project, a
                    narrative reflection, and an example of running Wikidata queries related to
                    linked topics associated with their Wikipedia pages. Students began the semester
                    exploring key concepts in theories at the intersection of rhetorical studies and
                    data studies and then moved into the Wikipedia project, which consisted of a
                    six-week instructional plan that emphasized the community-based nature of the
                    project by drawing on the expertise of our different team members (see appendix
                    A). </p>
                <p>This plan was designed to model what Schwan and Thomson refer to as <quote
                        rend="inline">a circular flow of knowledge between academia, other
                        organizations and communities</quote> <ptr target="#schwan-thomson_2023" loc="3"/>].<note> As
                        Trey Conatser reminds us, students themselves should also be recognized as a
                        community group in their own right: <quote rend="inline">While students
                            themselves represent one <soCalled>public </soCalled>in this network,
                            they also act as a conduit through which the archive and the academy at
                            large can address audiences in other professional organizations and
                            contexts as well as among the lay community</quote> <ptr target="#conatser_2022" loc="239"/>.</note> Our goal was to show students that collaborative work lies at
                    the heart of public humanities, both inside and outside of the university
                    <ptr target="#smulyan_2020"/>. Wikipedia projects are uniquely suited to provide students with
                    public opportunities that reach outside the university. Not only, as Julie D.
                    Nelson writes, does <quote rend="inline">Wikipedia encourage students to engage
                        in community-based research and writing…as students produce knowledges and
                        stories to share with (and intervene in) the global Wikipedia
                        community,</quote> but also <quote rend="inline">as students go into their
                        [own] communities to find local, valuable, and underrepresented
                        knowledges</quote> <ptr target="#nelson_2018" loc="490"/>. By completing Wikipedia and Wikidata
                    projects, students become a part of this circular flow of knowledge, noting
                    powerful inequities that shape it and finding ways to intervene. The plan
                    emphasized the following three themes: 1) Digital Rhetoric and Wikipedia, 2)
                    Integrating Oral Histories within Wikipedia Guidelines of Notability and
                    Verifiability, and 3) Information Infrastructure and Wikidata. </p>
                <div>
                    <head/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Digital Rhetoric of Wikipedia and Barriers to Participation</head>
                <p>To bridge previous coursework on data rhetorics with the Wikipedia project,
                    students were first introduced to the rhetorical affordances and limitations of
                    hypertext, Search Engine Optimization (SEO), and (quite directly) the processes
                    involved in editing Wikipedia. Building off of a class session that focused on a
                    genre analysis of Wikipedia pages by Rivard, Schnitzler provided a guest lecture
                    to lead a series of activities that helped students identify hypertext as a
                    central feature of a Wikipedia article’s design and citational practices. She
                    carefully pointed out the differences between hyperlinks and secondary-source
                    footnotes on Wikipedia. Both are forms of citation, but there is a key
                    distinction in their primary purposes — hyperlinks connect, and footnotes
                    verify. As the style guide notes: <quote rend="inline">Internal links bind the
                        project together into an interconnected whole… and external links bind
                        Wikipedia to the World Wide Web</quote> [ <hi rend="italic">Linking</hi>].
                    This means that when one is writing and editing on Wikipedia, they are writing
                    for (at least) two primary audiences, to which hyperlinks matter a lot — namely,
                    other Wikipedia readers and search engines. </p>
                <p>After a discussion of the considerations to be made when writing for these two
                    audiences, students were tasked with making their first Wikipedia edits in small
                    groups. In keeping with suggestions offered by the <title rend="quotes">Editing
                        Wikipedia: A Guide for Student Editors</title> by Wiki Education, students
                    created new accounts and then made small edits to an existing Wikipedia page to
                    achieve autoconfirmation status. Before a new user can create a new Wikipedia
                    page they need to obtain <title rend="quotes">autoconfirmed</title> status,
                    which occurs after they have made ≥10 edits to existing pages within 4 days.
                    Wikipedia explains, <quote rend="inline">the main reason for having autoconfirmed
                        status on Wikipedia is to prevent vandalism and other types of disruptive
                        changes to popular pages by allowing only users who have shown they can make
                        only good changes to change these pages</quote> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Autoconfirmed Users</hi>].<note>The more edits that a Wikipedian makes the
                        more power they obtain within the Wiki ecosystem. One can achieve extended
                        confirmed status if they make 500 edits in 30 days, and from there they can
                        work their way to administrator status with even more edits and successful
                        election by other administrators [<hi rend="italic">Autoconfirmed
                        Users</hi>].</note> We selected the Orange County Training School (OCTS)
                    Wikipedia page as the focus of this activity to encourage students to begin
                    their autoconfirmation process by engaging with the only existing Wikipedia page
                    that also had a presence in the <title rend="italic">From the Rock Wall
                    </title>archive. This page is the first Google search result when one searches
                        <title rend="quotes">Orange County Training School</title> and also provides
                    the content for the Google-generated quick-info sidebar (Figure 1). </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Front page Google results for <title rend="quotes">Orange County Training
                            School</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>After discussing terms and other webpages to link, students edited the OCTS page
                    to include more hyperlinks and, in turn, increase the connections of the page
                    both within Wikipedia and its visibility on search engines and across the
                    internet. However, within minutes of this class ending, multiple students who
                    edited the Orange County Training School page had their accounts suspended by a
                    much more established editor for <soCalled>disrupting</soCalled> Wikipedia by adding too many links
                    at once. These students were experiencing the exact <quote rend="inline">broken
                        pipeline</quote> in participation that so often works to reify existing
                    power hierarchies <ptr target="#tripodi_2021"/>. Suspending the students’ accounts rather than
                    just reverting the changes was a rather aggressive decision from this Wikieditor
                    that effectively prohibited students from doing anything within Wikipedia until
                    their accounts were restored. To address this problem, Rivard joined the talk
                    page for the Orange County Training School to discuss this issue with the
                    editor. Talk pages sit behind each Wikipedia page as a space for editors to
                    discuss changes. These talk pages evidence how different editors interpret
                    Wikipedia’s principles to come to a consensus about what information is allowed
                    to exist on the site. As such, it is within these pages that one can see how
                    power hierarchies and gatekeeping operate. </p>
                <p>Rivard explained that this was a class project and there was no malicious intent,
                    and questioned why the student’s accounts were suspended rather than just having
                    their changes reverted. The editor replied that the students did not add some of
                    the links correctly and took the multiple changes to one page as a sign of
                    attack, but agreed to reinstate the students’ accounts, along with only some of
                    the links they originally added. This perplexing exchange and punitive behavior
                    from the editor provided a powerful teaching moment. It evidenced how new
                    editors must not only accrue additional technical literacies,<note>Technical
                        literacies such as account creation, site navigation, adherence to the
                        Wikipedia pillars and manual of style, and the use of Wikitext markup for
                        formatting are other forms of literacies that are separate from the
                        discourse community literacies we focus on here. Nevertheless, they too
                        contribute to editorial friction in the classroom.</note> but must also take
                    the leap into a fresh discourse community of more experienced, powerful, and
                    opinionated editors. As Alexandra Lockett writes, <quote rend="inline">editing
                        Wikipedia to improve content gaps sounds good, but editors are often too
                        unfamiliar with the Wikipedia community to fight for the knowledge they seek
                        to represent</quote> <ptr target="#lockett_2019" loc="212"/>.</p>
                <p>As these Wikipedia pages for important sites in Chapel Hill’s historically Black
                    neighborhoods were drafted and posted, other editors began to take notice,
                    revising, reformatting, chatting, and flagging issues, some of which remain on
                    the current iterations of the pages. These interactions were variously positive,
                    negative, and neutral for the students — one student gained an official mentor
                    on Wikipedia, while several others were asked to defend their editorial choices.
                    All of these interactions left lasting impressions on students. In response to
                    an end-of-assignment survey question asking, <quote rend="inling">What barriers
                        do you see in the current structure of Wikipedia to creating articles that
                        equitably represent a diverse range of community contexts?,</quote> most
                    students (13 of 17) independently cited editors with higher levels of
                    administrative power as direct barriers. </p>
                <p>These interactions and experiences offered students a valuable lesson in
                    understanding how power operates in Wikipedia and its larger impact on the
                    relationship between data infrastructure and knowledge production. For example,
                    in their final paper, one student made a connection between the role of
                    algorithms and Wikipedia editors. They write,</p>
                <quote rend="block">In his <title rend="quotes">The Social Power of Algorithms,</title> David Beer
                    talks about the relationships between data, power, and algorithms. He argues
                    that algorithms play a profound role in shaping the way information is
                    distributed, giving them immense power in society. Algorithms have the power to
                    tell <soCalled>Places</soCalled> They can <quote rend="inline">decide what
                        matters and... what should be most visible</quote> <ptr target="#beer_2016" loc="6"/>. Wiki
                    editors have the same type of power, which we experienced firsthand. By blocking
                    our accounts and removing our edits, the Wiki editor had the power to identify
                    what information would be available to the public and what information would not
                    be.</quote>
                <p>While this lesson in power made students feel disheartened at first, we leveraged
                    it as a learning opportunity, encouraging them to think about the audience and
                    genre conventions of their Wikipedia writing. Noting precisely this, one student
                    wrote, <quote rend="inline">I realized that… the people who we were trying to
                        persuade were the Wikipedia editors; by following the pillars and guidelines
                        of Wikipedia we were trying to persuade these editors that these sites
                        deserved to stay up.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Making Oral Histories <soCalled>Places</soCalled> Wikipedia Guidelines of
                    Notability and Verifiability</head>
                <p>A central feature of this project for students was centering community knowledge
                    through the Jackson’s Center oral history project. Oral histories are inclusive,
                    as Barbara W. Sommer and Mary Kay Quinlan write, <quote rend="inline">bringing in
                        many voices, not just the more powerful or dominant that are traditionally
                        excluded in existing records</quote> <ptr target="#sommer-quinlan_2020" loc="4"/>. Done well,
                    oral histories <quote rend="inline">help to interpret and define written records
                        and make sense out of the most obscure decisions and events,</quote> adding
                    valuable interpretive context to histories often not centered in traditional
                    records <ptr target="#ritchie_2014" loc="118"/>. Individual stories, told by the people who lived
                    them, hold a unique power to illuminate not just personal histories, but history
                    writ large on a local, regional, and national scale. However, oral histories
                    fall outside of what Wikipedia accepts as reliable sources. Because Wikipedia
                    defines reliable sources as those that can be verified by published secondary
                    sources in which <quote rend="inline">no original research</quote> including
                    personal experience is allowed, it effectively prohibits oral history
                    <ptr target="#mcdowell-vetter_2021" loc="32"/>. While these guidelines are important for preventing
                    misinformation, they also end up outsourcing <quote rend="inline">its trust in
                        information to those who have the power to publish,</quote> thereby often
                    rendering marginalized histories as unreliable including those histories that
                    have only been captured through unpublished oral histories <ptr target="#mcdowell-vetter_2021" loc="66"/>.</p>
                <p>At first glance, this would mean that the robust oral history project created by
                    the Jackson Center would be ineligible for inclusion as a reliable source in
                    Wikipedia. To attend to this significant contradiction, we came up with a
                    workaround, or what Wall came to refer to as a <soCalled>Places</soCalled>
                    approach, to transform the Jackson Center oral histories into a
                        <soCalled>Places</soCalled> Wikipedia source. While oral histories on their
                    own are not considered reliable by Wikipedia, a published work that discusses
                    and contextualizes the material, can render them reliable. Websites, especially
                    organizational websites, are frequently cited as sources on Wikipedia.
                    Therefore, if the Jackson Center published excerpts of key oral histories on
                    their website then they would be considered reliable sources. We worked this
                        <soCalled>Places</soCalled> approach into the assignment structure and
                    post-course page revision processes, inviting students and DLC members to
                    contribute to an important intervention addressing inequity within this
                    knowledge system.</p>
                <p>After students had autoconfirmed Wikipedia accounts and understood the rhetorical
                    conventions of the genre, Wall, Odom, and Stein came for class visits to discuss
                    the complicated terrain of source reliability and what that meant for conducting
                    research for the Wikipedia page. Wall explained the significance of the Jackson
                    Center’s efforts and the centrality of oral history as a method in those
                    initiatives. Odom and Stein laid out Wikipedia’s policy around oral histories
                    and our <soCalled>Places</soCalled> approach for incorporating community
                    members’ knowledge through inclusion of excerpts of oral histories on the
                    Jackson Center’s website. They also helped students identify other secondary
                    sources that fit within the bounds of Wikipedia’s credibility guidelines to
                    provide adequate and diverse source support. Students were encouraged to use
                    local newspapers including those that specifically served the Black communities
                    in Chapel Hill and Carrboro, which were widely available through databases like
                    Digital NC, an online digitization project supported by the state library and
                    UNC-Chapel Hill.</p>
                <p>Following these sessions with Wall, Odom, and Stein, students were put into
                    groups based on their preferences for working on historical sites selected by
                    the Jackson Center: Hollywood Theater, Hargraves Community Center, Hackney
                    School, Pottersfield, St. Paul AME, and Watts Restaurant.<note>In order to
                        provide structure for students and draw attention to labor equity in group
                        work. Students were required to complete a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU)
                        before beginning work (see Appendix B). </note> In selecting these sites,
                    Wall first created a large list of sites the Jackson Center desired to be
                    featured in Wikipedia to draw greater attention to their oral history project
                    and the site’s historical significance. Rivard and the DLC staff then evaluated
                    which of these sites would work best for class work making sure there were
                    sufficient secondary sources and oral histories available. Students spent
                    several weeks conducting research for their respective sites, which included
                    referring to the databases identified by Odom and Stein as well as reviewing the
                    oral histories conducted by the Jackson Center. When students wanted to refer to
                    specific quotes from the oral histories, Wall would update a <title
                        rend="quotes">Places</title> page on <title rend="italic">From the Rock
                        Wall’</title>s website for that site to include the quote (Figure 2). The
                    students would then cite the <title rend="quotes">Places</title> page so that
                    the community’s history was centered in the Wikipedia page. Moreover, Wall plans
                    to refer to the Wikipedia pages on these <title rend="quotes">Places</title>
                    pages to encourage the circular flow of this knowledge.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 2: From the Rock Wall <title rend="quotes">Places</title> page
                        search results, with visible oral history quote for Pottersfield.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <p>By incorporating community residents’ voices into Wikipedia pages about
                    historically significant Black community sites, students used their knowledge of
                    the platform to amplify voices that might otherwise go unheard in spaces like
                    Wikipedia — particularly those of community members who are experts on their own
                    history. As of this writing, all of the class’s Wikipedia pages are still up,
                    all with references to <title rend="italic">From the Rock Wall</title>’s oral
                    histories (Figure 3). Moreover, through the process of creating and editing
                    these Wikipedia pages, students gained a deeper appreciation for the proud
                    history of the Black community in Chapel Hill and a commitment to honoring and
                    preserving it. After the project concluded, many students emphasized that the
                    class’s connection to Wall and the Jackson Center in particular made the most
                    impact. When asked about the value of working with community partners to create
                    Wikipedia pages, one student said that <quote rend="inline">I think this is
                        extremely important, as they [community partners] have the most knowledge
                        about their history, and the most accurate knowledge.</quote></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The References section from the Pottersfield Wikipedia page, one of the
                        student-originated Wikipedia pages.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <div>
                    <head>Information Infrastructure and Wikidata</head>
                    <p>Together with creating the Wikipedia pages, students also created
                        accompanying Wikidata pages for each site. They were also responsible for
                        using Wikidata’s query tool to investigate a dimension of data related to
                        their chosen site for their individual portfolio that accompanied their
                        group’s published sites. The last part of our lesson plan focused on
                        understanding the power and limitations of the structures on Wikidata and
                        its query tool. Learning about how Wikidata works helps students gain
                        important data literacy skills such as data processing, digital provenance,
                        data ethics, and data completeness <ptr target="#mcandrew_2017"/>. Rivard with the help of
                        a class visit from Rodriguez focused on equipping students with the
                        literacies needed to contribute to Wikidata, while also underscoring the
                        powerful role of information infrastructures represented by the structures
                        of Wikidata, especially when structured data is created by a community of
                        users, not just experts. As Marisa Ripoll et. al. explains, there are
                        limitations to vast open-ended collaboration within Wikidata as most editors
                        make only a few edits and do not completely grasp the way the data is
                        designed to be machine readable (i.e., the data is structured, standardized,
                        uniquely identified, and published in formats such as RDF and JSON designed
                        for computer use) <ptr target="#ripoll_2025"/>. The same content gaps and biases
                        demonstrated in Wikipedia around topics such as gender, race, and sexuality
                        are reproduced in Wikidata <ptr target="#ripoll_2025"/>. Because LLMs and search engines
                        constantly use Wikidata, these biases and gaps are then passed along. By
                        working to create their own Wikidata pages, students became aware of how
                        these biases are generated from the shape of data structures. </p>
                    <p>Contributing to Wikidata does not involve editorial review,<note>Other users
                            can, however, change the information that another user puts in, which
                            presents other issues of both power and accuracy.</note> so students
                        could add to Wikidata pages without fearing the kind of response that they
                        experienced on editing their first Wikipedia page. Students did, however,
                        struggle with property selection; they discovered that the seemingly
                        straightforward relational data structure of subject, predicate, object
                        (i.e., item, property, value) was far more interpretative than it first
                        appeared. Choosing the correct predicate to connect two objects revealed
                        some difficulty, as the vocabulary was not always straightforward and some
                        of the terms had similar definitions. Properties that indicated concrete
                        information of an item, such as its origin date or address, were grasped
                        with ease but more abstract properties were more difficult to understand.
                        Because these concepts were abstract and there was no editorial oversight,
                        there was a general lack of uniformity among the properties, which limited
                        the potential of its linked data. Even when the vocabulary used was
                        understood, students found that there was an absence of data (and relational
                        structures) concerning topics such as activists and cultural centers that
                        were key to connecting and describing the sites in the historically Black
                        neighborhoods served by the Jackson Center. </p>
                    <p>For example, the group of students who created the Wikipedia page for Watts
                        Restaurant noted that the restaurant marked the site of an important sit-in
                        protest in 1963 during the Civil Rights Movement. After creating the
                        Wikipedia page dedicated to explaining this history, the students wanted to
                        create a property in Wikidata for involvement in the civil rights movement
                        such that they could run a query that would show them all the important
                        sites in the Civil Rights Movement in North Carolina. However, no such
                        property existed, so they would not be able to answer this query. Unlike
                        other problems in Wikipedia, this was not an issue of an absence of data,
                        but instead an absence of the data structure to account for such a crucially
                        important part of American histories. As one student explained in their
                        final paper, <quote rend="inline">These gaps were not necessarily the result
                            of the data not existing but were rather the result of poor linking
                            connections. In turn, this causes an imbalance in power dynamics that
                            disadvantages marginalized groups of people.</quote> These gaps added
                        another valence through which students could think critically about why
                        certain data, such as items related to the histories of these communities
                        may be sparse compared to data related to others. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>DLC Revision and Community Feedback</head>
                    <p>By making use of an instructional design that introduced community experts
                        into the classroom, the community-based instructional design of the course
                        mirrored the community-based creation of the Wikipedia and Wikidata pages.
                        Our appeal to these different sites of knowledge made clear the fundamental
                        interdisciplinarity and interconnectedness intrinsic to the digital public
                        humanities. The community-based structure of the course drew students’
                        attention to the fraught and complicated ways in which power — often
                        exercised through definitions of legitimate data — is distributed between
                        the pedagogical space of the classroom, the institutional contexts of the
                        university, and the community-first perspectives of our partners at the
                        Jackson Center. Students were invited to intervene in this complicated
                        terrain as the assignment and the larger project that it fits within
                        positions <quote rend="inline">Wikipedia as a rhetorical challenge</quote> in
                        which we must <quote rend="inline">learn to push the boundaries of acceptable
                            Wikipedia style and content</quote> <ptr target="#nelson_2018" loc="490"/>. Because of the
                        real-world stakes of this project, students were committed to using the
                        tools we learned in class to address the uneven power relations in Wikipedia
                        and Wikidata. One student explained in their paper that they viewed the
                        objective of our project as making <quote rend="inline">the Jackson Center
                            initiatives more visible. By including these pages on Wikipedia, the
                            most comprehensive digital database, we get to decide what matters and
                            what is most visible… through our efforts, hopefully we have ’counted’
                            these histories [from the Jackson Center] into the modern digital
                            humanities sphere so that more people can learn about their
                            stories.</quote> Such feelings show how assignments that position <quote
                            rend="inline">Wikipedia as a rhetorical challenge</quote> give students
                        the opportunity to <quote rend="inline">learn to push the boundaries of
                            acceptable Wikipedia style and content</quote> <ptr target="#nelson_2018" loc="490"/>. </p>
                    <p>Though the course successfully met learning outcomes in digital and data
                        literacies and created valuable Wikipedia and Wikidata sites about Chapel
                        Hill’s Black history, our workflow prioritized sustainability beyond
                        individual semesters. We aimed to avoid the single course project model,
                        where community partners invest resources in a class only for the
                        collaboration to end when students leave, treating their work as a
                        conclusion rather than a foundation for ongoing engagement. Such single
                        course projects, even those with the best of intentions, contribute to
                        extractive and exploitative relationships between universities and
                        communities <ptr target="#knight_2022"/>. To ensure the longevity of the project, our
                        steps included continued editing by DLC lab staff, presentation of the sites
                        to community members, further revisions after community feedback, and
                        adjustments for subsequent sections of ENGL 114.</p>
                    <p>This workflow that extended beyond the course was made possible by
                        positioning the project within an already existing institution (the DLC
                        Lab). Rivard, who founded the lab in 2018, created a public humanities
                        initiative within the lab to fund the graduate students working on the
                        project as well as leverage the resources, expertise, and infrastructure of
                        the DLC. Having an infrastructural home-base for this project not only
                        helped secure the funding necessary to retain project staff but also
                        guaranteed continuity for this project and for this collaboration long term,
                        demonstrating the lab’s commitment to the Jackson Center that extends far
                        beyond the limits of a single semester of work. </p>
                    <p>While the sites created by ENGL 114 students represented good initial
                        Wikipedia pages that passed Wikipedia editors test of notability, more
                        editing was necessary to address issues raised by other Wiki editors and to
                        honor the complexities of the histories the pages discussed. DLC staff
                        edited each page with attention to the use of sources, paying particular
                        attention to their historical credibility. Much of the necessary editing
                        surrounded the use of sources, which partially was a result of students’
                        lack of training in historical research methods and Wikipedia’s rules of
                        verifiability. As we reviewed their final pages, we noted that the students
                        excelled at finding sources that helped them to understand the narrative
                        history of these sites. A common challenge, however, was their ability to
                        discern what was a credible secondary source. One page, for instance,
                        included a citation that was merely a hyperlink to a Word document with a
                        narrative about the history of the Hargraves Community Center, summarizing
                        an interview done with a former director of the Center in the 1980s from a
                        UNC archive [<hi rend="italic">Hargraves Community Center</hi>]. After
                        further research, we found relevant newspaper articles that confirmed the
                        information presented in the cited source. While the archival source was a
                        great starting point, it was just that — a starting point. Eventually, the
                        original citations and references were replaced with the stronger and more
                        credible citations to the original newspaper articles. </p>
                    <p>Our class discussions modeled how these documents could lead to stronger
                        secondary sources, but students needed more practice to understand which
                        sources met Wikipedia’s requirements. We adjusted our lesson plans for later
                        sections accordingly. Moreover, because this was a first-year course, many
                        of our students had not yet had in-depth experience or training with
                        identifying the kind of credible historical sources necessary for this
                        particular platform. It was essential to have advanced graduate students
                        trained in archival methods to extend these undergraduate students’ work.
                        Wiki editors are vigilant about attending to the principles of
                        verifiability, thus, the work done by these graduate students allowed us to
                        ensure that all sources were vetted. </p>
                    <p>After DLC staff further edited the pages, they presented the pages to the
                        Community Review Board (CRB) at the Jackson Center, and then held open
                        community meetings where anyone community members affiliated with the
                        Jackson Center could attend. Links to all of the pages as well as printed
                        copies were shared beforehand so that participants could review the work
                        that had been done. In these meetings, community members were asked to give
                        feedback on the pages and were also informed of the Wikipedia rules of
                        editing and page creation. Many CRB members had already been watching and
                        discussing the pages’ progress as updates were routinely shared by Wall
                        throughout the process. CRB member Pat Jackson relayed the community’s
                        excitement, commenting that one of the pages was <quote rend="inline">talked
                            about at [a local restaurant] for two weeks.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Importantly, community members provided critical feedback based on their
                        shared knowledge and lived experiences. For example, Mrs. Jackson noted an
                        error made on the Hackney School page in regard to its original location,
                        mentioning that it was something others had noticed as well [<hi
                            rend="italic">Hackney School</hi>]. In these meetings, CRB members gave
                        additional information that was essential to accurately, ethically, and
                        comprehensively representing the history of these important community spaces
                        such as those in the introduction of this article. The Jackson Center staff
                        also used this historical detail provided by community members to edit their
                        oral history website pages related to relevant sites thereby creating a
                        source of deep, accurate community history that serves as a source of
                        information and direct quotation for future Wikipedia edits.<note>The
                            Jackson Center’s website pages on these oral histories sites (referred
                            to as <title rend="quotes">Places</title> pages) also serve as stable
                            alternate sources of historical information about these historical sites
                            that are rich in community voices should Wikipedia editors reject oral
                            history quotations, even when they appear on reliable secondary sources
                            like the historian-curated and fully researched From the Rock Wall
                            website.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Though these lived experiences of community members were essential to
                        understanding the history of these sites and made available on the Jackson’s
                        Center website, we worried that only using quotations of oral histories that
                        explained these experiences on their website would likely not pass
                        Wikipedia’s <quote rend="inline">verifiability</quote> guideline [<hi
                            rend="italic">Reliable Sources</hi>]. Based on previous experience
                        editing pages and significant scholarly resources, we knew that there would
                        be increased attention to our sites as they focused on addressing historical
                        silences, and Wiki editors were quick to delete sections that did not have
                            <quote rend="inline">adequate sources</quote> <ptr target="#tripodi_2021"/>. </p>
                    <p>To ensure that our pages would not be deleted, we increased the size of the
                        DLC team by bringing in undergraduate research interns (Sarah Davey and Sage
                        Clausen), working alongside DLC graduate students with the goal of finding
                        additional sources that supported the knowledge of the community members.
                        For example, in one meeting, Mr. Gattis recalled a recent community event
                        where a family member of a Pottersfield resident told a story of her
                        childhood visits to the town. As she recalled these visits, she mentioned
                        that the neighborhood had no running water and that community members were
                        still using outhouses, a shocking difference from the town where she grew
                        up. From Mr. Gattis’s perspective, the story was told as if the Black
                        residents of Chapel Hill were merely <soCalled>Places</soCalled> country
                        folk, but the reality was their community was intentionally excluded from
                        municipal development. Davey and Clausen conducted extensive historical
                        research to further flesh out Mr. Gattis’ knowledge about this history
                        including that this lack of development was a symbol of institutional
                        racism. Through this research, they acquired articles from <title
                            rend="italic">Chapel Hill Weekly</title>, Board of Alderman meeting
                        minutes, and a Master’s thesis by Charles Freeman told the story of how the
                        community repeatedly petitioned for installation of sewers and water lines,
                        but were ignored for over a decade <ptr target="#freeman_1944"/>. We were then able to
                        cite these sources alongside oral history excerpts of Mr. Gattis from the
                        Jackson Center’s website, thereby providing extensive and abundant source
                        support that overwhelmingly meets Wikipedia’s verifiability guidelines. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Ensuring that the histories we collaboratively created remain on Wikipedia
                    requires extensive research (and related time and resources) as it is often
                    difficult to find sources that support community members’ knowledge as much of
                    this history has not been cataloged and preserved because of structural
                    inequities in library and archive systems. Another instance at this same meeting
                    on the Pottersfield neighborhood Wikipedia page evidences a research difficulty
                    that we found too common. There was a strong consensus among all members present
                    that Black residents were originally relegated to Pottersfield because it was a
                    geographically undesirable area in the late nineteenth century mostly due to
                    routine flooding that occurred, often experiencing significant run-off from the
                    adjacent university. Topographical maps make it clear that Pottersfield was
                    established in a place that was undesirable agriculturally and sat at a lower
                    elevation [Town of Chapel Hill]. The area was (and still is) easily flooded, and
                    huge swaths of it have rocky soil that would make it difficult for agricultural
                    development. It is also placed further away from the University and the city’s
                    main streets. While various features of the community and the collective memory
                    of this narrative make this claim of undesirability that led to the Black
                    community being relegated to this location clear, few sources from this time
                    period even exist as the town’s most prominent newspapers and many of the
                    government organizations that keep extensive records and meeting minutes about
                    the town’s happenings were created much later [<hi rend="italic">The Chapel Hill
                        Weekly</hi>, 1923-1972]. </p>
                <p>In such cases, Wikipedia’s editorial guidelines make it nearly impossible to
                    recount history accurately because they require editors to ground claims in
                    secondary sources that not only exclude the lived experience of marginalized
                    communities but have historically served to actively further the interests of
                    dominant groups. The result is a recollection of historical events that is often
                    unable to adequately represent the experience of communities like the one in
                    Chapel Hill. Despite the efforts of Black Chapel Hill residents to honor and
                    preserve their own history through extensive oral history projects, walking
                    tours, and community events and resources, many of the records they have created
                    do not meet Wikipedia’s requirements for <quote rend="inline">credible</quote>
                    sources [<hi rend="italic">Reliable Sources</hi>]. One can only imagine how this
                    would be even more challenging for communities who do not have formal
                    organizations like the Jackson Center that are committed to preserving local
                    histories. </p>
                <p>As Wikipedia continues to shape AI training data and search results, the stakes
                    of these editorial norms only grow higher. Our ongoing collaboration suggests
                    that sustained, reciprocal partnerships between universities and communities can
                    help intervene in these knowledge structures, but such interventions require
                    institutional support, dedicated resources, and a willingness to push against
                    Wikipedia’s boundaries. Most importantly, they require centering community
                    voices not just as sources to be cited, but as experts whose knowledge deserves
                    recognition within digital knowledge infrastructures. It is our hope that this
                    paper provides some practical tips about how to forge collaborative projects
                    that pool resources as well as how to push against the powerful boundaries of
                    Wikipedia to create more robust, accurate, and inclusive knowledge
                    structures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Appendix A: Wikipedia/Data Project Overview</head>
                <p>In this final project, we will explore the relationship between knowledge
                    production and data through a collaborative Wikipedia project with<ref
                        target="https://jacksoncenter.info/"> </ref>
                    <ref target="https://jacksoncenter.info/">Marian Cheek Jackson Center</ref>. The
                    Jackson Center is dedicated to “to honor, renew, and build community in the
                    historic Northside, Pine Knolls, and Tin Top neighborhoods of Chapel Hill and
                    Carrboro, NC.” Part of their mission to preserve history includes an oral
                    history project,<ref target="https://fromtherockwall.org/"> </ref>
                    <ref target="https://fromtherockwall.org/">From the Rock Wall</ref>. This robust
                    project contains so much important history though to get access to it, one must
                    navigate deep into the organization’s website. To help make some parts of this
                    history more easily accessible through web searches, we will create Wikipedia
                    pages of selected imported locations in the Northside neighborhoods. Because of
                    the linking structure, the frequent updates, and the great semantic markup,
                    Wikipedia almost always ranks high in search engines and is used as training
                    data for generative AI. Therefore, by creating these Wikipedia pages for the
                    Jackson Center, we will help to make their information more visible. Through
                    this effort, we will directly explore and analyze power structures within
                    Wikipedia through different types of data analytics.</p>
                <p>For this final project, you will work in groups of four people to create a
                    Wikipedia page with an accompanying Wikidata page on one important place in the
                    history of the Northside neighborhoods for the Jackson Center, and you will
                    present your Wikipedia and Wikidata pages together during our final exam period.
                    In addition to the group work, each person will individually turn in a portfolio
                    that describes their work, reflects on the process of creating these pages, and
                    conducts a Wikidata query based on the data generated from your project. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Group and Site Selection </head>
                    <p>We will select groups for your Wikipedia page in class, and you will create a
                        Memorandum of Understanding to identify specific roles and responsibilities
                        for each group member.</p>
                    <p>We will work in class to select historical sites based on group interest.
                        These sites were selected by the Jackson Center because of their importance
                        to local history. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements for Wikipedia pages</head>
                    <p>Each Wikipedia page must:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Follow the guideline of the 5 pillars of Wikipedia, including their
                            genre rules concerning a neutral point of view, using reliable sources,
                            and avoiding copyright and plagiarism</item>
                        <item>Include at least 2 internal links from each person in the group (for
                            example, a group of 3 will have at least 6 links)</item>
                        <item>Include at least 4 sources from each person in the group (for example,
                            a group of 3 will have at least 12 sources). Note: these sources can
                            include external links.</item>
                        <item>Include at least one image</item>
                        <item>Include an Infobox</item>
                        <item>Include the following sections: Lead section, body section entitled
                            “History” with at least 3 subtitles, See Also, and References<list
                                type="ordered">
                                <item>Note: if a different title/subtitle organization is necessary
                                    for your Wikipedia page, you can get approval for the
                                    alternative structure</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Be at least 500 words long, not including the references </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements for Wikidata pages</head>
                    <p>Each Wikidata page must:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Include at least 2 Wikidata properties from each person in the group
                            such that there are 8 properties. Each property must follow the Wikidata
                            conventions for data creation. </item>
                        <item>Include at least 1 reference for each property </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirements for Final Presentation</head>
                    <p>You will present your group’s Wikipedia and Wikidata pages together with
                        important points regarding the relationship of power and data that came up
                        during the project. </p>
                    <p>As a group, you will present your Wikipedia and Wikidata project to class
                        during your final exam period. Each group will have 12-15 minutes to
                        present. You will need to create slides for your presentation with
                        PowerPoint or another program to provide visuals alongside the spoken
                        portion of the presentation.</p>
                    <p>The final presentation should address the following:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Work Distribution<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Discuss the role of each person in the group, and the work
                                    they performed in the project.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Wikipedia page<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Present your Wikipedia page</item>
                                <item>Discuss the production process:</item>
                                <item>What pillars within the Wikipedia guidelines did you find most
                                        helpful?<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>What model article did you use to craft your
                                            page?</item>
                                        <item>What did you find most challenging about creating your
                                            Wikipedia page?</item>
                                        <item>What research did you find most helpful?</item>
                                        <item>What pages did you link to and why?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Describe how your pages' linking structure will impact the
                                    Jackson Center’s mission of promoting the history of the
                                    Northside communities. </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Wikidata Analysis<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Present your Wikidata page</item>
                                <item>Discuss the production process:<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>How did you decide what properties to create? </item>
                                        <item>What other Wikidata properties that were related to
                                            your Wikidata page did you look to for guidance in
                                            creating your properties?</item>
                                        <item>What links or connections were hoping to make by
                                            creating this property?</item>
                                        <item>What did you find most challenging about creating your
                                            Wikidata page?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Present the Wikidata query visualization of each group member.
                                    Each person should explain:<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>What did you query?</item>
                                        <item>What did you find in your query?</item>
                                        <item>Why did you choose to visualize this data in this
                                            way?</item>
                                        <item>Is there anything that you found surprising about this
                                            data (or the absence of it)?</item>
                                        <item>What else would need to be done to make this data more
                                            enriching and/or helpful?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Critical Reflection<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Discuss how your group saw the relationship between rhetoric,
                                    power, and data arise in the Wikipedia/Wikidata project?<list
                                        type="ordered">
                                        <item>What did you all find most interesting about this
                                            project?</item>
                                        <item>What was the greatest challenge?</item>
                                        <item>What advice would you give to the Jackson Center for
                                            creating other Wikipedia and Wikidata pages relating to
                                            their mission?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Requirement for Wikipedia Project Portfolio</head>
                    <p>In addition to the group portion of this project, you will individually turn
                        in a Wikipedia project portfolio. </p>
                    <p>The portfolio will consist of the following sections below. Please create
                        subheadings for each of the numbered sections. Answer each of the questions
                        in paragraph form (no bullet points).</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Work Sample<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Pdfs or screenshots of your Wikipedia and Wikidata
                                    pages</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Project Planning and Work Distribution<list type="ordered">
                                <item>A description of the work you contributed to the project
                                    including the 5 links and 2 sources you provided to the
                                    Wikipedia page and 2 properties and citations that you provided
                                    for the Wikidata page and how you performed given the
                                    responsibilities set out in your group’s MOU</item>
                                <item>Questions to address in your description:<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>How did your group divide the work for this
                                            project?</item>
                                        <item>What was your assigned role?</item>
                                        <item>How did you fulfill your role?</item>
                                        <item>What specifically did you contribute to the Wikipedia
                                            page?</item>
                                        <item>What specifically did you contribute to the Wikidata
                                            page?</item>
                                        <item>Were there any issues in labor distribution among your
                                            group mates? If so, explain.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Wikipedia Analysis<list type="ordered">
                                <item>A discussion of how your article corresponds to Wikipedia’s
                                    genre requirements</item>
                                <item>Questions to address in your description:<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>What pillars within the Wikipedia guidelines did you
                                            find most helpful?</item>
                                        <item>What model article did you use to craft your
                                            page?</item>
                                        <item>What did you find most challenging about creating your
                                            Wikipedia page?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>A hyperlink analysis of your Wikipedia page with an
                                    accompanying data visualization<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>To show the interconnectedness of your page, create a
                                            visualization (by hand or with a digital tool) that
                                            shows the pages your Wikipedia page links to. </item>
                                        <item>For example, if I created the Orange County Training
                                            School (OCTS) Wikipedia page, I would create a list of
                                            all the Wikipedia pages OCTS linked to and all the
                                            external sites it linked to (external sites will be in
                                            the reference section). I would then create a
                                            visualization that shows the effect of these
                                            links.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Describe what your visualization demonstrates and how this
                                    linking structure will impact the Jackson Center’s mission of
                                    promoting the history of the Northside communities. </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Wikidata Analysis<list type="ordered">
                                <item>A discussion of how your data corresponds to Wikidata genre
                                        requirements<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>Questions to address in your description:<list
                                                type="ordered">
                                                <item>How did you decide what properties to create? </item>
                                                <item>What other Wikidata properties that were
                                                  related to your Wikidata page did you look to for
                                                  guidance in creating your properties?</item>
                                                <item>What links or connections were hoping to make
                                                  by creating this property?</item>
                                                <item>What did you find most challenging about
                                                  creating your Wikidata page?</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>A Wikidata query analysis in which you run one query relevant
                                    to your Wikidata page and discuss the results with an
                                    accompanying data visualization<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>Just like we did in class, run one query that relates
                                            to your page, and create a corresponding visualization
                                            (by hand or with a digital tool).</item>
                                        <item>For example, if I created the OCTS page, I would run a
                                            query relating to the Rosenwald school Wikipedia page to
                                            find out where the Rosenwald schools were located. I
                                            would then create a map that showed these
                                            schools.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Address the following questions in relation to your Wikidata
                                        query<list type="ordered">
                                        <item>What did you query?</item>
                                        <item>What did you find in your query?</item>
                                        <item>Why did you choose to visualize this data in this
                                            way?</item>
                                        <item>Is there anything that you found surprising about this
                                            data (or the absence of it)?</item>
                                        <item>What else would need to be done to make this data more
                                            enriching and/or helpful?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Critical Reflection<list type="ordered">
                                <item>How did you see the relationship between rhetoric, power, and
                                    data arise in the Wikipedia/Wikidata project?</item>
                                <item>Cite and use at least 2 class readings in your discussion.
                                    When referencing a reader, make sure to use a direct quote and
                                    connect the quote to your argument.</item>
                                <item>The reflection portion of your paper should be 200-400
                                    words.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Appendix B: Memorandum of Understanding Assignment</head>
                <p>A Memorandum of Understanding is a voluntary agreement to assist in the
                    implementation plans of a collaborative project. It generally defines the
                    overall program goals and describes the collaborative nature and relationship
                    between the identified project and MOU-referenced participant. </p>
                <p>An effective Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) prevents misunderstandings and
                    disputes by clarifying the expectations of the partners. The process of
                    developing an MOU is an instructive and potentially invaluable experience for
                    partners. </p>
                <p>You will learn how responsive your partners will be — are your messages/emails
                    returned promptly? Do your partners give the partnership the attention and
                    seriousness it requires? You may also learn how your partners react when you
                    disagree on an issue (By: Nonprofit Risk Management Center).</p>
                <p>Create a copy of this MOU google doc and publish the link for the google doc in
                    your group’s google drive folder.</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Name of Wikipedia project </item>
                    <item>Name of people involved in the MOU </item>
                    <item>Identification of time period of project</item>
                    <item>Communication modes/standards:<list type="ordered">
                            <item>What are the desired modes of desired communication?</item>
                            <item>What will you do if standards and deadlines are not met?</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>Identification of roles and responsibilities each group member (see
                        below).</item>
                </list>
                <div>
                    <head>Wikipedia content editor</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Main responsibilities: <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Organize and manage development of the Wikipedia page (Note:
                                    everyone in the group must contribute content. Content editor
                                    manages development).</item>
                                <item>Divide labor of Wikipedia page writing evenly; </item>
                                <item>Create google doc as a space to draft the page; </item>
                                <item>Make necessary suggestions to your team’s contributors </item>
                                <item>Create the Wikipedia page once draft is finalized</item>
                                <item>Review content on Wikipedia page and make sure it meets
                                    corresponds with genre conventions of Wikipedia and requirements
                                    of the assignment</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Other responsibilities will be determined by each group</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Wikidata content editor</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Main responsibilities:<list type="unordered">
                                <item>Organize and manage development of the Wikidata page. (Note:
                                    everyone in the group must contribute content. Content editor
                                    manages development).</item>
                                <item>Divide labor of Wikidata page writing evenly; </item>
                                <item>Create google doc with proposed Wikidata statements</item>
                                <item>Make necessary suggestions to your team’s contributors</item>
                                <item>Create Wikidata page</item>
                                <item>Review content on Wikidata page and make sure it meets
                                    corresponds with genre conventions of Wikidata and requirements
                                    of the assignment; </item>
                                <item>Help group run data queries for their individual portfolio and
                                    group presentation</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Other responsibilities will be determined by each group</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Presentation editor</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Main responsibilities: <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Organize and manage development of the group’s final
                                    presentation. (Note: everyone in the group must contribute
                                    content. (Presentation editor manages development).</item>
                                <item>Divide labor of presentation creation evenly; </item>
                                <item>Create and manage google slides to collaboratively create
                                    group final presentation</item>
                                <item>Review content in presentation and make sure it meets
                                    corresponds with assignment and genre conventions of a
                                    presentation; </item>
                                <item>Make necessary suggestions to your team’s contributors</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Other responsibilities will be determined by each group</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Research Coordinator/Project Manager </head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Main responsibilities: <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Coordinate the different aspects of the project, </item>
                                <item>Serve as lead research manager - assign group members
                                    different sources to read and evaluate, organize sources
                                    collected by group, manage bibliography</item>
                                <item>Lead communications with the team and assure deadline
                                    compliance, </item>
                                <item>Store necessary assets and other materials needed for the
                                    project, including sources and images</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Other responsibilities will be determined by each group</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>This project would not have been possible without the generous collaboration
                    and guidance of folks at the Marion Cheek Jackson Center for Community
                    Engagement, particularly Kathryn Wall and Anna Spencer, whose vision and
                    commitment to preserving community histories made this partnership possible.
                    Our thanks extend to the Jackson Center Community Review Board members,
                    including William Gattis and Patricia Jackson, whose invaluable feedback,
                    lived experiences, and willingness to share their knowledge shaped this work
                    in fundamental ways. We are also grateful to new UNC members of this
                    collaborative who joined as we were in the editing stages of the paper,
                    including Sarah Ficke who taught another version of ENGL 114 and Aspen
                    Ballas who joined the DLC as a graduate student. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="autoconfirmed_2023">Wikimedia Foundation. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Autoconfirmed users</title>. <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Autoconfirmed_users">https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Autoconfirmed_users</ref> </bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ball_2019" label="Ball 2019">Ball, C. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                        >WikiLiteracy: Enhancing students' digital literacy with Wikipedia</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Information Literacy</title>, 13(2), pp.
                    253–271.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="beer_2016" label="Beer 2016">Beer, D. (2016) <title rend="quotes">The
                        social power of algorithms</title>, <title rend="italic">Information,
                        Communication &amp; Society</title>, 20(1), pp. 1–13. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118x.2016.1216147"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118x.2016.1216147</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="brown_2015" label="Brown 2015">Brown, J.J. (2015) <title rend="italic"
                        >Ethical programs: Hospitality and the rhetorics of software</title>. Ann
                    Arbor: University of Michigan Press.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="chapekis-lieb_2025" label="Chapekis and Lieb 2025">Chapekis, A. and
                    Lieb, A. (2025) <title rend="quotes">Google users are less likely to click on
                        links when an AI summary appears in the results</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Pew Research Center</title>, 22 July. <ref
                        target="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2025/07/22/google-users-are-less-likely-to-click-on-links-when-an-ai-summary-appears-in-the-results/"
                        >https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2025/07/22/google-users-are-less-likely-to-click-on-links-when-an-ai-summary-appears-in-the-results/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="chw_1923" label="The Chapel Hill Weekly 1923-1972"
                        ><title rend="italic">The Chapel Hill Weekly</title>. (1923-1972). Chapel
                    Hill, N.C.: Louis Graves. Available at: <ref target="https://www.loc.gov/item/sn92073229/"
                        >https://www.loc.gov/item/sn92073229/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="conatser_2022" label="Conatser 2022">Conatser, T. (2022) <title
                        rend="quotes">Open pedagogy and the archives: Engaging students in public
                        digital humanities</title>. In: Schwan, A., Thomson, T. (eds.) <title
                        rend="italic">The Palgrave Handbook of Digital and Public
                    Humanities</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, Cham. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-11886-9_13"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-11886-9_13</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="edwards-paschall_2022" label="From the Rock Wall, 2022"> From the Rock Wall (2022) <title rend="quotes">Cynthia Edwards-Paschall - On hanging out at Hargraves (clip).</title> <title rend="italic">From the Rock Wall</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://fromtherockwall.org/oral-histories/cynthia-edwards-paschall-on-hanging-out-at-hargraves-clip">https://fromtherockwall.org/oral-histories/cynthia-edwards-paschall-on-hanging-out-at-hargraves-clip</ref></bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="deckelmann_2023" label="Deckelmann 2023">Deckelmann, S. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Wikipedia's value in the age of generative AI</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Wikimedia Foundation</title>, 12 July. <ref
                        target="https://wikimediafoundation.org/news/2023/07/12/wikipedias-value-in-the-age-of-generative-ai/"
                        >https://wikimediafoundation.org/news/2023/07/12/wikipedias-value-in-the-age-of-generative-ai/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="dlc-lab" label="Digital Literacy and Communications Lab n.d.">Digital
                    Literacy and Communications Lab. University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
                        <ref target="https://dlclab.unc.edu/">https://dlclab.unc.edu/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="duncan_2020" label="Duncan 2020">Duncan, A. (2020) <title
                        rend="quotes">Towards an activist research: Is Wikipedia the problem or the
                        solution?</title>, <title rend="italic">Art Libraries Journal</title>,
                    45(4), pp. 155–161. doi:10.1017/alj.2020.24.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ewiki-education_2017" label="Wiki Education 2017">Wiki
                    Education. (2017) <title rend="italic">Editing
                    Wikipedia: A guide for student editors supported by Wiki Education.</title>  <ref
                        target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/90/Editing_Wikipedia_brochure_(Wiki_Education_Foundation)_(2017).pdf"
                        >https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/90/Editing_Wikipedia_brochure_(Wiki_Education_Foundation)_(2017).pdf</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="el-khatib_2020" label="El Khatib et al. 2020" sortKey="Elkhatib">El Khatib, R. et. al.
                    (2020) <title rend="quotes">An "open lab?" The Electronic Textual Cultures Lab
                        in the evolving digital humanities landscape</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 14(3). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/14/3/000480/000480.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/14/3/000480/000480.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="estill_2017" label="Estill 2017">Estill, L. (2017) <title
                        rend="quotes">Collaborative knowledge creation and student-led assignment
                        design: Wikipedia in the university literature class</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(3). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000320/000320.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000320/000320.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="farrar_2023" label="From the Rock Wall 2023" sortKey="Fromtheb"> From
                    the Rock Wall. (2023) <title>Eugene Farrar History (clip).</title> Available at: <ref
                        target="https://fromtherockwall.org/oral-histories/eugene-farrar-history"
                        >https://fromtherockwall.org/oral-histories/eugene-farrar-history</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ford-iliadis_2023" label="Ford and Iliadis 2023">Ford, H. and Iliadis,
                    A. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Wikidata as semantic infrastructure: Knowledge
                        representation, data labor, and truth in a more-than-technical
                        project</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Media + Society</title>, 9(3),
                    pp. 1–13. doi: 10.1177/20563051231195552.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="freeman_1944" label="Freeman 1944">Freeman, C. (1944) <title
                        rend="quotes">Growth and plan for a community: A study of Negro life in
                        Chapel Hill and Carrboro, North Carolina</title>. [Masters thesis,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]. <ref
                        target="https://cdr.lib.unc.edu/concern/dissertations/00000773z"
                        >https://cdr.lib.unc.edu/concern/dissertations/00000773z</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="gauthier-sawchuk_2017" label="Gauthier and Sawchuk 2017">Gauthier, M.
                    and Sawchuk, K. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Not notable enough: Feminism and
                        expertise in Wikipedia</title>, <title rend="italic">Communication and
                        Critical/Cultural Studies</title>, 14(4), pp. 385–402. doi:
                    10.1080/14791420.2017.1386321.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="gordon_2015" label="Gordon 2015">Gordon, T. (2015, February 22) <title
                        rend="quotes">Howard students and professors among many helping to add more
                        black history to Wikipedia's predominantly white database</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Atlanta Black Star</title>. <ref
                        target="https://atlantablackstar.com/2015/02/22/howard-students-professors-among-many-helping-add-black-history-wikipedias-predominantly-white-database/"
                        >https://atlantablackstar.com/2015/02/22/howard-students-professors-among-many-helping-add-black-history-wikipedias-predominantly-white-database/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="hackney-school_2026" label="Hackney School 2026">Hackney School.
                        <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>. (2026). [online] <ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackney_School"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackney_School</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="hcc" label="Hargraves Community Center n.d."><title rend="quotes">Hargraves
                    Center</title>. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">From the Rock Wall</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://fromtherockwall.org/images/hargraves-center-circa-1942"
                        >https://fromtherockwall.org/images/hargraves-center-circa-1942</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="hargraves_community_center_2026"
                    label="Hargraves Community Center 2026">Hargraves Community Center. <title
                        rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>. (2026). [online] <ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hargraves_Community_Center"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hargraves_Community_Center</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="heidebrink-bruno_2014" label="Heidebrink-Bruno 2014">Heidebrink-Bruno,
                    A. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Multiple and converging literacies: A review of
                        Learning the Virtual Life, edited by Peter Trifonas</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 8(3). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/3/000191/000191.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/3/000191/000191.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="iliadis_2023" label="Iliadis 2023">Iliadis, A. (2023) <title
                        rend="italic">Semantic media: Mapping meaning on the internet</title>.
                    Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="introduction_wikidata" label="Introduction. Wikidata">Introduction.
                        <title rend="italic">Wikidata</title>. <ref
                        target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Introduction"
                        >https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Introduction</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="kennedy_2017" label="Kennedy 2017">Kennedy, K. (2017) <title
                        rend="quotes">A long-belated welcome: Accepting digital humanities methods
                        into non-DH classrooms</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>, 11(3). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000315/000315.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000315/000315.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="kill_2012" label="Kill 2012">Kill, M. (2012) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Teaching digital rhetoric: Wikipedia, collaboration, and the politics of
                        free knowledge</title>, in Hirsch, B.D. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Digital
                        humanities pedagogy: Practices, principles and politics</title>. Cambridge:
                    Open Book Publishers, pp. 389–405.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="knight_2022" label="Knight 2022">Knight, A. (2022) <title
                        rend="italic">Community is the Way: Engaged Writing and Designing for
                        Transformative Change</title>. The WAC Clearinghouse; University Press of
                    Colorado. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.37514/PRA-B.2022.1480"
                        >https://doi.org/10.37514/PRA-B.2022.1480</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="lafferty_2025" label="Lafferty 2025">Lafferty, N. (2025) <title
                        rend="quotes">AI platform citation patterns: How ChatGPT, Google AI
                        Overviews, and Perplexity source information</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Profound</title>, 5 June. <ref
                        target="https://www.tryprofound.com/blog/ai-platform-citation-patterns"
                        >https://www.tryprofound.com/blog/ai-platform-citation-patterns</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="linking_2005" label="Linking 2005">Linking. Wikimedia Foundation.
                    (2005, February 28). <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>. <ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style/Linking"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style/Linking</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="littlejohn_2021" label="Littlejohn et al. 2021">Littlejohn, A., Hood,
                    N., Rehm, M., McGill, L., Rienties, B., &amp; Highton, M. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Learning to become an online editor: The editathon as a
                        learning environment</title>, <title rend="italic">Interactive Learning
                        Environments</title>, 29(8), pp. 1258–1271.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="lockett_2019" label="Lockett 2019">Lockett, A. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">Why do I have authority to edit the page? The politics of user
                        agency and participation on Wikipedia</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Wikipedia @ 20</title>. <ref
                        target="https://wikipedia20.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/5jb1d216"
                        >https://wikipedia20.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/5jb1d216</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ma-van-kleeck_2023" label="Ma and Van Kleeck 2023">Ma, X., &amp; Van
                    Kleeck, D. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Nothing new but better — adapting
                        pre-coordinated subject headings for digital collections</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Technical Services Quarterly</title>, 40(4), pp. 260–273. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/07317131.2023.2259693"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/07317131.2023.2259693</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="mcandrew_2017" label="McAndrew 2017" sortKey="Mcandrew">McAndrew, E.
                    (2017, November 22) <title rend="quotes">Wikidata in the classroom — data literacy
                        for the next generation</title>, <title rend="italic">Wikimedian in
                        Residence</title>. <ref
                        target="https://thinking.is.ed.ac.uk/wir/author/emcandre/page/6/"
                        >https://thinking.is.ed.ac.uk/wir/author/emcandre/page/6/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="mcdowell-vetter_2021" label="McDowell and Vetter 2021"
                    sortKey="Mcdowell">McDowell, Z.J., &amp; Vetter, M.A. (2021) <title
                        rend="italic">Wikipedia and the Representation of Reality</title>. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003094081"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003094081</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="minhaj-urs_2021" label="Minhaj and Urs 2021">Minhaj, M., &amp; Urs, S.
                    (2021) <title rend="quotes">Wikipedia infoboxes: The big data source for
                        knowledge bases behind Alexa and Siri virtual assistants</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Information Matters</title>. Vol.1, Issue 11. <ref
                        target="https://r7q.22f.myftpupload.com/2021/11/wikipedia-infoboxes-the-big-data-source-for-knowledge-bases-behind-alexa-and-siri-virtual-assistants"
                        >https://r7q.22f.myftpupload.com/2021/11/wikipedia-infoboxes-the-big-data-source-for-knowledge-bases-behind-alexa-and-siri-virtual-assistants</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="nelson_2018" label="Nelson 2018">Nelson, J. (2018) <title
                        rend="quotes">Rhetorical interventions: A project design for composing and
                        editing Wikipedia articles</title>. In K.L. Blair &amp; L. Nickoson (Eds.),
                        <title rend="italic">Composing Feminist Interventions: Activism, Engagement,
                        Praxis</title> (489–503). The WAC Clearinghouse; University Press of
                    Colorado. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.37514/PER-B.2018.0056"
                        >https://doi.org/10.37514/PER-B.2018.0056</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="jackson_2001" label="Oral History Interview with Fran Jackson 2001"
                    >Oral History Interview with Fran Jackson. <title rend="italic">Documenting the
                        American south: Oral histories of the American South</title>. (2001, March
                    23). <ref
                        target="https://docsouth.unc.edu/sohp/K-0208/excerpts/excerpt_7709.html"
                        >https://docsouth.unc.edu/sohp/K-0208/excerpts/excerpt_7709.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="our_story" label="Our Story">Our Story. <title rend="italic">The
                        Marian Cheek Jackson Center</title>. <ref
                        target="https://jacksoncenter.info/our-mission/our-story"
                        >https://jacksoncenter.info/our-mission/our-story</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="our_vision_2021" label="Our Vision and Mission 2021">Our Vision and
                    Mission. <title rend="italic">The Marian Cheek Jackson Center</title>. (2021,
                    February 13). <ref target="https://jacksoncenter.info/our-mission/"
                        >https://jacksoncenter.info/our-mission/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="piccardi_2021" label="Piccardi et al. 2021">Piccardi, T., Redi, M.,
                    Colavizza, G., &amp; West, R. (2021) <title rend="quotes">On the value of
                        Wikipedia as a gateway to the web</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings
                        of the Web Conference 2021</title>, 249–260. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3442381.3450136"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/3442381.3450136</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="prime_objective_2023" label="Prime objective 2023">Prime objective.
                    Wikimedia Foundation.  <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>.
                        <ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Prime_objective#:~:text=%22Imagine%20a%20world%20in%20which,Wikimedia%20movement%2C%20are%20working%20toward"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Prime_objective#:~:text=%22Imagine%20a%20world%20in%20which,Wikimedia%20movement%2C%20are%20working%20toward</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="reliable-sources" label="Reliable sources n.d.">Wikimedia Foundation. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Reliable sources</title>, <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>. Available at: 
                        <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Reliable_sources"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Reliable_sources</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ricoeur_2004" label="Ricœur 2004" sortKey="Ricaur">Ricœur, P. (2004) <title
                        rend="italic">Memory, History, Forgetting</title>. Translated by K. Blamey
                    and D. Pellauer. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ripoll_2025" label="Ripoll et al. 2025">Ripoll, M. et al. (2025)
                        <title rend="quotes">Filling in the blanks? A systematic review and
                        theoretical conceptualisation for measuring WikiData content gaps</title>,
                    arXiv preprint arXiv:2505.16383. <ref target="https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16383"
                        >https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16383</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ritchie_2014" label="Ritchie 2014">Ritchie, D.A. (2014) <title
                        rend="italic">Doing oral history</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="rivard_2022" label="Rivard 2022">Rivard, C. (2022) <title
                        rend="quotes">"Flagged for deletion": Wikipedia, the Federal Writers'
                        Project, and first-year composition</title>, <title rend="italic">Teaching
                        Through the Archives: Text, Collaboration, and Activism</title>,
                    248–262.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="sanders-thompson-hood_2016" label="Sanders Thompson and Hood 2016"
                    >Sanders Thompson, V.L. &amp; Hood, S.M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Academic
                        and community partnerships and social change</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Crisis of Race in Higher Education: A Day of Discovery and
                        Dialogue</title>, ed. W.F. Tate et. al., 127–149.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="schwan-thomson_2023" label="Schwan and Thomson 2023">Schwan, A., &amp;
                    Thomson, T. (Eds.). (2023) <title rend="italic">The Palgrave handbook of digital
                        and public humanities / edited by Anne Schwan and Tara Thomson</title>.
                    Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="sigalov-nachmias_2023" label="Sigalov and Nachmias 2023">Sigalov,
                    S.E., &amp; Nachmias, R. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Investigating the potential
                        of the semantic web for education: Exploring Wikidata as a learning
                        platform</title>, <title rend="italic">Education and Information
                        Technologies</title>, 28(10), pp. 12565–12614. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10639-023-11664-1"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/s10639-023-11664-1</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="silva-scott_2023" label="Silva and Scott 2023">Silva, E., &amp; Scott,
                    K. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Developing black feminist researcher
                        identities</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Information
                        Literacy</title>, 17(1). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.11645/17.1.3359"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11645/17.1.3359</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="simonite_2019" label="Simonite 2019">Simonite, T. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">Inside the Alexa-friendly world of Wikidata</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Wired</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.wired.com/story/inside-the-alexa-friendly-world-of-wikidata/"
                        >https://www.wired.com/story/inside-the-alexa-friendly-world-of-wikidata/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="smulyan_2020" label="Smulyan 2021">Smulyan, S. (ed.). (2021) <title
                        rend="italic">Doing public humanities.</title>.
                    Routledge.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="sommer-quinlan_2020" label="Sommer and Quinlan 2020">Sommer, B.W.,
                    &amp; Quinlan, M.K. (2020) <title rend="italic">The oral history manual</title>.
                    Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="town_chapel_hill" label="Town of Chapel Hill">Town of Chapel Hill. (n.d.)
                        <title rend="italic">Chapel Hill Open Data: Topography</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://opendata-townofchapelhill.hub.arcgis.com/search?q=topography&amp;tags=planning%2Chousing%2Ccommunity%2520development"
                        >https://opendata-townofchapelhill.hub.arcgis.com/search?q=topography&amp;tags=planning%2Chousing%2Ccommunity%2520development</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="tripodi_2021" label="Tripodi 2021">Tripodi, F. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Ms. categorized: Gender, notability, and inequality on
                        Wikipedia</title>, <title rend="italic">New Media &amp; Society</title>,
                    25(7), pp. 1687–1707. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/14614448211023772"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/14614448211023772</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="vetter_2014" label="Vetter 2014">Vetter, M. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Archive 2.0: What composition students and academic libraries
                        can gain from digital-collaborative projects</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Composition Studies</title>, 42(1), pp. 35–53.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="vincent-hecht_2021" label="Vincent and Hecht 2021">Vincent, N., &amp;
                    Hecht, B. (2021) <title rend="quotes">A deeper investigation of the importance
                        of Wikipedia links to search engine results</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction</title>, 5(CSCW1), pp.
                    1–15. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3449078"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/3449078</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="wikimedia-foundation" label="Wikimedia Foundation n.d.">Wikimedia Foundation. (n.d.)<title rend="quotes"> Wikimedia
                    projects.</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://wikimediafoundation.org/our-work/wikimedia-projects/#a3-technology"
                        >https://wikimediafoundation.org/our-work/wikimedia-projects/#a3-technology</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="zhao_2023" label="Zhao 2023">Zhao, F. (2023) <title rend="quotes">A
                        systematic review of Wikidata in digital humanities projects</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 38(2), pp.
                    852–874.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
