<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
   xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Graph based modelling
               of prosopographical datasets. Case study: Romans 1by1</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Rada <dhq:family>Varga</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Babeș-Bolyai University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rada.varga@ubbcluj.ro</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Stefan <dhq:family>Bornhofen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>CY Cergy Paris University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>stefan.bornhofen@cyu.fr</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000710</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000710/000710.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In this paper, we present and discuss a promising research avenue, that is the use of
               graph-based models and software for prosopographical data sets. Our case study will
               be constituted by Romans 1by1 (http://romans1by1.com/), a digital-born prosopography
               focusing on people attested in classical era inscriptions; it presently hosts
               approximately 18,000 open access persons files. The project aimed at employing new
               techniques and methodologies that come from other fields (i.e. computer science), in
               order to approach the study of ancient population in an innovative way, to ease the
               research, and to create an open-access tool, available for the academic community. In
               the scope of this paper, we use Romans1by1 as an example to explore the perspectives
               of ingesting the information from a prosopographical relational database into a graph
               database.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>I. Introduction</head>
            <p>Prosopography is a branch of historical research that emerged during the 19th century
               and soon became of major interest for the researchers of Antiquity. It is supposed to
               be <quote rend="inline">a study that identifies and relates a group of persons or
                  characters within a particular historical or literary context</quote>.<note>
                  Merriam Webster:<ref
                     target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/prosopography">
                     <!-- should be a citation instead of a note -->
                     https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/prosopography</ref>.</note> As for
               historical prosopography, K. Keats-Rohan canonically defines it as being<quote
                  rend="inline"> about what the analysis of the sum of data about many individuals
                  can tell us about the different types of connection between them, and hence about
                  how they operated within and upon the institutions — social, political, legal,
                  economic, intellectual — of their time</quote>
               <ptr target="#keatsrohan2000"/>. While it was initially oriented towards well-known
               elite personalities of the past, on whom information is rich, it has nowadays turned
               more and more towards the <q>normal people</q> of the ancient world, thus going into
               the depths of the socio-economic fabric of societies, revealed through micro-networks
               and the connections between them. </p>
            <p>In this paper, we present and discuss a promising research avenue, that is the use of
               graph-based models and software for prosopographical data sets. Our case study will
               be constituted by Romans 1by1 (<ref target="http://romans1by1.com/)"
                  >http://romans1by1.com/)</ref>, a digital-born prosopography focusing on people
               attested in classical era inscriptions; it presently hosts approximately 18,000 open
               access persons files. The project aimed at employing new techniques and methodologies
               that come from other fields (i.e. computer science), in order to approach the study
               of ancient population in an innovative way, to ease the research, and to create an
               open-access tool, available for the academic community. In the scope of this paper,
               we use Romans1by1 as an example to explore the perspectives of ingesting the
               information from a prosopographical relational database into a graph database.</p>
            <p>Most digital prosopographies are built as relational databases using SQL or similar
               query languages. Nowadays there is a trend toward exploring new approaches and new
               software. One example in this context is SPEAR, a project which translates factoid
               data into XML schemata <ptr target="#schwartz_etal2022"/>, and our current research
               comes as a new undertaking in the said direction.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>II. Graphs – a new way of insight into historical sources</head>
            <p>Over the past years, a great number of human cultural records have been digitized.
               They have been scanned, annotated, enriched with metadata and compiled in the form of
               digital collections. Henceforward domain experts strive to inspect these collections
               from multiple perspectives in order to understand their structure and inner
               correlations. Yet, the most efficient ways of studying this new amount of digital
               information still remain unclear. Traditional keyword or faceted searches rendering
               list and table views allow approaching the collections in the spirit of a data
               repository but they provide only little insight into patterns such as coverage,
               interconnections, co-occurrences or dynamics over time. As a consequence, they are
               often of only limited value, especially for exploratory data analysis. </p>
            <p>Graph models are a promising complementary approach to the exploration of such
               digital collections, by considering the data as a network of connected information
               through nodes and edges. The edges represent relationships between the nodes and
               their properties. By using graph models it is not only possible to apply network
               analysis metrics and algorithms to investigate the characteristics of the given data
               set. Furthermore, force-directed placement algorithms <ptr
                  target="#fruchterman_reingold1991"/> allow generating visual layouts where highly
               connected nodes are placed close together. Looking at these visualizations can help
               theresearcher to spot hidden implicit structures such as ego-networks, cliques, and
               central nodes which may point to historically relevant insights. </p>
            <p>A number of universal tools are readily available and widely used for graph analysis
               and visualization. Prominent examples include Gephi <ptr target="#bastian_etal2009"
               />, Cytoscape <ptr target="#shannon_etal2003"/> and Palladio (<ref
                  target="https://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio/"
                  >https://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio</ref>). The advantage of these off-the-shelf
               solutions lies in the fact that the graphs to be studied can be generated from any
               data source, as they are imported via pre-formatted files. However, the spreadsheets
               have to be structured and the considered data has to be limited in such a manner as
               to answer certain predetermined research questions. </p>
            <p>As an example, the user may be interested in the people cited in a set of documents
               and sets up the graph of all persons linked to the documents they are mentioned in.
               If a cluster of persons stands out for their high number of coappearances, the user
               may want to understand their family relationships, or learn more about the network of
               organizations and events they are connected to. However each follow-up graph requires
               exporting specific data from the database, and preparing and importing further
               spreadsheets. The resulting workflow is rather clumsy and not appropriate for
               exploratory studies with open questions. Moreover, when dealing with evolving data
               collections which are at times enriched or corrected, as is also the case with
               Romans1by1, it is more advisable to work with visualisations directly extracted from
               the original database and not via exported files that may become obsolete. </p>
            <p>Therefore, to keep the workflow swift and the visualisations up-to-date, the DH
               community started turning in the last years to the use of graph databases, i.e.
               dedicated database solutions where the information is from the outset inherently
               stored in the form of a graph. These solutions also typically come with built-in
               tools allowing the user to inspect their dataset in an interactive way via queries
               and straightforward visualizations. The next section discusses the conceptual key
               differences between traditional relational and graph databases, and presents several
               projects where a graph database have already been successfully applied.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>III. Relational databases vs. Graph databases</head>
            <p>Relational databases, simply defined as databases structured to save and recognize
               relationships between stored items, are extensively used in all scientific,
               industrial and commercial domains, and they continue as such to this day because of
               their efficient and non-redundant data storage and manipulation <ptr
                  target="#rob_coronel2000"/>. The relational database model organizes data into one
               or more tables of columns and rows, with a unique key identifying each row, called a
               primary key. The tabular structure is a good choice for many list like
               business-related records such as accounting or customer data management. However,
               relationships between data elements are often poorly represented in such databases.
               They have to be computed at query time by matching primary and foreign keys of all
               rows in the connected tables. These operations have exponential costs in calculus and
               memory footprint, so that relational databases tend to struggle with computing
               relationships efficiently <ptr target="#kleppmann2017"/>. Moreover, the rigid schemas
               of tabular data models makes it difficult to add new or different kinds of
               relationships.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, graph databases use particular graph-oriented data models with the
               concept of nodes and edges to store connections directly alongside the data. Nodes
               are the entities in the graph. They can hold any number of properties in the form of
               key-value pairs. Edges represent directed and named relationships between two nodes.
               Like nodes, edges can also have properties. In most cases, these are quantitative
               properties, such as weights, costs, or distances. It is important to understand that
               a graph data model cannot capture fundamentally new information compared to a
               relational data model. The key difference lies in the way data is organized and
               accessed. Where relational databases use indexing through unique keys to model
               relationships, graph databases, on the other hand, store edges through pointers
               allowing to rapidly find the neighbours of a node. Graph databases are therefore an
               efficient solution when dealing with volumes of highly connected data. As an example,
               the following relational table-based and graph based data models implement the same
               schema: <figure>
                  <head>Example of a relational table-based and the equivalent graph-based data
                     model</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Although two isolated connected nodes look like a triple of the form
                  <q>subject-verb-object</q>, note that a graph-based dataset is not organized in
               triples. Each node has a unique instance in the database and can be connected to many
               other nodes. </p>
            <p>A number of well-established graph databases is readily available, such as Neo4j
                  (<ref target="https://neo4j.com/">https://neo4j.com</ref>), ArangoDB (<ref
                  target="https://www.arangodb.com/">https://www.arangodb.com</ref>), DGraph (<ref
                  target="https://dgraph.io/">https://dgraph.io</ref>) and OrientDB (<ref
                  target="https://orientdb.org/">https://orientdb.org</ref>). Existing relational
               databases of digital historical collections have been imported or converted,
               partially or entirely, into such databases.  A typical example is the project <title
                  rend="italic">Regesta Imperii</title> (<ref
                  target="http://www.regesta-imperii.de/regesten/suche.html"
                  >http://www.regesta-imperii.de/regesten/suche.html</ref>), a vast collection of
               charters documenting the activities of Roman-German kings and emperors, as well as of
               the popes from the Middle Ages. Parts of this collection, divided into subcollections
               containing charters issued by a given emperor, have been transferred to graph
               databasesThe resulting visualizations allow for much easier comprehension of the
               connections between the appearing entities such as persons, places, actions, dates
               and events (<ptr target="#kuczera2017"/>; <ptr target="#kuczera2019"/>).</p>
            <p>The histoGraph project has been conducted at the Centre Virtuel de la Connaissance
               sur l’Europe (CVCE), a former research and documentation center that in 2016 was
               integrated into the University of Luxembourg. The project aimed at designing tools
               for exploratory investigation and analysis of an existing historical multimedia
               collection compiled by the CVCE (<ref target="https://www.cvce.eu/epublications"
                  >https://www.cvce.eu/epublications</ref>). The documents were processed via named
               entity recognition, and the links between the documents and the detected entities
               were stored in a graph database. As a key functionality, histoGraph implements an
               interactive graph visualization revealing co-occurrences of persons or locations in
               the collection (<ptr target="#novak_etal2014"/>; <ptr target="#guido_etal2016"
               />).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Histograph screenshot representing the network between prominent politicians in
                  the database. A click on a node shows additional information to the left (<ref
                     target="http://histograph.eu">http://histograph.eu</ref>)</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>A subset of the histograph dataset was reused in the BLIZAAR project whose objective
               was the design of innovative prototypes for the exploration of complex graph
               scenarios. Among other results, the interactive visualization platform Intergraph
                  <ptr target="#bornhofen_during2020"/> has been implemented and connected to the
               database. Intergraph offers a way to navigate through the data especially for users
               having no or very limited experience with database manipulation and graph theory.</p>
            <p>The above projects feature large and complex datasets with multiple types of
               connected entities (Persons, Places, Organizations, Things, Events, Dates, Actions,
               etc.). The Romans1by1 database stands out for its simplicity and allows showcasing
               the migration from relational to graph databases through a straightforward model
               procedure which can be readily adapted to many other uncomplicated historical
               datasets. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>IV. Romans 1by1 – from Relational to Graph database</head>
            <p>Most large datasets of ancient names or persons are not prosopographies in the
               technical sense, but <term>corpora</term> (defined as <emph>a collection of recorded
                  utterances used as a basis for analysis)</emph>. Nonetheless, some of them must be
               quoted for their role in the development of prosopographic research. So are <title
                  rend="italic">Prosopographia Imperii Romani</title> (PIR), <title rend="italic"
                  >Prosopography of the Byzantine World</title> (PBW), and <title rend="italic"
                  >Hellenistic Babylonia: Texts, Images, Names</title> (HBTIN), which tend to focus
               on specific and delimited time and place, and social class or categories of person.
               Equally valuable however, is the <title rend="italic">Lexicon of Greek Personal
                  Names</title> (LGPN), which does not gather the biographical data and other
               information typical of a prosopography, but identifies individuals and core
               information about them, including relationships with others. While these
                  <term>corpora</term> were paper-born, they have currently migrated to the digital
               environment. This phenomenon, the emergence of digital humanities in various forms,
               changes the shape of and perception on the non-elites prosopography for
               Antiquity.</p>
            <p>In the digital era, building prosopographies for the ancient world is very much
               tributary to the model suggested by John Bradley and his research group at King’s
               College London, which marked the shift from narrative descriptions to information on
               persons as structured data (<ref
                  target="https://www.kcl.ac.uk/factoid-prosopography)"
                  >https://www.kcl.ac.uk/factoid-prosopography)</ref>. Working mainly on the <title
                  rend="italic">Prosopography of Anglo-Saxon England</title> (PASE), Bradley
               theorized the concept of prosopographical <q>factoids</q> – small pieces of data
               about persons (name variants, occupations, places of residence, events in which they
               played a role, personal and professional relationships, possessions, etc.) provided
               by the sources, which are not exactly facts as we cannot verify their veracity (<ptr
                  target="#bradley2005"/>; <ptr target="#bradley_short2005"/>). Factoid
               prosopographers took these pieces of information and registered them into a
               relational database that reflected their connections and relationships. One of the
               main advantages of this model lies in the fact that it offers the opportunity to stay
               true to the source – a necessity when we are sometimes dealing with inconsistent or
               even antagonistic sources. </p>
            <p>Romans1by1 has been documented before (<ptr target="#varga2017a" loc="333–341"/>, and
               far more detailed, <ptr target="#varga2017b" loc="44–59"/>), thus we will only
               schematically present its architecture and the metadata. No doubt, one of the most
               important features is the creation of a born-digital prosopographical
                  <term>corpus</term>, constantly updated. Another advantage is given by the fact
               that the database was built in order to be very user-friendly and adaptable to the
               research question one has; more precisely, we speak of the search filters in each
               main category which allow the user to request a specific set of information from the
               database. In this manner, at a click distance, we can find, for example, who all
               members of private associations were, or who the attested governors of the provinces
               were. Moreover, all the information of our choice can be easily downloaded in an
               excel file and scientifically processed later on.</p>
            <p> Technically speaking, Romans 1by1 is a relational database, built in MySQL and
               following the best practice models for population databases <ptr
                  target="#mandemakers_dillon2004"/>. The metadata is structured into four major
               tables (<title rend="italic">Inscriptions</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Bibliography</title>, <title rend="italic">Personal Data </title>and <title
                  rend="italic">Personal relationships</title> – summing up to more than 100
               separate attributes).</p>
            <p>The first table to be filled in is the file of the source – <title rend="italic"
                  >Inscriptions</title>. To begin with, each inscription gets an identification
               code, formed of 5 digits and an acronym of the province’s name (D for Dacia, MS for
               Moesia Superior, MI for Moesia Inferior) – so we have, for example 00001MS. In this
               section, certain fields are linked to other existing resources, in order to obtain
               maximum efficiency for the users. The texts of the inscriptions are linked to the
               Epigraphische Datenbank Heidelberg (<ref
                  target="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/home"
                  >http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/home</ref>), Clauss-Slaby (<ref
                  target="http://www.manfredclauss.de/">http://www.manfredclauss.de/</ref>) and/or
               Packhum (<ref target="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/"
                  >https://epigraphy.packhum.org/</ref>) databases, while the places have been
               referenced to Pleiades (<ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/"
                  >https://pleiades.stoa.org/</ref>) or Trismegistos (<ref
                  target="http://www.trismegistos.org/">http://www.trismegistos.org/</ref>). The
                  <title rend="italic">Bibliography</title> section was conceived in a way so that
               extracting complete or selective bibliographical lists would be possible. Thus, a
               normalization table includes all bibliographical titles referred to and being quoted;
               with the help of a value list, one can choose one <title rend="italic">Bibliography
                  abbreviation</title> for which the full reference, detailed information and
               comments are then displayed. Of course, all data are linked to the <title
                  rend="italic">Inscription code</title>, selected as well from a value list.</p>
            <p>The core of the database is a table used for recording data about individual persons
               (labelled <title rend="italic">Personal data</title>), around which the entire
               network of relations is built. Each new entry represents a singular epigraphic
               attestation of an individual, and a unique ID is generated, which will help link the
               character within the various components of the database and with other database
               entries. The person is also manually linked to the source using a value list of the
               inscriptions` codes. In the case of one person being attested by multiple epigraphic
               sources, each attestation will be represented by a new entry, to which a new unique
               ID will be assigned and which will be doubled during linkage procedures by a common
               ID for all instances of the same person. Expectedly, this metadata is the most
               volatile one, being in a continuous process of modification and enlargement. As a
               principle, we are trying to remain faithful to the source and to record during the
               first phase only the minimum of deduced information. The first section of fields from
               this table includes personal identification information on the person: <title
                  rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Praenomen</foreign></title>, <title
                  rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Nomen</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"
                     ><foreign xml:lang="la">Cognomen</foreign>/Personal name</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Father/Master name</title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign
                     xml:lang="la">Agnomen</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign
                     xml:lang="la">Signum</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign
                     xml:lang="la">Natione</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"
               >Ethnicity</title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >Origo</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >Domus</foreign>, Local citizenship, Gender, Juridical status,
                  Occupation</title>, <title rend="italic">Deities</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Age</title> (at death), <title rend="italic">Details of life/death and
                  Observations</title>. For <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >Collegium</foreign>/Association </title>and <title rend="italic">Religious
                  position </title>we opted for check boxes, which open a series of fields. For the
               associative forms we have three free text boxes: <title rend="italic">Type of
                  association</title>, <title rend="italic">Position within the association</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Activities within the association</title>, which allow for
               certain flexibility and the possibility to accommodate information and realities from
               both Roman and Greek inscriptions. In the case of <title rend="italic">Religious
                  position</title>, the situation is a bit more complex: when checking this option,
               a drop down list of <title rend="italic">Sacerdotal office</title> opens whose values
               are (at the moment) <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >Augur</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >Flamen</foreign></title> and <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >Pontifex</foreign></title> and a series of further check-boxes: <title
                  rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Coloniae / Municipii
                  sacerdos</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic">Military <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >sacerdos</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic">Imperial priest</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Divinity priest</title>, <title rend="italic"><foreign
                     xml:lang="la">Laurentium Lavinatium</foreign></title>. All of them, with the
               exception of the last one, open a <title rend="italic">Details</title> text field for
               description (<ptr target="#varga2017b" loc="48–49"/>).</p>
            <p>The second half of the <title rend="italic">Personal information</title> table is
               dedicated to political and social status. This part of the metadata consists of a
               series of checkboxes, each opening different categories of specialized attributes:
                  <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Ordo senatorius, Ordo
                     equester</foreign></title>, <title rend="italic">Provincial Governor</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Procurator</title>, <title rend="italic">Local
                  magistrate</title>, <title rend="italic">Decurionate</title>. The next information
               items cover <title rend="italic">Imperial slave, Imperial freedman </title>and the
                  <title rend="italic">Military personnel</title>, all equipped with <title
                  rend="italic">Details</title> attributes.</p>
            <p>Based on the personal ID given to each individual, the <title rend="italic"
                  >Relationship</title> table will solely name the relationship between individuals
               (A to B and B to A) (<ptr target="#varga2017b" loc="50"/>), choosing from a drop-down
               menu. The relationship values have been encoded and we have tried to adjust the
               concepts to the SnapDrgn ontology (<ref target="https://snapdrgn.net/ontology"
                  >https://snapdrgn.net/ontology</ref>).</p>
            <p>Very important for us was the search interface of the database. Built with
               Ruby-on-rails, it was designed to respond to the most manifold and complex search
               options. Every component of the database has search filters for every particular
               field, as well as a general search.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Diagram of the Romans1by1 metadata</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Even though the schema seems complex due to the multitude of tables and fields, it is
               in fact straightforward. The main tables are the People (rpeople) and Inscriptions
               (rinscriptions), which are directly related, as people are attested solely and
               exclusively in inscriptions.  Another possible relationship is between people,
               attested in the same sources. Based on these, the design of the corresponding graph
               data model has been easy to conceptualize:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Persons and Inscriptions are graph nodes. Five Person types have been defined
                  according to their province: Dacia, MoesiaInf, MoesiaSup, PannoniaSup,
                  Dalmatia.</item>
               <item>Person-Person relationships and appearances of a Persons in an Inscription are
                  graph edges. The <title rend="italic">related_with</title> relationship between
                  two persons can be miscellaneous such as HusbandOf, FatherOf, WifeOf, SlaveOf,
                  etc.</item>
            </list>
            <figure>
               <head>The graph data model for Romans1by1</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>We selected the Neo4j database for the Romans1by1 use case because Neo4j:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Is an open-source native graph database publicly available since 2007</item>
               <item>Features Cypher, a declarative query language similar to SQL, but optimized for
                  graphs</item>
               <item>Offers built-in tools for manipulating and visualizing data, such as the Neo4j
                  Browser for developers and Neo4j Bloom for analysts</item>
               <item>Is used by companies and organizations in almost all industries</item>
               <item>Has an active graph community and sound documentation surrounding the
                  technology</item>
               <item>Is free to use under the GPLv3 licence for non-commercial use cases (Neo4j
                  Community Edition)</item>
               <item>Neo4j has been successfully used in other academic research projects (<ptr
                     target="#guido_etal2016"/>, <ptr target="#kuczera2017"/>).</item>
            </list>
            <p>The technical procedure for the data transfer of the relational to the graph database
               is the following:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>In MySQL, export the tables from the relational database in csv formatted
                  files</item>
               <item>In Neo4j, write import scripts in Cypher language which read the csv files and
                  create appropriate graph elements <list type="simple">
                     <item>a. Create a node for each entry in the tables Person and Inscription. All
                        table fields become node properties.</item>
                     <item>b. Create an edge for each entry in the many-many relationship tables
                        appears_in and related_with.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>When applying a graph model to ancient epigraphic sources, as it is the case of
               Romans1by1, we have to take into consideration two main factors: the texts are not
               standardized in any form, the details they offer being altogether subjective and the
               information is generally scarce. Nonetheless, a graph database brings forth the
               possibility to visualize connections in a direct manner, which can constitute an
               important advantage, especially for people who get in contact with the information
               for the first time such as students or researchers unfamiliar with the area.</p>
            <p>At this point, the main outcomes of our research can be divided in three general
               categories: source-connected, network-connected and diachronic distribution graphs.
               The relation of a given person to the sources and how he/she is represented in
               various texts is highly important, especially in the prosopography of Greek and Roman
               non-elite characters. Going a step further than the factoid model, we textualize
               individuals and individualize texts, meaning that the inscription itself - and the
                  <q>factoids</q> it narrates - become part of the individual’s ego-history <note>
                  The methodology comes from the Lived Ancient Religion group: <ref
                     target="https://www.uni-erfurt.de/en/max-weber-centre/projects/cooperation-projects/lived-ancient-religion/)"
                     >https://www.uni-erfurt.de/en/max-weber-centre/projects/cooperation-projects/lived-ancient-religion/</ref>.</note>
               Thus, the link between individual and source is rendered as more important than
               initially imagined by traditional historiography. The network analyses refer to
               individual networks, but it also allows researchers to compare and superpose two (or
               more) persons’ networks, as well as to visualize and investigate <q>immaterial</q>
               networks, connections between institutions, economic actors, etc. The diachronic
               distribution graphs show quantitative and qualitative changes that occur over time at
               the scale of epigraphic habits, network patterns and individual movement, in a
               certain region or micro-region. Correlating all these types of information and
               visualizing them comes with great analytic gains, as it reveals a more complex
               picture of the people we study and the fabric of their society.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>V. Case studies and preliminary results</head>
            <p>    Working on a virtually exhaustive repository, such as Romans1by1 is, gives one
               the opportunity to undertake macro-analyses, to dwell not only in the prosopographic
               data offered by a certain province but also to place these data in a wider context
               and get to relevant conclusions. The possibility to compare between provinces is also
               a huge gain, creating context and offering answers to questions that do not even
               reveal themselves otherwise.</p>
            <p>            What additions do we get from transposing the database into a graph
               format? Mainly, we get an extra degree of clarity, the possibility of bird eye
               visualizations of the people and the sources attesting them, as well as the
               possibility to identify more connections and relationships than a flatter,
               table-structured model would allow. All these allow us to reconstruct networks and
               undertake prosopographic analyses with more insight and relevance. </p>
            <p>For this section, we have selected a series of case studies to demonstrate how
               ingestion of information into a graph database model and their subsequent analysis
               from a historian’s perspective can improve our knowledge and understanding of ancient
               society. The first example is a selection of <hi rend="bold">all people attested in a
                  certain settlement - in our case Napoca, from Roman Dacia</hi>. In the graph
               below, the red nodes are our central entities, namely the attested people and the
               blue ones are the sources. Thus, here we can see not only the number of attested
               people but also the connection between them, as well as between them and the sources.
               Napoca was the first urban settlement of northern Dacia, became a <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">municipium</foreign> under Hadrian and a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >colonia</foreign> during Marcus Aurelius’ reign (<ptr target="#ardevan1998"
                  loc="61–65"/>; <ptr target="#voisian_etal2000"/>; <ptr target="#diaconescu2004"
                  loc="117–121"/>). As the administrative center of Dacia Porolissensis, it became
               the capital of the province and the seat of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >procuratores</foreign>, both praesidial (118/119-168) and financial (after 168).
               On the graphic representation, we have the chance to visualize the approx. 130 people
               of Napoca, their individual networks and pinpoint collective sources, which attest a
               multitude of persons implicitly connected. What is most striking at a first sight is
               an inscription attesting multiple people, thus creating a network. We are dealing
               with the list of members of the <foreign xml:lang="la">spira Asianorum</foreign> (CIL
               III 870) from 235, a local association reuniting people from the province of Asia. We
               know that the association, besides its social and religious role, was also involved
               in commerce. Unfortunately, no other member of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >spira</foreign> is attested by a different inscription as well and the network
               remains circular. Nonetheless, it tells us something about epigraphic habits: the
               source attesting a network is an association list, a document typical rather to Greek
               epigraphy; Latin commemoration or adulation habits imply rather small, often familial
               groups.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The people attested in Napoca and the sources</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Another possible case study of historical population is focused on onomastics.
               Namely, we have concentrated on the people bearing a certain name, in a certain area.
               The graph below lists all <emph>people bearing the nomen Claudius/Clodius in Pannonia
                  Superior</emph>. Here the interesting historical facts to take into account are,
               besides the number of name bearers in itself, the possibility to see relations and to
               observe if more members of the same family/group bear this <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >nomen</foreign>. In this case, we again mostly see small networks, but what
               strikes us in a few cases is the lack of explicit relationship between persons. For
               example, in one instance (CIL III 4244) we have two soldiers, named Tiberius Calusius
               Aplo and Tiberius Claudius Vanamius. The text explicates only the fact that Aplo is
               the heir of the deceased Vanamius, without revealing other potential relationship.
               Nonetheless, seeing them on an onomastic graph, the name similitude is much more
               obvious the possibility that the two were actually close relatives. </p>
            <p>In the case of the previous two examples, migrating from table-form to graph has a
               number of important and relevant aspects: first, we are able to see at a glance the
               entirety of people and adjacent sources (inscriptions). Then, we have a clear and
               immediate vision of the connections: in both cases we can easily observe that almost
               none of the characters is attested by more than one source. This ascribes the
               networks to very limited circumstances. Nonetheless, we do have a notable exception,
               in the person of Tiberius Claudius Victorinus (AE 1998, 1049; AE 2003, 1353),
               attested by two monuments. The man was a decurion of Savaria and we get to know him
               and his family from his son’s epitaph and from his own funerary monument. So, we have
               the representation of an elite family that doesn’t go beyond first degree blood
               connections. Even so, it is interesting to note that he outlived his son, as well
               that they preferred separate monuments (maybe connected to separate burial locations)
               instead of a larger family monument. </p>
            <p>As well, in both cases we see that we have a couple of major sources, attesting a
               multitude of people - more poignant in the first case, as we have the list of an
               association’s members from Napoca. All these features strike us as obvious on a graph
               representation and give us an overview of the epigraphic situation.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The people bearing the name Claudius/Clodius in Pannonia Superior</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Slightly different is the construction of personal networks. In this case, the
               research questions asked and answered are of a different nature.</p>
            <p>The first network we are showcasing is that of <hi rend="bold">Caius Ovinius
                  Tertullus</hi>, governor of Moesia Inferior in 198-201. What’s remarkable in this
               case is the fact that the many attestations don’t bring forth a proportionate
               quantity of human connections. Most attestations come from official monuments,
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">milliaria</foreign>, and dedications made by the governor
               alone. Only few inscriptions place him in a social context: the dedication for the
               emperors’ health made by a religious association (ISM II 82), or dedications made for
               his own health by members of his staff and other minor officials (as it is the case
               of Raesius Pudens, a <foreign xml:lang="la">primiscrinius officina</foreign> - CIL
               III 12370). So, what we get in this case is an important man, a local official, who
               doesn’t necessarily manifest himself epigraphically at a personal level, doesn’t
               dedicate to private deities and doesn’t associate family members to his acts, but is
               very present in the organization of the roads system from the province, as well as in
               the urban landscape building.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The network of Caius Ovinius Tertullus</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The last account focuses on the story of a relocation, of a merchant who leaves Dacia
               to live in Dalmatia, but retains links with his home province, around the year
               200.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Aurelius Aquila's network</hi> brings to the fore several topics of
               discussion. We know Aquila from an inscription discovered at Solin (ancient Salona,
               province of Dalmatia, in today's Croatia) and we learn that he was a merchant from
               the province of Dacia, former decurion of Potaissa. The inscription was placed on the
               front of a sarcophagus. The text of the inscription reveals the person buried in the
               sarcophagus: Valeria Ursina, daughter of Titus and wife of Aurelius Aquila. The
               husband, who dedicates the monument, tells us that the deceased was an "incomparable"
               wife and that they lived together for seven years without a single quarrel (CIL III
               2086). The sarcophagus, simple as it may have been as an accomplishment, denotes the
               status of the family in society, as obviously not everyone could afford such a
               monument.</p>
            <p>Aquila, however, is also known to us from an inscription from Split (Spalatum, near
               Salona). The two monuments have not been associated until recently <ptr
                  target="#varga2016"/>, and it was not known that we could reconstruct more of this
               person's life from them. This second monument is also funerary, but this time a stela
               - a gravestone. Here Aquila is in the role of 'most unfortunate father', as he was
               burying his son, Titus Aurelius Apollonius, who died at the age of 33 at Sirmium (in
               Lower Pannonia, now Sremska Mitrovica in Serbia). The young man had followed a
               military career, most likely as a centurion in a military cohort in Pannonia. But the
               tomb is not only Aurelius Apollonius', Aquila also buried two friends here: Aurelius
               Flavus, a Syrian merchant who died at 55, and Aurelius Lucianus. Of course, Flavus'
               trade immediately brings to mind the other monument, to which we shall return.</p>
            <p>An exact family reconstruction is impossible, and we have to wonder whether this son
               of Aquila is also the son of Valerius Ursina, or of a later wife of the decurion
               relocated to Dalmatia. There are, however, several clues suggesting that he is the
               son of Valeria. First, the name: the surname Titus is also that of the deceased
               wife's father. Then the age, 33 at the time of death, and the fact that the father
               was still fit, indicate the child was born in Aquila's youth. And finally, the lack
               of a mother to co-dedicate this funerary monument suggests her total absence from the
               landscape, and thus the death prior to that of the son. At this point, we must
               underline again the utility of a graph model, as the relationships, with or without a
               certain degree of ambiguity, appear visible, <q>clean</q>, and accurately connected
               to the sources, thus making interpretation easier and more to the point. </p>
            <p>Returning to the other two deceased honoured by this monument: of Aurelius Lucianus
               we know nothing else, as he is only attested here. Aurelius Flavus, however, appears
               on another monument in the province of Dacia itself. In Dacia, at Apulum, our
               character is attested with the same name and description as a merchant, Syrian by
               origin, on a dedication to Jupiter Optimus Maximus Dolichenus. This dedication was
               made together with another merchant, a Syrian as well, Aurelius Alexander.</p>
            <p>Aurelius Aquila, as decurion in Potaissa, was a member of the city's small local
               elite. It should be pointed out that Roman municipal elites were often actively
               engaged in local production and consumer markets, in commercial activities, lived and
               valued the same things as those who had a more or less similar economic position, but
               played no political role. At some point in his life, most likely while he was still
               quite young, our man moved to Dalmatia. We don't know his reasons, but they could be
               varied, ranging from better business opportunities offered by the Dalmatian coast to
               family reasons. We don't know if he came here married, or if he met Valeria Ursina in
               his new province of residence, but it is certain that after a few years of marriage
               the young woman died, leaving behind a son. The husband buries her with enough pomp
               to mark the family's position in society, and after this point we don't know what
               Aquila's life was like. We do know, however, that he remained in Salona and
               maintained his business ties with Dacia. Some of these ties overlap with personal
               ties of friendship. At one point, his and Valeria Ursina's son, a centurion in
               Pannonia, dies at the age of just 33, in circumstances unknown to us. At this point
               in his life we also find Aquila. But the Decurion honours not only the memory of his
               son by erecting a monument, but also of two friends, one of whom, Aurelius Flavus, a
               merchant from Dacia. Flavus, although he bears a very Latin name, is a Syrian
               merchant with connections in Dacia and Dalmatia, as the funerary monument shows.
               Aquila is in charge of the memory of these two friends, which leads us to believe
               that he also inherited them, at least in part, probably as a result of shared
               business and capital.</p>
            <p>Aurelius Aquila's small family and social network gives us a glimpse of real life and
               provides concrete details of the great mobility of merchants in the Roman Empire, as
               well as how strong and enduring the bonds built between them could be.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The network of Aurelius Aquila</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>VI. Concluding remarks</head>
            <p>The research behind this paper is still a work in progress — unavoidably, as a
               database such as Romans1by1 is a dynamic tool, constantly updated and clearly
               software development is iterative and will expand and evolve over time. Nonetheless,
               the selected case studies reflect the entirety of the scientific context, as known
               today. Applying a graph based data model to Romans1by1 led to visualizing not only
               the networks as defined in SNA, but also the entirety of people attested in a certain
               area, or displaying certain common features. </p>
            <p>As demonstrated, prosopographic researches for the ancient world have evolved greatly
               during the last few decades. The leap from paper to digital, followed by the
               implementation of the factoid model and its subsequent adapting to the needs of
               various projects, all represented great opportunities for researchers of the ancient
               world to gain new insight on their sources, as well as to present their results in a
               more synthetic and comprehensive manner. And while the historiography of the Roman
               Empire’s elites has been developing on a different level and scale since the 19th
               century, the prosopography of the non-elites, of the Empire’s middle classes, is very
               tributary to these recent developments. As the sources are scarce and practically
               unconnected, any possibility to connect them, to reveal patterns and understand
               social behaviours is a huge gain.</p>
            <p>This last point is where our researches come, as while absolute novelty is hard to be
               revealed when working on the same, known sources. What we managed to highlight are
               particular social and epigraphic habits: the preponderance of small, family networks
               in Napoca, the un-explicitated possible family relations from Pannonia Superior, a
               magistrate’s active involvement in the province’s organization, but lack of personal
               epigraphic manifestations, and finally a story of mobility, relocation and conserved
               networks which offer us a look into the lives of merchants.</p>
            <p>What our endeavour has proven is that new approaches take us a bit further into the
               social life of the Roman Empire, highlighting certain factual realities, as well as
               the possibilities the future holds for non-elite prosopography.</p>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ardevan1998" label="Ardevan 1998">Ardevan, R. (1998) <title rend="italic"
                  >Viața municipală în Dacia romană</title>. Mirton, Timișoara.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bastian_etal2009" label="Bastian, Heymann, and Jacomy 2009">Bastian, M.,
               Heymann, S., and Jacomy, M. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Gephi: an open source
                  software for exploring and manipulating networks</title>. Proceedings of the Third
               International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bornhofen_during2020" label="Bornhofen and During 2020">Bornhofen, S. and
               During, M. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Exploring dynamic multilayer graphs for
                  digital humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Applied Network Science</title> 5, 54</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bradley2005" label="Bradley 2005">Bradley, J. (2005) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Documents and Data: Modelling Materials for Humanities Research in XML and
                  Relational Databases.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 20.1 (2005):
                  133–51.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqh048"> </ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bradley_short2005" label="Bradley and Short 2005">Bradley, J. and Short,
               H. <title rend="quotes">Texts into Databases: The Evolving Field of New-style
                  Prosopography.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 20.1 (2005), pp.
                  3–24.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqi022"> </ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="diaconescu2004" label="Diaconescu 2004">Diaconescu, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Towns of Roman Dacia. An overview of recent archaeological
                  research in Romania</title>. In W.S. Hanson, I.P. Haynes (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Roman Dacia. The Making of a provincial society</title> (<title
                  rend="italic">Journal of Roman Archaeology Supplementary Series 56</title>),
               Portsmouth, Rhode Island (2004),  pp. 87-142.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fruchterman_reingold1991" label="Fruchterman and Reingold 1991"
               >Fruchterman, T.M.J., and Reingold, E. M. (1991) <title rend="quotes">Graph Drawing
                  by Force Directed Placement,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Software: Practice and Experience</title>, vol. 21(11), pp.
               1129-1164.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guido_etal2016" label="Guido et al. 2016">Guido, D., Wieneke, L., and
               Düring, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">histograph — Graph-based exploration,
                  crowdsourced indexation.</title>
               <title rend="italic">CVCE</title>, Luxembourg</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="keatsrohan2000" label="Keats-Rohan 2000">Keats-Rohan, K.S.B. (2000) <title
                  rend="quotes">Prosopography and computing: a marriage made in heaven?</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">History and Computing</title>, 12.1 , pp. 1-11.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kleppmann2017" label="Kleppmann 2017">Kleppmann, M. (2017) <title
                  rend="italic">Designing Data-Intensive Applications</title>. O’Reilly.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kuczera2019" label="Kuczera 2019">Kuczera, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Die <q>Regesta Imperii</q> im digitalen Zeitalter. Das Regest als Netzwerk von
                  Entitäten</title>
               <title rend="italic">Das Mittelalter</title>, vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 157-172.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kuczera2017" label="Kuczera 2017">Kuczera, A. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Graphentechnologien in den Digitalen Geisteswissenschaften</title>
               <title rend="italic">ABI Technik</title>, 37.3, pp. 179-196.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mandemakers_dillon2004" label="Mandemakers and Dillon 2004">Mandemakers, 
               K. and Dillon, L. (2004) <title rend="quotes">Best Practices with Large Datasets on
                  Historical Populations</title>, <title rend="italic">Historical Methods: A Journal
                  of Quantitative and Interdisciplinary History</title> 37.1: pp. 34-38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="novak_etal2014" label="Novak et al. 2014">Novak, J., Micheel, I.,
               Melenhorst, M., Wieneke, L., During, M., Moron J. G., Pasini C., Tagliasacchi, M.,
               and Fraternali, P. (2014)<title rend="quotes">HistoGraph - A visualization tool for
                  collaborative analysis of networks from historical social multimedia
                  collections,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proc. Int. Conf. Inf. Vis.</title>, 
               pp. 241–250.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rob_coronel2000" label="Rob and Coronel 2000"> Rob, P. and Coronel, C.
               (2000) <title rend="italic">Database Systems: Design, Implementation, and
                  Management</title>. (4th Ed.). Cambridge: Thomson Course Technology.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwartz_etal2022" label="Schwartz et al. 2022">Schwartz, D. L., Gibson,
               N. P. and Torabi, K. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Modeling a Born-Digital Factoid
                  Prosopography using the TEI and Linked Data</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal
                  of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>, pp. 1-35 </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shannon_etal2003" label="Shannon et al. 2003">Shannon, P., Markiel, A.,
               Ozier, O., Baliga, N. S., Wang, J. T., Ramage, D., Amin, N., Schwikowski, B., and
               Ideker, T. (2003) <title rend="quotes">Cytoscape: a software environment for
                  integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Genome Research</title> 13(11), pp. 2498-2504</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="varga2016" label="Varga 2016">Varga, R. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Aurelius Aquila, negotiator ex provincia Dacia. A prosopographic
                  reconstruction</title>. In R. Ardevan, E. Beu-Dachin (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Mensa rotunda epigraphica Napocensis, Cluj-Napoca</title>, pp. 27-34. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="varga2017a" label="Varga 2017a">Varga, R. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Romans 1 by 1. Documenting a population database for the Roman world</title>. In
               S. Orlandi, R. Santucci, P. M. Liuzzo, F. Mambrini (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital and traditional epigraphy in context</title>. Proceedings of the EAGLE
               2016 international conference, Roma, pp. 333-341.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="varga2017b" label="Varga 2017b">Varga, R. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Romans1by1 v.1.1. New developments in the study of Roman population</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Classics Online</title>, 3.2, pp. 44-50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="varga_etal2018" label="Varga et al. 2018">Varga, R., Pázsint, A., Boda,
               I., and Deac, D. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Romans 1by1. Overview of a research
                  project</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Classics Online</title>, 4.2, pp.
               37-63.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="voisian_etal2000" label="Voișian et al. 2000">Voișian, V., Bota, E., and
               Ciongradi, C. (2000) <title rend="quotes">Betrachtungen uber die Romerstadt
                  Napoca</title>. In  H. Ciugudean, V. Moga, (eds.) <title rend="italic">Army and
                  Urban Development in the Danubian Provinces of the Roman Empire, Alba
                  Iulia</title>, pp. 261–276.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
