<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Review of <title rend="italic">Intergenerational
                  Connections in Digital Families</title></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sucharita <dhq:family>Sarkar</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>D.T.S.S. College of Commerce, Mumbai, India</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>sarkarsucharita@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sucharita Sarkar is Associate Professor of English at D.T.S.S College of
                     Commerce, Mumbai, India. Her doctoral thesis investigated print and online
                     mothering narratives in contemporary India. Her research focuses on
                     intersections of maternity with body, family, culture, technology and
                     narrative. Some recent publications include articles in <title rend="italic"
                        >Open Theology</title> (2020); chapters in <title rend="italic">Food, Faith
                        and Gender in South Asia</title> (Bloomsbury, 2020); <title rend="italic"
                        >Thickening Fat </title>(Routledge, 2020); <title rend="italic">The Politics
                        of Belonging in Contemporary India</title> (Routledge, 2019), <title
                        rend="italic">Breastfeeding and Culture</title> (Demeter, 2018); <title
                        rend="italic">Mothers, Mothering and Globalization</title> (Demeter, 2017),
                        <title rend="italic">Motherhood(s) and Polytheisms</title> (Patron, 2017),
                     among others. Details of her research are available at
                     https://mu.academia.edu/SucharitaSarkar. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000530</idno>
            <idno type="volume">015</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2021-03-05">5 March 2021</date>
            <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-11-19" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This review synthesizes Sakari Taipale’s book <title rend="italic">Intergenerational
                  Connections in Digital Families</title> (Springer International Publishing, 2019),
               partially from an auto-ethnographic perspective. Borrowing from the book’s structure,
               the review is divided into three parts. The first section examines the definitions of
               digital families and the role of everyday communication technologies in connecting
               such families. The second section critiques the interconnected roles of family
               members and generations in maintaining digital connections, especially through
               Taipale’s revival of the notion of the <q>warm expert.</q> The final section assesses the
               book’s conclusions in the context of changing social policies. It also looks at the
               possibilities for future research in the domain of digital family studies (and, by
               extension, in digital humanities) that can germinate from Taipale’s concise
               study.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Auto-ethnographic review of Skarai Taipale's <title rend="italic">Intergenerational
               Connections in Digital Families</title> (2019)</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>As a <q>matricentric feminist</q> researcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers
            negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and
            extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly
            mediatized environment <ptr target="#oreilly2016"/>. As a mother, I belong to a
            dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across
            urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp
            groups. I, for instance, have separate WhatsApp groups for my immediate family (my
            partner and daughters), and for my extended family (a cousins’ group), besides also
            staying in touch with my mother, brother and his family through WhatsApp chats, in
            addition to phone calls. Hence, it is from a scholarly as well as a personal perspective
            that I started to read Sakari Taipale’s book, <title rend="italic">Intergenerational
               Connections in Digital Families</title> (Springer International Publishing, 2019),
            which examines the use and impact of digital social media communication among family
            generations. Although Taipale addresses the mother’s role in digital families, he moves
            beyond to explore the web of complex, multi-generational relationships that form modern
            families and traces the role of digital media in shaping and sustaining these
            relationships. </p>
         <div>
            <head>Defining Digital Families</head>
            <p>Taipale’s ethnographic research is based on extended group interviews conducted with
               sixty-six key respondents in Italy, Finland, and Slovenia in 2014 and 2015. He
               contextualizes his research against the rapid digitization of family life since the
               late 1980s and 1990s, limiting his observations to North America and Western Europe.
               Specifically, he notes a <quote rend="inline">general trend of families
                     <emph>consisting up to three generations</emph> now [becoming] digitally
                  increasingly connected</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="2"/> (emphases added). The way he chooses to define
                  <q>family</q> affords his research both scope and uniqueness. He rejects the
               stereotypical notion of the urban nuclear family confined to one household,
               preferring to engage with the emerging phenomena of <quote rend="inline">numerous
                  mixed and extended families made up of members regularly switching between
                  households and belonging to many families at once</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="2"/>. That shift in definition offers him a research
               gap: most existing research on digital communication practices in families focuses on
               dyadic connections in one-household families, especially communication between young
               members or between children and parents. Intra-family, digital, group communication
               practices of multi-generational, multi-household, geographically distributed families
               are an under-researched area, and Taipale’s research addresses this gap. </p>
            <p>Taipale examines the existing scholarship on extended families, referring to
               approximate terms like Rainie and Wellman’s concept of <quote rend="inline">networked
                  families</quote> as a <quote rend="inline">good starting point for understanding
                  the digitalization of family relationships</quote>
               <ptr target="#rainie2012"/>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="13"/>. However, such earlier definitions are mostly
               rooted in one-to-one communication technologies, and are thus too limited to
               accommodate the increasing popularity of group communication through social media
               networks within families. Building upon, and expanding, existing definitions, Taipale
               writes, <quote rend="inline">Digital family, as defined for the purposes of this
                  book, is one form of distributed extended family, consisting of related
                  individuals living in one or more households who utilize at least basic
                  information and communication technologies and social media applications to stay
                  connected and maintain a sense of unity despite no more than occasional in-person
                  encounters between them. Families of this type are, in fact, only now developing
                  and becoming visible, after older family members, grandparents in particular, have
                  begun to adopt and make use of a larger variety of digital technologies for family
                  communication</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="14"/>. His definition is flexible, accommodating a
               diverse range of family compositions beyond the immediate, from multiple generations
               living in a single household (like many of his respondents in Slovenia); to extended
               families that include cousins, aunts and uncles; to blended families that include
               step-relations; and dispersed families where children have moved out and may or may
               not be living with their own partners and/or children. Most significantly, in this
               fluid web of genetic, marital and even affective relationships, Taipale includes and
               explores the intra-family, <quote rend="inline">skipped-generation</quote>
               communication between grandparents and grandchildren, a relation which is often
               excluded from <quote rend="inline">official European data</quote> that focuses only
               on <quote rend="inline">first degree family relationships</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="16–7"/>. </p>
            <p>Examining the factors that led to the rise of the digital family, Taipale expectedly
               skims over the sociocultural transformations, like developments in Assisted
               Reproductive Technology (ART) and the reconfigurations of patriarchal systems.
               Instead, he focuses on the advancements in communication technologies that have
               changed the ways families relate and connect to each other. He considers the swiftly
               changing mobile-phone-that-has-morphed-into-the-smartphone, where the latest model
                  <quote rend="inline">grows old in just a couple of years,</quote> as a metaphor
               and metonym of the <quote rend="inline">fast pace of technological
                  advancement</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="26"/>. Taipale uses Madianou and Miller’s term <quote
                  rend="inline">polymedia</quote> to explain the <quote rend="inline">ever expanding
                  catalogue of personal media technologies</quote> as well as the <quote
                  rend="inline">personalizable</quote> content of smartphones that is accessible to
               members of digital families <ptr target="#madianou2012"/>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="27–8"/>. For families, personalization means that
               communication is often compartmentalized — children may use separate apps to connect
               with their parents and with their peers — and also that families may together choose
               specific apps like WhatsApp to form common interactive platforms. Digital families,
               thus, need increasingly larger numbers of digital appliances and technologies, as
               well as new skills and changing roles to be digitally ready and updated. </p>
            <p>Although classic sociological theories focus on parents’ roles in socialization,
               Taipale cites modern family studies research which explores the <quote rend="inline"
                  >two-way influences between older and younger family members</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="34"/>. Taipale believes two-way influences have not
               been adequately addressed because most existing research slants towards either the
               parents’ influences or the children’s agency. Taipale attempts to balance both
               aspects: how children teach some digital media use to their elders (smartphone and
               app use, but not e-banking or emails), whereas parents are increasingly more
               pro-technology at home. He also nuances this two-way support by exposing the
               escalation of conflict that sometimes accompanies it; by underscoring the context of
               wider social changes that has transformed conventional parent-child relations; and,
               also, by emphasizing the contextual contingency of any generalized conclusions. For
               instance, the eroding of parent-child hierarchies is not uniform across locations:
               Finland has more separation between adult children and parents than Slovenia or
               Italy. There are certain critical strategies that Taipale consistently deploys in the
               book: he takes a conclusion from established sociological research and either
               broadens its application or uses his triangular ethnographic research in Finland,
               Italy and Slovenia to indicate that most generalizations can be uneven or
               problematic. </p>
            <p>In a book on intergenerational digital communications, it is expected that there will
               be a central chapter examining the concept of generation and the processes of
               generationing. Taipale recognizes the obsoletion of the conventional notion of
               kinship-based, lineage-oriented generation in families because of the rapid and
               diverse pluralization of family forms. He rejects the concept of <quote rend="inline"
                  >strict generational division</quote> and considers a more flexible and processual
                  <quote rend="inline">post-Mannheimian approach to generational identity</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="41"/>. Mannheim distinguished between generation as
               location (based on birth year) and as actuality (where generational potential is
               actualized when people belonging to a particular generation unit live through and
               experience certain historical events in similar ways) <ptr target="#mannheim1952"/>.
               Taipale attempts to <quote rend="inline">update Mannheim’s original
                  conception</quote> of generational identity by inserting an <quote rend="inline"
                     ><emph>active process of <q>doing</q></emph> behind the formation of every
                  generation</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="49"/> (emphasis in original). This can occur through
               technology adoption and technology use in families. Taipale considers generationing
               as a life-course-long process which occurs as families are reconfigured over and
               over; for instance, when a person retires, he may need to stay in touch with his
               family through Skype even though he might never have needed it before. Instead of
               staying locked in generational binaries like digital natives and digital immigrants,
               Taipale urges for a more integrated approach that understands and examines how <quote
                  rend="inline">each cohort generation has no choice but to over and over again
                  reassess its technological self-understanding and reconsider its relative position
                  vis-à-vis other generations, as new digital tools, applications and services are
                  constantly being introduced that soon become perquisites for a well-functioning
                  independent life</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="51"/>. Taipale mostly uses ethnographic methods like
               interviews to study how family generationing processes are impacted through the
               everyday learning and use of digital media. However, these changes in digital
               families may also be studied through a digital humanities approach: for instance, by
               using methods of <quote rend="inline">digital pedagogy</quote> and <quote
                  rend="inline">digital literacy</quote> to understand the uneven digital learning
               processes and outcomes in family generations <ptr target="#kennedy2017" loc="¶2"
               />. Analysing everyday digital learning within families through digital humanities
               methods would also perhaps open up possibilities for applying such pedagogic tools to
               improve digital learning in family generational cohorts. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Gendered Role of Warm Experts</head>
            <p>In the second part of his book, Taipale continues his critical strategy of
               re-contextualizing and nuancing current theoretical concepts, as he attempts to
               articulate the new roles and everyday practices that are shaping digital families.
               One of the pivotal concepts that Taipale revisits is the role of the <quote
                  rend="inline">warm expert,</quote> Maria Bakardjieva’s term for <quote
                  rend="inline">an Internet/computer technology expert in the professional sense or
                  simply in a relative sense</quote> who is in a <quote rend="inline">close personal
                  relationship</quote> with, and is <quote rend="inline">immediately
                  accessible</quote> to, the <quote rend="inline">less knowledgeable other</quote>
               (in contrast with the cold expert — the external professional helper) <ptr
                  target="#bakardjieva2005" loc="99"/>. Taipale deploys the concept of the warm
               expert to analyse the digital family relations that he researches, and he concludes
               that there are one or two younger family members in most families who are assigned
               the role of warm experts. These experts help to improve or sustain the digital skills
               of older members. </p>
            <p>Warm experts may be physically present and may co-use digital technologies and
               applications with older members (for instance, grandchildren using Skype when
               visiting grandparents), or, they may be proxy users for older members who are unable
               to learn new digital skills (like paying bills online). Taipale’s research indicates
               that most warm experts are youth between 20-35 years helping their parents or older
               siblings; some are <quote rend="inline">skipped-generation warm experts,</quote> who
               provide help to grandparents without parents getting involved; and sometimes, even,
               older family members are acting as warm experts <quote rend="inline">for their
                  age-mates</quote> especially if they lived in the same household <ptr
                  target="#taipale2019" loc="66"/>. In countries like Slovenia, where
               multi-generation families stay in the same household, help-giving and help-taking
               between warm experts and others are organic; whereas in dispersed families in
               Finland, help is often given via the telephone. Taipale also explores the complex
               affects generated through the warm expert-novice relationships. While most warm
               experts feel a sense of reward, some do occasionally feel frustrated, especially at
               the need to repeat instructions multiple times or at the excessive time taken by
               novices. Conversely, the older generation learners are sometimes dissatisfied with
               the limited expertise of the warm experts. Taipale’s recuperation of the role of the
               warm expert resonates with me as a digital family member, as I recall learning how to
               navigate smartphone apps from my often-impatient daughters, and as I recall both me
               and them being more patient in teaching my mother how to use Facebook and
               WhatsApp.</p>
            <p>Along with rejuvenating the notion of the warm expert, Taipale introduces the concept
               of digital housekeeping, referring to all the responsibilities and tasks required for
               the functioning of the digital family. As the digital housekeeper, the warm expert is
               consulted — in varying degrees — about most digital <quote rend="inline">hardware
                  purchases</quote> by the family, although the <quote rend="inline">cultural
                  norm</quote> is that parents make decisions regarding purchase of appliances,
               since they pay for them <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="78"/>. Moreover, in all cases
               the warm experts are given responsibility for the proper functioning of the
               appliances, as well as for installing and teaching others about latest software and
               applications. However, Taipale’s research suggests that knowledge transfer within the
               family is often two-way, with the older generation, especially parents, teaching the
               younger members, including warm experts, about the risks of certain digital practices
               like data oversharing. Taipale’s research uses the concepts of the warm expert and
               digital housekeeping to flip normative, hierarchical generational relations, and to
               propose a more fluid, intergenerational cooperation that <quote rend="inline"
                  >empowers younger family members, consolidates family connections and enhances
                  solidarity across generations</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="85"/>. Taipale here restructures intergenerational
               relations through flexible digital concepts that allow him to reassign varied family
               dynamics into categorizable and analysable data. His concepts of warm experts and
               digital housekeeping recall Carlson’s talk on data cleaning that demonstrates how
               computing processes aid in the study of human culture (and society), or Schöch's view
               of <quote rend="inline">smart data</quote> which is <quote rend="inline"
                  >clean,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline">structured,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline"><hi rend="italic">selectively constructed</hi></quote> and represents <quote
                  rend="inline"><hi rend="italic"
                     >some aspects of a given object of humanistic inquiry</hi>:</quote> the object of inquiry, in this case, being the digital
               family as interpreted through the data and lens selected by Taipale <ptr
                  target="#carlson2016"/>
               <ptr target="#schoch2013" loc="¶8"/> (emphases in original). </p>
            <p>However, Taipale is insistent about not replacing one homogenized norm with another
               generalized conclusion. He points out how gendered anomalies often exist even in the
               generationally radical concept of digital housekeeping. Some of his key respondents
               articulated <quote rend="inline">normative expectations</quote> of motherhood: <quote
                  rend="inline">Digitally skilled mothers sometimes considered themselves
                  responsible for ensuring the proper functioning of software and applications in
                  the family</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="83"/>. Taipale acknowledges the sense of empowerment
               such mothers feel, but does not limit himself to this one-dimensional perspective. He
               problematizes the extension of the <quote rend="inline">traditional role of mothers
                  as the maintainers of the home and domestic social relationships</quote> into the
               domain of <quote rend="inline">software care,</quote> because, with the rise of
               women’s digital skills, even the task of digital housekeeping would perhaps <quote
                  rend="inline">quietly end up being included</quote> in the already time-consuming
               burden of domestic care work that women are expected to manage <ptr
                  target="#taipale2019" loc="83"/>. As a matricentric feminist researcher, I wish
               that Taipale had further unpacked this gendered anomaly: <emph>why</emph>
               should the empowering function of the warm expert become burdensome for mothers? The
               answer, of course, is not that the work of digital housekeeping is specifically
               challenging for mothers; it is that the non-digital housekeeping and caregiving have
               always been considered the primary responsibility of mothers, and so any addition to
               that pre-existing workload is, often, an overload. My lived experience also
               pluralizes Taipale’s argument: I am mostly so overloaded with domestic and
               professional work that the digital housekeeping is done by my partner, while our
               teenaged daughters are the warm experts. Conversely, it is only when the non-digital
               domestic housekeeping is shared by others (when the partner cooks, for instance),
               that I can devote some time to digital housekeeping or communicating. Readers will do
               well to reflect on how more <quote rend="inline">visible feminism</quote>
               <ptr target="#wernimont2013"/> around the use of personal technologies would shift
               the assignments and everyday assumptions of roles.</p>
            <p>Taipale does, however, reveal other findings that are significant from a motherhood
               studies perspective. In his analysis of the increasing uses of WhatsApp in
               intra-family communication, he notes how this multimodal, scalable, private, instant
               messenger service enables both dyadic and also larger group communication between
               family members. For Taipale, the <quote rend="inline">larger meaning of sharing and exchanging small
               messages, photos and video clips</quote> on WhatsApp resides in the insertion and expansion
               of the ethics of <q>sharing as caring</q> into the everyday family digital space <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="95"/>. Taipale’s research indicates that this sharing-as-caring aspect of
               WhatsApp communication is usually gendered as it is most visible in mother-daughter
               interactions. Many of his respondents emphasized the centrality of mothers in
               creating and maintaining WhatsApp groups as opposed to fathers’ more limited
               involvement. For Taipale, this finding consolidates his earlier argument about the
               gendered inequities of digital housekeeping functions. Therefore, even specific
               technologies like WhatsApp emerge as <quote rend="inline">new forms of immaterial labour</quote> or care work
               that is gendered <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="93"/>. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Implications of Re-familization</head>
            <p>Moving around feminist analyses of intra-family digital communication, Taipale
               chooses to probe deeper by using Bengtson and Roberts’s model of intergenerational
               solidarity <ptr target="#bengtson1991"/>. Bengtson and Roberts contend that there are
               six types of solidarity within families: associational solidarity (spontaneous and
               ritual forms of communication); affectual solidarity (exchange of emotions and
               sentiments like trust); functional solidarity (exchange of help); normative
               solidarity (endorsement of family obligations); consensual solidarity (shared
               beliefs, etc), and structural solidarity (availability of family members, which
               depends on physical proximity and health). Taipale argues that digital families
               demonstrate these solidarities to varying degrees, as new media communication
               technologies are mostly associated with affectual, associational and functional forms
               of intergenerational solidarity. Forming of family WhatsApp groups is an action based
               on associational solidarity; the inclusion or exclusion of family members from family
               WhatsApp groups depend on the affectual solidarity within groups; whereas functional
               solidarity is evident in, for instance, grandchildren providing intergenerational
               digital knowledge and help to grandparents. However, Taipale is careful never to
               flatten his research findings. He stresses the differences in WhatsApp use in the
               three countries where his research is conducted. Finland has small-sized, scattered
               families that use group messaging services to reinforce family ties. In Italy, family
               WhatsApp groups are larger, including cousins, aunts, uncles, even those who live
               abroad. In Slovenia, family members often live in close proximity, and consequently
               do not feel the need for digital connections — this is distinct from other digital
               skills and practices — as much as the others. </p>
            <p>Grounded in the theory of intergenerational solidarities, and acknowledging the
               differences in the various respondents, Taipale introduces the <quote rend="inline">notion of
               re-familization</quote> to understand the <quote rend="inline">cohesive impact of digital technologies in the
               context of extended and geographically distributed families;</quote> he politicizes this
               notion by contextualizing the current social thrust on re-familization against the
               earlier policies of de-familization pursued by welfare states <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="117"/>.
               De-familization refers to the combination of social policies between 1950s to the
               late 1980s that promoted increased participation by women in workplaces and
               independence of the citizenry through governmental spending on welfare measures like
               childcare, elderly care, and paid maternity leave. In contrast, the European Union’s
               post-1980s thrust on re-familization, which claims to promote <quote rend="inline">citizen empowerment</quote>
               through policies accelerating digitalization, is rooted in <quote rend="inline">the need to restrain
               public expenditure</quote> <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="119"/>. Taipale notes how re-familization manifests
               itself both positively and problematically through his research findings.
               Generational hierarchies in digital families are often democratized through the rise
               of warm experts; members spend more time and effort in <q>doing</q> families; the
               internal, intergenerational solidarities within digital families increase. However,
               Taipale also notes the unevenness in re-familization in the three countries studied.
               He notes the continuation of inequities marking re-familization, as <quote rend="inline">fathers and
               grandparents are left out while mother-children communicate</quote> <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="122"/>. </p>
            <p>Taipale mentions the digital skills gap that exists between older and younger
               generations, and also between the less educated and more educated members in
               families. However (and perhaps expectedly), there is no mention of the digital divide
               that is so marked in countries like India, where I am located. Even his choice of
               respondents excludes ethnic minorities or immigrants. This may be considered a
               limitation, but it also helps in sharpening the focus of his investigations on his
               selected group of ethnic-majority digital families in Finland, Italy and Slovenia
               that may be multi-generational, blended, extended, and distributed. In Taipale’s
               concise book, each chapter has an abstract, keywords and a separate references
               section. It is, according to the publisher’s strategy, explicitly directed towards a
               mixed readership of students, lay readers, and researchers. The heterogeneous target
               readership perhaps accounts for the repetitiveness of certain concepts, arguments and
               conclusions throughout the book. The book also reads somewhat drily, without the
               conversational flows and narrative interest that often mark interview-based
               ethnographic research. Taipale’s interview extracts are inserted within his analyses
               in specifically marked sections, and they are not integrated into the flow of the
               writing. We do not get to know the fleshed-out <q>stories</q> of the respondents, even
               those whose quotes appear multiple times in the book. In contrast, Julie Wilson and
               Emily Yochim’s recent book, <title rend="italic">Women’s Work and Digital
                  Media</title>, develops the life stories of the mothers interviewed by the
               researchers, and almost each chapter begins with a narrative probe into the life of a
               mother <ptr target="#wilson2017"/>. As a digital humanist, I wish that the rigid
               structure of Taipale’s book had flexed enough to document and narrate the nascent
               stories of the respondents.</p>
            <p>Despite the structural and stylistic stiffness, the book adds significant insights to
               the emerging scholarship about digital communication and family, which is where
               Taipale locates his research. He moves beyond earlier research that focuses on
               technology use by individuals or by diasporic/transnational families, and focuses on
               studying the everyday use of digital media in families. Unlike existing research
               which often concludes that digital media has negatively impacted the affective,
               intimate relations between family members, Taipale takes a moderate, balanced view in
               his study of linkages between digital connections and caring relationships within
               families. In his concluding chapter, Taipale suggests that further research may be
               done to <quote rend="inline">investigate how caring relationships are played out in
                  practice in the digital family</quote> or on <quote rend="inline">any possible
                  positive long-term effects of the help and care provided by warm experts</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="129"/>. Early on in the book, Taipale emphasized the
               concept of <quote rend="inline">doing family</quote> rather than <quote rend="inline"
                  >being family,</quote> configuring family as asynchronous, always-in-process, and
               mediated through communication technologies: his aim, he states, is <quote
                  rend="inline">to promote thinking that deviates from that represented by the
                  individual networking and one-household approaches</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="17"/>. His research is exclusively focused on
               intra-family use of ICTs and social media connections, and his definition of the
               digital family includes multiple generations, relations and households. This flexible
               definition of the digital family opens up other domains of research into the
               processes and connections that <q>do</q> families. For instance, Taipale acknowledges that
               although use of WhatsApp between peer-to-peer groups among children and youth have
               been documented, the growing use of WhatsApp in <quote rend="inline">the everyday
                  life of extended families is still an unexplored territory</quote>
               <ptr target="#taipale2019" loc="89"/>. This indicates potentialities of research at
               various intersections of relationships (families/peers) and technologies (newer forms
               of social media) that allow participants to fulfil the needs of social bonding rather
               than merely exchanging information. I know my own story — the frequent updates,
               messages and video-chats that my partner, daughters and I have several times every
               day are essential in sustaining and strengthening the bonds among us. I know of so
               many similar emerging stories that are undocumented and under-researched. As a
               matricentric feminist scholar and a mother belonging to a dispersed, digital family
               located in South Asia, Taipale’s work makes me hope for further research that
               narrates, compares and theorizes our shared yet unique experiences. </p>
            <p>There are several possibilities for further research that extends digital family
               studies to digital humanities, and this can include scholarship with a matricentric
               feminist focus. Scholars have made persuasive arguments for including <quote
                  rend="inline">genealogy and family history</quote> in the cohort of humanities
               computing and digital humanities <ptr target="#hoeve2018"/>. There can be similar
               overlaps between digital humanities and the domains of digital family
               communication/learning or digital family/generational relations. To envision one such
               project (located in Taipale’s research problem but moving away from his chosen
               ethnographic methods) we can archive, compare and analyse the data from anonymised
               WhatsApp conversations within or between family cohorts through digital humanities
               tools for data mining and text analysis, which may lead to new understandings of how
               the concepts of warm experts and digital housekeeping operate within digital
               families. Focusing on the quality and quantity of maternal involvement in these
               WhatsApp conversation-texts would constitute a much-needed matricentric feminist
               intervention. Similarly, digital family relations, networks, learning (and other ways
               of <q>doing</q> families) can be mapped and studied through other ‘texts’ such as
               mom-blogs or Facebook posts. Expanding the possibilities beyond social media texts,
               we may apply the findings regarding relational dynamics within digital families to
               analyses of family relations in literary texts studied in digital humanities. Many
               such interventions from multiple theoretical and multidisciplinary standpoints are
               possible in the imbrications of digital family studies and digital humanities. The
               Digital Humanities 2.0 Manifesto states that <quote rend="inline">Digital Humanities
                  studies the cultural and social impact of new technologies as well as takes an
                  active role in the design, implementation, interrogation, and subversion of these
                  technologies</quote>
               <ptr target="#svensson2012" loc="¶78"/>. Taipale’s ethnographic research studies
               the impact and implementation of new technologies in digital families, and future
               researchers of family studies and digital humanities can use it as a pivot or a
               springboard for many exciting and forward-looking explorations into family-digital
               interactions. </p>
         </div>


      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bakardjieva2005" label="Bakardjieva 2005">Bakardjieva, M. <title
                  rend="italic">Internet Society: The Internet in Everyday Life</title>. Sage,
               London (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bengtson1991" label="Bengtson and Roberts 1991">Bengtson, V. L. and
               Roberts, R. E. <title rend="quotes">Intergenerational Solidarity in Aging Families:
                  An Example of Formal Theory Construction,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Marriage and Family</title> 53.4 (1991):
               856-870.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carlson2016" label="Carlson 2016">Carlson, S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Grateful Data: Digital Humanities, Data Cleaning, and the Grateful
                  Dead,</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Frontiers</title>. UNT Digital Library,
               Texas (September 22, 2016). <ref
                  target="https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc948134/m1/"
                  >https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc948134/m1/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoeve2018" label="Hoeve 2018">Hoeve C.D. <title rend="quotes">Finding a
                  place for genealogy and family history in the digital humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Library Perspectives</title> 34.3 (2018): 215-226. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1108/DLP-11-2017-0044"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1108/DLP-11-2017-0044</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kennedy2017" label="Kennedy 2017">Kennedy, K. <title rend="quotes">A
                  Long-Belated Welcome: Accepting Digital Humanities Methods into Non-DH
                  Classrooms,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 11.3 (2017). <ref
                  target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000315/000315.html"
                  >https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000315/000315.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="madianou2012" label="Madianou and Miller 2012">Madianou, M. and Miller, D.
                  <title rend="italic">Migration and New Media: Transnational Families and
                  Polymedia</title>. Routledge, London and New York (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mannheim1952" label="Mannheim 1952">Mannheim, K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Essay on the Problem of Generations.</title> In P. Kecskemeti (ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">Essays on the Sociology of Knowledge by Karl Mannheim</title>,
               Routledge and Kegan Paul, New York (1952), pp. 276-320. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oreilly2016" label="O’Reilly 2016">O’Reilly, A. <title rend="italic"
                  >Matricentric Feminism: Theory, Activism, Practice</title>. Demeter Press,
               Bradford, ON (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rainie2012" label="Rainie and Wellman 2012">Rainie, L. and Wellman, B.
                  <title rend="italic">Networked: The New Social Operating System</title>. MIT
               Press, Cambridge, MA (2012). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schoch2013" label="Schöch 2013">Schöch, C. <title rend="quotes">Big?
                  Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities </title>2.3 (2013). <ref
                  target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/"
                  >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2012" label="Svensson 2012">Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Envisioning the Digital Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 6.1 (2012). <ref
                  target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/1/000112/000112.html"
                  >https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/1/000112/000112.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="taipale2019" label="Taipale 2019">Taipale, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title>. Springer International
               Publishing (2019). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013" label="Wernimont 2013">Wernimont, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary
                  Archives,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7.1 (2013). <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilson2017" label="Wilson and Yochim 2017">Wilson, J. A. and Yochim, E. C.
                  <title rend="italic">Mothering through Precarity: Women’s Work and Digital
                  Media</title>. Duke University Press, Durham (2017). </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
