<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Stacks and Intersections: Feminist Thinking in
                    Digital Humanities, a view from <q>these islands</q>
                </title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Caroline <dhq:family>Bassett</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3788-7381</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Cambridge</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>cab238@cam.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Caroline Bassett is Professor of Digital Humanities at the University of
                            Cambridge. She is the author of Anti-Computing and the co-authored
                            Furious. She was UK PI on IFTE, a gender and technology network, with
                            researchers from Sussex and Maynooth. Recent publications include
                            articles on deadbeats and the digital afterlife, on AI and literature,
                            and on cruel optimism, feminism and AI.  She is currently writing a new
                            monograph on the end of thinking. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Kylie <dhq:family>Jarrett</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2631-3430</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University College Dublin</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kylie.jarrett1@ucd.ie</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Kylie Jarrett is Professor in the School of Information and Communication
                            Studies at University College Dublin. She is author of <title rend="italic">Digital Labor</title> (2022) and <title rend="italic">Feminism, Labour, and Digital Media: The Digital Housewife</title>
                            (2016) and co-author of <title rend="italic">NSFW: Sex, Humor and Risk
                                in Social Media</title> (2019) and <title rend="italic">Google and
                                the Culture of Search</title> (2013). She is also editor of the new
                            journal <title rend="italic">Dialogues in Digital Society</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sharon <dhq:family>Webb</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4148-7324</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Sussex</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sharon.webb@sussex.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr Sharon Webb is an Associate Professor of Digital Humanities and a
                            Director of the Sussex Digital Humanities Lab at the University of
                            Sussex. With an interdisciplinary background in history and computer
                            science, their research sits at the intersection of digital humanities,
                            critical archival studies, and digital preservation. Her expertise spans
                            several key areas, including gender and technology, feminist and queer
                            archives, critical digital archives, community heritage, and the
                            socio-political impacts of technological development. She was Co-I for
                            AHRC-IRC funded project, IFTE, and more recently PI for the AHRC-IRC
                            funded project, Full Stack Feminism in Digital Humanities.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000807</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2025-10-17">17 October 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#archives"/>
                    <term corresp="#gender"/>
                    <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    
                
                  <term>feminist digital humanities</term>
                  <term>stack politics</term>
                  <term>full stack feminism</term>
                  <term>feminist theory</term>
                  <term>intersectional feminism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist" target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000807/000807.xml">GitHub</ref>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Intersectional feminist work around digital archiving can productively develop
                    stack models to address questions concerning the location, site, and materiality
                    of possible and effective feminist intervention. Developing this proposition, we
                    draw on two DH research projects undertaken between the UK and Ireland (2020 and
                    on-going) focussing on work around community archives at a moment of their
                    radical transformation. </p>
                <p>Asking what feminist DH can be in relation to these archives, we engage with the
                    hollowing out of intersectional feminism – noting that it at times becomes a
                    reached for category rather than a useful signifier, while also recognizing that
                    theorizing forms of intersection between categories and groups experiencing
                    discrimination is essential to grappling with issues including new forms of
                    institutionalization, context dependency, and privacy. </p>
                <p>An exploration of various forms of Critical Race Theory (CRT) and of more
                    historically materialist thinking around intersectionality enables us to develop
                    a feminist-informed stack approach able to grapple with the complicated stakes
                    of archiving histories of trauma – including those undertaken by those in
                    different situated positions. </p>
                <p>We use this to inform a discussion of <q>where feminism should act</q> and
                    develop an argument that stack models – echoing in theory what is found in
                    material infrastructure – can be useful as guides to think about appropriate and
                    expanded sites for feminist intervention in DH. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>This discussion is about feminisms, Digital Humanities (DH), stacks, and
                    archives. We argue for Full Stack Feminism, as a methodological approach,
                    informed by the successes of previous feminist interventions in DH.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head/>
                <p>This discussion is about feminisms, Digital Humanities (DH), stacks, and
                        archives.<note> Authorship is listed in alphabetical order – authors
                        contributed equally to developing, writing, and editing. </note> It is
                    fuelled by a recognition that much has come into feminism to shake it out of its
                    comfort zone in recent years, including specifically – but not only – Critical
                    Race Theory (CRT). We argue that this process is on-going. Further consideration
                    of intersectional feminism(s) is necessary to reconsider the operations of
                    feminist DH, including asking <hi rend="italic">where</hi> it operates, <hi rend="italic">how</hi> it operates, and for <hi rend="italic">whom</hi>. In
                    this context, we explore how a stack model, referring to the layers that
                    constitute a specific technical architecture nested within connected systems and
                    also to their relations, can be used to map the geo-political, social, cultural,
                        <hi rend="italic">and technical location</hi>s of possible and effective
                    feminist interventions within and across DH. The argument made is for Full Stack
                    Feminism, as a methodological approach, informed by the successes of previous
                    feminist interventions in DH, and seeks to build on them. </p>
                <p>We work through these questions, and test our approach, by exploring issues that
                    arise as archives are transformed through digital processes, while also
                    recognizing the intersecting networks that constitute today’s digital systems –
                    the internet, libraries, platforms – of which archives are only one part. The
                    focus on archives appears to us apt in that it recognizes that we are in a
                    pivotal archival moment – and because working with archives in a digital era
                    demands addressing questions that relate to multiple operational layers – in
                    relation to infrastructure, metadata, and presentation, for instance.
                    Intersectionality, often conceived of as a horizontal model, thus joins with
                    stack approaches sensitive to depths and vertical layers.</p>
                <p>What are the archival changes to which we refer? On the one hand <q>The
                        Archive</q>, as a concept, an institution, and in its various iterations, is
                    being <q>queered</q>, transformed, lauded, criticized, decolonized, and
                    demystified. On the other, digitization programmes – coupled with born digital
                    ephemera, and new standards formally enabling openness and transferability –
                    have created an opportunity to rethink the boundaries of archives, to ask what
                    gets archived and where. As (Arondekar 2005) puts it, <quote rend="inline">the
                        archive is no longer the sacrosanct domain of the discipline of
                        history</quote>; and nor, we might add, of archival or information studies,
                    both of which may also have felt that the archive was their own. Today’s
                    archival systems link to other networks and are integral to our daily lives,
                    shaping our interactions and preserving our memories. It is within this context
                    that we specifically investigate how archives and feminist archival practices
                    can be comprehended within a stack model or framework.</p>
                <p>The discussion is informed by a research network<note> The IFTe Network
                        (Intersections; Feminism, Technology and Digital Humanities) sought to
                        address a critical challenge in contemporary society and culture (the gender
                        imbalance in computational practices and systems), to address issues of
                        feminism in DH, and also to think specifically about (other) forms of
                        post-colonial history; notably those traversing the UK and Ireland. Funded
                        by UKRI-AHRC and the Irish Research Council under the <title rend="quotes">UK-Ireland Collaboration in the Digital Humanities Networking
                            Call</title> (AH/V00199X/1 and IRC/V00199X/1). Followed up by Full Stack
                        Feminism (on-going). </note> co-funded by the UK and Irish research
                    councils, exploring feminisms and DH; <title rend="italic">Intersections:
                        Feminism, Technology and Digital Humanities (IFTe), a transnational
                        networking project between researchers in the UK and Ireland – these islands
                        of ours</title>, IFTe (2020-21). Its aims were to explore a proposition,
                    generate new connections, and produce new forms of working, including working
                    collaboratively, across the Irish Sea – <q>these islands</q> being a term
                    referencing the history of racism, gender oppression, heteronormativity, and
                    colonialism that pertain to the UK and Irish contexts and that condition their
                    relationship with each other.<note> The toponym <q>British Isles</q> refers to a
                        European archipelago consisting of Great Britain, Ireland, and adjacent
                        islands. In documents drawn up jointly between the British and Irish
                        governments, the archipelago is referred to simply as <q>these islands.</q>
                        We frame our experiences of feminism within the context of our experiences
                        of intersectional feminism in the UK and Ireland. By its very nature, a
                        feminist perspective from the UK and Ireland (Republic of) must be
                        considered within a colonial and decolonial lens – both as coloniser (UK)
                        and colonised (Ireland). While there is much debate about how Ireland has
                        historically fit the <q>colonised</q> model, we know Ireland was used as a
                        sandpit or playground for English imperial training and
                        methodologies/atrocities. </note> It also located our situated position as
                    joint authors as this paper is intended to be globally responsive but doesn’t
                    make a global statement or claim. </p>
                <p>Issues of the archive, and the generation, storage, and circulation of archival
                    material, were key in the work of the IFTe network. The IFTe network drew on
                    archival history and memory studies, and was centrally informed by
                    discussions and interactions with communities and individuals with experiences
                    of lack, silencing, or othering in memory – institutionally and/or socially –
                    for whom archives at times constituted an uneasy restitution, and at others
                    threatened to be a further expropriation. </p>
                <p>This paper explores three key questions. First, we seek to elucidate how an
                    approach to generating a feminist analysis structured around the concept of
                    stacking can be informed by an engagement with diverse perspectives on feminism
                    and intersectionality. Second, we ask how various kinds of intersectional
                    feminist interventions into DH can respond to stack models, stacked
                    architectures, and other theoretical or analytic models that have drawn on
                    stacks. Third, it questions at what levels at what levels (what depths), across which materials, and by
                    refusing or conforming to which real and imaginary architectures, with their
                    boundaries and openings, do feminisms need to work? Here, community archiving
                    and questions of archival justice constitute a case study, but they are also
                    more than that, being also a provocation for the work done. </p>
                <p>The paper begins by considering intersectional feminisms’ current entanglements
                    with DH before turning to consider debates around intersectionality itself –
                    this being undertaken through a focus on Critical Race Theory and historical
                    materialism (each of which are, in different ways, interested in how relations
                    are articulated in various forms). These discussions, and in particular asking
                    how various explorations of structural (even base and superstructural) forms of
                    discrimination and/in their tensioned relationship, can play out in the context
                    of issues emerging in DH, particularly around digital justice, returns us to the
                    stack, considered as an explanatory model <hi rend="italic">and</hi> as an
                    operating and multi-layered infra-structure that conditions digital politics.
                    Finally, the possibilities for Full Stack Feminisms are evidenced through
                    examples drawn from the IFTe’s activities and engagements, specifically through
                    archives and archival work. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The stack </head>
                <p>What is a stack? It is first of all a technical model (for instance the OSI
                    model), which sets out how systems like the internet operate. It consists of
                    hierarchical layers, with each layer abstracting upwards, handling functions
                    independently, and defining principles for interaction. Potentially fostering
                    platform agnosticism (or interoperability) and promoting ideas of layered
                    emergence, it can also promote compartmentalized thinking. The stack has
                    variously been taken up as a way of modelling extant systems, as a technical
                    diagram, as a global cybernetic order, as a metaphor, as a means through which
                    to articulate a demand, as a manifesto, and as one of the ways the relationship
                    between digital transformation and social justice has been explored in recent
                    times (see e.g. (Bratton 2016) (Flanders 2018) (Liu 2020) (Terranova 2014)
                    (Berry 2017) (Bassett et al. 2019)). Stack approaches to exploring technological
                    systems are thus contested and operate in different registers. </p>
                <p>In this paper, we use a stack model to point to the material affordances of
                    extant digital architectures – specifically including those found in archives
                    and doing so with an understanding of the degree to which technological
                    imaginaries operate powerfully at multiple levels and in many materialities. We
                    also do so with cognisance of the ways the stack has also been adopted as a
                    powerful metaphor, both analytic and political (and at times how this has been
                    done by productively confounding the division between the metaphorical and
                    material). We return to this below. The move now is to ask what is lacking in
                    intersectional feminisms’<hi rend="italic">current entanglements with DH.</hi>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>A typical OSI reference module which helps demonstrate stack models and
                        metaphors. Ardika6879, CC BY-SA 4.0, <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0</ref>, via Wikimedia
                        Commons</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Intersectional Orthodoxy? </head>
                <p>Digital Humanities communities claim to wish to be inclusive and equal,
                    particularly in relation to gender, and recently the official aspiration towards
                    gender equality in DH has been pretty uniformly defined in terms of the
                    intersectional. A DH feminism that explicitly claimed it was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> intersectional would likely be looked at askance. How could it be
                    otherwise now? The <q>now</q> we are referring to here relates to the time after
                    the killing of George Floyd, to the second wave of BLM, and to a time where CRT
                    and new forms of thinking around race are defining a lack, articulating a claim,
                    making urgent demands, and breaking into multiple fields, including those that
                    might not wish to entertain them. </p>
                <p>These same developments point to <hi rend="italic">why</hi> intersectionality,
                    and intersectional feminism, both as it is formally <q>adopted</q> by DH<note>
                        (as an aspiration even if one that is not fully or generously accepted).
                    </note> and as it is variously practised by those who are actively pursuing
                    feminist agendas within it, must not be taken for granted. Insofar as DH has
                    adopted intersectional feminism as its new common sense, this has been
                    productive. Writers <q>in</q> DH, particularly feminists, have deployed it to
                    forcefully critique various institutional forms of exclusion, and to question DH
                    certainties around knowledge production, ethical accountability, and the
                    politics of care. This paper therefore seeks to supplement – not displace –
                    feminist thinking in DH. However, it also seeks to unsettle some virtuous
                    certainties about what kind of feminism is needed. These <hi rend="italic">need</hi> to be unsettled partly because intersectional feminism itself is
                    fraught, contested, perhaps in some ways in crisis, and is certainly not an
                    entity reducible to a tick box about <q>inclusion</q>. </p>
                <p>
                    If a commitment to intersectional forms of
                    gender equality is today a common sense in DH, operating in name if not in fact,
                    this itself was fought for. Tara McPherson (2012) examined and critiqued the
                    whiteness of DH as a field of inquiry back in 2012, while the powerful
                    contribution by Deb Verhoeven through her furious talk at the 2015 DH
                    conference, <title rend="quotes">Has Anyone Seen a Woman</title>, forced a
                    long-overdue debate to which this project and paper owe much. More recently,
                    work key to thinking how DH can engage with intersectional feminism includes in
                        <title rend="italic">Intersectionality in Digital Humanities</title> (2019),
                    edited by Barbara Bordalejo and Roopika Risam. Also relevant is Risam’s <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory,
                        Praxis and Pedagogy</title>, advocating for a DH built by <quote rend="inline">sustained communities of practice that foreground critiques of
                        colonialism in scholarship</quote>
                    <ptr target="#risam_2019" loc="16"/>. </p>
                <p>The 2018 <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information; Intersectional Feminism and
                        Digital Humanities</title> anthology edited by Elizabeth Losh and Jacqueline
                    Wernimont also constitutes a foundational engagement; current drives to more
                    fully develop an approach to intersectional feminism in DH owe much to it. This
                    publication often frames discussions of DH around a specific DH community –
                    those that attend or do not attend the AHDO’s international conference –
                    although the authors recognise this is not DH at large. For this reason, it
                    might also constitute a mapping, not only of particular positions and
                    developments in, for instance, work around gender, race or sexuality-based
                    equality, but also of their relations and intersections. All these areas, of
                    course, are covered. However, they are not necessarily explored together. A
                    chapter explicitly considering issues of representation at DH conferences
                    (eponymously titled: <title rend="quotes">Representations of DH
                        conferences</title>) and does so in order to consider percentages of women
                    versus men presenters. The authors rightly denigrate the fact that data is not
                    made available to explore ethnicity. On the other hand, there is no
                    acknowledgment of the lack of data exploring how to think <q>beyond the
                        binary</q>. Other chapters include discussions on queering DH, on lesbian
                    feminist methods in DH and decolonising DH. What is striking is thus not that
                    central issues are set aside (on the contrary). It is rather that the question
                    of <hi rend="italic">how</hi> the various issues explored <hi rend="italic">come
                        together</hi> is left relatively unelaborated, or remains implicit. </p>
                <p>We suggest that running throughout the collection is a tension between two
                    perspectives. The first, a liberal perspective, advocates for more inclusivity,
                    arguing for more diversity in actors, corpus, languages, and methodology. Among
                    the various appeals to action within the volume responding through this
                    perspective are interlocking calls to: recognise and value the varied forms of
                    labour of all those working in the building of DH projects and supporting social
                    justice or diversity work (e.g. Brown; Brundage et al.; Chatelain); examine and
                    correct the dispersal of funding and institutional infrastructures which skews
                    against diversity and justice (e.g. Boyles; Cole et al.; Aiyegbusi); recover,
                    record, and respond in a reflexive manner to artefacts and histories that belong
                    to more diverse groups – including the histories of DH itself (e.g. Earhart;
                    Leon; Eichmann et al.); and (re-) politicise the theoretical and material tools
                    of the field (e.g. Murray; Risam). In many (not all) of these contributions, <hi rend="italic">defining</hi> intersectionality or intersectional feminism is
                    not the priority. Rather, it is taken as something of a <hi rend="italic">given</hi> (to be developed, found, cultivated further), posited as an <hi rend="italic">inherent good</hi>. </p>
                <p>The second perspective within the book aligns with a more complicated demand for
                    systemic, structural re-calibration of practices, processes, technologies,
                    texts, theories, and research infrastructures, through an intersectional
                    feminist lens. Taking on board queer, post-colonial, critical race, materialist,
                    disability, and feminist interventions, informed by decades of critical research
                    into these questions in cognate and linked fields, this might add up to a demand
                    for root and branch renewal of the objects and processes of DH through a
                    reconceptualization of its politics. </p>
                <p>The problem is that this is a <hi rend="italic">muffled</hi> demand, since the
                    two perspectives entertained in the collection are entwined together in ways
                    that, by virtue of the whole, greater inclusivity – of topic, method, tool, or
                    personnel – is proposed as the answer. In the absence of clear definitions, or
                    specific discussion, intersectional feminism thus defaults to a kind of
                        <q>additive</q>
                    <ptr target="#bassett_2022"/> inclusive diversity; each submission adding a
                    missing element that warrants incorporation. Rather than wrestling with the
                    underlying socio-technical stacks into which the discipline folds, or indeed
                    exploring where – at what level, through what material(s), let’s say at what
                    stack level, with what expectation of a stacked relation – intervention might be
                    most effective, the implication is that the structures will inevitably change
                    under the summary weight of the difference added by enough good projects. </p>
                <p>If there is a lack of clarity in how and where DH feminisms might need to operate
                    then, this relates to an imprecision – or perhaps a big tent version – of
                    intersectionality, made to bear more than it should even while it threatens to
                    become increasingly empty. It is for this reason that we believe a consideration
                    of the stakes of intersectionality is required in order to recalibrate or adapt
                    a stack politics for feminisms. Since DH’s somewhat fuzzy adherence to (multiple
                    forms of) intersectional feminism reflects the situation in the broader field,
                    we now turn to this in a move which considers CRT in relation to historical
                    materialist approaches. </p>
                <p>Ashley Bohrer comments that intersectionality has been called <quote rend="inline">hegemonic</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bohrer_2019"/>. Bridget Byrne says it has become a central <quote rend="inline">buzz word</quote> in feminist studies and a <quote rend="inline">signifier for good research</quote> in US and European gender
                    studies <ptr target="#byrne_2015"/>. Jennifer Nash suggests the framework is
                    both hyper-valued and devalued <ptr target="#nash_2019"/>, while Sara Ahmed has
                    cautioned that too often calls for diversity and increased inclusivity are used
                    to absolve institutions, or research fields, of the necessity to actively
                    generate structural change <ptr target="#ahmed_2017"/> . Historical-materialist orientated
                    feminists, who would not have used the term in previous times, comment that its
                        <hi rend="italic">thereness</hi> makes it necessary to do so now as it
                    crosses between public culture and academic thinking. <ptr target="#bilge_2020"/> thus says its success means it has become an <quote rend="inline">empty
                        shell</quote>. Perhaps then, it has become <q>empty signifier</q> or
                    tokenistic of a form of inclusion that is paid lip service to; I <hi rend="italic">heart</hi> intersectionality… </p>
                <p>It is partly because of its success, and its importance, that intersectionality
                    has also become a contested term, and a term whose terms of use are contested.
                    Three positions exploring this development rapidly set out here inform the
                    return to stack feminism, as a form of intersectional feminism useful in DH,
                    which we make in the later stages of the paper. </p>
                <p>There are a number of origin stories for intersectional feminism, but most agree
                    that a form of intersectional feminism was developed by Kimberlé Crenshaw to
                    understand and articulate the ways multiple forms of discrimination and
                    exclusion were experienced by Black women, and other early developers of the
                    term were also women of colour <ptr target="#crenshaw_1989"/>. There are also
                    different reasons given for its emergence. The direct experience of African
                    American women in the US carceral system to which Crenshaw responded is one of
                    them. It is also useful to understand the emergence of intersectional feminism
                    in a different register; as a response to post-feminism which celebrated
                    difference while ignoring differential positioning and multiple discriminations.
                    Post-feminism resonated with Web 2.0 optimism, which for most people was of the
                    cruel kind <ptr target="#berlant_2011"/>, and corresponds to the rise of
                        <q>capitalist realism</q> or that situation in which the possibilities for
                    any form of collective future appear constrained to market options – and the
                    project of self-improvement overtakes collective identifications and solidarity
                        <ptr target="#fisher_2009"/><hi rend="italic">. </hi>By contrast,
                    intersectional politics <hi rend="italic">begins</hi> by recognizing a system.
                    Crenshaw’s point, after all, was the foregrounding of structural, systemic
                    discrimination. </p>
                <p>Intersectionality has expanded and evolved since its beginnings. Key here is
                    Critical Race Theory (CRT), beginning in the US but claiming global purchase,
                    and certainly having international reach. Aswani Sharma’s discussion of the
                    eclipse, at CRT’s hands, of an older form of multiculturalism, informed by
                    British cultural studies, and specifically by Paul Gilroy’s work, explores this
                    from a UK perspective and is useful in that it de-naturalizes intersectionality
                    by historicizing it, exploring it in relation to a particular set of global
                    flows <ptr target="#sharma_2009"/>. Sharma, reading intersectionality as a
                    theorization and a critical/political position currently entangled with CRT,
                    underscores the degree to which it also has travelled, being the outcome of a
                    series of exchanges, the terms of which are complex and interesting to explore. </p>
                <p>Three contemporary positions that we find useful in further thinking through
                    these issues, and in relating them to specifically technological feminisms and
                    to our own situated positions as feminist scholars working between the UK and
                    Ireland – historically colonising and colonised nations – are briefly set out
                    below. </p>
                <p>The first argument comes via Sirma Bilge, who demands to know: <quote rend="inline">What makes intersectionality an empty shell onto which
                        scholars of all stripes can conveniently project their own concerns and feel
                        completely legitimate to do so? What authorizes the easy removal of Black
                        feminists from their theoretical innovation, intersectionality?</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bilge_2020" loc="2298"/></p>
                <p>Bringing afro-pessimism into dialogue with intersectional thinking, Bilge adheres
                    to a theory of permanent extraction, i.e. the persistence of the exploitation of
                    Black people in the slavery era of the US which made of them fungible goods,
                    robbed of their personhood. Rendered object not subject, and therefore outside
                    of <q>history</q> and the agency it may afford, slavery is a state of <quote rend="inline">social death</quote>
                    <ptr target="#patterson_1982"/> that persists today. The crux of Bilge’s
                    argument is that intersectionality, which belonged to Black women, has been
                    expropriated and has become part of a <hi rend="italic">post-racial</hi>
                    formation, aka white liberal feminism. Many critical race theorists,
                    acknowledging some white appropriation, would nonetheless argue that theory
                    can’t be owned in this way – or even territorialized. </p>
                <p>In the UK, Bridget Bryne’s friendly critique of intersectionality-as-given takes
                    two main routes. She (too) acknowledges that mainstreaming has hollowed out
                    intersectionality’s critical edge. She argues that it is becoming a consensus
                    builder not a critical analytic and sees this as an appropriation. On the other
                    hand, she also argues that CRT moves to entirely frame intersectionality around
                    women of colour, reducing its capacity to explore <quote rend="inline">the
                        construction and maintenance of <hi rend="italic">structures</hi> of
                        power</quote> (including whiteness, discrimination, exploitation, exclusion,
                    and how illegitimacy is made and remade) <ptr target="#byrne_2015"/>. It is
                    this, she argues, that produces a flattened form of intersectionality. Byrne
                    melds a CRT-aware account of power with an engagement with a form of cultural
                    materialism, inflected by Hall, whose work was always attuned to Britain’s
                    colonial histories and its legacies – although less attuned to its specific
                    relations with Ireland <ptr target="#beatty_2022"/>.</p>
                <p>Finally, Ashley Bohrer has explored the possibilities of perming out a form of
                    intersectionality with a form of socialist or Marxist feminism. As she points
                    out, it is not only CRT that hosts divisions within itself <ptr target="#bohrer_2019"/>. The 20th century history of Marxist feminism can be
                    viewed as an argument around how to theorize the relationship between
                    oppression, discrimination, and inequality based on anything <hi rend="italic">other</hi> than or, <hi rend="italic">in the determinate analysis only</hi>
                    class. The orthodox Marxist framework, at least as instantiated in political
                    organizations, did recognize multiple oppressions but did not see them as
                    intersecting <hi rend="italic">vectors</hi> – as bearing a capacity for making
                    real change. Revolutionary <hi rend="italic">feminisms,</hi> however, were
                    (are), arguably, always more intersectional in spirit than the traditions
                    (organizations) within which they found a home. The goal of Marxist feminism, a
                    feminism that some of us recognise from our own activism and experience, has
                    been to bring into view the workings of the social whole and the relations of
                    power within it – including those pertaining around gender, sex, and race –
                    seeing these as vectors for change, as well as conditions to be surpassed
                    primarily through class struggle. We would add too, that Marxist traditions have
                    always included questions about how to understand <q>layers</q> and their
                    interaction; base and superstructure, ideological layers and material
                    determinants, medium and media, and how one could apparently slip into the other
                    and back, or offer itself as having the characteristics of one of these whilst
                    being the other. Capitalist realism, after all, sells an idea of a material
                    future as inevitable. </p>
                <p>How do we now read this situation back into our discussion of DH? The
                    intersectional as variously defined by CRT-influenced work, offers one model of
                    a social relation; Marxism offers another. Each approach is capacious, demanding
                    notice be taken of structures as well as signs, and of materials alongside
                    representations. We’ve argued that the kind of feminism-that-intersects that is
                    useful for DH needs to be both systematic and systemic. For us, historical
                    materialism <hi rend="italic">and</hi> many latter-day intersectional feminisms
                    manifest this kind of approach and we aim to entangle them into a <quote rend="inline">theoretical coalition</quote>, as suggested by <ptr target="#bohrer_2019" loc="23"/>, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> articulate them in relation to DH as it is
                    invested in both theory <hi rend="italic">and in practice; </hi>that is, and
                    specifically, in thinking and engaging with questions concerning technology. The
                    need to engage with material operations as well as (materialized and symbolic)
                    ideologies is key to what makes DH distinctive within the broad range of
                    humanities work around the digital. Further, the desire to explore the
                    relationship between these operations, rather than siloing them constitutes one
                    of the defining features of critically engaged digital humanities work. </p>
                <p>The question we now move on to ask is <hi rend="italic">how</hi> these kinds of
                    approaches to DH feminism can be articulated. It is with this in mind that we
                    turn, in the final sections of the paper, first back to a more general
                    consideration of stacks and stack politics, and then on to a consideration of
                    archives. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Back to the stack</head>
                <p>Stacks have already been introduced, but here demand some elaboration. Amongst
                    other things, stacks have been employed as a way of understanding how the
                    internet works as a layered system. The OSI (Open Systems Interconnection)
                    reference model, which deals with the internet and associated networks, and what
                    enables interconnection between them, is one example of this, and has become
                    somewhat canonical. It consists of layers rising from the physical base towards
                    the lighter super-structures, an ordering often understood in terms of
                    etherealization (from the physical depths, up to the application layers enabling
                    human computer interaction). What are also modelled are the principles
                    controlling the intersections between various layers. The system abstracts
                    upwards and is modular, each layer handing off functions to the layer above. In
                    theory at least, the principles of heritance and autonomy between layers means
                    that what happens on one layer is not the business of the next. </p>
                <p>We are interested in how intersectional feminist digital politics may be
                    configured within extant material conditions and possibilities, those that the
                    stack model and its layers might help us understand. The stack models the real
                    and stack politics reflect that. We are also interested in the ideological heft
                    of the model; in particular, in the way it might, in so far as it has become a
                    naturalized way of understanding the affordances of the different technical
                    layers of network systems, imply that there is a <q>proper</q> place for
                    particular kinds of engagement (for instance, those that are viewed <hi rend="italic">as</hi> political rather than technical). Finally, we believe
                    there is potential for the stack to be used metaphorically within a feminist
                    digital politics. In all these ways, we believe stacks can be useful for DH as
                    it seeks to think through the specifically technical elements of a form of
                    (feminist) (intersectional) (historically materialist) politics, whilst also
                    understanding those technical elements as techno-cultural. </p>
                <p>Specifically, we wish to explore the prospects for a depth model of
                    intersectional feminism; one that foregrounds the material possibilities and
                    constraints of operations at particular and multiple levels of the stack and
                    recognizes technical heritance, but that also (i) seeks to refuse conventional
                    assignations that arise when stack layers are mistaken for social structures and
                    conventions (and vice versa), and (ii) that stresses the connective tissues that
                    link operations undertaken at different levels in stacked systems <hi rend="italic">in operation</hi> or <hi rend="italic">in location</hi>, which
                    may exceed the technical and abstraction principles apparently constraining the
                    possible or ordering <q>the system</q>.<note> The question of the inheritances
                        between material and symbolic layers has particular resonance in the context
                        of these islands. The continued dominance of the English language in the
                        Republic, the flow of culture back and forth across the Irish sea, and the
                        material, cultural, and economic infrastructures of the geographic border
                        (made more complex by Brexit), indicate how handing off between
                        nation-states is never simple and certainly not clean. This also applies to
                        the digital infrastructure. What, for instance, does it mean to label one
                        part of Ireland .uk and the other .ie? Is this simply a naming issue at one
                        level of the stack? How does the political context these domains inherit
                        shape relations between the people and things that traverse their logics?
                    </note> Stack violations may constitute a (non-metaphorical) political
                    intervention; feminism has often got things done by refusing to stay in its
                    allotted place. </p>
                <p>We are not the first to get stacked. And not the first to do so with critical
                    intent either. Of note here is Alan Liu’s beautiful DH-focussed demand for a
                    diversity stack <ptr target="#liu_2020"/>. Tiziana Terranova’s digital media
                    studies’ <title rend="italic">Red Stack Attack</title> meanwhile is both
                    analytic (mapping out forces and structures), and constitutes a demand for
                    change (Terranova, 2014). A markedly different approach is that of Benjamin
                    Bratton, who understands the stack to have environmentalised to form an <quote rend="inline">accidental megasphere</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bratton_2016"/>; as Terranova notes, this essentially amounts to
                    cybernetics, or a reading of the earth as a cybernetic system. Others working
                    with stacks include: David Berry who use the stack as a tool to re-model forms
                    of net culture <ptr target="#Berry_2017"/>; Julie Flanders who prompts us to
                        <quote rend="inline">read the entire stack as a cultural text</quote>
                    <ptr target="#flanders_2018"/>; and one of us, via <title rend="italic">Furious:
                        Technological Feminism and Digital Futures</title> where the cloud is
                    preferred to the stack as a figure for generating specifically utopian
                    possibilities <ptr target="#bassett_2019"/>. Recently, Nancy Mauro-Flude and Yoko Akama
                    have argued for a feminist stack that is attentive to the materiality of the
                    sites <quote rend="inline">where the ethical, political and intersectional
                        agonisms manifest 5</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mauro-flude_2022" loc="49"/>, advocating for continuous co-design
                    in the physical substrate of the stack and in its imaginaries. </p>
                <p>So, should we have a feminist stack for DH? And would it be part of Bratton’s
                    totalized cybernetic reading, fuel a mode of utopian antagonism as it does for
                    Terranova, become a tool to model culture as Berry suggests, or work in relation
                    to design as for Mauro-Flude and Akama? Or would it work in tandem with Alan
                    Liu’s more specifically DH thinking? How does (can) intersectional feminist
                    thinking, as we have reconceptualized it, relate to the stack? How can it be
                    operationalised?</p>
                <p>Our <q>stack attack</q> takes inspiration both from Terranova’s political
                    commitment and from Liu’s refusal to countenance the DH status quo, as well as
                    his questioning of where, or on what layer, change needs to come. His work
                    exposes a disjuncture between a laudable DH rhetoric (democratise the global
                    internet) and the possible engine(s) of its effecting. His call is to change the
                    net’s working language at the infra-structural level rather than, or as well as,
                    addressing proximate issues of <q>content</q> or translation<note> We explored
                        the example of English as the <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> of DH in
                        our workshops. </note> which might obtrude more conspicuously. However,
                    where Liu considers specific language layers within the diagram of the whole, we
                    look at archives and archival practices as layered systems, drawing on work
                    around community archiving, and/in relation to structural/infrastructural
                    developments in institutional collections, and in direct relation to issues of
                    memory and politics. </p>
                <p>An archive stack can be understood as a static technical<hi rend="italic">
                        diagram</hi> expressing the various materialities and affordances of what a
                    digital archive is constituted by (e.g. location, hardware, physical networks,
                    protocols, software, content), with these layers being relatively autonomous
                    from the next layer up or down and verticality being defined by trajectory
                    (layers hand off upwards). Intersectional feminisms can work with digital
                    archiving by working <hi rend="italic">with</hi> the kind of layering and
                    handing off the stack foregrounds. But it is also possible to trouble some of
                    the assumptions that this kind of modelling produces about suitable sites for
                    intervention and also about the reality of the system in operation; handing off
                    between layers implies a <hi rend="italic">clean</hi> process, but, in practice,
                    of course, what is handed over – or handled – are people, documents, images,
                    histories, stories, institutions. There are moments when the stakes of the
                    relationship between various layered operations, and their real and assumed
                    relative autonomy from each other, are more visible. Finding these moments, or
                    making them, and addressing the issues they raise begins to constitute a
                    feminist response to archival institutions, institutional archiving, and
                    archiving’s norms as a practice. In the sense that the archival stack enables
                    this kind of exploration, it might also become a pointer to a more generalisable
                    DH politics of feminist intervention based on an ethics of care – across the
                    stacks of the archive and its socio-cultural contexts. Below, this is worked
                    through in relation to various archival projects including those with which IFTe
                    engaged. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Community archives </head>
                <p>Large archives and institutional repositories are facing radical digital
                    disruption, and also changing in response to cultural shifts as well as demands
                    for archival justice coming from multiple directions, including those engaging
                    with intersectional feminisms. Archives and archival practices are in many other
                    cases beginning to become post-custodial, decentralized and, in some cases,
                    democratized. But archivalization still entails the gathering together and
                    linking in of myriad previously, relatively autonomous collections, and
                    contributions from individuals. This is a process that subjects them to archival
                    discipline, often including the archival discipline of large institutions – and
                    includes not only issues of capture, but also relates to the terms of storage,
                    and the politics of re-circulation. In this sense, we are interested in the
                    material realities of the archive as well as its technical and social
                    structures. </p>
                <p>Community archives or community heritage groups and projects, multi-voiced and
                    often co-curated, grapple with issues around ethics, access, and datafication,
                    often challenging, explicitly or through practices, what are taken as
                    self-evident axioms of the Open Access movement and Open Research alike.<note>
                        IFTe’s 2021 series <title rend="quotes">Transforming Archives:
                            Intersectional Feminist Approaches to the Practice and Reading of
                            Archives</title> problematized archives and archiving as having <quote rend="inline">... a troubling history. At their worst, they have
                            involved the reification of their objects, turning living cultural
                            practices into decontextualised objects stripped of their richer
                            purpose. Curation and collection involve decisions of value which have
                            too often imposed dominant meanings and created exclusions from the
                            historical narrative. Archives have been associated with othering and
                            colonisation practices and the abstractions of masculinised thinking.
                            With the dominance of archiving projects within Digital Humanities it is
                            vital to understand how we may build more inclusive archives but also
                            how we may break the models so that they can express different
                            ideals.</quote>
                        [https://web.archive.org/web/20220215160604/http%3A%2F%2Fifte.network%2Fifte-programme-21%2F]
                    </note> Community archives indeed, outrage the kind of precision that giant
                    institutional archives rely on, historically at least. The latter are models of
                    hierarchical order whose ordering both articulates a cultural logic (that of
                    empire, for instance) whilst also obfuscating it (via an appeal to the
                    neutrality of the general or universal), thus employing, well before the
                    computer, the fantasy of automated and impartial systems.<note> Niamh Moore
                        (2020) invokes Star’s thinking on boundary objects to describe the way in
                        which feminist archives, and community archives more broadly, sit between
                            <quote rend="inline">between professional and amateur practices...[and]
                            official institutions and grassroots organisations</quote> (Moore,
                        2020).</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Cork LGBT Archive, founded by Orla Egan, a queer archival activist, and
                    Haringey Vanguard (HV), founded by Veronica McKenzie, film director, curator and
                    archivist, both contributed to debates taken up in the IFTe network project.
                    Both archives, engaging with intersectional gender and sexuality issues, stem
                    from grassroots activism. Both became digital archives following the collection
                    and digitization of context-specific ephemera. A third archive invoked in this
                    discussion is the Archiving Reproductive Health project run by the Digital
                    Repository of Ireland (DRI) which includes work to archive #inHerIrishShoes
                    Facebook posts, and as such is born digital.<note> These Facebook posts, part of
                        the campaign to repeal the 8th amendment in the Irish constitution which
                        prohibited access to abortion services, were/are public facing but were part
                        of an active political campaign.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In all three cases though, what is produced through the archiving process is a
                    change of state; with the HV and the Cork LGBTQ Archive, objects in a basement are moved
                    or a photo album is transposed, but this is also the case for the posts taken
                    <q>out</q> of Facebook, as per the Archiving Reproductive Health project. Through archiving processes, all become different
                    (digital|) objects: contextually accessible, useable, and situationally
                    meaningful, significant, and affective, as they are tagged, recategorized, and
                    move within and between various technological systems. In this process, they
                    both carry and lose their original affective intensity, and their original
                    significance formed by the practices of production and collaboration that made
                    them, and are now re-formed by the operations and contexts of the work done –
                    the institutionalization – that makes them executable in multiple digital
                        contexts.<note> The emotive experience felt by those digitising the physical
                        objects, and creating the digital archive as an act of archival activism,
                        may not be felt or coherent to users of Europeana in this iteration or in
                        any other configuration any other user might encounter them. What is lost
                        and/or gained in these processes is the necessary focus for an
                        intersectional feminist interrogation of the kind we advocate. </note>
                    Ethical considerations arise anew in relation to each new instance of an object
                    which, while stripped of its original context, remains fiercely context
                    dependent, albeit now <hi rend="italic">also</hi> being placed in relation to
                    more fluid and complex contexts (see <ptr target="#webb_2013"/>)<note>
                        <quote rend="inline">Bounded and unbounded to their original
                            conceptualisation, their functionality and meaning dependent upon user
                            and system interactions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#webb_2013"/>. </note>. The vulnerabilities and possibilities
                    of digital LGBTQ+ archives, like those of the Haringay Vanguard project, which
                    concurrently reveal, empower, and riskily expose already marginalized people
                    recorded there <ptr target="#chenier_2015"/> <ptr target="#cowan_2018"/> are a case
                    in point. This is complicated more by legislation like the EU’s <q>right to be
                        forgotten</q> which assumes, in fact, that you were remembered in the first
                    place. </p>
                <p>All of these repositories emerged through geo-political community concerns and
                    community outreach efforts, but within the context of the digital space now
                    transcend their original geographical boundaries. The Cork LGBT Archive is now
                    an Omeka archive, which has been ingested into the DRI and from there, content
                    has been aggregated into Europeana, the EU digital cultural heritage content
                    aggregator. Cork LGBT Archive, or more accurately its data, has crossed multiple
                    infrastructural stacks. It has been transcoded, cross-walked and migrated,
                    enabled by interoperability, across different systems and platforms. Haringey
                    Vanguard now has a digital archive, launched in 2021 alongside a physical
                    exhibition, <title rend="italic">We have always been here</title>, at Bruce
                    Castle, Haringey, London.<note> See <ref target="https://www.hqbh.co.uk/">https://www.hqbh.co.uk/</ref> See also <ref target="https://www.hqbh.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/Haringey_Vanguard_Report_FINAL.pdf">https://www.hqbh.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/Haringey_Vanguard_Report_FINAL.pdf</ref>
                    </note> This process is never one of static ingestion; these archival objects
                    are modified through ongoing computational transactions as these archival
                    objects variously manifest over time and every time the elements of the archival
                    database are assembled into a new interface. </p>
                <p>Each passing through the archive layer, (re)framing at the code layer and
                    decoding at the symbolic layer alters, impacts and reshapes what the archive
                    gives us. The archon was never (only) the archivist – the work of the stack
                    upon/with the objects that it is partly co-constituted through, and partly
                    makes, is never done. Issues of <hi rend="italic">circulation and
                        re-circulation</hi> therefore are central to thinking about archival
                    architectures and emerging digital archival infrastructures and practices; not
                    least, as those that emerge as community (located, of interest, via commitment)
                    archives are ingested into public archives, and also linked in to the larger
                    archival economy (the multiple stacks that are joined via e.g. data harvesting
                    or aggregation, linked open data, as well as IIIF etc.). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Ontology of Objects </head>
                <p>Thinking through stacks invites thinking about these processes in terms of
                    layers. And here Temi Odumoso’s (2020) intervention into thinking about archival
                    justice in relation to images from the former Danish Virgin Islands, held at the
                    Royal Danish Library, is informing. Odumoso’s study articulates the tensions
                    involved in digitizing and making available particular kinds of <q>cultural
                        heritage</q> as acts of (re)representation and repatriation. Their argument
                    centres on the image of a Black child, once a photograph, then a postcard, now
                    digital code, and therefore reproducible, and shareable in new ways. The image
                    may be explored for what it represents; a child crying turned into a curiosity
                    for others, and it may justly be argued that the representation itself outrages
                    an ethics of looking. But at the heart of Odumosu’s argument, there is also a
                    critique of the failure to register, or take account of, the power of
                    circulation itself with relation to archival ethics.<note> See also Tonia
                        Sutherland’s research presentation, <title rend="quotes">Digital Remains:
                            Reflections on Race and the Digital Afterlife</title> (2021), at IFTe’s
                        public lecture in collaboration with the Irish Museum of Modern Art. </note>
                    Odomuso’s critique, and their search for a response to the question, <quote rend="inline">What is the best way to attend to violated bodies and
                        biographies without replicating historical patterns of abuse?</quote>
                    <ptr target="#odumosu_2020" loc="295"/> is essentially a demand to think about
                    how the infrastructure layers of the archive (and/as it connects into the larger
                    stack being constituted through technologies like IIIF), are shaping the terms
                    on which an image is ethically engaged with, and also how the image needs to be
                    understood as an image in relation to its capacity to circulate (its digital
                    ontology).</p>
                <p>It is often assumed that <q>politics</q>, including feminist politics, should
                    confine itself to particular layers of the stack, or to particular kinds of DH
                    activity. Odomuso’s investigation points to the need for stack violation, for a
                    refusal to be contained by – or to contain – an ethical or political practice,
                    which might be a practice of general refusal, or take-down, or restriction, or
                    opening, or a call for an intersectional feminist politics to the
                        <q>appropriate</q> place. This is not essentially an argument about
                    distinctions between what is legal and what is ethical, but is rather about at
                    what intersections intersectional feminism <hi rend="italic">needs</hi> to
                    operate at to operate an ethics and politics of care. Thus, while it is clear
                    that in a technical sense the operations determining and conditioning
                    circulation of the images are handed off between layers, the image itself
                    (properly understood) and the grounds for intervention – by feminists for
                    instance – cross those layers, and refuse those divisions. Ethics is all the way
                    up and all the way down. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Archival Refusal? </head>
                <p>Some of the issues Odomuso explores arose in different contexts, for some of us
                    closer to home, in relation to campaigns in Ireland around abortion rights<note>
                        Here we are drawing in part on Aileen O’Caroll’s discussion with IFTe (April
                        2021)</note>. <title rend="italic">Archiving the 8th</title> sets out to
                        <quote rend="inline">provide long-term preservation and access to the many
                        at-risk archives generated by grassroots women’s reproductive health
                        movements during the [Repeal the 8th] campaign</quote> <ptr target="#arh_n.d."/>.
                    However, the #inHerIrishShoes Facebook posts, already referenced and central to
                    the campaign to repeal the 8th Amendment that the archiving project responds to,
                    should be viewed in relation to the <hi rend="italic">on-going </hi>history of
                    occlusion and denial around the systemic and systematic oppressions of the
                    Magdalene Laundries. Specifically, the histories of women’s experience in
                    so-called <q>Mother and Baby</q> homes in Ireland have been swept under the
                    proverbial archival carpet as the Irish state has sealed the records and
                    findings of the investigating commission.<note> See Justice for Magdalene
                        Research <ref target="http://jfmresearch.com/">http://jfmresearch.com/</ref>, see also <ref target="https://www.oireachtas.ie/en/bills/bill/2020/38/">https://www.oireachtas.ie/en/bills/bill/2020/38/</ref>) </note>
                </p>
                <p>Within the context of Irish reproductive rights and women’s health, archival
                    refusal may appeal counter to contemporary political and societal sentiment,
                    particularly amongst feminists who demand openness. However, it does respond to
                    women’s own activities to inscribe – and at times conceal – a history when
                    formal histories excise it; <quote rend="block">When our history isn’t important
                        enough for men to write it down in ink, we take to needle and thread, sewing
                        ourselves into the quilts for our daughters and sons, telling stories in
                        embroidery. When our histories are not safe to voice aloud, we ensure they
                        are folded in the hems of skirts, sharp daggers tucked in hats. We will not
                        go silently. We write our own history into legislation, into the Dáil, in
                        poems and books, in music and art. Our stories keep us alive. 
                        [Erin Darcy. (11 November 2021). <title rend="italic">In Her Shoes – Women Of The Eighth.</title> Available at <ref target="https://www.facebook.com/InHerIrishShoes">https://www.facebook.com/InHerIrishShoes</ref>. Accessed 13 October 2025]</quote></p>

                <p>Archival ingestion is not simply a matter of making a history visible, but of
                    rendering into a form amenable to <hi rend="italic">computational</hi>
                    operations – circulation, recombination, distant reading, meta-dating,
                    exploration via new tools, comparison at large scales. Among the questions
                    arising: The stories contained in the data set are stories of trauma, re-lived
                    for a national campaign now preserved for historical futures. But what happens
                    when we create a dataset of trauma that can be read computationally? When we
                    make computational assumptions and analysis? What happens when we distance read
                    instead of close read? What connections do we lose when we connect data sets?
                    What do we join which had not been thought joinable? In the future, could the
                    anonymous participants (speaking and concealing) be identified through more
                    sophisticated computational author recognition analysis or techniques?
                    Datafication of the self and data fusion are creating unique data profiles
                    linked through systems without our knowledge. The production of these archives,
                    in other words, involves various and multiple forms of <hi rend="italic">handing
                        off</hi> between the original object and its archiving, and between the
                    layers of the archival stack. <hi rend="italic">With each transition, they
                        change ontology.</hi> They are no longer objects in a basement, a photo in
                    an album, a post on a social media page. </p>
                <p>Many of these issues are also pertinent in relation to the Cork LGBT archive, and
                    also to the Haringey Vanguard collection; where various forms of Black queer
                    socialist activism, based around 70s–90s organized left political milieus are
                    documented, and where materials designed for circulation in specific
                    communities, contextualized by local and temporally specific struggles, are
                    exposed to a broader view and to audiences never intended to be addressed. There
                    is a need to re-frame these issues not only in relation to the politics of the
                    visible (making visible, the terms of the visible, the gaze, objectification,
                    for instance), but also in terms of access, and circulation, where this is
                    explored in more infra-structural or multi-layered ways. </p>
                <p>Across the digital archiving landscape, the Open Access movement and FAIR
                    principles for data management have created findable, accessible, interoperable,
                    and reusable data sets and collections. The kinds of (intersectional feminist)
                    ethics of care we are beginning to point to, drawing on what these archivists
                    have found and on work by scholars including <ptr target="#odumosu_2020"/>, is
                    in tension with this; not against it, but demanding more nuanced thinking,
                    rather than a technical or absolute solution. Adopting and considering the
                    (FAIR) CARE Principles for Indigenous Data Governance (Collective Benefit,
                    Authority to Control, Responsibility and Ethics) to data management, data
                    access, and dissemination is one response to this tension. Archival refusal as a
                    political tool is bound up with what haunts the stacks as well as with the data
                    that might be collected there; one way to think this through is to explore the
                    resonances between data bodies and real selves, another is to think about the
                    collective inheritance of trauma. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Stack politics? </head>
                <p>To think about an intersectional feminist stack politics, as this relates to
                    archival activities and more generally, is thus to refuse the temptation to
                    enfold feminist activities around archival issues into sets of demands that can
                    be simply and comfortably resolved, but that do not address the complexity of
                    the technical inheritances of the systems we work within, nor the ways in which
                    they are also non-neutral. It is also to insist on defining the object in
                    relation to the circulation that its digital form allows. At the interface
                    layers, the social structures that condition meaning are more clearly
                    discernible as legacies carried into code than those further down the stack.
                    These might appear to be evident only on that layer. Nevertheless, they are
                    connected through the stack, via the technical process(es) of handing off,
                    whereby infrastructure conditions layers above it. And, they are connected as
                    well as in more indirect and lateral ways, through network architectures on a
                    global scale having been forged, in their incompleteness, their unevenness, in
                    their gateways and closures, in relation to cultural and social histories and
                    conflicts, and struggles around justice around gender, race, class and sexuality
                    and its structural withholding. </p>
                <p>An intersectional feminist approach to archiving, based on the demand for care,
                    allows for both critique, intervention and mobilisation, but all of these
                    require a holistic view of the materials and processes entailed in making and
                    using archives, their practical and symbolic affordances. It must understand the
                    impact of the inheritances up and down the stack in order to fully appreciate
                    the complexity of any holding or object – understood as an archival object. It
                    must also understand these dynamics as producing a particular, situated material
                    reality but one that can be analysed as discrete moments; it retains the
                    specificity of discriminations manifesting in a particular layer while insisting
                    that these layers are imbricated together. Finally, it must understand the power
                    and force of arguments that claim large parts of the social reality that is
                    computational culture have become inevitable, unchangeable, and are not amenable
                    to feminist demands. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion </head>
                <p>Thinking about intersectional feminism and DH through stacks isn’t a panacea.
                    There are issues with the formalism of the model; the temptation is real to
                    simply take the stack (model) for the reality of complex and layered
                    techno-social systems that make up the digital archive archipelago emerging as
                    digitalisation processes intensify; and this is not a matter of mixing metaphor
                    with material, but rather assuming that the model of a system becomes its
                    reality. However, we find it helpful to use it to think through or hold together
                    a set of considerations of the necessarily intersectional modes of feminism at
                    play in contemporary global society with all its multiple forms of
                    discrimination. </p>
                <p>Our exploration of the stack concept has led us to explore a series of questions
                    about <hi rend="italic">where</hi> DH feminism should operate – at which levels,
                    and in what ways. Informed by the IFTe Network, we have expanded upon our stack
                    orientation in our subsequent project, <title rend="italic">Full Stack Feminism
                        in Digital Humanities</title>.<note>
                        <title rend="italic">Full Stack Feminism in Digital Humanities</title>
                        (2021-24) was funded by UK Research and Innovation-Arts and Humanities
                        Research Council and the Irish Research Council under the <title rend="quotes">UK-Ireland Collaboration in the Digital Humanities
                            Research Grants Call</title> (grant numbers AH/W001667/1 and
                        IRC/W001667/1).</note> This project maintains a commitment to an engagement
                    with the stacked reality of the networked systems we engage with, but it also
                    uses the stack as a conceptual metaphor, delineating three distinct stacks: data
                    and archives; infrastructure, tools, and code; access, experience, and
                    integration. This new engagement with stacks, isn’t undertaken with the aim of
                    finding a technological solution, or an infra-structural <q>answer</q> to
                    algorithmic discriminations. Our suggestion is that attending to the kinds of
                    relations stack models model – and also asking about the status of the stack –
                    model or metaphor, closed or open, for instance – can be productive. Using the
                    stack as a framework for structuring feminist thinking and practices, we can
                    challenge assumptions that certain questions are irrelevant, or of marginal
                    importance, when they are posed in relation to particular material layers or
                    operations of digital systems. For example, the stacks outlined in Full Stack
                    Feminism provide a structured framework for contemplating the connections
                    between different layers, which are often iterative, accumulative, and
                    cumulative. </p>
                <p>By employing the stack analogy, whether through the FSF framework or earlier
                    iterations, we provoke critical reflection on where, within the stack or layer,
                    a sense of intersectional politics in DH truly belongs. In this context,
                    questions about the place of intersectional feminisms arise, and various
                    perspectives have offered diverse suggestions on how to address this issue.
                    Exploring these propositions, in the context of archives and on issues arising
                    around archival practice, we wanted to both illuminate the material conditions
                    we found and also use the example to challenge some assumptions about stack
                    hierarchy. Feminisms need to operate to grapple with the questions DH raises
                    both for itself and as – or in so far as – it wishes to engage with digital
                    cultures in a critical and questioning way that seeks justice. <hi rend="italic">All that seems solid may melt…</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Funding Acknowledgement</head>
                <p>This research, part of The IFTe Network (Intersections; Feminism, Technology and Digital Humanities, 2020-21) was jointly funded by UK Research and Innovation – Arts and Humanities Research Council (UKRI-AHRC) and the Irish Research Council (IRC) under the <title rend="quotes">UK-Ireland Collaboration in the Digital Humanities Networking Call</title> (AH/V00199X/1 and IRC/V00199X/1).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ahmed_2017" label="Ahmed 2017">Ahmed, S. (2017) <title rend="italic">Living a Feminist Life</title>. Durham and London: Duke University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arh_n.d." label="Archiving Reproductive Health n.d.">Archiving Reproductive Health. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Digital Preservation of Reproductive Health Resources: Archiving the 8th</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://dri.ie/archiving-reproductive-health/">https://dri.ie/archiving-reproductive-health/</ref> </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arondekar_2005" label="Arondekar 2005">Arondekar, A. (2005) <title rend="quotes">Without a trace: Sexuality and the colonial archive,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of the History of Sexuality, </title>14(1/2), pp.
                    10–27. Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/3704707">https://www.jstor.org/stable/3704707</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bassett_2022" label="Bassett 2022">Bassett, C. (2022) <title rend="quotes">The performative function of hope: An archaeology of
                        LambdaMOO</title> in James Gabrillo and Nathaniel Zetter’s (eds.) <title rend="italic">Articulating Media: Genealogy, Interface, Situation</title>,
                    pp. 96–111. Open Humanities Press, London. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bassett_2019" label="Bassett et al. 2019">Bassett, C., et al. (2019)
                        <title rend="italic">Furious: Technological Feminism and Digital
                        Futures</title>. Pluto Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beatty_2022" label="Beatty 2022">Beatty, A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Stuart Hall and the absent Irish</title>, <title rend="italic">Radical History Review</title>, 143, pp. 205–211. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-9566230">https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-9566230</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berlant_2011" label="Berlant 2011">Berlant, L. (2011) <title rend="italic">Cruel Optimism. </title>Durham and London: Duke University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Berry_2017" label="Berry 2017">Berry, D.M. (2017) <title rend="quotes">The post-archival constellation: The archive under the technical conditions
                        of computational media</title> in Ina Bloom, Trond Lundemo, and Eivind
                    Rossaak’s (eds.) <title rend="italic">Memory Archives in Motion: Archives,
                        Technology and the Social</title>, pp. 103–125. Amsterdam: Amsterdam
                    University Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt1jd94f0.8">https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt1jd94f0.8</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bilge_2020" label="Bilge 2020">Bilge, S. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The fungibility of intersectionality: an Afropessimist reading.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title> 43(13), pp. 2298–2326.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2020.1740289">https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2020.1740289</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bohrer_2019" label="Bohrer 2019">Bohrer, A.J. (2019) <title rend="italic"> Intersectionality and Marxism: Race, Gender, Class and
                        Sexuality Under Contemporary Capitalism</title>. Bielefeld:
                    transcript.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bordalejo_2019" label="Bordalejo and Risam 2019">Bordalejo, B. and
                    Risam, R. (eds.) (2019) <title rend="italic">Intersectionality in Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Leeds: ARC Humanities Press. Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctvs32szz">https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctvs32szz</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bratton_2016" label="Bratton 2016">Bratton, B.H. (2016) <title rend="italic">The Stack: On Software and Sovereignty</title>. Cambridge, Ma:
                    MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="byrne_2015" label="Byrne 2015">Byrne, B. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Rethinking intersectionality and whiteness at the border of
                        citizenship</title>, <title rend="italic">Sociological Research
                        Online,</title> 20(3), pp. 178–189. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5153%2Fsro.3790">https://doi.org/10.5153/sro.3790</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chenier_2015" label="Chenier 2015">Chenier, E. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Privacy anxieties: Ethics versus activism in archiving Lesbian
                        Oral History Online</title>, <title rend="italic">Radical History
                        Review</title>, 122, pp. 129–141. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-2849576">https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-2849576</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cowan_2018" label="Cowan and Rault 2018">Cowan, T.L. and Rault, J.
                    (2018) <title rend="quotes">Onlining queer acts: Digital research ethics and
                        caring for risky archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Women &amp;
                        Performance: a journal of feminist theory</title>, 28(2), pp. 121–142. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0740770X.2018.1473985">https://doi.org/10.1080/0740770X.2018.1473985</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crenshaw_1989" label="Crenshaw 1989">Crenshaw, K. (1989) <title rend="quotes">Demarginalizing the intersection of race and sex: A Black
                        feminist critique of antidiscrimination doctrine, feminist theory, and
                        antiracist politics</title>, <title rend="italic">University of Chicago
                        Legal Forum</title>, 140, pp. 139–167. Available at: <ref target="https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/uclf/vol1989/iss1/8">https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/uclf/vol1989/iss1/8</ref>
                </bibl>
               
                <bibl xml:id="fisher_2009" label="Fisher 2009">Fisher, M. (2009) <title rend="italic">Capitalist Realism: Is There No Alternative?
                    </title>Winchester: Zero Books</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders_2018" label="Flanders 2018">Flanders, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Building otherwise</title>, in Elizabeth Losh and Jacqueline
                    Wernimont’s (eds.) <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional
                        Feminism and the Digital Humanities</title>, pp. 289–304. Minneapolis:
                    University of Minnesota Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctv9hj9r9.19">https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctv9hj9r9.19</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu_2020" label="Liu 2020">Liu, A. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Toward
                        a diversity stack: Digital Humanities and diversity as technical
                        problem</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 135(1), pp. 130–151.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1632/pmla.2020.135.1.130">https://doi.org/10.1632/pmla.2020.135.1.130</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="losh_2018" label="Losh and Wernimont 2018">Losh, E. and Wernimont, J.
                    (eds.) (2018) <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional
                        Feminism and Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: University of
                    Minnesota Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctv9hj9r9">https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctv9hj9r9</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson_2012" label="McPherson 2012" sortKey="Mcpherson">McPherson,
                    T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Why are the digital humanities so white? Or,
                        thinking the histories of race and computation</title>, in Matthew K. Gold’s
                    (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities</title>, pp. 139–160.
                    Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctttv8hq.12">https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctttv8hq.12</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcrobbie_2009" label="McRobbie 2009" sortKey="Mcrobbie">McRobbie, A.
                    (2009) <title rend="italic">The Aftermath of Feminism: Gender, Culture and
                        Social Change</title>. London: Sage.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moore_2020" label="Moore 2020">Moore, N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">‘Wibbly-wobbly timey-wimey’ LGBT histories: Community archives as boundary
                        objects</title>, in Simon Popple, Andrew Prescott, and Daniel Mutibwa’s
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">Communities, Archives and New Collaborative
                        Practices</title>, pp. 195–206. Bristol University Policy Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.46692/9781447341932.016">https://doi.org/10.46692/9781447341932.016</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mauro-flude_2022" label="Mauro-Flude and Yoko 2022">Mauro-Flude, N.
                    and Yoko A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">A feminist server stack: Co-designing
                        feminist web servers to reimagine internet futures</title>, <title rend="italic">CoDesign</title>, 18(1), pp. 48–62. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2021.2021243">https://doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2021.2021243</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nash_2019" label="Nash 2019">Nash, J.C. 2019. <title rend="italic">Black Feminism Reimagined: After Intersectionality</title>. Durham and
                    London: Duke University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odumosu_2020" label="Odumosu 2020">Odumosu, T. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The crying child. On colonial archives, digitization, and
                        ethics of care in the cultural commons</title>, In <title rend="italic">Current Anthropology</title>, 61(S22), pp. 289–302. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1086/710062">https://doi.org/10.1086/710062</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="patterson_1982" label="Patterson 1982">Patterson, O. (1982) <title rend="italic">Slavery and Social Death</title>. Cambridge, Ma: Harvard
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_2019" label="Risam 2019">Risam, R. (2019) <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and
                        Pedagogy</title>. Illinois: Northwestern University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sandberg_2013" label="Sandberg 2013">Sandberg, S. (2013)<title rend="italic"> Lean In: Women, Work and the Will to Lead</title>. Knopf
                    Doubleday.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sharma_2009" label="Sharma 2009">Sharma, A. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Postcolonial racism: White paranoia and the terrors of
                        multiculturalism</title>, in Graham Huggan and Ian Law’s (eds.) <title rend="italic">Racism, Postcolonialism Europe</title>, pp. 119–130.
                    Liverpool: Liverpool University Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5949/liverpool/9781846312199.003.0008">https://doi.org/10.5949/liverpool/9781846312199.003.0008</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terranova_2014" label="Terranova 2014">Terranova, T. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Red stack attack: Algorithms, capital and the automation of
                        the common</title>, <title rend="italic">Report from the Algorithms and
                        Capital workshop</title>, Goldsmiths’ College, London, January. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://www.academia.edu/8430149/Red_Stack_Attack_Algorithms_Capital_and_the_Automation_of_the_Common">https://www.academia.edu/8430149/Red_Stack_Attack_Algorithms_Capital_and_the_Automation_of_the_Common</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="verhoeven_2015" label="Verhoeven_2015">Verhoeven, D. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Has anyone seen a woman?</title>, paper presented at <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities conference, </title>Sydney. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://speakola.com/ideas/deb-verhoeven-has-anyone-seen-a-woman-2015">https://speakola.com/ideas/deb-verhoeven-has-anyone-seen-a-woman-2015</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webb_2013" label="Webb et al. 2013">Webb, S., et al. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The born digital graduate: Multiple representations of and
                        within digital humanities PhD theses</title>, <title rend="italic">Internet
                        Research, Theory, and Practice: Perspectives From Ireland</title>, pp.
                    381–404. Available at: <ref target="https://eric.ed.gov/?q=PhD+AND+thesis&amp;pg=5&amp;id=ED576206">https://eric.ed.gov/?q=PhD+AND+thesis&amp;pg=5&amp;id=ED576206</ref>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>