<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding for Endangered Tibetan Texts</title>
            <author>Linda E. Patrik</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Linda E. <dhq:family>Patrik</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Department of Philosophy, Union College</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>patrikl@union.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Linda E. Patrik, Professor of Philosophy at Union College, works on bridges
                     between Asian philosophy and western philosophy, particularly with regard to
                     ethical issues and philosophical issues concerning the nature of consciousness.
                     She has studied and taught with Tibetan Buddhist philosophers at the Nitartha
                     Institute, and she is part of a Tibetan text preservation effort based at
                     Nitartha International's Document Input Center in Kathmandu.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000004</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-04-03">3 April 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2007-01-18" who="Julia Flanders">Entered changes per author response to
            questions</change>
         <change when="2007-01-17" who="Julia Flanders">Copyedited document</change>
         <change when="2007-01-17" who="Julia Flanders">Encoded document</change>
         <change when="2007-03-07" who="John Walsh">Changed acknowledgements from paragraphs to
            list, Added pound signs to internal id references, eg. target="fig1" to
            target="#fig1"</change>
         <change when="2007-03-17" who="John Walsh">Changed link to audio file from ref to
            xref</change>
         <change when="2007-03-25" who="Julia Flanders">Gave italic titles explicit rend value;
            fixed spacing and punctuation errors; adjusted spacing in the CDATA section to improve
            formatting; added cit encoding.</change>
         <change when="2007-03-30" who="Julia Flanders">Final fixes based on author review</change>
         <change when="2008-06-16" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added publicationStmt,
            added # to target attribute of ref (internal references) and ptr, changed xref to ref
            and changed file attribute of graphic element to url attribute for validation with new
            schema</change>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>For over a thousand years, Tibet has preserved and translated ancient Buddhist Sutras
               from India, keeping the tradition of Buddhist philosophy and meditation alive long
               after it died out in India by the 12th Century. Recent efforts to digitize materials
               from this textual tradition offer opportunities to broaden the circulation of rare
               materials to the exiled Tibetan scholarly community, but also suggest conceptual
               challenges arising from the complexity of the texts and their inherently multimodal
               character. This paper describes the scholarly and meditative traditions from which
               these texts come, and discusses possible approaches to their digitization. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Describes the scholarly and meditative traditions from which Buddhist Sutras from
               India come, and discusses possible approaches to their digitization.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>For over a thousand years, Tibet has preserved and translated ancient Buddhist Sutras
            from India, keeping the tradition of Buddhist philosophy and meditation alive long after
            it died out in India by the 12th Century. The accuracy of the Tibetan translations of
            Sanskrit Buddhist texts meant that modern scholars could establish the oldest versions
            of Buddhist theories with some reliability. As the 19th Century scholar F. Max Müller
            noted, <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#muller1894">The Tibetan version [of The Buddha-karita of
                  Asvaghosha] appears to be much closer to the original Sanskrit than the Chinese;
                  in fact from its verbal accuracy we can often reproduce the exact words of the
                  original, since certain Sanskrit words are always represented by the same Tibetan
                  equivalents, as for instance the prepositions prefixed to verbal roots. </quote>
               <ptr target="#muller1894" loc="vii"/>
            </cit> Known not only for their care in translation but also for their understanding of
            Buddhism, Tibet’s monastic scholars added commentaries to the original Indian root
            texts, and they established hundreds of libraries and universities where the texts could
            be studied. Through the ages, Tibet’s ancient texts have received careful handling and
            storage as sacred texts; they were printed by hand from wood blocks, wrapped in silk
            covers, and stored on shelves behind the main altars of the shrine rooms in monasteries
            and temples. Representing one of the Three Jewels of Buddhism — the Dharma — the texts
            instruct Buddhists on how to achieve enlightenment.</p>
         <p>But canonical texts represent only one piece of what has always been a multimedia
            enactment of the key meanings of Vajrayana Buddhism, the particular form of Buddhism
            that Tibet inherited from India. Vajrayana Buddhism (also known as Tantra) emphasizes
            intensive meditation, but its meditation methods incorporate complex visual imagery,
            bodily movements, the sounds of drums and horns, as well as the chanting of the texts
            within the overall container of quiet meditation practice. Instructions on these
            visualizations, bodily gestures and chanting practices have been passed down through
            oral lineages, teacher to student, codified by sacred rituals in which monastics joined
            together in learning and standardizing these practices. </p>
         <p>Today the Tibetan textual tradition faces extinction unless serious efforts are made to
            preserve it and the Vajrayana practices it supports. In the years following the Chinese
            invasion of Tibet in the 1950s, Tibetan scholars struggled to preserve and circulate the
            classical texts of their ancient Buddhist heritage. Many books were lost during the
            1960s and 70s when the Chinese launched the Cultural Revolution on Tibetan soil,
            destroying the libraries, temples, monasteries and universities in Tibet that had kept
            the books safe. Some important, time-honored texts elucidating Tibet’s distinctive
            Vajrayana meditation methods, liturgies and philosophical investigations may never be
            found again, although the search by Tibetans still continues today for these famous
            commentaries and instruction manuals. </p>
         <p>The Tibetan scholars who fled into India first attempted to preserve the texts they
            carried with them by printing the texts without delay. But at that time, the paper
            available in India was of such poor quality (it was non-acid-free paper or rice paper)
            that the print bled through from both sides, making the texts illegible <ptr
               target="#marvet2006"/>. Many classical Tibetan texts were never reprinted at all but
            were left in their original hand-printed, woodblock form (called <q>pecha</q> texts; see
               <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The lack of facilities and poor economic
            conditions for Tibetan refugees as they scattered abroad introduced added risks for the
            storage of their paper texts. Simply transcribing the rescued texts and protecting them
            in archives were stopgap measures. With Tibetan refugees living in India, Europe, North
            America, South America, and other parts of Asia, it was impossible to establish
            centrally located archives where all Tibetans could easily study the texts and learn the
            highly detailed Vajrayana meditation methods described in the texts. When Western
            scholars and meditators became interested in learning about Tibetan Buddhism, they also
            found it difficult to locate or understand the old Tibetan texts mentioned in more
            recent commentaries. Not only were indigenous Tibetan scholars unable to verify which
            ancient texts had actually been preserved or where the texts had been stored, but the
            iconography and complex symbolism associated with Vajrayana texts were not explained in
            the texts themselves. </p>
         <figure xml:id="figure01">
            <head>Tibetan <q>pecha</q> texts</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>An image of three Tibetan texts</figDesc>

         </figure>
         <p> By the late 1980s Tibetan scholars recognized the possibilities of digital formats for
            preserving their texts and for circulating the texts amongst the far-flung members of
            the Tibetan community <ptr target="#chilton2006"/>. Digitized texts could be made
            accessible to Tibetan and western scholars around the world through the Internet, and
            digital formats also made cataloguing the texts and searching for specific titles
            easier, so that a more accurate assessment could be made of which texts had survived and
            which texts were still missing. Several digitizing projects began in India, Nepal,
            Europe and North America. </p>
         <p> Today, after over a decade of work, there are digital archives of thousands of Tibetan
               books.<note>Digitizing projects include the Nitartha International Document Input
               Center (<ref target="http://www.nitartha.org/collections.html"
                  >http://www.nitartha.org/collections.html</ref>); the Asian Classics Input Project
               (ACIP) (<ref target="http://www.asianclassics.org"
               >http://www.asianclassics.org</ref>); University of Virginia's Tibetan and Himalayan
               Digital Library (<ref target="http://www.thdl.org/index.html"
                  >http://www.thdl.org/index.html</ref>); the Tibetan Buddhist Resource Center (<ref
                  target="http://www.tbrc.org">http://www.tbrc.org</ref>); the Otani Tibetan
               Project, Otani University, Kyoto Japan; the Drukpa Kagyu Heritage Project (<ref
                  target="http://tibet.dk/dkhp/page2.htm">http://tibet.dk/dkhp/page2.htm</ref>); the
               Electronic Catalogues of the Tibetan and Mongolian Collections of Buryatia Project,
               Institute of Mongolian, Tibetan and Buddhist Studies of the Siberian Branch of the
               Russian Academy of Sciences, Ulan Ude, Buryatia; and the Research Institute for Inner
               Asian Studies (<ref
                  target="http://www.indiana.edu/~rifias/rifias_and_inner_asian_studies.htm"
                  >http://www.indiana.edu/~rifias/RIFIAS_and_Inner_Asian_Studies.htm</ref>)</note>
            For example, one of the Tibetan scholars committed to digitizing the Tibetan canon, the
            Dzogchen Ponlop Rinpoche, established the Nitartha International Document Input Center
            in Kathmandu, Nepal, with a team of Tibetan monks, Tibetan refugees born in diaspora,
            and western computer specialists. At the Input Center, indigenous Tibetan scholars
            represent classical Tibetan texts in digital formats that would be most useful for
            Tibetan scholars in exile and for Tibetan translators. In addition to its digitization
            of texts, Nitartha International has developed a Tibetan font software, several
            informative websites on Tibetan Buddhism, and modern educational materials linked to
            classical texts, such as CDs with interactive modules that outline the logic of
            philosophical arguments, define basic concepts used in Buddhist philosophy, and
            represent key points through visual images. </p>
         <p> Recently, some indigenous Tibetan scholars have also begun to learn TEI encoding for
            their digitized texts. The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) is an XML language designed
            for representing literary and historical texts. Maintained by an international
            consortium of major universities, the TEI publishes detailed guidelines and
            documentation of this language, maintains a listserv for questions, trouble-shooting and
            general discussion amongst TEI users, and holds a yearly meeting for the hundreds of TEI
            projects and encoders scattered around the world. What Tibetan scholars see in TEI is
            not only a markup language, but a flexible text publishing method for digital texts, a
            cataloguing schema for archiving the texts, and an application that will make it easier
            to conduct analytical searches and link the texts to their translations. One obstacle to
            using TEI (or any XML language) for the Tibetan canon is that Unicode for the Tibetan
            language only became available recently, in partial form. Even though texts can now be
            encoded in Unicode, they cannot be printed in the Tibetan Unicode script. </p>
         <p>This example of Tibetan scholars experimenting with TEI for their ancient texts shows
            the promise of TEI for multicultural texts. Multiculturalism as a theoretical approach
            aims to respect the autonomy and value of other cultures. Recently, the TEI consortium
            has initiated a project to translate its Guidelines into as many languages as possible
               <ptr target="#rahtz2005"/>. Without denying the very concrete economic and political
            forces that create the Digital Divide, the TEI consortium intends to support indigenous
            scholars as they protect and sustain their own textual traditions. In this way the Text
            Encoding Initiative is expanding its work beyond its original North American and
            European borders, becoming a global digital technology that is supportive of
            multicultural textual traditions. The TEI consortium has welcomed Tibetan forays into
            what started as a western scholarly undertaking, because TEI members understand that
            text preservation by multicultural, and especially minority, populations is important.
            Providing indigenous scholars and teachers with tools for keeping their textual
            traditions alive helps secure the future for all the literatures of the world. </p>
         <p> Not only is TEI an important strategy for preserving rare texts, but the TEI Guidelines
            offer a standard set of schemas and documentation that is widely used in the
            international scholarly community. By representing their texts through this scholarly
            framework, indigenous Tibetan scholars can introduce their textual tradition to the
            wider scholarly community. Over the centuries, Tibetan scholars have developed a
            painstaking system for marking up the internal organization of their texts — a system
            which delineates between several layers of scholastic commentaries on the original
            Sanskrit root text. Its inherent complexity makes the Tibetan canon a natural for TEI
            encoding. The TEI guidelines have been designed with complex historical texts in mind —
            the texts expected to endure through the ages. The guidelines also offer specific ways
            to represent the complicated scholarly features of historical texts. This precision of
            TEI encoding is a good match for the complexity of Tibet’s commentarial tradition.
            Tibetan commentaries form a nesting structure, such that later commentaries include and
            surround earlier commentaries, which themselves include and surround the original Indian
               Sutra.<note>It is not uncommon for a second-level Tibetan commentary — that is, a
               Tibetan commentary on an earlier commentary on an Indian Sanskrit root text — to have
               sections with complicated numbering (not to mention their incredibly long titles).
               For example, the 8th Karmapa Mikyö Dorje's commentary on Chandrakirti's commentary on
               Nagarjuna's root text includes a famous passage that explains the distinction between
               the two truths, relative truth and ultimate truth. This passage, <q>The extensive explanation of the individual natures of the two
                  truths</q>, is numbered 231.112.112.221.212.211.2. The title of the commentary
               by the 8th Karmapa Mikyö Dorje is <title rend="italic">The Chariot of the Dakpo Kagyü
                  Siddhas: The Quintessential Oral Instructions of the Glorious Düsum Khyenpa
                  Explaining Chandrakirti's <title rend="quotes">Entrance to the Middle Way</title>
               </title>. (Translated by Elizabeth Callahan and included in the third-level
               commentary by the Dzogchen Ponlop Rinpoche, which is entitled <title rend="italic"
                  >Commentary on <title rend="quotes">The Chariot of the Dakpo Kagyü Siddhas: The
                     Sixth Mind Generation: The Manifest</title>
               </title>, published by the Nitartha Institute, 1999.)</note> The Tibetan commentaries
            proceed paragraph by paragraph, verse by verse, or sometimes even line by line in
            explicating the meaning of the earlier text(s). All of these complicated internal
            divisions of a text can be captured by TEI encoding. TEI encoding can also represent
            linkages between texts, for example between the original Tibetan text and translations
            of the text in western languages. </p>
         <p>As an example, consider the following passage from a Tibetan commentary which concerns
            the differences between two philosophical schools, the Consequentialists and the
            Autonomists. The indented verses are from a root text, Nagarjuna’s Fundamental Verses on
            Centrism. Generally, Tibetan commentaries such as the one below quote lines from the
            earlier root text and then explain the meaning of that quoted passage in detail or
            explore the philosophical debates that have arisen in response to that passage. </p>
         <dhq:example>
            <head>Passage from English translation of The Treasury of Knowledge </head>
            <quote rend="block" source="#thaye2002">
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <head>Chapter on Madhyamaka, by Jamgön Kongtrul Lodrö Thaye, translated by Karl
                        Brunnhölzl (Nitartha Institute, 2002).</head>
                     <div>
                        <head>6.2.1.2.1.2.3.1.1.1. The system of the Centrists Following the
                           Sutras</head>
                        <p>In general, there originated many ways of commenting on the intention of
                           the text, The Fundamental [Verses on] Centrism [called] Supreme Knowledge
                           by noble Nagarjuna. However, these mainly fall under the two [schools of]
                           the Consequentialists and the Autonomists. The [first verse after the
                           eulogy] at the beginning of [Nagarjuna’s] treatise reads,</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Not from themselves, not from others,</l>
                           <l>Not from both and not without a cause — </l>
                           <l>At any place and any time,</l>
                           <l>...Entities lack arising.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p> As for the way to explain the meaning of this [verse]: [First], through
                           the four claims of non-arising from the four extremes, master
                           Buddhapalita has invalidated the [four] antitheses [of these claims], but
                           did not set up any means to prove an actual thesis. Then, master
                           Bhavaviveka criticized the way in which Buddhapalita had formulated his
                           invalidation. He set up the [above four] initial sentences [about
                           non-arising] as autonomous [probative arguments] and also proved the
                           subject property in an autonomous way. After that, venerable Chandrakirti
                           explained how Bhavaviveka’s critique of Buddhapalita does not apply and
                           that Bhavaviveka’s acceptance of autonomous arguments in the context of
                           his own explanation of reasonings that analyze the ultimate is flawed.
                           Thus, he was the one who founded the tradition of the Consequentialists
                           in an extensive manner.... </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </quote>
         </dhq:example>
         <dhq:example>
            <head>TEI encoding of the same passage</head>
            <eg> &lt;head type="argument"&gt;6.2.1.2.1.2.3.1.1.1. The system of the &lt;name
               type="philosophical school"&gt;Centrists&lt;/name&gt; Following the
               Sutras&lt;/head&gt; &lt;p&gt;In general, there originated many ways of commenting on
               the intention of the text &lt;title rend="italic"&gt;The Fundamental [Verses on]
               &lt;name type="philosophical school"&gt;Centrism &lt;/name&gt; [called] Supreme
               Knowledge&lt;/title&gt; by noble &lt;persName key="N1"&gt;Nagarjuna&lt;/persName&gt;.
               However, these mainly fall under the two [schools of] the &lt;name
               type="philosophical school"&gt;Consequentialists&lt;/name&gt; and the &lt;name type=
               "philosophical school"&gt;Autonomists&lt;/name&gt;. The [first verse after the
               eulogy] at the beginning of [&lt;persName key="N1"&gt; Nagarjuna&lt;/persName&gt;'s]
               treatise reads,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;q&gt;&lt;lg&gt; &lt;l&gt;Not from themselves, not from
               others,&lt;/l&gt; &lt;l&gt; Not from both and not without a
               cause&lt;mdash&gt;&lt;/l&gt; &lt;l&gt; At any place and any time,&lt;/l&gt;
               &lt;l&gt;...Entities lack arising.&lt;/l&gt;&lt;/lg&gt; &lt;/q&gt; &lt;p&gt;As for
               the way to explain the meaning of this [verse]: [First], through the four claims of
               &lt;rs type="basic argument"&gt;non-arising from the four extremes&lt;/rs&gt;, master
               &lt;persName key="BP1"&gt;Buddhapalita &lt;/persName&gt; has invalidated the [four]
               antitheses [of these claims], but did not set up any means to prove an actual thesis.
               Then, master &lt;persName key="BP2"&gt;Bhavaviveka&lt;/persName&gt; criticized the
               way in which &lt;persName key="BP1"&gt;Buddhapalita&lt;/persName&gt; had formulated
               his invalidation. He set up the [above four] initial sentences [about &lt;rs
               type="basic concept"&gt;non-arising&lt;/rs&gt;] as autonomous [probative arguments]
               and also proved the subject property in an autonomous way. After that, venerable
               &lt;persName key="C1"&gt;Chandrakirti&lt;/persName&gt; explained how &lt;persName
               key="BP2"&gt;Bhavaviveka&lt;/persName&gt;'s critique of &lt;persName
               key="BP1"&gt;Buddhapalita&lt;/persName&gt; does not apply and that &lt;persName
               key="BP2"&gt;Bhavaviveka&lt;/persName&gt;'s acceptance of autonomous arguments in the
               context of his own explanation of reasonings that analyze &lt;rs type="basic
               concept"&gt;the ultimate&lt;/rs&gt; is flawed. Thus, he was the one who founded the
               tradition of the &lt;name type= "philosophical
               school"&gt;Consequentialists&lt;/name&gt; in an extensive manner....&lt;/p&gt; </eg>
         </dhq:example>
         <p>The challenge in using TEI to capture these Tibetan materials lies in what escapes this
            kind of basic encoding. Because the TEI was initially developed by scholars familiar
            with the western textual tradition, features of some non-western textual traditions may
            pose theoretical and practical challenges, and may require some adaptation of the TEI.
            For example, one important feature is the enunciative mode associated with the text. It
            is not irrelevant to Tibetan scholars whether a text is chanted, read silently,
            transmitted by a teacher in a lung (a ritual that empowers listeners to practice
            meditation or study denoted by the text), or scanned on a computer screen. Tibetans
            believe that their texts do not simply record information but actually embody ancient
            ideas or meanings that, in some situations, require appropriate methods of transmission.
            Thus if we were to understand Tibetan texts according to a theoretical and operational
            paradigm that treats them only as information, we would not only lose the original
            Tibetan cultural context but would lose the different degrees of <q>transmission
               power</q> said to be generated by different media (reading, chanting, lung
            transmission, etc.) within the Tibetan textual tradition. This representation of the
            enunciative mode, which is essential to practicing with Tibetan texts, might be
            accomplished by additional, customized TEI elements for the chanted sections of the
            texts. </p>
         <p> Another challenging dimension is the readers’ actions in association with a text. Some
            of the most advanced Tibetan meditation techniques include hand movements (called
            mudras; <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref> shows examples of these gestures), bodily
            movements (such as prostrations), chanting, and complex visualizations. Texts are always
            central to these meditation methods, but engagement with the Vajrayana text is far more
            active than what occurs by simply reading or even chanting the text. <figure
               xml:id="figure02">
               <head>Khenpo Karthar Rinpoche and Bardor Tulku Rinpoche leading a Vajrayana
                  meditation by chanting a text and doing mudras</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of two Tibetan monks leading a meditation</figDesc>

            </figure> For example, one of the sections of the <title rend="quotes">Medicine
               Buddha</title> meditation (which is used for healing) requires special hand movements
            (mudras), performed while imagining a dark blue Buddha figure as one chants the mantra
            of Medicine Buddha. The co-ordination of body (mudras), speech (mantra), and mind
            (visualization of blue Buddha figure; see <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>) is
            difficult but necessary for the Vajrayana meditation practice. Instructions on how to
            perform the mudras and how to chant the mantra are not in the Tibetan text itself; the
            image of the blue Buddha is not in the text either. Traditionally, the mudras and chant
            melody must be learned from a Tibetan teacher, and the visualization image is usually
            memorized by focusing on a thangka painting in a shrine room. </p>
         <figure xml:id="figure03">
            <head>Thangka Painting of Medicine Buddha. © 2006 Karma Triyana Dharmachakra</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>Thangka Painting of Medicine Buddha</figDesc>
         </figure>
         <p>These additional dimensions are not simply contextual information necessary to
            understand the text being encoded: in an important sense, they are integral parts of the
            text and its meaning, without which it cannot be said to be truly preserved. Tibetans
            are intent upon preserving their textual heritage, but not simply as information in
            storage. Instead, they aim for <q>real preservation</q> that records and encodes enough
            of the living textual tradition so that the texts may be taken up again by future
            generations in a way that continues Tibetan culture’s most meaningful values and
            customs. Transcription or simple digitization of Tibetan texts constitutes mere
               <q>storage preservation</q>; the texts may be read and studied in the future, but
            their Vajrayana elements of mantra, mudra and meditation will not be captured, since
            these elements need to be practiced <q>live</q>, so to speak, not just read. If a
            Tibetan text sits in a library or a digital archive, but no one knows how to chant it or
            meditate with it or debate in response to it, then the text has lost virtually all of
            its meaning. The fossil of the text would be preserved, but the text itself would have
            become extinct. </p>
         <p>Real preservation requires the help of indigenous <q>text custodians</q> who teach the
            traditional ways of working with the texts. This is a pressing concern because the older
            Tibetan teachers who were born in Tibet before the diaspora will die in the next decade
            or two. When they are gone, there may no longer be Buddhist practitioners who know
            exactly how to chant certain texts or how to perform mudras in connection with specific
            textual passages or how to lead more complex rituals based on the texts. To preserve as
            complete a record as possible, so that the texts can live again in the meditation
            practices and rituals performed with the texts, the gestural, musical and mental
            dimensions of these texts must ideally also be recorded. Linking audio, video, and
            images to the transcriptions may help, but it may also be worth exploring ways to notate
            gestural and other information within the transcription itself. The TEI offers some
            approaches to this in its chapters on transcription of speech and on performance texts,
            and these could be extended further to accommodate the distinctive combination of
            information carried in Tibetan texts. </p>
         <p>The encoded TEI file can also form the basis of a more complex multimedia
            representation. The TEI version of the Medicine Buddha liturgy can be linked to an audio
            file of the correct pronunciation and melody of the mantra, to pictures of the hand
            mudras that must be performed during the chanting of the text, and to a visual image of
            the blue Buddha figure. The TEI transcription itself can also contain instructions on
            how to perform the mudras or other bodily movements that occur at each point in the
            text, allowing them to be displayed or suppressed as appropriate. By linking the TEI
            transcription to multimedia resources, an editor could allow the appearance of videos,
            graphics or photos as memory aids at certain points in the text, which would help the
            reader/practitioner perform the visualization of the Buddha figure. An example is shown
            in <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>, which gives the text of a chant in multiple
            scripts together with a description of the mudras to be performed; these mudras are
            illustrated in <ref target="#table1">Table 1</ref> below. The practitioner's voicing of
            the chant could be corrected or accompanied by an audio file of an indigenous Tibetan
            chant master's articulation or by an audio file of Tibetan horns, symbols and bells.
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>Medicine Buddha text. © Heart Center Karma Thegsum Chöling</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Medicine Buddha text</figDesc>

            </figure>
            <table xml:id="table1">
               <head>Diagram of mudras associated with Medicine Buddha text</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>Argham</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/argham.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Padyam</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/padyam.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Pupe</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/pupe.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dhupe</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/dhupe.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Aloke</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/aloke.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Gendhe</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/gendhe.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Newidye</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/newidye.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Shapda</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/shapda.gif"/>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <dhq:example>
               <p>Click for an audio file <media mimeType="audio/x-ms-wma" url="resources/audio/mudra.wma"><desc>audio file of a Tibetan mantra</desc></media> of a Tibetan
                  mantra. Audio file © 2005 Karma Kagyu Institute. Chanted by Umdze Lodro
                  Samphel.</p>
            </dhq:example>
         </p>
         <p>How could the Text Encoding Initiative help indigenous <q>text custodians</q> around the
            world, who are struggling to protect their ancient cultural heritages? Ideally, we might
            envision creating a simple shared descriptive system to facilitate the cataloguing of
            endangered texts, so that international scholars become more aware of which texts have
            been lost and which have been saved. Ideally such a system would be easy to learn, by
            any scholar, working in any language. However, the significant differences between
            textual traditions and descriptive goals make it hard to create a system that would be
            both simple and widely agreed upon. It may be more practical to work on disseminating
            TEI expertise more widely among <q>text custodians</q>. A second step, therefore, would
            be to hold workshops on these digital technologies in the universities and teachers’
            colleges of developing countries. The Digital Divide is closing in some parts of the
            world (for example, India), and outreach from well-endowed scholarly communities to
            poorer scholarly communities could include the sharing of digital methods for preserving
            texts. Supported by occasional workshops, a virtual, international community of <q>text
               custodians</q> trained in TEI could grow and bridge the Digital Divide between
            developed and developing countries. </p>
         <p> In this endeavor, it is important to respect the control that indigenous scholars have
            over their own textual heritage. A textual heritage is a cultural property that can
            speak to the world, but it should be maintained by the people whose ancestors created
            it. If there are traditional rules about access to certain texts, digital technologies
            should not bypass these rules. Digital technologies should not be used to appropriate
            the world’s textual riches or simply to add inventory to western digital archives. The
            model of broad <q>access</q> that often motivates western digitization efforts does not
            apply universally, and may in some cases go directly against the indigenous textual
            tradition. This issue comes up with regard to Tibetan texts, because some of these texts
            are esoteric texts, reserved for advanced meditators. It is generally presumed by
            western scholars that increased access to texts is better. But this presumption is not
            shared by Tibetan scholars, who deal with texts that require special permission and
            instruction from a qualified teacher before they can be read, studied, chanted or
            memorized. The restricted nature of some Tibetan texts relates to the difficulty of the
            meditation practices described in the text. Not everyone has advanced meditation skills
            or sufficient commitment to undertake the mental training methods relayed in the text.
            Before the Chinese invasion of Tibet, there were monastic libraries that contained
            esoteric volumes which never circulated beyond the monastery or even amongst all members
            of the monastery. Thus although most western scholars do not consider <q>trespassing</q>
            a serious textual practice crime, Tibetan scholars might regard TEI-encoded texts as
            inviting trespassers. This is why it is essential for any multicultural development of
            TEI to involve indigenous scholars, who understand the threats faced by their endangered
            textual tradition and are committed to protecting it. </p>
         <p>When a culture is endangered, as the Tibetan culture is, members of that culture not
            only try to preserve its texts but try to continue the rituals and other practices that
            keep the culture alive. Transcribing texts and digitizing them are important
            preservation methods, but these methods need to be supplemented with other tools for
            awakening the texts from their archival slumber. The benefits of TEI encoding for the
            Tibetan canon range from enhanced preservation of the texts and greater accessibility
            for scholars, to support for the continuation of Vajrayana meditation practices that
            renew the Tibetan Buddhist heritage. Despite the challenges of reconciling Tibetan
            textual assumptions and western digital methods, especially if Tibetan scholars
            themselves learn to apply TEI encoding there is a chance that 21st century technology
            will not leave the ancient Tibetan textual tradition behind. </p>
         <p>Why are modern digital methods such as TEI encoding so important for endangered Tibetan
            texts? There are a couple of reasons. First, digital text applications support the
            Tibetan scholarly community, which is spread across the globe. Online digitized Tibetan
            texts can be accessed by a Tibetan in exile no matter where he or she has taken up
            residence. The circulation of texts is made easier when the cataloguing and searching of
            texts follows standardized guidelines, and TEI encoding provides just this kind of
            standardized information. The other side of this point, however, is that the exiled
            Tibetan scholarly community lacks the kind of financial support that a government would
            normally provide for modernizing its textual tradition; this community must rely on the
            largesse of western scholarly institutions. By concerning itself with the plight of
            endangered textual traditions, the Text Encoding Initiative might provide aid to these
            Tibetan scholars in exile.</p>
         <p>Another reason is that TEI encoding gives the Tibetan textual tradition entrance to an
            international scholarly enterprise that may make it easier for non-Tibetans to
            understand Tibetan Buddhism. Even though the Tibetan Buddhist tradition is being lost on
            its home soil, an international Tibetan Buddhist culture is appearing. Scholars and
            meditators in Europe and the western hemisphere are studying Vajrayana Buddhism and
            practicing its meditation methods, liturgies and philosophical debate techniques.
            Vajrayana Buddhism depends upon the direct transmission of teachings from a qualified
            teacher to students, but there is also a virtual dimension to this spread of Tibetan
            Buddhism. Tibetan Buddhists often go online to find information and to communicate with
            one another; digital technologies have been used to forge connections between western
            newcomers to Tibetan Buddhism and indigenous Tibetan monks and nuns. Compared to the
            restrictions on the study and practice of Tibetan Buddhism within Tibet itself, there is
            greater freedom online to discuss the issues and share the achievements that are
            important to Tibetan Buddhists. This global Tibetan Buddhist community is forming with
            the aid of digital communication tools unavailable twenty years ago. The adoption of TEI
            encoding will add a scholarly tool to this digital toolkit.</p>
         <p>Finally, the rich heritage of Vajrayana Buddhism cannot be represented by a
            one-dimensional medium. Its exuberant visual imagery, its complex symbolism, its
            deep-toned chanting and music, and its engagement of the body in ritualized motions
            combine within the most advanced meditation practices. Although Tibetans do practice
            quiet, unmoving meditation, what is distinctive about the Tibetan tradition is the
            overabundance of forms — painting, music, ritualized gesture, chanting, dance, even
            formal philosophical debate — within its meditation practices. Digital technologies
            capture this rich dimension of Tibetan texts better than the simple transcription of
            texts can. Because TEI encoding offers ways to release a Tibetan liturgy, meditation
            manual or philosophical inquiry from its text-cocoon and express its full
            multidimensionality, TEI is one of the digital technologies that holds promise for
            preserving the Vajrayana textual tradition.</p>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item> Jeff Hoogmoed, http://www.freespacegraphix.biz</item>
               <item> Union College East Asian Studies Freeman Foundation grant</item>
               <item> Union College Humanities Faculty Development grant</item>
               <item> Editors of Digital Humanities Quarterly </item>
               <item> Photographs courtesy of Tenzin Namdak, Nitartha International Document Input
                  Center, Kathmandu, Nepal and Karma Triyana Dharmachakra Monastery, Woodstock,
                  NY</item>
               <item> Audio file courtesy of Karma Kagyu Institute, Woodstock, NY </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2003" label="Anderson 2003" key="anderson2003">
               <author>Anderson, Deborah</author>. <title rend="quotes">Unicode and Historic
                  Scripts</title>, Ariadne 37 (2003). Accessed 2005-03-03. <ref
                  target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue37/anderson/"
                  >http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue37/anderson/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bia2004" label="Bia 2004" key="bia2004">
               <author>Bia, Alejandro</author>, and <author>Sanchez-Quero, Manuel</author>. <title
                  rend="italic">The Future of Markup is Multilingual</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.hum.gu.se/allcach2004/ap/html/prop119.html"
                  >http://www.hum.gu.se/allcach2004/AP/html/prop119.html</ref>. Accessed 2005-03-03. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chilton2006" label="Chilton 2006" key="chilton2006">
               <author>Chilton, Robert</author>. <title rend="quotes">Tibetan Buddhism at the
                  Digital Frontier</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.chibs.edu.tw/exchange/conference/4cicob/fulltext/chilton.htm"
                  >http://www.chibs.edu.tw/exchange/CONFERENCE/4cicob/fulltext/Chilton.htm</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dreyfus2003" label="Dreyfus 2003" key="dreyfus2003">
               <author>Dreyfus, Georges B.J.</author>
               <title rend="italic">The Sound of Two Hands Clapping: The Education of a Tibetan
                  Buddhist Monk</title>. <pubPlace> Berkeley</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of
                  California Press</publisher>, <date>2003</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dutt1962" label="Dutt 1962" key="dutt1962">
               <author>Dutt, Sukumar</author>. <title rend="italic">Buddhist Monks and Monasteries
                  of India</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>G. Allen and
                  Unwin</publisher>, <date>1962</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2002" label="Hayles 2002" key="hayles2002">
               <author>Hayles, N. Katherine</author>. <title rend="italic">Writing Machines</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>,
                  <date>2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marvet2006" label="Marvet 2006" key="marvet2006">
               <author>Marvet, Martin</author>. <title rend="quotes">Lost Textual Treasures</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">The Home for Digital Tibetan</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.nitartha.org/lost_texts.html"
                  >http://www.nitartha.org/lost_texts.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="muller1894" label="Müller 1894" key="muller1894">
               <author>Müller, F. Max</author>. <title rend="italic">Buddhist Mahâyâna
               Texts</title>. In <title rend="italic">The Sacred Books of the East</title>,
                  vol. 49. E. B. Cowell, F. Max Müller, and J.
               Takakusu (trans). <pubPlace> Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1894</date>. Available online at <ref
                  target="http://www.sacred-texts.com/bud/sbe49/index.htm"
                  >www.sacred-texts.com/bud/sbe49/index.htm</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rahtz2005" label="Rahtz 2005" key="rahtz2005">
               <author>Rahtz, Sebastian</author>. <title rend="quotes">TEI
                  Internationalisation</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/wiki/index.php/tei_internationalisation"
                  >http://www.tei-c.org.uk/wiki/index.php/TEI_Internationalisation</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Treasury of Knowledge (trans. 2002)" xml:id="thaye2002">Thaye, Jamgön Kongtrul Lodrö. <title rend="quotes">Chapter on Madhyamaka,</title> <title rend="italic">The Treasury of Knowledge.</title> Eng. trans. by Karl Brunnhölzl. Nidartha Institute, 2002.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
