<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tenure, Promotion and Digital Publication</title>
            <author>Joseph Raben</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Joseph <dhq:family>Raben</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Queens College, City University of New York</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>joeraben@ncsa.uiuc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Joseph Raben is a professor emeritus of English at Queens College of the City
                     University of New York, where he taught for 30 years. Before that he was a
                     teaching fellow at Indiana University and an instructor at Princeton
                     University. He was awarded a B.A. with honors at the University of Wisconsin
                     and a Ph.D. at Indiana University, where he minored in folklore under Stith
                     Thompson. His bachelor's honors thesis was on pronunciation as revealed by
                     rhyme schemes in American folksongs, and his doctoral dissertation studied folk
                     speech in Scott's novels. After graduating from Wisconsin, he worked as an
                     engineering aide on the construction of the Hanford Engineer Works, and then
                     entered the Army, where he was trained in spoken Japanese and served in Tokyo
                     as an editor of translations in the Allied Translator and Interpreter Service,
                     attached to GHQ. In this service he translated documents used in the war crimes
                     trials.</p>
                  <p>At Queens he developed an interest in using computers in humanities research
                     and in 1966 founded the innovative journal <title rend="italic">Computers and
                        the Humanities</title> to provide a platform for younger pioneering scholars
                     to publish their research. He both edited and carried a large share of this
                     journal's publication chores for 20 years. Among its most useful features was a
                     semiannual <title rend="italic">Directory of Scholars Active</title>, which
                     informed practitioners around the world of recent applications of computer
                     technology to humanities and related social science problems. These notes he
                     cumulated into a print volume, <title rend="italic">Computer-Assisted Research
                        in the Humanities</title> (New York: Pergamon Press, 1977). In 1978 he
                     founded the Association for Computers and the Humanities and served as its
                     president for two years before turning it over to younger successors. During
                     this same period, he helped to organize several international conferences at
                     the University of Southern California, Grinnell College, Dartmouth College,
                     Rutgers University, North Carolina State University and Auburn University. He
                     also presented papers at many international conferences organized by others and
                     represented humanities computing at conferences organized by groups within the
                     computer industry, such as the ACM, the American Federation of Information
                     Processing Societies, the International Federation for Information Processing,
                     and the American Society for Information Science. He organized special interest
                     groups at several MLA conventions and within the ACM. He was an invited
                     lecturer at academic institutions all over the United States, Canada, and
                     Western Europe, and in India, China, and Japan. Much of the same effort was
                     contained in articles published in a variety of journals, along with his
                     contributions to Shelley scholarship, some of it based on the manuscript
                     materials in the Bodleian Library.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000006</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>opinion</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-04-03">3 April 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2007-03-02" who="Julia Flanders">Encoded revised article</change>
         <change when="2007-03-12" who="John Walsh">Removed empty abstract, Re-ordered author/name
            (first,last)</change>
         <change when="2007-03-30" who="Julia Flanders">Minor wording change per Raben request, and
            updated author email address</change>
         <change when="2008-06-12" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added publicationStmt,
            added blank teaser and abstract for validation with new schema</change>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
         <change when="2009-12-03" who="CRB">Changed emph elements to title in bio</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This is a discussion of the impact of <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Humanities Quarterly</title>'s launch on humanities scholarship.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Discusses the impact of <title rend="italic">Digital
               Humanities Quarterly</title>'s launch on humanities scholarship.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>The launching of an online journal like <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
               Quarterly</title> represents much that is positive about the current status of our
            community and much that still must be accomplished. It is satisfying to see a totally
            online scholarly publication, especially one that seeks to fill the niche created 40
            years ago by <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>, a repository for
            information on the evolving relationship between humanistic endeavors and computer
            technology. That the technology this new journal employs is also the one that it studies
            can be counted as a step forward. At the same time, however, the absence of parallel
            publications in other sectors of humanities research is a measure of the distance still
            to be traveled before computer publishing is regarded as fully equal to the book and the
            print journal.</p>
         <p>Underlying the status of online publication as an inferior medium is probably the
            concern on the part of potential contributors that appearance in electronic media is not
            as highly regarded by the gatekeepers of tenure and promotion as the traditional
            hard-bound book and the article offprint, at least in the humanities. In the survey of
            attitudes among chairs and deans of all academic disciplines I organized in 1980, long
            before even the Internet had developed, much less the World Wide Web and the widespread
            availability of personal computers and laptops, the opinion of only half the respondents
            was in favor of treating online publication, even with all the traditional safeguards of
            peer review and editorial control, as earning the same credit toward tenure and
            promotion as was provided by traditional publication. How much the balance has tilted in
            favor of the newer technology has not (to my knowledge) been measured recently. A study
            of language departments conducted by the Modern Language Association is mentioned below. </p>
         <p>This reluctance to provide wider and less costly access to humanities scholarship
            represents a disjuncture with the expectations of the potential audience for this
            information. The generation of students in our graduate schools today has already become
            completely at ease with computers and online communication. Even in their non-academic
            activities, theses students rely increasingly on computers for access to information of
            almost every sort. In their academic activities they download electronic information to
            such an extent that their instructors must plead for at least the partial use of print
            media. Now, with the drive promoted by Google to scan the contents of several major
            university and public libraries, the time is drawing close when very few reasons will
            remain to argue the superiority of books and print journals over online databases. Thus
            the arguments for directing publishing scholars toward the devious route of publishing
            new material in print, only to have it then scanned for online access become
            increasingly illogical. </p>
         <p>The time it will take for the academic establishment to recognize the value of online
            publication is a function of its willingness to accept the replacement of a system that
            has seemed to operate relatively well until now. Books and print articles have been the
            stairs leading to the tenure, promotion, higher salaries and reduced teaching loads that
            are the system’s rewards for scholarly industry. When deans and even chairs are
            incapable of evaluating the content of such publications, they have been able to rely on
            the number of a candidate’s publications, their substance, the prestige of their
            publishers and (to a limited extent in the humanities) the number of times they are
            cited elsewhere. </p>
         <p>With understandable ergophobia, these administrators do not eagerly anticipate learning
            a new system without these comforting means of measuring accomplishment. The latest
            newsletter of the Modern Language Association announces that <q>40.8% of departments in
               doctorate-granting institutions report no experience in evaluating refereed articles
               in electronic format, and 65.7% report no experience in evaluating monographs in
               electronic format.</q> How daring must a pioneering candidate for tenure and/or
            promotion be to risk career advancement in this dangerous environment? </p>
         <p>
            <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> therefore strikes out a new
            path for humanities scholarship. The journal’s long-term success may well establish a
            pattern followed by humanities journals devoted to topics other than the application of
            the technology. If so, future issues may need to consider the consequences of that wider
            adoption of this publication mode. And future articles in this space can consider the
            implications of our impact on the evolution of academe.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
