<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
        <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Johanna<dhq:family> Drucker</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Breslauer Professor of Bibliographical Studies Department of Information
            Studies, UCLA</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>drucker@gseis.ucla.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Johanna Drucker has lectured and published widely on topics related to the visual
              production of knowledge in graphical, textual, and digital forms. She is currently
              working on a project to design a virtual Museum of Writing in collaboration with Simon
              Eliot, University of London, and Paul Vetch, King’s College London. She has recently
              completed a book manuscript on the interpretation of diagrams and their use in
              humanistic interpretation. Her recent titles include <title rend="italic">Sweet
                Dreams: Contemporary Art and Complicity</title> (2008), <title rend="italic">Graphic
                Design History: A Critical Guide</title>, with Emily McVarish (2008), and <title rend="italic">SpecLab: Projects in Digital Aesthetics and Speculative
                Computing</title> (2009).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000091</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2011-03-10">10 March 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
      <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2010-11-12" who="Amy">began entering content, not yet including footnotes,
        figures or other references, still need to enter body text highlights</change>
         <change when="2010-11-13" who="Amy">coninued editing, marking up emp and terms, entering
        figure content, still need to enter figure descriptions, only go so far as fig 6a-c (not
        sure about the cd, issues)</change>
         <change when="2010-12-01" who="Amy">entered footnotes and bibliographic information</change>
         <change when="2011-01-13" who="Amy">began entering corrections, check document</change>
         <change when="2011-02-03" who="Alyssa">started corrections</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
        <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>As digital humanists have adopted visualization tools in their work, they have borrowed
          methods developed for the graphical display of information in the natural and social
          sciences. These tools carry with them assumptions of knowledge as observer-independent and
          certain, rather than observer co-dependent and interpretative. This paper argues that we
          need a humanities approach to the graphical expression of interpretation. To begin, the
          concept of <term>data</term> as a given has to be rethought through a humanistic lens and
          characterized as <term>capta</term>, taken and constructed. Next, the forms for graphical
          expression of capta need to be more nuanced to show ambiguity and complexity. Finally, the
          use of a humanistic approach, rooted in a co-dependent relation between observer and
          experience, needs to be expressed according to graphics built <emph>from</emph>
          interpretative models. In summary: all data have to be understood as capta and the
          conventions created to express observer-independent models of knowledge need to be
          radically reworked to express humanistic interpretation. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
        <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>From data to capta: Do humanists need their own graphical tools?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</head>
         <!-- Use <div> only if there is more than one section -->
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>As digital visualization tools have become more ubiquitous, humanists have adopted many
          applications such as GIS mapping, graphs, and charts for statistical display that were
          developed in other disciplines. But, I will argue, such graphical tools are a kind of
          intellectual Trojan horse, a vehicle through which assumptions about what constitutes
          information swarm with potent force. These assumptions are cloaked in a rhetoric taken
          wholesale from the techniques of the empirical sciences that conceals their
          epistemological biases under a guise of familiarity. So naturalized are the Google maps
          and bar charts generated from spread sheets that they pass as unquestioned representations
          of <soCalled>what is</soCalled>. This is the hallmark of realist models of knowledge and needs to be
          subjected to a radical critique to return the humanistic tenets of constructed-ness and
          interpretation to the fore. Realist approaches depend above all upon an idea that
          phenomena are <emph>observer-independent</emph> and can be characterized as
            <emph>data</emph>. Data pass themselves off as mere descriptions of a priori conditions.
          Rendering <term>observation</term> (the act of creating a statistical, empirical, or subjective account
          or image) as if it were <emph>the same as the phenomena observed</emph> collapses the
          critical distance between the phenomenal world and its interpretation, undoing the basis
          of interpretation on which humanistic knowledge production is based. We know this. But we
          seem ready and eager to suspend critical judgment in a rush to visualization. At the very
          least, humanists beginning to play at the intersection of statistics and graphics ought to
          take a detour through the substantial discussions of the sociology of knowledge and its
          developed critique of realist models of data gathering<note>
                  <ptr target="#knorr1990"/>
                  <ptr target="#lynch1988"/>
                  <ptr target="#anderson2007"/>
                  <ptr target="#anderson2008"/>
                  <ptr target="#porter1995"/>
                  <ptr target="#lochlann2010"/>
                  <ptr target="#latour1986"/>.</note>
          At best, we need to take on the challenge of developing graphical expressions rooted in
          and appropriate to interpretative activity.</p>
            <p>Because realist approaches to visualization assume transparency and equivalence, as if
          the phenomenal world were self-evident and the apprehension of it a mere mechanical task,
          they are fundamentally at odds with approaches to humanities scholarship premised on
          constructivist principles. I would argue that even for realist models, those that presume
          an observer-independent reality available to description, the methods of presenting
          ambiguity and uncertainty in more nuanced terms would be useful. Some significant progress
          is being made in visualizing uncertainty in data models for GIS, decision-making,
          archaeological research and other domains.<note>
                  <ptr target="#griethe2006"/>
                  <ptr target="#jones2008"/>
                  <ptr target="#maceachren2005"/>
                  <ptr target="#shneiderman2005"/>
                  <ptr target="#skeels2008"/>
                  <ptr target="#wells2008"/>
               </note> But an important
          distinction needs to be clear from the outset: the task of representing ambiguity and
          uncertainty has to be distinguished from a second task – that of using interpretations
          that arise in observer-codependence, characterized by ambiguity and uncertainty, as the
          basis on which a representation is constructed. This is the difference between putting
          many kinds of points on a map to show degrees of certainty by shades of color, degrees of
          crispness, transparency etc., and creating a map whose basic coordinate grid is
          constructed <emph>as an effect</emph> of these ambiguities. In the first instance, we have
          a standard map with a nuanced symbol set. In the second, we create a non-standard map that
          expresses the constructed-ness of space. Both rely on rethinking our approach to
          visualization and the assumptions that underpin it.</p>
            <p>To overturn the assumptions that structure conventions acquired from other domains
          requires that we re-examine the intellectual foundations of digital humanities, putting
          techniques of graphical display on a foundation that is humanistic at its base. <emph>This
            requires first and foremost that we reconceive all data as capta</emph>. Differences in
          the etymological roots of the terms data and capta make the distinction between
          constructivist and realist approaches clear. <emph>Capta</emph> is <soCalled>taken</soCalled> actively while
          <emph>data</emph> is assumed to be a <soCalled>given</soCalled> able to be recorded and observed. From this
          distinction, a world of differences arises. Humanistic inquiry acknowledges the situated,
          partial, and constitutive character of knowledge production, the recognition that
          knowledge is constructed, <emph>taken</emph>, not simply given as a natural representation
          of pre-existing fact.</p>
            <p>My distinction between data and capta is not a covert suggestion that the humanities and
          sciences are locked into intellectual opposition, or that only the humanists have the
          insight that intellectual disciplines create the objects of their inquiry. Any
          self-conscious historian of science or clinical researcher in the natural or social
          sciences insists the same is true for their work. Statisticians are extremely savvy about
          their artifices. Social scientists may divide between realist and constructivist
          foundations for their research, but none are naïve when it comes to the rhetorical
          character of statistics. The history of knowledge is the history of forms of expression of
          knowledge, and those forms change. What can be said, expressed, represented in any era is
          distinct from that of any other, with all the attendant caveats and reservations that
          attend to the study of the sequence of human intellectual events, keeping us from any
          assertion of progress while noting the facts of change and transformation. The historical,
          critical study of science is as full of discussions of this material as the
          humanities.</p>
            <p>Thus the <emph>representation</emph> of knowledge is as crucial to its cultural force as
          any other facet of its production. The graphical forms of display that have come to the
          fore in digital humanities in the last decade are borrowed from a mechanistic approach to
          realism, and the common conception of data in those forms needs to be completely rethought
          for humanistic work. To reiterate what I said above, the sheer power of the graphical
          display of <soCalled>information visualization</soCalled> (and its novelty within a humanities community
          newly enthralled with the toys of data mining and display) seems to have produced a
          momentary blindness among practitioners who would never tolerate such literal assumptions
          in textual work.</p>
            <p>The polemic I set forth here outlines several basic principles on which to proceed
          differently by suggesting that what is needed <emph>is not a set of applications to
            display humanities <soCalled>data</soCalled> but a new approach that uses humanities principles to
            constitute capta and its display</emph>. At stake, as I have said before and in many
          contexts, is the authority of humanistic knowledge in a culture increasingly beset by
          quantitative approaches that operate on claims of certainty. Bureaucracies
          process human activity through statistical means and when the methods grounded in
          empirical sciences are put at the service of the social sciences or humanities in a
          crudely reductive manner, basic principles of critical thought are violated, or at the
          very least, put too far to the side. To intervene in this ideological system, humanists,
          and the values they embrace and enact, must counter with conceptual tools that demonstrate
          humanities principles in their operation, execution, and display. The digital humanities
          can no longer afford to take its tools and methods from disciplines whose fundamental
          epistemological assumptions are at odds with humanistic method.</p>
            <p>This paper is a call to imaginative action and intellectual engagement with the challenge
          of rethinking digital tools for visualization on basic principles of the humanities. I
          take these principles to be, first, that the humanities are committed to the concept of
          knowledge as interpretation, and, second, that the apprehension of the phenomena of the
          physical, social, cultural world is through constructed and constitutive acts, not
          mechanistic or naturalistic realist representations of pre-existing or self-evident
          information. Nothing in intellectual life is self-evident or self-identical, nothing in
          cultural life is mere fact, and nothing in the phenomenal world gives rise to a record or
          representation except through constructed expressions. The rhetorical force of graphical
          display is too important a field for its design to be adopted without critical scrutiny
          and the full force of theoretical insight. Let me suggest what that means for the
          visualization of informational, temporal, and spatial phenomena.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Data as capta: from information visualization to graphical expressions of
          interpretation</head>
            <p>If I set up a bar chart or graph, my first act is to draw a set of one or more axes and
          divide them into units. The conventional forms of the graphical display of information,
          <soCalled>data</soCalled>, make use of a formal, unambiguous system of standard metrics. Charts use simple
          (if often misleading) geometric forms that lend themselves to legible comparison of
          values, proportions, or the exhibition of state changes across time. Lines, bars, columns,
          and pie charts are the common and familiar forms. They render <emph>quantitative</emph>
          relations with a transparency that seems natural, so that, for instance, if we look at the
          changes in population across a series of years for a particular location, we can simply
          accept that from one year to the next rises or drops occurred in the numbers of persons
          alive in X city in X country at X time. A pie chart showing percentage of resource
          allocation from national budgets seems completely transparent, self-evident even. A bar
          chart could compare daylight hours at different longitudes, or the average size of men and
          women in different countries, or the number of hospital beds in different institutions in
          a single geographical location and not raise a skeptical eyebrow, right? Yes, but the
          rendering of statistical information into graphical form gives it a simplicity and
          legibility that hides every aspect of the original interpretative framework on which the
          statistical data were constructed. The graphical force conceals what the statistician
          knows very well — that no <soCalled>data</soCalled> pre-exist their parameterization. <emph>Data
            are capta</emph>, taken not given, constructed as an interpretation of the phenomenal
          world, not inherent in it.</p>
            <p>To expose the constructedness of data as capta a number of systematic changes have to be
          applied to the creation of graphical displays. That is the foundation and purpose of a
            <emph>humanistic approach</emph> to the qualitative display of graphical information.
          Read that last formulation carefully, <emph>humanistic approach</emph> means that the
          premises are rooted in the recognition of the <emph>interpretative</emph> nature of
          knowledge, that the <emph>display</emph> itself is conceived to <emph>embody qualitative
            expressions</emph>, and that the information is understood as <emph>graphically
            constituted</emph>. Each of these factors contains an explicit critique of assumptions
          in the conventional <soCalled>visual display of quantitative information</soCalled> that is the common
          currency.</p>
            <p>Let me work through a specific case to show how each of these principles —
          humanistic approach, qualitative display, and graphical information — can be
          demonstrated. As an example, we can use that bar chart mentioned above, one that compares
          the percentage of men and women in various national populations at the present time.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>A basic bar chart compares the number of men (top bar) and the
                  number of women (bottom bar) in seven different nations, A through F, at the present
                  time (2010). The assumptions are that quantities (number), entities (nations),
                  identities (gender) and temporality (now) are all self-evident. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc>Bar chart comparing the percentage of men and women in national populations at
            the present time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Certain issues immediately arise. A standard critique of data introduces reservations
          about the appearance of certainty such a chart presents. What counts as a nation? Are
          transient and immigrant populations documented? What kind of time span counts as <soCalled>at the
            present time</soCalled> within which these populations are counted? If the basic bar chart would
          have looked like a series of bands showing discrete categories of information in finite
          and certain numbers (all due statistical caveats noted), what are the problems? Gender
          definition assumes a simple binary distinction of men and women, an assumption much
          debated and highly problematic (gender can be understood as a factor of behavior,
          physiological changes, social expectations, dress, etc., and nation as a function of
          permeability of borders, citizenship patterns, naturalization rules, immigration
          regulations, quotas and border policies). So the bar chart reifies several categories,
          naturalizing them as discrete and fixed: national populations, time span, and gender
          defined as a simple binary. The representation can only be modified by changing the terms
          and premises on which it is constructed. What would a representation of gender by sliding
          scale look like? How would permeable boundaries to nations whose populations cross each
          others borders be shown? How would they dissolve the bar chart’s basic structure? How
          would notions of the present be defined? <figure xml:id="figure02">
             <head>In this chart gendered identity is modified. In nation A, the
                top bar contains a changing gradient, indicating that <soCalled>man</soCalled> is a continuum from male
                enfant to adult, or in countries E and D, that gender ambiguity is a factor of genetic
                mutation or adaptation, thus showing that basis on which gendered individuals are
                identified and counted is complicated by many factors. In country F women only
                register as individuals after coming of reproductive age, thus showing that quantity
                is a effect of cultural conditions, not a self-evident fact. The movement of men back
                and forth across the border of nations B and C makes the <soCalled>nations</soCalled> unstable
                entities. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Bar chart showing gender modification with paired male and female columns
              labelled A through F.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>The point I’m making is that the basic categories of supposedly quantitative information,
          the fundamental parameters of chart production, are already interpreted expressions. But
          they do not present themselves as categories of interpretation, riven with ambiguity and
          uncertainty, because of the <emph>representational</emph> force of the visualization as a
          <soCalled>picture</soCalled> of <soCalled>data</soCalled>. For instance, the assumption that gender is a binary category, stable
          across all cultural and national communities, is an assertion, an argument. Gendered
          identity defined in binary terms is not a self-evident fact, no matter how often Olympic
          committees come up against the need for a single rigid genital criterion on which to
          determine difference. By recognizing the always interpreted character of data we have
          shifted from data to capta, acknowledging the constructed-ness of the categories according
          to the uses and expectations for which they are put in service. Nations, genders,
          populations, and time spans are not self-evident, stable entities that exist a priori.
          They are each subject to qualifications and reservations that bear directly on and arise
          from the reality of lived experience. The presentation of the comparison in the original
          formulation grotesquely distorts the complexity — but also, the basic ambiguity
          — of the phenomenon under investigation (gender, nations, populations). If the
          challenge we are facing were merely to accommodate higher levels of complexity into a data
          representation model, that would require one set of considerations and modifications. But
          the more profound challenge we face is to accept the ambiguity of knowledge, the
          fundamentally interpreted condition on which data is constructed, in other words, the
          realization of my refrain–that all data is capta.</p>
            <p>The humanistic aspect of this approach should be obvious — that knowledge
          created with the acknowledgement of the fundamentally constructed nature of its premises
          is not commensurate with principles of certainty guiding empirical or realist methods.
          Humanistic methods are counter to the idea of reliably repeatable experiments or standard
          metrics that assume observer independent phenomena. By definition, a humanistic approach
          is centered in the experiential, subjective conditions of interpretation. Phenomena and
          their observers are co-dependent, not necessarily in equal measure. A viewer gazing on a
          sublime landscape or recording migrations at a large scale may be more affected by the
          phenomena than the phenomena is by the observation. Theoretical physicist Werner
          Heisenberg never suggested that the relation of intervening observer and effect on
          phenomena were symmetrical, merely that they were codependent, when he introduced the
          concept of uncertainty in the early 20th century.</p>
            <p>Creating bar charts with ambiguity and degrees of uncertainty or other variables in them
          might cause champions of legibility and transparency some unease, but the shift away from
          standard metrics to metrics that express interpretation is an essential move for humanists
          and/or constructivists across disciplines. To emphasize the expressive quality of
          interpretation, I’m going to characterize constructed information as
            <emph>subjective</emph> – expressing the marks of its inflection in some formal way. The
          shift to expressive metrics and graphics is essential in changing from the
            <emph>expression of subjective information</emph> to the <emph>subjective expression of
            perceived phenomena</emph>, but subjectivity and inflection are not the only features of
          interpretative approaches. Capta is not an expression of idiosyncracy, emotion, or
          individual quirks, but a systematic expression of information understood as constructed,
          as phenomena perceived according to principles of interpretation. To do this, we need to
          conceive of every metric <q>as a factor of X</q>, where X is a point of view, agenda,
          assumption, presumption, or simply a convention. By qualifying any metric as a factor of
          some condition, the character of the <soCalled>information</soCalled> shifts from self-evident
          <soCalled>fact</soCalled> to
          constructed interpretation motivated by a human agenda.<note>Subjective carries
            structuralist connotations, as position and enunciated identity; and is meant to suggest
            both the codependent conditions of construction and expressive graphical
            features.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The standard elements of graphic display for statistical information are simple and
          limited: scale divisions, coordinate lines, scale figures, circles, rectangles, curves,
          bars (or columns or percentages of pie charts or other forms) and labels (numbers and
          terms), signs of movement, flow, or state change (arrows, vectors, paths). The ordering
          and arrangement of elements within a chart create another level of information, relational
          information. Relational information is graphically produced – the ordering of elements by
          size, by color, by alphabetical order, by texture, shape or other feature happens in
          graphical space. The resulting arrangement has a semantic value produced by features of
          proximity, grouping, orientation, apparent movement, and other graphical effects.</p>
            <p>Now take these basic elements of graphical display and rethink them according to
          humanistic principles:</p>
            <p>In conventional statistical graphics, the scale divisions are equal units. In humanistic,
          interpretative, graphics, they are not.</p>
            <p>In statistical graphics the coordinate lines are always continuous and straight. In
          humanistic, interpretative, graphics, they might have breaks, repetitions, and curves or
          dips. Interpretation is stochastic and probabilistic, not mechanistic, and its
          uncertainties require the same mathematical and computational models as other complex
          systems.</p>
            <p>The scale figures and labels in statistical graphics need to be clear and legible in all
          cases, and all the more so in humanistic, interpretative, graphics since they will need to
          do quite a bit of work.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the most striking feature distinguishing humanistic, interpretative, and
          constructivist graphical expressions from realist statistical graphics is that the curves,
          bars, columns, percentage values would not always be represented as discrete bounded
          entities, but as conditional expressions of interpretative parameters–a kind of visual
          fuzzy logic or graphical complexity. Thus their edges might be permeable, lines dotted and
          broken, dots and points vary in size and scale or degree of ambiguity of placement, and so
          on. These graphical strategies express interpreted knowledge, situated and partial, rather
          than complete. They can be employed as systematically as other charting elements, though
          part of my intention is to disturb the grounds of certainty on which conventions of
          statistical legibility are based. Point of view systems introduced into graphs and charts
          will make evident a perspectival position with respect to their information, an inner
          standing point in the graphical rendering of space. This is true of all cartographic
          projections. Every map contains within its coordinate system for graphical expression, a
          set of assumptions about the place from which the map is drawn. Information spaces drawn
          from a point of view, rather than as if they were observer independent, reinsert the
          subjective standpoint of their creation into the graphical expression. Finally, any point
          or mark used as a specific node in a humanistic graph is assumed to have many dimensions
          to it – each of which complicates its identity by suggesting the embedded-ness of its
          existence in a system of co-dependent relations. Information entities, or units, are thus
          understood as fictional abstractions serving a purpose. But their potential to be read
          again in relation to any number of other equally significant relations can be made
          evident. This approach destroys the ground on which standard metrics are used to abstract
          quantitative information from human circumstances. Humanistic premises replace notions of
          statistical concepts of self-identity with entangled co-dependence and contingencies.</p>
            <p>All of this may sound unduly complicated to someone merely wanting to count the number of
          pupils enrolled in a group, calculate the number of pencils needed, or to show budgetary
          expenditures on a per capita basis in the classroom, for example. But this example
          — an instance of administrative and bureaucratic management — shows
          that such crudely conceived numeric statistics are useful only in the most reductive
          circumstances. They tell us nothing about whether the pencils can be used, whether the
          pupils are prepared or disposed to their work, or whether the budgets will have any effect
          on learning outcomes or any of the many other factors that come into play in assessments
          based on metrics extracted from lived experience. But each metric — number of X
          or Y — is actually a number as a factor of a particular intellectual assumption
          or decision: pupils as a factor of seats in a room, birthdates, population, illness, etc.
          pencils as a factor of resource allocation, and so on. All metrics are metrics about
          something for some purpose.</p>
            <p>Any humanistic study based on statistical methods, even the simplest techniques of
          counting, has to address the assumption involved in the categories on which such
          techniques (<q>how many of X</q>) are based. Take another example from work in data mining or
          <soCalled>distant reading</soCalled> as it is known in the digital humanities: counting the number of novels
          published in a given year. This involves an enormous number of interpretative decisions –
          each of which has more intellectual dimensions than any numeric assessment could.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
               <head>A chart shows the number of new novels put into print by a single
                  publisher in the years 1855-1862.</head>
               <figDesc>Chart showing novels put into print by a single publisher in the years
            1855-1862.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>The <soCalled>appearance</soCalled> in 1855 of fourteen novels is shown in relation
                  to the time of writing, acquisition, editing, pre-press work, and release thus showing
                  publication date as a factor of many other processes whose temporal range is very
                  varied. The date of a work, in terms of its cultural identity and relevance, can be
                  considered in relation to any number of variables, not just the moment of its
                  publication. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc/>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>For instance, what is a novel, what does <soCalled>published</soCalled> mean in this context (date of
          appearance, editing, composition, acquisition, review, distribution), and how was the
          <soCalled>year</soCalled> determined. Statistical methods come into play <emph>after</emph> these decisions
          have been made, counting objects whose identity was established by <emph>interpretative
            decisions</emph>. Many aspects of constructed-ness are in play. But the graphical
          presentation of supposedly self-evident information (again, formulated in this example as
          <soCalled>the number of novels published in a year</soCalled>) conceals these complexities, and the
          interpretative factors that bring the numerics into being, under a guise of graphical
          legibility. I cannot overstate the perniciousness of such techniques for the effect of
          passing construction off as real, and violating the very premises of humanistic
          inquiry.</p>
            <p>The challenge is to design graphical expressions suited to the display of interpreted
          phenomena: information <emph>about subjective user-dependent metrics</emph>,
            <emph>subjective displays of information</emph>, and <emph>subjective methods</emph> of
          graphical expression. The term <term>subjective</term> is used as shorthand for interpretative
          construction, for the registration of point of view, position, the place from which and
          agenda according to which parameterization occurs. Subjectivity is not the same as
          individual inflection or mere idiosyncracy, but is meant to put codependent relations of
          observer and phenomena (in contrast to presumptions of objectivity, or
          observer-independent phenomena).</p>
            <p>The display of information about inflection of affective experience can easily use
          standard metrics. For example, a chart that shows mood changes or degrees of attraction or
          any other information related to subjectivity can be created with standard metrics and
          visual conventions.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure05">
               <head>A chart of data about affect – the record of positive and negative
                  feelings in the course of an afternoon. Standard metrics are used and a graphical
                  display of the quantized experience appears. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc>A chart showing mood over time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The next task is more complicated. Subjective information, that is information whose
          constitution exhibits its subjective character, deviates from the standard norms by using
          graphic variables such as intensity of tone, size, color, or other feature to embody its
          qualities. Subjective information can use graphical means to show its inflected character,
          demonstrating its deviation from standard norms in the way the display looks, or, in
          dynamic displays, <emph>the way it acts</emph>. One might imagine skittish points on an
          unstable grid to display the degrees of anxiety around a particular event or task, for
          instance, or points that glow hot or cold depending on the other elements that approach
          them. That would be a <emph>subjective — even affective — display of
            information</emph>.</p>
            <p>Creating a display whose structure arises from <emph>subjective methods</emph> of
          graphical expression extends this last example to the design of the basic visual
          structure.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure06">
               <head>A chart in which the subjective information shapes the metric. The activities
                  are given tonal values, size, and weight in order to create a mass or volume that then
                  determines the dimensions of the <soCalled>day</soCalled> which they constitute. The box <soCalled>day</soCalled> does not
                  have an a priori dimension that is used to contain the elements, it is created as an
                  effect of the elements. This is a distinctly different approach to metrics. The chart is
                  generated to express the co-dependent relation of viewer and experience rather than to
                  display user experience as if it were independent of observation. The temporal
                  dimensional of each day depends upon the relations among events, moods, and activities,
                  but not predictably. The shape of the days is made by the creation of the list. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.
               </head>
               <figDesc>A chart featuring words of different sizes, shades, and boldness in multiple
            columns.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>A subjective grid to show anxiety might have a widely varying set of spacings to show
          that the information on display is constituted as a variable of some other aspect of
          experience (number of family members present at an event, for instance). Recognizing that
          such subjective methods are anathema to the empirically minded makes me even more
          convinced that they are essential for the generation of graphical displays of
          interpretative and interpreted information.</p>
            <p>The basic principle underlying such graphical displays is that capta marks its
          interpreted status. Interpreted knowledge is situated, observer co-dependent, and partial.
          Its variables are, in theory, infinite, but they are always present in some degree or
          measure by virtue of the performative and participatory character of interpretative
          information. Interpretation depends upon and is an expression of an individual reading in
          a particular set of circumstances and never presumes to completeness or observer
          independence. The requirements for legibility increase with these unfamiliar graphics, and
          they will need labeling to make explicit the justifications for their non-normative
          seeming appearance. I’m not advocating idiosyncracy, or intellectual solipsism, but a
          systematic approach to graphics that is appropriate to its principles.</p>
            <p>These humanistic principles can be readily applied to the graphical display of temporal
          and spatial information. So I will turn my attention in these next two sections to some of
          the principles on which temporality and spatiality can also be given graphical expression
          through humanistic approaches.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Time as Temporality</head>
            <p>Since antiquity, human conceptions of time have divided between those that consider time
          a given, an a priori existing container within which events occur, and those who consider
          time an effect of occurrences in temporal relation to each other. I take the latter view.
          The relational structure of temporality is always constituted according to inflections and
          variables. Not all days are equal. Or all minutes. Or all hours. Time understood as
          temporality can be succinctly stated as follows: <emph>Temporality = time as a factor of
            X</emph> where <emph>X</emph> is any variable (fear, speed, anxiety, foreshadowing,
          regret, reconsideration, narration, etc.).</p>
            <p>Humanists deal with the representation of temporality <emph>of</emph> documents (when
          they were created), <emph>in</emph> documents (narrated, represented, depicted
          temporality), the construction of temporality <emph>across</emph> documents (the
          temporality of historical events), and also the shape of temporality that emerges
            <emph>from</emph> documentary evidence (the shape of an era, a season, a period or
          epoch). They need a way to graph and chart temporality in an approach that suits the basic
          principles of interpretative knowledge.</p>
            <p>Conceptions of temporality in humanities documents do not conform to those used in the
          social and empirical sciences. In empirical sciences, time is understood as continuous,
          uni-directional, and homogenous. Its metrics are standardized, its direction is
          irreversible, and it has no breaks, folds, holes, wrinkles, or reworkings. But in the
          humanities time is frequently understood <emph>and represented</emph> as discontinuous,
          multi-directional, and variable. Temporal dimensions of humanities artifacts are often
          expressed in relational terms – before such and such happened, or after a significant
          event. Retrospection and anticipation factor heavily in humanistic works, and the models
          of temporality that arise from historical and literary documents include multiple
          viewpoints.</p>
            <p>The temporal modeling project Bethany Nowviskie and I designed almost ten years ago made
          use of these basic insights in order to create a graphical application that was the
          working proof of a concept. We were intent on demonstrating that a graphical model could
          be created intuitively as an interpretation and then used to generate structured data as a
          result. Inverting the sequence of intellectual events was a radical move for digital
          humanities, especially at the time, suggesting that graphical knowledge could be primary,
          leading an interpretation, rather than always and only functioning to display what was
          already known (or assumed to be known). We wanted to demonstrate that visual spaces could
          be a primary site of intellectual work. Of course, that added yet another level of
          unfamiliarity to our already complex project – and many even in our immediate community
          were unsettled by elastic or stretchy timelines, multiple points of view from within the
          system, or other novel seeming conventions meant to serve for interpretation of literary
          and historical artifacts.</p>
            <p>Briefly summarized, the original Temporal Modelling project aimed at creating a set of
          conceptual primitives for the modeling of temporal relations. These included graphical
          expressions meant to meet the needs of multiple points of view, reworking events according
          to a changed position within a temporal sequence, and a set of what we called inflections.
          Inflections, a kind of legend for marking points, intervals, or events (our basic units)
          with a quality or attribute, were divided into semantic and syntactic types. Semantic
          inflections were given their characteristics independently, as entities, and the
          vocabulary of attributes included degrees of intensity and other qualities. Syntactic
          inflections were characterized as relational, marking the effect of one event, point, or
          interval or another.</p>
            <p>Methods for graphing the elastic or <soCalled>rubber-sheet</soCalled> timelines meant to show the subjective
          variations in temporality can be derived from catastrophe theory, chaos diagrams, and the
          visualizations of stochastic and complex systems. <figure xml:id="figure07">
             <head>Models of events as temporal folds along a line of crisis. The
                first is a simple fold, showing an event as a combination of stresses warping a plane.
                An upper branch of consequences peels off towards an abrupt termination while the
                lower branch curve back to allow a retrospective view of the event’s unfolding back
                onto an earlier moment. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Terminus event and critical response images.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
               </figure> These visualizations express the topological and systemic complexity necessary
          to model the number of variables (of coordinates, forces, and the changing relations of
          variables) present in the experience of events, and/or analysis of their representation in
          humanistic documents (e.g. novels, films, letters, etc.). Some of the features of our
          earlier design, such as the dynamic behaviors of syntactic relations, could not be
          expressed in a standard Cartesian coordinate system (such as the one on which XML output
          is generated), even though dynamic and performative syntactic relations can be made
          operational by using vectors or forces. <figure xml:id="figure08">
             <head>Two models of an event reaching a crisis with stress factors
                shown as vectors. The first shows the event as a fold, the second shows it as a
                vortex. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>     
                  <figDesc>Two charts showing an event reaching crisis.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
               </figure> But even standard coordinate systems, such as the conventions of perspectival
          drawing, allow for the interpretative quality temporal experience to be expressed more
          fully than is possible with standard timelines. A parallax view, in which prospective
          anticipation is gradually replaced with retrospective reassessment, can be generated with
          a slider that animates the dynamic transformation in the value, identity, and relation of
          temporal events. In such a view, temporal events expressed as a set of conditions, rather
          than givens. The slider indicates a point of view, a perspective from which the experience
          of temporality originates in an individual. <figure xml:id="figure09">
             <head>A linear model of parallax showing anticipation and
                retrospective assessment of an event. The <soCalled>event</soCalled> is the combination of the moods of
                the <soCalled>eye</soCalled> individual, indicated by the anticipatory arrow and then the retrospective
                view (lower arrow) across the bar and star that mark a moment and a duration in the
                temporal span. The event is warped in the retrospective view. The metric might be
                altered as an effect, though it is not in this depiction. The <soCalled>eye</soCalled> is a now-slider,
                as per the old temporal modeling design, and its position on the bottom line indicates
                the position of the observer within the course of even. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Figure 9 — Two linear charts showing anticipation and assessment of an event.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
               </figure> By breaking the relentlessly regular grid, the potential for graphing temporal
          modeling as a complex system of events is greatly enhanced. The relational, and
          co-dependent quality of temporal events finds its expression in these more sophisticated
          models</p>
            <p>Several fundamental principles can now guide these designs. These principles of
          non-continuous, non-homogenous, and multi-directional <emph>temporality</emph>, as well as
          the point of view parallax, refine the reductive crudeness of models linked to standard a
          priori metrics of uni-directional, continuous, homogenous <emph>time</emph>. In this
          refinement temporality is conceived according to the basic formulation mentioned above:
          time as a function of x (temporality= time <hi rend="superscript">(x)</hi>). In these formulations, x is any of the
          (theoretically infinite) variables that inflect the model (mood, events, influences,
          events, constraints, etc.). Because temporality is an act of form-making (constructivist),
          not an act of expressing pre-existing or a priori phenomena (realism), the sequence of
          intellectual events in this formulation insists on temporality (and, likewise, spatiality
          as the result of constitutive relations among temporal and spatial phenomena. The full
          realization of this approach requires a multi-dimensional, complex, model of space and
          time and imaginative realizations as graphical expression.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure10">
               <head>In the first image, anxiety (measured subjectively but charted on
                  a standard metric) is charted against time, also depicted with standard intervals. The
                  change from one state to another (changes in degrees of anxiety) is shown in a
                  continuous line. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc>A chart showing anxiety over time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure11">
               <head>The difference between one state and the next is used to generate
                  a graphical form that is expresses the changes from one moment to another. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc>A chart showing anxiety intensity over time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure11.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure12">
               <head/>
               <figDesc>A chart showing percieved anxiety over perceived time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure13">
               <head>The differences between states are projected onto the
                  anxiety and time axes to create a metric that is the effect of perception, rather than
                  an a priri given. By rotating the angles that marked changes of levels of anxiety into a
                  position parallel to the time line, the metrics can be changed as a projection of these
                  lines (whose lengths were generated by a combination of duration and change of intensity
                  of anxiety) onto the temporal axis, thus moving from a <soCalled>perceived</soCalled> time to a <soCalled>projected</soCalled>
                  time. The result is a set of transformations from an uninflected, supposedly observer
                  independent <soCalled>time</soCalled> and <soCalled>anxiety</soCalled> to one created as an effect of the experience of time
                  on its expression. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
               <figDesc> A chart showing perceived anxiety over projected time.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure13.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Space as Spatiality</head>
            <p>The discussion of space corresponds exactly to that of time, and the distinctions between
          the conception of space as an a priori given and that of space as relationally constituted
          marks the same philosophical division of approaches as those that are used in charting or
          understanding time and temporality. Likewise, spatiality is to be understood as space as a
          function of x (spatiality= space <hi rend="superscript">(x)</hi>).<note>I first understood this notion when I read
            Sigfried Giedion's <title rend="italic">Space Time and Architecture</title> about thirty
            years ago. His arguments about structure as space-making left a deep
          impression.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To give graphical expression to these ideas requires using non-standard metrics,
          intuitive and subjective principles of design. They are meant as provocations to the
          larger project of creating more systematic renderings of humanistic phenomena, introducing
          basic transformations of the graphical fields we created for time lines into mapping and
          GIS applications. Precedents for such renderings can be found–e.g. Francis Galton’s
          rendering of space as a function of travel time. Galton’s problem, formulated in the mid
          19th century, takes into account that most statistical phenomena are observer-dependent
          and situated, and can’t be separated from the various dependencies that bear upon the
          creation of data. Galton, in other words, recognized that in many circumstances, data were
          capta. The statistical description of phenomena depend upon the observer’s circumstances.
          A more recent demonstration of these principles is a map designed by Tom Carden. His
          dynamic interface redraws the London Underground map as function of time of travel from
          any selected station to any other station.<note>See:<ptr target="#carden"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Subjective parameters are even more difficult to inscribe, since they cannot, by
          definition, be based on simple consensual standards. We can easily understand these
          distortions– space as a result of travel time. But how could we visualize the spatial
          distortions introduced by variables such as fearfulness, anxiety, anticipation,
          distraction, or dalliance and thus render space as <emph>spatiality, space as a factor of
            x</emph>? Some variable is always in play in the experience of space as well as its
          representation, so space is also always constructed according to a specific agenda and a
          situated experience etc. While this is the common experience of the phenomenal world,
          representations of spatiality have lagged behind, dominated by the navigational or
          descriptive systems of standard mapping whose conventions are well known and recognized,
          and which partake of and impose the dominant realist model.</p>
            <p>In proposing a new model for humanities’ work, I am suggesting that the subjective
          display of humanistic phenomena can be applied across the domains with which we are
          concerned at at least four basic levels of interpretation or knowledge production.</p>
            <p>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>Modelling phenomenological experience in the making of
              humanities (data as capta, primary modeling, the representation of temporal and
              spatial experience);</item>
                  <item>Modeling relations among humanities documents i.e. discourse fields (a different
              metric is needed to understand dates on diplomatic documents in the spring of 1944
              than one needed to constitute understanding of those dated to the same period of the
              spring of 1950 etc.);</item>
                  <item>Modeling the representations of temporality and spatiality that are in humanities
              documents (narrative is the most obvious);</item>
                  <item>Modeling the interpretation of any of the above (depicting or graphing the
              performative quality of interpretation).</item>
               </list> Let me describe a concrete
          example and see how it can be understood across these four different models. Take the
          first instance, the modeling of a phenomenon. Three people are waiting for a bus, how long
          does it take? One is late for work and anxious, one is in desperate need of a bathroom,
          and the other does not want to go to the afterschool program. How can the variations in
          perception be expressed? Recent experiments on the way time is understood in relation to
          different circumstances and tasks have made this experiential variable apparent to
          psychologists. So, the initial graphical expression of the humanistic phenomenon requires
          a variable metric, an elastic timeline, even a field that might fold or break under
          extreme circumstances.</p>
            <p>When we shift from modeling experience to find graphical expressions for the
          representation of experience, the complexity of the problem increases. The modeling of
          time in documents, in relation to the duration of the documents (time of telling) and the
          experiences they recount (the time of the told) as well as the relations among these and
          possible external temporal references, forms a subset of linguistic and narrative
          analyses. The graphical forms to represent these are generally inadequate to the
          complexity of the textual or visual (and/or filmic and audio) documents.</p>
            <p>Modelling the temporal relations among documents about temporal experience (imagine
          letters, emails, text messages, or diary entries from these various bus riders, only some
          of which is date stamped), gives rise to yet further ambiguities and complexities. A
          letter sent that was delayed, email re-routed, messages held in suspense on a server will
          change the temporal effect. For instance, letters or emails arranging family events and
          travels over the holidays contain many temporal values that are contingent on each other
          and often in constant flux as plans are being made. The temporal sequence and the date
          stamps are not one and the same, a temporal relation of the exchanges might include
          messages that cross in mid-stream, and whose temporal sequence does not match the simple
          alignment with dates on a line.</p>
            <p>Plans change, travel times are altered, arrivals and departures re-arranged, moods shift,
          frustrations intensify, disappointments or unexpected surprises arise in relation to the
          sequence of events. An email recounting something that occurred <soCalled>yesterday</soCalled> in relation to
          a date stamp might also contain more vaguely identified <soCalled>earlier</soCalled> and <soCalled>before</soCalled> statements
          that put events into a relative sequence without explicitly identifying when these
          occurred. As the telling unfolds, these relations may change in the writer’s expression
          and perception, so that the textual description of a recollected event continues to shift
          its place in the temporal order. Who was supposed to do what when and who was depending on
          which order of events? By the time holiday travels and expectations are sorted out, each
          family member has a very distinct view of what happened when and how the sequence of lived
          events occurred and where. Was the bus station large or small, far or near to any other
          spot in the itinerary, or located in a familiar landscape. How was the space experienced
          as a function of time spent in it? These constructions of temporality and spatiality from
          within documents, across documents or a discourse field, and of phenomena are all created
          with time/space as functions of interpretation. The act of interpreting a series of
          documents creates its own temporality, that of the production of a reading, that is not
          the same as the telling or the told within the documents, but an independent phenomenon.
          An interpretation has its own temporality ad spatiality.</p>
            <p>We can construct a concrete example of spatiality that parallels this example of
          temporality, and also depends on temporal models. For instance, imagine an open stretch of
          beach, relatively unconstrained and unconstructed. When a sailing ship is washed up at a
          certain point on the beach, not only that point, but the space around it, becomes
          transformed. The presence of the wreck creates a huge impact, and the space almost
          palpably bends, compresses, expands, and warps around it, with waves of resonance rippling
          outward from that point. <figure xml:id="figure14">
             <head>In this example, a geographical space (a stretch of beach) is
                affected by a change in the state or circumstance. First we see the space mapped
                according to a regular Cartesian coordinate system. Then the grid is inflected by the
                arrival of a beached ship, around which the beach bends because the sense of each spot
                as relative equal is distorted by the attention that the ship commands. The space
                acquires one inflection after another as graffiti marks the ship, a chain link fence
                goes up with a police notice, footprints create a pattern in the sand, pathways for
                observation re-route pedestrian traffic etc. The <soCalled>space</soCalled> of the beach is transformed
                physically and in terms of attention getting and effect so that it is no longer a set
                of equal and neutral elements of a rational spatial system, but one that must be
                expressed with graphical distortions that show these inflections. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Four charts showing change in state or circumstance.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure14.jpg"/>
               </figure> Police barriers are set up and suddenly make that bit of beach into a highly
          charged site. Additional fences create zones of potential transgression and prohibition,
          lines in the literal sand that when crossed by graffiti artists and taggers, vandals and
          looters, introduce a whole set of spatial relations governed by different rules and
          expectations. The space of and around the shipwreck becomes a hot point, a zone, an arena
          of complex spatial negotiations and marked coordinates, each differently charged depending
          on the players and circumstances (law enforcement, owners, passersby, taggers at night, in
          early morning, broad daylight etc.). Even more than the open, indeterminate space of the
          beach, this spot becomes an area of shifting values and interpretation. Space, always
          marked, has become explicitly so, and the spatial relations demarcate regions of authority
          and behavior whose dimensions are not in strict correspondence to physical space. The same
          amount of physical space half a mile down the beach has none (or few) of these dimensions.
          Can we still locate the wreck on a Cartesian grid available through any GPS system? Of
          course, the two approaches, constructivist and realist, don’t cancel each other out. But
          they are not equivalent. The GPS standards locate the spot within those coordinates, but
          say nothing about the constituted space as a phenomenon created by these many variables.
          We have many adequate models for the first mode of visualization, but very few for the
          constructivist approach grounded in an interpretative mode of experience.</p>
            <p>Take another example, a map tracing a journey between London and Prague in the
            1810s.<note>Alternate example was a street map of Tehran on which points are plotted to
            show a disturbance in progress. Let the points expand to register degrees of intensity
            of impact, disruption of normal function, fear and anger, violence. That would be the
            registration of subjective data on a conventional map. Now change the map, distort its
            proportions so that it becomes a terrain shaped by fear, by obstacles, by disruptions
            and confusions.</note>; How does the space change dimensions to reflect hazard, delays,
          dalliances, terrain changes, interruptions of war and political strife, danger, weather,
          or illness? A legend or set of labels or markings could indicate these inflections of the
          space simply by putting symbols on a map. That would be the registration of
            <emph>subjective data</emph> on a conventional map. But mapping conventions don’t morph
          the landscape to accommodate the effects of fear, anger, or violence. Now change the map,
          distort its proportions so that it becomes a terrain shaped by fear, by obstacles, by
          disruptions and confusions. <figure xml:id="figure15">
             <head>Geographical terrain warped by the experience of travel so that
                the standard distances are distorted by the effects of difficulty, fear, delays, and
                other factors. The map shows the landscape as an effect of experience rather than a
                standard ground on which to depict experience. In the second instance, the points on
                the metric grid are warped by the impact of an event, or events, that have simply
                reordered the standard grid. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Geographical terrain and experienced travel image.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure15.jpg"/>
               </figure> That is a subjective expression. The two approaches are radically
          different. In the second instance, space is an effect of spatial relations, spatiality is
          expressed as a factor of disturbance, and it might be expressed as a factor of many
          variables occurring across a temporal extension (fear, anxiety, confusion, anger,
          disorientation).</p>
            <p>The challenge of representing large corpora of texts and immense archives also requires
          attention, in part because the conventions of wayfinding and navigation that are part of
          print media and its institutional structures are not yet reworked in a digital environment
          meant to address the shifts in scale and experience brought on by new media. On top of the
          challenge of representing repositories and their use, we can point to another challenge
          –that of giving graphical expression to interpretations built on and out of documents, or
          collections of documents. These present different challenges than the humanistic
          interpretation of temporal, spatial, and informational phenomena, but depend upon the
          basic recognition that subjective and co-dependent principles must govern their design.
          The conventional graphical features of texts that inscribe interpretation include all of
          the features of layout and format, typography, and design that organize and structure its
          presentation on the page, screen, or other surface or medium. The features that inscribe
          interpretation in archives are those that embody or express the imprint of the point of
          view according to which the archive takes shape. These include classification systems,
          nomenclature, hierarchies and categories of organization and ordering, systems of search
          and access, information architecture, the format of storage and display, and any other
          feature of the archive that is intrinsic to the forms of its expression. While all of
          these are expressions of arguments, and thus interpretations, they do not show or model
          interpretation on the fly as a constitutive act of reading, relating, connecting, and
          sense making. In sum, these acts of interpretation make use of the format features of
          graphical presentation as well as responding to and thus producing the <soCalled>content</soCalled> of these
          artifacts. Some combination of user-centered but co-dependent systems analysis and
          critical reading practices as performative acts would have to underpin such graphical
          visualizations. But that is also work for another time.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>My argument is a polemical call to humanists to think differently about the graphical
          expressions in use in digital environments. A fundamental prejudice, I suggest, is
          introduced by conceiving of data within any humanistic interpretative frame on a
          conventional, uncritical, statistical basis. Few social scientists would proceed this way,
          and the abandonment of interpretation in favor of a naïve approach to statistical
          certainly skews the game from the outset in favor of a belief that <term>data</term> is
          intrinsically quantitative — self-evident, value neutral, and
          observer-independent. This belief excludes the possibilities of conceiving data as
          qualitative, co-dependently constituted — in other words, of recognizing
            <emph>that all data is capta</emph>.</p>
            <p>Again, to reiterate, I am not suggesting that we simply introduce a quantitative analysis
          of qualitative experience into our data sets. I am suggesting that we rethink the
          foundation of the way <term>data</term> are conceived as <term>capta</term> by shifting
          its terms from certainty to ambiguity and find graphical means of expressing
          interpretative complexity. In some circumstances (the example of the bar chart given
          earlier that was displaying information about gender, nations, and populations) ambiguity
          merely requires a higher order level of complexity in the model, so that apparent
          <soCalled>certainties</soCalled> are qualified by variables and nuances that can be specified in mathematical
          terms. But the idea of capta as fundamentally co-dependent, constituted relationally,
          between observer and observed phenomena, is fundamentally different from the concept of
          data created as an observer-independent phenomena. That realization has to be at the heart
          of humanistic approaches to the graphical display of interpretative phenomena, of
          interpreted artifacts and the acts of interpretation themselves. Because interpretation is
          performative, bringing objects into view through a reading or other act of intervention,
          it forecloses the possibility that autonomous objects or phenomena exist within the
          horizon of human experience. Phenomena of human experience are constituted as
          interpretative acts.</p>
            <p>The natural world and its cultural corollary exist, but the humanistic concept of
          knowledge depends upon the interplay between a situated and circumstantial viewer and the
          objects or experiences under examination and interpretation. That is the basic definition
          of humanistic knowledge, and its graphical display must be specific to this definition in
          its very foundational principles. The challenge is enormous, but essential, if the
          humanistic worldview, grounded in the recognition of the interpretative nature of
          knowledge, is to be part of the graphical expressions that come into play in the digital
          environment. If we don’t engage with this challenge, we give the game away in advance,
          ceding the territory of interpretation to the ruling authority of certainty established on
          the false claims of observer-independent objectivity in the <soCalled>visual display of
          quantitative information.</soCalled>
               <note>This citation is of course the title of Edward Tufte's
            first volume.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I’ll finish with one more concrete example of the shift from observer-independent realism
          to co-dependent constructivism. Snow’s justly famous chart of deaths from cholera allowed
          city officials to track the source of the epidemic to a single water pump. <figure xml:id="figure16">
             <head>Dr. John Snow’s famous chart tracing the source of an epidemic
                using graphical methods that plotted frequency of outbreaks and geographical location.
                But each outbreak was an individual, and their degrees of vulnerability, impact of
                their illness, effect on the family and loved ones, was specific and particular in
                ways that a single dot cannot express. Seen from the point of view of an individual
                participant in these tragic events, some of these individuals loom much larger than
                others when depicted from within the gaze of someone actually seeing them occur.
                Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Dr. John Snow's chart tracing the source of an epidemic.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure16.jpg"/>
               </figure> The distribution of dots on the street map makes evident the role of the pump by
          the way they cluster. A useful map, crucial to analysis, its clarity and succinctness
          served an important purpose. It was sufficient to that purpose, adequate, but we could
          revisit that map and use it to express other factors. Who are those dots? Each individual
          had a profile, age, size, health, economic potential, family and social roles. In short,
          each dot represents a life, and none of these are identical. Many demographic features
          could be layered into this map to create a more complex statistical view of the epidemic.
          That is neither subjective data nor a subjective display. But what if we take the rate of
          deaths, their frequency, and chart that on a temporal axis inflected by increasing panic.
          Then give a graphical expression to the shape of the terrain, that urban streetscape, as
          it is redrawn to express the emotional landscape. Then imagine drawing this same
          streetscape from the point of view of a mother of six young children, a recent widow, a
          small child, or an elderly man whose son has just died. 
               <figure xml:id="figure17">
                  <head>Snow's chart altered. Graphic credit Xárene Eskandar.</head>
                  <figDesc>Snow's chart altered.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000091/resources/images/figure17.jpg"/>
               </figure>
          These latter are all instances of the graphical expression of humanistic interpretation. They are as different from the
          visual display of quantitative information as a close reading of a poem is from the chart
          of an eye tracker following movements across a printed page. They are fundamentally
          different in character and in their basic assumptions about the role of graphical
          expression as an aspect of knowledge production. We have a very long way to go in creating
          graphical expressions that serve humanistic interpretation, but I hope I have suggested
          some of the premises on which this work might begin.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
        <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->

            <bibl xml:id="anderson2008" label="Anderson 2008" key="anderson2008">
               <author>Anderson, Margo</author>. <title rend="quotes">The Census, Audiences, and Publics</title>, Presidential Address, <title rend="italic">Social Science History</title> 32:1, Spring 2008, 1-18.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2007" label="Anderson 2007" key="anderson2007a">
               <author>Anderson, Margo.</author> 
               <title rend="quotes">Quantitative History</title>, <title rend="italic">The Sage Handbook of
            Social Science Methodology</title>, ed. William Outwaite and Stephen Turner, London:
          Sage Publications, 2007, 246-63.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="carden" label="Carden" key="carden">
               <author>Carden, Tom</author>. <title rend="italic">Travel Time Tube Map</title> 
               <ref target="http://www.tom-carden.co.uk/p5/tube_map_travel_times/applet/">http://www.tom-carden.co.uk/p5/tube_map_travel_times/applet/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="griethe2006"
                  label="Griethe &amp; Schumann 2006"
                  key="griethe2006">
               <author>Griethe, Henning
            and Heidrun Schumann</author>. <title rend="quotes">Visualizing Uncertainty for Improved
            Decision Making</title>, <title rend="italic">SimVis</title> 2006, 143-156.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jones2008" label="Jones et. al 2008" key="jones2008">
               <author>Jones, Josh, Remco Chang, Thomas
            Butkiewicz and William Ribarsky</author>. <title rend="quotes">Visualizing uncertainty
            for geographical information in the terrorism database</title>, <title rend="italic">SPIE Security
            Symposium</title>, 2008. <ref target="dvg.uncc.edu/publications/index.html">
            dvg.uncc.edu/publications/index.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knorr1990"
                  label="Knorr-Cetina &amp; Amann 1990"
                  key="knorr1990">
               <author>Knorr-Centina,
            Karin and Klaus Amann</author>. <title rend="quotes">Image Dissection in Natural
            Scientific Inquiry</title>, <title rend="italic">Science, Technology, and Human Values</title>, 15: 1990, 259.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lochlann2010" label="Lochlann 2010" key="lochlann2010">
               <author>Lochlann, Jain</author>.<title rend="quotes"> Morality Effect: Counting the Dead in the Cancer Trail</title>,<title rend="italic"> Public Culture.</title>
               <date> 2010</date>, 89-117.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour1986" label="Latour 1986" key="latour1986">
               <author>Latour, Bruno</author>. <title rend="quotes">Visualization and Cognition: Drawing Things Together</title>, <title rend="italic">Knowledge and Society</title>, 6: 1986, 1-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lynch1988" label="Lynch &amp; Woolgan 1988" key="lynch1988">
               <author>Lynch, Michael, and
            Steve Woolgar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Sociological Orientations to
            Representational Practice in Science</title>, <title rend="italic">Human
            Studies</title>, 11: 1988, 99-116.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maceachren2005"
                  label="MacEachren et. al 2005"
                  key="maceachren2005">
               <author>MacEachren, Alan M.,
            Anthony Robinson, Susan Hopper, Steven Gardner, Robert Murray, Mark Gahegan and
            Elisabeth Hetzler</author>. <title rend="quotes">Visualizing Geospatial Information
            Uncertainty: What We Know and What We Need to Know</title>, <title rend="italic">
            Cartography and Geographic Information Science</title>, Vol. 32, No. 3: 2005, 139-160.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="porter1995" label="Porter 1995" key="porter1995">
               <author>Porter, Ted</author>. <title rend="italic">Trust in Numbers: The Pursuit of Objectivity</title>, Princeton, NJ:
          Princeton University Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shneiderman2005"
                  label="Shneiderman &amp; Pang 2005"
                  key="shneiderman2005">
               <author>Shneiderman,
            Ben and Alex Pang</author>. <title rend="italic">Visualizing Uncertainty: Computer
            Science Perspective</title>, National Academy of Sciences Workshop, Washington, DC:
            March 3-4, 2005. <ref target="http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/pubs/presentations/NAS-VisUncertainty6_files/frame.htm">http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/pubs/presenations/NASVisUncertainty6_files/frame.htm</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skeels2008" label="Skeels et. al 2008" key="skeels2008">
               <author>Skeels, Meredith, Bongshin Lee,
            Greg Smith and George Robertson</author>. <title rend="quotes">Revealing Uncertainty for
            Information Visualization</title>, Microsoft Publications, 2008. <ref target="http://research.microsoft.com/pubs/64267/avi2008-uncertainty.pdf">http://research.microsoft.com/pubs/64267/avi2008-uncertainty.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wells2008" label="Wells 2008" key="wells2008">
               <author>Wells, Audrey Elizabeth</author>. <title rend="italic">Virtual Reconstruction of a Seventeenth Century Portuguese Nau</title>, Master's Thesis, Texas &amp;M University, Visualization Sciences, 2008. <ref target="repository.tamu.edu/bitstream/handle/1969.1/86071/Wells.pdf">repository.tamu.edu/bitstream/handle/1969.1/86071/Wells.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>

         </listBibl>

      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
