<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Productive Unease of 21st-century Digital Scholarship</title>
            <author>Julia Flanders</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Julia <dhq:family>Flanders</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Brown University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Julia Flanders is the Director of the Brown University <ref
                        target="http://www.wwp.brown.edu">Women Writers Project</ref>, and has
                     served as the Chair of the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding
                        Initiative</ref> and the President of the <ref target="http://www.ach.org"
                        >Association for Computers and the Humanities</ref>. Her research focuses on
                     the use of text encoding as a form of scholarly digital text
                     representation.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000055</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-06-13" who="JF">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Despite prevailingly progressive narratives surrounding the impact of digital
               technology on modern academic culture, the field of digital humanities is
               characterized at a deeper level by a more critical engagement with technology. This
               engagement, which I characterize as a kind of <soCalled>productive unease</soCalled>, is focused around issues of representation, medium,
               and structures of scholarly communication. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Beyond the inexorable logic of abundance</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Technological Progressivism</head>
            <p>The narratives that surround technology tend, understandably, to be progressive.
               Moore’s law, which states that the complexity and hence the processing power of
               computer chips is doubling every couple of years, and Kryder’s law, which says
               something similar about disk capacity, have visible and in some cases stunning
               illustrations in the world around us. We see evidence in products such as palmtop
               devices that have thousands of times the computing power and storage capacity of
               ENIAC, the first stored-program electronic computer; personal disk storage is now
               purchasable almost by the terabyte, and processor speed is now measured by the
               gigahertz; both of these statements will have dated by the time this article is
               published. We also see the effects of these developments in processes whose
               increasing speed produces subtle luxuries that creep into our lives, almost without
               our taking particular notice: for example, color screens for computers,
               three-dimensional icons, the clever animation behaviors that are as ubiquitous (and
               as useful) as small plastic children’s toys. Or, more substantively: the fact that
               you can now store and edit digital video footage on your laptop, or view streaming
               movies on a device you can put in your pocket. These kinds of change produce easy
               metrics for success and a correspondingly easy sense of progress.</p>
            <p>Digital humanities scholarship to a large degree shares this sense of progress. We
               see, first of all, simple infrastructural developments that change the social
               location of computers and bring them into our sphere of activity. The ubiquity of
               computing resources means that it’s no longer remarkable for humanities scholars to
               work with computers: one doesn’t have to get a special account from Central Computing
               or explain why one needs it; it’s not considered quaint or cute or bizarre. Certain
               efficiencies and conveniences are now commonplace; it has become expected that things
               scholars want to read or learn will be more or less easily available from anywhere,
               at any hour, electronically. And there are indirect effects as well: all of these
               changes produce the conditions for consumer-level products like electronic book
               readers, hand-held browsing devices, social software like Flickr and YouTube. These
               products provide extended horizons of usage, and produce a generation of students
               (and eventually future scholars) for whom computers mean something completely
               different: for whom they are not a specialized tool but part of the tissue of the
               world.</p>
            <p>The effects of these developments are all around us in the emerging shape of digital
               scholarly tools and research materials. At a basic level, the increased power of
               modern computers is almost literally what makes it possible to use them effectively
               for humanities research. In early computer systems, scarcity of storage space
               dictated extremely frugal methods of representing characters: because it only uses 7
               bits of information to represent each character, ASCII can represent only 128
               characters, of which only 95 are actually printable characters. This limited the
               effective alphabet to upper- and lower-case roman letters, Arabic numerals, and
               common punctuation marks, with no accented characters or characters from non-roman
               alphabets. The advent of Unicode in the 1990s is a direct outcome of the increase in
               storage space, allowing the representation of nearly all human writing systems and
               freeing digital scholarship on texts from early artificial limitations.</p>
            <p>This same comparative abundance of space has also opened up the whole domain of image
               processing, giving us another information vector to use for research, leading to work
               in which the graphical meaning of text can be explored alongside its linguistic
               meaning. and allowing us also to explore the interpenetration of image-based and
               text-based approaches. To appropriate a term Jerome McGann suggested in his opening
               keynote to the conference at which this paper was originally presented, there is a
               dialectical process opening up here as well: the mutual pressure of image and text,
               of alphabetic and figural modes of representing meaning, is now blossoming into an
               extremely lively field of study.</p>
            <p>The rhetoric of abundance which has characterized descriptions of digital resource
               development for the past decade or more has suggested several significant shifts of
               emphasis in how we think about the creation of collections and of canons. It is now
               easier, in some contexts, to digitize an entire library collection than to pick
               through and choose what should be included and what should not: in other words,
               storage is cheaper than decision-making. The result is that the rare, the
               lesser-known, the overlooked, the neglected, and the downright excluded are now
               likely to make their way into digital library collections, even if only by accident.
               In addition, the design of digital collections now frequently emphasizes precisely
               the recovery of what has been lost, the exposure of what has been inaccessible.
               Projects like the Women Writers Project, or Early English Books Online, or any one of
               countless digital projects now under way at universities across the country, focus on
               providing access to materials that would otherwise be invisible to researchers. This
               access proceeds on two fronts: first, by digitizing them so that they can be read
               without visiting the specific archive where they are held, but also, more
               importantly, by aggregating them and making them discoverable, by heaping them up
               into noticeable piles. The result is that minority literatures, non-canonical
               literary works, and the records of what goes on in (what appeared earlier to be) the
               odd corners of the universe are all given a new kind of prominence and parity with
               their more illustrious and familiar cousins.</p>
            <p>Invisibly, under the hood (so to speak), increased speed and computing power has also
               given us tools that finally propel us over the threshold of possibility: humanities
               novices are becoming able to participate meaningfully in what would formerly have
               appeared to be impossibly technical projects. Examples include tools for XML text
               encoding that are good enough, and fast enough, that anyone can learn to use them
               within ten minutes; or, similarly, tools for image manipulation that put real power
               in a novice’s hands. Even improvements in things like compression algorithms, as
               Morris Eaves observes in his contribution to this issue, have a huge impact on the
               accuracy and effectiveness of digital image representation.</p>
            <p>But despite the fact that these are tangible improvements, there is also an important
               sense in which their progressive momentum is not, ultimately, what is characteristic
               of the digital humanities as a field. John Unsworth, in an article entitled <title
                  rend="quotes">What is Humanities Computing and What is Not?</title> makes a point
               of noting the difference between using a computer for any of its many practical
               purposes, and using the computer as a scholarly tool: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2002">...one of the many things you can do
                     with computers is something that I would call humanities computing, in which
                     the computer is used as tool for modeling humanities data and our understanding
                     of it, and that activity is entirely distinct from using the computer when it
                     models the typewriter, or the telephone, or the phonograph, or any of the many
                     other things it can be.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#unsworth2002"/>
               </cit> Unlike its comparatively recent ability to model the telephone or the
               phonograph, the computer’s role as a tool for modeling humanities data is of long
               standing — arguably extending back to Father Roberto Busa’s 1945 <title rend="italic"
                  >Index Thomisticus</title> and certainly including early tools and methods
               including concordancing, text analysis, and text markup languages. Although our
               ability to work with these models has without doubt been made easier by the advent of
               faster, more seamless tools, the complexity and interest of the models themselves has
               been affected little if at all. We have only to consider as an example Willard
               McCarty’s remarkable project of modeling mutability in his <title rend="italic"
                  >Analytical Onomasticon to the <title rend="none">Metamorphoses</title> of
                  Ovid</title>, a project of great complexity and nuance which was undertaken almost
               entirely through markup and without the aid of any specialized tools for model
               construction, visualization, or data manipulation. The nature of the models being
               created in the digital humanities may be changing with time, but not as a function of
               speed or power, but rather as a result of changes in emphasis or theoretical
               concern.</p>
            <p>In this respect, the digital humanities domain reflects the non-progressiveness of
               the humanities disciplines more generally, and also reveals what may be a fundamental
               tension at its heart. If the rhetoric at the heart of the <q>digital</q> side of
                  <q>digital humanities</q> is strongly informed by a narrative of technological
               progress, the <q>humanities</q> side has equally strong roots in a humanities
               sensibility which both resists a cumulative idea of progress (one new thing building
               on another) and yearns for a progressive agenda (doing better all the time). The
               theoretical and methodological shifts that constitute disciplinary change in the
               humanities, when viewed in retrospect, do not appear clearly progressive in the way
               that sequences of scientific discoveries do, though they do appear developmental:
               they are an ongoing attempt to understand human culture, from the changing
               perspective of the culture itself. But the resilience of fundamental habits and
               assumptions concerning literary value, scholarly method, and academic standards
               suggests that the humanities are in fact governed by a self-healing ideology that
               persists comparatively unchanged.</p>
            <p>In charting the intellectual aspirations of the digital humanities, it is tempting to
               elide the difference between this sense of ongoing debate and the gains in size and
               speed that come from the technological domain. But the intervention made by digital
               technology when it truly engages with humanities disciplines is something apart from
               both the simple progressivism of technology and the canonical resilience of the
               traditional humanities. In the same article I quoted from earlier, John Unsworth
               characterized humanities computing as follows:</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2002">[h]umanities computing is a practice of
                  representation, a form of modeling or [...] mimicry. It is[...] a way of reasoning
                  and a set of ontological commitments, and its representational practice is shaped
                  by the need for efficient computation on the one hand, and for human communication
                  on the other.</quote>
               <ptr target="#unsworth2002"/>
            </cit>
            <p>In other words, it is neither about discovery of new knowledge nor about the solidity
               of what is already known: it is rather about modeling that knowledge and even in some
               cases about modeling the modeling process. It is an inquiry into how we know things
               and how we present them to ourselves for study, realized through a variety of tools
               which make the consequences of that inquiry palpable. This is why, when humanities
               practitioners learn a technology like text encoding, they feel both a frisson of
               recognition — of a process that is familiar, that expresses familiar ideas — and also
               the shock of the new: the requirement that one distance oneself from one’s own
               representational strategies and turn them about in one’s hands like a complex and
               alien bauble. As Unsworth puts it further along,</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2002">Humanities computing, as a practice of
                  knowledge representation, grapples with this realization that its representations
                  are surrogates in a very self-conscious way, more self-conscious, I would say,
                  than we generally are in the humanities when we <q>represent</q> the objects of
                  our attention in essays, books, and lectures.</quote>
               <ptr target="#unsworth2002"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Representational technologies like XML, or databases, or digital visualization tools
               appear to stand apart from the humanities research activities they support, even
               while they encapsulate and seek to do justice to the assumptions and methods of those
               activities. Humanities scholarship has historically understood this separateness as
               indicating an ancillary role — that of the handmaiden, the good servant/poor master —
               in which humanities insight masters and subsumes what these technologies can offer.
               Technology implements what humanities insight projects as a research trajectory. But
               in fact the relationship is potentially more complex: by expressing <q>human
                  communication</q> in the formal language needed for what Unsworth calls <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#unsworth2002">efficient computation,</quote> these representational
               technologies attempt to restate those methods in terms which are not identical to,
               not embedded in the humanities discourse. They effect a distancing, a translation
               which, like any translation or transmediation, provides a view into (and requires an
               understanding of) the deep discursive structures of the original expression.</p>
            <p>Unsworth is careful to observe that not all digital humanities activities — in fact,
               very few — really constitute this kind of intervention, or count as <q>humanities
                  computing</q> according to his strict definition. The act of publishing digital
               content, of making an uncritical digital facsimile of a physical artifact, does not
               produce this effect of translation or the resulting potential for insight. I would
               argue that we can recognize humanities computing in his sense of the term, precisely
               by a kind of productive unease that results from the encounter and from its product.
               This unease registers for the humanities scholar as a sense of friction between
               familiar mental habits and the affordances of the tool, but it is ideally a
               provocative friction, an irritation that prompts further thought and engagement. In
               the nature of things — systems and people being imperfect — it might produce a
               suspicion that the tool in question is maladapted for use in humanities research. In
               some cases that may be true, and in some cases that may be a self-defensive response
               which deserves further probing. But where that sense of friction is absent — where a
               digital object sits blandly and unobjectionably before us, putting up no resistance
               and posing no questions for us — humanities computing, in the meaningful sense, is
               also absent. Humanists may learn from the content of such objects, treated as
               research materials, as they always have. These objects will serve as more or less
               effective surrogates for their physical originals and may produce efficiencies of
               access and other practical benefits of one sort or another. But they have no
               contribution to make to humanities scholarship: they make no intervention, they leave
               no intellectual mark.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Productive Unease</head>
            <p>Where, then, is this unease manifesting itself? and what useful insights and
               intellectual traction does digital humanities scholarship provide on the central
               problems of the humanities? Here are three areas where I would argue that interesting
               critical friction is being produced by work in digital humanities.</p>
            <div>
               <head>1. Digital scholarship is uneasy about the significance of medium.</head>
               <p>One almost immediate effect of the emergence of digital texts was to instigate a
                  discussion of medium: a discussion which raised the stakes and broadened the scope
                  of the discussion, which had previously been of concern primarily in scholarly
                  editing, in the tradition of D. F. McKenzie. The initial manifestations of this
                  discussion were expressed as anxiety about the unreliability of digital texts,
                  linking this quality to the medium itself rather than to social practices such as
                  peer review. As the Women Writers Project reported in summarizing its 1995 survey
                  of scholars, <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders1999">anxiety about the accuracy of
                     electronic texts was so acute that some respondents discussed it even in answer
                     to questions on other subjects, and it clearly represented the single largest
                     obstacle to general scholarly use of electronic texts.</quote> Early threads in
                  electronic discussion forums such as SEDIT-L also foregrounded this problem of
                  inaccuracy as a kind of worrisome dark side to the <soCalled>polymorphic, polysemic, protean</soCalled> qualities attributed to
                  digital texts in more optimistic analyses. The theme attests to an odd sense of
                  self-consciousness about how to make digital texts reliable — in other words, how
                  to transplant a familiar set of social practices into unfamiliar territory, as if
                  this might involve profoundly different processes from those which had been used
                  to produce reliable print texts.</p>
               <p>This anxiety looks dated in retrospect, but it has had a salutary effect: it has
                  produced an interest in understanding medium and its role in anchoring our textual
                  perceptions. Digital humanities scholarship now includes an awareness of the
                  representational significance of medium as a fundamental premise. This is not only
                  because the digital medium is seen as a kind of meta-medium in which other media
                  can be modeled or represented (which requires us to think about the special
                  characteristics of those other media, for modeling purposes), but also because the
                  digital medium itself is not representationally uniform. The kinds of sampling and
                  decomposition that seem at first blush like typically <q>digital</q> effects are
                  very different from the formalizing properties of text encoding or vector
                  graphics. </p>
               <p>The digital humanities world is in fact full of intensive and fruitful debate
                  about representation and medium. Jerome McGann’s sustained engagement with the
                  question of how structured text markup may fail or succeed at representing
                  literary texts — his account of the dialectical influence of different
                  representational modes and what we can learn by their insufficiencies — and the
                  responses and research this work has elicited from markup theorists, taken
                  together have provided a great deal of insight into how digital formats represent
                  textual and figural information. And this insight has in turn shed light backwards
                  (as it were) upon the traditional printed scholarly edition.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2. Digital scholarship is uneasy about the institutional structures of
                  scholarly communication.</head>
               <p>By its emergence through innately cross-disciplinary and cross-organizational (and
                  widely differing) formations, the digital humanities domain has helped to create a
                  critical self-consciousness about the role institutions play in establishing and
                  maintaining cultural habits that affect how humanities research is done. Alan Liu,
                  in a 2003 MLA presentation, asserted that <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2003">The
                     humanities should embrace the poiesis of IT for alternative ends — first of all
                     at the level of organizational imagination</quote> to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2003">reimagine the protocols of the work of
                        education</quote>
                     <ptr target="#liu2003" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#liu2003">Here I come to what I perceive to be one of
                     the frontiers of IT in the humanities. That is the far territory on which the
                     many, scattered humanities computing programs, centers, projects, and so on
                     that have used IT as a catalyst to reorganize the normal disciplinary work of
                     the humanities evolve from ad hoc organizational experiments into strategic
                     paradigms of interest to the profession as a whole. In general, we must
                     acknowledge, the profession of the humanities has been appallingly
                     unimaginative in regard to the organization of its own labor, simply taking it
                     for granted that its restructuring impulse toward <q>interdisciplinarity</q>
                     and <q>collaboration</q> can be managed within the same old divisional,
                     college, departmental, committee, and classroom arrangements supplemented by ad
                     hoc interdisciplinary arrangements.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#liu2003" loc="7"/>
               </cit>
               <p>Digital humanities projects, practices, and practitioners typically emerge out of
                  working relationships which by their nature raise questions about the politics of
                  work, and occupy a space that is naturally and productively critical of current
                  tenure and reward systems. These systems are still struggling to understand the
                  fundamentally collaborative and interdisciplinary work of digital humanities or
                  the new modes of scholarly communication it is engendering. </p>
               <p>Following almost inevitably from this unease about institutional and
                  organizational containers for professional identity is a related concern with
                  published expressions of professional identity and the question of how we evaluate
                  new forms of communication and scholarly work. In effect, digital scholarship
                  reveals a conundrum that has lain at the heart of humanities scholarship for
                  decades: how can we simultaneously encourage paradigm shifts and radical revisions
                  of our modes of analysis, and also know how to evaluate them once we have them
                  before us? Digital scholarship proceeds through collaborations and hybridizations
                  that challenge our notions of discipline — indeed, often that is the desired goal
                  — but evaluation and professional acknowledgement are typically provided through
                  conduits that are slower to adapt and may not necessarily view such a challenge as
                     <foreign>ipso facto</foreign> valuable. The MLA’s <title rend="quotes"
                     >Guidelines for Evaluating Work with Digital Media in the Modern
                     Languages</title> acknowledge this difficulty, marking the disciplinary changes
                  that are taking place and the uncertain position that <quote rend="inline"
                     source="#mla2002">traditional notions of scholarship</quote> occupy in relation to
                  emerging forms of academic work:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#mla2002">
                     <p>Digital media have created new opportunities for scholarship, teaching, and
                        service, as well as new venues for research, communication, and academic
                        community. Information technology is an integral part of the intellectual
                        environment for a growing number of humanities faculty members. Moreover,
                        digital media have expanded the scope of textual representation and analysis
                        to include, for example, image and sound. These innovations have
                        considerably broadened the notion of <q>text</q> and <q>textual studies,</q>
                        the traditional purview of modern language departments.</p>
                     <p>While the use of computers in the modern languages is not a new phenomenon,
                        the popular success of information networks like the World Wide Web, coupled
                        with the proliferation of advanced multimedia tools, has resulted in an
                        outpouring of critical publications, applied scholarship, and curricular
                        innovation. Humanists are not only adopting new technologies but are also
                        actively collaborating with technical experts in fields such as image
                        processing, document encoding, and information science. Academic work in
                        digital media should be evaluated in the light of these rapidly changing
                        institutional and professional contexts, and departments should recognize
                        that some traditional notions of scholarship, teaching, and service are
                        being redefined.</p>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#mla2002"/>
               </cit>
               <p>At the same time, the Guidelines suggest that there may be a necessary — and
                  fairly durable — interdisciplinarity in play here, which will always place work of
                  this kind in a procedurally awkward interdepartmental space. In their
                  recommendations they advise tenure and promotion committees to:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#mla2002">
                     <hi rend="bold">Seek Interdisciplinary Advice.</hi> If faculty members have
                     used technology to collaborate with colleagues from other disciplines on the
                     same campus or on different campuses, departments and institutions should seek
                     the assistance of experts in those other disciplines to assess and evaluate
                     such interdisciplinary work. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#mla2002"/>
               </cit>
               <p>If the future of digital scholarship may thus be (for some time at least) to
                  remain <q>other</q> to the standard disciplinary structures of the academy,
                  however, this should not be taken as a misfortune. The unease that is the theme of
                  this essay is productive in this case precisely because it makes us aware of
                  discipline as both a formative intellectual constraint, and a somewhat arbitrary
                  institutional reality. Acknowledging the arbitrariness is crucial because it
                  reminds us that change is possible and may be necessary. But acknowledging the
                  formative qualities of the constraint is equally crucial, because it reminds us
                  that we cannot simply posit a return to some pre-lapsarian, pre-disciplinary state
                  of unfettered intellectual free play. Digital scholarship works in relation to
                  established disciplines, even as it stands in some degree usefully apart from
                  them. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3. Digital scholarship is uneasy about the significance of representation in
                  forming models of the world.</head>
               <p>Jerome McGann observed, at the start of the conference for which this cluster of
                  essays was written, that humanistic study is all about representation: it is about
                  decoding, understanding, historicizing, and critiquing the representational modes
                  and artifacts of the past and present, and reflecting on what they tell us about
                  human culture. But while we are good at distancing ourselves critically from the
                  representational forms we encounter in the materials we study, we’re surprisingly
                  less so when it comes to the modes we use ourselves. One of the most significant
                  contributions of the digital humanities on modern scholarship is precisely to
                  foreground issues of how we model the sources we study, in such a way that they
                  cannot be sidestepped. Where printed editions allowed us to treat their contents
                  as if no change in medium had taken place, digital editions force us to confront
                  the very same set of issues with far more rigor and clarity. As John Unsworth
                  observes, </p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2002">once we begin to express our
                     understanding of, say, a literary text in a language such as XML, a formal
                     grammar that requires us to state the rules according to which we will deploy
                     that grammar in a text or texts, then we find that our representation of the
                     text is subject to verification – for internal consistency, and especially for
                     consistency with the rules we have stated.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#unsworth2002"/>
               </cit>
               <p>The word <term>verification</term> stands out here, sounding very cut and dried,
                  threateningly technical, a mental straitjacket, but in fact the key phrase there
                  is <q>the rules we have stated</q>: it is the act of stating rules that requires
                  the discipline of methodological self-scrutiny. It is in fact precisely the
                  distance, the discomfort even, that digital representations carry vis-à-vis their
                  print counterparts that reminds us that they are models. At first, this distance
                  registers as a loss: digital representations are models <q>rather than</q> the
                  real thing, taking the place it should occupy. But as our tools for manipulating
                  digital models improve, the model stops marking loss and takes on a clearer role
                  as a strategic representation, one which deliberately omits and exaggerates and
                  distorts the scale so that we can work with the parts that matter to us. </p>
               <p>In effect, digital scholarship embodies an unresolved conflict about scale, human
                  effort, and the nature of digital work. The great bulk of digital research
                  material now available does not look very <q>scholarly</q>; with the institutional
                  focus on digital library development and the funnelling of digitization money
                  through efforts of this type, there has been a great deal of emphasis on
                  large-scale activities with light informational yield and strong tradeoff of scale
                  against precision, such as Google Books. Traditionally, humanistic scholarship has
                  been focused on high-labor <q>craft</q> activities where care and precision
                  matter, and despite the importance of digital libraries, there is thus a kind of
                  mismatch between current digital library approaches and scholarly expectations.
                  Typically, scholars are not involved closely in the development of these
                  resources: they are alienated, in a way, from the technology because they see it
                  as intrinsically not about their craft, intrinsically maladapted to the kinds of
                  thoughts they are accustomed to think.</p>
               <p>Alan Liu has observed this shift in the way digital resources are crafted, and
                  noted the politics of the change. In an essay called <title rend="quotes"
                     >Transcendental Data,</title> he charts the emergence of a new aesthetic of the
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004">data pour</quote> in which information is in
                  its most characteristic and powerful state when separated from specific form. The
                  information design of 21st-century digital resources draws on precisely this
                  approach: on presentational models that can scale up by orders of magnitude to
                  accommodate the vast and increasing quantities of material. But they do so by
                  decreasing our ability to apprehend the details of individual objects. The
                  challenge information designers now face is how to span that distance, and how to
                  represent the macrocosm so that we don’t lose sight of its parts. This is true not
                  only literally, but also intellectually: the question is how scholarly methods can
                  adapt to this shift in scale without losing their grasp on the concrete and
                  beloved quiddity of texts and words and books and artifacts.</p>
               <p>The world of social software is way ahead of us, in some ways, in addressing these
                  problems. Although without our critical sensitivity and unease, casual users are
                  experimenting with tools like Flickr and YouTube and del.icio.us, which attempt to
                  represent the texture of the relevant landscape, as imagined by the people living
                  in it: the photographs that matter to people, the web sites they read, the topics
                  they think these things are about. But the scholarly tribe are not so very far
                  behind, or at least they are in the race: efforts like TAPoR, the Text Analysis
                  Developers Alliance, NINES, and MONK are setting their sights on this same
                  problem, trying to see how far the human perceptual mechanisms can be stretched as
                  they try to grasp both the macrocosm and the microcosm and the informational
                  strands that connect the one to the other.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Looking to the Future</head>
            <p>All of this unease, as my title has already asserted, is productive: not of forward
               motion but of that same oscillating, dialectical pulsation that is the scholarly mind
               at work. Digital tools add a challenge and give us a new set of terms — like a new
               planet in the system, they change the vectors of all the other things we have in our
               universe. They will probably change the way humanities research is done. When writing
               the grant proposals that so often fund digital humanities work, all of the natural
               rhetoric is progressive — there will be more, and it will be better, and it will open
               up new ways of thinking. But it is healthy to remember that the most interesting
               papers and books we read, in any genre, are those that neither foretell doom nor
               glory, but give us instead an interesting idea about the world to play with. Methods
               and tools that combine what has been gained in power and scale with a real measure of
               scholarly effort and engagement can give us such an idea. But the intellectual
               outcomes will not be judged by their power or speed, but by the same criteria used in
               humanities scholarship all along: does it make us think? does it make us keep
               thinking?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders1999" label="Flanders 1999" key="flanders1999"> Flanders, Julia.
                  <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Habits and Digital Resources: Observations from a
                  User Survey</title>. Women Writers Project, 1999. <ref
                  target="http://www.wwp.brown.edu/research/publications/reports/rwo/rwo_initial_report.html"
                  >http://www.wwp.brown.edu/research/publications/reports/rwo/rwo_initial_report.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2004" label="Liu 2004" key="liu2004">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Transcendental Data: Toward A Cultural History and Aesthetics of the New Encoded
                  Discourse.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 31 (2004): 49-84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2003" label="Liu 2003" key="liu2003"> Liu, Alan, <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Humanities: A Technical Profession.</title> Panel on <title rend="quotes"
                  >Information Technology and the Profession.</title> Modern Language Association
               Convention. San Diego. 18 December 2003. <ref
                  target="http://www.english.ucsb.edu/faculty/ayliu/research/talks/2003mla/liu_talk.pdf"
                  >http://www.english.ucsb.edu/faculty/ayliu/research/talks/2003MLA/Liu_Talk.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mla2002" label="MLA 2002" key="mla2002"> Modern Language Association.
                  <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for Evaluating Work with Digital Media in the
                  Modern Languages</title>, 2002. <ref
                  target="http://www.mla.org/resources/documents/rep_it/guidelines_evaluation_digital"
                  >http://www.mla.org/resources/documents/rep_it/guidelines_evaluation_digital</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg1993" label="Shillingsburg 1993" key="shillingsburg1993"
               >Shillingsburg, Peter. <title rend="quotes">Polymorphic, Polysemic, Protean, Reliable
                  Electronic Texts</title>. In <title rend="italic">Palimpsest: Editorial Theory in
                  the Humanities</title>, ed. George Bornstein and Ralph G. Williams. Ann Arbor:
               University of Michigan Press, 1993.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2002" label="Unsworth 2002" key="unsworth2002">Unsworth, John.
                  <title rend="quotes">What is Humanities Computing, and What is Not?</title> In
                  <title rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie</title> 4, Georg Braungart,
               Karl Eibl and Fotis Jannidis, eds. Paderborn: mentis Verlag 2002. <ref
                  target="http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg02/unsworth.html"
                  >http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg02/unsworth.html</ref>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
