<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">The Digital Future is Now: A Call to Action for the Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Christine L. <dhq:family>Borgman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Professor &amp; Presidential Chair in Information Studies, UCLA</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Borgman@gseis.ucla.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>
                     <ref target="http://is.gseis.ucla.edu/cborgman/">Christine L. Borgman</ref> is Professor and Presidential Chair in Information
            Studies at UCLA. She is the author of more than 180 <ref target="http://works.bepress.com/borgman/">publications</ref> in the fields of
            information studies, computer science, and communication. Both of her sole-authored
            monographs, <ref target="http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=11333">
                        <title rend="italic">Scholarship in the Digital Age: Information, Infrastructure, and the
                Internet</title>
                     </ref> (MIT Press, 2007) and <ref target="http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=9661">
                        <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to the Global Information Infrastructure: Access to
                    Information in a Networked World</title>
                     </ref> (MIT Press, 2000), have won the
            <ref target="http://www.asis.org/awards/book.html">Best Information Science Book of the
            Year</ref> award from the American Society for Information Science and Technology. She
            is a lead investigator for the <ref target="http://research.cens.ucla.edu/">Center for
            Embedded Networked Systems</ref> (CENS), a National Science Foundation Science and
            Technology Center, where she conducts data practices research. She chaired the Task
            Force on Cyberlearning for the NSF, whose report, <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/publications/pub_summ.jsp?ods_key=nsf08204">
                        <title rend="italic">Fostering Learning in the Networked World</title>
                     </ref>, was released
            in July, 2008. Prof. Borgman’s keynotes and plenary presentations in 2009 include the
            <ref target="http://www.mith2.umd.edu/dh09/">Digital Humanities Conference</ref>, <ref target="http://www.jcdl2009.org/">Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</ref>, 40th
            Anniversary Conference of the <ref target="http://www.open.ac.uk/">Orpen University</ref>, <ref target="http://www.anderson.ucla.edu/x681.xml">Marschak Lecture</ref> (UCLA), <ref target="http://www.kanazawa-it.ac.jp/ekit/">Kanazawa Institute</ref> International Seminar on Libraries (Japan), and invited talks at the <ref target="http://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/events/?id=259">University of Oxford</ref>, <ref target="http://iic.harvard.edu/events/year/2009">Harvard University</ref>, <ref target="http://scholcomm.columbia.edu/scholarship-digital-age-information-infrastructure-and-i">Columbia University</ref>, <ref target="http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=2520">University of Pittsburgh</ref>, and Michigan State University.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000077</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2010-03-20">20 March 2010</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
      
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
      <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change who="alyssa" when="2010-01-26">Started encoding</change>
         <change when="2010-03-03" who="alyssa">Added bio, made author corrections</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The digital humanities are at a critical moment in the transition from a specialty area to a full-fledged community with a common set of methods, sources of evidence, and infrastructure — all of which are necessary for achieving academic recognition.  As budgets are slashed and marginal programs are eliminated in the current economic crisis, only the most articulate and productive will survive. Digital collections are proliferating, but most remain difficult to use, and digital scholarship remains a backwater in most humanities departments with respect to hiring, promotion, and teaching practices. Only the scholars themselves are in a position to move the field forward. Experiences of the sciences in their initiatives for cyberinfrastructure and eScience offer valuable lessons. Information- and data-intensive, distributed, collaborative, and multi-disciplinary research is now the norm in the sciences, while remaining experimental in the humanities. Discussed here are six factors for comparison, selected for their implications for the future of digital scholarship in the humanities: publication practices, data, research methods, collaboration, incentives, and learning. Drawing upon lessons gleaned from these comparisons, humanities scholars are <q>called to action</q> with five questions to address as a community: What are data? What are the infrastructure requirements? Where are the social studies of digital humanities? What is the humanities laboratory of the 21st century? What is the value proposition for digital humanities in an era of declining budgets?</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>A critical moment for the digital humanities</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>The Digital Future is Now: A Call to Action for the Humanities</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This is a pivotal moment for the digital humanities.  The community has laid a foundation of research methods, theory, practice, and scholarly conferences and journals.  Can we seize this moment to make digital scholarship a leading force in humanities research? Or will the community fall behind, not-quite-there, among the many victims of the massive restructuring of higher education in the current economic crisis?  Much is at stake in the community’s ability to argue for the value of digital humanities scholarship and to assemble the necessary resources for the field to move from <q>emergent</q> to <q>established.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The sciences, arts, and humanities have converged and diverged in various ways over the
          centuries. In the area of digital scholarship, many interests are in common across the
          disciplines.  It is the pace of adoption that is divergent. The sciences, and to a lesser
          extent the social sciences, have been successful in developing the technical, social, and
          political infrastructure for digital scholarship under the rubrics of
          <term>cyberinfrastucture</term> — the term used in the U.S., and <term>eScience</term> —
          the term more widely used in the U.K. and elsewhere <ptr target="#ukrc2009"/>; <ptr target="#atkins2003"/>. Digital scholarship remains emergent in the humanities, while eScience has become the norm in the sciences. The humanities need not emulate the sciences, but can learn useful lessons by studying the successes (and limitations) of cyberinfrastructure and eScience initiatives.</p>
            <p>While leaving definitions of <q>the humanities</q> to the reader, two complementary
          definitions of <q>digital humanities</q> provide a useful scope statement. Frischer’s
          definition is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#frischer2009">the application of information technology as an
            aid to fulfill the humanities’ basic tasks of preserving, reconstructing, transmitting,
            and interpreting the human record</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#frischer2009" loc="15"/>
               </cit>.
          One resulting from the UCLA Mellon seminar claims that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#manifesto2008">Digital
            humanities is not a unified field but an array of convergent practices that explore a
            universe in which print is no longer the exclusive or the normative medium in which
            knowledge is produced and/or disseminated</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#manifesto2008"/>
               </cit>. Taken together, the digital humanities is a new set of practices, using new sets of technologies, to address research problems of the discipline. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Problem Statement</head>
            <p>Interest in the digital humanities has grown steadily for several decades. The Digital
          Humanities Conferences have occurred annually since 1989, sponsored by the Alliance of
          Digital Humanities Organizations. Constituent organizations of the Alliance have held
          conferences since 1973 <ptr target="#adho2009"/>. MITH <ref target="#mith2009">(Maryland
            Institute for Technology in the Humanities 2009)</ref>
          celebrated its tenth anniversary, and IATH <ref target="#iath2009">(Institute for Advanced
            Technology in the Humanities 2009)</ref> at the University of Virginia its 17th anniversary. Academic research in
          the digital humanities at UCLA, Duke, Stanford, King’s College London, and elsewhere also
          appears to be thriving. Funding continues apace, with the Mellon Foundation, Council on
          Library and Information Resources, National Endowment for the Humanities, U.K. Arts and
          Humanities Research Council, and others focusing on infrastructure, tools, and services to
          support humanities scholarship in digital environments.  Yet digital scholarship remains a
          backwater in much of the humanities. Concerns about publishing, tenure, and promotion for
          digital humanities scholars are a continuing theme in the conferences and in the
          literature of the field <ptr target="#friedlander2008"/>; <ptr target="#friedlander2009"/>; <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/>.</p>
            <p>Despite many investments and years of development, basic infrastructure for the digital humanities is still lacking. Those who wish to gather and analyze digital data for humanities problems often find the overhead daunting, as exemplified by this emailed complaint from a history student in my scholarly communication course, who is pursuing a doctoral dissertation about the German enlightenment:
          
          <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#private">I’m finding that something as simple as constructing my maps of
            related concepts are not easily applied to primary sources in digital libraries.
            <emph>So what use are the digital libraries, if all they do is put digitally unusable information on the web?</emph> The digital libraries don’t offer a platform for traditional note taking, much less for larger scale analysis, either quantitative or qualitative.</quote> 
                  <ref type="offline">emphasis added; quoted with permission</ref>
               </cit>
          
          
               <q>Digital libraries,</q> the term used by my student, usually
          implies the existence of tools, services, and a library imprimatur of cataloging and
          curation. Her complaint is more about digital collections, which often lack basic
          capabilities for retrieval or analysis. This distinction is particularly relevant to the
          digital humanities.  Content in digital collections may be <quote rend="inline" source="#lynch2002">relatively
          raw,</quote> as <ptr target="#lynch2002"/> puts it; others can add layers of
          interpretation, presentation, tools, and services, but these layers may be maintained
          separately from the content <ptr target="#borgman1999"/>; <ptr target="#borgman2000"/>;
          <ptr target="#lynch2002"/>. The invisibility of essential infrastructure for digital scholarship in the humanities is but one of many challenges to be addressed in growing the field. Until analytical tools and services are more sophisticated, robust, transparent, and easy to use for the motivated humanities researcher, it will be difficult to attract a broad base of interest within the humanities community.</p>
            <p>Whose problem is it to improve the situation — that is, to design, develop, and deploy the
          scholarly infrastructure for digital humanities?  As my UCLA colleague, Johanna Drucker,
          put it so well, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">Leaving it to <q>them</q> is unfair, wrongheaded,
          and irresponsible. Them is us</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#drucker2009" loc="B8"/>
               </cit>.  She believes
          that the digital humanities are at a <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">critical juncture,</quote> and is concerned that her fellow scholars are deferring responsibility for action to librarians, computer scientists, technology developers, publishers, and others.</p>
            <p>The operant terms in <q>digital humanities scholarship</q> are the latter two.  Scholarly
          methods are as deeply seated in the humanities as they are in the sciences <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>.  Only those who do the work and who require the infrastructure are in a position to take the field forward.  Librarians and technology developers are essential partners, but those who conduct the research must take the lead.</p>
            <p>This article, based on a keynote presentation to the most recent Digital Humanities
          Conference, reviews and reflects upon the differences between the approaches of the
          sciences and the humanities to digital scholarship <ptr target="#borgman2009"/>.  First, I frame the notion of scholarly information infrastructure, then compare the approaches to digital scholarship of the sciences and the humanities.  My analysis concludes with a call to action for the humanities community.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Scholarly Information Infrastructure</head>
            <p>The term <term>scholarly information infrastructure</term> encompasses the technology, services,
          practices, and policy that support research in all disciplines.  Cyberinfrastructure and
          eScience — both coined initially in reference to the sciences and technology, and both now
          used more broadly — refer to an infrastructure that enables forms of scholarship that are
          information- and data-intensive, distributed, collaborative, and multi-disciplinary.
          eResearch has become the collective term for variants such as eScience, eSocial Science,
          and eHumanities <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>. The report of the <title rend="italic">Commission on Cyberinfrastructure
          for the Humanities and Social Sciences</title> 
               <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/> was modeled on the
          strategy for science and technology <ptr target="#atkins2003"/>, while diverging to
          emphasize the humanities’ motivations to make cultural heritage more widely available for
          teaching, research, and outreach.  A similar argument is made by <ref target="#presner2009">Todd Presner and Chris
            Johanson</ref> that digital humanities offers the opportunity to reconceptualize society as our cultural heritage migrates to digital formats, thus altering our relationship to knowledge and culture.</p>
            <p>The technical and policy infrastructure for scholarship is being built rapidly,
          particularly for the sciences <ptr target="#cyber2007"/>; <ptr target="#hey2009"/>.  Rare are the encompassing visions for scholarly
          infrastructure that originate in the humanities.  Amy Friedlander provides a
          notable exception <ptr target="#friedlander2009"/>. She identified four research areas in digital scholarship where the interests of humanists, technology researchers, and others converge. These are scale, language and communication, space and time, and social networking. Issues of scale are of general interest because methods and problems must be approached much differently when one has, for example, the full text of a million books rather than a handful. Inspection is no longer feasible; only computational methods can examine corpora on that scale.  Issues of language and communication, which are central to the humanities, are of broader interest for problems such as pattern detection and cross-language indexing and retrieval.  Space and time encompass the new research methods possible with geographic information systems, geo-tagged documents and images, and the increased ability to make temporal comparisons. Social network analysis, long popular in sociology and bibliometrics, has become generalized to include patterns of social relationships in older texts or in online communication. Cross-cutting agendas such as these can be very influential in the design of an encompassing infrastructure.  Humanities researchers need to be at the table as fundamental infrastructure decisions are being made.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Science [and/or/versus] the Humanities</head>
            <p>The humanities and the sciences each encompass broad swaths of scholarship, with much
          internal diversity. These two communities have significant commonalities, while differing
          in important ways. Identified here are six factors for comparison, selected for their
          implications for the future of digital scholarship in the humanities: publication
          practices, data, research methods, collaboration, incentives, and learning. The first five
          of these are drawn from longer analyses published elsewhere <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>;
          the last is drawn from the <title rend="italic">NSF Task Force on Cyberlearning</title> 
               <ptr target="#borgman2008"/>. The sequence of topics is cumulative to reflect how the boundaries are blurring between the sciences and the humanities.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Publication Practices</head>
               <p>Scholarly journal publication is shifting rapidly toward electronic formats, especially
            in the sciences.  Some journals are dropping print publication altogether; others are
            declaring the online version (usually released several weeks to several months prior to
            the printed edition) to be the edition of record. Under pressure from authors, the
            majority of scholarly journals now appear to allow online posting of some form of
            pre-print or post-print <ptr target="#sherpa2009"/>.</p>
               <p>For physics and related areas of computer science and mathematics, arXiv is the locus
            of scholarly communication.  Monthly deposits of new papers now number more than 5,000;
            the site, which contains over 500,000 papers, typically receives 50,000 visits per hour
            <ptr target="#arxiv2009"/>.  At least three iPhone applications are
            available for arXiv searching and retrieval.  ArXiv, similar repositories in fields such
            as economics, and institutional repositories such as ePrints, employ standard data
            structures that make their contents readily discoverable by search engines <ptr target="#oaip2009"/>; <ptr target="#rpe2009"/>; <ptr target="#eprints2010"/>. It is little wonder that our science colleagues claim they never go to their campus libraries any more; their libraries come to them.</p>
               <p>In the humanities, neither journal nor book publishing has moved rapidly toward online
            publication, despite pioneering efforts such as the 1990 launch of the <title rend="italic">Journal of Post Modern Culture</title> as an electronic-only journal and
            the 2005 launch of <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> as an online-only multi-media
            journal <ptr target="#jpmc2000"/>; <ptr target="#vectors2009"/>; <ptr target="#hamma2009"/>; <ptr target="#king2006"/>; <ptr target="#whalen2009"/>.
            A few of the established humanities journals have begun online versions that take advantage of digital technologies. Beginning in March 2010, for example, the <title rend="italic">JSAH</title> (Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians) will publish an online version that will support <q>zoomable images, video, GIS map integration, Adobe Flash VR, 3-D models, and online reference linking</q> — while continuing to publish its static print version.</p>
               <p>The reasons for the slow adoption of digital publishing in the humanities are many,
            from not trusting online dissemination to a general reluctance to experiment with new
            technologies, even those well proven — <quote rend="inline" source="#hamma2009">professionally indisposed to
              change</quote> as Ken Hamma puts it <ptr target="#hamma2009"/>. Monographic publishing, which is
            core to humanities scholarship, has begun a seismic shift toward digital publishing
            <ptr target="#jaschik2008"/>; <ptr target="#jaschik2009"/>; <ptr target="#poe2001"/>;
            <ptr target="#willinsky2006"/>; <ptr target="#willinsky2009"/>. A growing number of
            university presses are offering online access to monographs they publish in print,
            whether or not they also offer digital-only or print-on-demand formats. Other university
            presses are reinventing themselves in digital form <ptr target="#rice2008"/>. The
            University of California Press recently announced a partnership with the California
            Digital Library, which hosts the university’s institutional repository, to offer
            <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ucps2009">a suite of publishing services robust and flexible enough to
              support the complexities of content, format, and dissemination that increasingly
              define scholarly communications</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#ucps2009"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#whalen2009">love affair with print</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#whalen2009"/>
                  </cit> of art historians and other humanities
            scholars places not only <q>traditional</q> humanities scholarship at risk but also that
            of digital humanities. The distinction between print and digital publication is as much
            about epistemology as genre. Digital publishing is not simply repackaging a book or
            article as a computer file, although even a searchable pdf has advantages over paper. By
            incorporating dynamic multi-media or hypermedia, digital publishing offers different
            ways of expressing ideas and of presenting evidence for those ideas <ptr target="#lynch2002"/>; <ptr target="#presner2010"/>; <ptr target="#presner2009"/>.  When digital scholarship is published in print venues, much of its sophistication is lost.</p>
               <p>Digital publishing differs from print publishing in several ways.  One is the shorter time from submission to publication.  While speed of publication is a much greater concern in the sciences than in the humanities, much of that time delay involves the physical production of the journal or book.  Reviewing time varies little between print and digital formats. The humanities could benefit from faster turnaround, reaching audiences much sooner.</p>
               <p>A second advantage of digital publishing — even more critical — is the larger audience
            for online publications. Anyone with an online connection and a subscription (in the
            case of fee-paid content), anywhere in the world, can read digital publications.  Only
            those with access to a physical copy can read print-only publications. The number of
            titles and the number of copies of scholarly books and journals published in print form
            are decreasing rapidly, thus limiting both publishing outlets and readership. Maureen
            Whalen’s concern for art history, with its continuing reliance on print publishing, is
            that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#whalen2009">the voices of authority ... will be talking amongst
            themselves</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#whalen2009"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>Two other consequences of the inexorable shift toward digital publication should be of
            concern to the humanities.  One is that print material — including older material —
            becomes <q>widowed</q> as students and scholars alike search only online. The widowing
            problem was recognized early in the days of online catalogs, and was a major impetus for
            research libraries to digitize their entire back catalogs rather than only records of
            new material <ptr target="#borgman2000"/>; <ptr target="#lynch2003"/>; <ptr target="#lynch1995"/>.</p>
               <p>The other consequence is that easier access to online material frequently increases its
            rate of citation. Articles published in open access journals, open repositories, or
            dual-published by providing preprints or postprints online, tend to have a citation
            advantage over articles published only in closed-access journals, whether print or
            online. The degree of advantage varies by field and by a number of other factors,
            including how <soCalled>open access</soCalled> is defined <ptr target="#facts2005"/>; <ptr target="#doar2008"/>; <ptr target="#doaj2009"/>; <ptr target="#oca2009"/>; <ptr target="#effect2009"/>; <ptr target="#bailey2005"/>.</p>
               <p>While the details of these studies are much contested between authors, editors,
            librarians, and publishers, the simple tautology that easier discovery is associated
            with higher citation is difficult to dispute. As do authors in other fields, scholars in
            the humanities desire recognition in the form of citations to their work. Universities
            consider citation metrics in hiring and promotion decisions, despite known problems in
            their use for evaluating scholarly productivity <ptr target="#bollen2008"/>; <ptr target="#kurtz2010"/>; <ptr target="#monastersky2005"/>; <ptr target="#reedijk2008"/>.</p>
               <p>In sum, the sciences have benefited from online publication in ways that the humanities have not (yet).  Digital publication is faster, reaches a wider audience, and tends to increase the citation rate over print-only publication.  As the proportion of print-only publication continues to decrease, those for whom it is their only venue risk reaching an ever smaller and more closed community with their scholarship.  Curation of digital objects is a concern in all fields, and is a topic that has the attention of management in libraries and archives. Nonetheless, digital publication has become the norm, and those who cling to print publication as the only acceptable format for promotion and tenure may be left out of the academic mainstream.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Data in Digital Scholarship</head>
               <p>Central to the notion of cyberinfrastructure and eScience is that <q>data</q> have become
            essential scholarly objects to be captured, mined, used, and reused.  This trend has
            been under way in science for many years, to varying degrees by field.  As the technical and communications infrastructure became sufficiently robust to support large-scale data analysis and exchange, data became more valuable commodities. The availability of large volumes of data has enabled scientists to ask new questions, in new ways. Environmental scientists can conduct longitudinal analyses and make comparisons between locales using datasets compiled from multiple sources. Similarly, genome data offer analytical power at much finer granularity, and at larger scales.</p>
               <p>While <q>data</q> is a less familiar terminology in the humanities, the availability of large
            text, image, audio, and multi-media corpora has a similar result, enabling scholars in
            multiple fields to interrogate sources in new ways <ptr target="#crane2007"/>. Judging by presentations at the 2009 Digital Humanities Conference,
            <term>data</term> is becoming a popular term, whether framed in terms of <q>mining</q>
            or <q>cultural analytics.</q> Data mining <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#nctm2009">is the process of
              identifying patterns in large sets of data . . . to uncover previously unknown, useful
              knowledge</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#nctm2009"/>
                  </cit>. Cultural
            analytics is a term that arose in the humanities as an analog to <q>visual
            analytics,</q> 
                  <q>business analytics,</q> and <q>web analytics,</q> and includes the
            use of <quote rend="inline" source="#manovich2009">computer-based techniques for quantitative analysis and
            interactive visualization</quote> to identify patterns in large cultural data sets
            <ptr target="#manovich2009"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>What Are Data?</head>
               <p>The increasing value of data begs the question of <q>what are data?</q> Definitions
            associated with archival information systems offer a useful starting point: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#rmoais2002">A reinterpretable representation of information in a formalized manner
              suitable for communication, interpretation, or processing. Examples of data include a
              sequence of bits, a table of numbers, the characters on a page, the recording of
              sounds made by a person speaking, or a moon rock specimen</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#rmoais2002" loc="1–9"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>Another way to think about data is by origin. In the context of cyberinfrastructure,
            the four categories of data identified in an influential U.S. policy report
            <ref target="#llddc2005">
                     <title rend="italic">Long-Lived Data Collections</title> 2005</ref>, and incorporated in National Science
            Foundation strategy <ref target="#cyber2007">
                     <title rend="italic">Cyberinfrastructure Vision for 21st Century Discovery</title> 2007</ref>, are now widely accepted. <emph>Observational</emph> data include weather measurements and attitude surveys, either of which may be associated with specific places and times or may involve multiple places and times (e.g., cross-sectional, longitudinal studies). <emph>Computational</emph> data result from executing a computer model or simulation, whether for physics or cultural virtual reality. Replicating the model or simulation in the future may require extensive documentation of the hardware, software, and input data. In some cases, only the output of the model might be preserved. <emph>Experimental</emph> data include results from laboratory studies such as measurements of chemical reactions or from field experiments such as controlled behavioral studies. Whether sufficient data and documentation to reproduce the experiment are kept varies by the cost and reproducibility of the experiment. <emph>Records</emph> of government, business, and public and private life also yield useful data for scientific, social scientific, and humanistic research.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Data as Evidence</head>
               <p>The need to address categories and levels of data is a pragmatic concern for managing
            information. Yet data are often in the eye of the beholder.  In Buckland’s terms, data
            are <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#buckland1991">alleged evidence</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#buckland1991"/>
                  </cit>.  What counts as good data varies widely, as
            one person’s noise is often another person’s signal. Similarly, the choices of data
            depend heavily on the questions being asked <ptr target="#scheiner2004"/>.</p>
               <p>Whether any given set of observation or records can be considered data depends on
            context, even in the sciences. In our research on science and technology researchers in
            the environmental sciences, we found differing views of data on concepts as basic as
            temperature. Some of the computer science and engineering researchers interviewed said, roughly, <said>temperature is temperature,</said> whereas biologists gave much more
            nuanced descriptions of how temperature was measured: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#borgmanetal2007">
                        <said>There are hundreds of ways to measure temperature. <q>The
              temperature is 98</q> is low-value compared to, <q>the temperature of the surface,
              measured by the infrared thermopile, model number XYZ, is 98.</q> That means it is
                measuring a proxy for a temperature, rather than being in contact with a probe, and
                it is measuring from a distance. The accuracy is plus or minus .05 of a degree. I
                [also] want to know that it was taken outside versus inside a controlled
                environment, how long it had been in place, and the last time it was calibrated,
                which might tell me whether it has drifted…</said>
                     </quote> 
                     <ptr target="#borgmanetal2007"/>
                  </cit>. Thus these two groups of researchers, often working side-by-side in the field as collaborators, had very different perspectives on what were acceptable data for their evidentiary purposes.</p>
               <p>Studies of scientific practice, such as our work in embedded sensor networks, is
            providing insights for the design of cyberinfrastructure and eScience. The social
            studies of science and technology is a large and burgeoning field, with multiple
            journals and book series, and a scholarly society established more than 40 years ago
            <ptr target="#vanhouse2004"/>. No comparable body of research on scholarly practices in the
            humanities exists, with the exception of research on information-seeking behavior
            <ptr target="#anderson2004"/>; <ptr target="#bates1996a"/>; <ptr target="#bates1996b"/>; <ptr target="#bates1993"/>; <ptr target="#bates1995"/>; <ptr target="#case2006"/>; <ptr target="#siegfried1993"/>; <ptr target="#stone1982"/>; <ptr target="#tibbo2003"/>; <ptr target="#wiberley2003"/>; <ptr target="#wiberley1994"/>. Lacking an external perspective, humanities scholars need to be
            particularly attentive to unstated assumptions about their data, sources of evidence,
            and epistemology.  We are only beginning to understand what constitute data in the
            humanities, let alone how data differ from scholar to scholar and from author to reader.
            As Allen Renear remarked, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">In the humanities, one person’s data is
              another’s theory</quote> 
                     <ref type="offline">personal communication, June 22, 2009</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Data Sources</head>
               <p>The sciences and humanities differ greatly in their sources of data and the degree of
            control they have over those data <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>. Scientific data sources vary by discipline, as seen in these few examples: 
           <list type="unordered"> 
                     <item>Medicine: x-rays</item>
                     <item>Chemistry: protein structures</item>
                     <item>Astronomy: spectral surveys</item>
                     <item>Biology: specimens</item>
                     <item>Physics: events, objects</item>
                     <item>Ecology: weather, ground water, sensor readings, historical records</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Scientists, generally speaking, use data that were created by and for scientific purposes.  They usually generate their own data, as in field observations or laboratory studies, or may acquire data from collaborators or other scientists. They may also acquire data from repositories in their field or from government sites, such as records of rainfall or river flow.  Scientific documentation such as laboratory and field notebooks is sometimes considered to be data and sometimes metadata.</p>
               <p>The social sciences occupy the middle position between the sciences and humanities on a
            continuum of data sources and control. Those at the scientific end of the scale gather
            their own observations, whether opinion polls, surveys, interviews, or field studies;
            build models of human behavior; and conduct experiments in the laboratory or field.
            Other social scientists rely on records collected by others, such as economic indicators
            or demographic data from the census. Government and corporate records are often of
            interest, as are the mass media. A number of important data repositories exist,
            especially for large social surveys (e.g., <ptr target="#src2009a"/>; <ptr target="#src2009b"/>; <ptr target="#ukda2009"/>).</p>
               <p>The humanities and arts are the least likely of the disciplines to generate their own data in the forms of observations, models, or experiments.  Humanities scholars rely most heavily on records, whether newspapers, photographs, letters, diaries, books, articles; records of birth, death, marriage; records found in churches, courts, schools, and colleges; or maps.  Any record of human experience can be a data source to a humanities scholar.  Many of those sources are public while others are private.  Cultural records may be found in libraries, archives, museums, or government agencies, under a complex mix of access rules. Some records are embargoed for a century or more. Some may be viewable only on site, whether in print or digital form.  Data sources for humanities scholarship are growing in number and in variety, especially as more records are digitized and made available to the public.</p>
               <p>
                  <ref target="#lynch2002">Lynch’s dichotomy</ref> of raw material vs. interpretation has
            a number of implications for the digital humanities. Two are of concern here. One is that raw materials are more likely to be curated for the long term than are scholars’ interpretations of those materials. It is the nature of the humanities that sources are reinterpreted continually; what is new is the necessity of making explicit decisions about what survives for migration to new systems and formats. Second is the implication for control of intellectual property. Generally speaking, humanities scholars have far less control over the intellectual property rights of their sources — these raw materials — than do scientists, whose data usually are original observations or specimens.  Typically, scholars can read, view, and cite cultural records, but often need explicit permission to reproduce them — and frequently need to pay a fee, especially in the case of images, to include them in reports of their research.</p>
               <p>Intellectual property constraints on publishing of digital humanities scholarship are
            much different than those that usually apply in other disciplines.  Rights to reproduce
            material remain closely tied to a print model, specified by number of copies printed and
            by temporal rules on sale that are irrelevant to online publication.  Even cultural
            institutions as sophisticated as the Getty Trust encounter structural barriers to online
            publication of humanities scholarship <ptr target="#whalen2009"/>. The policy shift
            toward data sharing, well under way in the sciences, generally presumes that those who
            produce the data have the authority to release or deposit them for reuse <ptr target="#oecd2007"/>; <ptr target="#arzberger2004"/>.</p>
               <p>In sum, <q>what are data?</q> is an important question for the humanities.  The answer
            will determine what data are produced, how they are captured, and how they are curated
            for reuse.  Data sharing in the humanities is a complex set of issues — not that they
            are simple in the sciences — that must be addressed. The humanities community needs a
            critical mass of digital resources and needs common tools, services, and repositories if
            they are to move beyond <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#friedlander2009">boutique projects</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#friedlander2009"/>
                  </cit> to a solid foundation of theory and method.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Research Methods</head>
               <p>Questions of <q>what are data?</q> are inextricable from the choice of research method.
            Many of the sciences, especially those <q>big science</q> areas that require large scale
            instrumentation and produce vast volumes of data, are in transition to a data-driven
            paradigm <ptr target="#bell2009"/>; <ptr target="#foster2009"/>. As the analysis, modeling, and merging of data become more central to scientific research, partnerships between scientists and computer scientists are becoming the norm.</p>
               <p>An important case example of the changing role of data in science is the <ref target="#sloan2006">Sloan Digital
            Sky Survey</ref>, begun in 1992 by Jim Gray, Alex
            Szalay, and others <ptr target="#gray2005"/>; <ptr target="#gray2002"/>; <ptr target="#szalay2008"/>.  It was the first major astronomical survey founded on the premise that the resulting data would be openly and freely available, both to the astronomy community and to the public at large.  Not only did astronomers mine the Sloan datasets for research purposes — more than 1700 scholarly papers were published — but manifold more users of these data were students and amateur astronomers. Amateurs, whose backyard telescopes could never yield data of such quality, also made important discoveries.</p>
               <p>The Sloan Digital Sky Survey is significant for its openness, research productivity,
            and community engagement, and because it instantiates the <quote rend="inline" source="#borgman2007">value chain</quote> of scholarship
            <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>.  On the SDSS site, papers are linked to the datasets on which
            they are based and datasets are linked to papers about them.  One can enter the chain
            from either point and follow the relationships.  While the project has ceased collecting
            new observations, the Sloan data remain available for use and are a canonical experiment
            in curation of large-scale datasets <ptr target="#choudhury2008"/>; <ptr target="#choudhury2007"/>. Astronomers and computer scientists are now engaged in the next
            generation project, Panoramic Survey Telescope and Rapid Response System, which is
            yielding about twenty times as much data as Sloan <ptr target="#panstarrs2009"/>.</p>
               <p>Humanities scholars are more likely to find their data sources in the library — their traditional laboratory — than in the skies. While the library continues to be more central to scholarship in the humanities than it is to other fields, the characteristics of that relationship are changing. The use of physical space and of library staff has changed radically in the last two decades, largely in response to flat or declining university library budgets.  Campus libraries have been consolidated in efforts to minimize the number of public service points to be staffed.  Books, journals, and other physical materials have been moved to remote facilities, paged from the stacks upon request.  Professional librarians, while a smaller proportion of library staffs, are turning their attention away from collection building — given the budget crises — and toward making the best use of the materials they have. The sciences are placing less demand on the physical library, allowing university libraries to reconfigure their spaces to benefit faculty and students in the humanities.  Prime floor space previously devoted to card catalogs, journals, and book stacks is now available for groups to work together with physical and digital resources. More librarians have backgrounds in the humanities than in the sciences, and many are eager to partner with humanities scholars in building better tools and services for discovering, interpreting, and using scholarly content.</p>
               <p>At most universities today, humanities scholars and students are the primary constituency for physical books, journals, and records. This community also makes the finest distinctions among editions, printings, and other variants — distinctions that are sometimes overlooked in the transition from print to digital form. For general reading, any edition may suffice, and some degradation in image quality may be an acceptable tradeoff for access to large corpora of books and journals.  Scholars are much more dependent on metadata to identify and compare variants, and may require physical copies to examine characteristics of printing and paper, annotations, and other details.</p>
               <p>Differences in the methods of using print and digital objects are being thrown into
            sharp relief by mass digitization projects, most recently by the intense public debate
            over Google’s book-scanning project. Concerns include not only the quality of scanning
            and of metadata, but the possibility that libraries will discard physical copies of
            books for which scans are available <ptr target="#ucgbs2009"/>; <ptr target="#duguid2007"/>; <ptr target="#nunberg2009"/>; <ptr target="#samuelson2009"/>.  Also lost in most
            of these discussions is the distinction between scanning for search and access purposes
            (the Google approach) and scanning for preservation purposes, which has higher standards
            for image quality and for metadata <ptr target="#ninch2002"/>; <ptr target="#mass2006"/>; <ptr target="#greenstein2004"/>.</p>
               <p>Digital humanities projects have yet to achieve the scale of data, audience, or
            participation as the Sloan Digital Sky Survey.  However, several long-lived digital
            humanities projects have made important contributions to research methods and data
            quality.  Perseus is usually considered the first digital library in the humanities,
            with planning begun in 1985 and services available by 1987 <ptr target="#perseus2009"/>; <ptr target="#crane2001"/>; <ptr target="#marchionini1994"/>. The initial collections
            of Perseus cover the history, literature, and culture of the Greco-Roman world. They
            have since expanded into other areas, and conducted significant research on the
            classification, management, and use of visual and textual materials <ptr target="#crane2006"/>; <ptr target="#mahoney2002"/>; <ptr target="#smith2002"/>.  Rome Reborn, begun in 1997 at UCLA, was
            first concerned with digital library problems such as metadata, organization of
            historical and architectural periods, and representing relationships between textual
            sources and visual models <ptr target="#rome2009"/>;
            <ptr target="#frischer2009"/>. Now the
            system exists in multiple manifestations, supports three-dimensional
            <q>fly-throughs,</q> audio typical of the time period (including spoken Latin), and
            gladiator fights in the amphitheater using the latest computer graphics technology.
            Perseus, Rome Reborn, and newer projects such as HyperCities integrate map layers from
            Google Earth and other sources, which broadens their scope, audience, and
            interoperability with other components of the scholarly information infrastructure <ptr target="#hypercities2009"/>; <ptr target="#presner2010"/>.</p>
               <p>In sum, choices of data sources, research methods, and research problems are
            inextricably linked. Research methods in the sciences and in the humanities are becoming
            more data-driven.  The key to <q>better</q> data — that is, data suitable for curation, reuse, and sharing — is capturing data as cleanly as possible and as early as possible in its life cycle.  Agreements about data sources, structures, and formats will further the development of information infrastructure for digital humanities scholarship.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Collaboration</head>
               <p>The size of collaborations is increasing in all fields, as measured by the number of
            co-authors on papers, and at the fastest rate in the sciences <ptr target="#cronin2005"/>.  In
            sciences that rely heavily on instrumentation, such as astronomical observatories and particle accelerators, collaborations are large, diverse, and essential.  Sciences that are more inductive and are conducted in field settings, such as habitat biology, tend to work in smaller groups. Sciences of all sizes are grappling with data management issues, as data are the glue — and often the product — of collaboration.</p>
               <p>As noted above, the new forms of scholarship characterized by eResearch are information- and data-intensive, distributed, collaborative, and multi-disciplinary. Collaborations, when effective, produce new knowledge that is greater than the sum of what the participating individuals could accomplish alone.  In fields where collaboration is the norm, graduate students learn teamwork, whether in the laboratory, the field, or in group work on data collection and analysis.  Science dissertations frequently are carved out of larger group projects, with the student identifying a research problem worthy of sustained investigation.  Funding agencies in the sciences consider dissertations to be important products of awards to faculty investigators.  Dissertations and theses are listed explicitly in National Science Foundation annual reports, for example.</p>
               <p>While the digital humanities are increasingly collaborative, elsewhere in the humanities the image of the <q>lone scholar</q> spending months or years alone in dusty archives, followed years later by the completion of a dissertation or monograph, still obtains. Students often are discouraged from conducting dissertation research under a faculty grant. Instead, they are expected to spend yet more time identifying funding for solo research. When one is groomed to work alone and does so for the years required to complete the doctorate, collaborative practices do not come easily.</p>
               <p>Friedlander argues that for digital humanities to thrive, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#friedlander2009">one component must be a set
            of organizational topics and questions that do not bind research into legacy categories
            and do invite interesting collaborations that will allow for creative
            cross-fertilization of ideas and techniques and then spur new questions to be pursued by
            colleagues and students</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#friedlander2009" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>. As she
            suggests, the digital humanities need to move beyond large numbers of small,
            uncoordinated projects. Collaborative projects attract more resources and more
            attention.  If properly designed, they also may be more sustainable, creating platforms
            on which new projects can be constructed.  The plethora of boutique digital humanities
            projects risks the same fate as most digital learning objects. While intended for
            general use, they lack a common technical platform, common data structures, and common means to
            aggregate or decompose modules to a useful level of granularity <ptr target="#borgman2008"/>.</p>
               <p>An indicator of collaboration in the digital humanities community is the shift over the
            last two decades from a focus on the audience — those who might learn or appreciate the
            cultural content presented — to a focus on participation, in which scholars, students,
            and the public can contribute content or conduct their own investigations
            <ptr target="#ecai2009"/>; <ptr target="#ivanhoe2009"/>; <ptr target="#thl2009"/>; <ptr target="#presner2010"/>. The latter approach is more readily sustainable, as more people
            have vested interests in its capabilities and availability, and because it reflects
            current technical practices for Internet architecture <ptr target="#JacobsAndWalsh2004"/>; <ptr target="#swaw3c2009"/>.</p>
               <p>Scholarly collaboration is much studied but little understood.  Among the predictors of
            success are the ability to achieve a common vocabulary and shared knowledge
            <ptr target="#kanfer2000"/>; <ptr target="#olson2000"/>.  The more disciplines involved,
            the more effort is required to achieve common ground. Investments must be made in
            learning enough about each other’s disciplines that at least a pidgin language is
            established <ptr target="#galison1997"/>. Relationships take time, and must be nurtured.  One
            important measure of success, and a worthwhile goal in eResearch, is that papers
            suitable for publication in each of the participating disciplines arise from a joint
            project. The recent multi-national, multi-disciplinary, multi-year funding awards for
            innovative uses of data included several humanities-computer science partnerships <ptr target="#odh2009"/>.  Virtual Vellum, for example, applies advanced computational
            methods to explore authorship of 15th century manuscripts <ptr target="#ainsworth2009"/>. The results are likely to advance the state of optical character recognition and other computing techniques with broad application.</p>
               <p>In sum, the digital humanities community could benefit from more collaborative partnerships within the field and between the humanities and disciplines such as computer science.  Collaboration requires investment in listening skills, always being alert to nuanced differences in assumptions, theories, definitions, and methods.  Lessons and skills learned from these partnerships can enhance the scholarship of all participants. Common technology platforms also are important to achieve interoperability and sustainability, and can be leveraged as investments across projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Incentives to Participate</head>
               <p>Constructing a critical mass of data sources for scholarship in any field presumes that people will share the products of their research. Because data and collaboration are so central to the methods of digital scholarship, data sharing is an important indicator of success for eResearch, although practices are somewhat different in the sciences and in the humanities.</p>
               <p>The public nature of scholarship has deep roots. Notions of <q>open science</q> date
            back at least to Francis Bacon, with scientific findings being accepted only after peer
            review. Scholars’ incentives to share their results include recognition and acceptance
            of their work, which in turn drives hiring and promotion. In the sciences, authors may
            be required to release data as a condition of publishing the papers on which they are
            based.  Funding agencies also are becoming more assertive about the release of data that
            result from grants. However, publishing data is a far less mature practice than is
            publishing books and articles. Releasing a major dataset rarely brings as much
            recognition as releasing a major paper or book, but that balance is shifting, at least
            in the sciences <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>; <ptr target="#hey2009"/>.</p>
               <p>Scholars compete as well as collaborate, and thus have reasons <emph>not</emph> to share their data
            sources.  The following are disincentives that apply to all disciplines, albeit to
            varying degrees <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>:  (1) Faculty get more rewards for publishing papers and books than for releasing data; (2) the effort of individuals to document their data for use by others is much greater than the effort required to document them only for use by themselves and their research team; (3) data and sources offer a competitive advantage and are essential to establishing the priority of claims; and (4) data are often viewed as one’s own intellectual property to be controlled, whether or not the data (or their sources) are legally owned.  Means exist to address each of these concerns, but all are complex responses to a complex environment.</p>
               <p>The first disincentive is the most universal across disciplines.  The sciences and
            medicine are under the greatest pressure to release their data. In these disciplines the
            reward structure is adapting, and repositories and data structures exist.  While humanities scholars are under less pressure to release their data and sources, they are contributing models, modules, and tools to participatory projects and shared collections.</p>
            
               <p>Data documentation is an issue in all fields, but as the volume of data increases, consistent documentation becomes progressively more necessary.  Once data are captured cleanly, sharing them later becomes less of a problem.  Humanities scholars are acutely aware of the importance of metadata and finding aids in discovering sources. Metadata are equally important for data curation. Scholars understand the roles that documentation must play, while librarians and archivists have the expertise in documentation standards, practices, and technologies.  Data documentation is thus an obvious area of partnership for humanities scholars and information professionals, together addressing the requirements for sustainability of research products.</p>
               <p>The third disincentive — competitive advantage — is often addressed in the sciences
            through embargoes, whereby the investigators have a set period of time (from a few
            months to a few years, depending on the field) after the end of a grant before being
            required to share their data.  Embargoes serve two complementary purposes: they protect
            the scholars’ control over data, and they ensure that others will have access to the
            data within a reasonable time period. In the humanities, scholars are similarly
            concerned about controlling access to the sources of their data, whether the Dead Sea
            Scrolls or a set of manuscripts in a university archive, until they have published their
            research. As data sources such as manuscripts and out-of-print books are digitized and
            made publicly available, individual scholars will be less able to hoard their sources.
            This effect of digitization on humanities scholarship has been little explored, but
            could be profound. Open access to sources promotes participation and collaboration,
            while the privacy rules of libraries and archives ensure that the identity of
            individuals using specific sources is not revealed. Libraries and archives endeavor to
            maintain privacy in the use of digital as well as print sources. However, when digital
            content is controlled by commercial entities, protecting the privacy of users is a
            greater concern <ptr target="#mass2006"/>; <ptr target="#hoofnagle2009"/>.</p>
               <p>Intellectual property, the fourth disincentive to share data and sources, is the most
            intractable. The need to establish data sharing agreements in collaborative projects
            arose early in eScience initiatives and is far from resolved <ptr target="#david2003"/>; <ptr target="#davidspence2003"/>.  In the case of the sciences, ownership — or at least control — usually
            can be clarified through negotiation. If the research depends upon material acquired
            from others, such as cell lines, rules on data release will be governed by contract. The
            reliance of humanities scholarship on cultural records, as discussed above, creates
            particularly complex intellectual property challenges in the sharing of data. For
            example, an art historian usually can publish his or her notes, but not the paintings on
            which the research is based.  In the case of cultural models such as digital cities, it
            can be difficult to distinguish between data that represent an individual city and the
            model in which those data are incorporated. Difficulties in separating data from models
            (a problem in the sciences and in the humanities) plague both curation and data release
            efforts <ptr target="#hypercities2009"/>; <ptr target="#rome2009"/>; <ptr target="#save2009"/>.</p>
               <p>In sum, the digital humanities encounter most of the same incentives and disincentives for sharing data and sources faced by the sciences and by other disciplines.  The details play out somewhat differently, of course. The need to build critical masses of cultural sources and interoperable technology platforms affirms the need to broker agreements about data. If the infrastructure for the digital humanities errs toward openness, as is the norm in much of the sciences, the field will advance more quickly.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Learning</head>
               <p>The last comparison between the sciences and humanities, but by no means the least, is
            the role of information technology in learning. <soCalled>Cyberlearning,</soCalled> as argued by the
            National Science Foundation’s Task Force, can leverage the nation’s investment in
            cyberinfrastructure to benefit learning at all ages — <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#borgman2008">from K to
            grey</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#borgman2008"/>
                  </cit>.  This argument was made earlier in
            the humanities, claiming that cyberinfrastructure could serve the humanities both       
            for scholarship and for making cultural material more readily accessible for learning and
            outreach <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/>.  Cyberlearning is defined as the use of networked computing and communications technologies to support learning. The scope of cyberlearning concerns in the Task Force report was necessarily constrained to the U.S. and to the domains funded by the NSF, which do not include the arts and humanities. However, the Task Force noted explicitly that the value of cyberlearning encompasses the sciences, social sciences, humanities, and arts, and is an important international initiative.</p>
               <p>Several of the recommendations for advancing the state of cyberlearning have analogies
            for advancing the state of digital humanities.  One is the need to build a vibrant field
            by promoting cross-disciplinary communities, publishing best practices, and recruiting
            diverse talents. The Cyberlearning Task Force made a careful distinction between
            cyberlearning as learning <emph>with</emph> distributed computing technologies and
            workforce development as teaching people <emph>about</emph> cyberinfrastructure. The
            latter is also a concern of the National Science Foundation <ptr target="#cyber2007"/>.  In the humanities as in the sciences, people need to learn <emph>about</emph> cyberinfrastructure before they can learn <emph>with</emph> it — or use it for their research and teaching.</p>
               <p>Another analogous recommendation from the cyberlearning report is the need to instill a
            <q>platform perspective.</q>  As noted earlier, the takeup rate of digital learning
            modules has been limited by reliance on unique tools, proprietary software, and general
            lack of interoperability. Unless products are easily adapted to new uses, others have
            little incentive to invest in them. Both cyberinfrastructure and cyberlearning
            initiatives are constructing common technical platforms that will improve the
            sustainability and reuse of tools, services, and content.  Some of these technical
            platforms can be leveraged for digital humanities scholarship.  Where capabilities are
            lacking, the community can work in concert to construct them.  Common platforms and
            standards are among the goals of the Mellon-funded Bamboo project, for example <ref target="#pb2009">Project Bamboo 2009</ref>.</p>
               <p>The Cyberlearning Task Force also recommended initiatives to enable students to use
            data.  By embedding data skills early in the science curriculum — in the primary grades
            where feasible — students can learn to <q>think like
            scientists</q> early on.  Hands-on science approaches endeavor to engage students
            in <q>real</q> science, making it more interesting and exciting than purely textbook
            approaches <ptr target="#pea2003"/>. Projects like the Sloan Digital
            Sky Survey and eBird encourage individuals to contribute their observations — whether
            about the sky or about birds in their backyards — for use in scientific investigations
            <ptr target="#sloan2006"/>; <ptr target="#ebird2009"/>. The same promise applies to the
            humanities.  If students can explore cultural records from the early grades and learn to
            construct their own narratives, they may find the study of humanities more lively.  By
            the time they are college students, they will have learned methods of collaborative work
            and the use of distributed tools, sources, and services. Projects such as Perseus,
            HyperCities, and the Valley of the Shadow already enable students in humanities courses
            to engage in new forms of collaborative discourse <ptr target="#perseus2009"/>; <ptr target="#ayers2003"/>; <ptr target="#presner2010"/>.</p>
               <p>Lastly, the Task Force made a strong recommendation to the NSF to promote open
            educational resources. Educational content resulting from cyberlearning grants should be
            made available online with permission for unrestricted use and recombination.  New
            proposals for research and development in cyberlearning should include plans to make
            their materials available and sustainable.  These recommendations are relevant to all
            disciplines.  Open educational resources are growing rapidly in variety and number
            <ptr target="#atkins2007"/>; <ptr target="#baker2009"/>; <ptr target="#thierstein2009"/>.  Licensing models
            such as Creative Commons <ptr target="#creative2009"/> now include specific
            capabilities for licensing learning materials <ptr target="#cclearn2009"/> and
            scientific data <ptr target="#sc2009"/>.  Digital humanities projects, whether or not they include a learning component, also can benefit from Creative Commons licenses.  The owners of intellectual property retain their copyright; they simply license it for reuse under publicly stated conditions.  Intellectual property owned by others must not be appropriated, of course, but usually it can be linked if not specifically licensed.</p>
               <p>Openness matters for the digital humanities for reasons of interoperability, discovery,
            usability, and reusability.  Open resources — that is, those that can be used under
            license or are in the public domain — are more malleable for research and for learning.
            They can be mixed up and mashed up, and others can add value to them.  Resources that
            are available via open repositories also are more readily discovered than those posted
            on local websites <ptr target="#oerc2009"/>; <ptr target="#opened2009"/>; <ptr target="#case2006"/>; <ptr target="#atkins2007"/>.</p>
               <p>In sum, cyberlearning is important for the digital humanities for a number of reasons.  One is the need to learn how to use and how to evaluate digital cultural materials early; graduate school is rather late. Second is the need to build common technology platforms for digital humanities scholarship, which will advance the field by leveraging efforts and resources and by increasing interoperability.  Third is the value of open access to resources, which then become more malleable for research and for learning. Last is the need to build a strong community of digital humanities scholars, one that represents a much larger portion of the humanities than is the case today.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Summary</head>
               <p>My student’s complaint, <said>So what use are the digital libraries, if all they do is put digitally unusable information on the web?</said> nicely captures the challenges facing the humanities today. Digital content, tools, and services all exist, but they are not necessarily useful or usable. Much work remains to build the scholarly infrastructure necessary for digital scholarship to become mainstream in the humanities. Humanities scholars must lead the effort, because only they understand the goals and requirements for what <emph>should</emph> be built. Librarians, archivists, programmers, and computer scientists will be essential collaborators, each bringing complementary skills.</p>
               <p>A number of developments in cyberinfrastructure, eScience, and eResearch offer guidance to the digital humanities community in the quest to become a more established field with a broader base of infrastructure.  One is in the area of publication practices.  The humanities lag in digital publication of journals and books.  Digital publishing, while far from a panacea, offers a number of advantages in the speed, scope, and format of communication. Scholarly print publishing is on the decline, and those who publish only in print form risk being isolated, talking only to each other.  More digital-only venues are needed, where dynamic and visual work can be published in its vernacular form.</p>
               <p>Another area is the dissemination and use of data.  The humanities community should continue to clarify their choices of data and data sources, for these will drive what content is produced, captured, managed, and available for reuse.  Questions of data are closely related to research methods, which also are evolving.  Data-driven research methods are most valuable when they enable scholars to ask new questions in new ways.</p>
               <p>Collaboration is essential in digital humanities projects.  Few individuals have the range of expertise required to execute these projects alone.  Humanists should continue to seek out complementary partners and encourage people to listen and learn from each other.  Working together is also more likely to lead to common platforms and other means of reducing the overhead of technical projects.</p>
               <p>In both the sciences and the humanities, incentives to share one’s writing are more obvious than are incentives to share one’s data and sources.  In the sciences, data release is being encouraged (or required) by journals and funding agencies, and data-driven research methods can draw upon large corpora that grow as new observations are contributed. In the humanities, data release is less of an issue, but the availability of common technical platforms, tools, and services will promote the sharing of data and sources. The disincentives to share are complex in both the sciences and the humanities, but are being addressed.  As the sciences learn how to share data and to share credit for their findings, the humanities can build upon their best practices. Intellectual property constraints remain a major stumbling block, and the considerations vary between the sciences and the humanities.</p>
               <p>Opportunities for using cyberinfrastructure for learning exist in all disciplines.  Distributed access to scholarly content, common technical platforms, and open resources will advance the humanities as well as the sciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>A Call to Action</head>
               <p>In the process of developing the keynote presentation for the 2009 Digital Humanities Conference and in writing this paper, I consulted many individuals in the digital humanities community for their thoughts on the issues facing the field.  From these discussions and my analyses above, five pressing problems emerged.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>What are data?</head>
                  <p>What constitute data in the humanities? What are data sources? How are they made, shared, valued, used, and reused? Answering these questions will enable the digital humanities community to be more articulate about its scope and its goals, and better positioned to identify their requirements for infrastructure.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>What are the infrastructure requirements?</head>
                  <p>The sciences have struggled with this question for a decade or two already. They have
              convened workshops and study panels, and launched funding initiatives addressed
              specifically at defining, designing, and deploying the necessary infrastructure for
              eScience.  The humanities have tackled this question on a much smaller scale, leaving
              them in the position of building upon the infrastructure constructed by and for other
              disciplines.  As Johanna Drucker put it so well, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009">them is
                us</quote> 
                        <ptr target="#drucker2009"/>
                     </cit>.  It is time for the community to articulate its own requirements and to act upon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Where are the social studies of digital humanities?</head>
                  <p>Why is no one following digital humanities scholars around to understand their practices, in the way that scientists have been studied for the last several decades? This body of research has informed the design of scholarly infrastructure for the sciences, and is a central component of cyberinfrastructure and eScience initiatives. Given how rapidly scholarship in the humanities is evolving, it is fertile ground for behavioral research.  The humanities community should invite more social scientists as research partners and should make themselves available as objects of study.  In doing so, the community can learn more about itself and apply the lessons to the design of tools, services, policies, and infrastructure.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>What is the humanities laboratory of the 21st century?</head>
                  <p>This is a question of great concern to research libraries as well as to humanities scholars.  The library continues to be a laboratory for the humanities, but not the only laboratory.  Humanities scholars run computing laboratories and may work in distributed virtual environments for research and for learning. Humanists need to partner both with librarians and with the information technology planning and policy groups on their campuses.  These communities urgently need to <q>think together</q> about the common challenges faced in a time of shrinking budgets for collections, physical space, staffing, and technology services.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>What is the value proposition for digital humanities in an era of declining budgets?</head>
                  <p>For universities, the current economic recession is like no other.  Public and private universities alike are re-examining core principles as budgets are slashed by 10% to 30% from one year to the next.  Nothing is sacred, and <q>because it’s beautiful</q> is not a viable economic argument.  The sciences have been remarkably effective at making the argument for their value in economic and political terms, whether to university administrations, legislatures, funding agencies, or the general public.  While the humanities will have difficulty making parallel arguments in terms of economic competitiveness and medical advances, they have plenty to offer in terms of cultural understanding, writing and design skills, and critical thinking.  Digital scholarship also promotes technical skills, which can be highlighted.</p>
                  <p>Digital projects require resources in the form of computers, software, staff, and content.  Non-digital scholarship also costs money, of course, but more often in the form of travel and subsistence expenses for research in remote archives.  Tradeoffs in travel and digitization can be made more explicit.  The number of people who will use and benefit from any given project also can be made clearer. Investments in common technical platforms and standards that leverage resources across larger numbers of people and projects are easier to justify.</p>
                  <p>The digital humanities community has produced some beautiful work and made many
              advances in technology, design, and standards.  Now is the moment to consolidate that
              knowledge and to articulate the community’s requirements and goals.  Go forth and do
              great things...</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="acknowledgements">
               <head>Acknowledgements</head>
               <p>I am grateful to the colleagues who provided thoughtful commentary on an earlier draft
            of this paper, including Murtha Baca, Gregory Britton, and Maureen Whalen of the Getty
            Trust; Johanna Drucker, Alberto Pepe, Todd Presner, and Katie Shilton of UCLA; Amy Friedlander, Council on Library and Information Resources; Bernard Frischer, University of Virginia; Alexander Parker, Harvard University; and two anonymous reviewers.</p>
               <p>Many other people were very generous with their time in response to my inquiries about
            the past, present, and future of the digital humanities, including (in alphabetical
            order)  William Dutton, Oxford Internet Institute; Neil Fraistat, University of
            Maryland; Richard Furuta, Texas A&amp;M; Kimberly Garmoe, Anne Gilliland, UCLA; Charles Henry, Council on Library and Information Resources; Jason Hewitt, UCLA; Jieh Hsiang, National Taiwan University; Marina Jirotka, University of Oxford; Matthew Kirschenbaum, University of Maryland; Clifford Lynch, Coalition for Networked Information; Lev Manovich, University of California, San Diego; Ann O’Brien, Loughborough University; Susan Parker, UCLA; Allen Renear, University of Illinois; David Robey, University of Oxford; Ben Shneiderman, University of Maryland; Harold Short and Paul Spence, King’s College, London; Joshua Sternfeld, UCLA; Sarah Thomas, Bodleian Library; Sharon Traweek, UCLA; Anne Trefethen, University of Oxford; John Unsworth, University of Illinois; Sarah Watstein and Robert Winter, UCLA.</p>
            </div>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ainsworth2009" label="Ainsworth 2009" key="ainsworth2009">Ainsworth, P. (2009). Virtual Vellum.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.shef.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/virtualvellum.html">http://www.shef.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/virtualvellum.html</ref> on 31 December 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adho2009" label="Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations 2009" key="adho2009">Alliance
          of Digital Humanities Organizations.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2004" label="Anderson 2004" key="anderson2004">Anderson, I. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Are you being served? Historians and the search for primary sources</title>.
          <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 58: 81-129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="JacobsAndWalsh2004" label="Jacobs and Walsh 2004" key="JacobsAndWalsh2004">Architecture of the
          World Wide Web. (2004). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/</ref> on 2 June 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arxiv2009" label="ArXiv.org 2009" key="arxiv2009">ArXiv.org e-Print archive.  (2009).
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://arxiv.org/">http://arxiv.org/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arzberger2004" label="Arzberger et al. 2004" key="arzberger2004">Arzberger, P., Schroeder, P.,
          Beaulieu, A., Bowker, G. C., Casey, K., Laaksonen, L., Moorman, D., Uhlir, P. F. &amp;
          Wouters, P. (2004). <title rend="quotes">An International Framework to Promote Access to Data.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Science</title>, 303(5665): 1777-1778.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="atkins2007" label="Atkins et al 2007" key="atkins2007">Atkins, D. E., Brown, J. S. &amp;
          Hammond, A. L. (2007). <title rend="italic">A Review of the Open Educational Resources (OER) Movement:
          Achievements, Challenges, and New Opportunities</title>. William and Flora Hewlett Foundation.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.hewlett.org/oer">http://www.hewlett.org/oer</ref> on 9 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="atkins2003" label="Atkins et al. 2003" key="atkins2003">Atkins, D. E., Droegemeier, K. K.,
          Feldman, S. I., Garcia-Molina, H., Klein, M. L., Messina, P., Messerschmitt, D. G.,
          Ostriker, J. P. &amp; Wright, M. H. (2003). <title rend="italic">Revolutionizing Science
            and Engineering Through Cyberinfrastructure: Report of the National Science Foundation
            Blue-Ribbon panel on Cyberinfrastructure.</title> National Science Foundation. Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/cise/sci/reports/atkins.pdf">http://www.nsf.gov/cise/sci/reports/atkins.pdf</ref> on 18 September 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ayers2003" label="Ayers 2003" key="ayers2003">Ayres, E. L. (2004). <title rend="italic">The
          Valley of the Shadow.</title> University of Virginia. Retrieved from <ref target="http://valley.vcdh.virginia.edu/">http://valley.vcdh.virginia.edu/</ref> on 28 September 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bailey2005" label="Bailey 2005" key="bailey2005">Bailey, C. (2005). <title rend="italic">Open
          Access Bibliography: Liberating Scholarly Literature with E-Prints and Open Access
          Journals</title>. Washington, DC: Association of Research Libraries. Retrieved from <ref target="http://info.lib.uh.edu/cwb/oab.pdf">http://info.lib.uh.edu/cwb/oab.pdf</ref> on 28 September 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baker2009" label="Baker 2009" key="baker2009a">Baker, J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">It Takes a Consortium to
          Support Open Textbooks.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title>, 44(1): 30-33.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bates1996a" label="Bates 1996a" key="bates1996a">Bates, M. J. (1996a). <title rend="quotes">Document familiarity,
        relevance, and Bradford's law: The Getty online searching project report no. 5.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Information Processing &amp; Management</title>, 32(6): 697-707.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bates1996b" label="Bates 1996b" key="bates1996b">Bates, M. J. (1996b). <title rend="quotes">The Getty end-user
          online searching project in the humanities: Report No 6: Overview and conclusions.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">College &amp; Research Libraries</title>, 57(6): 514-523.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bates1993" label="Bates et al. 1993" key="bates1993">Bates, M. J., Wilde, D. N. &amp;
          Siegfried, S. L. (1993). <title rend="quotes">An analysis of search terminology used by
            humanities scholars — The Getty Online Searching Project Report No.1.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Library Quarterly</title>, 63(1): 1-39.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bates1995" label="Bates et al. 1995" key="bates1995">Bates, M. J., Wilde, D. N. &amp;
          Siegfried, S. L. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Research practices of humanities scholars in an online
          environment - The Getty Online Searching Project Report No. 3.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Library &amp; Information Science Research</title>, 17(1): 5-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bell2009" label="Bell et al. 2009" key="bell2009">Bell, G., Hey, T. &amp; Szalay, A. (2009).
          <title rend="quotes">Beyond the data deluge.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Science</title>, 323: 1297-1298.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bollen2008" label="Bollen &amp; Van de Sompel 2008" key="bollen2008">Bollen, J. &amp; Van de
          Sompel, H. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Usage Impact Factor: the effects of sample
            characteristics on usage-based impact metrics.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</title>, 59(1): 136-149.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman1999" label="Borgman 1999" key="borgman1999">Borgman, C. L. (1999). <title rend="quotes">What are digital
          libraries? Competing visions.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Information Processing &amp; Management</title>, 35(3): 227-243.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2000" label="Borgman 2000" key="borgman2000">Borgman, C. L. (2000).  <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to the Global Information Infrastructure: Access to Information in the Networked World.</title> Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2007" label="Borgman 2007" key="borgman2007">Borgman, C. L. (2007). <title rend="italic">Scholarship in the Digital Age: Information, Infrastructure, and the Internet</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2009" label="Borgman 2009" key="borgman2009a">Borgman, C. L. (2009). Scholarship in the
          Digital Age: Blurring the Boundaries between the Sciences and the Humanities.  Digital
          Humanities '09,  College Park, MD,  Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://works.bepress.com/borgman/216/">http://works.bepress.com/borgman/216/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2008" label="Borgman et al. 2008" key="borgman2008">Borgman, C. L., Abelson, H., Dirks,
          L., Johnson, R., Koedinger, K. R., Linn, M. C., Lynch, C. A., Oblinger, D. G., Pea, R. D.,
          Salen, K., Smith, M. S. &amp; Szalay, A. (2008). <title rend="italic">Fostering Learning in the Networked
          World: The Cyberlearning Opportunity and Challenge. A 21st Century Agenda for the National
          Science Foundation.</title> Report of the NSF Task Force on Cyberlearning. Office of Cyberinfrastructure and Directorate for Education and Human Resources. National Science Foundation. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/publications/pub_summ.jsp?ods_key=nsf08204">http://www.nsf.gov/publications/pub_summ.jsp?ods_key=nsf08204</ref> on 12 August 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgmanetal2007" label="Borgman et al. 2007" key="borgman2007b">Borgman, C. L., Wallis, J. C.,
          Mayernik, M. S. &amp; Pepe, A. (2007). <title rend="italic">Drowning in Data: Digital
            Library Architecture to Support Scientists’ Use of Embedded Sensor Networks</title>. Proceedings of the 7th Joint Conference on Digital Libraries,  Vancouver, BC,  Association for Computing Machinery.  269-277.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="buckland1991" label="Buckland 1991" key="buckland1991">Buckland, M. K. (1991). <title rend="quotes">Information as thing.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information Science</title>, 42(5): 351-360.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="case2006" label="Case 2006" key="case2006">Case, D. O. (2006).  <title rend="italic">Looking for Information: A Survey of Research on Information Seeking, Needs, and Behavior (2nd ed.)</title>. San Diego: Academic Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cclearn2009" label="ccLearn 2009" key="cclearn2009">ccLearn.  (2009). A Project of Creative
          Commons. Retrieved from <ref target="http://learn.creativecommons.org/">http://learn.creativecommons.org/</ref> on 6 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="choudhury2008" label="Choudhury et al. 2008" key="choudhury2008">Choudhury, S., DiLauro, T.,
          Szalay, A., Vishniac, E., Hanisch, R., Steffen, J., Milkey, R., Ehling, T. &amp; Plante,
          R. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Digital data preservation for scholarly publications in
          astronomy.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Digital
            Curation</title>, 2(2): 20-30. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/issue/view/3">http://www.ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/issue/view/3</ref> on 17 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="choudhury2007" label="Choudhury &amp; Stinson 2007" key="choudhury2007">Choudhury, S. &amp;
          Stinson, T. (2007). The Virtual Observatory and the Roman de la Rose: Unexpected
          Relationships and the Collaborative Imperative. Academic Commons. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.academiccommons.org/commons/essay/VO-and-roman-de-la-rose-collaborative-imperative">http://www.academiccommons.org/commons/essay/VO-and-roman-de-la-rose-collaborative-imperative</ref> on 22 July 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2006" label="Crane 2006" key="crane2006f">Crane, G. R. (2006). <title rend="quotes">What
        do you do with a million books?</title> 
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title>,
          12(3). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/march06/crane/03crane.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/march06/crane/03crane.html</ref> on 17 August 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2007" label="Crane et al. 2007" key="crane2007a">Crane, G. R., Babeu, A. &amp; Bamman, D.
          (2007). <title rend="quotes">eScience and the humanities.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">International Journal on Digital Libraries</title>, 7(1-2): 117-122.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2001" label="Crane et al. 2001" key="crane2001">Crane, G. R., Chavez, R. F., Mahoney, A.,
          Milbank, T. L., Rydberg-Cox, J. A., Smith, D. A. &amp; Wulfman, C. E. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Drudgery and deep thought: Designing a digital library for the
            humanities.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Communications of the Association for Computing Machinery</title>, 44(5): 35-4018. April 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="creative2009" label="Creative Commons 2009" key="creative2009">Creative Commons.  (2009).
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.creativecommons.org">http://www.creativecommons.org</ref> on 18 April 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cronin2005" label="Cronin 2005" key="cronin2005">Cronin, B. (2005). <title rend="italic">The Hand of Science:  Academic Writing and its Rewards</title>. Lanham, MD: Scarecrow Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cyber2007" label="National Science Foundation 2007" key="foundation2007">Cyberinfrastructure Vision for 21st Century Discovery (2007). National Science
          Foundation. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/">http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/</ref> on 17 July 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="david2003" label="David 2003" key="david2003">David, P. A. (2003). <title rend="quotes">The economic logic of <q>Open
        Science</q> and the balance between private property rights and the public domain in
        scientific data and information: A primer.</title> In <title rend="italic">The Role of the
        Public Domain in Scientific Data and  Information</title>. Washington, D.C., National
          Academy Press: 19-34. Retrieved from <ref target="http://siepr.stanford.edu/publicationsprofile/445">http://siepr.stanford.edu/publicationsprofile/445</ref> on 30 September 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="davidspence2003" label="David &amp; Spence 2003" key="davidspence2003">David, P. A. &amp; Spence, M.
          (2003). <title rend="quotes">Towards Institutional Infrastructures for E-Science: The Scope of the Challenge.</title>
          Oxford Internet Institute Research Reports: University of Oxford. Retrieved from <ref target="http://129.3.20.41/eps/le/papers/0502/0502002.pdf">http://129.3.20.41/eps/le/papers/0502/0502002.pdf</ref> on 30 September 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="odh2009" label="ODH 2009" key="odh2009">Digging into Data. (2009).
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.diggingintodata.org/">http://www.diggingintodata.org/</ref> on 31 December 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manifesto2008" label="Digital Humanities Manifesto 2008" key="manifesto2008">
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
          Manifesto</title> (2008). UCLA. Retrieved from <ref target="http://dev.cdh.ucla.edu/digitalhumanities/2008/12/15/digital-humanities-manifesto/">http://dev.cdh.ucla.edu/digitalhumanities/2008/12/15/digital-humanities-manifesto/</ref> on 3 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="doaj2009" label="Directory of Open Access Journals 2009" key="doaj2009">Directory of Open
          Access Journals. (2009). Open Society Initiative, Scholarly Publishing and Academic
          Resources Coalition. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.doaj.org">http://www.doaj.org</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="doar2008" label="Directory of Open Access Repositories 2008" key="doar2008">Directory of Open
          Access Repositories. (2008). University of Nottingham, UK and University of Lund, Sweden. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.opendoar.org">http://www.opendoar.org</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009" key="drucker2009b">Drucker, J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Blind Spots: Humanists must plan their digital future.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 55(30): B6. Retrieved from <ref target="http://chronicle.com/free/v55/i30/30b00601.htm">http://chronicle.com/free/v55/i30/30b00601.htm</ref> on 25 June 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="duguid2007" label="Duguid 2007" key="duguid2007">Duguid, P. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Inheritance and loss? A
        brief survey of Google Books.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">First Monday</title>, 12(8).
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/1972/1847">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/1972/1847</ref> on 3 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ebird2009" label="eBird 2009" key="ebird2009">eBird.  (2009). Cornell Lab of Ornithology and
          Audobon Society. Retrieved from <ref target="http://ebird.org/content/ebird/">http://ebird.org/content/ebird/</ref> on 9 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edwards2007" label="Edwards et al. 2007" key="edwards2007">Edwards, P. N., Jackson, S. J.,
          Bowker, G. C. &amp; Knobel, C. P. (2007). <title rend="italic">Understanding
          Infrastructure:  Dynamics, Tensions, and Design.</title> National Science Foundation:
          University of Michigan. NSF Grant 0630263. Retrieved from <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/49353">http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/49353</ref> on 26 July 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ecai2009" label="Electronic Cultural Atlas Initiative 2009" key="ecai2009">Electronic
          Cultural Atlas Initiative.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.ecai.org">http://www.ecai.org</ref> on 15 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eprints2010" label="EPrints 2010" key="eprints2010">EPrints.  (2010). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.eprints.org/">http://www.eprints.org/</ref> on 2 January 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foster2009" label="Foster 2009" key="foster2009">Foster, Ian (2009). eScience and Cloud
          Computing. American Association for the Advancement of Science. Chicago, IL. Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://www.slideshare.net/ianfoster/aaas-data-intensive-science-and-grid">http://www.slideshare.net/ianfoster/aaas-data-intensive-science-and-grid</ref> on 23 May 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="friedlander2008" label="Friedlander 2008" key="friedlander2008">Friedlander, A. (2008). <title rend="italic">Head in the Clouds and Boots on the Ground: Science, Cyberinfrastructure and
          CLIR.</title> Kanazawa Institute of Technology Library Roundtable. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/resources/articles.html">http://www.clir.org/pubs/resources/articles.html</ref> on 15 August 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="friedlander2009" label="Friedlander 2009" key="friedlander2009">Friedlander, A. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Asking
          questions and building a research agenda for digital scholarship.</title> In <title rend="italic">Working Together or
          Apart:  Promoting the Next Generation of Digital Scholarship</title>. Washington, DC, Council on
          Library and Information Resources. CLIR Publication No. 145: 1-15. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.clir.org">http://www.clir.org</ref> on 15 June 2009.</bibl>
        
            <bibl xml:id="frischer2009" label="Frischer 2009" key="frischer2009">Frischer, B. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Art and Science in the Age of Digital Reproduction: From Mimetic Representation to Interactive Virtual Reality.</title>  I Congreso Internacional de Arqueología e Informática Gráfica, Patrimonio e Innovación,  Sevilla, 17-20 de Junio de 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="galison1997" label="Galison 1997" key="galison1997">Galison, P. (1997).  <title rend="italic">Image and Logic:  A Material Culture of Microphysics</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gray2005" label="Gray et al. 2005" key="gray2005">Gray, J., Liu, D. T., Nieto-Santisteban,
          M., Szalay, A., DeWitt, D. &amp; Heber, G. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Scientific data management in the
          coming decade.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">CT Watch Quarterly</title>, 1(1). Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://www.ctwatch.org/quarterly/articles/2005/02/scientific-data-management/">http://www.ctwatch.org/quarterly/articles/2005/02/scientific-data-management/</ref> on 25 August 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gray2002" label="Gray &amp; Szalay 2002" key="gray2002">Gray, J. &amp; Szalay, A. (2002).
          <title rend="quotes">The world-wide telescope.</title> Communications of the ACM, 45(11): 51-55.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greenstein2004" label="Greenstein et al. 2004" key="greenstein2004">Greenstein, D., Ivey, B., Kenney, A.
          R., Lavoie, B. &amp; Smith, A. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Access in the Future
            Tense.</title> Council on Library and Information Resources. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub126/contents.html">http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub126/contents.html</ref> on 4 October 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamma2009" label="Hamma 2009" key="hamma2009">Hamma, K. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Professionally indisposed to change.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title>, 44(2): 8-9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hey2009" label="Hey et al. 2009" key="hey2009a">Hey, T., Tansley, S. &amp; Tolle, K. (Eds.).
          (2009). <title rend="italic">The Fourth Paradigm:  Data-Intensive Scientific
          Discovery</title>. Redmond, WA: Microsoft. Retrieved from <ref target="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/collaboration/fourthparadigm/">http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/collaboration/fourthparadigm/</ref> on 16 December 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoofnagle2009" label="Hoofnagle 2009" key="hoofnagle2009">Hoofnagle, C. J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Beyond Google and Evil: How policy makers, journalists, and consumers should
          talk differently about Google and privacy.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">First
            Monday</title>, 14(4). Retrieved from <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2326/2156">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2326/2156</ref> on 15 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hypercities2009" label="HyperCities 2009" key="hypercities2009">HyperCities.  (2009). UCLA.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.hypercities.com">http://www.hypercities.com</ref> on 17 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iath" label="Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities           2009" key="iath">Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities.  (2009). University of
          Virginia. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu">http://www.iath.virginia.edu</ref> on 6 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ivanhoe2009" label="Ivanhoe 2009" key="ivanhoe2009">Ivanhoe: a game of critical interpretation. 
          (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.speculativecomputing.org/ivanhoe/index.html">http://www.speculativecomputing.org/ivanhoe/index.html</ref> on 3 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jaschik2008" label="Jaschik 2008" key="jaschik2008">Jaschik, S. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Publishing and values.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Inside Higher
            Ed</title>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2007/08/22/anthro">http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2007/08/22/anthro</ref> on 10 March 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jaschik2009" label="Jaschik 2009" key="jaschik2009">Jaschik, S. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Farewell to the printed
          monograph.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed</title>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2009/03/23/michigan">http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2009/03/23/michigan</ref> on 24 March 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jpmc2000" label="Journal of Post Modern Culture 2000" key="jpmc2000">Journal of Post Modern
          Culture.  (2000). Retrieved from <ref target="http://pmc.iath.virginia.edu/">http://pmc.iath.virginia.edu/</ref> on 2 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jsah2009" label="Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians           2009" key="jsah2009">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.sah.org/index.php?src=gendocs&amp;ref=JSAH&amp;category=Publications">http://www.sah.org/index.php?src=gendocs&amp;ref=JSAH&amp;category=Publications</ref>
            on 2 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kanfer2000" label="Kanfer et al. 2000" key="kanfer2000">Kanfer, A. G., Haythornthwaite, C.,
          Bruce, B. C., Bowker, G. C., Burbules, N. C., Porac, J. F. &amp; Wade, J. (2000). <title rend="quotes">Modeling distributed knowledge processes in next generation multidisciplinary alliances.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Information Systems Frontiers</title>, 2(3-4): 317-331.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="king2006" label="King et al. 2006" key="king2006a">King, C. J., Harley, D., Earl-Novell, S.,
          Arter, J., Larence, S. &amp; Perciali, I. (2006). Scholarly Communication: Academic Values
          and Sustainable Models. Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, Center for Studies in Higher
          Education, University of California, Berkeley. Retrieved from <ref target="http://cshe.berkeley.edu/publications/publications.php?id=230">http://cshe.berkeley.edu/publications/publications.php?id=230</ref> on 28 July 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kurtz2010" label="Kurtz &amp; Bollen 2010" key="bollen2010">Kurtz, M. J. &amp; Bollen, J.
          (2010). <title rend="quotes">Usage bibliometrics.</title> In Cronin, B. (Ed.). <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Information Science and Technology</title>. Medford, NJ, Information Today. 44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="board2005" label="National Science Board 2005" key="board2005">Long-Lived Digital
          Data Collections.  (2005). National Science Board. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2005/nsb0540/">http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2005/nsb0540/</ref> on 18 April 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lynch2002" label="Lynch 2002" key="lynch2002">Lynch, C. A. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Digital collections, digital libraries and the digitization of cultural
          heritage information.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">First Monday</title>, 7(5). Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/949/870">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/949/870</ref> on 8 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lynch2003" label="Lynch 2003" key="lynch2003a">Lynch, C. A. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Life
          after graduation day: Beyond the academy's digital walls.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title>, 38(5): 12-13.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lynch1995" label="Lynch &amp; Garcia-Molina 1995" key="lynch1995">Lynch, C. A. &amp;
          Garcia-Molina, H. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Interoperability, scaling, and the digital libraries research
          agenda.</title> IITA Digital Libraries Workshop. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www-diglib.stanford.edu/diglib/pub/reports/iita-dlw/main.html">http://www-diglib.stanford.edu/diglib/pub/reports/iita-dlw/main.html</ref> on 1 October 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mahoney2002" label="Mahoney 2002" key="mahoney2002">Mahoney, A. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Finding texts in Perseus.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">New England Classical Journal</title>, 29(1): 32-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich2009" label="Manovich 2009" key="manovich2009a">Manovich, L. (2009). Cultural Analytics.
          Software Studies Initiative, University of California, San Diego. Retrieved from <ref target="http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2008/09/cultural-analytics.html">http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2008/09/cultural-analytics.html</ref> on 1 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marchionini1994" label="Marchionini &amp; Crane 1994" key="marchionini1994">Marchionini, G. &amp;
          Crane, G. R. (1994). <title rend="quotes">Evaluating hypermedia and learning:  Methods and results from the Perseus project.</title> ACM Transactions on Information Systems, 12(1): 5-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mass2006" label="Mass Digitization 2006" key="mass2006">Mass Digitization: Implications for
          Information Policy (2006). Report from <title rend="quotes">Scholarship and Libraries in
          Transition: A Dialogue about the Impacts of Mass Digitization Projects</title> —
          Symposium held on March 10-11, 2006, University of Michigan: National Commission on
          Libraries and Information Science. ED495775. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.eric.ed.gov/">http://www.eric.ed.gov/</ref> and <ref target="http://www.lib.umich.edu/mdp/symposium/NCLIS-report.pdf">http://www.lib.umich.edu/mdp/symposium/NCLIS-report.pdf</ref> on 10 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mith2009" label="Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities           2009" key="mith2009">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities.  (2009). University of
          Virginia. Retrieved from <ref target="http://mith.umd.edu/">http://mith.umd.edu/</ref> on 6 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monastersky2005" label="Monastersky 2005" key="monastersky2005">Monastersky, R. (2005). <title rend="quotes">The number that's devouring
          science.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 52(8): A12-A17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nctm2009" label="National Centre for Text Mining 2009" key="nctm2009">National Centre for
          Text Mining.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.nactem.ac.uk/">http://www.nactem.ac.uk/</ref> on 2 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ninch2002" label="NINCH 2002" key="ninch2002">NINCH Guide to Good Practice in the Digital
          Representation and Management of Cultural Heritage Materials (2002). National Initiative
          for a Networked Cultural Heritage. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.nyu.edu/its/humanities/ninchguide/">http://www.nyu.edu/its/humanities/ninchguide/</ref> on 8 September 2009.
        </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nunberg2009" label="Nunberg 2009" key="nunberg2009">Nunberg, G. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Google's Book Search: A Disaster for Scholars.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/Googles-Book-Search-A/48245/">http://chronicle.com/article/Googles-Book-Search-A/48245/</ref> on 3 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oecd2007" label="OECD 2007" key="oecd2007">OECD Principles and Guidelines for Access to Research Data from Public Funding (2007). Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oerc2009" label="OER Commons 2009" key="oerc2009">OER Commons.  (2009). Retrieved from
          <ref target="http://www.oercommons.org/">http://www.oercommons.org/</ref> on 18 April 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="olson2000" label="Olson &amp; Olson 2000" key="olson2000">Olson, G. M. &amp; Olson, J. S.
          (2000). <title rend="quotes">Distance matters.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Human-Computer Interaction</title>, 15(2-3): 139-178.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oaip2009" label="Open Archives 2009" key="oaip2009">Open Archives Initiative Protocol for
          Metadata Harvesting.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/">http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oca2009" label="Open Content Alliance" key="opencontent">Open Content Alliance.  (2009).
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.opencontentalliance.org/">http://www.opencontentalliance.org/</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="opencit2009" label="The Open Citation Project" key="opencit2009">
               <title rend="quotes">The effect
          of open access and downloads (<q>hits</q>) on citation impact: a bibliography of
          studies.</title> (2009). The Open Citation Project - Reference Linking and Citation
          Analysis for Open Archives. Retrieved from <ref target="http://opcit.eprints.org/oacitation-biblio.html">http://opcit.eprints.org/oacitation-biblio.html</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="opened2009" label="Open Education 2009" key="opened2009">Open Education.  (2009). A Project of
          Creative Commons. Retrieved from <ref target="http://opened.creativecommons.org/Main_Page">http://opened.creativecommons.org/Main_Page</ref> on 6 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="panstarrs2009" label="PAN-STARRS 2009" key="panstarrs2009">PAN-STARRS.  (2009). Panoramic Survey
          Telescope &amp; Rapid Response System. Retrieved from <ref target="http://pan-starrs.ifa.hawaii.edu/public/">http://pan-starrs.ifa.hawaii.edu/public/</ref> on 14 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pea2003" label="Pea. et al 2003" key="pea2003">Pea, R., Wulf, W. A., Elliott, S. W. &amp;
          Darling, M. A. (2003).  Planning for Two Transformations in Education and Learning
          Technology: Report of a Workshop. Washington, D.C.: National Academies Press. Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://www.nap.edu/catalog/10789.html">http://www.nap.edu/catalog/10789.html</ref> on 8 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perseus2009" label="Perseus Digital Library 2009" key="crane2009d">Perseus Digital Library. 
          (2009). Tufts University. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/</ref> on 3 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="poe2001" label="Poe 2001" key="poe2001">Poe, M. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Note to self:
        Print monograph dead; invent new publishing model.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">The
          Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>, 7(2). Retrieved from <ref target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0007.204">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0007.204</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="presner2010" label="Presner 2010" key="presner2010">Presner, T. S. (2010, forthcoming). <title rend="quotes">HyperCities:  Building a Web 2.0 learning platform.</title> In Natsina, A.
          &amp; Tagialis, T. (Eds.). <title rend="italic">Teaching Literature at a Distance</title>. London and New York, Continuum books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="presner2009" label="Presner &amp; Johanson 2009" key="presner2009a">Presner, T. S. &amp; Johanson, C. (2009).
          The Promise of Digital Humanities: A White Paper.  1-19. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.ucla.edu/">http://www.digitalhumanities.ucla.edu/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pb2009" label="Project Bamboo 2009" key="pb2009">Project Bamboo.  (2009). Retrieved from
          <ref target="http://projectbamboo.org/">http://projectbamboo.org/</ref> on 15 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reedijk2008" label="Reedijk &amp; Moed 2008" key="reedijk2008">Reedijk, J. &amp; Moed, H.
          (2008). <title rend="quotes">Is the impact of journal impact factors decreasing?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 64(2): 183-192.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rmoais2002" label="Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems 2002" key="committee2002">Reference Model for an Open Archival Information System.  (2002). Recommendation for
          Space Data System Standards, Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems Secretariat,
          Program Integration Division (Code M-3), National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://public.ccsds.org/publications/archive/650x0b1.pdf">http://public.ccsds.org/publications/archive/650x0b1.pdf</ref> on 4 October 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rpe2009" label="Research Papers in Economics 2009" key="rpe2009">Research Papers in
          Economics.  (2009). University of Connecticut. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.repec.org/">http://www.repec.org/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rice2008" label="Rice University 2008" key="rice2008">Rice University Press Mission
          Statement.  (2008). Retrieved from <ref target="http://rup.rice.edu/about/mission">http://rup.rice.edu/about/mission</ref> on 1 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rome2009" label="Rome Reborn 2009" key="rome2009">Rome Reborn.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.romereborn.virginia.edu/">http://www.romereborn.virginia.edu/</ref> on 17 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="samuelson2009" label="Samuelson 2009" key="samuelson2009">Samuelson, P. (2009). <title rend="quotes">The Dead Souls of the Google Book Search Settlement.</title> Communications of the Association for Computing Machinery, 52(7): 28-30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="scheiner2004" label="Scheiner 2004" key="scheiner2004">Scheiner, S. M. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Experiments,
        observations, and other kinds of evidence.</title> In Taper, M. L. &amp; Lele, S. R.
          (Eds.). <title rend="italic">The Nature of Scientific Evidence: Statistical, Philosophical, and Empirical Considerations</title>. Chicago, University of Chicago Press: 51-66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sc2009" label="Science Commons 2009" key="sc2009">Science Commons.  (2009). A Project of
          Creative Commons. Retrieved from <ref target="http://sciencecommons.org/about/index.html">http://sciencecommons.org/about/index.html</ref> on 6 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="swaw3c2009" label="Semantic Web Activity: W3C 2009" key="swaw3c2009">Semantic Web Activity:
          W3C.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/">http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/</ref> on 14 April 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="save2009" label="Serving and Archiving Virtual Environments 2009" key="save2009">Serving and
          Archiving Virtual Environments.  (2009). Serving and Archiving Virtual Environments.
          Retrieved from <ref target="http://www3.iath.virginia.edu/save/">http://www3.iath.virginia.edu/save/</ref> on 13 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sherpa2009" label="SHERPA/RoMEO 2009" key="sherpa2009">SHERPA/RoMEO: Publisher copyright
          policies &amp; self-archiving. (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.sherpa.ac.uk/romeo/">http://www.sherpa.ac.uk/romeo/</ref> on 12 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="siegfried1993" label="Siegfried et al. 1993" key="siegfried1993">Siegfried, S. L., Bates, M. J.
          &amp; Wilde, D. N. (1993). <title rend="quotes">A profile of end-user searching behavior
            by humanities scholars — The Getty online searching project report no. 2.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of The American Society for Information Science</title>, 44(5): 273-291.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sloan2006" label="Sloan Digital Sky Survey 2006" key="sloan2006">Sloan Digital Sky Survey. 
          (2006). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.sdss.org/">http://www.sdss.org/</ref> on 15 August 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2002" label="Smith et al. 2002" key="smith2002c">Smith, D. A., Mahoney, A. &amp; Crane, G.
          R. (2002). Integrating harvesting into digital library content. 2nd ACM IEEE-CS Joint
          Conference on Digital Libraries,  Portland, OR,  New York:  ACM.  183-184. Retrieved from
          <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/Articles/oaishort.pdf">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/Articles/oaishort.pdf</ref> on 4 October 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stone1982" label="Stone 1982" key="stone1982">Stone, S. (1982). <title rend="quotes">Humanities scholars: Information needs and uses.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 38(4): 292-313.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="src2009a" label="Survey Research Center 2009a" key="src2009a">Survey Research Center, Institute
          for Social Research.  (2009). University of Michigan. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.isr.umich.edu/src/">http://www.isr.umich.edu/src/</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="src2009b" label="Survey Research Center 2009b" key="src2009b">Survey Research Center,
          UC-Berkeley.  (2009). University of California, Berkeley. Retrieved from <ref target="http://srcweb.berkeley.edu/">http://srcweb.berkeley.edu/</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="szalay2008" label="Szalay 2008" key="szalay2008">Szalay, A. (2008). Jim Gray, astronomer.
          <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>, 51(11): 59-65.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="educause2009" label="EDUCAUSE 2009" key="educause2009">
               <title rend="quotes">The Case of the Textbook: Open
          or Closed?</title>  (2009). <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title>, 44(1): 13.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="effect2009" label="Effect of Open Access 2009" key="effect2009">The effect of open access and
          downloads (<hi rend="quotes">hits</hi>) on citation impact: a bibliography of studies.  (2009). The Open
          Citation Project - Reference Linking and Citation Analysis for Open Archives. Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://opcit.eprints.org/oacitation-biblio.html">http://opcit.eprints.org/oacitation-biblio.html</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="facts2005" label="Facts about Open Access 2005" key="facts2005">The Facts about Open Access: A
          Study of the Financial and Non-Financial Effects of Alternative Business Models on
          Scholarly Journals (2005). Kaufman-Wills Group LLC: Association of Learned and
          Professional Society Publishers. Retrieved from <ref target="http://sippi.aaas.org/Pubs/">http://sippi.aaas.org/Pubs/</ref> on 27 September 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thierstein2009" label="Thierstein 2009" key="thierstein2009">Thierstein, J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Education in the Digital Age.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title>, 44(1): 33-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tibbo2003" label="Tibbo 2003" key="tibbo2003">Tibbo, H. R. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Primarily history in
          America: How U.S. historians search for primary materials at the dawn of the digital
          age.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title>, 66 (Spring-Summer): 9-50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thl2009" label="Tibetan and Himalayan Library 2009" key="thl2009">Tibetan and Himalayan
          Library.  (2009). University of Virginia. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.thlib.org/index.php">http://www.thlib.org/index.php</ref> on 1 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ukrc2009" label="U.K. Research Council e-Science Programme 2009" key="ukrc2009">U.K. Research
          Council e-Science Programme.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/escience/default.htm">http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/escience/default.htm</ref> on 13 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ucgbs2009" label="University of California 2009" key="ucgbs2009">UC and the Google
          Book Settlement: Frequently Asked Questions.  (2009). University of California, Office of
          Scholarly Communication. Retrieved from <ref target="http://osc.universityofcalifornia.edu/google/faq.html">http://osc.universityofcalifornia.edu/google/faq.html</ref> on 3 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ukda2009" label="UK Data Archive 2009" key="ukda2009">UK Data Archive.  (2009). Retrieved
          from <ref target="http://www.data-archive.ac.uk/about/about.asp">http://www.data-archive.ac.uk/about/about.asp</ref> on 16 August 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ucps2009" label="University of California Publishing Services 2009" key="ucps2009">University
          of California Publishing Services.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.ucpress.edu/pubservices/">http://www.ucpress.edu/pubservices/</ref> on 2 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2006" label="Unsworth et al. 2006" key="unsworth2006">Unsworth, J., Courant, P., Fraser,
          S., Goodchild, M., Hedstrom, M., Henry, C., Kaufman, P. B., McGann, J., Rosenzweig, R.
          &amp; Zuckerman, B. (2006). Our Cultural Commonwealth: The Report of the American Council
          of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for Humanities and Social Sciences.
          American Council of Learned Societies. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/cyber.htm">http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/cyber.htm</ref> on 17 July 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanhouse2004" label="Van House 2004" key="vanhouse2004">Van House, N. A. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Science and technology studies and information studies.</title> In Cronin,
          B. (Ed.). <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Information Science and Technology</title>. Medford, NJ, <title rend="italic">Information Today</title>. 38: 3-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vectors2009" label="Vectors 2009" key="vectors2009">Vectors: Journal of Culture and Technology
          in a Dynamic Vernacular.  (2009). Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.vectorsjournal.org/">http://www.vectorsjournal.org/</ref> on 8 September 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whalen2009" label="Whalen 2009" key="whalen2009">Whalen, M. (2009). <title rend="quotes">What's
          wrong with this picture? An examination of art historians' attitudes about electronic publishing opportunities and the consequences of their continuing love affair with print.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Art Documentation</title>, 28(2): 13-22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wiberley2003" label="Wiberley 2003" key="wiberley2003">Wiberley, S. E. (2003). <title rend="quotes">A methodological approach to developing bibliometric models of types of humanities scholarship.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Library Quarterly</title>, 73(2): 121-159.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wiberley1994" label="Wiberley &amp; Jones 1994" key="wiberley1994">Wiberley, S. E. &amp; Jones,
          W. G. (1994). <title rend="quotes">Humanists Revisited — A Longitudinal Look At The Adoption Of Information
          Technology.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">College &amp; Research Libraries</title>, 55(6): 499-509.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willinsky2006" label="Willinsky 2006" key="willinsky2006">Willinsky, J. (2006). <title rend="italic">The Access Principle: The Case for Open Access to Research and Scholarship</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willinsky2009" label="Willinsky 2009" key="willinsky2009">Willinsky, J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Toward the Design
          of an Open Monograph Press.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>, 12(1). Retrieved from <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0012.103">http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0012.103</ref> on 1 April 2009.</bibl>

         </listBibl>
      
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>