<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Revista Digital Universitaria: A Workshop of Digital Editing at the Universidad
			Nacional Autónoma de México</title>
            <author>Ernesto Priani Saisó</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
			            <dhq:author_name>Ernesto <dhq:family>Priani Saisó</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
			            <dhq:affiliation>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</dhq:affiliation>
			            <email>epriani@gmail.com</email>
			            <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ernesto Priani Saisó was born and grown up in Mexico
				City. He entered to the Philosophy Faculty of the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de
				México and studied until he obtained the degree of Doctor in Philosophy. In 1990 he
				began to teach Medieval Philosophy and to work as an editor for the specialized
				newspaper, El Economista, at the same time.</p>
                  <p>In 1998 he began to work for one of the first web designing companies in Mexico and was
					the chief editor of sites such as Microsoft's official site for Latin America, the
					services provider, Universo Estudiantil, and many others. Since the year 2003 he is the
					editor of the Revista Digital Universitaria, an online magazine where he has developed a
					project, targeted to improve online creativity. At the present time, and besides
					teaching at the UNAM and editing the Revista Digital Universitaria, he hosts the radio
					broadcast <title rend="quotes">Ráfagas de pensamiento</title>, for the University Radio Channel, Radio UNAM.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
		          </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000014</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>opinion</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-09-12">12 September 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace" rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
         <change when="2008-06-16" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added
					publicationStmt, changed xref to ref for validation with new schema</change>
         <change when="2007-08-28" who="Julia Flanders">encoded document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Revista Digital Universitaria </title> (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx">http://www.revista.unam.mx</ref>) at the
				Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM) is an experimental digital magazine
				that serves as a <q>workshop of digital editing at the
				university</q>. In this article its editor explores how its authors and
				producers have experimented with the form and content of the publication.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>A digital magazine experiments with form</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>At the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM) an experiment in digital editing,
			promoting culture and developing forms of academic communication, called the <title rend="italic">Revista Digital Universitaria </title> (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx">http://www.revista.unam.mx</ref>), has set
			itself three goals, seeking not only their integration in a single publishing effort,
			but attempting also to surpass its own standards. While spreading what we now call
				<q>culture</q> to a general reading public, we are simultaneously learning
			to expand the possibilities of digital editing and demonstrating the potential of this
			new medium in the publication itself.</p>
         <div>
            <head>The Tradition of Promoting Culture and a Digital Magazine</head>
            <p>The law which established the university in 1945 gives it three main goals: to
				educate, to investigate and to promote culture. The third goal, <q>promoting culture,</q> is ambiguous, since <q>culture</q> has
				been a changeable concept for the university over the past sixty years; in the
				beginning it was understood as <q>knowledge about arts,</q> but nowadays,
				it comprises sciences, social studies and humanities. It can thus be understood as
				part of the social responsibility of the public university in Mexico, which has to
				provide cultural spaces and media for a nation that has no other means to develop
				them. But the concept can also be understood as all the activities performed inside
				those spaces and media, activities that tend to promote culture among the
				population. </p>
            <p>Magazines have been, since the first days, one of the tools created by the university
				to promote culture. The first magazine created to support this goal was the <title rend="italic">Revista de la Universidad de México</title>. During the 1940s,
				promoting culture was understood as promoting certain arts, basically graphical and
				lyrical. Later on, during the 1970s, some groups of scientists from the university
				began to promote natural science as an important branch of knowledge that had been
				forgotten by cultural promoters. During the next twenty years, then, many magazines
				attempted to promote scientific knowledge in the university, until the arrival in
				1998 of <title rend="italic">Cómo vez</title>, a print magazine that reports on science from the UNAM. The
				university, having separated the arts from science, now faces the challenge of
				promoting the more recent conceptualization of <q>culture,</q> that is,
				the humanities and social sciences, which don’t have this kind of channel. </p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Revista Digital Universitaria</title>, first published in
				the year 2000 (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.0/index.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.0/index.html</ref>), is sponsored by the
				Direccion General de Cómputo Académico, an administrative department which has
				played, and continues to play, a central role in the introduction of Web
				technologies and Internet services, not just to the University but to the entire
				country. Serving a community of 279,000 students and 41,000 teachers, the magazine
				acquires special duties and some advantages over its paper peers. Among these duties
				are the responsibility to be an inclusive and representative magazine for the entire
				university, to further the students’ education and teachers’ improvement, and to
				target general audiences. To achieve these goals, the magazine enjoys certain
				advantages. With no commitment to a single meaning of culture, it can publish
				articles about arts, humanities, social studies and science. It can, and actually
				must, develop investigative and editing techniques. It is committed to promoting
				culture with an appropriate diction, with interesting topics and with creative
				expositions. </p>
            <p>Although only six years old, the magazine has lived two ages. During the first one,
				the main purpose was to use the digital technology, but not to explore or to
				understand it. During the first three years, the editing guidelines of a paper
				magazine were applied to this digital publication. Doing so created some problems
				with the magazine’s personality, because it was compared with paper magazines, and
				also because it attempted to be a magazine of specialized investigations, but
				specializing in <q>everything</q>. </p>
            <p>In 2003, a new editorial team, the one which I lead, took charge of the magazine.
				While planning the next season of the magazine, we had to answer three main
				questions: What are the goals and duties for a digital magazine that should be
				representative of the whole university? How should we define the magazine’s
				personality, since we hadn’t defined the kind of content that would be included?
				What kind of editing guidelines must a digital magazine have? </p>
            <p>We answered those questions as follows. The magazine’s goals and duties are to create
				a space for innovation, development, practices and education in the world of digital
				publishing and to promote analysis, reflection and creation among the university’s
				population by means of digital resources. The supporting idea was and still is to
				make digital editing the main topic of the magazine, and to discover new tools, ways
				and guidelines for a rapidly developing area of publication that has not yet
				established its own rules. </p>
            <p>Our goal and our duty therefore coincide: the magazine should be the workshop of
				digital editing at the university. The magazine’s personality should emerge from the
				same idea: it is defined by its articles, which are digitally edited. That means a
				non-lineal publication that takes advantage of Internet resources such as hypertext,
				graphics, image and audio, regardless of their source or the topic of the article —
				science, arts or social studies — so that we can test the web’s possibilities for
				publication. </p>
            <p>All of this resulted in two basic challenges. Who would be the authors, designers,
				editors and programmers? Because there were no digital editors in Mexico in 2003, we
				didn’t have a proper culture of digital publishing. In finding authors, we had two
				problems. First, we needed a great number of authors to get enough articles for a
				monthly publication. Second, we needed authors who could think in digital terms. And
				it was the same for editors, designers and programmers; we needed them to think in
				digital terms. </p>
            <p>We solved the amount problem by turning the magazine into a monographic publication.
				Every month we propose a main topic and give it to a manager — commonly a
				professional investigator in the corresponding area — who contacts the authors on
				his own. The number of articles in each issue depends mainly on the manager’s
				leadership. But finding authors, editors, designers and programmers who can think in
				digital terms remains our principal job, because the magazine has a pedagogical
				role. Since it promotes the use of new technologies, we need to develop an
				intentional strategy to educate the new professionals for the new media. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Abilities for the Digital Medium</head>
            <p>When we asked ourselves how to educate and inform editors, designers, programmers and
				writers for the environment of digital publishing, we realized that the magazine and
				its collaborators must develop, beyond the proper use of digital tools, some
				abilities that could make possible the digital representation of scientific,
				humanistic, technical, artistic and cultural languages. The goal was that, by means
				of those abilities, the magazine and its editors, designers, programmers and writers
				would be able to make the digital expression of those languages and styles offer
				something different and better than its written expression. Since the magazine
				itself has been an experimenting and teaching tool, it is possible, in the course of
				developing those abilities, to follow the road of tentative solutions, in the first
				place, and the way of the magazine’s consolidation, in the second, in order to get a
				digital rebuilt of languages and expressions. </p>
            <div>
               <head>From Text to Digital Revision</head>
               <p>In the beginning, like many other digital magazines, the <title rend="italic">Revista Digital Universitaria</title> tried to simulate a paper magazine,
					using the screen as if it was a sheet of paper, and using the home page as a
					magazine cover (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/indexabr01.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/indexabr01.html</ref>). The first meaningful
					step toward leaving behind the <q>simulation</q> trend was to break
					the lineal sequence of texts and, therefore, the unity of the page. We did that
					by digitally revising the text, creating a net which represented its logical
					structure with a menu (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.4/num3/art5/art5.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.4/num3/art5/art5.html</ref>). The change
					demonstrated its advantages, not only because it eased the process of reading
					the screen, by shortening the length of the texts, but also because it changed
					the reading logic from a sequential model to one with different alternatives on
					the same level. That means that we left behind the visual metaphor of the pages
					that can be turned, and created a new model of links between different segments
					which contain logical components. Soon, the solution became a standard model for
					the magazine. </p>
               <p>Today, the representation of the logical structure of the text in a menu is a
					widely developed ability among editors, designers and some authors. It is true
					that we have faced the challenge of revising entire articles with inappropriate
					structures, or made the reading difficult instead of easing it. In that we
					clearly failed. There are some examples of that failure (<ref target="http://www.//www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num4/art25/art25.htm">http://www.//www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num4/art25/art25.htm</ref>). But
					beyond those difficulties, this step established a new order for the publishing
					process and therefore an opening to new alternatives for the digital
					representation of the text. </p>
               <p>The nature of those alternatives was revealed by a wrongly solved problem. It was
					an article about the image and its reading (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num9/art60/art60.htm">http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num9/art60/art60.htm</ref>); although it
					was the analysis of graphical material, it was difficult, because of the lineal
					writing, to establish a dialogue between the text and the image. When we
					represented the text’s structure with a menu, we weren’t able to create a useful
					relation between images and texts and we didn’t get the author to understand
					that it would be better to divide his text by linking it with the fragmented
					image, and to use the graphics but not the text as a guideline for his analysis.
					The solution that we gave him — to set the image corpus on one side, and the
					improperly segmented text on the other — showed us the next step to revising the
					different scientific languages. We had to apply segmentation and make the most
					of the digital tools, which allow revising underlying elements of the text, like
					content nets and structures, inherent to sciences and humanities. </p>
               <p>In the articles just mentioned, those elements were the links between the image
					and its analysis. Although we took some steps in that direction, we couldn’t
					improve the text value and include some underlying nets until we got an article
					about fish. In fact, the problem with the articles about fish (a whole issue,
						<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_agosto05.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_agosto05.html</ref>) was that editors
					understood neither the terminology nor the content relevance of those articles,
					which came from a very specialized branch of science. So we decided to talk with
					the authors, in order to clarify terms and relevance, and we took this dialogue
					to the final article. We highlighted some relevant and specialized concepts and
					linked them with a body of descriptive notes; that was a successful solution and
					we will apply it again in some scientific papers. </p>
               <p>The solution of including underlying nets in the texts is not completely
					developed and, as happened with an article about visual anthropology (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.7/num9/art75/int75.htm">http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.7/num9/art75/int75.htm</ref>), we can link
					theoretical, informative and critical elements to a cinematographic document, in
					order to enlarge the comprehension of the film. Then, the main ability that the
					magazine creators have to develop is an identification of the elements which
					accomplish or really enlarge collaborations, because they are some of the
					essential values of any form of digitalization. Also, as we discovered early,
					those <q>enlargements</q> are part of and are used for the digital
					reconstruction of the style of cultural promotion. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Searching for New Narratives</head>
               <p>When we approach promotion, we don’t target experts but general audiences without
					specialized knowledge about the topics that they read about. That implies a
					different writing style, one which uses certain narrative and graphic resources
					to obtain the expected communication and to cause the expected effects on the
					readers. Science has been the main creator of this language and has formed the
					basis of cultural promotion. We have to recognize that this particular language
					has not been adopted by the humanities and social studies, which find no point
					in modifying their narratives in order to make them easier to understand. For
					them, promotion is only the diffusion of content, not the use of a different
					language. </p>
               <p>In any case, the Internet is a medium specially qualified to go beyond the
					cultural promotion style, because it not only eases the integration of
					underlying elements — as we have said — but also incorporates alternative
					narratives to attract non-specialized readers. In one case, we received an
					article, written as a play, about Kepler’s doctrine (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num5/art29/intro.htm">http://www.revista.unam.mx/vol.5/num5/art29/intro.htm</ref>). We tried to
					represent this in a narrative-dramatic style, using an object with an animated
					structure in which the characters of the play <q>act</q> the play,
					following the reading time. The result was very interesting; we found that we
					could graphically rebuild some narrative structures and use this graphic
					representation to create forms of interaction between the content of the
					magazine and the <q>reader,</q> in order to inspire the expectation
					and interest about knowing something new. </p>
               <p>So we explore other forms to do this. In the issue about Kant (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/indexdic04.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/indexdic04.html</ref>) we used the underlying
					nets and explored the forms of alternative narrative to produce expectation in
					the reader. First we used the image as a map. The picture on the cover became a
					map that guides the reader through the different articles. So the image is, at
					the same time, the structure for a possible reading, a point of view from the
					main character in the same image, and a reference to an underlying net, because
					the image is also a text to be read. It’s not casual that Kant’s butler is the
					one who introduces the text about the picture. Who are the characters over
					there? And when, why and about what are they talking? Also, the picture presents
					the Kantian ideas that merge during an after-dinner chat, among other things. </p>
               <p>By means of the exploration of alternative narratives, like the ones that turn
					the image into text and the text into image, the magazine’s authors and
					producers have tried to develop the ability of building machines, as well as
					mazes, maps, hieroglyphics, calligraphy and instructions in different time
					sequences, in which the construction of a new narrative goes beyond the
					differences of styles and surpasses the limitations of the language of
					promotion. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Towards Digital Creation</head>
               <p>As a result of all this experimentation with the texts, we have found that
					digital editing could be a device for constructing new narratives and new
					languages beyond the traditional narratives as well as humanities, sciences,
					arts or even promotion. That’s because the use of words and forms in the digital
					sphere creates different orders for writing; those orders are not unknown to
					literature — let’s remember the <hi rend="italic">carmina figurata</hi> or the
					graphic poems of José Juan Tablada — but they mean new ways to transform the
					narrative of a text. In our particular case they let us make it more attractive
					for a bigger audience, helping us to solve the difficulties implied by the use
					of technical narratives by some authors. In other words, digital editing can
					generate reading and meaning processes, parting from a digital rewriting which
					exploits the relation between graphic, sound, video, animation and words, and
					becomes a tool that promotes knowledge. </p>
               <p>Following this route, the magazine has continued with its experimentation, but
					now searching for creations produced specifically in and for the digital media.
					We aim to go beyond the digital representation of the text, towards its digital
					production. We have approached to this by two roads. We have published some
					experimental projects that authors send to the magazine and organized a workshop
					of digital creation, whose final results were presented on the magazine’s issue
					of December, 2006 (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_dic06.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_dic06.html</ref>). </p>
               <p>One example of the first initiative is <q>The case of the
						penalty that never happened</q> (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_junio05.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_junio05.html</ref>). The idea is to
					provide a sequence that motivates the reader to reflection. The sequence has two
					dimensions; it begins with a graphic, continues with a listing and then opens a
					structure where the reader can choose between many options, parting from his own
					convictions. The final sequence is a reflection on the impossibility of breaking
					personal rules-–that means a reflection on the impossibility of moral failing —
					and can have different endings, according to the reader’s ability to understand
					that in certain normative structures, like the ones of soccer, the rule is
					fulfilled even when the referee makes a mistake. </p>
               <p>In the December issue (<ref target="http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_dic06.html">http://www.revista.unam.mx/index_dic06.html</ref>), the digital objects
					that resulted from the workshop follow two directions. The first is the one that
					we have called <q>digital intervention</q> in the text. The second one
					is the direct production of objects, conceived as digital since its origin. One
					main activity of the workshop directed by the magazine was to ask the assistants
					to choose a poem, give it a digital representation and intervene in its cadence,
					rhythm, meaning, sequence and reading. The idea behind this experiment was to
					show that, when taken to the digital media, the text can be modified in other
					aspects than its structure or graphics, and can be turned into something else;
					maybe another poem, or maybe another thing, like a prize. Talking about the
					production of digital objects, the workshop searched for two goals: production,
					as a prime achievement, but also, as a second goal, the way in which these
					objects can be described. </p>
               <p>The creative results — the production of objects — were interesting and followed
					two directions. First, producing objects with a basic textual component, and
					second, producing objects without text, to make the best join of images, sounds
					and interactivity. Both are, of course, the first steps given by the magazine
					towards the digital creation and they represent, by now, the first approach to
					the production of originally digital objects for a digital magazine. </p>
               <p>The secondary goal of the production of digital objects, that of
						<q>description,</q> is a topic that has concerned the magazine’s
					developers for a long time. As we are a magazine that not only receives authors
					who are trained in the use of digital tools, but also tries to show the
					advantages of digital editing, even to those writers who aren’t familiar with
					the digital media, one of our challenges has been to explain to authors how they
					can expose their ideas in order to be published by the magazine’s developers.
					The intention is that the <q>description</q> model serves also to
					promote some of the extensions that digitalization can incorporate to the text. </p>
               <p>The creation of a standard <q>description</q> for the objects — we
					don’t even know if we must call it <q>script</q> — is still in
					process, but it has already generated different discussions about the profile
					and the technical abilities (or the lack of them) of the digital author; and
					also about the possibility of translating intentions and digital ideas by means
					of maps or guides of the object, which designers, editors and programmers can
					follow. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>A Conclusion as a Step</head>
            <p>The nature of the <title>Revista Digital Universitaria</title> and its immediate
				challenge and goals, have led us to explore the nature of digital editing, its aims,
				and its possibilities to enlarge the academic communication and the promotion of
				knowledge. Our work is far from ended, of course. But in the latter years we have
				built the bases to promote the culture of digital editing and to form a group of
				editors, designers and programmers who can think in digital terms. It is hard to
				foresee who the digital authors of the future will be. We don’t know if they will be
				experts in the technical aspects of Internet and multimedia, or authors deeply
				concerned with the creation of texts and their digital interventions or
				representations. </p>
            <p>Anyway, the main goal of the magazine, by now, remains the same; to create the tools
				and the experimental spaces for any kind of author, the highly technical or the
				essentially creative. Finally, the magazine is still an invitation to explore on the
				digital editing world. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>