<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reinventing the Classroom Edition: <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>
               Book IX Flash Audiotext</title>
            <author>Olin Bjork</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Olin <dhq:family>Bjork</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Georgia Institute of Technology</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>olin.bjork@lcc.gatech.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Olin Bjork is a Marion L. Brittain Postdoctoral Fellow at the Georgia Institute
                     of Technology, where he teaches courses in composition, literary/cultural
                     studies, technical communication, and web design. His research interests
                     include John Milton, Textual Studies, the Digital Humanities, Instructional
                     Technology, and Computers and Writing. He recently received his Ph.D. in
                     English from the University of Texas at Austin, where he served as assistant
                     director of the Computer Writing and Research Lab (CWRL), taught literature and
                     composition courses in the CWRL's computer-assisted classrooms, and worked as
                     the English department's webmaster. For the past several years, he has worked
                     as technical editor of an electronic edition of John Milton's Paradise Lost
                        <ref target="http://www.laits.utexas.edu/miltonpl"
                        >http://www.laits.utexas.edu/miltonpl</ref> and, more recently, an
                     electronic edition of Walt Whitman's Leaves of Grass <ref
                        target="http://www.laits.utexas.edu/leavesofgrass"
                        >http://www.laits.utexas.edu/leavesofgrass</ref>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000056</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-06-16" who="jhf">Initial encoding</change>
         <change when="2009-08-05" who="Alyssa">added bio, teaser and corrections</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>In the spring of 2005, a grant
               from the University of Texas at Austin made possible the development of a digital classroom edition of
               <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>, John Milton's seventeenth-century
               poem. The resulting prototype <q>audiotext</q> of Book Nine of the twelve-book epic
               incorporates and synchronizes text, explanatory notes, and audio within a Flash
               interface that resembles a book lying open on a table.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Flash audiotext edition gives new voices to Milton's timeless epic</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Poster Abstract</head>
            <p>In the spring of 2005, Professor John Rumrich and I applied for and received a grant
               from the University of Texas at Austin to develop a digital classroom edition of
                  <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>, John Milton's seventeenth-century
               poem. Our prototype <q>audiotext</q> of Book Nine of the twelve-book epic
               incorporates and synchronizes text, explanatory notes, and audio within a Flash
               interface that resembles a book lying open on a table. It uses a karaoke-style moving
               highlight to indicate the line currently being played in the audio track and a
               stationary highlight to mark annotated words and phrases. The application allows
               students to read the notes with less disruption to the reading experience than is
               possible with footnotes or endnotes: when the audiotext is in annotation mode, notes
               replace the text on the page opposite the one being read/heard. During audio
               playback, furthermore, the pages turn automatically, largely alleviating the
               interruption of page-turning and so encouraging users to continue reading. The
               guiding principle of our interface runs counter to that of hypertext theory and
               praxis — we seek to keep the user centered and focused on the primary text, which
               students find difficult to read due to its intricate syntax and archaic expressions.
               To facilitate an adequate depth of immersion, we avoid implementing potentially
               distracting website features that are useful in some contexts but have made reading
               literature online an unappealing prospect for many: hyperlinks, pop-up windows, and
               scrollbars. The audio voiceover serves to increase reading comprehension and
               confidence by allowing users to listen to experienced readers whose understanding of
               the poem is communicated through vocal pacing and inflection. The audiotext's
               combination of oral and visual language is especially fitting for an epic poem like
               Paradise Lost, which the blind Milton dictated to scribes. In alternative viewing
               modes, students can type and save their own notes and display a semi-diplomatic
               transcript of our 1674 copy-text (with a font similar to the original) in parallel
               with our modernized, annotated, reading (and listening) text. We have recently added
               audiotexts of books one and two of the epic to the project website at <ref
                  target="http://www.laits.utexas.edu/miltonpl"
                  >http://www.laits.utexas.edu/miltonpl</ref>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Poster</head>
            <p>Download <ref target="resources/images/figure01.pdf">poster</ref> (PDF file) <graphic
                  url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
