<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mining Eighteenth Century Ontologies: Machine Learning and Knowledge
               Classification in the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>
            </title>
            <author>Russell Horton</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Russell <dhq:family>Horton</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Library Development Center, University of
                  Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>russ@diderot.uchicago.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Russell Horton is a research programmer at The ARTFL Project and the Digital
                     Library Development Center at the University of Chicago, where he received his
                     BA in Linguistics in 2002. He works on machine learning and text analysis
                     software for the humanities.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Robert Morrissey</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Robert <dhq:family>Morrissey</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rmorriss@uchicago.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Robert Morrissey, who began teaching at the University of Chicago in 1978,
                     earned his Ph.D. with honors in French literature in 1981. Morrissey
                     specializes in 18th- and 19th-century French history, literature and critical
                     theory. His work concentrates on themes and cultural currents over the longue
                     durée. Professor Morrissey is the director of the ARTFL Project and editor of
                     the online edition of Diderot and d'Alembert's Encyclopédie.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Mark Olsen</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Mark <dhq:family>Olsen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>ARTFL Project, University of Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>markymaypo57@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p> Mark Olsen is the Assistant Director of the ARTFL Project at the University of
                     Chicago. Mark received his Ph.D. in French history from the University of
                     Ottawa in 1991 and has been involved in digital humanities and computer-aided
                     text analysis since the mid-1980s. His current ambition is to write a biography
                     of the Marquis de Pastoret by candle-light with a quill. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Glenn Roe</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Glenn <dhq:family>Roe</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>ARTFL Project, University of Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>glenn@diderot.uchicago.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Glenn Roe is a Ph.D. candidate in the Department of Romance Languages and
                     Literatures and a Senior Project Manager at the ARTFL Project, both at the
                     University of Chicago. Aside from his research interests in computer-assisted
                     text analysis and knowledge classification during the French Enlightenment and
                     19th century, Mr. Roe's doctoral work is primarily concerned with the
                     intersection of history and literature in the work of the French essayist and
                     poet Charles Péguy.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Robert Voyer</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Robert <dhq:family>Voyer</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Powerset</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rlvoyer@diderot.uchicago.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Robert Voyer recently joined the ranks at Powerset as a computational linguist.
                     Before joining the natural language search world, Robert worked as a research
                     developer for The ARTFL Project at the University of Chicago, where he also
                     earned his MS in Computer Science and BA in Romance Languages.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000044</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-06-18">18 June 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2008" who="AR">Encoded document</change>
         <change who="Melanie Kohnen" when="2008-12-18">Added bios and teaser</change>
         <change who="Melanie Kohnen" when="2009-01-13">Added email addresses</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> of Denis Diderot and Jean le Rond
               d'Alembert was one of the most important and revolutionary intellectual products of
               the French Enlightenment. Mobilizing many of the great – and the not-so-great –
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">philosophes</foreign> of the 18th century, the <title
                  rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> was a massive reference work for the arts and
               sciences, which sought to organize and transmit the totality of human knowledge while
               at the same time serving as a vehicle for critical thinking. In its digital form, it
               is a highly structured corpus; some 55,000 of its 77,000 articles were labeled with
               classes of knowledge by the editors making it a perfect sandbox for experiments with
               supervised learning algorithms. In this study, we train a Naive Bayesian classifier
               on the labeled articles and use this model to determine class membership for the
               remaining articles. This model is then used to make binary comparisons between
               labeled texts from different classes in an effort to extract the most important
               features in terms of class distinction. Re-applying the model onto the original
               classified articles leads us to question our previous assumptions about the
               consistency and coherency of the ontology developed by the Encyclopedists. Finally,
               by applying this model to another corpus from 18th century France, the <title
                  rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux, or Mémoires pour l'Histoire des Sciences &amp;
                  des Beaux-Arts</title>, new light is shed on the domain of Literature as it was
               understood and defined by 18th century writers. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Examining the classification of knowledge in the Encyclopédie of Diderot and
               d'Alembert</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Mining Eighteenth Century Ontologies: Machine Learning and Knowledge Classification
            in the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>.</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction </head>
            <p>One of the crowning achievements of the 18th-century Enlightenment was the <title
                  rend="italic">Encyclopédie ou Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et des
                  métiers, par une société de gens de lettres</title>, edited by Diderot and
               d'Alembert. Published in Paris between 1751 and 1772, in 17 volumes of text and 11
               volumes of plates, it contains some 77,000 articles written by more than 140
               contributors. The <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> was a massive reference
               work for the arts and sciences, as well as a <foreign xml:lang="fr">machine de
                  guerre</foreign> that served to propagate Enlightenment ideas. The impact of the
                  <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> was enormous. Through its attempt to
               classify learning and to open all domains of human activity to its readers, the
                  <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> gave expression to many of the most
               important intellectual and social developments of its time.<note>For an exhaustive
                  treatment of the Encyclopédie and its authors, see <ptr target="#schwab1984"/>.
                  For a more general discussion of the work, see <ptr target="#proust1995"/>. The
                  ARTFL implementation of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> is discussed
                  in <ptr target="#morrissey2001"/>, and <ptr target="#andreev1999"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The scale and ambition of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> inspired its
               editors to adopt three distinct modes of organization which, taken together, Diderot
               described as encyclopedic: dictionary, hierarchical classification, and the
                  <emph>renvois</emph> (cross-references). The interaction of these three modes has
               led modern commentators to describe the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> as
               an <q>ancestor of hypertext</q> and to depict Diderot as <q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">l'internaute d'hier</foreign>
               </q> (<q>websurfer <foreign xml:lang="fr">avant la lettre</foreign>
               </q>) <ptr target="#brian1998"/>. D'Alembert underscores the importance of the
               organization of knowledge in the <title rend="italic">Discours Préliminaire</title>:
                  <quote rend="block" source="#hoyt1965">As an <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopedia</title>, it is to set forth the <emph>order</emph> and
                     <emph>connection</emph> of the parts of human knowledge. As a <title
                     rend="italic">Reasoned Dictionary of the Sciences, Arts, and Trades</title>, it
                  is to contain the general principles that form the basis of each science and each
                  art...and the most essential facts that make up the body and substance of
                     each.<note>English translation cited in <ptr target="#hoyt1965" loc="xxiii"/>
                     (our emphasis).</note>
               </quote> Of the three modes of organization, the dictionary mode (organization of
               entries in alphabetical order) is certainly the simplest and the most arbitrary. The
               second mode of organization is classification, wherein each dictionary entry is
               assigned to a <q>class of knowledge,</q> placing it within the <q>order</q> of human
               understanding, as depicted in the <title rend="italic">Système Figuré des
                  connaissances humaines</title>. Modeled after Bacon's classification of knowledge
               and Enlightenment theories of epistemology, all understanding is founded upon memory,
               reason, or imagination, with numerous categories and sub-categories branching out
               from these three faculties.<note>For various representations of the <title
                     rend="italic">Système Figuré</title> and the Editors' descriptions, see <ref
                     target="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/artfl/projects/encyc/texts/"
                     >http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/projects/encyc/texts/</ref> and <ref
                     target="http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cactus/"
                     >http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cactus/</ref>.</note> However, simply placing an
               entry into this hierarchy of knowledge was insufficient to indicate the
               interconnections of knowledge. Thus, Diderot created an extensive system of <foreign
                  xml:lang="fr">renvois</foreign> , or cross-references, the third mode of
               organization, providing a lattice of interconnections between individual leaves of
               the tree as well as between classes of knowledge.<note>Blanchard and Olsen examined
                  the structure of the <emph>renvois</emph> generating a <q>mappemonde</q> of the
                  cross-references and node level classes of knowledge. See <ptr
                     target="#blanchard2002"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The central role of the classification system in the intellectual objectives of the
                  <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> editors is indicated by the extent to
               which it has been discussed and debated by both contemporary scholars and later
               researchers. The editors were remarkably diligent in assigning classes of knowledge
               to each article and sub-article. Of the 77,085 main and sub articles, we have
               identified 55,248 as having classes of knowledge.<note>Classes of knowledge were
                  originally extracted automatically using a simple rule-based identifier, written
                  in Perl, based on typographic conventions in the text. A small number of
                  classified articles remain either misclassified or unclassified altogether.</note>
               The editors were, however, somewhat less diligent in maintaining a precisely
               controlled list. Thus the classifications as found in the text are an amalgam of
               abbreviations, conflations, and singular categories that are not found on the <title
                  rend="italic">Système Figuré</title> at all. We have recently completed
               orthographic normalization of the classes of knowledge assigned to each
                  article,<note>The normalized classifications are the result of a collaborative
                  project with Professor Dena Goodman, Kevin Hawkins, and Benjamin Heller at the
                  University of Michigan.</note> resulting in some 54,289 articles with 2,620
               normalized classes of knowledge. The twenty most frequent classifications by number
               of articles are: <table>
                  <head>Original counts of top 20 most frequent classifications by number of
                     articles</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Géographie</cell>
                     <cell>5513</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Géographie moderne</cell>
                     <cell>4794</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Géographie ancienne</cell>
                     <cell>3084</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Jurisprudence</cell>
                     <cell>2396</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Grammaire</cell>
                     <cell>2304</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marine</cell>
                     <cell>1894</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Commerce</cell>
                     <cell>1483</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Histoire naturelle. Botanique</cell>
                     <cell>1277</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Histoire moderne</cell>
                     <cell>1194</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mythologie</cell>
                     <cell>1115</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Histoire naturelle</cell>
                     <cell>1069</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Histoire ancienne</cell>
                     <cell>889</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Medecine</cell>
                     <cell>796</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Architecture</cell>
                     <cell>730</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Jardinage</cell>
                     <cell>689</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Littérature</cell>
                     <cell>682</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Maréchallerie</cell>
                     <cell>627</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Botanique</cell>
                     <cell>614</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Histoire ecclésiastique</cell>
                     <cell>614</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Théologie</cell>
                     <cell>517</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> Like the <title rend="italic">Système Figuré</title>, these classifications
               are a reflection of how knowledge was ordered and classified in the 18th century.
               This paper reports the results of experiments using machine learning and data mining
               techniques to understand and exploit this unique resource.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Preliminary Objectives</head>
            <p>Our initial experimental objectives were threefold: <list type="ordered">
                  <item>To train our classifier on all of the normalized classified articles of the
                        <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> and then to apply the resulting
                     model to the 22,796 unclassified articles, labeling each with a predicted class
                     of knowledge.</item>
                  <item>Using the same model, we then sought to reclassify all of the classified
                     articles, verifying the relative success of our classifier by examining the
                     misclassified instances and then exploring the relationships of discrete
                     classes of knowledge to one another through feature set analysis.</item>
                  <item>Finally, we wanted to apply the classification model generated from the
                        <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> to other 18th century texts,
                     allowing us to evaluate the applicability of this ontology to sources outside
                     of the encyclopedic enterprise.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Methodology</head>
            <p>Before we could begin any classification tasks we needed to preprocess the data into
               a usable format. To this end, we extracted the text from all articles and
               sub-articles in the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> with a normalized class
               of knowledge. Explicit markers of class membership, present at the beginnings of
               these articles (e.g., <hi rend="italic">Comm.</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                  >Commerce</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Phys.</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Physics</hi>,
               etc.) were removed to ensure that they would not provide facile criteria for
               classification. The texts were then tokenized and lemmatized<note>Lemmatization was
                  accomplished using TreeTagger, a probabilistic part-of-speech tagger and
                  lemmatization utility developed by Helmudt Schmidt under the auspices of the TC
                  Project at the University of Stuttgart. It is freely available for download from
                  the project's official homepage at <ref
                     target="http://www.ims.uni-stuttgart.de/projekte/corplex/treetagger/"
                     >http://www.ims.uni-stuttgart.de/projekte/corplex/TreeTagger/</ref>.</note>
               automatically, and frequencies of words and lemmas were computed both globally and
               for each article. Words and lemmas were then used as attributes, and vectors for each
               article were generated from the number of occurrences of each attribute in that
               article.</p>
            <p>Text categorization is an extensively studied subfield of information science and
               accordingly, there exist many time-tested classification algorithms, each with their
               own strengths and weaknesses. We chose to implement a Multinomial Naive Bayesian
               classifier because of its simplicity and efficacy on large corpora.<note>See <ptr
                     target="#hand2001"/>.</note> Multinomial Naive Bayes (MNB) treats documents as
               bags of words, where word order is considered irrelevant. Essentially, we measure the
               likelihood of words occurring in a given class by calculating how many times they
               occur in all documents with known classes. These conditional probabilities allow us
               to guess the most <q>probable</q> class of an unclassified article based on the
               frequency of the words that occur within it. MNB assumes that the probability of a
               word occurring within a document is independent of the words that occur around it, an
               assumption that we know to be false. Yet, despite this, MNB is known to perform very
               well on large data sets and in fact, has been shown to produce more accurate results
               than many other classification algorithms.<note>See <ptr target="#witten2005"
                     loc="94–96"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We designed a test bed using this implementation that allowed for easy modification
               of several parameters including the minimum word count required for an article to be
               included in our model, as well as the minimum and maximum number of occurrences
               across the entire corpus required for a word or lemma to be included in our
               vocabulary. Massaging the data in this way, we can avoid, as much as possible, skewed
               results caused by high frequency function words or highly weighted words occurring in
               a relatively small number of articles. After several rounds of experimentation we
               found that our classifier was most successful when excluding articles of 25 words or
               fewer and words (lemmas) occurring in less than 4 articles.<note>Success can be
                  gauged in various ways. The accuracy achieved when testing our classifier against
                  the same set of classified articles on which it was trained is generally
                  indicative of the Naive Bayesian algorithm's power. However, this sort of
                  validation often leads to over-fitting. Given that our accuracy never exceeded
                  75%, we can only assume that there are enough anomalies in the data to have
                  compensated for any over-fitting. Additionally, we believe that it is these
                  anomalies that often end up being the most revelatory.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Results</head>
            <div>
               <head>Classifying the Unclassified</head>
               <p>Our first classification task was to train the classifier on the 54,289 articles
                  that were assigned categories of knowledge by the editors of the <title
                     rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> and to then apply this model to the 22,796
                  unclassified articles in an attempt to predict class membership for the articles
                  in question. Once classified, the twenty most frequent labels for the newly
                  classified articles were: <table>
                     <head>Counts of top 20 most frequent classifications for previously
                        unclassified articles.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Jurisprudence</cell>
                        <cell>4276</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Art méchanique</cell>
                        <cell>1260</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie</cell>
                        <cell>828</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commerce</cell>
                        <cell>802</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Anatomie</cell>
                        <cell>643</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Marine</cell>
                        <cell>557</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire moderne</cell>
                        <cell>475</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Architecture</cell>
                        <cell>435</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Grammaire</cell>
                        <cell>402</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire naturelle. Ornithologie</cell>
                        <cell>367</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Medecine</cell>
                        <cell>363</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie moderne</cell>
                        <cell>347</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Art militaire</cell>
                        <cell>311</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire ecclésiastique</cell>
                        <cell>308</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géométrie</cell>
                        <cell>306</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie ancienne</cell>
                        <cell>306</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Musique</cell>
                        <cell>295</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Astronomie</cell>
                        <cell>274</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire naturelle. Botanique</cell>
                        <cell>266</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Théologie</cell>
                        <cell>215</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table> While this distribution of classes bears some resemblance to the overall
                  distribution cited above, we have no real way of verifying the accuracy of the
                  classifier given the unknown content/classes of the unclassified
                     articles.<note>The accuracy of a classifier refers to its ability to correctly
                     predict the label of an unseen instance. Typically, classifier accuracy is
                     estimated using a test set that is independent of the training set, one that is
                     often generated by hand-labeling a set of unseen documents and measuring how
                     often the result of the classifier corresponds to the class given by the human
                     tagger. However, asking modern scholars to classify a large number of articles
                     by hand would necessarily involve not only a large amount of effort, but also a
                     fair amount of guesswork, particularly given the fact that we are dealing with
                     an ontology that is more than 200 years old.</note> While it is entirely
                  plausible that 19% of the unclassified articles are concerned with Jurisprudence
                  in a general sense, it is also likely that Jurisprudence (which represents only 5%
                  of the classified articles) becomes of sort of <q>catch-all</q> category for the
                  classifier into which articles concerned with any specific aspect of law (i.e.
                     <emph>droit romain</emph>, <emph>droit canonique</emph>, <emph>droit
                     civil</emph>, etc.) are grouped.</p>
               <p>The sample of results we examined reveal that the classifier performed reasonably
                  well. By this, we mean that some classifications seemed right on; some made a good
                  degree of sense, while others were perhaps a bit too general, failing to
                  accurately represent the specificity of the subject matter. Naturally, the more
                  than 22,000 newly generated classifications could not all be verified by hand, and
                  so we focused on major articles and a selection of smaller ones. We were
                  particularly encouraged by the assigned classifications for the 10 longest
                  unclassified articles. The <title rend="italic">Discours Préliminaire</title>,
                  d'Alembert's famous preface to the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>
                  detailing the intellectual underpinnings of the enterprise, comes back as
                  belonging to the class Philosophy.<note>This classification coincides nicely with
                     the conclusions drawn by Martine Groult, one of our collaborators at the CNRS,
                     whose work on the philosophy of <title rend="italic">Discours
                        préliminaire</title> is summarized here: <ref
                        target="http://encyclopedie.uchicago.edu/?q=node/162"
                        >http://encyclopedie.uchicago.edu/?q=node/162</ref>.</note> Going down the
                  list we see that the article <title rend="quotes">Anatomie</title> is assigned its
                  own classification in Anatomy and <title rend="quotes">Chimie</title> is rightly
                  placed into Chemistry, results we had originally hoped were easy enough for the
                  algorithm to attain. Most of the classifications, however, don't fall into such
                  clear categories. For example, <title rend="quotes">Venerie</title> — the art of
                  hunting — was assigned to Natural History; the philosophical article <title
                     rend="quotes">Eclectisme</title> to the History of Philosophy, etc. Indeed,
                  while these and the better part of the predicted classifications can be justified
                  on a general level, we had to concede that the overall utility of this task was
                  somewhat questionable. Quite simply, as we mention above, there was just too much
                  data to sort through. The new labels were often interesting, but we were not able
                  to study them easily or thoroughly enough to come to any deeper understanding
                  about how the <foreign xml:lang="fr">philosophes</foreign> structured knowledge or
                  indeed how the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> itself fits together.
                  Thus, trying to develop an experiment that could generate more legible results, we
                  decided instead to leverage the information given us by the editors in exploring
                  the known classifications and their relationship to each other and then later, to
                  consider the classification scheme as a whole by examining the general
                  distribution of classes over the entire work as opposed to individual
                  instances.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Classified vs. Classified — Feature set evaluation</head>
               <p>Having run a set of predictive classification experiments on the unclassified
                  articles, our next task was an attempt at what we have named "comparative"
                  classification, wherein we train the classifier on two particular classes, and
                  then reclassify them in an effort to determine how separable they are and to
                  ascertain which features best distinguish articles from the two sets. The goal
                  here has less to do with the accuracy of the classifications than with the feature
                  sets that are generated during the classification task. Any two classes can be
                  compared. Feature weights are generated using the Naive Bayes Perl module written
                  by Ken Williams. These weights represent the conditional probability of a feature
                  f given a class c and are generated based on their frequency in the known
                     articles.<note>It is worth noting that Williams' implementation of the Naive
                     Bayesian classifier uses the log-likelihood ratio of features <hi rend="italic"
                        >fi</hi> given each class c in question. It also uses a smoothing term to
                     account for probabilities of zero. Because these probabilities are in general
                     very small, their logarithmic weights are very negative. We find it easier to
                     deal with positive numbers, so for display purposes, we make each of these
                     scores positive by raising 2 to the power of that weight. <graphic
                        url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/> Williams' Perl module can be
                     downloaded at <ref
                        target="http://search.cpan.org/~kwilliams/algorithm-naivebayes-0.04/lib/algorithm/naivebayes.pm"
                        >http://search.cpan.org/~kwilliams/Algorithm-NaiveBayes-0.04/lib/Algorithm/NaiveBayes.pm</ref>.</note>
                  To give an example of this sort of comparative classification, 889 articles
                  classified as <q>Histoire ancienne</q> were compared with 1194 articles in the
                     <q>Histoire moderne</q> class and the following features and their weights were
                  extracted as the most relevant in determining class membership: <table>
                     <head>Conditional probabilities of top 20 most common words in articles from
                           <title rend="italic">Histoire ancienne</title>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>étoient</cell>
                        <cell>0.04356</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>avoit</cell>
                        <cell>0.03705</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>romains</cell>
                        <cell>0.02472</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>avoyer</cell>
                        <cell>0.02455</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>an</cell>
                        <cell>0.02341</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>peuple</cell>
                        <cell>0.02271</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>chez</cell>
                        <cell>0.02188</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>sous</cell>
                        <cell>0.02182</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tems</cell>
                        <cell>0.02170</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>mot</cell>
                        <cell>0.02146</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>empereur</cell>
                        <cell>0.02146</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>0.02122</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>appelloit</cell>
                        <cell>0.01880</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>premier</cell>
                        <cell>0.01847</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>nous</cell>
                        <cell>0.01802</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>encore</cell>
                        <cell>0.01783</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>après</cell>
                        <cell>0.01763</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>homme</cell>
                        <cell>0.01756</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>dieu</cell>
                        <cell>0.01683</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>rome</cell>
                        <cell>0.01683</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Conditional probabilities of top 20 most common words in articles from
                           <title rend="italic">Histoire moderne</title>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>roi</cell>
                        <cell>0.03744</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ordre</cell>
                        <cell>0.02870</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>prince</cell>
                        <cell>0.02390</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>sous</cell>
                        <cell>0.02314</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>nommer</cell>
                        <cell>0.02180</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>titre</cell>
                        <cell>0.02165</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>empire</cell>
                        <cell>0.02065</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>chevalier</cell>
                        <cell>0.02046</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>officier</cell>
                        <cell>0.02039</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tems</cell>
                        <cell>0.02030</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>étoient</cell>
                        <cell>0.02003</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>premier</cell>
                        <cell>0.01959</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>empereur</cell>
                        <cell>0.01903</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>porter</cell>
                        <cell>0.01891</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>état</cell>
                        <cell>0.01871</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>mot</cell>
                        <cell>0.01851</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>avoit</cell>
                        <cell>0.01823</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>prendre</cell>
                        <cell>0.01814</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>maître</cell>
                        <cell>0.01814</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>sans</cell>
                        <cell>0.01780</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table> The overall performance of the classifier came in at 95.63%, which tells
                  us that while both belong to the same <q>branch</q> of science, namely History,
                  the ancient and the modern are nonetheless significantly distinguishable from one
                  another. When considering the two lists of features, one immediately notices that
                  the results make good sense, i.e., we find more verbs in the past tense ( <foreign
                     xml:lang="fr">avoient</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="fr">étoient</foreign>,
                  etc.) in the Ancient History articles as well as references to antiquity (
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">romains</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                     >empereur</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">rome</foreign>, etc.). The
                  single-letter feature <q>g</q> is the signature of the Abbé Mallet who was the
                  author of a significant portion of the articles on Ancient History. Interestingly,
                  some of the features occur in both lists, which is more than likely a result of
                  the close relationship and dialogue between the two classes. In the feature set
                  for Modern History, we find references to forms of government that quite rightly
                  belong to the modern period ( <foreign xml:lang="fr">état</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="fr">prince</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">roi</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="fr">chevalier</foreign>, etc.) and the notable absence of the word <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">dieu</foreign>
                  </q> (<q>god</q>).</p>
               <p>We can also run comparative classification tasks on seemingly dissimilar classes
                  of knowledge such as the 682 Literature articles and the 200 articles dealing with
                  Physics. Not surprisingly, we obtain a very high rate of success for this sort of
                  classification, in this case, 99.29%: <table>
                     <head>Conditional probabilities of top 20 most common words in articles from
                           <title rend="italic">Littérature</title>.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>nous</cell>
                        <cell>0.03330</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>mot</cell>
                        <cell>0.02902</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>avoit</cell>
                        <cell>0.02607</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>étoient</cell>
                        <cell>0.02294</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>livre</cell>
                        <cell>0.02283</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ancien</cell>
                        <cell>0.02149</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>je</cell>
                        <cell>0.02117</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tems</cell>
                        <cell>0.02030 </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>bien</cell>
                        <cell>0.01997</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>encore</cell>
                        <cell>0.01963</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>sans</cell>
                        <cell>0.01956</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>vers</cell>
                        <cell>0.01907</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>dieu</cell>
                        <cell>0.01835</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>auteur</cell>
                        <cell>0.01820</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>latin</cell>
                        <cell>0.01785</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>usage</cell>
                        <cell>0.01742</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>devoir</cell>
                        <cell>0.01738</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>notre</cell>
                        <cell>0.01695</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>homme</cell>
                        <cell>0.01691</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>chose</cell>
                        <cell>0.01671</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Conditional probabilities of top 20 most common words in articles from
                           <title rend="italic">Physique</title>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>corps</cell>
                        <cell>0.05394</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>air</cell>
                        <cell>0.04216</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>eau</cell>
                        <cell>0.04185</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>nous</cell>
                        <cell>0.03507</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>froid</cell>
                        <cell>0.02597</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>chaleur</cell>
                        <cell>0.02584</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>monsieur</cell>
                        <cell>0.02580</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>degré</cell>
                        <cell>0.02296</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>moins</cell>
                        <cell>0.02251</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fort</cell>
                        <cell>0.02242</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>glace</cell>
                        <cell>0.02196</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>couleur</cell>
                        <cell>0.02169</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>feu</cell>
                        <cell>0.02160</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>lorsque</cell>
                        <cell>0.02109</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>effet</cell>
                        <cell>0.02048</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>peu</cell>
                        <cell>0.01991</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>rayon</cell>
                        <cell>0.01986</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fluide</cell>
                        <cell>0.01962</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>mouvement</cell>
                        <cell>0.01952</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>trouver</cell>
                        <cell>0.01948</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The feature scores from this model are what we would expect. The Literature class'
                  most significant features are those words pertaining to language and grammar (
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">mot</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">livre</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">vers</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">auteur</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">latin</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">usage</foreign>,
                  etc.) whereas the Physics class is dominated by materialistic terminology (
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">corps</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">air</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">eau</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">degré</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">fluide</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                     >mouvement</foreign>, etc.) consistent with the scientific writings of the
                  period.</p>
               <p>Evaluation of these feature sets can be invaluable when testing certain
                  hypotheses, such as word usage differences across similar disciplines or between
                  authors. In this particular case, the features provide an intuitive illustration
                  of the differences between these two distinct classes of knowledge. While features
                  are simply terms that the algorithm finds statistically representative of a
                  particular class, the feature sets as a whole can also give a snapshot of the
                  make-up of the individual classes or indeed of larger concepts more generally.
                  From the list for literature, for example, we get a sense of the importance that
                  classical Roman authors still had for the <emph>philosophes</emph> with the terms
                     <q>ancien</q> (<q>ancient</q>) and <emph>latin.</emph>
                  <q>Vers</q> (<q>verse</q>) perhaps reflects the fact that versification was a
                  predominant aspect of literary style, whether in poetic, dramatic, and other
                  writing at that time. Terms such as <q>mot</q> (<q>word</q>) and <q>usage</q>
                     (<q>use</q>) might point to the 18th century's expansive, belle-lettristic
                  sense of literature that we discuss below. In a more general manner, feature sets
                  provide us with an expanded thesaurus for any given classification task -- leads
                  for further investigation and study -- that can then be exploited by a more
                  traditional full text analysis system.<note>The importance of word usage and the
                     evolution of language in the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>, key
                     concepts when considering feature set analysis, are discussed in <ptr
                        target="#anderson1984"/>.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Reclassifying the Classified — the Ontology of the Encyclopédie</head>
               <p>Finally, we applied the model assembled for our first experiment — trained on all
                  of the known classifications — onto all of the already classified articles. By
                  this, we mean that we effectively ignored any given classes of knowledge, treating
                  each article as if it were unclassified, and then assigned class membership using
                  the algorithm described above. Here our goal in the results analysis was twofold:
                  first, we were curious as to the overall performance of our classification
                  algorithm, i.e., how well it correctly labeled the known articles; and secondly,
                  we wanted to use these new classifications to examine the outliers or
                  misclassified articles in an attempt to understand better the presumed coherency
                  and consistency of the editors' original classification scheme.</p>
               <p>We achieved a 71.4% success rate in the re-categorization of the 54,289 classified
                  articles, a performance that could perhaps be improved with a more accurate
                  morphological stemmer and the inclusion of n-grams as features, fucnctions we
                  intend to implement in the future. Nonetheless, developing a model to reliably
                  guess an article's given class of knowledge is ultimately not our primary concern
                  as even a perfect model, while impressive in terms of performance, could only
                  yield that which we already know, namely the assigned classes of knowledge. The
                  sheer size and complexity of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>,
                  drawing its contents from hundreds of distinct writers, all but guarantees a lower
                  rate of performance for any classification algorithm. This fact need not be
                  discouraging however, as we are more interested in exploring the use of these text
                  mining techniques as knowledge discovery tools, uncovering previously unnoticed
                  connections and classifications, such as the particular use of the class
                     <q>Literature</q> outlined below, rather than simply using these approaches as
                  a statistical platform for hypothesis testing.</p>
               <p>The twenty most frequent classes after re-classification: <table>
                     <head>The 20 most frequent classes of knowledge by number of articles after
                        re-classification.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie</cell>
                        <cell>3926</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie ancienne</cell>
                        <cell>3492</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie moderne</cell>
                        <cell>3273</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Jurisprudence</cell>
                        <cell>2552</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Commerce</cell>
                        <cell>2104</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Art méchanique</cell>
                        <cell>1662</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire naturelle. Botanique</cell>
                        <cell>1615</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Marine</cell>
                        <cell>1575</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire moderne</cell>
                        <cell>1514</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mythologie</cell>
                        <cell>1334</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Architecture</cell>
                        <cell>1213</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Grammaire</cell>
                        <cell>1111</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire ancienne</cell>
                        <cell>1061</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire ecclésiastique</cell>
                        <cell>781</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Medecine</cell>
                        <cell>746</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire naturelle</cell>
                        <cell>727</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Littérature</cell>
                        <cell>646</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Maréchallerie</cell>
                        <cell>592</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Morale</cell>
                        <cell>573</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Jardinage</cell>
                        <cell>566</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>When comparing the results to the original classifications we note that the class
                     <q>Grammar</q> falls out of the top ten while <q>Art méchanique,</q> which is
                  not included in the original top twenty, ranks as the sixth most frequent class.
                  The Grammar class is known to be problematic as Diderot frequently used this
                  seemingly innocuous label to hide more polemical entries.<note>The use and abuse
                     of the category <q>Grammar</q> by Diderot is one of the subjects treated in
                        <ptr target="#lecatsiomis1999"/>.</note> As for the <q>Art méchanique</q>
                  category, we suspect that many of the overly specific classes dealing with the
                  mechanical arts were subsumed into this larger, more inclusive set. By and large
                  the rest of the classes are consistent with the overall distribution in the <title
                     rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> although the rankings differ slightly.</p>
               <p>The most interesting results here come from the examination of misclassified
                  articles, which belie vocabularies that do not belong probabilistically to their
                  assigned categories. Upon analyzing a random subset of the misclassified articles,
                  we identified three distinct types of misclassifications. First, there are
                  articles whose original classification was too infrequent; for example, the
                  article <title rend="quotes">Accrues</title> (metal rings used to knit together
                  fishing net) is the sole member of the class <q>Marchands de Filets</q> (net
                  merchants) and was placed into the more general class of <q>Pêche</q> (fishing).
                  There are also articles whose vocabularies mislead the classifier. One such case
                  is the article <title rend="quotes">Achées</title> (a type of worm used in
                  bait-fishing), originally classified as <q>Pêche,</q> it was later assigned to the
                  class <q>Jardinage</q> (gardening). The article is in fact less a description of
                  anything to do with fishing, but rather contains instructions on how to find and
                  cultivate bait worms in a garden. Finally, there are entries whose predicted
                  class, while incorrect, seems more logical than the original. The article <title
                     rend="quotes">Tepidarium,</title> which describes an ancient Roman bathhouse,
                  would appear to have more in common with its predicted class, Architecture, than
                  the one assigned by the editors, namely Literature. Certainly our judgment that
                  the predicted class is more appropriate than the original class of knowledge is
                  biased by our modern epistemological paradigm, but this does not necessarily mean
                  that the original system of classification was entirely consistent and coherent.
                  Naturally then, applying our model onto other 18th century French texts should
                  provide further insight into the power of the classifier and more importantly,
                  into the ontology originally laid out by the <emph>philosophes</emph>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Classification outside of the Encyclopédie</head>
               <p>The <title rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux</title>, or <title rend="italic"
                     >Mémoires pour l'Histoire des Sciences &amp; des Beaux-Arts</title>, was one of
                  the most influential 18th century French periodicals. A sort of literary/scholarly
                  journal reviewing and commenting on a wide variety of contemporary publications,
                  the <title rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux</title> dealt with almost every
                  discipline of knowledge. Given the great variety of subject matter contained in
                  this collection we felt it would be a natural choice for us to begin studying the
                  relationship of the Encyclopédie ontology to other 18th century texts. Of course,
                  the 18th century in France was a time of intellectual ferment and, as in most
                  historical moments, there existed more than one approach to the classification of
                  the known world. And, indeed, the <emph>philosophes</emph>' intellectual and
                  political bent made their way of organizing ideas different from that of other
                  thinkers, particularly the Jesuits who were behind the <title rend="italic"
                     >Journal de Trévoux</title>. Knowing this, we wanted to test the degree of
                  overlap between the structure of knowledge in the <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopédie</title> and the <title rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux</title>,
                  discovering in the process the commonalities, differences, and unique aspects of
                  each. We hoped this experiment would give us a "slice of life" look at the
                  intellectual milieu of the day, or at least provide an insight into the presumed
                  differences in discourse between the two camps. To this end, we processed the
                  ARTFL Project's 109 volumes of the <title rend="italic">Journal de
                  Trévoux</title>, splitting them into 1,027 separate articles. Extending from 1751
                  to 1757, this collection covers the years during which the editors of the <title
                     rend="italic">Journal</title> engaged in a fierce polemic with the
                  encyclopédistes concerning the publication of the <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopédie</title>.<note>The ARTFL database of the <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal de Trévoux</title> can be found at <ref
                        target="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/artfl/projects/trevoux"
                        >http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/projects/trevoux</ref>.</note> Our
                  previous model, trained on all of the classified <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopédie</title> articles, was thus applied to the Trévoux articles,
                  assigning each with a predicted class of knowledge. The twenty most frequent
                  assigned classes are listed below: <table>
                     <head>The 20 most frequent classes of knowledge assigned to the Trévoux
                        articles using the Encyclopédie model.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Littérature</cell>
                        <cell>317</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Morale</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie moderne</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Théologie</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Philosophie</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire moderne</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Belles lettres</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Astronomie</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Métaphysique</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire ecclésiastique</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Physique</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Art militaire</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Economie politique</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Géographie</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Medecine</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire romaine</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Peinture</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Histoire naturelle</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Chimie</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>A cursory glance at these results gives us a general idea about the most
                  significant themes found in the <title rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux</title>;
                  themes that correspond nicely to our preconceived notions concerning the <title
                     rend="italic">Journal</title>, its writers and subject matter. Along these
                  lines, it is not surprising to find in a Jesuit publication such as this a greater
                  emphasis on articles about Literature, Morality, Theology, and Philosophy.
                  However, the surprising fact that more than 1/3 of the 1000 articles were assigned
                  the label of <title rend="italic">Littérature</title> caused us to question
                  somewhat the performance of the classifier and ultimately, to reconsider our
                  modern notion of Literature when applied to the specific instances of this
                  classification.</p>
               <p>In the first edition (1694) of the <title rend="italic">Dictionnaire de l'Académie
                     française</title> the entry for <title rend="quotes">Littérature</title> reads
                  thus: <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">Litterature. s. f. Erudition, doctrine. <emph>Grande litterature. profonde litterature. il est homme de
                           grande litterature. il n'a point de litterature. il a beaucoup de
                           litterature.</emph>
                     </foreign>
                  </q> and indeed the definition changes little by the fourth edition of 1762:
                     <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">LITTÉRATURE. s.f. Érudition, doctrine. <emph>Grande littérature. Profonde littérature. Il est homme de grande
                           littérature. N'avoir point de littérature. Avoir beaucoup de littérature.
                           Un ouvrage plein de littérature.</emph> Ce mot regarde proprement les
                        Belles-Lettres.</foreign>
                  </q> The addition of the last sentence, <q>This
                     word is properly used in regard to Belles Lettres,</q> in the 1762 edition
                  seemingly restricts this particular form of erudition to the more traditionally
                  literary realm of the <q>Belles-Lettres,</q> or Poetry and Rhetoric. The
                  definition offered by the Jesuit editors of the <title rend="italic">Dictionnaire
                     de Trévoux</title> (1742) differs only slightly from that of the Academy:
                     <q>LITTÉRATURE, s. f. Doctrine, connoissance
                     profonde des Lettres. <emph>Doctrina, litteratura,
                     eruditio</emph>.</q> While these definitions shed little light as to why the
                     <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> literature class should be so
                  prevalent in the classification of such a diverse collection of articles, many of
                  which deal with the Sciences and Natural History, the ambiguity of this erudite
                  possession of <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">littérature</foreign>
                  </q> and <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">lettres</foreign>
                  </q> should nonetheless cause us to broaden our understanding of these terms as
                  they were used in the mid-18th century.</p>
               <p>We thus began a more thorough investigation of the Literature category by
                  examining five randomly selected articles belonging to the assigned class
                     <q>Littérature</q> in the <title rend="italic">Journal de Trévoux</title>.
                  While some categorizations make sense as literature — e.g., the article <title
                     rend="quotes">Nouvelles Litteraires,</title> a sort of literary <q>news of the
                     day</q>; and, less convincingly, a commentary on Rousseau's first discourse —
                  others have ostensibly nothing to do with our modern idea of Literature — e.g.,
                  articles commenting on a history of jurisprudence, a treatise on diseases, and a
                  compilation of treatises on Physics and Natural History<note>The full titles of
                     the <q>Literature</q> articles we uncovered are as follows: <foreign
                        xml:lang="fr">1) ARTICLE XII. NOUVELLES LITTERAIRES. 2) ARTICLE XXIX.
                        DISCOURS QUI A REMPORTE' le prix à l'Académie de Dijon en l'année 1750, sur
                        cette question proposée par la même Académie: Si le rétablissement des
                        Sciences &amp; des Arts a contribué à épurer les moeurs. Par un Citoyen de
                        Genève. 3) ARTICLE XXXV. HISTOIRE DE LA JURISPRUDENCE Romaine. 4) ARTICLE
                        LXI. TRAITÉ DES MALADIES qu'il est dangereux de guérir. 5) ARTICLE XIV.
                        RECUEIL DE DIFFERENS Traités de Physique &amp; d'Histoire
                        Naturelle.</foreign>
                  </note>. This apparent anomaly necessarily leads us back to the <title
                     rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> and the articles belonging to the class of
                  knowledge Literature, which serve as the basis for these class assignments.</p>
               <p>As we mentioned above concerning the reclassification of the article <title
                     rend="quotes">Tepidarium,</title> there are a great many articles whose
                  original classifications seem inappropriate. This phenomenon is all the more
                  evident when examining the reclassification of the Literature articles, the
                  majority of which deal more with Ancient History, Mythology, and Architecture than
                  with accepted literary issues. Of the 682 Literature articles, 460 were written by
                  the Chevalier de Jaucourt, author of more than 17,000 <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopédie</title> entries. Jaucourt is known to have borrowed extensively
                  from other sources and thus, we attributed these inconsistencies to intellectual
                  laziness, given the enormous number of articles for which he was
                     responsible.<note>For a thorough discussion of Jaucourt's contributions to the
                        <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>, see <ptr target="#lough1973"
                     />.</note> Upon closer examination of the Literature class of knowledge
                  however, this characterization proves unjust.</p>
               <p>Indeed, the article titled <title rend="quotes">Littérature</title> belongs not to
                  its own class of knowledge, but rather to three seemingly unrelated and disparate
                  classes: Sciences, <emph>Belles-Lettres</emph>, and Antiquity. The text of the
                  article, written by Jaucourt, is in fact a polemic advocating a universal
                  erudition and an expanded definition of what it means to possess a great
                  literature — in a word to be literate. Jaucourt includes a <emph>renvoi</emph> to
                  the article <q>Lettres</q> in an effort to define better this notion of
                  Literature. Following the cross-reference we find that the article in question,
                     <q>Lettres,</q> an article that normally falls innocuously amongst numerous
                  similarly titled entries, is the sole member of the class <q>Encyclopédie,</q>
                  suggesting that the idea of literacy is essential to the entire encyclopedic
                  enterprise. Here, Jaucourt's understanding of <q>Lettres</q> as a much larger
                  category of knowledge than <q>belles-lettres</q> or even the Humanities as a whole
                     (<emph>les lettres humaines</emph>), harkens back to the Classical acceptation
                  of the term which encompassed all areas of human understanding from Epic Poetry to
                  Physics. The inter-connectedness of knowledge, both literary and scientific, is
                  thus the essence of Jaucourt's idea of encyclopedic literacy, wherein <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">il en résulte que les <emph>lettres</emph> &amp; les
                        sciences proprement dites, ont entr'elles l'enchaînement, les liaisons,
                        &amp; les rapports les plus étroits; c'est dans l'<title rend="italic"
                           >Encyclopédie</title> qu'il importe de le démontrer</foreign>
                  </q> (<q>the result is that Letters and
                     Sciences, properly speaking, have between each other a strong and direct
                     network of links and relationships; it is in the Encyclopaedia that the
                     demonstration of this network becomes important</q>).<note>From the article
                        <title rend="quotes">Lettres</title> in the <title rend="italic"
                        >Encyclopédie</title>.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions and Future Work</head>
            <p>This discovery — that for the writers of the <title rend="italic"
                  >Encyclopédie</title>, Literature as a branch of human understanding included not
               only what we today consider Literature (<foreign xml:lang="fr">les
                  Belles-Lettres</foreign>) but also Natural History, the Natural Sciences, the
               study of Antiquity, etc. — was made possible through the machine learning techniques
               outlined in this paper. We now understand precisely why the classifier, using the
               ontology of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>, labels so many Trévoux
               entries as <q>Littérature.</q> Furthermore, the presence of this more inclusive view
               of lettered erudition should come as no surprise given that, as is expressed in the
               very title of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>, this <title
                  rend="italic">Dictionnaire raisonné</title> was the work of a society of <q>Gens
                  de Lettres.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It would seem, however, that this notion of Literature as a sort of universal
               erudition did not survive the turmoil of the late 18th century, and by 1798 the fifth
               edition of the <title rend="italic">Dictionnaire de l'Académie française</title> had
               already begun restricting Literature to a purely literary domain, defined as the
                  <q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">Connoissance des ouvrages, des matières, des règles, et des
                     exemples <emph>littéraires</emph>
                  </foreign>
               </q> (our emphasis).<note>Note that we are focusing exclusively on the
                  definitions of Literature as a discipline, rather than a collection of literary
                  and/or other documents (as in <q>I have consulted all the available literature on
                     cancer and have found nothing</q>). This modern usage of literature is
                  expressed somewhat in the dictionaries we mention, i.e. <q>
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">L'ensemble des productions littéraires d'une nation,
                        d'un pays, d'une époque. La littérature française. La littérature du moyen
                        âge</foreign>
                  </q> (Émile Littré, <title rend="italic">Dictionnaire de la langue
                     française</title> (1872-77).</note> 19th century lexicography would move
               further in this direction, eliminating any mention of <q>doctrine</q> or
                  <q>erudition</q> in its definition of Literature as <q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">La science qui comprend la grammaire, l'éloquence et la
                     poésie, et qu'on appelle autrement Belles-lettres</foreign>
               </q> (<title rend="italic">Dictionnaire de l'Académie française</title>, 6th
               edition 1832). By 1872, perhaps as a reflection of the disciplinary codification
               which took place during the first part of the 19th century, the positivist
               lexicographer Émile Littré simply defines Literature as the <q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">Connaissance des belles-lettres</foreign>
               </q> which is by and large its accepted meaning today.</p>
            <p>These modest conclusions lend further weight to our initial view that traditional
               humanistic inquiry can be enhanced and broadened through the judicious application of
               machine learning and data mining techniques. As large-scale textual resources such as
               the <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title> become more readily available to
               scholars in a digitized format, new search and analysis tools will be needed. It is
               our opinion that approaches similar to those outlined above can successfully leverage
               the power of data mining tools for use in the Humanities. And while these techniques
               can certainly aid in a variety of hypothesis testing and classification tasks, it is
               our hope that they will also lead to the discovery of new knowledge through the
               uncovering of previously unnoticed textual connections.</p>
            <p>Moving forward, we plan to continue improving the performance of our classifiers
               through better morphological text extraction, allowing for a greater freedom in the
               selection of features. Possible features would include n-grams (bi- and tri-grams of
               surface forms, bi- and tri-grams of lemmas) as well as part of speech information. We
               are also planning to investigate several different unsupervised machine learning
               techniques such as vector space analysis, latent semantic indexing (LSI), and several
               other clustering models. When applied to the <title rend="italic"
                  >Encyclopédie</title> and other 18th century works, these tools will propose
               connections based on a measure of lexical similarity between arbitrary chunks of
               texts, whether paragraphs, articles, chapters, or entire works. It is our hope that
               within this new system, researchers will be able to explore and, more importantly, to
               evaluate the proposed connections between these articles and texts. Although the
               connections will be brought to light with the help of computers, it will nonetheless
               be necessary for scholars to provide the system with the critical element of human
               scrutiny that is essential to Humanities research.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson1984" label="Anderson 1984" key="anderson1984"> Anderson, Wilda.
                  <title rend="italic">Between the Library and the Laboratory: The Language of
                  Chemistry in Eighteenth-Century France</title>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins,
               1984.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andreev1999" label="Andreev et al. 1999" key="andreev1999"> Andreev,
               Leonid, Jack Iverson, and Mark Olsen. <title rend="quotes">Re-engineering a War
                  Machine: ARTFL's <title rend="italic">Encyclopédie</title>
               </title> in <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 14:1
               (1999), 11-28.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blanchard2002" label="Blanchard and Olsen 2002" key="blanchard2002">
               Blanchard, Gilles, and Mark Olsen. <title rend="quotes">Le système de renvois dans
                  l'Encyclopédie: une cartographie de la structure des connaissances au XVIIIème
                  siècle</title> in <title rend="italic">Recherches sur Diderot et sur
                  l'Encyclopédie</title>, 31-32, April 2002, 45-70.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brian1998" label="Brian 1998" key="brian1998"> Brian, Eric. <title
                  rend="quotes">L'ancêtre de l'hypertexte,</title> in <title rend="italic">Les
                  Cahiers de Science et Vie</title>, 47 (October 1998), 28-38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hand2001" label="Hand and Yu 2001" key="hand2001"> Hand, David J., and
               Keming Yu. <title rend="quotes">Idiot's Bayes — Not So Stupid after All?</title>,
               International Statistical Review 69:3 (December 2001), 385-398.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoyt1965" label="Hoyt and Cassirer 1965" key="hoyt1965"> Hoyt, Nelly, and
               Thomas Cassirer. <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title> to <title rend="italic"
                  >Encyclopedia: Selections by Diderot, D'Alembert, and a Society of Men of
                  Letters</title>. Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, 1965.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lecatsiomis1999" label="Leca-Tsiomis 1999" key="lecatsiomis1999">
               Leca-Tsiomis, Marie. <title rend="italic">Ecrire l'Encyclopédie: Diderot: de l'usage
                  des dictionnaires à la grammaire philosophique</title>. Oxford: Voltaire
               Foundation, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lough1973" label="Lough 1973" key="lough1973"> Lough, John. <title
                  rend="italic">The Contributors to the <title rend="quotes">Encyclopédie</title>
               </title>. London: Grant and Cutler, 1973.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="morrissey2001" label="Morrissey et al. 2001" key="morrissey2001">
               Morrissey, Robert, Jack Iverson, and Mark Olsen. <title rend="quotes">Présentation:
                  L'Encyclopédie Electronique</title> in Robert Morrissey and Philippe Roger, eds.,
                  <title rend="italic">L'Encyclopédie du réseau au livre et du livre au
                  réseau</title>. Paris: Champion, 2001. 17-27.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="proust1995" label="Proust 1995" key="proust1995"> Proust, Jacques. <title
                  rend="italic">Diderot et l'Encyclopédie</title>. Paris: Albin Michel, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwab1984" label="Schwab et al. 1971-1984" key="schwab1984"> Schwab,
               Richard, Walter Rex, and John Lough. <title rend="italic">Inventory of Diderot's
                  Encyclopédie</title>, 7 vols. Oxford: Studies on Voltaire and the Eighteenth
               Century, 1971-1984.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="witten2005" label="Witten and Frank 2005" key="witten2005"> Witten, Ian,
               and Eibe Frank. <title rend="italic">Data Mining: Practical Machine Learning Tools
                  and Techniques</title>, 2nd ed. San Francisco, CA: Morgan Kaufmann, 2005,
               94-96.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
