<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Introducing Issues in Humanities Computing</title>
            <author>Joseph Raben</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Joseph <dhq:family>Raben</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Queens College, City University of New York</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>joeraben@ncsa.uiuc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Joseph Raben is a professor emeritus of English at Queens College of the City
                     University of New York, where he taught for 30 years. Before that he was a
                     teaching fellow at Indiana University and an instructor at Princeton
                     University. He was awarded a B.A. with honors at the University of Wisconsin
                     and a Ph.D. at Indiana University, where he minored in folklore under Stith
                     Thompson. His bachelor's honors thesis was on pronunciation as revealed by
                     rhyme schemes in American folksongs, and his doctoral dissertation studied folk
                     speech in Scott's novels. After graduating from Wisconsin, he worked as an
                     engineering aide on the construction of the Hanford Engineer Works, and then
                     entered the Army, where he was trained in spoken Japanese and served in Tokyo
                     as an editor of translations in the Allied Translator and Interpreter Service,
                     attached to GHQ. In this service he translated documents used in the war crimes
                     trials.</p>
                  <p>At Queens he developed an interest in using computers in humanities research
                     and in 1966 founded the innovative journal <title rend="italic">Computers and
                        the Humanities</title> to provide a platform for younger pioneering scholars
                     to publish their research. He both edited and carried a large share of this
                     journal's publication chores for 20 years. Among its most useful features was a
                     semiannual <title rend="italic">Directory of Scholars Active</title>, which
                     informed practitioners around the world of recent applications of computer
                     technology to humanities and related social science problems. These notes he
                     cumulated into a print volume, <title rend="italic">Computer-Assisted Research
                        in the Humanities</title> (New York: Pergamon Press, 1977). In 1978 he
                     founded the Association for Computers and the Humanities and served as its
                     president for two years before turning it over to younger successors. During
                     this same period, he helped to organize several international conferences at
                     the University of Southern California, Grinnell College, Dartmouth College,
                     Rutgers University, North Carolina State University and Auburn University. He
                     also presented papers at many international conferences organized by others and
                     represented humanities computing at conferences organized by groups within the
                     computer industry, such as the ACM, the American Federation of Information
                     Processing Societies, the International Federation for Information Processing,
                     and the American Society for Information Science. He organized special interest
                     groups at several MLA conventions and within the ACM. He was an invited
                     lecturer at academic institutions all over the United States, Canada, and
                     Western Europe, and in India, China, and Japan. Much of the same effort was
                     contained in articles published in a variety of journals, along with his
                     contributions to Shelley scholarship, some of it based on the manuscript
                     materials in the Bodleian Library.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000008</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>opinion</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-04-03">3 April 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2007-03-30" who="Julia Flanders">Encoded article.</change>
         <change when="2008-06-12" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added publicationStmt,
            added blank abstract for validation with new schema</change>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
         <change when="2009-12-03" who="CRB">Changed emph elements to title in bio</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This is the introduction to the inaugural issues of <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Humanities Quarterly</title>, on <title rend="quotes">Issues in Humanities
                  Computing</title>. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Introduction to the inaugural issues of <title rend="italic">Digital
               Humanities Quarterly</title>, on <title rend="quotes">Issues in Humanities
                  Computing</title>.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>The feature we are introducing in this inaugural issue of <title rend="italic">Digital
               Humanities Quarterly</title>, called <title rend="quotes">Issues in Humanities
               Computing</title>, is one end of a road that began forty-five years ago in the old
            Reading Room of the British Museum. (The other end of that road is the <title
               rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Humanities and Social Science Computing</title>, which
            I am organizing with Vernon Burton under the auspices of the National Center for
            Supercomputer Applications at the University of Illinois and scheduled to be published
            by Idea Group in 2008.) My immediate impetus to consider computers as a means of solving
            a scholarly problem was the difficulty I experienced in locating the significant echoes
            of Milton’s <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title> that Shelley had embedded in his
               <title rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound</title> in order to enhance its resonance as
            a master statement of poetic truth. Once back at Queens College, the quest for
            assistance from computers led to the IBM Watson Laboratories in Yorktown Heights, New
            York, where the language group, relieved of responsibility for creating machine
            translation but not formally dismissed, created for me a crude mechanism for locating
            some of those echoes.</p>
         <p>That initial effort was reported in September 1964 at what was probably the first
            conference on computers and humanities research, the so-called Literary Data Processing
            Conference organized by Harry Arader of IBM and chaired by Stephen M. Parrish of Cornell
            and Jess B. Bessinger of NYU. Among the other speakers, Roberto Busa expatiated on the
            problems of managing 15 million words for his magnum opus on Thomas Aquinas. Parrish and
            Bessinger, along with the majority of other speakers, reported on their efforts to
            generate concordances with the primitive data processing machines available at that
            time. In light of the current number of projects to digitize literary works it is ironic
            to recall Martin Kay’s plea to the audience not to abandon their punch cards and
            magnetic tapes after their concordances were printed and (hopefully) published.</p>
         <p>My discovery of the number of scholars from around the country who were engaged to some
            extent in using computers for humanistic research inspired the thought that we should
            keep in touch with one another, and after two years I persuaded IBM to fund what at
            first I called <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities: A Newsletter</title>.
            Even after original articles started to come in and this publication was exalted to the
            status of a scholarly journal, it maintained as a primary function the exchange of
            information in this new and perilous environment. I have been told that our biennial
               <title rend="quotes">Directory of Scholars Active</title>, later compiled into a book
            published by Pergamon Press, helped many recent initiates into humanities computing to
            find their footing and locate collaborators. Even more satisfying was the knowledge that
            several young assistant professors, coming up for tenure, succeeded in retaining their
            grip on an academic career by publishing in the pages of CHum. An offprint on the
            chairman’s desk or the dean’s, looking as dignified as one from any of the older
            established journals, reportedly had the weight to outbalance the strangeness of the
            activity that had attracted these young persons.</p>
         <p>By 1975, Bob Dilligan of the University of Southern California, co-editor of a Keats
            concordance, offered to organize a conference as a sequel to one held two years
            previously at the University of Minnesota, and being there on sabbatical, I helped with
            that effort. That involvement led, in turn to my participating in the organization of
            similar conferences at Dartmouth and Rutgers. Sensing a need to broaden our view of
            humanities computing and recognizing the growth of databases as a resource in their own
            right (rather than as simply the raw material of concordances), I began a series of
            International Conferences on Data Bases in the Humanities and Social Sciences at
            Darmouth, Grinnell and Auburn at Montgomery. The growing number of attendees at these
            conferences seemed to require a permanent organization to sponsor them, and in 1978 I
            convened the session at the annual MLA meeting that created the Association for
            Computers and the Humanities. After two years as president, I turned that operation over
            to Mary Dee Harris and then Nancy Ide, so that younger people could gain whatever
            academic credit they could through that position and so that the operation would have an
            independent stature.</p>
         <p>When New York suffered its financial crisis in 1974, and it was no longer possible to
            publish under the aegis of Queens College, I entrusted the journal to two commercial
            publishers, neither of which saw much importance in either humanities or humanities
            computing and treated this publication with consequent lack of concern. In 1984,
            therefore, I took early retirement and set up my own small publishing operation in
            Sarasota, Florida. I was thus able to publish several collections of essays on databases
            in the humanities and social sciences and to start up two new journals, <title
               rend="italic">Computers and the Social Sciences</title> (later combined with the
               <title rend="italic">Social Science Computing Record</title>) and <title
               rend="italic">Computers and Translation</title> (renamed <title rend="italic">Machine
               Translation</title> and published now by Springer). Like so many small businesses,
            this one proved less than financially viable, and by 1987, I had sold off the various
            titles and returned to my more congenial academic environment.</p>
         <p>In this situation I am now able to concentrate on the encyclopedia project and the
            “op-ed” page of DHQ. It is our hope that this feature will provide a forum for
            discussion of the larger issues that confront us as we continue our effort to bring
            computer technology up to what we consider its proper status in academe and scholarly
            activity. The initial offering is my own take on the problem of achieving the same
            respect for online publishing that is held now by print. My hope is to set a tone of
            serious reflection that will be adopted by those who submit future contributions to this
            section of the journal.</p>
         <p>Rather than brief comments, we are hoping for thought-out and substantially developed
            opinions on all the aspects of our developing discipline. Responses to these discussions
            are equally welcome and will be tagged to establish a continuous flow along evolving
            threads. Of course, publication will depend on the approval of the Editorial Board. A
            few possible topics are suggested below, but we hope these will prompt contributions on
            a much wider range of issues and questions.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Can software development, rather than conventional research, serve as a step up
               the promotion ladder?</item>
            <item>Are there better ways to organize our information than the current search programs
               provide?</item>
            <item>How do we confront the trend toward English as a universal scholarly language in
               the face of objections, such as those from France? How far need we go in
               accommodating other world languages — Spanish, Russian, Chinese?</item>
            <item>How concerned should we be about the consequence of Web accessibility undermining
               the status of major research centers in or near metropolitan cities?</item>
            <item>Has the availability of the Internet as a scholarly medium enhanced the academic
               status of women and minorities?</item>
            <item>Will humanists’ dependence on computer-generated data lead to a scientistic search
               for objective and reproducible results?</item>
            <item>Can we learn anything about today’s resistance to new technologies from studying
               the reactions in the Renaissance to the introduction of printing?</item>
            <item>Will digital libraries make today’s libraries obsolete?</item>
            <item>Are the concepts and development of artificial intelligence relevant to humanistic
               scholarship?</item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
