<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digital Criticism: Editorial Standards for the Homer Multitext </title>
            <author>Casey Dué</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Casey <dhq:family>Dué</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Houston, Texas</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>casey@chs.harvard.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Casey Dué is Associate Professor and Director of Classical Studies at the
                     University of Houston, as well Executive Editor for publications at Harvard’s
                     Center for Hellenic Studies in Washington, D.C. She holds a B.A. in Classics
                     from Brown University, and an M.A. and Ph.D in Classical Philology from Harvard
                     University. Her teaching and research interests include ancient Greek oral
                     traditions, Homeric poetry, Greek tragedy, and textual criticism. Publications
                     include: <title rend="italic">Homeric Variations on a Lament by
                     Briseis</title>. (Lanham, Md.: Rowman and Littlefield Press, 2002), <title
                        rend="italic">The Captive Woman’s Lament in Greek Tragedy</title> (Austin:
                     University of Texas Press, 2006) and the edited volume <title rend="italic"
                        >Recapturing a Homeric Legacy: Images and Insights from the Venetus A
                        Manuscript of the Iliad</title> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
                     forthcoming Fall 2008). She is also one of the co-editors of the <ref
                        target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/homer_multitext">Homer Multitext
                        Project</ref>. She is currently working together with Mary Ebbott on a
                     multitextual edition with essays and commentary on book 10 of the Iliad (<title
                        rend="italic">Iliad 10 and the Poetics of Ambush</title> (Cambridge, MA:
                     Harvard University Press, forthcoming Fall 2009).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Mary Ebbott</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Mary <dhq:family>Ebbott</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>College of the Holy Cross</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ebbott@chs.harvard.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mary Ebbott is Associate Professor in the Classics Department at the College of
                     the Holy Cross in Worcester, Massachusetts. She earned her B.A. in Classical
                     Languages at Bryn Mawr College and her Ph.D. in Classical Philology from
                     Harvard University. She is co-editor of the Homer Multitext project (<ref
                        target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/homer_multitext"
                        >http://chs.harvard.edu/​chs/​homer_multitext</ref>), and her publications
                     include <title rend="italic">Imagining Illegitimacy in Classical Greek
                        Literature</title> (Lanham, Md.: Lexington Books, 2003) and the forthcoming
                     book, <title rend="italic">
                        <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> 10 and the Poetics of Ambush: A Multitext
                        Edition with Essays and Commentary</title>, co-authored with Casey Dué.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000029</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-02-26">26 February 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2008-10-29" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-10-30" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-11-19" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-11-21" who="JHF">Checked encoding, minor fixes.</change>
         <change when="2008-12-09" who="Melanie Kohnen">Added figure</change>
         <change when="2008-12-09" who="Melanie Kohnen">Fixed errors after authors proofread the
            encoded article</change>
         <change when="2009-01-30" who="CRB">Added publicationStmt element and associated
            content.</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>In this article we argue for the necessity of a digital edition to most accurately
               represent the textual tradition of the Homeric epics and to better understand the
               oral performance tradition that created the poems. We demonstrate how such a digital
               criticism would differ from the traditional textual criticism as practiced for
               editions in print and suggest how a digital criticism might open new avenues for the
               interpretation of the poetry. In defining our needs and goals for a digital edition,
               we discuss what our project has in common with other digital editions of literary
               works, but how the oral, traditional nature of the poetry creates special
               requirements as well. In addition to elaborating the editorial approach for the
               project, we reaffirm the principles of collaboration, international standards, and
               open access that we have learned from Ross Scaife, the founder of the Stoa
               Consortium.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Digital editions for Homeric epic</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Digital Criticism: Editorial Standards for the Homer Multitext</head>
            <p>The so-called Homeric Question (in reality, several related questions) that has
               animated and in various ways divided modern scholarship on the <title rend="italic"
                  >Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> since the 18th century
               centers on the origins and transmission of the epics. How were they composed and by
               whom? How were they recorded in writing, and how were they then transmitted to the
               witnesses that have survived until today? How is it possible that such complex poetry
               stands at the very beginning of Western literature, even before writing as a
               technology was well developed? Editorial practice for critical editions of the epics
               will necessarily be affected by how each editor approaches and answers these
               questions <ptr target="#nagy2000"/>.<note>That an editor’s assumptions and approaches
                  will affect the edition is not particular to Homeric textual criticism, of course.
                  Stringer makes an analogous argument about editions of John Donne’s poetry <ptr
                     target="#stringer1999" loc="87"/>.</note> Yet a critical edition in the print
               medium will give a particular, and we would argue misleading, impression about the
               answers to these questions. A standard print edition will present a main text, and
               then record alternative readings in an apparatus (generally printed at the bottom of
               the page in smaller-sized font), giving the impression that there is <emph>the</emph>
               text — and then there is everything else. Compounding this problem and further
               obscuring the situation for nonspecialists, the apparatus as developed and practiced
               in classical textual criticism uses conventions and abbreviations that can only be
               deciphered by those who have received special training in these
                  practices.<note>Dahlström, who is not focused on Homeric epic in particular, cites
                  the <quote rend="inline" source="#dahlstrom2000">privileging of one particular
                     work version</quote> and the inscrutability of the apparatus as problems with a
                  codex-based scholarly edition for any classical work <ptr target="#dahlstrom2000"
                  />.</note> In effect, the standard critical edition seems to offer only one answer
               to these questions: that the Homeric epics are just like any other ancient text in
               their composition and transmission.</p>
            <p>A digital medium provides an opportunity to construct a truly different type of
               critical edition of the Homeric epics, one that better reflects the circumstances of
               its composition and transmission. The <ref
                  target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/homer_multitext">Homer Multitext</ref> of the
               Center for Hellenic Studies (CHS) in Washington, D.C., seeks to use the advantages of
               digital editions to give a more accurate visual representation of the textual
               tradition of Homeric epic than the current use of the printed page does. Most
               significantly, our digital design is also intended to reveal more readily the oral
               performance tradition in which the epics were composed, a tradition in which
               variation from performance to performance was natural and expected. The Homeric epics
               were composed again and again in performance: the digital medium, which can more
               readily handle multiple texts, is therefore eminently suitable for a critical edition
               of Homeric poetry — indeed, the fullest realization of a critical edition of Homer
               may require a digital medium.<note>Dahlström notes that synoptic, variorum, or
                  genetic editions that seek to be complete and inclusive <quote rend="inline"
                     source="#dahlstrom2000">illustrate the very limitations of print
                     media</quote> and demonstrate the need for a change in media for scholarly,
                  critical editions <ptr target="#dahlstrom2000"/>. Robinson argues <quote
                     rend="inline" source="#robinson2005a">it is difficult to think of any genre
                     that is so well adapted to the computer as the scholarly edition</quote>
                  because of the need to handle multiple texts <ptr target="#robinson2005a"
                     loc="§12"/>.</note> To achieve our goals, the digital Multitext must be
               fundamentally different from these print editions in conception, structure, and
                  interface.<note>De Smedt and Vanhoutte made this point about digital editions in
                  general: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#desmedt2002">Electronic editions, however, should
                        essentially be organized differently</quote>
                     <ptr target="#desmedt2002"/>
                  </cit>. Vanhoutte elaborates on this fundamental point, disagreeing with G. Thomas
                  Tanselle in his MLA volume Electronic Textual Editing that <quote rend="inline"
                     source="#vanhoutte2007">the conceptual status of the texts</quote> does not
                  differ in print and electronic editions <ptr target="#vanhoutte2007" loc="160–161"
                  />. Our argument for the need for the Multitext is that print editions cannot
                  serve the purposes we envision for our digital edition, and that to achieve our
                  goals for the Multitext we must indeed make a change on the conceptual level of
                  what an edition of Homeric epic is, not simply how it is delivered to the
                  reader.</note> In this article we would like to explain in more depth than we have
               elsewhere how the oral, traditional poetry of these epics and their textual history
               call for a different editorial practice from what has previously been done and
               therefore also for a new means of representation. We will also demonstrate how the
               Homer Multitext shares features with but also has different needs and goals from
               other digital editions of literary works that were composed in writing. These
               comparisons will help to highlight our editorial approach to the variations attested
               in the textual record. We will conclude by stating our commitment to three
               foundational principles of the Multitext project that are essential to this digital
               criticism.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Textual Criticism of an Oral Poem in a Digital Medium</head>
            <p>When dealing with ancient texts, we never have access to the author’s own manuscript;
               moreover, our witnesses are copies many iterations and many centuries removed from
               any such <q>original.</q> The practice of textual criticism, in this case as applied
               to classical Greek texts, has the goal of recovering the original composition of the
               author <ptr target="#reynolds1991"/>. To create a critical edition, a modern editor
               assembles a text by collating the various written witnesses to an ancient Greek text,
               understanding their relationship with each other, knowing the kinds and likelihoods
               of mistakes that can occur when texts are copied by hand, and, in the case of poetry,
               applying the rules and exceptions of the meter as well as grammar. The final
               published work will then represent what she or he thinks are the author’s own words
               (or as close to this as possible). An editor may follow one manuscript almost
               exclusively, or pick and choose between different manuscripts to compile what seems
               truest to the original. The editor also places in the apparatus criticus what s/he
               judges to be significant variants recorded in the witnesses. The reader must rely on
               the editor for the completeness of the apparatus in reporting variants. For a text
               that was composed and originally published in writing, this goal of recovering the
               original text and these practices for achieving it have been valuable and productive,
               even if the author’s original composition may never be fully achieved because of the
               state of the evidence. </p>
            <p>A helpful comparison can be made to the critical editions of Shakespeare’s plays
               known as the <q>Variorum</q> editions, which are sponsored by and overseen by the
               Modern Language Association (<ref target="http://www.mla.org/variorum_handbook"
                  >http://​www.mla.org/​variorum_handbook</ref>). Although the textual tradition of
               Shakespeare is far less old than that of Archaic and Classical Greek texts, editors
               for each play in much the same way painstakingly compare and evaluate readings from
               different sources, make choices as to which is most likely to be correct, and justify
               their decisions. The Greek New Testament is another group of texts for which a
               rigorous system of evaluation of the various readings and their witnesses has
               developed (see, e.g., <ptr target="#aland2005"/>). Some digital projects, such as the
               Cervantes Project digital library, while capturing variation in the textual tradition
               in an Electronic Variorum Edition, do so for the stated goal of producing <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#monroy2002">a more correct edition closer to
                     Cervantes’ original manuscript</quote>
                  <ptr target="#monroy2002"/>
               </cit>. Similarly, Stringer argues that a variorum edition of John Donne’s poetry has
               allowed the restoration of a particular line <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#stringer1999">to its original form</quote>
                  <ptr target="#stringer1999" loc="91"/>
               </cit>. For an edition of Don Quixote de la Mancha or poems of Donne, this goal is
               appropriate to the fundamental notion of an original manuscript of an individual
               author and a text composed in writing.</p>
            <p>Because the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Odyssey</title> were not composed in writing, however, this editorial system
               cannot be applied in the same way. These epics come from a long oral tradition in
               which they were created, performed, and re-performed, all without the technology of
               writing. In the earliest phases of this tradition, the <title rend="italic"
                  >Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> would never have been
               performed in the same way twice. In other words, in such a tradition in which the
               composition is occurring in the course of performance, there is no one <q>author’s
                  original composition</q> to try to recover, for there is not only no one
               composition, but also no one author. This fundamental difference in the composition
               and history of this poetry, then, means that we must adjust our assumptions in our
               understanding of the variations in the written record. What does it mean when we see
               variations, which still fit the meter and language of the poetry, in the witnesses to
               the texts? Instead of <q>mistakes</q> to be corrected or choices that must be weighed
               and evaluated, as an editor would do in the case of a text composed in writing, we
               assert that these variations are testaments to the system of language that underlies
               the composition-in-performance of the oral tradition. Textual criticism as practiced
               is predicated on selection and <q>correction</q> as it creates the fiction of a
               singular text. The digital criticism we are proposing for the Homer Multitext
               maintains the integrity of each witness to allow for continual and dynamic
               comparison, better reflecting the multiplicity of the textual record and of the oral
               tradition in which these epics were created.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> as
               Oral Poetry</head>
            <p>We have learned from the comparative fieldwork of Milman Parry and Albert Lord, who
               studied and recorded a living oral tradition during the 1930s and again in the 1950s
               in what was then Yugoslavia, that the Homeric epics were composed in performance
               during a long oral tradition that preceded any written version (<ptr
                  target="#parry1971"/>, <ptr target="#lord1960"/>, <ptr target="#lord1991"/>, and
                  <ptr target="#lord1995"/>; see also <ptr target="#nagy1996a"/> and <ptr
                  target="#nagy2002"/>). In this tradition, the singer did not memorize a static
               text prior to performance, but would compose the song as he sang it. How is that
               possible, especially for a song such as the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>? As
               Parry and Lord were able to illustrate comparatively by way of the South Slavic
               tradition, the composition depends on a traditional system that can best be
               understood as a specialized language with its own specialized grammar and vocabulary.
               We refer to this specialized language as <q>formulaic,</q> using Parry’s terminology.
               This traditional language is most familiar to us in name-epithet combinations (e.g.,
                  <q>swift-footed Achilles</q>), but as scholarship over the past 75 years has
               shown, the whole epic is composed using this formulaic system. A singer trained in
               this system of language and in the traditional stories, as Parry and Lord themselves
               observed in action, can then rapidly compose while performing <ptr target="#lord1960"
               />.</p>
            <p>One of the most important revelations of the fieldwork of Parry and Lord is that
               every time the song is performed in an oral composition-in-performance tradition, it
               is composed anew. The singers themselves do not strive to innovate, but they
               nevertheless compose a new song each time <ptr target="#due2002" loc="83–89"/>. The
               mood of the audience or occasion of performance are just two factors that can
               influence the length of a song or a singer’s choices between competing, but still
               traditional, elements of plot. The training of the singer or the pressures of
               performance may influence which traditional formulas he employs in any particular
               line in performance. The term <q>variant,</q> as employed by textual critics when
               evaluating witnesses to a text, is not appropriate for such a compositional
                  process.<note>See for Van Hulle for his discussion of objections to the term
                     <q>variant</q> by practitioners of genetic criticism. Although Van Hulle
                  himself will use <q>variant</q> as an <quote rend="inline"
                     source="#vanhulle2004">umbrella term for both compositional and
                     transmissional variants,</quote> these objections arise when textual critics
                  pay attention to the process of composition and the natural variation that may
                  arise within that process <ptr target="#vanhulle2004" loc="514"/>. Working with
                  texts by modern authors like Joyce and Beckett, as Van Hulle does, is of course
                  very different from working with ancient works, and from working with orally
                  derived texts as well. But the parallel concerns about highlighting compositional
                  variants we share with the inclusive approaches of genetic criticism can perhaps
                  promote shared progress in developing the infrastructure of digital
                  editions.</note> Lord explained the difference this way: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lord1995">the word <emph>multiform</emph> is more
                     accurate than <emph>variant</emph>, because it does not give preference or
                     precedence to any one word or set of words to express an idea; instead it
                     acknowledges that the idea may exist in several forms</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lord1995" loc="23"/>
               </cit>. Our textual criticism of Homeric epic, then, needs to distinguish what may
               genuinely be copying mistakes and what are performance multiforms: that is, what
               variations we see are very likely to be part of the system and the tradition in which
               these epics were composed <ptr target="#due2001a"/>. </p>
            <p>Once we begin to think about the variations as parts of the system rather than as
               mistakes or corruptions, textual criticism of the Homeric texts can then address
               fresh questions. Some of the variations we see in the written record, for example,
               reveal the flexibility of this system. Where different written versions record
               different words, but each phrase or line is metrically and contextually sound, we
               must not necessarily consider one <q>correct</q> or <q>Homer</q> and the other a
                  <q>mistake</q> or an <q>interpolation.</q> Rather, each could represent a
               different performance possibility, a choice that the singer could make, and would be
               making rapidly without reference to a set text (in any sense of that word). </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Variation in the Homeric Corpus: Two Examples</head>
            <p>Let’s look at two brief examples of such multiforms and the questions they can raise
               for interpretation as well as what they add to our understanding of this system.
               These examples are intended to show why making the editorial choices that classical
               textual criticism demands can be disruptive for our understanding of the oral,
               traditional nature of this poetry, but they are not meant to be <emph>exempla</emph>
               in the sense of representing the whole range of multiforms. We will discuss the types
               and sources of variation further below.</p>
            <p>In 3, Priam asks Helen about a man on the battlefield, whom Helen identifies as
               Odysseus. Antenor, a Trojan, then reminisces about an earlier meeting he had with
               Odysseus and Menelaos when they came to negotiate for Helen’s return (<title
                  rend="italic">Iliad</title> 3.203–224). This whole episode is intriguing in terms
               of the storytelling, but we will limit our discussion here to just one recorded
               difference in one line of what Antenor says. He first compares the two Achaeans in
               terms of looks, and then on line 212 begins to compare the impression each made as a
               public speaker: <quote rend="block" source="#canonical">
                  <l>ἀλλ’ ὅτε δὴ μύθους καὶ μήδεα πᾶσιν ὕφαινον/ἔφαινον</l>
                  <l>But when they began to <hi rend="bold">weave/bring to light</hi> words and
                     schemes among all…</l>
               </quote> Many of the manuscripts have ὕφαινον (<q>weave</q>), but other witnesses
               report ἔφαινον (<q>bring to light</q>), which some modern editors, such as Ludwich,
               have preferred. In the usual criticism of a text composed in writing, as described
               above, this kind of variation would present the editor with a choice. There is only
               one letter (and breathing mark) different between the two, so a text-based assumption
               would be that one is original and one is a mistake made by a scribe at some point in
               the transmission. Are Odysseus and Menelaos weaving their words and schemes, or are
               they revealing them? Using the methods we outlined above, a textual critic would
               examine the evidence of the manuscripts to determine in which manuscripts and how
               often each verb shows up and consider which one is most likely to be confused for the
               other by a copyist. She or he would then make a decision about which one s/he thinks
               the author originally wrote and which one was the mistake. </p>
            <p>But when we think about these verbs as part of the traditional system of
               composition-in-performance, we can see that either verb is possible, and that either
               could be used in a performance. The two epics together provide our only
                  <q>database,</q> as it were, for seeing how the system of language works. In our
                  <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> ἔφαινον is used in this final position in the
               line (<title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> 4.12 and 19.25), but so is ὕφαινον
               (Odyssey 4.678 and 9.422). Thus, either is possible metrically in this position and
               is in fact used there within the compositional system. Considering the metrical
               position of the word in addition to its overall use helps to illustrate that a singer
               would be able to use it in this line <emph>in performance</emph>. Either is also
               equally possible in the context and sense of the line: Odysseus and Menelaos could be
               revealing their plans by telling the Trojans what they hope to achieve in meeting
               with them, or they could be speaking in a particular way for which the metaphor of
               weaving is used in this traditional language. The two line-final uses of ὕφαινον in
               the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> are particularly telling in this respect: in
               both of those cases the object of the verb is μῆτιν <q>craft, scheme.</q> (And this
               verb is also used with μῆτις in other metrical positions, such as at <title
                  rend="italic">Iliad</title> 8.324 or 9.93.) Thus we can see that the verb is often
               used in this metaphorical sense, and those instances can help us to better understand
               it at <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> 3.212. If they are weaving their μήδεα, they
               are plotting, whereas if they are revealing their μήδεα, they are telling the Trojans
               their plans. According to the system of traditional language, either is possible, and
               thus the singer who is composing in performance may use either characterization. The
               question to be pursued here is not which is right and which is wrong, but how to
               understand the coloring that each multiform gives to Antenor’s recollection. Thus we
               want readers to be able to easily be aware of both possibilities that have been
               transmitted and be able to see clearly which witnesses record them without taking the
               words out of their context within the source, as an apparatus does.</p>
            <p>Another example of multiformity, but one which does not involve the possibility of a
               spelling or copying mistake, is present in the written record of <title rend="italic"
                  >Iliad</title> 5.53. In this battle scene, Menelaos kills Skamandrios, the son of
               Strophios, whom, we hear, Artemis herself had taught to hunt (<title rend="italic"
                  >Iliad</title> 5.49–52). One version of 5.53 picks up on this association when it
               says: <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">ἀλλ᾽ οὔ οἱ τότε γε χραῖσμ᾽ Ἄρτεμις ἰοχέαιρα,
                     <hi rend="quotes">but Artemis who pours down arrows was no help to him
                     then</hi>.</quote> This is a reading known to Aristarchus (for more on whom,
               see below), and is recorded both in manuscripts and in papyrus fragments.
               Aristarchus’ predecessor as Librarian of Alexandria, Zenodotus, however, recorded a
               version of this line that reads <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">ἀλλ᾽ οὔ οἱ τότε γε
                  χραῖσμεν θανάτοιο πέλωρα, <hi rend="quotes">but portents of death were no help to
                     him then</hi>.</quote> The name-epithet combination of Ἄρτεμις ἰοχέαιρα shows
               up several more times in our <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">Odyssey</title>, mostly in this line-end position (e.g., <title
                  rend="italic">Iliad</title> 5.447, 6.428, 20.39, 24.606; <title rend="italic"
                  >Odyssey</title> 11.172 and 15.478). We do not have the exact phrase θανάτοιο
               πέλωρα elsewhere in our <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Odyssey</title>, but each word does show up in these particular metrical
               positions in other verses (πέλωρα at <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> 10.219;
               θανάτοιο eleven times in our <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and four times in our
                  <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> at that position), indicating that the two
               words could fit within a line together in those positions. Contextually, as well, the
               expression works, if perhaps a bit more mysteriously. Instead of asking how such a
                  <q>mistake</q> or <q>interpolation</q> could have crept into the written record
               (or just ignoring it altogether, as is more likely), we can instead consider how
               Zenodotus might have known about that multiform and inquire into his editorial
               practices for recording these lesser known (to us) versions. Such questions will
               ultimately be far more enlightening about the textual tradition of the poems as well
               as the system that makes composition in performance possible.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Representing Multiformity</head>
            <p>Yet it is difficult to indicate the parity of these multiforms in a standard critical
               edition on the printed page. As we noted in our introduction, one version must be
               chosen for the text on the upper portion of the page, and the other recorded
               variations must be placed in an apparatus below, often in smaller text, a placement
               that necessarily gives the impression that these variations are incorrect or at least
               less important. Within a digital medium, however, the Homer Multitext will be able to
               show where such variations occur, indicate clearly which witnesses record them, and
               allow users to see them in an arrangement that more intuitively distinguishes them as
               performance multiforms. Thus a digital criticism — one that can more readily present
               parallel texts — enables a more comprehensive understanding of these epics.</p>
            <p>An approach to editing Homer that embraces the multiformity of both the performative
               and textual phases of the tradition — that is to say, a multitextual approach — can
               convey the complexity of the transmission of Homeric epic in a way that is simply
               impossible on the printed page. The variations that the textual critic of Homer
               encounters come from many different kinds of sources and many time periods. In his
               edition of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> Allen included 188 manuscripts,
               dating from the 10th century CE on, and the relationship between manuscripts or
               manuscript families and their descent from earlier exemplars can be only partially
               reconstructed <ptr target="#allen1931"/>. From the scholia that survive in our
               medieval manuscripts — which includes commentary that is derived from scholarship as
               old as the second century BCE — we learn of readings attributed to the texts of
               various cities (some as far away as Marseilles), texts in the collection of
               individuals, texts called <q>common</q> or <q>standard,</q> and texts that are <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nagy2004">more refined</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nagy2004" loc="20"/>
               </cit>.<note>Monella proposes a digital model in which what he calls <quote
                     rend="inline" source="#monella2008">paratexts</quote> (for example,
                  commentary or glosses or the scholia such as we have in our manuscripts of Homeric
                  epic) remain connected to the main texts of the document in which they are found,
                  and then the various main texts and paratexts are aligned so that they can be
                  compared <ptr target="#monella2008"/>. The Multitext has similar goals of
                  presenting the scholia within their context as part of a specific manuscript and
                  even in their particular place on the page. That is, we hope to be able to capture
                  the spatial relationship of the comment and the main text on the page.</note> In
               the literature that survives from Classical Athens, especially in the Attic orators
               and in Plato, we find quotations of Homer, some quite extensive, and these texts can
               vary considerably from the medieval texts of Homer on which we rely for our printed
               editions (<ptr target="#due2001a"/> and <ptr target="#due2001b"/>). Some of our
               earliest witnesses to the text of Homer are the fragmentary papyri that survived in
               the sands of Egypt from the third century BCE onwards. These texts too are often
               quite different than their medieval counterparts <ptr target="#due2001a"/>. A
               multitextual approach can be explicit about these many different channels of
               transmission, placing each in its historical and cultural framework and allowing the
               reader to understand better their relationships to one another, rather than giving
               the false impression that they are all of the same kind and same time.</p>
            <p>From these sources, we find a number of different kinds of multiforms as well. We
               looked at two examples of different, but equally formulaic, words and phrases, and
               this is one kind of multiform. There are also smaller cases of word change,
               differences in word division or accent, and other matters of orthography. These
               differences are important for what they can reveal about the textual tradition and
               the editorial practices of earlier stages of the transmission. As we look at the
               earliest sources, papyri from the 3rd century BCE or quotations in Classical authors,
               such as Plato or Aeschines, we also see differences on the level of entire lines of
               the poetry. There are numerous verses in the papyri that are seemingly intrusive from
               the standpoint of the medieval transmission. These additional verses, the so-called
               plus verses, are not present in the majority of the medieval manuscripts of the
                  <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>. Other verses that are canonical in the
               medieval manuscripts are absent from the papyri — these may be termed minus verses.
               Composition in performance allows for expansion or compression of the theme or
               episode that the singer is performing, and these plus and minus verses are evidence
               of what a performance might have included, how the system underlying the performance
               operates, and what the epic tradition included <ptr target="#due2001a"/>.</p>
            <p>Yet even as we emphasize the historical significance of these multitudinous channels
               of transmission, we must be careful to acknowledge that there was never one <title
                  rend="italic">Iliad</title> or one <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> at any
               given time or place in the ancient world that we can seek to reconstruct. In earlier
               stages of the project, we have ourselves been tempted to create and include such a
               reconstruction. For example, we had considered attempting to reconstruct what would
               have been the <q>common</q> or koinē text at the time of Aristarchus, the great
               second century BCE scholar and editor who worked at the ancient library at Alexandria
                  <ptr target="#due2004"/>. Having this particular text would be a dream come true,
               for Aristarchus’ critical work on the text of Homer is referred to throughout the
               scholia that survive in the margins of our medieval manuscripts. But here the
               situation is no less complex, no less multiform. As Gregory Nagy has demonstrated,
               Aristarchus had available to him at the library of Ptolemaic Alexandria a great
               number of Homeric texts (see especially <ptr target="#nagy2004"/>). Aristarchus’
               practice was to collate the many texts known to him and to comment on the various
               readings that he found, often asserting which reading he felt to be the correct one.
               Unlike a modern editor, however, Aristarchus confined his opinions to his commentary,
               which was published in its own separate volume. The text that would have accompanied
               this commentary was what Aristarchus and subsequent scholars refer to as the
                  <q>standard</q> or <q>common</q> edition. But was this indeed a single edition
               that is reconstructable? Aristarchus himself does not seem to have ever published his
               own text of Homer, with his own preferred readings. But even if he had, we would know
               from his commentaries about the many other texts that were available to him, and so
               once again we are forced to confront the multiformity of the Homeric tradition. </p>
            <p>An emphasis on actual, complete witnesses to the transmission has thus driven many of
               our considerations in building the Multitext.<note>As Robinson notes, <quote
                     rend="inline" source="#robinson2005a">Fundamental to the model of electronic
                     scholarly edition as it has developed over the past decade is the inclusion of
                     full transcripts of all witnesses to the text</quote>
                  <ptr target="#robinson2005a" loc="§26"/>. </note> Presenting the witnesses to the
               user without the obstacle of an apparatus entails a fundamental change from textual
               criticism as practiced for print editions. As Edward Vanhoutte says about his
               electronic edition of <title rend="italic">De trein der traagheid</title>, which
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#vanhulle2004">guarantees the completely equal
                  treatment of each version of the text in the generating processes invoked by the
                  user,</quote> such an approach <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#vanhoutte2007">deliberately puts some central
                     concepts and issues of conventional textual scholarship in crisis. Amongst them
                     the base text, the edited text, the textual apparatus, and the variant. All of
                     these concepts are dependent on the static perception of the scholarly
                     edition</quote>
                  <ptr target="#vanhoutte2007" loc="165–166"/>
               </cit>. The move from a static perception to a dynamic presentation is central to our
               editorial standards for the Homer Multitext: that is, a shift not just in offering
               the witnesses to users, but in giving them tools to make comparisons and other
               relational assessments. Such tools allow for <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#vanhulle2004">a relative concept of calibration,</quote> where there is
               no one text as the <q>base text</q> or <q>invariant</q> that the others are compared,
               but where comparison of multiformity happens dynamically in an ever shifting
               selection of texts <ptr target="#vanhulle2004" loc="514"/>.<note>See also the
                  discussion of this concept and its application in <ptr target="#vanhoutte2007"
                     loc="166–168"/>. One concern for our project, as discussed further below, is
                  that the large number of witnesses, and the complexity of their historical
                  relationships to one another, could be overwhelming for a nonspecialist, and we
                  want to address this potential problem with some sort of guidance to the witnesses
                  that users may select and compare.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We share with many digital editions the value of including images of the sources,
               especially for wider access to fragile manuscripts (<ptr target="#dahlstrom2000"/>,
                  <ptr target="#monroy2002"/>, <ptr target="#kiernan2005"/>, <ptr
                  target="#robinson2005a"/>, <ptr target="#ulman2006"/>, <ptr target="#porter2007"
               />; for examples of textual edition projects using images, see the <ref
                  target="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/index.html">Internet Shakespeare
                  Editions</ref> and the <ref target="http://digitaldonne.tamu.edu">Digital Donne
                  project</ref>). The Multitext has now published for the first time digital images
               of three manuscripts of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> housed in the Marciana
               Library in Venice, Italy: the tenth-century Marcianus Graecus Z. 454 (= 822), the
               eleventh-century Marcianus Graecus Z. 453 (= 821), and the twelfth/thirteenth-century
               Marcianus Graecus Z. 458 (= 841). (See <ref
                  target="http://zeus.chsdc.org/chs/​manuscript_images"
                  >http://​zeus.chsdc.org/​chs/manuscript_images</ref>.) <figure xml:id="figure1">
                  <head>Screen shot of the manuscript browser</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/due_and_ebbott_figure1.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Figure 1: Screen shot of the manuscript browser on the CHS
                     website</figDesc>
               </figure> Each manuscript contains its own set of scholarly commentary in the
               margins. The initial publication of these images is focused on making them available
               as quickly as possible,<note>Thaller argues that one difference, and advantage, that
                  digital editions have over print editions is that digitized resources can be made
                  available to users while other aspects of the project are still in process. In
                  contrast to a print edition, which is only available when finished and <quote
                     rend="inline" source="#thaller2004">as close to perfect</quote> as possible,
                  digital editions can take what Thaller calls a <q>layered</q> approach, publishing
                  each stage of the process rather than waiting until it is <q>complete</q>
                  <ptr target="#thaller2004" loc="504"/>. In fact, he argues, the edition should be
                  seen as an ongoing process, not a <q>completed</q> product <ptr
                     target="#thaller2004" loc="505–510"/>. We have taken a similar approach with
                  publication of components of the Multitext even as we continue to add more and
                  continue to develop tools for using them.</note> but as we work to integrate them
               with other components of the Multitext, an important question we will be facing is
               how to make them truly accessible, not just available, to a range of users broader
               than just those who happen to be experts in Greek palaeography (cf. <ptr
                  target="#kiernan2005"/>). </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Fluidity vs. Rigidity and a Diachronic Approach to Homeric Poetry</head>
            <p>Here it is once again instructive to return to the comparison we made earlier to the
               transmission of the works of Shakespeare. Now that we have a better understanding of
               both the performance medium in which the Homeric poems were created and the
               complexities of their textual transmission, we can better appreciate how the two sets
               of texts share features but also differ in important ways. The transmission of
               Shakespeare’s plays is indeed quite complex. Authoritative editions of the plays were
               not overseen by Shakespeare himself, and the earliest editions seem to have in some
               instances at least been made on the basis of faulty transcripts of actual
               performances, requiring substantial reconstruction of the text <ptr
                  target="#greg1955"/>. The First Folio edition of 1623, which is the most
               authoritative of the early editions, was put together seven years after Shakespeare’s
               death by two actors in the King’s Men, the company for which Shakespeare wrote. The
               texts of the thirty-six plays included in the edition are of various provenance. Some
               derive from the heavily annotated copies prepared for prompters; others are based on
               Shakespeare’s own working drafts. It is clear that some plays were revised for
               subsequent performances during the course of Shakespeare’s lifetime, with the result
               that there are multiple versions of the same work that are equally Shakespearean.
               Editors of such important Classical authors as (Greek) Aristophanes and (Roman) Ovid
               face similar difficulties. </p>
            <p>What the plays of Shakespeare share with the Homeric tradition is that they were
               created in the context of performance. Individual instances of performance could
               result in new texts, depending on the occasion of performance, the intervention of
               actors and/or others involved in the production, or the desire of Shakespeare
               himself. A transcript created on the basis of a given performance would no doubt vary
               from transcripts created on other occasions. Such variations can teach us a great
               deal about the performance traditions of Shakespeare’s plays, the creative process,
               and Shakespeare’s working methods. Scholars of recent decades have rightly seen the
               value in the variation that we find in the textual transmission, and several
               web-based projects have been developed that make the quartos and folios available to
               an interested public. Of particular note is <ref
                  target="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/index.html">The Internet Shakespeare
                  Editions</ref>, which plans to publish high-resolution photographs of these early
               editions together with a variety of supplementary information, electronic texts, and
               fully edited (modern) editions. </p>
            <p>But the Shakespeare analogy can only be taken so far. Homeric poetry was not only
               created <emph>for</emph> performance, it was created <emph>in</emph> performance. As
               we noted previously, in the earliest stages of the tradition no song would have ever
               been sung the same way twice. The content and form of the songs were traditional and
               the tradition was a highly conservative one, but the compositional process was
               nonetheless dynamic. As editors of the Homer Multitext, we are not seeking to recover
               the most authoritative performance, because such a performance does not exist. Rather
               than screen out variation in the search for the author’s own words, we seek out
               variation for what it can tell us about Homeric composition-in-performance and the
               evolution of the texts we now recognize as our <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>.</p>
            <p>Perhaps unexpectedly, a much more modern text provides us with a different and
               interesting analogy. The Homer Multitext faces some of the same questions, problems,
               and demands as those laid out by Loranger for an editor of William Burroughs’s <title
                  rend="italic">Naked Lunch</title>
               <ptr target="#loranger1999"/>. Loranger points out that there is no one definitive
               version of <title rend="italic">Naked Lunch</title>, that none of the changes to the
               narrative <quote rend="inline" source="#loranger1999">can be considered accidental
                  variants … [or] deliberate authorial revisions</quote> (#2). The narrative
               underwent an evolution (#1), and its assembly has its own mythology, as she terms it
               (#6–7). She begins and ends by looking for a <emph>reliable</emph> edition, and
               argues that such an edition would have to allow readers to move, in any order,
               between the different textual elements, fragments, and even images, such as the
               drawings Burroughs produced for the U.S. edition (#1, 24). We are in no way looking
               to create a <q>postmodern</q> Homer, but what we know about oral
               composition-in-performance, in which each time the song is sung it is composed anew,
               requires a similar attention to the evolution as much as we can trace it and to the
               creation or application of tools for allowing the reader to explore and understand
               that evolution.</p>
            <p>The texts on which modern printed editions of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>
               and <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> are based date to the Medieval period, the
               earliest being the tenth-century CE manuscript known as the Venetus A (Marcianus
               Graecus Z. 454). These texts do not differ substantially from one another, although
               there is no <q>vulgate</q> text on which the others are based; there is some
               variation to be found among the different manuscript groups. If we proceed
               considerably back in time, to the fragmentary papyrus texts of the Ptolemaic era
               (third to second centuries BCE) we find substantial variation. Still earlier are the
               quotations of Homer in authors of the Classical era. These too are often
               substantially different from the medieval texts. Further back than that we cannot go,
               because of the lack of textual witnesses before the Classical period, but internal
               evidence indicates the poetic tradition extends as far back as the sixteenth century
               BCE, a date that, incidentally, long precedes most accepted dates for an historical
               Trojan War <ptr target="#sherratt1990"/>; <ptr target="#watkins1995" loc="499"/>.
               Needless to say, whatever songs were being created in the sixteenth century BCE would
               likely have resembled our <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Odyssey</title> only very vaguely, but they were nevertheless composed in the
               same system of language that produced these epics. </p>
            <p>The questions of how much variation is natural to the Homeric tradition and how much
               variation can be recovered are complicated ones to answer, because they tie into all
               of the uncertainty surrounding the figure of Homer (if he ever existed) and the
               nature of Homeric authorship <ptr target="#nagy1996b"/>, <ptr target="#due2006"/>. It
               was at one time fashionable in Homeric Studies to apply statistics to the Homeric
                  corpus.<note>Besides the examples discussed here, two others should be noted. In
                  1924, T. W. Allen analyzed variations in early papyrus texts to come up with
                  percentage degrees of difference from the Medieval texts of Homer <ptr
                     target="#allen1924"/>. In 1982, Richard Janko published a statistical analysis
                  of the dialects and other language features in Homer, Hesiod, and the Homeric
                  Hymns and used them to argue (among other things) that our <title rend="italic"
                     >Iliad</title> was composed and fixed in the eighth century BCE <ptr
                     target="#janko1982"/>. Unfortunately, the studies of both Allen and Janko are
                  marred by their small sample size, which limits the strength of any inferences
                  that can be drawn from analysis of the data. Allen himself admitted as much,
                  noting that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#allen1924">many of the figures are
                        meaningless</quote>
                     <ptr target="#allen1924" loc="300"/>
                  </cit>.</note> Scholars attempted to use mathematical methods to find what parts
               of the Homeric diction are <q>formulaic</q> and what parts are innovations on the
               part of a master poet, imagined as Homer. Parry, for example, by way of demonstration
               analyzed the first 15 verses of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and found them
               to be over 90% <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#parry1971">formulaic</quote>
                  <ptr target="#parry1971" loc="301–304"/>
               </cit>. Later, Albert Lord analyzed the same passage, and although his definition of
               the individual formulas involved differed slightly from Parry’s the results were
               roughly the same <ptr target="#lord1960" loc="142–144"/>. The fundamental problems
               with this kind of analysis are twofold, as Lord himself pointed out already in 1960.
               First and foremost, it is based on faulty data. Only two of the large number of
               Archaic Greek epics that we know were current in antiquity have survived to the
               current day. If more of the Epic Cycle (as these other epics are commonly called)
               survived, we would have a much larger amount of material to work with. Partly because
               of the relatively small amount of comparison material, our understanding of the
               nature of the formula and the composition process is imperfect. Secondly, if the
               tradition in which the Greek poets were working was as Parry and Lord described,
               every verse should be formulaic, and there is much to suggest that this true of
               Homeric poetry <ptr target="#lord1960" loc="47, 147"/>. </p>
            <p>For Shakespeare, multiformity — that is to say, the existence of multiple versions of
               the same text — is an unintended accident of transmission. For most of the plays,
               there is only one version that Shakespeare himself would have considered definitive,
               even if he would acknowledge other drafts he produced and even though we today would
               no doubt consider those drafts worth saving. For Homeric epic, the relative
               uniformity of the medieval manuscripts is the accident of transmission, and
               multiformity is the natural result of the process by which they were created.
               Hundreds of the relatively uniform Medieval texts of Homer survive, whereas no
               complete text of Homer survives on papyrus, and only certain passages are quoted in
               Classical authors. In a 2001 publication, Dué examined in detail a Homeric quotation
               from the orator Aeschines together with some Ptolemaic papyri <ptr target="#due2001a"
               />. Dué found that the kinds of variation presented in those sources are of a
               formulaic nature. There are extra verses, alternative verses, and variation within
               lines, but the nature of the variations is such that they are equally <q>Homeric</q>
               as those that survived in our Medieval transmission. This kind of variation, which is
               primarily on the level of formula and fluctuation in the number of verses, would not
               interest all readers of Homer, but it is what is to be expected in a relatively late
               stage of the transmission, at a point when the poems were largely fixed. For even as
               early as the Classical period — whence the earliest textual evidence survives — the
               Homeric poems seem to have had a cohesiveness and unity that borders on the adjective
                  <q>fixed</q>.</p>
            <p>Before we attempt to go even further back in time, and consider a far more fluid
               state of the text, it might be helpful here to consider the evolutionary model for
               the development of the Homeric poems that has been proposed by Gregory Nagy. Nagy
               traces the evolution of the poems in five stages, that go from <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#nagy2004">most fluid</quote> to <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nagy2004">most rigid</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nagy2004" loc="27"/>
               </cit>: <list type="ordered">
                  <item>a relatively most fluid period, with no written texts, extending from the
                     early second millennium into the middle of the eighth century in the first
                     millennium BCE.</item>
                  <item>a more formative or <q>Panhellenic</q> period, still with no written texts,
                     from the middle of the eighth century to the middle of the sixth BCE. </item>
                  <item>a definitive period, centralized in Athens, with potential texts in the
                     sense of <emph>transcripts</emph>, at any or several points from the middle of
                     the sixth century to the later part of the fourth BCE; this period starts with
                     the reform of Homeric performance traditions in Athens during the régime of the
                     Peisistratidai. </item>
                  <item>a standardizing period, with texts in the sense of transcripts or even
                        <emph>scripts</emph>, from the later part of the fourth century to the
                     middle of the second BCE; this period starts with the reform of Homeric
                     performance traditions in Athens during the régime of Demetrius of Phalerum,
                     which lasted from 317 to 307 BCE</item>
                  <item>a relatively most rigid period, with texts as <emph>scripture</emph>, from
                     the middle of the second century onward; this period starts with the completion
                     of Aristarchus’ editorial work on the Homeric texts, not long after 150 BCE or
                     so, which is a date that also marks the general disappearance of the so-called
                        <q>eccentric</q> papyri.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>When we discuss the relative multiformity of the Classical and Ptolemaic eras, we are
               speaking of periods (3) and (4) in Nagy’s model, the <q>definitive</q> period and
                  <q>standardizing</q> period, respectively. It is interesting to compare Nagy’s
               suggestion of the possibility of <q>transcripts</q> at this time to our discussion of
               the multiformity that we find in the textual transmission of Shakespeare, where we
               noted the influence of transcripts on the early printed editions of the plays. During
               these centuries, there was an interaction between performances and texts, with many
               performances (and state regulations of such performances) and many texts potentially
               influencing one another. The relative multiformity we see in our sources from these
               periods highlight the lasting dynamism of the performance tradition. The introduction
               of written texts did not shut this tradition down, but participated in it. </p>
            <p>Can a Multitext of Homer tell us anything about Nagy’s periods (1) and (2), the
                  <q>most fluid</q> and <q>formative</q> phases of our <title rend="italic"
                  >Iliad</title> and <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>? This is our hope, that by
               making available the historical witnesses to the texts of these poems, as they
               circulated in antiquity and the Medieval period, we can allow users to understand
               with even more precision the workings of the traditional system within which our
               poems were created, and the semantic possibilities that are opened up when the system
               is viewed diachronically. </p>
            <p>The most fluid and formative phases of Homeric poetry are only accessible to us
               through careful study of what survived through to later periods, and in this sense
               our project is somewhat speculative. Our knowledge of other oral traditions, studied
               by anthropologists working while these traditions were/are still flourishing, is
               another important resource that can help us go further back, as we consider the kinds
               of meaning that are conveyed and preserved by performance generated texts <ptr
                  target="#foley1991"/>, <ptr target="#foley1995"/>, <ptr target="#foley1999"/>. The
               difficulties inherent in the enterprise should not deter us from the work, however,
               and that the answers revealed by a Multitext may at times makes us uncomfortable
               because of our own notions about Homer should not keep us from raising these
               questions. </p>
            <p>It has frequently been asserted that the multiformity of the Homeric tradition is not
               interesting, and that the few variations we do find are banal and inconsequential.
               From our perspective, this assertion is simply untrue (see especially <ptr
                  target="#due2001a"/>). It seems that the expectation or desire would be for a
               recorded variation that would dramatically change the story — Achilles goes home!
               Odysseus dies at sea! But the idea that the manuscripts, coming so late in the
               tradition as they do, would have as much multiformity as earlier stages of the
               textual tradition, not to mention the full oral tradition itself, is both misinformed
               and misleading. What is interesting about the multiforms that are recorded in our
               textual sources — and let us emphasize again that the older the source, the greater
               the multiformity we see — is that they are both a window onto the underlying system
               of oral poetry as well as being crucial evidence for the textual tradition itself. It
               cannot be denied that the multiforms in the manuscripts, papyri, scholia, and
               quotations have much to teach us about the composition and transmission of the
               poetry. In turn, they also provide substantial food for thought in how we then
               interpret the poetry that has been transmitted. The profit to be gained here is not
               in the kinds of variants that would make a huge difference in any one line or
               episode, but that do make a significant difference in our understanding of the system
               of Homeric epic as a whole.</p>
            <p>The multiforms go to the heart of the Homeric Question. It would be intellectually
               dishonest and scientifically invalid, moreover, to try to show how <q>multiform</q>
               our text of Homer is with percentages, charts and graphs — though as we have pointed
               out, such attempts have been made. It is more intellectually honest to assert that
               every verse in Homeric poetry is at least potentially a multiform, and to explore the
               implications of that potential whenever we analyze the text for its poetic
               possibilities. The Homer Multitext seeks to give users many of the tools they need to
               confront and explore the poetics of a multiform epic tradition. </p>
            <p>We know, therefore, that the circumstances of the composition of the Homeric epics
               demand a new kind of scholarly edition, a new kind of representation. We believe that
               a digital criticism of the witnesses to the poetry provides a means to construct one.
               Now the mission is to envision and create the Multitext so that it is true to these
               standards. The framework and tools that will connect these texts and make them
               dynamically useful are, as Peter Robinson has frankly stated (<ptr
                  target="#robinson2005a"/> and <ptr target="#robinson2005b"/>), the challenge that
               lies before us, as it does for other digital scholarly editions. How shall we
               highlight multiforms so as to make them easy to find and compare? We cannot simply
               have a list of variants, as some digital editions have done, for this would take them
               once again out of their context within the textual transmission and in many ways
               repeat the false impression that a printed apparatus gives.<note>E.g., the Digital
                  Donne project at <ref target="http://digitaldonne.tamu.edu/00a-variants-list.html"
                     >http://​digitaldonne.tamu.edu/​00A-variants-list.html</ref>.</note> Another
               consideration is that the hexameter line in Homeric epic is a unit of composition, so
               we want to display and compare complete lines — not just point out what differences
               exist within the line, as an apparatus often does.<note>Dirk Van Hulle describes a
                  digital edition of Samuel Beckett’s <title rend="italic">Stirrings Still</title>
                  in which the reader can arrange all versions of sentences, paragraphs, or sections
                  of different drafts in a vertical juxtaposition, or compare two versions in a
                  parallel format <ptr target="#vanhulle2004" loc="517"/>.</note> In addition to
               this need for easy comparison, we need to display lines as part of whole texts to
               maintain the historical contexts of the witnesses. But we also need a way for our
               users to find compositional multiforms without already being aware of their existence
               or without reading every line of every witness.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Foundational principles of the Homer Multitext</head>
            <p>Given the complexity of the Homeric transmission and these challenges, one might well
               ask how such an ambitious project can be achieved. The technological infrastructure
               of the project has been described on the <ref
                  target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/homer_multitext">project website</ref> and a
               series of technological papers have been commissioned to document how we will proceed
               (see <ref target="http://katoptron.holycross.edu/cocoon/diginc/techpub"
                  >http://​katoptron.holycross.edu/​cocoon/​diginc/techpub</ref>). As we continue to
               build our collection of texts, there are still questions to be answered about how to
               construct the architecture to achieve the visual representation we envision and that
               will achieve the results we have described here. But no matter what the details end
               up being, we have committed to three foundational principles: collaboration, open
               access, and interoperability. We would like to conclude this essay by emphasizing
               them, for these principles are essential to this project but also vital to the future
               of the humanities as a whole. </p>
            <p>First and foremost is the collaborative nature of the project. Dozens of scholars of
               every rank and from many different kinds of institutions currently play vital roles,
               contributing their own areas of expertise. Although the model for Homeric research is
               most often that of the individual genius working alone, we suggest that the kind of
               collaboration that is at the heart of the Multitext allows for a higher quality of
               research and analysis that can be accomplished in a more timely manner. As other
               digital edition projects amply demonstrate, these large, long-term undertakings
               simply cannot be accomplished without this fruitful, energizing collaboration. We
               have been fortunate to collaborate with technologically informed classical scholars:
               indeed, one special aspect of our project is that the information architects,
               Christopher Blackwell and Neel Smith, are themselves Classics scholars, and we expect
               that this project will demonstrate how our sustained collaboration can lead to more
               thoughtful, thorough, and creative scholarship on the Homeric epics.</p>
            <p>Second, the Homer Multitext project is an open access project: that is, it is
               on-line, free of charge to all, and free of most copyright or licensing restrictions.
               A prime example of our ideals of open access is the digital photographs of the three
               manuscripts. These images will be a significant element of the Multitext, but even
               before we have fully integrated them into the project, we want to make them available
               to any and all through the CHS website so that others may use them in their own
               research. As other digital scholarly editions have noted (e.g., the Cervantes
               Project, see <ptr target="#monroy2002"/>), providing users access to these rare and
               normally inaccessible manuscripts or other texts is an important goal for the project
               in and of itself.</p>
            <p>Now that we have collaborated with so many scholars who share this ideal of open
               access (and learned from the many open access projects that now exist in the
               Humanities), it sometimes seems almost unnecessary to assert it. Yet almost as soon
               as we think so, we are once again faced with proprietary systems that cannot work
               with others, or a publishing ethos that believes barriers to access are either
               necessary, profitable, or at least acceptable. (<ref
                  target="http://www.apaclassics.org">The American Philological Association</ref>,
               for example, recently added a <q>Members Only</q> section of the website, which
               includes on-line access to the APA-sponsored journal, <title rend="italic"
                  >Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association</title>.
                  <q>Members Only</q> requires an annual membership fee and perpetuates an elitist
               notion of the field.) We instead believe that it is in the best interest of all who
               work in the humanities to embrace open access. Doing so is a matter of survival for
               our field in particular. The popularity of movies like <title rend="italic"
                  >Gladiator</title> and <title rend="italic">Troy</title> and the HBO television
               series <title rend="italic">Rome</title> indicates that the Classical world continues
               to fascinate and have relevance for our culture, and yet the importance of the study
               of ancient Greece and Rome at the university level has been questioned in recent
               decades by budget-minded administrators. Classicists have themselves partially to
               blame. Too often we cultivate that elite mentality that is off-putting to newcomers
               to the field and administrators alike. Indeed it is a sense of elitism that very
               often promotes barriers to access to our scholarly resources. We must reach out in
               order to sustain our discipline, and we must create resources for our discipline that
               adhere to open access standards. The Center for Hellenic Studies strives to be a
               model for other institutions in its support for digital scholarship and in its
               commitment to making that scholarship available and accessible, free of charge.</p>
            <p>Third, we are committed to using international standards based technology. We want
               our project to talk to other digital initiatives in the Classics and in the
               humanities at large. We want scholars and readers to be able <emph>easily</emph> to
               find and use the texts and images that are part of this project, including re-using
               them for their own purposes. Toward this goal, we use TEI-conformant XML and Creative
               Commons Licensing in our publishing, and scholars affiliated with the CHS have
               developed the Canonical Text Services protocol, described on the Multitext website
               (see <ref target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/technological_infrastructure"
                  >http://​chs.harvard.edu/​chs/​technological_infrastructure</ref>). All three of
               these principles are themselves connected to a larger ideal of sharing these texts
               and our work with as large an audience as possible, and not allowing barriers or
               restrictions to prevent others from using them in their own research or in other
               creative endeavors.</p>
            <p>For these foundational principles we are indebted to the ideals of the <ref
                  target="http://www.stoa.org">Stoa Consortium</ref> and its founder Ross Scaife.
               The Multitext was born in a summer meeting at the Center for Hellenic Studies, to
               which Ross was invited as a potential collaborator. He quickly became our mentor and
               guide in the ever-evolving world of electronic publishing in the Humanities. It was
               clear from the beginning that Ross had a vision that extended far past the point
               where most classicists were working at that time. He saw how Classics could fit into
               a global, interdisciplinary, and collaborative environment, and he was willing to be
               a pioneer in enforcing standards that today keep the web open and democratic. We are
               grateful for his leadership and guidance as we strive to maintain these standards and
               attain the ideals of all a digital medium can do for research on Homeric epic. We
               will miss his expertise and his patient and generous giving of that expertise, but
               most of all, we miss him as a cherished colleague and friend. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aland2005" label="Aland 2005" key="aland2005"> Aland, K. <title
                  rend="italic">Synopsis quattuor evangeliorum: locis parallelis evangeliorum
                  apocryphorum et patrum adhibitis</title>. Stuttgart, Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft:
               2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allen1924" label="Allen 1924" key="allen1924"> Allen, T. W. <title
                  rend="italic">Homer: The Origins and Transmission</title>. Oxford, 1924.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allen1931" label="Allen 1931" key="allen1931"> Allen, T.W. <title
                  rend="italic">Homeri Ilias</title>. Oxford, 1931.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dahlstrom2000" label="Dahlström 2000" key="dahlstrom2000"> Dahlström, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Drowning by Versions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Human IT</title> 4 (2000). Available on-line at <ref
                  target="http://hb.se/bhs/ith/4-00/md.htm"
               >http://hb.se/bhs/ith/4-00/md.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="desmedt2002" label="De Smedt and Vanhoutte 2002" key="desmedt2002a"> De
               Smedt, M. and Vanhoutte, E. <title rend="quotes">The Best of Three Worlds:
                  Eclecticism in Editorial Theory</title> Preprint, <title rend="italic">Sichtungen
                  Online</title> 06-24-2002, <ref
                  target="http://www2.onb.ac.at/sichtungen/berichte/smedt-m-1a.html"
                  >http://www2.onb.ac.at/sichtungen/berichte/smedt-m-1a.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="due2001a" label="Dué 2001a" key="due2001a"> Dué, C. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Achilles’ Golden Amphora in Aeschines’ Against Timarchus and the Afterlife of
                  Oral Tradition.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Classical Philology</title> 96 (2001): 33-47. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="due2001b" label="Dué 2001b" key="due2001b">
               <title rend="quotes">Sunt Aliquid Manes: Homer, Plato, and Alexandrian Allusion in
                  Propertius 4.7.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Classical Journal</title> 96 (2001): 401-413.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="due2002" label="Dué 2002" key="due2002">
               <title rend="italic">Homeric Variations on a Lament by Briseis</title>. Lanham, Md.:
               Rowman and Littlefield Press, 2002. <ref target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/du_1"
                  >http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/du_1</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="due2006" label="Dué 2006" key="due2006">
               <title rend="quotes">The Invention of Ossian.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Classics</title>@ 3 (2006). <ref
                  target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/files/classics_issue3_due.pdf"
                  >http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/files/classics_issue3_due.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="due2004" label="Dué and Ebbott 2004" key="due2004"> Dué, C. and Ebbott, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">As Many Homers As You Please: an On-line Multitext of
                  Homer,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Classics</title>@ 2 (2004), C. Blackwell, R. Scaife, edd., <ref
                  target="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/issue_2_-_du__and_ebbott"
                  >http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/issue_2_-_du__and_ebbott</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foley1991" label="Foley 1991" key="foley1991a"> Foley, J. M. <title
                  rend="italic">Immanent Art: From Structure to Meaning in Traditional Oral
                  Epic</title>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press: 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foley1995" label="Foley 1995" key="foley1995"> Foley, J. M. <title
                  rend="italic">The Singer of Tales in Performance</title>. Bloomington: Indiana
               University Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foley1999" label="Foley 1999" key="foley1999"> Foley, J. M. <title
                  rend="italic">Homer’s Traditional Art</title>. University Park, Pennsylvania State
               University Press: 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greg1955" label="Greg 1955" key="greg1955"> Greg, W. W. <title
                  rend="italic">The Shakespeare First Folio: Its Bibliographical and Textual
                  History</title>. London: Clarendon Press, 1955.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="janko1982" label="Janko 1982" key="janko1982"> Janko, R. <title
                  rend="italic">Homer, Hesiod, and the Hymns: Diachronic Development in Epic
                  Diction</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kiernan2005" label="Kiernan 2005" key="kiernan2005"> Kiernan, K. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Fascimilies in Editing: Some Guidelines for Editors of
                  Image-based Scholarly Editions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Electronic Textual Editing</title>, ed. Burnard, Lou, Katherine
               O'Brien O’Keeffe and John Unsworth. New York: Modern Language Association of America,
               2005. Preprint at: <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/activities/ete/preview/kiernan.xml"
                  >http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/ETE/Preview/kiernan.xml</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loranger1999" label="Loranger 1999" key="loranger1999"> Loranger, C.
                  <title rend="quotes">This Book Spills Off the Page in All Directions: What is the
                  Text of Naked Lunch?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Postmodern Culture</title> 10.1 (1999). <ref
                  target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/pmc/text-only/issue.999/10.1loranger.txt"
                  >http://www.iath.virginia.edu/pmc/text-only/issue.999/10.1loranger.txt</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lord1960" label="Lord 2000" key="lord2000"> Lord, A. B. <title
                  rend="italic">The Singer of Tales. </title>. 1960. 2nd rev. edition. Cambridge,
               MA: Harvard University Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lord1991" label="Lord 1991" key="lord1991"> Lord, A. B. <title
                  rend="italic">Epic Singers and Oral Tradition. </title> Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell
               University Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lord1995" label="Lord 1995" key="lord1995"> Lord, A. B. <title
                  rend="italic">The Singer Resumes the Tale. </title> Ithaca, N.Y.:Cornell
               University Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monella2008" label="Monella 2008" key="monella2008"> Monella, P. <title
                  rend="quotes">Towards a digital model to edit the different paratextuality levels
                  within a textual tradition.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</title> 4 (2008). <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/4/monella/"
                  >http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/4/monella/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monroy2002" label="Monroy et. al. 2002" key="monroy2002"> Monroy, C.,
               Kochumman, R., Furuta, R., Urbina, E., Melgoza, E., and Goenka, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Visualization of Variants in Textual Collations to Anaylze the
                  Evolution of Literary Works in The Cervantes Project.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 6th European Conference on Research and
                  Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries</title>, 2002: 638-653. <ref
                  target="http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/cervantes/pubs/ecdl2002.pdf"
                  >http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/cervantes/pubs/ecdl2002.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nagy1996a" label="Nagy 1996a" key="nagy1996a"> Nagy, G. <title
                  rend="italic">Poetry as Performance. </title> Cambridge: Cambridge University
               Press, 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nagy1996b" label="Nagy 1996b" key="nagy1996b"> Nagy, G. <title
                  rend="italic">Homeric Questions. </title> Austin, TX: University of Texas Press,
               1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nagy2000" label="Nagy 2000" key="nagy2000"> Nagy, G. Review of Martin L.
               West (ed.) <title rend="italic">Homeri Ilias. </title>
               <title rend="italic">Bryn Mawr Classical Review</title> 2000.09.12: <ref
                  target="http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/bmcr/2000/2000-09-12.html"
                  >http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/bmcr/2000/2000-09-12.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nagy2002" label="Nagy 2002" key="nagy2002"> Nagy, G. <title rend="italic"
                  >Plato’s Rhapsody and Homer’s Music: The Poetics of the Panathenaic Festival in
                  Classical Athens. </title> Cambridge, MA: Center for Hellenic Studies,
               2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nagy2004" label="Nagy 2004" key="nagy2004a"> Nagy, G. <title rend="italic"
                  >Homer’s Text and Language</title>. Champaign, IL: University of Illinois Press,
               2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parry1971" label="Parry 1971" key="parry1971"> Parry, A. (ed.). <title
                  rend="italic">The Making of Homeric Verse. </title> Oxford: Clarendon Press,
               1971.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="porter2007" label="Porter 2007" key="porter2007"> Porter, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Examples of Images in Text Editing.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 19th Joint International Conference of the
                  Association for Computers and the Humanities, and the Association for Literary and
                  Linguistic Computing, at the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign,
                  2007</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dh2007/abstracts/xhtml.xq?id=250"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dh2007/abstracts/xhtml.xq?id=250</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reynolds1991" label="Reynolds and Wilson 1991" key="reynolds1991">
               Reynolds, L. D. and Nigel G. Wilson. <title rend="italic">Scribes and Scholars: A
                  Guide to the Transmission of Greek and Latin Literature.</title> Oxford: Clarendon
               Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2005a" label="Robinson 2003" key="robinson2003"> Robinson, P.
                  <title rend="quotes">Where We Are with Electronic Scholarly Editions, and Where We
                  Want to Be.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie Online</title> 1.1 (2005) at
                  <ref target="http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg03/robinson.html"
                  >http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg03/robinson.html</ref>, January 2004.
               In print in <title rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie</title> 2004:
               123-143.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2005b" label="Robinson 2005b" key="robinson2005b"> Robinson, P.
                  <title rend="quotes">Current Issues in Making Digital Editions of Medieval texts —
                  or, Do Electronic Scholarly Editions have a Future?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</title> 1.1 (2005). <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/article.cfm?recid=6"
                  >http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/article.cfm?RecID=6</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sherratt1990" label="Sherratt 1990" key="sherratt1990"> Sherrat, E. S.
                  <title rend="quotes">Reading the Texts: Archaeology and the Homeric
                  Question.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Antiquity</title> 64 (1990): 807–824.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stringer1999" label="Stringer 1999" key="stringer1999"> Stringer, G.
                  <title rend="quotes">An Introduction to the Donne Variorum and the John Donne
                  Society.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Anglistik</title> 10.1 (March 1999): 85–95. Available on-line at
                  <ref target="http://donnevariorum.tamu.edu/anglist/anglist.pdf"
                  >http://donnevariorum.tamu.edu/anglist/anglist.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thaller2004" label="Thaller 2004" key="thaller2004"> Thaller, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Manuscripts as Base Line for Dynamic Editions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Lingusitica Computazionale XX-XXI</title> (2004): 489–511. The
               issue is titled <title rend="italic">Digital Technology and Philological
                  Disciplines</title> and was edited by A. Bozzi, L. Cignoni, and J-L.
               Lebrave.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ulman2006" label="Ulman 2006" key="ulman2006"> Ulman, H. L. <title
                  rend="quotes">Will the Real Edition Please Stand Out?: Negotiating Multi-Linear
                  Narratives encoded in Electronic Textual Editions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Code Conference</title>, 2006. <ref
                  target="http://www.units.muohio.edu/codeconference/papers/papers/ulman-code03.pdf"
                  >http://www.units.muohio.edu/codeconference/papers/papers/Ulman-Code03.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanhulle2004" label="Van Hulle 2004" key="vanhulle2004"> Van Hulle, D.
                  <title rend="quotes">Compositional Variants in Modern Manuscripts.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Lingusitica Computazionale XX-XXI</title> (2004): 513–527. The
               issue is titled <title rend="italic">Digital Technology and Philological
                  Disciplines</title> and was edited by A. Bozzi, L. Cignoni, and J-L.
               Lebrave.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanhoutte2007" label="Vanhoutte 2007" key="vanhoutte2007"> Vanhoutte, E.
                  <title rend="quotes">Traditional Editorial Standards and the Digital
                  Edition.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Learned Love. Proceedings of the Emblem Project, Utrecht
                  Conference on Dutch Love Emblems and the Internet</title> (November 2006), ed. Els
               Stronks and Peter Boot. The Hague: DANS, 2007: 157-174. <ref
                  target="http://emblems.let.uu.nl/static/images/project/learned_love_157-174.pdf"
                  >http://emblems.let.uu.nl/static/images/project/learned_love_157-174.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="watkins1995" label="Watkins 1995" key="watkins1995"> Watkins, C. <title
                  rend="italic">How to Kill a Dragon: Aspects of Indo-European Poetics</title>. New
               York: Oxford University Press, 1995. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
