<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digital Geography and Classics</title>
            <author>Tom Elliott</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Tom <dhq:family>Elliott</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>New York University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>tom.elliott@nyu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Tom Elliott is Associate Director for Digital Programs and Senior Research
                     Scholar at the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World at New York
                     University. Information about his current work — which spans digital approaches
                     to epigraphy, papyrology, historical geography and other aspects of ancient
                     studies — is provided on his home page at <ref
                        target="http://homepages.nyu.edu/~te20/"
                        >http://homepages.nyu.edu/~te20/</ref>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Sean Gillies</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Sean <dhq:family>Gillies</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>New York University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>sean.gillies@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sean Gillies is a computer programmer and pioneer in the field of open source
                     geographic information systems. He has been a member of the MapServer Project's
                     Steering Committee and now leads the GIS-Python Laboratory, an international
                     effort to develop excellent GIS tools for the Python programming language. His
                     sometimes influential blog focuses on the geospatial industry, open source
                     software, and the Web. He currently directs software development at New York
                     University's Institute for the Study of the Ancient World.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000031</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-02-26">26 February 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2008-09-23" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-09-25" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-10-07" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-10-28" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-10-29" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-10-31" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-11-18" who="Melanie Kohnen">Encoding</change>
         <change when="2008-12-03" who="JHF">Fixed captions and figure descriptions; checked
            encoding.</change>
         <change when="2008-12-15" who="Alyssa">copyedited</change>
         <change when="2009-01-30" who="CRB">Added publicationStmt element and associated
            content.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The authors open by imagining one possible use of digital geographic techniques in
               the context of humanities research in 2017. They then outline the background to this
               vision, from early engagements in web-based mapping for the Classics to recent,
               fast-paced developments in web-based, collaborative geography. The article concludes
               with a description of their own Pleiades Project (<ref
                  target="http://pleiades.stoa.org">http://pleiades.stoa.org</ref>), which gives
               scholars, students and enthusiasts worldwide the opportunity to use, create and share
               historical geographic information about the Greek and Roman World in digital
               form.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>The history of computing, classics and geography can be seen as a rich and profitable
               dialogue between many disciplines and practitioners now reinvigorated by a wave of
               technological and societal change that is breaking down artificial boundaries between
               scholars and a wider public whose skills, hobbies and interests coincide at the
               fascinating intersection of humanity, space and time.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Digital Geography and Classics</head>
         <div>
            <head>The View From 2017</head>
            <p>As I settle into my chair, a second cup of morning coffee in my hand, an expansive
               view of the eastern Mediterranean fades in to cover the blank wall in front of me.
               It's one of my favorite perspectives: from a viewpoint a thousand kilometers above
               the Red Sea, you can look north and west across an expanse that encompasses Jordan,
               Egypt and Libya in the foreground and Tunisia, Calabria and the Crimea along the
               distorting arc of the horizon. A simple voice command clears some of my default
               overlays: current precipitation and cloud cover, overnight news hotspots, and a
               handful of icons that represent colleagues whose profiles indicate they're currently
               at work. Now I see a new overlay of colored symbols associated with my current work:
               various research projects, two articles I'm peer-reviewing and various other bits of
               analysis, coding, writing and reading. These fade slowly to gray, but for two. Both
               of them are sprawling, irregular splatters and clumps of dots, lines and polygonal
               shapes.</p>
            <p>The view pivots and zooms to frame these two symbol groups. The pink batch indicates
               the footprint of one of the review pieces, a survey article comparing Greek, Roman
               and Arabic land and sea itineraries. The other group, in pale blue, corresponds to my
               own never-ending <q>Roman boundary disputes</q> project. In both cases, I've
               previously tailored the display to map findspots of all texts and documents cited or
               included, as well as all places named in notes or the cited modern texts and ancient
               sources. These two sets of symbols remain highlighted because potentially relevant
               information has recently appeared.</p>
            <p>I suspect the <q>hits</q> for the boundary disputes are just articles in the latest
               (nearly last) digitized Supplementband of the Pauly-Wissowa
                  <emph>Real-encyclopädie</emph> to be delivered to subscribing libraries...nothing
               new from the old print version. I'll double-check that later. The more interesting
               results are illustrated when I switch focus to the itineraries article I'm reviewing.
               A new collection of colored symbols appear on the landscape, their intensity
               automatically varied to indicate likely similarity to the selected article. One
               particular subset jumps out at me: a series of bright red dots paralleling the
               southern bank of the Danube. They are connected by line segments and join up with a
               network of other points and lines that fan out northward into the space once occupied
               by the Roman province of Dacia. A new and extensive Roman-era itinerary has been
               discovered in Romania and published.</p>
            <p>I can't resist making some quick explorations. It's easy enough to select the new
               publication and ask for an extract of the itinerary's geography, as well as the place
               names in their original orthographies. I follow up with a request for the results of
               two correlation queries against all of the itineraries cited in the review article:
               how similar are their geographies and how similar are their place names? My
               programmatic research assistant reports back quickly: there's a strong correlation
               between the sequential locations in a portion of the new document and an overlapping
               portion of our only surviving copy of a Roman world map, the so-called <q>Peutinger
                  Map</q>, but the forms of several place names differ in some particulars.<note>
                  The most recent published work on the Peutinger map at the time of publication was
                     <ptr target="#elliott2008"/>, which looks forward to Richard Talbert's
                  forthcoming digital edition of this unique primary source for the study of Roman
                  cartography. A number of digital offprints on related topics are available from
                  the Ancient World Mapping Center at <ref
                     target="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/talbertarticles.html"
                     >http://​www.unc.edu/​awmc/​talbertarticles.html</ref>.</note> Another
               intriguing result shows that the distances between nodal points in the new itinerary
               are statistically consistent with those recorded in the Claudian-era inscribed
               itinerary from Patara in Turkey, the so-called <emph>Miliarium
                  Lyciae</emph>.<note>The definitive publication of the so-called Miliarium Lyciae
                  is <ptr target="#sahin2007"/>.</note> I bundle up these results and the new
               article, and add them to the review project. I can attach a short note to the author
               about it later. </p>
            <p>But now it's time to teach. Another voice command stores the research stuff and
               clears the projected display, which reforms in two parts: another virtual globe
               draped with the day's lecture materials, and a largely empty grid destined to be
               slowly populated over the next half-hour by the various icons, avatars and video
               images of my students. I double-check that I'm set to do-not-disturb and lean back to
               review my lecture notes. Today, Caesar will cross the Rubicon. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The View, Explained (and what we have left out)</head>
            <p>We've taken an equally imagined, but less frenetic, view of the scholarly future a
               decade from now as that recently sketched for freelance business consultants by <ptr
                  target="#sterling2007"/>. Nonetheless, we share with Sterling a number of common
               assumptions about the ways in which location will alter our next-decade information
               experiences, both at work and in private life. We envision a 2017 in which the
               geo-computing revolution, now underway, has intersected with other computational and
               societal trends to effect major changes in the way humanist scholars work, publish
               and teach. The rapid developments occurring at the intersection of geographic
               computing and web-based information technology cannot be identified with any single
               label, nor are they effectively described by any single body of academic literature.
               A variety of terms are in use for one or another aspect of this domain, including
                  <q>web mapping</q>, <q>neogeography</q>, <q>social cartography</q>, <q>the
                  geoweb</q>, <q>webGIS</q> and <q>volunteered geographic information</q>. Those
               unfamiliar with this fast-moving field – one in which speculation and innovation are
               widespread – will gain some appreciation of its breadth and heterogeneity if they
               start their reading with <ptr target="#turner2006"/>, <ptr target="#goodchild2007"/>,
                  <ptr target="#boll2008"/> and <ptr target="#hudsonsmith2008"/>.<note>An
                  interesting range of ideas and views surfaced in the context of the meeting in
                  late 2007 that occasioned Goodchild's paper (see the position papers and
                  presentations collected at <ref target="http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/projects/vgi/"
                     >http://​www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/​projects/vgi/</ref>), but it is instructive to
                  note the discussion this meeting and paper generated beyond the academy: see the
                  list thread beginning with <ref
                     target="http://geowanking.org/pipermail/geowanking_geowanking.org/2008-january/016319.html"
                     >http://​geowanking.org/​pipermail/​geowanking_geowanking.org/​2008-January/​016319.html</ref>,
                  as well as <ptr target="#fee2008"/> (including comments). For clarity in this
                  article, we adopt the phrase VGI throughout to denote the full range of open,
                  community-oriented geographic collaborations.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For humanists, general research tasks will remain largely unchanged: the discovery,
               organization and analysis of primary and secondary materials with the goal of
               communicating and disseminating results and information for the use and education of
                  others.<note>It is not our intent to imply, by this formulation, that we reject
                  the notion that humanistic research will extend to address questions that cannot
                  be formulated or investigated outside a computational context; rather we seek to
                  emphasize certain underlying tasks that we believe will persist even if automated
                  and applied to novel research goals. It is a formulation shared to one degree or
                  other by (e.g.) <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/> and <ptr target="#mostern2008"/>.
                  With regard to these, and the rest of the assumptions outlined in this paragraph,
                  we cannot possibly predict the details of their manifestation, nor the order in
                  which they will appear. Collaboration and automation of data finding, information
                  management and scholarly communication/publication tasks are widely assumed (e.g.,
                     <ptr target="#boonstra2004" loc="91–99"/>; <ptr target="#genoni2005"/>; <ptr
                     target="#boast2007"/>; <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/>; <ptr target="#dunn2008"
                  />; <ptr target="#guthrie2008" loc="16017"/>; <ptr target="#pritchard2008"/>; <ptr
                     target="#spiro2008"/>). These assumptions spring from knowledge of work in a
                  variety of fields. Web search customization, based on profiling, social
                  bookmarking and other novel ranking schemes, has been an active area of research
                  for over a decade, building on a venerable lineage of research in information
                  retrieval and text mining. Hinrich Schütze's Information Retrieval Resources page
                  provides an excellent entry point to the literature (via standard texts), as well
                  as links to related professional societies, research centers, courses and
                  conferences: <ref
                     target="http://www-csli.stanford.edu/~hinrich/information-retrieval.html"
                     >http://​www-csli.stanford.edu/​~hinrich/​information-retrieval.html</ref>.
                  Emerging tools, frameworks and standard data formats for easy discovery, creation
                  and social management and annotation of bibliographic information (e.g., WorldCat
                     <ref target="http://www.wordcat.org">http://www.wordcat.org</ref>; Bibsonomy
                     <ref target="http://www.bibsonomy.org/">http://www.bibsonomy.org/</ref>;
                  LibraryThing <ref target="http://www.librarything.com/"
                     >http://www.librarything.com/</ref>; The Open Library <ref
                     target="http://openlibrary.org/">http://openlibrary.org/</ref>; and Zotero <ref
                     target="http://www.zotero.org/">http://www.zotero.org/</ref>) lend credence to
                  our expectation that the tedious, citation-management aspects of bibliographic
                  work will become increasingly automated. The intersection of such systems with
                  emerging digital archives and digital publications (both retrospective and
                  born-digital) will create opportunity for a wide range of potential research
                  support services for information discovery, document delivery and text mining. It
                  is beyond the scope of this article to venture any authoritative summary or
                  quantitative assessment of the progress and ultimate <q>success</q> of the vast
                  range of digitization and digital publication efforts – commercial, public and
                  consortial – now underway, but <ptr target="#wilson2007"/> and <ptr
                     target="#crawford2008"/> provide recent assessments and access to related
                  announcements and publications.</note> But we expect to see a more broadly
               collaborative regime in which a far greater percentage of work time is spent in
               analysis and professional communication, all underpinned by a pervasive, always-on
               network. Much of the tedious and solitary work of text mining, bibliographic research
               and information management will be handled by computational agents, but we will
               become more responsible for the quality and effectiveness of that work by virtue of
               how we publish our research results. Ubiquitous, less-obtrusive software will respond
               to our specific queries, and to the interests implied in our past searches, stored
               documents, cited literature and recently used datasets. The information offered us in
               return will be drawn from a global pastiche of digital repositories and publication
               mechanisms, surfacing virtually all new academic publication, as well as digital
               proxies for much of the printed, graphic and audio works now for sale, in circulation
               or on exhibit in one or more first-world, brick-and-mortar bookstores, libraries or
               museums. </p>
            <p>It would be impossible in an article-length treatment to produce a comprehensive
               history of geography and the classics, digital or otherwise. The non-digital,
               cartographic achievements of the field to 1990 were surveyed in detail by <ptr
                  target="#talbert1992"/>. Many of the projects discussed then have continued,
               diversified or gone digital, but there has not been to our knowledge a more recent
               survey. Developments on the complementary methodological axis of <q>Historical
                  GIS</q> have been addressed recently in <ptr target="#gregory2002"/>, <ptr
                  target="#knowles2002"/> and <ptr target="#knowles2008"/>.<note>A major conference
                  on the topic, Historical GIS 2008, has just concluded (August 2008). It is hoped
                  that proceedings from the meeting will be forthcoming (see <ref
                     target="http://www.hgis.org.uk/hgis_conference/index.htm"
                     >http://​www.hgis.org.uk/​HGIS_conference/​index.htm</ref>).</note> No
               conference series, journal or research center has yet been able to establish the
               necessary international reporting linkages to provide a regular review of classical
               geographical research (digital or otherwise), an increasingly urgent need in a
               rapidly growing subfield.</p>
            <p>Readers will detect this gap (and the compounding effects of limited space and time)
               in three regrettable categories of omission. Firstly, we have been unable to address
               many important comparanda for other periods, cultures and disciplines, for example
               the China Historical GIS (<ref target="http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~chgis/"
                  >http://​www.fas.harvard.edu/~chgis/</ref>), the AfricaMap Project (<ref
                  target="http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k28501"
                  >http://​isites.harvard.edu/​icb/​icb.do?keyword=k28501</ref>), both spearheaded
               by Harvard's Center for Geographic Analysis. Secondly, our examples here are heavily
               weighted toward the English-speaking world; we have not been able to address such
               seminal efforts as the <foreign xml:lang="turkish">Türkiye Arkeolojik
                  Yerleşmeleri</foreign> (TAY) Projesi (Archaeological Settlements of Turkey
               Project: <ref target="http://tayproject.org/">http://tayproject.org/</ref>). Finally,
               we cannot possibly grapple in this article with the burgeoning practice of GIS and
               remote sensing for large-scale site archaeology and regional survey, though we can
               point to examples of projects seeking to facilitate aggregation, preservation and
               discovery of related data, including FastiOnline (<ref
                  target="http://www.fastionline.org/">http://www.fastionline.org/</ref>), the
               Mediterranean Archaeological GIS (<ref target="http://cgma.depauw.edu/magis/"
                  >http://cgma.depauw.edu/MAGIS/</ref>) and OpenContext (<ref
                  target="http://opencontext.org/">http://opencontext.org/</ref>).</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the initial impact on historical work of the publication in 2000
               of the <title rend="italic">Barrington Atlas of the Greek and Roman World</title> (R.
               Talbert, ed., Princeton) has been assessed by a number of reviews in major journals,
               and significant works have since appeared that take it as the reference basis for
               classical geographic features (e.g., <ptr target="#hansen2004"/>). Planning for a
               digital, user-friendly version of the Atlas continues as an area of active discussion
               between the Ancient World Mapping Center at the University of North Carolina in
               Chapel Hill (<ref target="http://www.unc.edu/awmc">http://www.unc.edu/awmc</ref>) and
               other parties. Meanwhile, the analog and digital materials that underpinned
               publication of the Atlas are the present focus of the authors' Pleiades project (see
               further, below). </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Primacy of Location: A Recent Example Drawn from Google</head>
            <p>The ability to identify and locate relevant items of interest is of prime importance
               to users of scholarly information systems, and geography is a core axis of interest.
               As Buckland and Lancaster put it in their 2004 D-Lib Magazine article: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#buckland2004">The most fundamental advantage of the
                     emerging networked knowledge environment is that it provides a much-improved
                     technological basis for sharing resources of all sorts from all sources. This
                     situation increases the importance of effective access to information. Place,
                     along with time, topic, and creator, is one of the fundamental components in
                     how we define things and search for them.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#buckland2004"/>
               </cit> Indeed, to realize the vision we have outlined above, spatial information must
               become as easily searched — within, between and outside individual digital libraries
               — as HTML web pages are today. The Googlebot began crawling and indexing web-posted
               documents encoded in the Keyhole Markup Language (KML; <ref
                  target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/keyhole_markup_language"
                  >http://​en.wikipedia.org/​wiki/​Keyhole_Markup_Language</ref>), as well as web
               feeds containing GeoRSS markup (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/georss"
                  >http://​en.wikipedia.org/​wiki/​Georss</ref>) in late 2006 <ptr
                  target="#ohazama2007"/>; <ptr target="#schutzberg2007"/>. Microsoft added similar
               support to its Local Search and Virtual Earth services in October 2007 (GeoWeb
               Exploration 2007). It is already safe to say that this is now a routine function for
               viable web search services. Henceforth, KML and GeoRSS resources on the Web will be
               found and indexed if they are surfaced via stable, discoverable URLs.</p>
            <p>Obviously, much of the information that the web search providers seek to index is not
               in one of these geospatial formats. To determine the geographic relevance of
               web-facing content in HTML, MSWord and PDF files and the like, a process called
               geoparsing must be employed cf. <ptr target="#hill2006" loc="220"/>. Geoparsing
               entails first a series of steps, often called collectively <q>named entity
                  recognition</q>, in which proper nouns in unstructured or semi-structured texts
               are disambiguated from other words and then associated with known or notional
               entities of interest (e.g., places, persons, concepts). The potential of course
               exists for false identifications, ambiguous matches (i.e., one name for many discrete
               entities) and complete failures (e.g., due to the obscurity of a name or a referenced
               entity). Assuming some level of success in disambiguation and identification of
               geographic entities in a text, the next step is to associate coordinates with each
               named entity. Unless the textual source is itself a geographic gazetteer containing
               map coordinates that can be parsed accurately, the coordinates must be supplied from
               an external reference dataset that ideally holds the exact name variants occurring in
               the text as well as the geospatial coordinates; we must recognize that it will often
               be the case, especially with regard to primary sources and academic literature on
               historical topics, that such a reference dataset does not exist. Nonetheless, once
               coordinates are assigned to as many entities as possible, and the results are stored
               in an index with a link to the original document, mapping, geosearch and other
               geographic computations can be performed.<note>The Perseus Digital Library team at
                  Tufts University was an early leader in this field (see references at note 13),
                  and continues to push forward research on named entity work (<ptr
                     target="#crane2006"/>, <ptr target="#crane2006a"/>). The recently released,
                  open-licensed Perseus text files include the name tagging inserted by their system
                     (<ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/opensource"
                     >http://​www.perseus.tufts.edu/​hopper/​opensource</ref>); cf. <ptr
                     target="#crane2006b"/>. Outside the Perseus milieu, geoparsing has become
                  increasingly important in both academic and commercial contexts. Some recent
                  academic papers on name entity recognition, with additional bibliography, include
                     <ptr target="#kozareva2006"/>, <ptr target="#nadeau2006"/>, <ptr
                     target="#babeu2007"/>, <ptr target="#lucarelli2007"/> and <ptr
                     target="#shaalan2008"/>. In 2006, the commercial firm Metacarta (<ref
                     target="http://www.metacarta.com/">http://www.metacarta.com/</ref>) unveiled
                  Gutenkarte (<ref target="http://gutenkarte.org/">http://gutenkarte.org/</ref>) as
                  a demonstration of its geoparsing techniques using public domain texts from
                  Project Gutenberg. <ptr target="#bell2008"/> provides a recent, concise
                  description of geoparsing techniques from the point of view of Yahoo!'s Geo
                  Technologies division. Google also is a major player in this space: we treat some
                  of their services and approaches in detail below.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Despite clear challenges and the real possibility of incomplete results for many
               texts (we shall consider an example below), we believe that geoparsing-based services
               will mature and diversify rapidly. By 2017, we expect that all web-facing textual
               resources will be parsed (rightly or wrongly) for geographic content. Audio and video
               works, where these can be machine-transcribed, will receive similar treatment,
               whether they are accompanied by extensive metadata or not. Some texts, especially
               those produced by academics and specialist communities will have coordinates encoded
               into the digital texts in a way that facilitates automatic extraction, making their
               geographic indexing relatively simple (e.g., KML, GeoRSS or the like). The majority
               of texts, however, will still have only geographic names and geographic description,
               most with neither special tagging nor authority control. The search engines will
               automatically identify these components and add associated entries to their
               geographic indexes by matching them with coordinate data in reference datasets. We
               believe that these datasets will include information drawn from KML and
               GeoRSS-enabled documents on the web, as well as previously geo-parsed texts
               (especially those whose genre, topic and regional nature are easily identified using
               automated techniques). Topic- and genre-aware geoparsing may well prove essential to
               accurate disambiguation of non-unique place names.</p>
            <p>The first fruits of geographic search are already apparent in information sets being
               surfaced to the web. Consider, for example, Google Books. A copy of J.S. Watson's
               1854 translation of Xenophon's <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title> was digitized at
               Harvard in June 2006. Bundled into the original print work by the publisher was
                  <name>W.F. Ainsworth</name>'s geographical commentary (pp. 263-338). Google's
                  <q>About this book</q> page demonstrates the range of connections the search
               company's software is so far able to make between the book and other
                  resources.<note>Google Books' <title rend="quotes">About this Book</title> page
                  for Xenophon, <title rend="italic">The Anabasis, or Expedition of Cyrus, and the
                     Memorabilia of Socrates</title>, <name>J.S. Watson</name> (trans.), London:
                  1854 (copy scanned from Harvard University Library on 21 June 2006): <ref
                     target="http://books.google.com/books?id=wqckoon76amc&amp;dq=editions:0gclhkhlks0men2kdt76mh/"
                     >http://​books.google.com/​books?id=wqcKoOn76aMC&amp;dq=editions:0GclhKHLkS0MeN2kDT76mh/</ref>;
                  accessed 30 September 2007.</note> Basic bibliographic metadata is surfaced, along
               with direct links to a downloadable PDF file and the Google book reader application
               (and thence to the optically-recognized text itself). A variety of links to other
               services are also provided (e.g., Amazon and OCLC WorldCat). Of chief interest in the
               present discussion are the geographic components introduced under the heading
                  <q>Places mentioned in this book.</q> These consist at present of a map and an
               index of select places, as illustrated in <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref>.
                  <figure xml:id="figure1">
                  <graphic url="resources/images/ShelbyPlacesFull.png"/>
                  <figDesc>A screen shot of a Google map showing places mentioned.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>It would appear that most of the <q>places</q> currently highlighted in the Google
               Books presentation (evidently a maximum of 10) have been parsed from Ainsworth's
               commentary or the unattributed <q>Geographical Index</q>, which we assume to be
               Watson's (pp. 339 - 348). As is the case with many Google search results, we are
               given no information about how the indexing or correlation with geographic
               coordinates (i.e., the geo-parsing) was accomplished. Some of the results are mapped
               correctly, but others have clearly gone awry. Consider, for example, the placement of
               Olympia, Syracuse and Tempe (see <ref target="#figure2">Figure 2</ref>). <figure
                  xml:id="figure2">
                  <graphic url="resources/images/ShelbyNorthAmerica.png"/>
                  <figDesc>A screen shot of a Google map showing a pop-up annotation.</figDesc>
               </figure> The placement of these ancient features in North America illustrates one of
               the most obvious failure modes of geo-parsing algorithms. If the algorithm succeeds
               in finding a match at all, it may find more than one match or a single, but incorrect
               match. Given the information publicly available, we cannot know for certain which of
               these two circumstances produced the results in question here. It seems probable,
               however, that at least the Olympia and Syracuse errors result from selecting the
               wrong result of several, as both of these well-known sites appear in many of the
               standard gazetteers and geographic handbooks.</p>
            <p>There are published methods for resolving such ambiguities on the basis of proximity
               to other locations more reliably geo-parsed from the work, but these presuppose
               knowledge of a coherent geographic footprint for the work under consideration as well
               as a relatively comprehensive and highly relevant reference dataset that can provide
               at least a single match for most geographic names (<ptr target="#smith2001"/> and
                  <ptr target="#smith2002a"/>). Google has not revealed, to our knowledge, whether
               such self-calibrating algorithms are at work, but we can be certain that they do not
               have access to a comprehensive, highly relevant reference dataset for the ancient
               Greek world. Many datasets — including the <title rend="italic">Getty Thesaurus of
                  Geographic Names</title>, the <title rend="italic">Alexandria Digital Library
                  Gazetteer</title> and the open-content <title rend="italic">GeoNames
                  database</title>
               <note>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names: <ref
                     target="http://www.getty.edu/research/conducting_research/vocabularies/tgn/"
                     >http://​www.getty.edu/​research/​conducting_research/​vocabularies/tgn/</ref>;
                  Alexandria Digital Library Gazetteer: <ref
                     target="http://middleware.alexandria.ucsb.edu/client/gaz/adl/index.jsp/"
                     >http://​middleware.alexandria.ucsb.edu/​client/​gaz/​adl/​index.jsp/</ref>;
                  Geonames: <ref target="http://www.geonames.org/">http://www.geonames.org/</ref>
               </note> — contain significant numbers of historical Greek and Roman names; however,
               the authors' experience confirms that many ancient sites and regions are unaccounted
               for or incorrectly identified in these gazetteers, and many name variants and
               original-script orthographies are omitted. A complete and reliable dataset simply
               does not yet exist in a useful form.</p>
            <p>It seems reasonable to assume that Google and its competitors will continue to seek
               or construct more comprehensive reference datasets to support geo-parsing
               improvements. Indeed, Google's embrace of VGI can be seen as a deliberate strategy
               for this purpose. The Google Earth Community Bulletin Board (<ref
                  target="http://bbs.keyhole.com">http://bbs.keyhole.com</ref>) provides a venue for
               the sharing of thematic sets of labeled geographic coordinates. The expansion of the
               Googlebot's competencies to include KML and GeoRSS expand the harvest potential to
               the entire web. This circumstance highlights a class of research and publication work
               of critical importance for humanists and geographers over the next decade: the
               creation of open, structured, web-facing geo-historical reference works that can be
               used for a variety of purposes, including the training of geo-parsing tools and the
               population of geographic indexes (see <ptr target="#elliott2006"/>).</p>
            <p>The automated features outlined above were added to Google Books in January 2007. The
               stated motivation was cast in terms of helping users <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#petrou2007">plan your next trip, research an area
                     for academic purposes or visualize the haunts of your favorite fictional
                     characters</quote>
                  <ptr target="#petrou2007"/>
               </cit>. In August 2007, Google made a further announcement of new features, which
               refined that motivation to echo the company's vision statement <ptr
                  target="#badger2007"/>, emphasis ours; compare the Google Company Overview, first
               sentence: <quote rend="block" source="#http://www.google.com/corporate/">Earlier this year, we announced
                  a first step toward <emph>geomapping the world's literary information</emph> by
                  starting to integrate information from Google Book Search into Google Maps. Today,
                  [we] announce the next step: a new layer in Google Earth that allows you to
                  explore locations through the lens of the world's books...a dynamic and
                  interesting way to explore the world's literature...a whole new way to visualize
                  the written history of your hometown as well as your favorite books.</quote>
               <note>As it appeared in September 2007 at <ref
                     target="http://www.google.com/corporate/"
                     >http://​www.google.com/corporate/</ref>.</note> If the <q>Places in this
                  book</q> component of Google Books is intended to help users explore the geography
               of the book, the Google Books layer in Google Earth offers users the opportunity to
               discover books by way of the geography. If, by chance, we should find ourselves
               browsing northeastern Turkey in Google Earth, the Google Books layer offers us a book
               icon in the vicinity of the town of İspir. This icon represents Watson's 1854
               translation of the Anabasis. Links on the popup description kite will take us back to
               specific pages of the scanned Harvard copy we discussed above. Another link provides
               us with a way to <q>Search for all books referencing Ispir.</q> On 30 September 2007,
               we were offered information about 706 books. By refining the search to include the
               keyword <q>ancient,</q> we narrowed the result set to 167 books. We judged these
               results to be highly relevant to our interests. We then selected a further suggested
               refinement from a list of links at the bottom of the page: <q>Geography, Ancient.</q>
               The resulting 7 matches are unsurprisingly spotty and largely out-of-date, given the
               current state of Google's book digitization project, copyright restrictions and the
               degree of publisher text-sharing partnerships. Taking this into account, we again
               judged the results highly relevant. The results included <ptr target="#kiepert1878"
               />, <ptr target="#kiepert1881"/> and <ptr target="#kiepert1902"/>, <ptr
                  target="#bunbury1883"/>, <ptr target="#fabricius1888"/> and <ptr
                  target="#syme1995"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Prelude to Geographic Search: Web-based Mapping</head>
            <p>We should not be surprised that web-wide geo-search is with us already in embryo. It
               follows naturally, as a user requirement, once you have assembled a large index of
               web content and developed the ability to parse that content and discriminate elements
               of geographic significance.</p>
            <p>Quick and accurate geographic visualization had long been one of the holy grails of
               the web. The now-defunct Xerox PARC Map Viewer <ptr target="#putz1994"/> demonstrated
               to early users the potential of dynamic, web-based mapping, even if it was a
               stand-alone application. A variety of services have come and gone since, some
               concentrating on screen display, others attempting to provide dynamic maps suitable
               for print. Some sites have provided scans of paper maps (like the David Rumsey
               Historical Map Collection: <ref target="http://www.davidrumsey.com/"
                  >http://www.davidrumsey.com/</ref>); others have served out digital remotely
               sensed imagery or readily printed static maps in PDF and other formats (the AWMC Maps
               for Students collection, for example: <ref
                  target="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/mapsforstudents.html"
                  >http://​www.unc.edu/​awmc/​mapsforstudents.html</ref>). Flash and Shockwave have
               also been popular ways of providing animation and interactivity on the web (for
               example, some maps in <ptr target="#mohr2006"/>). Until recently, however, the
               dominant paradigms for dynamic on-line maps comprised iterative, server-side map
               image generation, sometimes mediated by a client-side Java applet, in response to
               discrete mouse clicks. To one degree or another most such map tools emulate the look
               and feel of desktop GIS programs, perpetuating the thematic layering inherited from
               analog film-based cartographic composition. This paradigm continues in active use
               (consider the map interface for <ptr target="#foss2007"/>, for example).</p>
            <p>Recent innovations in on-line cartographic visualization are revolutionary. We have
               only just grown accustomed to digital globes (like NASA WorldWind and Google Earth)
               and continuous-panning, <q>slippy</q> browser-side maps. Google, Yahoo, Microsoft
               Live Search and MapQuest have all gone this route, and there is now an excellent,
               open-source toolkit for building this sort of client-side maps: OpenLayers (<ref
                  target="http://openlayers.org">http://openlayers.org</ref>). Many of these
               applications are doing more than giving us compelling new visual environments. Many
               of them are also breaking down traditional divisions between browse and search,
               thematic layers, web content, spatial processing and geographic datasets, not least
               through the mechanisms known generically as <q>mashups</q> (web applications that
               dynamically combine data and services from multiple, other web applications to
               provide a customized service or data product). These tools remain an area of intense,
               active development, so we should expect more pleasant surprises. Moreover, as the
               costs of projectors, large-format LCD displays and graphics cards fall, and as
               digital television standards encourage the replacement of older televisions, display
               sizes and resolutions will at last improve. Efficient techniques for the simple
               mosaicing of multiple display units and for the ad-hoc interfacing of mobile devices
               and on-demand displays provided by third parties expand the horizon still further. It
               will not be long before a broader canvas opens for cartographic display.<note>The
                  U.S. Congress has legislated 17 February 2009 as the date by which all licensed,
                  full-power television stations in the United States stop broadcasting in analog
                  format and broadcast only in digital format (<ref
                     target="http://www.fcc.gov/cgb/consumerfacts/digitaltv.html"
                     >http://​www.fcc.gov/​cgb/​consumerfacts/​digitaltv.html</ref>). Recent
                  technological advances treating large displays, multi-projector displays and
                  on-demand displays for mobile devices are treated in <ptr target="#czerwinski2006"
                  />, <ptr target="#bhasker2007"/> and <ptr target="#stodle2007"/>. Our assumption
                  about the increasing ubiquity of pixels is shared by Tim Berners-Lee, who last
                  year expanded on his vision of <q>pixels everywhere</q> in the context of mobile
                  computing (see <ptr target="#berlind2007"/>).</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is not space in this article to treat other forms of geographic visualization,
               especially 3D modeling, in detail. It must suffice for us to say that this too is an
               area of vigorous change. From the earliest QuickTime VR panoramas (classicists will
               remember <name>Bruce Hartzler</name>'s <title rend="italic">Metis</title>, still
               hosted today by the Stoa: <ref target="http://www.stoa.org/metis/"
                  >http://www.stoa.org/metis/</ref>) to such contemporary services as Google
               StreetView (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/google_street_view"
                  >http://​en.wikipedia.org/​wiki/​Google_Street_View</ref>), 3D modeling and its
               integration with geographic and cartographic visualization tools proceeds apace.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Web-mapping the Geographic Content of Texts: Example of the Perseus Atlas</head>
            <p>Geo-mapping of texts has been with the field of classics since the late 1990s, a
               development that paralleled interdisciplinary innovations in digital library research
               and development. Although its technology has now been eclipsed by rapid and recent
               developments in web-based cartographic visualization, the Perseus Atlas stands as a
               pivotal early exemplar of the power of this approach.<note>To our knowledge, there is
                  no comprehensive published account of the development and workings of the Atlas;
                  what follows therefore derives from papers published by the Perseus team on
                  aspects of their named entity recognition and temporal-spatial metadata work, as
                  well as the authors' recalled experience, short announcements and help documents
                  on the Perseus website and a telephone interview with Rob Chavez (17 July
                  2007).</note>
            </p>
            <p>The first version of the Perseus Atlas was rolled out in June 1998, shortly after Rob
               Chavez joined the Perseus team with the atlas as his primary task.<note>Announcing
                  the New Perseus Web Atlas (12 June 1998): <ref
                     target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/atlas.ann.html"
                     >http://​www.perseus.tufts.edu/​atlas.ann.html</ref>.</note> Its coverage was
               limited to the <q>Greek world,</q> and it was designed solely to provide geographic
               context (illustrative maps) for discrete content items in the Perseus collection,
               e.g., individual texts (or portions of texts) or object records. Perseus was already
               in control of a significant amount of geographical information drawn from its texts
               through geo-parsing.<note>See <ptr target="#rydbergcox2000"/>; <ref
                     target="#crane2001">Crane 2001, pp. 6,8 and figures 3-5, 8-11</ref>; <ptr
                     target="#smith2001"/>; <ptr target="#smith2002a"/>; <ptr target="#smith2002b"
                  />.</note> This was further augmented from metadata associated with its coin and
               pottery databases. In the main, this dataset consisted of place names. A rudimentary
               digital gazetteer had been developed through computational matching of this names
               list with gazetteer records in various publicly-available US Government geographical
               datasets (especially the resource now known as the GEONet Names Server of the
               National Geospatial Intelligence Agency), which provided coordinates. After some
               initial experimentation, the Perseus team selected an early version of MapServer to
               provide dynamic mapping, and by way of Perl and CGI, this was integrated with the
               existing Perseus tooling. Geographic data was stored in a plain PostgreSQL database,
               the PostGIS spatial data extension for PostgreSQL having not yet been developed.
               Vector linework and polygons from the Digital Chart of the World were added to
               provide geographic context.</p>
            <p>The Perseus Atlas saw two upgrades subsequent to its 1998 debut.<note>Perseus Web
                  Atlas Update (28 September 2000): <ref
                     target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/pr/atlas2000.ann.html"
                     >http://​www.perseus.tufts.edu/​PR/​atlas2000.ann.html</ref>; An Upgrade to the
                  Perseus Interactive Web Atlas (26 March 2002): <ref
                     target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/pr/atlas.ann.html"
                     >http://​www.perseus.tufts.edu/​PR/​atlas.ann.html</ref>.</note> The 2000
               upgrade rolled out a rewritten and expanded Atlas that boasted several new features:
               global geographic coverage, a relief base layer, and tighter integration between the
               Atlas and the Perseus Lookup Tool. This last feature — a collaboration between Chavez
               and David Smith — transformed the Atlas from a cartographic illustration mechanism to
               an alternative interface for the entire collection, capable of both object-specific
               and cross-object cartographic visualization and query. A fork of the Atlas, designed
               to support the Historic London Collection, also appeared during this period.<note>New
                  Collections, New Navigation (17 November 2000): <ref
                     target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/pr/frontpage.ann.html"
                     >http://​www.perseus.tufts.edu/​PR/​frontpage.ann.html</ref>. This development,
                  of course, depended heavily on Smith's named entity recognition work (see
                  references in note 13).</note> It offered essentially the same features, but
               employed a separate geographic datum, higher-resolution imagery and rudimentary
               temporal filtering capabilities by way of user-selectable, dated map layers. The 2002
               upgrade improved the place name lookup and navigation tools in both Atlas branches,
               added an option for saving map views and augmented the London Atlas with links to
               QuickTime VR panoramas for select streets.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Geo-Library, the Web and Geographic Search</head>
            <p>It is clear from even a cursory review of contemporaneous developments that the
               Perseus team was in the vanguard of an important revolution in web-based cartographic
               visualization. When Perseus first fielded its atlas in 1998, The Alexandria Digital
               Library (ADL) Project team had been working for four years to realize Larry Carver's
               1983 vision of geographic search in a digital maps catalog <ptr target="#hill2006"
                  loc="49"/>. At about the same time the Perseus team was conceptualizing its atlas
               as an interface to their entire, heterogeneous collection, the ADL vision was
               expanding to encompass geographic browsing and search in an entire digital library
               containing materials of all kinds, not just maps <ptr target="#goodchild2004"/>. A
               year after the Perseus Atlas appeared, the ADL vision of the <q>geo-library</q> was
               endorsed by the National Research Council Mapping Science Committee (National
               Research Council Mapping Science Committee 1999; see further <ptr target="#hill2006"
                  loc="11–17"/>). The 2000 upgrade to the Perseus Atlas represented the first
               realization of this vision for the humanities outside ADL, and one of the first
               anywhere.</p>
            <p> It is clear that, despite significant challenges, geo-library functionality like
               that pioneered by ADL and Perseus is rapidly maturing into one of the standard modes
               for browsing and searching all manner of digital information on the web.<note>
                  <ptr target="#asadi2007"/> assesses some aspects of the state-of-the-art and
                  provides recent bibliography on techniques and problems.</note> Simple spatial
               queries (within bounding boxes, by proximity to points, and by proximity to other
               features) are becoming commonplace.<note>Google Earth provides this functionality in
                  its <q>Find Businesses</q> widget: you enter (e.g.) <q>Pizza</q> in the
                     <q>What</q> text box; the <q>Where</q> text box is prepopulated with the
                  default value <q>Current View</q> (effectively a bounding box). MapQuest provides
                  geographic proximity search through its <q>Search Nearby</q> feature (<ref
                     target="http://help.mapquest.com/jive/entry.jspa?externalid=349&amp;categoryid=6"
                     >http://​help.mapquest.com/​jive/​entry.jspa?externalID=349&amp;categoryID=6</ref>).
                  Yahoo! Local provides similar capability (<ref target="http://local.yahoo.com/"
                     >http://local.yahoo.com/</ref>). Other examples and experiments abound; their
                  enumeration here would overly belabor the point.</note> We expect that such
                  <q>geo-aware</q> searches will occur more frequently outside special map-oriented
               interfaces and services, with the target coordinates being provided automatically and
               transparently by search software and other computational proxies.</p>
            <p>These developments are being fueled by now-familiar business models.<note>Our own
                  casual review of U.S. patents and patent applications, via online patent search
                  services, reinforced our long-standing perception of widespread commercial
                  interest in <q>location-based</q> services and information retrieval; although not
                  rigorously screened, we believe the number of patents and applications in this
                  field over the past decade may easily number in the thousands. A web search for a
                  phrase like <q>location-based</q> or <q>location-aware search</q> will retrieve a
                  significant number of relevant blog postings, articles and business
                  websites.</note> The proximity of a retail outlet or entertainment venue to a
               customer (or the customer's preferred transportation method) is of interest to both
               the consumer and the vendor. Likewise, the location of a potential customer — or the
               locations of places she frequents, or that hold some sentimental or work-related
               interest for her — all have monetizable value. Location-aware ads and free-to-user
               planning, shopping and information-finding tools will be paid for by the businesses
               that stand to gain from the trade that results. Competition between search providers
               will open up more free search tools, some visible to users only by virtue of their
               results; however, it seems likely that industrial-strength GIS access to the
               underlying spatial indexes and georeferenced user profiles will remain a paid
               subscription service.</p>
            <p>Spatial search will help manage more seamlessly the inevitable heterogeneity of the
               2017 web. Formats, delivery mechanisms, cost models and access challenges will surely
               continue to proliferate. We assume that some resources will be little advanced from
               the average 2007 vintage web page or blog post, whereas other works will exhibit the
               full range of meaningful structures and linkages now being worked out under the
               rubrics <q>semantic web</q> and <q>linked data</q>.<note>It would be naïve for us to
                  assert that, in 10 years, the Semantic Web as presently imagined (see <ptr
                     target="#shadbolt2006"/>; <ptr target="#miller2007"/>) will constitute the web
                  itself. Rather, we expect to see a range of practices develop from the creative
                  intersection of current patterns with proposed Semantic Web approaches and with
                  other proposals and innovations. Our own recent experiments with linked data (see
                     <ref target="http://linkeddata.org/">http://linkeddata.org/</ref>) have
                  encouraged us to imagine that an increasing number of resources – especially those
                  useful for academic research and reference – will be exposed to the web in ways
                  that provide stable, discrete URIs and multiple standard formats for each
                  potentially cited or remixed element of interest. Such a development, combined
                  with methods for the virtual aggregation and linking of resources in a manner
                  compatible with basic web architecture and indexing (e.g., OAI/ORE in Atom: <ref
                     target="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/0.9/atom-implementation.html"
                     >http://​www.openarchives.org/​ore/​0.9/​atom-implementation.html</ref>), would
                  be of great service to humanities scholars (see further <ptr target="#cohen2008"
                  />, <ptr target="#elliott2008a"/>).</note> Some works will be posted to basic
               websites. Copies of other works will reside in institutional repositories, federated
               archive networks, publishers' portal sites or massive grid environments. Whether
               stand-alone or integrated in a collection, some resources will have appeared (or will
               be augmented subsequently) with a range of metadata and rich, relevant links to other
               resources and repositories. Others will constitute little more than plain text. </p>
            <p>We expect current distinctions between geographic content and other digital works
               will continue to erode over the next decade. As the geographic content in most
               documents and datasets is identified, surfaced and exploited, <q>born geographic</q>
               works will be fashioned in increasingly flexible and interoperable ways. To some
               extent, specific industries and institutional consortia will surely continue to use
               specialized protocols, service-oriented architectures and specialist formats to
               provide lossless interchange and rich contextualization of critical data. Smaller
               players, and big players wishing to share data with them, will increasingly use
               RESTful models, simple URLs and widely understood open formats for basic information
               publishing and exchange, even when these methods are lossy.<note>REpresentational
                  State Transfer (REST) is an approach to the development of web services that seeks
                  to exploit essential modes of web interaction to provide simpler, stabler and more
                  open systems than traditional service-oriented architectures (see <ptr
                     target="#tilkov2007"/> for a good introduction). It shares some principles with
                  the linked data movement now championed by Tim Berners-Lee and others (see note 16
                  for references). The uneven uptake of REST in the geo-computing community was
                  highlighted by links and comments in <ptr target="#gillies2008"/>; note also this
                  recent press release from ESRI, a leading developer of commercial GIS software:
                     <ref
                     target="http://www.esri.com/news/arcnews/spring08articles/attendees-get.html"
                     >http://​www.esri.com/​news/​arcnews/​spring08articles/​attendees-get.html</ref>.
               </note> In some cases, these documents will serve as proxies for the unadulterated
               content, encoded in whatever format is necessary to express its creators' intent,
               even if it is totally idiosyncratic. The value of universal, geo-aware search and
               manipulation will trump concerns about surfacing <q>incomplete</q> data. Even now, a
               KML file with appropriate descriptive content and hyperlinks can function as a table
               of contents, geographic index or abstract for a document collection coded in TEI or a
               custom web application running in Plone. We expect that extensible web feeds (like
               the recently codified Atom Syndication Format, RFC 4287: <ref
                  target="http://www.atompub.org/rfc4287.html"
                  >http://​www.atompub.org/​rfc4287.html</ref>) will form a simple, web-wide
               infrastructure for notification and metadata exchange, alongside the more complex and
               difficult-to-implement special protocols that are already linking federated digital
               repositories and grid systems.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Big Science, Repositories, Neo-geography and Volunteered Geographic
               Information</head>
            <p>Many commercial innovations for online search, retrieval and visualization will be of
               benefit to humanist scholars and their students. Such benefits will depend, to a
               significant degree, on the willingness and ability of humanists, their employers and
               their publishers to adapt their practices to fit the new regime.</p>
            <p>To date, humanists have taken one of two approaches in preparing and disseminating
               geo-historical information on the web. Large projects with significant funding have
               tended to follow the lead of the larger geo-science and commercial GIS communities in
               placing emphasis on the elaboration of extensive metadata describing their datasets,
               thereby creating a basis for their discovery and inclusion in digital repositories.
               In some countries (notably the U.K.) emphasis by national funding bodies has
               encouraged such behavior. At the other end of the spectrum, hand-crafted datasets and
               web pages are posted to the web with minimal metadata or distributed informally
               within particular research communities. The neo-geographical revolution, and in
               particular the explosive interest in Google Earth, has recently provided a much
               richer and easier mechanism for the dissemination of some types of work in this
               latter class (e.g., <ptr target="#scaife2006"/>).</p>
            <p>In the United States, e-science approaches have long been dominated by ideas
               expressed in an executive order issued by President Clinton in 1994 and amended by
               President Bush in 2003 <ptr target="#executive_order_12906"/> and <ptr
                  target="#executive_order_13286"/>. These orders chartered a National Spatial Data
               Infrastructure, encompassing a federally directed set of initiatives aimed at the
               creation of a distributed National Geospatial Data Clearinghouse (<ref
                  target="http://clearinghouse1.fgdc.gov/">http://​clearinghouse1.fgdc.gov/</ref>);
               standards for documentation, collection and exchange; and policies and procedures for
               data dissemination, especially by government agencies. More recently, the Library of
               Congress constructed, through the National Digital Information Infrastructure and
               Preservation Program, a National Geospatial Digital Archive (<ref
                  target="http://www.ngda.org/">http://www.ngda.org/</ref>), but this entity so far
               has been of little use to classicists, as it has focused collection development on
                  <quote rend="inline" source="http://www.ngda.org/research.php#cd">content
                  relating to the east and west coasts of the United States</quote> (<ref
                  target="http://www.ngda.org/research.php#cd"
                  >http://www.ngda.org/research.php#CD</ref>).<note>In private correspondence with
                  Elliott, NGDA principals have expressed interest in eventual accession of Pleiades
                  data, but to date no concrete requirements or processes have been
                  articulated.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <q>national repository</q> approach has similarly found a coherent advocate for
               academic geospatial data in the UK by way of EDINA, the national academic data center
               at the University of Edinburgh (<ref target="http://edina.ac.uk/"
                  >http://edina.ac.uk/</ref>); however, the recent governmental decision to de-fund
               the UK Arts and Humanities Data Service has introduced a significant level of
               uncertainty and chaos into sustainability planning for digital humanities projects
               there (details at <ref target="http://ahds.ac.uk/">http://ahds.ac.uk/</ref>). More
               broadly, the Global Spatial Data Infrastructure Association seeks to bring together
               representatives of government, industry and academia to encourage and promote work in
               this area (<ref target="http://gsdi.org">http://gsdi.org</ref>), but to date it seems
               to have focused exclusively on spatial data as it relates to governance, commerce and
               humanitarian activities.</p>
            <p>The top-down, national repository model (and its cousin, the institutional
               repository) contrasts sharply with the neo-geographical methods now rapidly
               proliferating on the web. To a certain degree, the differences reflect alternative
               modes of production. The repository model was born in a period when spatial datasets
               were created and used almost exclusively by teams of experts wielding specialized
               software. Concerns about efficiency, duplication of effort and preservation were key
               in provoking state interest, and consequently these issues informed repository
               specifications. VGI, however, has only recently been enabled on the large scale by
               innovations in web applications.<note>See above, and note 3.</note> Many such efforts
               – from early innovators like the Degree Confluence Project (1996; <ref
                  target="http://www.confluence.org/">http://www.confluence.org/</ref>), to more
               recent undertakings like Wikimapia (2006; <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/"
                  >http://wikimapia.org/</ref>) – reflect the interests of communities whose
               membership is mostly or almost entirely composed of non-specialists. They tend to be
               more broadly collaborative, iterative and open than traditional geospatial data
               creation efforts, but both commercial and institutional entities are also
               increasingly engaged in collaborative development or open dissemination of geographic
               information. VGI datasets are published via a wide range of web applications; recent
               standardization of formats and accommodation by commercial search engines has opened
               the field to <q>webby</q> distribution. For example, KML and GeoRSS-tagged web feeds
               can now be posted and managed just like other basic web content.<note>The publicly
                  open and collaborative aspects of VGI projects has sometimes led to the impression
                  that use of the resulting data for serious geospatial work is irresponsible, not
                  least because of perceptions of disregard for traditional forms of metadata (e.g.,
                  in a discussion thread on the closed-archive Maps-L discussion list in April 2007;
                  subject line <q>Query: map and GIS user needs</q>). It may be that the inherently
                  public aspect of VGI efforts makes it far easier to discover such oversights;
                  however, we are not aware of any authoritative study addressing the issue in
                  quantitative terms. There can be no doubt that many VGI datasets, and many of the
                  web applications that enable their creation and use, fail to address issues as
                  fundamental as precision, accuracy and data origin. It is particularly
                  frustrating, for example, that content from Google's geo-aware photo sharing
                  service, Panoramio (<ref target="http://www.panoramio.com/"
                     >http://www.panoramio.com/</ref>), is surfaced in Google Earth with no
                  reflection of its spatial accuracy. This despite the fact that Panoramio content
                  includes both images that were geo-tagged manually using an arbitrarily scaled map
                  interface and images whose EXIF headers originally contained high-resolution
                  coordinates and other metadata provided automatically by GPS-enabled digital
                  cameras. On the other hand, an increasing number of VGI projects whose technical
                  staff include academic or professional geographers are addressing these concerns
                  and finding innovative ways to solve them in the new media.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Electronic Cultural Atlas Initiative</head>
            <p>In 1997, The Electronic Cultural Atlas Initiative was chartered in Berkeley to ease
               and promote cross-project sharing of spatio-temporal data in the humanities <ptr
                  target="#buckland2004"/>; <ref target="http://www.ecai.org"
                  >http://www.ecai.org</ref>. Among its initiatives was a metadata clearinghouse for
               registered projects (<ref target="http://ecaimaps.berkeley.edu/clearinghouse/"
                  >http://​ecaimaps.berkeley.edu/​clearinghouse/</ref>). Scholars wishing to
               register their projects arrange for the published data to be posted to the web, and
               create <q>ECAI metadata</q> (a Dublin Core derivative), which is then added to the
               clearinghouse. Geographic and temporal components of the search are facilitated by a
               map-and-timeline interface realized with server-side TimeMap software (see <ref
                  target="http://www.timemap.net">http://www.timemap.net</ref>). This tool may be
               seen, on one level, as a reflection of the dominant web search mode of the day, the
               directory. But it also anticipated the future of VGI, appreciating that many
               humanities projects with spatial components would not be able to fit their content
               into the formats supported by the big repositories. Instead, it assumed that these
               projects would arrange for web hosting themselves, and take voluntary steps to share
               it with others. ECAI's Clearinghouse was also innovative in providing for the
               discovery of indexed projects through a combination of search and browse methods that
               exploited both spatial and temporal information in intuitive ways. ECAI remains a
               vibrant international community, organizing regular conferences and maintaining
               linkages across a wide range of projects and disciplines (see <ref
                  target="http://ecai.org/activities/conferences.asp"
                  >http://​ecai.org/​Activities/​conferences.asp</ref>). </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Stoa Waypoint Database and the Register of Ancient Geographic Entities</head>
            <p>The first attempt at full-fledged VGI in Classics was the Stoa Waypoint Database, a
               joint initiative of Robert Chavez, then with the Perseus Project, and the late Ross
               Scaife, on behalf of the Stoa Consortium for Electronic Publication in the Humanities
                  (<ref target="http://www.stoa.org">http://www.stoa.org</ref>). In its public
               unveiling, <ptr target="#scaife1999"/> cast the resource as <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#scaife1999">an archive [and] freely accessible source of geographic
                  data...for archaeologists...students...digital map makers, or anyone else engaged
                  in study and research</quote>. At initial publication, the dataset comprised
               slightly over 2,000 point features (settlements, sites and river mouths), drawn from
               work Chavez and Maria Daniels had done for the Perseus Atlas and personal research
               projects. The points included both GPS coordinates and coordinates drawn from various
               public domain (mostly US government) gazetteers and data sources. Chavez and Scaife
               also invited contributions of new data, especially encouraging the donation of GPS
               waypoints and tracks gathered in the field. A set of Guidelines for Recording
               Handheld GPS Waypoints were promulgated to support this work <ptr
                  target="#chavez1999"/>. The original application for download of the database was
               retired from the Stoa server some time ago; however, the data set has recently been
               reposted by the Ancient World Mapping Center in KML format (<ref
                  target="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/pleiades/data/stoagnd/"
                  >http://​www.unc.edu/​awmc/​pleiades/​data/​stoagnd/</ref>). Despite limited
               success in soliciting outside contributions, the idea of the Stoa Waypoint Database
               had a formative influence on the early conceptualization of the authors' Pleiades
               project.</p>
            <p>The Stoa's interest in GPS waypoints reflected a worldwide trend: in April 1995, the
               NAVSTAR Global Positioning System constellation had reached full operational
               capability, marking one of the pivotal moments in the geospatial revolution we are
               now experiencing. Originally conceived as a military aid to navigation, GPS quickly
               became indispensable to both civilian navigation and map-making, as well as the
               widest imaginable range of recreational and scientific uses. In May 2000, an
               executive order eliminated the intentional degradation of publicly accessible GPS
               signals, known as selective availability <ptr target="#office2000"/>. This decision
               effectively placed unprecedentedly accurate geo-referencing and navigating
               capabilities in the hands of the average citizen (~15m horizontal accuracy).</p>
            <p>Work on the Stoa Waypoints Database was clearly informed by the Perseus Atlas
               Project, and also by another concurrent project at the Stoa: the Suda Online (SOL;
                  <ref target="http://www.stoa.org/sol/">http://www.stoa.org/sol/</ref>). This
               all-volunteer, collaborative effort undertook the English translation of a major
               Byzantine encyclopedia of significance for Classicists and Byzantinists alike. The
               Suda provides information about many places and peoples. An obvious enhancement to
               the supporting web application would have been a mapping system like the Perseus
               Atlas. In exploring the possibility, Scaife and Chavez realized that the variant
               place names in the Suda and in the Perseus Atlas were a significant impediment to
               implementation. The solution they envisioned in collaboration with Neel Smith was
               dubbed the Register of Geographic Entities (RAGE). They imagined an inventory of
               conceptual spatial units and a set of associated web services that would store
               project-specific identifiers for geographic features, together with associated names.
               This index would provide for cross-project lookup of names, and dynamic mapping. Some
               development work was done subsequently at the University of Kentucky <ptr
                  target="#mohammed2002"/>, and the most current version may be had in the Registry
               XML format currently under development by Smith and colleagues at the Center for
               Hellenic Studies via the CHS Registry Browser (cf., <ptr target="#smith2005"/>). At
               present, it contains just over 3,500 entries drawn almost entirely from Ptolemy's
               works and thus has so far not seen wide use as a general dataset for the classical
                  world.<note>Of course the primary source of delay for RAGE was the lack of
                  availability of a comprehensive set of coordinates, identifiers and names around
                  which to array the content of other gazetteers. The Barrington Atlas constitutes
                  such a resource, but has not been available in an appropriate form, nor under a
                  suitable license that would permit such reuse. Elliott and Gillies, in
                  collaboration with others (including Smith) and with funding from the National
                  Endowment for the Humanities and the U.K. Joint Information Systems Committee have
                  recently devised and promulgated a list of identifiers and name strings for every
                  discrete geographic feature in the Barrington Atlas (see <ptr
                     target="#elliott2008b"/>). Projects and publishers are encouraged to use these
                  identifiers in their digital datasets; the Pleiades project aims to establish a
                  web service for linking these identifiers to its online coordinate and name data
                  as it is digitized. Linking or incorporation of the Ptolemaic information now in
                  the RAGE registry will thereafter be a straightforward matter.</note> The concern
               that informed the RAGE initiative remains valid: geographic interoperation between
               existing classics-related digital publications will require the collation of
               disparate, project-level gazetteers. It is our hope that, as Pleiades content is
               published, its open licensing and comprehensive coverage will catalyze a geo-webby
               solution.  </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Pleiades Project</head>
            <p>Our own project, Pleiades (<ref target="http://pleiades.stoa.org"
                  >http://pleiades.stoa.org</ref>), is heavily influenced by both by the scholarly
               practices of our predecessors and by on-going developments in web-enabled geography.
               We are producing a standard reference dataset for Classical geography, together with
               associated services for interoperability. Combining VGI approaches with
               academic-style editorial review, Pleiades will enable (from September 2008) anyone —
               from university professors to casual students of antiquity — to suggest updates to
               geographic names, descriptive essays, bibliographic references and geographic
               coordinates. Once vetted for accuracy and pertinence, these suggestions will become a
               permanent, author-attributed part of future publications and data services. The
               project was initiated by the Ancient World Mapping Center at the University of North
               Carolina, with development and design collaboration and resources provided by the
               Stoa. In February 2008, the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World joined the
               project as a partner and it is there that development efforts for the project are now
               directed.</p>
            <p>Pleiades may be seen from several angles. From the point of view of the Classical
               Atlas Project and its heir, the Ancient World Mapping Center, Pleiades is an
               innovative tool for the perpetual update and diversification of the dataset
               originally assembled to underpin the Barrington Atlas, which is being digitized and
               adapted for inclusion. From an editorial point of view, Pleiades is much like an
               academic journal, but with some important innovations. Instead of a thematic
               organization and primary subdivision into individually authored articles, Pleiades
               pushes discrete authoring and editing down to the fine level of structured reports on
               individual places and names, their relationships with each other and the scholarly
               rationale behind their content. In a real sense then Pleiades is also like an
               encyclopedic reference work, but with the built-in assumption of on-going revision
               and iterative publishing of versions (an increasingly common model for digital
               academic references). From the point of view of <q>neo-geo</q> applications, Pleiades
               is a source of services and data to support a variety of needs: dynamic mapping,
               proximity query and authority for names and places.</p>
            <p>Pleiades incorporates a data model that diverges from the structure of conventional
               GIS datasets. Complexity in the historical record, combined with varying uncertainty
               in our ability to interpret it, necessitate a flexible approach sensitive to inherent
               ambiguity and the likelihood of changing and divergent interpretations (cf. <ptr
                  target="#peuquet2002" loc="262–281"/>). In particular, we have rejected both
               coordinates and toponyms as the primary organizing theme for geo-historical data.
               Instead, we have settled upon the concept of <q>place</q> understood as a bundle of
               associations between attested names and measured (or estimated) locations (including
               areas). We call these bundles <q>features</q>. Individual features can be positioned
               in time, and the confidence of the scholar or analyst can be registered with respect
               to any feature using a limited vocabulary.</p>
            <p>We intend for Pleiades content to be reused and remixed by others. For this reason,
               we release the content in multiple formats under the terms of a Creative Commons
               Attribution Share-Alike license (<ref
                  target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"
                  >http://​creativecommons.org/​licenses/​by-sa/​3.0/</ref>). The Pleiades website
               presents HTML versions of our content that provide users with the full complement of
               information recorded for each place, feature, name and location. In our web services,
               we employ proxies for our content (KML and GeoRSS-enhanced Atom feeds) so that users
               can visualize and exploit it in a variety of automated ways. In this way, we provide
               a computationally actionable bridge between a nuanced, scholarly publication and the
               geographic discovery and exploitation tools now emerging on the web. But for us,
               these formats are lossy: they cannot represent our data model in a structured way
               that preserves all nuance and detail and permits ready parsing and exploitation by
               software agents. Indeed, we have been unable to identify a standard XML-based data
               format that simply and losslessly supports the full expression of the Pleiades data
                  model.<note>The original Pleiades proposal, written in 2005, anticipated that the
                  Alexandria Digital Library (ADL) Gazetteer format (<ref
                     target="http://www.alexandria.ucsb.edu/gazetteer/contentstandard/version3.2/gcs3.2-guide.htm"
                     >http://​www.alexandria.ucsb.edu/​gazetteer/​ContentStandard/​version3.2/​GCS3.2-guide.htm</ref>)
                  would provide an export and archiving vehicle (Elliott had supplied comments to
                  the joint ADL and ECAI teams that developed the gazetteer format with this use in
                  mind). We went so far as to propose that Pleiades would support the full ADL
                  Gazetteer Protocol for the exchange of such data. Unfortunately, development of
                  this putative standard seems to have stalled with the retirement of its primary
                  research leader (a Pleiades Steering Committee member), and to our knowledge it
                  has not seen significant adoption outside its original application in the
                  Alexandria Digital Library and a few closely collaborating historical-cultural
                  academic projects. In our view, its complex and deeply hierarchical XML file
                  structure lost ground in competition with the Open GIS (OGC) Consortium’s detailed
                  Geography Markup Language (in use by government and commercial GIS entities) and
                  the lightweight KML format introduced by Google Earth. Recently introduced
                  guidance for the description of <q>places</q> (in addition to <q>place names</q>)
                  by the Text Encoding Initiative might provide another <q>lossless</q> alternative,
                  but it seems unlikely to see wide adoption outside scholarly humanities circles
                  (see TEI Consortium 2008, sub <q>13. Names, Dates, Peoples and Places</q>, <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/nd.html"
                     >http://​www.tei-c.org/​release/​doc/​tei-p5-doc/​en/​html/​ND.html</ref>).</note>
            </p>
            <p>In 2009, we plan to address users' need for a lossless export format by implementing
               code to produce file sets composed of ESRI Shapefiles and attribute tables in
               comma-separated value (CSV) format. The addition of a Shapefile+CSV export capability
               will facilitate a download-oriented dissemination method, as well as position us to
               deposit time-stamped versions of our data into the institutional repository at NYU
               and other archival contexts as appropriate. Indeed, this is the most common format
               requested from us after KML. Although the Shapefile format is proprietary, it is used
               around the world in a variety of commercial and open-source GIS systems and can be
               readily decoded by third-party and open-source software. It is, in our judgment, the
               most readily useful format for individual desktop GIS users and small projects, and
               because of its ubiquity has a high likelihood of translation into new formats in the
               context of long-term preservation repositories. </p>
            <p>Historical time remains a problematic aspect of the web that cannot be divorced from
               geography. The use of virtual map layers to represent time periods remains a common
               metaphor. Timelines and animated maps are also not uncommon, but all these techniques
               must either remain tied to specific web applications or rely on cross-project data in
               standard formats that only handle the Gregorian calendar and do not provide
               mechanisms for the representation of uncertainty. Bruce Robertson's Historical Event
               Markup Language (HEML; <ref target="http://heml.mta.ca">http://heml.mta.ca</ref>)
               remains the most obvious candidate for providing the extra flexibility humanists need
               in this area, both for modeling and for expression in markup. It is our hope that it
               too will find modes of realization in the realm of web feeds and semantic
               interchange. </p>
            <p>In its final report, the American Council of Learned Societies Commission on
               Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social Sciences highlighted the importance
               of accessibility, openness, interoperability and public/private collaboration as some
               of the prerequisites for a culture of vigorous digital scholarship <ptr
                  target="#unsworth2006" loc="28"/>. We believe that Pleiades exemplifies these
               characteristics, both on its own terms and as an emulator of prior efforts that
               helped identify and define them. We recommend our two-fold agenda to other digital
               projects in the Classics whose content includes or informs the geographic:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>Publish works that help (in terms of content, structure, delivery and
                  licensing) other humanists work and teach</item>
               <item>Publish works that potentially improve the performance and accuracy of the
                  (geo)web</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>We view the history of computing, classics and geography as a rich and profitable
               dialogue between many disciplines and practitioners. It is tragic indeed that we lost
               much too soon our friend and mentor Ross Scaife, who emerges as a pivotal figure in
               our narrative of this history. It was he who invited Elliott to the University of
               Kentucky in 2001 to give the first public presentation about the proposed Pleiades
               Project at the Center for Computational Studies, and it was he who provided the
               development server that supported the first two years of Pleiades software
               development. We are confident that, were Ross with us today as he was at the workshop
               that occasioned the original version of this paper, he would still be motivating us
               with challenging examples and stimulating ideas, connecting us with new collaborators
               and encouraging us to push harder for the changes we wish to see in our
               discipline.</p>
            <p>Despite the sense of loss that inevitably runs through the papers in this volume, and
               despite the challenges we face in a chaotic and interdisciplinary milieu, we also
               view the history of geographic computing and the classics as a hopeful omen for the
               future. We have a spectacular rising wave to ride: a wave of technological and
               societal change that may well help us conduct research and teach with more rigor and
               completeness than before while breaking down artificial boundaries between scholars
               in the academy and members of an increasingly educated and engaged public whose
               professional skills, public hobbies and personal interests coincide with ours at the
               fascinating intersection of humanity, space and time.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="asadi2007" label="Asadi 2007" key="asadi2007"> Asadi, Saeid et al. <title
                  rend="quotes">Location-Based Search Engines Tasks and Capabilities: A Comparative
                  Study.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Webology</title> 4.4 (December 2007). <ref
                  target="http://www.webology.ir/2007/v4n4/a48.html"
                  >http://www.webology.ir/2007/v4n4/a48.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="babeu2007" label="babeu 2008" key="babeu2007">Babeu, A., Bamman, D.,
               Crane, G., Kummer, R. and Weaver, G. “Named Entity Identification and
               Cyberinfrastructure.” In <title rend="italic">11th European Conference, ECDL 2007,
                  Budapest, Hungary, September 16-21, 2007. Proceedings. Lecture Notes in Computer
                  Science</title> 4675, Springer 2007: 259-270.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="badger2007" label="Badger 2007" key="badger2007a"> Badger, B. <title
                  rend="quotes">Google Book Search in Google Earth,</title> Google LatLon Blog (20
               August 2007): <ref
                  target="http://google-latlong.blogspot.com/2007/08/google-book-search-in-google-earth.html"
                  >http://google-latlong.blogspot.com/2007/08/google-book-search-in-google-earth.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bell2008" label="Bell 2008" key="bell2008">Bell,Tyler. <title
                  rend="quotes">A Tale of Two Cities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Yahoo! Geo Technologies Blog</title>. 28 August 2008: <ref
                  target="http://www.ygeoblog.com/blog/2008/08/28/a-tale-of-two-cities/"
                  >http://www.ygeoblog.com/blog/2008/08/28/a-tale-of-two-cities/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berlind2007" label="Berlind 2007" key="berlind2007"> Berlind, David.
                  <title rend="quotes">Web inventor Sir Tim Berners-Lee waxes on 'pixels
                  everywhere'.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Between the Lines</title>, June 7, 2007. <ref
                  target="http://blogs.zdnet.com/btl/?p=5318"
                  >http://blogs.zdnet.com/BTL/?p=5318</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bhasker2007" label="Bhasker 2007" key="bhasker2007"> Bhasker, Ezekiel et
               al. <title rend="quotes">Advances towards next-generation flexible multi-projector
                  display walls.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2007 workshop on
                  Emerging displays technologies: images and beyond: the future of displays and
                  interacton</title>, 11. San Diego, California: ACM, 2007.
               doi:10.1145/1278240.1278251. <ref
                  target="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1278240.1278251&amp;coll=guide&amp;dl=guide&amp;cfid=8598811&amp;cftoken=44119944"
                  >http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1278240.1278251&amp;coll=GUIDE&amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;CFID=8598811&amp;CFTOKEN=44119944</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boast2007" label="Boast 2007" key="boast2007"> Boast, R., et al., <title
                  rend="quotes">Return to Babel: Emergent Diversity, Digital Resources, and Local
                  Knowledge,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Information Society</title> 23 (2007), 395-403.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boll2008" label="Boll 2008" key="boll2008"> Boll, S. et al (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">LOCWEB '08: Proceedings of the First International Workshop on
                  Location and the Web</title>, New York: ACM, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boonstra2004" label="Boonstra 2004" key="boonstra2004"> Boonstra, O. et
               al., <title rend="quotes">Past, Present and Future of Historical Information Science,
                  Historical Social Research</title> / <title rend="italic">Historische
                  Sozialforschung</title> 29.2 (2004), <ref
                  target="http://www.gla.ac.uk/centres/hca/ahc/docs/pastpresentfuture.pdf"
                  >http://www.gla.ac.uk/centres/hca/ahc/docs/pastpresentfuture.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="buckland2004" label="Buckland 2004" key="buckland2004"> Buckland, M. and
               Lancaster, L. <title rend="quotes">Combining Place, Time and Topic: The Electronic
                  Cultural Atlas Initiative,</title>
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 10.5 (May 2004): <ref
                  target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may04/buckland/05buckland.html"
                  >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may04/buckland/05buckland.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bunbury1883" label="Bunburry 1883" key="bunbury1883"> Bunbury, E. <title
                  rend="italic">A History of Ancient Geography Among the Greeks and Romans from the
                  Earliest Ages till the Fall of the Roman Empire</title>, 2d. ed, 2 vols., London:
               John Murray, 1883.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carlson2007a" label="Carlson 2007a" key="carlson2007a"> Carlson, N. <title
                  rend="quotes">Google Earth's GM John Hanke,</title> Internetnews.com (6 July
               2007): <ref target="http://www.internetnews.com/xsp/article.php/3687471"
                  >http://www.internetnews.com/xSP/article.php/3687471</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chavez1999" label="Chavez 1999" key="chavez1999"> Chavez R. <title
                  rend="italic">Guidelines for Recording Handheld GPS Waypoints</title> (1999): <ref
                  target="http://www.stoa.org/guides/gps.shtml"
                  >http://www.stoa.org/guides/gps.shtml</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2008" label="Cohen 2008" key="cohen2008a">Cohen, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Vision of ORE,</title> Dan Cohen's Digital Humanities Blog (3
               March 2008), <ref target="http://www.dancohen.org/2008/03/03/the-vision-of-ore/"
                  >http://www.dancohen.org/2008/03/03/the-vision-of-ore/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2001" label="Crane 2001" key="crane2001"> Crane, Gregory R. et al,
                  <title rend="quotes">Drudgery and Deep Thought: Designing a Digital Library for
                  the Humanities,</title> Communications of the Association for Computing Machinery
               44.5 (2001): a copy is available at <ref
                  target="http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/articles/cacm2000.pdf"
                  >http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/Articles/cacm2000.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2006" label="Crane 2006" key="crane2006a"> Crane, Gregory R. and
               Jones, Alison, <title rend="quotes">The Perseus American Collection 1.0</title>: <ref
                  target="http://dl.tufts.edu//view_pdf.jsp?urn=tufts:facpubs:gcrane-2006.00001"
                  >http://dl.tufts.edu//view_pdf.jsp?urn=tufts:facpubs:gcrane-2006.00001</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2006a" label="Crane 2006a" key="crane2006e"> Crane, Gregory R. and
               Jones, Alison, <title rend="quotes">The Challenge of Virginia Banks: An Evaluation of
                  Named Entity Analysis in a 19th-Century Newspaper Collection,</title> pp. 31-40 in
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 6th ACM/IEEE-CS joint conference on
                  Digital libraries</title>, Chapel Hill: 2006: a copy is available at <ref
                  target="http://dl.tufts.edu/view_pdf.jsp?pid=tufts:pb.001.001.00007"
                  >http://dl.tufts.edu/view_pdf.jsp?pid=tufts:PB.001.001.00007</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crane2006b" label="Crane 2006b" key="crane2006b"> Crane, Gregory R. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Perseus Digital Library: New content and services for 19th
                  century American documents,</title>
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 12.3 (March 2006): <ref
                  target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/march06/03featured-collection.html"
                  >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/march06/03featured-collection.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crawford2008" label="Crawford 2008" key="crawford2008"> Crawford, W.
                  <title rend="quotes">Updating the Book Discovery Projects,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cites &amp; Insights: Crawford at Large</title> 8 (September
               2008): <ref target="http://citesandinsights.info/v8i9b.htm"
                  >http://citesandinsights.info/v8i9b.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="czerwinski2006" label="Czerwinski 2006" key="czerwinski2006">Czerwinski,
               M. <title rend="quotes">Large Display Research Overview,</title> CHI '06 extended
               abstracts on Human factors in computing systems, New York, 2006: 69-74.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunn2008" label="Dunn 2008" key="dunn2008"> Dunn, S. and Blanke, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Next Steps for E-Science, the Textual Humanities and VREs: A Report
                  on Text and Grid: Research Questions for the Humanities, Sciences and Industry, UK
                  e-Science All Hands Meeting 2007,</title>
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 14 (2008), <ref
                  target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january08/dunn/01dunn.html"
                  >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january08/dunn/01dunn.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elliott2006" label="Elliott 2006" key="elliott2006"> Elliott, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Pleiades: Beyond the Barrington Atlas,</title> a paper presented to
               the annual meeting of the American Philological Association, San Diego, California, 6
               January 2006, <ref
                  target="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/pleiades/wiki/elliottapapaper"
                  >http://www.atlantides.org/trac/pleiades/wiki/ElliottAPAPaper</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elliott2008a" label="Elliott 2008a" key="elliott2008a"> Elliott, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Constructing a Digital Publication for the Peutinger Map</title> in
               R. Talbert and R. Unger (eds.), <title rend="italic">Cartography in Antiquity and the
                  Middle Ages: Fresh Perspectives, New Methods</title>, Leiden: 2008: 99-110.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elliott2008b" label="Elliott 2008b" key="elliott2008b"> Elliott, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Hidden Web: Don't Love It, Leave It,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Horothesia</title> (1 August 2008), <ref
                  target="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/08/hidden-web-dont-love-it-leave-it.html"
                  >http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/08/hidden-web-dont-love-it-leave-it.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elliott2008" label="Elliott2008" key="elliott2008"> Elliott, T. <title
                  rend="quotes">Barrington Atlas IDs,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Horothesia</title> (10 July 2007, with updates), <ref
                  target="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/07/barrington-atlas-ids.html"
                  >http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/07/barrington-atlas-ids.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="executive_order_12906" label="Executive Order 12906"
               key="executive_order_12906"> Coordinating Geographic Data Acquisition and Access: The
               National Spatial Data Infrastructure (11 April 1994), <ref
                  target="http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/executive-orders/pdf/12906.pdf"
                  >http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/executive-orders/pdf/12906.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="executive_order_13286" label="Executive Order 13286"
               key="executive_order_13286"> Amendment of Executive Orders, and Other Actions, in
               Connection With the Transfer of Certain Functions to the Secretary of Homeland
               Security (28 February 2003), <ref
                  target="http://edocket.access.gpo.gov/2003/pdf/03-5343.pdf"
                  >http://edocket.access.gpo.gov/2003/pdf/03-5343.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fabricius1888" label="Fabricius 1888" key="fabricius1888"> Fabricius, W.
                  <title rend="italic">Theophanes von Mytilene und Quintus Dellius als Quellen des
                  Geographie des Strabon</title>, Strassburg: Heitz und Mündel, 1888.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fee2008" label="Fee 2008" key="fee2008"> Fee, J. <title rend="quotes">VGI
                  – Meh,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Spatially Adjusted</title> (13 March 2008), <ref
                  target="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2008/03/13/vgi-meh/"
                  >http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2008/03/13/vgi-meh/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foss2007" label="Foss 2007" key="foss2007"> Foss, P. and Schindler, R.
               (eds.), MAGIS: Mediterranean Archaeological GIS, DePauw University, 2007: <ref
                  target="http://cgma.depauw.edu/magis/">http://cgma.depauw.edu/MAGIS/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gillies2008" label="Gillies 2008" key="gillies2008">Sean Gillies, <title
                  rend="quotes">Entries: Category [REST]: Representational State Transfer</title>,
               Sean Gillies Blog, <ref target="http://sgillies.net/blog"
                  >http://sgillies.net/blog</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="genoni2005" label="Genoni 2005" key="genoni2005"> Genoni, P. et al.,
                  <title rend="quotes">The Use of the Internet to Activate Latent Ties in Scholarly
                  Communities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 10 (2005): <ref
                  target="http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/viewarticle/1301/1221"
                  >http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/viewArticle/1301/1221</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="geoweb2007" label="GeoWeb Exploration 2007" key="geoweb2007">
               <title rend="quotes">GeoWeb Exploration: Mining Information from Collections and
                  KML,</title> Virtual Earth / Live Maps Blog (19 October 2007): <ref
                  target="http://virtualearth.spaces.live.com/blog/cns!2bbc66e99fdcdb98!9381.entry"
                  >http://virtualearth.spaces.live.com/blog/cns!2BBC66E99FDCDB98!9381.entry</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goodchild2004" label="Goodchild 2004" key="goodchild2004"> Goodchild, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Alexandria Digital Library Project: Review, Assessment,
                  and Prospects,</title>
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 10.5 (May 2004): <ref
                  target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may04/goodchild/05goodchild.html"
                  >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may04/goodchild/05goodchild.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goodchild2007" label="Goodchild 2007" key="goodchild2007"> Goodchild, M.
               Citizens as Sensors: The World of Volunteered Geography (18 September 2007): <ref
                  target="http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/projects/vgi/docs/position/goodchild_vgi2007.pdf"
                  >http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/projects/vgi/docs/position/Goodchild_VGI2007.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goodchild2007a" label="Goodchild 2007a" key="goodchild2007a"> Goodchild,
               M. and Gupta, R. Workshop on Volunteered Geographic Information, December 13-14,
               2007: Meeting Products: <ref target="http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/projects/vgi/"
                  >http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/projects/vgi/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gregory2002" label="Gregory 2002" key="gregory2002"> Gregory, I. A Place
               in History: A Guide to Using GIS in Historical Research, AHDS Guides to Good
               Practice, August 2002: <ref target="http://hds.essex.ac.uk/g2gp/gis/index.asp"
                  >http://hds.essex.ac.uk/g2gp/gis/index.asp</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guthrie2008" label="Guthrie 2008" key="guthrie2008"> Guthrie, K, et al.,
               Sustainability and Revenue Models for Online Academic Resources: An Ithaka Report,
               2008: <ref
                  target="http://sca.jiscinvolve.org/files/2008/06/sca_ithaka_sustainability_report-final.pdf"
                  >http://sca.jiscinvolve.org/files/2008/06/sca_ithaka_sustainability_report-final.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hansen2004" label="Hansen 2004" key="hansen2004"> Hansen, M. and Nielsen,
               T. <title rend="italic">An Inventory of Archaic and Classical Poleis</title>, Oxford:
               2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hartzler1998" label="Hartzler 1998" key="hartzler1998"> Hartzler, B. Metis
               QTVR, The Stoa (1998-): <ref target="http://www.stoa.org/metis"
                  >http://www.stoa.org/metis</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hill2006" label="Hill 2006" key="hill2006"> Hill, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Georeferencing: The Geographic Associations of Information</title>, Cambridge,
               Mass. 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hudsonsmith2008" label="Hudson-Smith 2008" key="hudsonsmith2008">
               Hudson-Smith, Andrew and Crooks, Andrew. <title rend="quotes">The Renaissance of
                  Geographic Information: Neogeography, Gaming and Second Life,</title> CASA Working
               Paper 142, Centre for Advanced Spatial Analysis, University College London, 2008:
                  <ref target="http://www.casa.ucl.ac.uk/publications/workingpaperdetail.asp?id=142"
                  >http://www.casa.ucl.ac.uk/publications/workingPaperDetail.asp?ID=142</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kiepert1878" label="Kiepert 1878" key="kiepert1878"> Kiepert, H. <title
                  rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Alten Geographie</title>, Berlin: D. Reimer,
               1878.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kiepert1881" label="Kiepert 1881" key="kiepert1881"> Kiepert, H. and
               Macmillan, G.A. (trans.), <title rend="italic">A Manual of Ancient Geography</title>,
               London: Macmillan and Co, 1881.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kiepert1902" label="Kiepert 1910" key="kiepert1902"> Kiepert, H. <title
                  rend="italic">Atlas Antiquus</title>, Berlin: D. Reimer, 1902.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knowles2002" label="Knowles 2002" key="knowles2002"> Knowles, A. (ed).
                  <title rend="italic">Past Time, Past Place: GIS for History</title>, Redlands, CA,
               2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knowles2008" label="Knowles 2008" key="knowles2008"> Knowles, A. and
               Hillier, A. (eds.). <title rend="italic">Placing History: How Maps, Spatial Data and
                  GIS are Changing Historical Scholarship</title>, Redlands, CA, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kozareva2006" label="Kozareva 2006" key="kozareva2006">Kozareva, Z. <title
                  rend="quotes">Bootstrapping Named Entity Recognition with Automatically Generated
                  Gazetteer Lists.</title> In <title rend="italic">11th Conference of the European
                  Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Proceedings</title>. The
               Association for Computer Linguistics, 2006: 15-21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lucarelli2007" label="Lucarelli 2007" key="lucarelli2007">Lucarelli, G.;
               Vasilakos, X. and Androutsopoulos, I. <title rend="quotes">Named Entity Recognition
                  in Greek Texts with an Ensemble of SVMs and Active Learning.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal on Artificial Intelligence Tools</title>,
               16 (2007): 1015-1045.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="miller2007" label="Miller 2007" key="miller2007b"> Miller, P. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Semantic Web - Is Everyone Confused?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Nodalities: From Semantic Web to Web of Data</title> (20
               September 2007): <ref
                  target="http://blogs.talis.com/nodalities/2007/09/the_semantic_web_is_everyone_c.php"
                  >http://blogs.talis.com/nodalities/2007/09/the_semantic_web_is_everyone_c.php</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mohammed2002" label="Mohammed 2002" key="mohammed2002"> Mohammed, S.
                  <title rend="italic">From SOL to RAGE: New Work on Collaborative Technologies for
                  Classics </title>(19 March 2002): <ref
                  target="https://www.ccs.uky.edu/ccs/profiles/spring02/bbag/feb19.html"
                  >https://www.ccs.uky.edu/ccs/profiles/Spring02/bbag/feb19.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mohr2006" label="Mohr 2006" key="mohr2006"> Mohr, J, Nicols, J., Funke,
               P., and Stollberg-Rilinger, B (eds.), <title rend="italic">Mapping History</title>
               (1997-2006): <ref target="http://mappinghistory.uoregon.edu"
                  >http://mappinghistory.uoregon.edu</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mostern2008" label="Mostern 2008" key="mostern2008a"> Mostern, R. <title
                  rend="quotes">Historical Gazetteers: An Experiential Perspective, with Examples
                  from Chinese History,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Historical Methods: A Journal of Quantitative and
                  Interdisciplinary History</title>, 41 (2008), 39-46.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nadeau2006" label="Nadeau 2006" key="nadeau2006">Nadeau, D.; Turney, P. D.
               and Matwin, S. <title rend="quotes">Unsupervised Named-Entity Recognition: Generating
                  Gazetteers and Resolving Ambiguity.</title> In Lamontagne, L. and Marchand, M.
               (ed.). <title rend="italic">Canadian Conference on AI 2006, Proceedings. Lecture
                  Notes in Computer Science</title> 4013, Springer 2008: 266-277.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="office2000" label="Office 2000" key="office2000"> Office of the Press
               Secretary, The White House, Statement by the President Regarding the United States'
               Decision to Stop Degrading Global Positioning System Accuracy, 1 May 2000: <ref
                  target="http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/space/gps_clinton.htm"
                  >http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/space/gps_clinton.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ohazama2007" label="Ohazama 2007" key="ohazama2007"> Ohazama, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">Search for KML in Google Earth,</title> Google Maps API Blog (14
               February 2007): <ref
                  target="http://googlemapsapi.blogspot.com/2007/02/search-for-kml-in-google-earth.html"
                  >http://googlemapsapi.blogspot.com/2007/02/search-for-kml-in-google-earth.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="petrou2007" label="Petrou 2007" key="petrou2007"> Petrou, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Books: Mapped,</title> Inside Google Book Search (25 January 2007,
               10:31 p.m.): <ref target="http://booksearch.blogspot.com/2007/01/books-mapped.html"
                  >http://booksearch.blogspot.com/2007/01/books-mapped.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="peuquet2002" label="Peuquet 2002" key="peuquet2002"> Peuquet, Donna.
                  <title rend="italic">Representations of Space and Time</title>. New York: Guilford
               Press, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pritchard2008" label="Pritchard 2008" key="pritchard2008">Pritchard, D.
                  <title rend="quotes">Working Papers, Open Access, and Cyber-infrastructure in
                  Classical Studies.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 23 (2008):
               149-162.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="putz1994" label="Putz 1994" key="putz1994"> Putz, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Interactive Information Services Using World-Wide Web Hypertext</title> (1994):
                  <ref target="http://www2.parc.com/istl/projects/www94/iisuwwwh.html"
                  >http://www2.parc.com/istl/projects/www94/iisuwwwh.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ratliff2007" label="Ratliff 2007" key="ratliff2007"> Ratliff, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Google Maps Is Changing the Way We See The World,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wired Magazine</title> 15.007 (July 2007): <ref
                  target="http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/magazine/15-07/ff_maps"
                  >http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/magazine/15-07/ff_maps</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rohs2007" label="Rohs 2007" key="rohs2007"> Rohs, M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >WikEye – Camera Phones as Magic Lenses for Paper Maps</title> (3 September 2007):
                  <ref target="http://www.deutsche-telekom-laboratories.de/~rohs/wikeye/"
                  >http://www.deutsche-telekom-laboratories.de/~rohs/wikeye/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rydbergcox2000" label="Rydberg-Cox 2000" key="rydbergcox2000">
               Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A. et al.,<title rend="quotes">Knowledge Management in the
                  Perseus Digital Library,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Ariadne</title> 25 (24 September 2000): <ref
                  target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue25/rydberg-cox/"
                  >http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue25/rydberg-cox/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sahin2007" label="Şahin 2007" key="sahin2007"> Şahin, S. and M. Adak
               (eds.), <title rend="italic">Stadiasmus Patarensis Itinera Romana Provinciae
                  Lyciae</title>, Istanbul: 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="scaife1999" label="Scaife 1999" key="scaife1999"> Scaife, R. Stoa Waypoint
               Database (fwd), posting to the classics-l listserv, 5 October 1999: <ref
                  target="http://web.archive.org/web/20031206054959/http://omega.cohums.ohio-state.edu/mailing_lists/cla-m/1999/0294.php"
                  >http://web.archive.org/web/20031206054959/http://omega.cohums.ohio-state.edu/mailing_lists/CLA-M/1999/0294.php</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="scaife2006" label="Scaife 2006" key="scaife2006"> Scaife, Ross. Bronze Age
               Crete: Archaeological Sites of Minoan Crete and the Cyclades Associated with
               Descriptive Scholarly Resources (22-31 May 2006): <ref
                  target="http://bbs.keyhole.com/ubb/showflat.php?cat=0&amp;board=earthhistory&amp;number=425243"
                  >http://bbs.keyhole.com/ubb/showflat.php?Cat=0&amp;Board=EarthHistory&amp;Number=425243</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schutzberg2007" label="Schutzberg 2007" key="schutzberg2007"> Schutzberg,
               A. <title rend="quotes">Google KML Search: What Does It Mean for Geospatial
                  Professionals?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Directions Magazine</title> (16 February 2007): <ref
                  target="http://www.directionsmag.com/article.php?article_id=2409"
                  >http://www.directionsmag.com/article.php?article_id=2409</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shaalan2008" label="Shaalan 2008" key="shaalan2008">Shaalan, K. F. and
               Raza, H. <title rend="quotes">Arabic Named Entity Recognition from Diverse Text
                  Types.</title> In Nordström, B. and Ranta, A. (ed.). <title rend="italic">Advances
                  in Natural Language Processing, 6th International Conference, GoTAL 2008,
                  Gothenburg, Sweden, August 25-27, 2008, Proceedings. Lecture Notes in Computer
                  Science</title> 5221. Springer 2008: 440-451. <ref
                  target="http://dblp.uni-trier.de/db/conf/tal/gotal2008.html#shaalanr08"
                  >http://dblp.uni-trier.de/db/conf/tal/gotal2008.html#ShaalanR08</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shadbolt2006" label="Shadbolt 2006" key="shadbolt2006"> Shadbolt, N. et
               al. <title rend="quotes">The Semantic Web Revisited,</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Intelligent Systems 21.3</title> (2006): 96-101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2001" label="Smith 2001" key="smith2001"> Smith, D. and Crane, G.
                  <title rend="quotes">Disambiguating Geographic Names in a Historical Digital
                  Library.</title> In P. Constantopoulos and I.T. Solvberg (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Research and Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries, Proceedings
                  of the 5th European Conference, ECDL 2001</title>, Darmstadt, Germany, Berlin,
               2001: 127-136.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2002a" label="Smith 2002a" key="smith2002a"> Smith, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Detecting Events with Date and Place Information in Unstructured
                  Text,</title>. In G. Marchionini and W. Hersh (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the Second ACM/IEEE Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</title>
               (JCDL 2002), Portland, OR. New York: 191-196.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2002b" label="Smith 2002b" key="smith2002b"> Smith, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Detecting and Browsing Events in Unstructured Text,</title> pp.
               73-80 in SIGIR '02: Proceedings of the 25th annual international ACM SIGIR conference
               on Research and development in information retrieval, New York: 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2005" label="Smith 2005" key="smith2005"> Smith, N. Registry
               Services, Digital Incunabula pre-release - development version (19 August 2005): <ref
                  target="http://chs75.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/techpub/registry"
                  >http://chs75.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/techpub/registry</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="spiro2008" label="Spiro 2008" key="spiro2008"> Spiro, L. <title
                  rend="quotes">Signs that Social Scholarship is Catching on in the
                  Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> (11 March 2008):
                  <ref
                  target="http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2008/03/11/signs-that-social-scholarship-is-catching-on-in-the-humanities"
                  >http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2008/03/11/signs-that-social-scholarship-is-catching-on-in-the-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sterling2007" label="Sterling 2007" key="sterling2007"> Sterling, B.
                  <title rend="quotes">Dispatches From the Hyperlocal Future,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wired Magazine</title> 15.07 (July 2007): <ref
                  target="http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/magazine/15-07/local"
                  >http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/magazine/15-07/local</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stodle2007" label="Stødle 2007" key="stodle2007"> Stødle, D. et al. <title
                  rend="quotes">The 22 Megapixel Laptop</title> in <title rend="italic">EDT '07:
                  Proceedings of the 2007 workshop on Emerging displays technologie</title>s, New
               York, 2007: article no. 8, <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1278240.1278248"
                  >http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1278240.1278248</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="syme1995" label="Syme 1995" key="syme1995"> Syme, R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Anatolica: Studies in Strabo</title>. Oxford University Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="talbert1992" label="Talbert 1992" key="talbert1992"> Talbert, R. <title
                  rend="quotes">Mapping the Classical World: Major Atlases and Map Series
                  1872-1990,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Roman Archaeology</title> 5 (1992): 5-38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tilkov2007" label="Tilkov 2007" key="tilkov2007"> Tilkov, S. <title
                  rend="quotes">A Brief Introduction to REST</title> InfoQ (December 2007): <ref
                  target="http://www.infoq.com/articles/rest-introduction"
                  >http://www.infoq.com/articles/rest-introduction</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2006" label="Turner 2006" key="turner2006"> Turner, A. <title
                  rend="italic">Introduction to NeoGeography</title>. O'Reilly Media, 2006: <ref
                  target="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596529956"
                  >http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596529956</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2000" label="Unsworth 2000" key="unsworth2000"> Unsworth, J.
                  <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods Do Humanities Researchers
                  Have in Common, and How Might Our Tools Reflect This?</title>. Symposium on
               Humanities Computing: Formal Methods, Experimental Practice, sponsored by King's
               College, London, May 13, 2000 (no date): <ref
                  target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/kings.5-00/primitives.html"
                  >http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2006" label="Unsworth 2006" key="unsworth2006"> Unsworth, J.,
               Welshons, M. (eds.). <title rend="italic">Our Cultural Commonwealth: The Report of
                  the American Council of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for
                  the Humanities and Social Sciences, 2007</title>: <ref
                  target="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/"
                  >http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilson2007" label="Wilson 2007" key="wilson2007"> Wilson, B. <title
                  rend="quotes">News About Digitization Projects,</title>
               <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 13 (2007), <ref
                  target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/november07/11editorial.html"
                  >http://www.dlib.org/dlib/november07/11editorial.html</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
