<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">Determining Value for Digital Humanities Tools: Report on a Survey
               of Tool Developers </title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Susan <dhq:family>Schreibman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Observatory</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>susan.schreibman@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Susan Schreibman is the Director of the Digital Humanities Observatory (Dublin,
                     Ireland), a national digital humanities centre <ref target="http://dho.ie"
                        >(http://dho.ie)</ref>, which is being developed under the auspices of the
                     Royal Irish Academy. She was previously Assistant Dean for Digital Collections
                     and Research, University of Maryland Libraries (2005-2008), and Assistant
                     Director of the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities
                     (2001-2004). Dr Schreibman is the Founding Editor of The Thomas MacGreevy
                     Archive <ref target="http://macgreevy.org">(http://macgreevy.org)</ref> and
                     Irish Resources in the Humanities <ref target="http://irith.org"
                        >(http://irith.org)</ref>. She is the co-editor of <title rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title> (Blackwell, 2008) and A
                     Companion to Digital Humanities (Blackwell, 2004), as well as the author of
                        <title rend="italic">Collected Poems of Thomas MacGreevy: An Annotated
                        Edition</title>. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ann M. <dhq:family>Hanlon</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Marquette University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ann.hanlon@marquette.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ann Hanlon is Digital Projects Librarian at Marquette University. She manages
                     Marquette's institutional repository and provides guidance regarding digital
                     collections management. Previously, she was the Digital Collections Librarian
                     at the University of Maryland.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000083</idno>
            <idno type="volume">004</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2010-09-01">1 September 2010</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-05-04" who="Alyssa">Encoded</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>

            <p>While the purpose and direction of tools and tool development for the Digital
               Humanities have been debated in various forums, the value of tool development as a
               scholarly activity has seen little discussion. As a way of filling this gap, the
               authors conducted an online survey of developers of digital humanities tools in March
               2008. The survey focused on their perceptions of their work, how they felt their tool
               development fit into a structure of academic rewards, and the value of tool
               development as a scholarly pursuit. Survey results indicate that tool development is
               indeed considered a scholarly activity by developers, but recognition of this work
               and rewards for it lag behind rewards for traditional scholarly pursuits (such as
               journal articles and book publication). This paper presents a summary of the results
               of the survey, ending with some suggestions for further research.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Survey results indicate that DH tool development is considered a scholarly activity
               by developers, but recognition of this work lags behind recognition of traditional
               scholarly pursuits.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Determining Value for Digital Humanities Tools: Report on a Survey of Tool
            Developers</head>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <p>Tool development in the Digital Humanities has been the subject of numerous articles
               and conference presentations.<note>
                  <ptr target="#ahrc2006"/>; <ptr target="#bradley2003"/>; <ptr
                     target="#mccarty2005"/>; <ptr target="#mcgann2005"/>; <ptr target="#ramsay2003"
                  />; <ptr target="#ramsay2005"/>; <ptr target="#schreibman2007a"/>; <ptr
                     target="#schreibman2003"/>; <ptr target="#summit2005"/>; <ptr
                     target="#unsworth2003"/>.</note> While the purpose and direction of tools and
               tool development for the Digital Humanities has been debated in various forums, the
               value of tool development as a scholarly activity has seen little discussion. This
               may be, in part, because of the perception that tools are developed to aid and abet
               scholarship, but that their development is not necessarily considered scholarship in
               and of itself.</p>
            <p>This perception, held by the vast majority of tenure review boards, dissertation
               committees, and our peers, may be an impediment to the development of the field of
               digital humanities. Indeed, as our survey results indicate, some tool developers also
               subscribe to this. A majority of respondents, however, consider tools development
               positively linked to more traditional scholarly pursuits. As one respondent
               indicated, <quote rend="block" source="#private">I develop a tool as a specific means to an
                  end, and the end is always pertinent to some literary question. Tool development
                  is deeply informed by the research agenda and thus the tool development might be
                  seen as analogous to other <q>research</q> activities. Archival research is one
                  way of obtaining data. To get that data one must employ a methodology etc. The
                  development of a tool is akin to this.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Tool development as a methodological approach was considered no less rigorous and
               scholarly than other approaches: <quote rend="block" source="#private">My field is the
                  digital humanities, and some part of my research is on how computing affects
                  (positively and negatively) scholarly activity. Building the tool — which
                  expresses a particular intellectual stance on certain issues — is meant to be a
                  research activity.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Several major recent reports urge the academic community (particularly in the
               humanities) to consider tool development as a scholarly pursuit, and as such, build
               it into our system of academic rewards. The clearest statement of such a shift in
               thinking came from the recommendations of the <title rend="italic">ACLS Commission on
                  Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social Sciences</title>, which called
               not only for <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth2006">policies for tenure and promotion that
                  recognize and reward digital scholarship and scholarly communication</quote> but
               likewise stated that <quote rend="inline" source="unsworth2006">recognition should be given not
                  only to scholarship that uses the humanities and social science
                  cyberinfrastructure but also to scholarship that contributes to its design,
                  construction and growth.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>The hurdles we might expect in seeing these recommendations implemented are
               complicated by a parallel but distinct issue noted by the <title rend="italic">MLA
                  Report on Evaluating Scholarship for Tenure and Promotion</title>: namely, that a
               majority of departments have little to no experience evaluating refereed articles and
               monographs in electronic format. The prospects for evaluating tool development as
               scholarship, at least in the near term, in these departments would appear dim.
               However, coupled with the more optimistic recommendations of the ACLS report, as well
               as the MLA Report’s findings that evaluation of work in digital form is gaining
               ground, the notion of tool development as a scholarly activity may not be far
               behind.</p>
            <p>In 2005, scholars from the humanities, the social sciences, and computer science met
               in Charlottesville, Virginia for a <title rend="italic">Summit on Digital Tools for
                  the Humanities</title>. While the summit itself focused primarily on the use of
               digital resources and digital tools for scholarship, the Report on Summit
               Accomplishments that followed touched on development, concluding that <quote rend="inline" source="#summit2005">the development of tools for the interpretation of
                  digital evidence is itself research in the arts and humanities.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>The present study was thus undertaken in response to some of the questions and
               conclusions that came out of the Digital Tools summit and also as a follow-up to our
               own experiences in conducting an earlier survey in the spring of 2007 on the
               perceived value of <ref target="http://v-machine.org">
                  <title rend="italic">The Versioning Machine</title>
               </ref>. One of the intriguing results of The Versioning Machine survey, which was
               presented as a poster at the 2007 <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities</title>
               conference <ptr target="#schreibman2007b"/> was in the area of value. The vast
               majority of respondents found it valuable as a means to advance scholarship in spite
               of the fact that they themselves did not use it, or at least did not use it in the
               ways the developers of <title rend="italic">The Versioning Machine</title> envisioned
               its use. As a result of feedback during and subsequent to the poster session, the
               authors decided to conduct a survey focusing on tool development as a scholarly
               activity.</p>
            <p>The authors developed the survey to meet in one small way John Unsworth’s challenge,
               made at the 2007 <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Centers Summit</title>,
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth2007">to make our difficulties, the shortcomings of our
                  tools, the challenges we haven't yet overcome, something that we actually talk
                  about, analyze, and explicitly learn from.</quote> There were many ways to
               approach this study: by surveying the community for whom the tools were developed; by
               surveying digital humanities centres where much (but certainly not all) of the tool
               development takes place; by questioning department chairs or tenure committee heads
               as to their perceptions on tool development as a scholarly activity and how it fits
               within the academic reward system.</p>
            <p>In the end it was decided to focus the study on developers of digital humanities
               tools: their perceptions of their work, how it fits into a structure of academic
               rewards, and the value of tool development as a scholarly pursuit. Rather than invite
               select respondents to take the survey, we decided that we would allow the field of
               respondents to self select. Notices of the survey were sent to mailing lists such as
               Humanist, the TEI list, XML4Lib, Code4Lib, and Centernet. Additionally we sent
               invitations to about two dozen people whom we knew developed tools.</p>
            <p>An initial set of questions were drawn up in autumn 2007. This was circulated to
               several prominent tool developers for feedback. The survey was refined on the basis
               of their feedback and issued to mailing lists in December 2007. By March 2008, when
               the survey closed, 54 individuals had completed it. Survey questions were grouped
               into four main categories: <hi rend="italic">Demographics</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                  >Tool Development</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Specific Tools</hi>, and <hi
                  rend="italic">Value</hi>. These categories reflected the main emphases for the
               survey — i.e., what kinds of tools were being developed and why; and specifically
               whether the process of developing tools was considered to have value to the
               developers, particularly with respect to career development and scholarship.</p>
            <p>In order to allow developers to comment on their experiences with more than one tool,
               the survey provided for demographic information to be collected once and linked to
               any number of tools developed by an individual. The survey was constructed in this
               way because we were curious as to whether developers had different experiences with
               particular tools, or whether perceptions of value would be consistent regardless of
               the type of tool developed. For the most part, developers who described experiences
               with more than one tool had similar perceptions of value regardless of the tool.</p>
            <p>There were, however, some differences, including a developer who did not feel that
               one tool developed early in his career could be categorized as a scholarly activity,
               while two others were. The <q>non-scholarly</q>
               tool was singled out as being <q>merely a response to
                  needs for workable data management, even though quite a lot of the conceptual work
                  was reused later [in the development of another tool].</q> The two tools that
               this developer considered scholarly conferred benefits to his individual research
               agenda and raised his profile in his field.</p>
            <p>We were impressed with the thoroughness with which the majority of respondents
               completed the survey. Most respondents took the time to provide lengthy answers to
               questions that demanded more than a quantifiable response (such as yes/no/maybe). As
               returns came in, however, we realized that there were several questions we did not
               ask but wish we had. One involved geographic location of the respondent. It was
               possible to extract some of this information based on IP address, but it is cruder
               than we would have liked: we know that approximately half of the respondents were in
               the United States (51%), 27% were in Europe, most of whom were in the U.K., which by
               itself accounted for 13% of all respondents, while 7% were in Canada. Another
               question we regretted not asking is what career stage the respondent was (tenured,
               tenure-track, non-tenure, etc.), although we could ascertain if respondents were
               graduate students. And lastly respondents were not asked their gender.</p>
            <p>We approached the survey with several assumptions. The results of <title
                  rend="italic">The Versioning Machine</title> survey indicated that users found
               tools valuable even if they did not use tools in the ways their developers intended
               them to be used. We also assumed that developers might be less optimistic about the
               value of tools that were not widely adopted.</p>
            <p>Survey responses did demonstrate that low adoption rates were something that
               developers felt hurt the value of their tools, but it was not their biggest concern:
               level of adoption was ranked fourth among four potential measures of a tool’s
               success. We also assumed that there might be a more negative response regarding tool
               development and career advancement. While our survey did not reveal an academia
               suddenly receptive to tool development as a scholarly activity, we were surprised at
               the relatively positive response, as well as the range of ways that developers
               articulated scholarly value in relation to tool development.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Analysis of Data</head>
            <div>
               <head>Basic Demographics</head>
               <p>There were 108 responses to the survey. Of those, 63 were complete responses — in
                  other words, all questions in the survey were completed. This represents several
                  individuals who returned multiple times to describe different tools (in total 54
                  individuals completed the survey). Of the four respondents who filled up the
                  survey multiple times, one person described six tools, two described three tools,
                  and one described two tools.</p>
               <p>Partially completed surveys that were partial because the respondent was returning
                  to discuss a second or third tool, or because the respondent had skipped a
                  question that was not relevant, were kept. Partially completed surveys in which
                  the respondent had only filled out the consent form and demographic information
                  were discarded.</p>
               <p>Forty-eight respondents answered the multiple-choice question about who they were:
                  32 respondents (67%) identified themselves as Faculty (teaching). The next highest
                  was Programmer/Developer with 6 respondents (13%). Libraries (faculty or
                  non-faculty) came in third, with 4 respondents (8%). Departmental affiliations
                  were entered by the respondent (i.e., there was no controlled vocabulary): English
                  departments were the most represented (11 respondents); Libraries and Information
                  Studies were next (eight respondents); six identified their primary affiliation as
                  a Humanities Center.</p>
               <p>Tool development was categorized in four broad areas: text analysis, authoring,
                  teaching, and visualization. Interestingly, the percentage of tools developed in
                  each category were remarkably similar.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>Responses to the question of the purpose of the tool development.</head>
                  <figDesc>Response chart for the question <q>What is
                        the purpose of the tools you have developed?</q>
                  </figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000083/resources/figure01.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Other categories that were not captured but which had more than one response were
                  database management tools, indexing tools, and archiving tools.<note>If we are to
                     do further work on this topic we would develop (or more desirably use) an
                     established vocabulary for this question.</note> Many of the tools developed by
                  practitioners in the digital humanities community are represented in the survey.
                  These include tools with <q>brand</q> names many might recognize: Hyperpo, Image
                  Markup Tool, Ivanhoe, Collex, Justa, nora, Monk, Tact, TactWeb, Tamarind, Tapor,
                  Taporware, teiPublisher, TokenX, Versioning Machine, and Zotero. It was clear that
                  frequently more than one project participant filled up the survey. Equally, many
                  respondents developed <q>unbranded tools,</q> simply describing them as scripting
                  tools, perl routines, tei stylesheets, or exercise authoring tools.</p>
               <p>This latter category seemed to the authors to be the more invisible side of tool
                  development. While branded tools frequently gain public recognition through their
                  websites, public announcements on mailing lists, conference presentations, and
                  published articles, tools developed to do particular routines or to make work
                  easier for a particular developer or project, are less frequently considered in
                  discussions in the academic system of rewards particularly to those on tenure or
                  tenure track lines.</p>
               <p>There does appear to be some correlation between branding tools and the perception
                  that tool development has contributed to career advancement. There were twenty-two
                     <q>yes</q> answers to the question, <q>Has your
                     tool development counted towards career advancement (i.e., it has counted
                     towards tenure or promotion)?</q> Of those 22, it was possible to correlate
                  18 with degree of collaboration on tool development and name or description of the
                  tool developed. Of those 18 individuals, 8 reported that they had developed tools
                  with <q>brand</q> names. Compare these numbers to those who answered <att>no</att>
                  to the career development question — out of 11 who felt that tool development had
                  not helped advance their careers, only 2 reported working on tools with <q>brand
                     names.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Our presumption going into the survey was that tool development in the Humanities
                  is an inherently collaborative activity. The results bore this out: 50.8% of
                  respondents described their collaboration as extensive. Interestingly, 15.3%
                  described collaboration from <hi rend="italic">not at all</hi> to <hi
                     rend="italic">moderately</hi> (or 1-3 on a scale of 5). In terms of whom
                  collaboration was with, 85% were with programmers, with nearly 80% of
                  collaboration with colleagues in the humanities. In one way this is not
                  surprising: a majority of humanities scholars probably need to collaborate with
                  programmers in tool development. What was unexpected was that nearly as many
                  respondents indicated that their collaboration involved humanities scholars. As
                  only 12% of respondents self-identified as programmers/developers, it seems
                  logical to presume that tool development takes place within teams in which there
                  is more than one humanities scholar.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Value and Success</head>
            <div>
               <head>Success of Tools Development Activities</head>
               <p>Overall, survey respondents responded positively regarding the success of the
                  tools they had developed. 94% of the respondents (54 of 58) said that the tool
                  they had developed still fulfilled its original purpose. A lower percentage
                  (though still a majority) reported that they considered their tool development
                  endeavors successful — 33 of 54 indicated <q>yes</q> (61%); 21 said
                     <q>somewhat</q> (39%); interestingly, not one respondent ticked the <q>no</q>
                  box. </p>
               <p>Respondents who felt their tools were successful described how they measured the
                  success from a controlled list. The highest ranked answer was <q>ability of the tool to do the job it was intended to do</q>
                  (with 96% of respondents choosing that option). The next highest option was that
                  the <q>tool enabled the respondent to further their
                     research,</q> (with 78.4% of respondents choosing that option). The lowest
                  choice, but still with a majority (52%) measured success by the <q>number of users who have adopted the tool.</q>
                  Nine respondents chose <q>other</q> and their answers tended to focus on tool
                  development as an activity that enables further research.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>Responses to the question, <q>How do you
                     measure the success of tool development activities?</q>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>Response chart for the question, <q>How do
                        you measure the success of tool development activities?</q>
                  </figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000083/resources/figure02.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Twenty-one respondents checked that their tool development was <q>somewhat
                     successful.</q> The reasons for their lack of success fit, by and large, into
                  one of three categories: lack of resources or funding (5 answers); too early in
                  development to determine success (5 answers); and the tool was somehow not
                  suitable for users — either not adopted by many users or not as useful as intended
                  (5 answers).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Relationship to Scholarship</head>
               <p>While we were interested in the value developers placed on their own tools, we
                  were also interested in how valuable they felt the development of tools was to
                  their own research and how they perceived the value placed on these activities in
                  terms of scholarship, promotion, and tenure. All of the respondents answered the
                  question, <q>Do you consider tool development a
                     scholarly activity?</q> 51 respondents, or 94%, said yes. The three
                  respondents who answered no gave these reasons: <list type="ordered">
                     <item>didn’t want to check <q>yes</q> or <q>no</q> — consider it more a service
                        activity than scholarly activity;</item>
                     <item>one respondent focused on their particular tool, which they said was only
                        a <q>response to needs for workable data
                           management</q>;</item>
                     <item>the third respondent wrote that <q>it does
                           not in itself advance scholarly knowledge; it is implicit in the word
                           ‘tool’ that its just a tool which other use to do scholarly
                           activity.</q>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>More interesting, however, were the detailed responses to the question for those
                  who answered that they derived scholarly benefit from tool development.
                  Respondents cited benefits such as a better understanding of source materials or
                  processes (11 of 51 or 21%); creating traditional intellectual output, such as
                  publications and conference papers (6 of 51, or 12%); cognitive benefits — such as
                  a better understanding of analytical methods, systematic reasoning, and <soCalled>the problem space</soCalled> (3 of 51, or 6%.) Several
                  responses clustered around the area of creativity. One of the respondents answered
                  that the tool is a community/public artwork/creative work that enables
                  interdisciplinary collaboration, while another answered that tool development
                  furthered the relations between objects, making it a playground for innovative
                  user interfaces and browsers with visualisation capacity.</p>
               <p>Two responses described deferred benefits. One simply replied, <q>Awaiting benefits.</q> Another deferred benefit
                  was tied to traditional publication: <q>None so far
                     but we will publish in journals later.</q> One respondent’s experience was
                  clearly mixed when describing the scholarly benefits derived from tool
                  development: <q>None,</q> was the reply: <q>Was never promoted and lost salary, but was amply
                     rewarded by the sales of the product.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Relationship to Career Development</head>
               <p>When asked if tool development has counted toward career advancement, respondents
                  were less certain (<emph>although more confident than our assumptions going into
                     the survey</emph>). All of the respondents answered this question: 22 (40%)
                  ticked <q>yes</q>; 18 (33%) responded <q>don’t know</q>; and 14 (26%) ticked
                     <q>no.</q> We correlated those responses with the respondents’ departmental
                  affiliations to see if patterns emerged. Of the two departments most represented
                  in the survey, those in English responded with six <q>don’t know</q>s, three
                     <q>yes</q>, and only two <q>no</q>. Library and Information Science was
                  similar, with four <q>don’t know</q>s, two <q>yes</q> and two <q>no</q>. Those who
                  identified a Humanities Center as their primary affiliation were most confident as
                  a whole, with four <q>yes</q> and one each for <q>don’t know</q> and <q>no.</q>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Responses to the question, <q>Has tool
                     developed counted towards career advancement?</q>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>Response chart for the question, <q>Has
                        tool developed counted towards career advancement?</q>
                  </figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000083/resources/figure03.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>There were several repeated themes among the 51 respondents who elaborated on
                  their answers: the most-often-cited positive responses included raising one’s
                  profile in the field; winning grant money; increasing avenues for publication and
                  presentations; gains in salary; and new job opportunities. One respondent
                  concluded that it must not have hurt as <q>I
                     continue to be gainfully employed.</q> Others were more positive: <q>It was an important part of my tenure package and
                     understood well in my department.</q>
               </p>
               <p>However, at least four respondents felt that despite the other rewards they might
                  have gained, promotion or tenure were less likely due to the inability of tenure
                  committees to properly evaluate tool development as a scholarly activity. Other
                  responses were even more succinct as to the negative impact the activity had on
                  their careers: <q>It derailed it</q>; another
                  answered, <q>For whatever reason, the University
                     never rewarded this activity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Other responses hint at the grey area that many practitioners work in — neither
                  knowing if their development activities hinders or helps: <q>I keep including tools in my professional reports, but I doubt the
                     time, intellectual investment, and impact are considered. I keep hoping for a
                     turning point . . .</q>
               </p>
               <p>Another grey area emerged from a closer examination of degree of collaboration
                  reported in the survey. The average degree of collaboration was somewhat higher
                  among respondents who reported that tool development had advanced their careers
                  than among those who reported that it hadn’t. On a scale of 1 to 5 (with 5 being
                  the highest level of collaboration) the combined average for the <q>no</q> group
                  was 3.09 while the <q>yes</q> group was 3.68. The <q>yes</q> group included 9 of
                  19 respondents reporting <q>5,</q> the highest level of collaboration, with only 2
                  reporting <q>1</q> or essentially no collaboration. In the <q>no</q> group, 4 of
                  11 respondents reported a <q>5,</q> and 3 reported <q>1</q> or no collaboration.
                  What our survey cannot tell us, however (and this may be future research), is
                  whether those who reported both a high degree of collaboration <emph>and</emph>
                  career advancement felt that their advancement stemmed from the collaborative
                  development of the tools themselves, or from single-author papers and
                  presentations that resulted from their work. In other words, is collaborative,
                  cross-disciplinary work beginning to be better recognized and rewarded in
                  disciplines that value single-author works, or are the secondary outputs of that
                  work — i.e., articles and presentations — being rewarded?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Distribution</head>
               <p>We were also interested to know what avenues were used to publicize tools and what
                  percentage of tools were developed for public use. The vast majority, 84% (48
                  responses), replied that the tools were made available to others. When asked about
                  obtaining feedback on the usefulness of the tool, as a whole, tool developers were
                  less systematic. The vast majority of respondents indicated that their main
                  mechanism for feedback was asking colleagues (86%), while 47% obtained feedback
                  via the tool website. Less than a third of the responses (31%) indicated that
                  usability studies were conducted, and even fewer, 14%, utilized surveys. Mailing
                  lists, or more specifically project mailing lists, were frequently cited as a mode
                  for obtaining feedback.</p>
               <p>Dissemination of tools was along traditional scholarly lines, with 75% responding
                  that they made their tools known via conference presentations. This was closely
                  followed by the project website (71%), with word-of mouth- dissemination at
                  conferences coming in third at 64%. Not surprisingly, Humanist was the most
                  frequently cited mailing list, with TEI-L coming in second.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>There is clearly more research that should be done into this area, from surveying
               department or tenure committee chairs as to the obstacles in considering tool
               development a scholarly activity to surveying the secondary scholarship that results
               from tool development.</p>
            <p>It is equally clear that the survey supports the findings of the reports mentioned at
               the outset of this article in that as a discipline we have considerable work to do in
               making tool development an activity that is rewarded on par with more traditional
               scholarly outputs: articles, monographs, and conference presentations.</p>
            <p>We found that tool developers, by and large, derived both personal satisfaction and
               professional recognition from their work. Sometimes this recognition translated into
               academic rewards such as promotion and tenure. But more frequently respondents wrote
               about the intellectual insights derived from their work, the new methodologies
               developed, deeper insights into their area of study and developing new models, and
               analytical methods.</p>
            <p>Equally, many respondents indicated that tool development led to more traditional
               scholarly outputs: conference papers and articles in journals (both peer-reviewed and
               non peer-reviewed). If the tool development itself was not rewarded, then these
               secondary products were.</p>
            <p>The overwhelming majority of respondents (94%) considered tool development a
               scholarly activity, although the range of responses to this question made it clear
               that many departments and institutions do not. Digital Humanities as a field has been
               pushing the boundaries of what is considered scholarship: from the creation of
               thematic research collections to e-literature. New tools that foster new insights
               into work with the ever increasing amount of digital data available to us are not a
               luxury but a necessity: who better to develop them than humanists who have both a
               knowledge of the content domain and of the content as data.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2006" label="Unsworth et al 2006" key="unsworth2006">American
               Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), <title rend="italic">Our Cultural Commonwealth:
                  The Final Report of the American Council of Learned Societies Commission on
                  Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities &amp; Social Sciences</title>, 2006, <ref
                  target="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/OurCulturalCommonwealth.pdf"
                  >http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/OurCulturalCommonwealth.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Arts and Humanities Research Council 2006" xml:id="ahrc2006" key="ahrc2006"
               >Arts and Humanities Research Council (AHRC), <title rend="italic">AHRC ICT Methods
                  Network Workgroup on Digital Tools Development for the Arts and
               Humanities</title>, 2006, <ref
                  target="http://www.methnet.ac.uk/redist/pdf/wg1report.pdf"
                  >http://www.methnet.ac.uk/redist/pdf/wg1report.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bradley2003" label="Bradley 2003" key="bradley2003">Bradley, John. <title
                  rend="quotes">Finding a Middle Ground between <q>Determinism</q> and <q>Aesthetic
                     Indeterminacy</q>: A Model for Text Analysis Tools.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 18.2 (2003):
               185-207.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kenny 1991" xml:id="kenny1991" key="kenny1991">Kenny, Anthony. <title
                  rend="quotes">Keynote Address: Technology and Humanities Research.</title> In
                  <title rend="italic">Scholarship and Technology in the Humanities: Proceedings of
                  a Conference held at Elvetham Hall, Hampshire, UK, 9th-12th May 1990</title>, ed.
               May Katzen (London: Bowker Saur, 1991), 1-10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccarty2005" label="McCarty 2005" key="mccarty2005">McCarty, Willard.
                  <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing</title>. New York: Palgrave Macmillan,
               2005.</bibl>
            <bibl label="McGann 2005" xml:id="mcgann2005" key="mcgann2005">McGann, Jerome. <title
                  rend="quotes">Culture and Technology: The Way We Live Now, What Is to Be
                  Done?</title>
               <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 36.1 (2005): 71-82.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mla2006" label="Modern Language Association of America 2006" key="MLA2006"
               >Modern Language Association of America, <title rend="italic">Report of the MLA Task
                  Force on Evaluating Scholarship for Tenure and Promotion</title>, December 2006,
                  <ref target="http://www.mla.org/tenure_promotion_pdf"
                  >http://www.mla.org/tenure_promotion_pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2005" xml:id="ramsay2005" key="ramsay2005">Ramsay, Stephen. <title
                  rend="quotes">In Praise of Pattern.</title>
               <title rend="italic">TEXT Technology</title> 14.2 (2005): 177-190.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramsay2003" label="Ramsay 2003" key="ramsay2003">Ramsay, Stephen. <title
                  rend="quotes">Reconceiving Text Analysis: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 18.2 (2003):
               167-174.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Schreibman et al. 2007b" xml:id="schreibman2007b" key="schreibman2007b"
               >Schreibman, Susan, et al. <title rend="quotes">The Versioning Machine 3.0: Lessons
                  in Open Source Software [Re]Development.</title> Poster presentation at Digital
               Humanities 2007. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dh2007/dh2007.abstracts.pdf"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dh2007/dh2007.abstracts.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Schreibman et al. 2007a" xml:id="schreibman2007a" key="schreibman2007a"
               >Schreibman, Susan and Ann Hanlon, Sean Daugherty, Tony Ross. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Versioning Machine 3.1: Lessons in Open Source [Re]Development.</title>
               Poster session at Digital Humanities (Urbana Champaign, June 2007).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="schreibman2003" label="Schreibman et al. 2003" key="schreibman2003"
               >Schreibman, Susan, Amit Kumar and Jarom McDonald. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Versioning Machine.</title> Proceedings of the 2002 ACH/ALLC Conference. <title
                  rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 18.1 (2003)
               101-107.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Summit 2005" xml:id="summit2005" key="summit2005">Summit on Digital Tools
               for the Humanities (September 28-30, 2005), <title rend="italic">Report on Summit
                  Accomplishments</title>, May 2006. <ref
                  target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/dtsummit/SummitText.pdf"
                  >http://www.iath.virginia.edu/dtsummit/SummitText.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2003" label="Unsworth 2003" key="unsworth2003">Unsworth, John.
                  <title rend="quotes">Tool-Time, or <q>Haven’t We Been Here Already?</q>: Ten Years
                  in Humanities Computing,</title> Delivered as part of Transforming Disciplines:
               The Humanities and Computer Science, Saturday, January 18, 2003, Washington, D.C.
                  <ref target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/carnegie-ninch.03.html"
                  >http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/carnegie-ninch.03.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Unsworth 2007" xml:id="unsworth2007" key="unsworth2007">Unsworth, John.
                  <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Centers as Cyberinfrastructure,</title>
               Digital Humanities Centers Summit, National Endowment for the Humanities, Washington,
               DC, Thursday, April 12, 2007, <ref
                  target="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/dhcs.html"
                  >http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/dhcs.html</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
