<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The Idiocy of the Digital Literary (and what does it have to
                    do with digital humanities)?</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sandy <dhq:family>Baldwin</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>West Virginia University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>charles.baldwin@mail.wvu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sandy Baldwin (PhD NYU) is Director of the Center for Literary Computing
                            and Associate Professor of English at West Virginia University. Baldwin
                            is the author of many essays and several book of poetic "codework," as
                            well as creator of numerous elit/new media artworks. He is editor and
                            publisher of the Computing Literature book series and Executive Editor
                            of the journal <title rend="italic">electronic book review</title>. His
                            projects as CLC director include scholarship on massive multiplayer
                            games, explorations of creativity and new media, and leading the
                            Consortium for Electronic Literature project developing a metadata
                            standard for works of electronic literature.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000155</idno>
                <idno type="volume">007</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2013-07-01">1 July 2013</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="JHF">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>What does the category of the literary give to digital humanities? Nothing and
                    everything. This essay considers the "idiocy" of the literary: its unaccountable
                    singularity, which guarantees that we continue to return to it as a source,
                    inspiration, and challenge. As a consequence, digital humanities is inspired and
                    irritated by the literary. </p>
                <p> My essay shows this in three ways. First, through a speculative exploration of
                    the relation between digital humanities and the category of "the literary."
                    Second, through a quick survey of the use of literature in digital humanities
                    project. Thirdly, through a specific examination of TEI and character rendering
                    as digital humanities concerns that necessarily engage with the literary. Once
                    again, the literary remains singular and not abstract, literal in a way that
                    challenges and provokes us towards new digital humanities work.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>The Idiocy of the Digital Literary is not concerned with how digital humanities
                    handles literary content, but rather with how the literary is both resisted and
                    needed by digital humanities.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head> The Category of the Literary and the Essence of Digital Humanities, or Some
                    Notes on the Context of My Essay for <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>
                </head>
                <p>Literary criticism says nothing about the category of the literary. It describes
                    literary works and makes distinctions between them <emph>because</emph> they are
                    literary. A novel or poem may be good or bad, but it is a subject of criticism
                    because it is literary.</p>
                <p>I assert this categorically. You may disagree. You may say that literary
                    criticism’s distinction-making criteria are criteria about the literary. True
                    enough. Criticism is the application of these criteria. True enough as well that
                    the history of literature is tracked by the history of criticism and by the
                    revision and renovation of the criteria involved. In short, I am not asserting
                    that the literary criticism does not deal with literature. Clearly it does. It
                    knows precisely what literature is and addresses it as such. But still, none of
                    this, none of literary criticism, says anything about the literary. We all know
                    the complexity and extent of the set of critical classifications and theories
                    applied to literature. Knowing this makes us good literary critics but does not
                    equip us to consider the literary. The self-evidence of literature – the
                    given-ness that there are works of literature – makes literary criticism the
                    worst way to consider the literary.</p>
                <p>What is the literary? What is its existence, occurrence, and condition? I find
                    this very hard to answer, but at least I make an attempt, which makes my work
                    not or no longer literary criticism. For literary criticism, the literary is
                    precisely a category, as announced in the call for papers for this special issue
                    of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, inviting <q>essays that consider the study of literature and
                        the category of the literary to be an essential part of the digital
                        humanities.</q> I was asked to comment on the form of my essay
                    contribution. In particular: why did I write it in the form I did, and not in
                    literary critical form? The question was put to me and I am happy to respond,
                    though the response will no doubt only deepen the question. The simplest
                    response is that I took the question literally, or at least part of it: I
                    focused on the <q>category of the literary</q>
                    as an <q>essential part of the digital
                        humanities.</q> You might respond in turn that I took this <emph>too
                        literally</emph>, that what was asked for was some description of digital
                    humanities projects that adopt a more creative and thus
                        <soCalled>literary</soCalled> approach, or a reading of precedents for
                    digital humanities in literary works, or a survey of the advanced status of
                    studying literary works as the content of digital humanities projects. All this
                    is not a bad response on your part, though I am left with the simple
                    counter-response that <emph>taking it literally</emph> is exactly the
                    consideration needed for understanding the category of the literary. Is not the
                    reading of a text that is swept away by the literal, one that is taken in by
                    words that state the impossible or the fictional, is this not precisely
                        <emph>too literal</emph> and <emph>literary</emph>? Is not the idiotic focus
                    on the words precisely the literary?</p>
                <p>N. Katherine Hayles’ benchmark study <title rend="italic">Electronic
                        Literature</title> is subtitled <title rend="italic">New Horizons for the
                        Literary</title>. Given this, one would think that the book would deal with
                        <soCalled>the literary.</soCalled> The burden of Hayles’ argument is that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2008">electronic literature can be
                            understood both as partaking of literary tradition and introducing
                            crucial transformations to redefine what literature is</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayles2008" loc="3"/>
                    </cit>. What the book repeatedly refers to as <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2008"
                        >the category of the literary</quote> is tied to this both/and, a category
                    both in tradition and redefining it. The term <q>horizon</q> is complicated as well. It invokes phenomenology and its
                    concern with the given. Horizon implies a permeable boundary. On the horizon,
                    objects stand out and are perceived, as the sun does as it sets on the horizon,
                    but the horizon is also a threshold to another space beyond perception. As a
                    horizon, electronic literature lets us perceive the literary with a particular
                    intensity but also forces the question of the boundaries or boundlessness of the
                    literary.</p>
                <p>So far, so good. But Hayles does not deal with the literary in this book, at
                    least not in any direct way. On the page following the quote above, she offers a
                    provisional definition of the literary as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2008">creative artworks that interrogate
                            the histories, contexts, and productions of literature, including as
                            well the verbal art of literature proper</quote>
                        <ptr loc="4" target="#hayles2008"/>
                    </cit>. Perhaps it is odd that the promised definition is a list of attributes
                    of a certain kind of creative artwork. The definition is no definition of the
                    category but a description of elements that fall within it. Perhaps this is not
                    so odd and perhaps the literary can only be defined by such a lateral
                    approach.</p>
                <p>It easy enough to show that any and all <q>creative
                        artworks</q> – any one, all of them, you name it – interrogate <q>the histories, contexts, and productions of
                        literature, including as well the verbal art of literature proper.</q>
                    The premise of literary criticism is that works offer this evidence and there is
                    no literary work that does not offer at least the minimum of such interrogation.
                    The literary in this definition is exactly a category: the definition says
                        <q>there is literature.</q> In the end, Hayles can say nothing about the
                    literary. But then, her book is a work of literary criticism (simply look at the
                    publisher’s label on the back cover, not to mention the overall technique of the
                    book). Hayles’ definition of the literary re-asserts the self-evidence that
                    there are works of literature.</p>
                <p>When I situated my essay in what I termed the <emph>idiocy</emph> of digital
                    humanities, I was not simply or only trying to be provocative or playful. Such a
                    naïve position was my best attempt to displace more than twenty-five years of
                    training as a literary critic. To focus on the literary requires a disinvestment
                    in the task and vocation of the critic. The same applies to the digital
                    humanist, insofar as that task and vocation recapitulates epistemic commitments
                    to critical monuments and methods. As I show in my essay, the literary is
                    announced and invoked whenever digital humanities is described. The literary is
                    inscribed in the natural history of digital humanities.</p>
                <p>In a similar way, the adaption of information theory to texts can set literature
                    in the circuit of information but can say nothing of the literary. At best, it
                    offers compromises such as a <soCalled>code</soCalled> of the literary added on
                    to the other semiotic codes. Yet the place or event of the literary may be the
                    opening and condition of information. My essay briefly addresses Roman
                    Jakobson’s use of information theory in distinguishing the poetic code (which
                    functions as a useful though problematic synonym for the literary). Claude
                    Shannon’s work, the first work of information theory, is complex and would need
                    to be dealt with at length elsewhere. On the one hand, literature has no place
                    in his mathematical model. On the other hand, it functions as a differentiating
                    example of extreme information. The most sophisticated contemporary version of
                    such a communications-based approach is Philippe Bootz’s account of the
                    communication situation of electronic textuality and authorship. As Bootz
                    quickly pointed out to me in personal conversation, his model is equally suited
                    to describing literature as it is to any other text, but for this reason has no
                    theory of the literary.</p>
                <p>The convergence of literary criticism and information theory repeats and does not
                    resolve the question of the category of the literary. To consider the
                        <term>category of the literary</term> may require turning away from
                    literature. In fact, this is precisely the astute claim in the call for papers
                    for this special issue: essays that consider <q>the category of the literary to be an essential part of the digital
                        humanities.</q> This medial — or perhaps better and more McCluhanesque,
                    rear-view medial — appearance of the literary clarifies the category by
                    situating it elsewhere and, in doing so, burns away the self-evidence and
                        <soCalled>naturalness</soCalled> of literature.</p>
                <p>
                    <soCalled>Category</soCalled> is notoriously difficult to categorize. I will
                    only mention the major points involved. In philosophy, the Aristotelian concern
                    with categories as the many ways being is given is not compatible with
                    mathematical category theory that deals with transformations of objects. As a
                    term, category involves foundational problems within disciplines. There is no
                    easy way to arbitrate these disputes and define the term across disciplines, no
                    easy way to define the category category. I am not being obscure or playful:
                    this is obvious, an obvious aspect of the term category. In fact,
                        <soCalled>obviousness</soCalled> is part of what a category is.</p>
                <p>Category names a class of things. It deals with things within this class in the
                    most general possible terms. Mathematically this generality may be qualified as
                    isomorphic relations and philosophically as ways of given-ness. Because of this
                    generality, a category <soCalled>names</soCalled>  in a logical and existential
                    way. A category is not simply a name in the sense of an arbitrary and contingent
                    choice of language applied to a thing. No, category extends and exhausts the
                    thing it names in naming it. A category extends the thing that it names because
                    the term (the category) is the most general possible name for the thing. And it
                    exhausts naming through this same generality. It announces what can be said of
                    the thing.</p>
                <p>My idiotic take on literary criticism shows the extension and the exhaustion of
                    the category of the literary in the announcement that there is literature.
                    Literary criticism can say no more about the category of the literary. But this
                    does not mean there can be no category theory, no understanding of the
                    transformations involving the literary as it announces itself.</p>
                <p>My essay submission to the special issue concludes with a rudimentary attempt at
                    such an understanding. It is equally an attempt to consider the category of the
                    literary as an essential part of digital humanities. Simply put: I show that
                        <emph>the literary as a category</emph> is the differentiating momentum that
                    enables something like digital humanities to take place. I write <q>something like</q> because the literary as an
                    essential part of digital humanities makes digital humanities never entirely
                    itself, always inhabited by this other part, by literalness at its essence, by
                    the transformation enacted by the literary on the digital. In the same way, I
                    write <q>take place</q> because the literary
                    is an event that occupies digital humanities and that digital humanities needs
                    in order to exist.</p>
                <p>It is the question of the literary, literally of the letter on the screen, that I
                    consider the essential part of digital humanities. What an idiotic part it is! I
                    underline and insist on a chiasm that separates matter and conceptuality,
                    appearance and abstraction. In this chiasm, the digital letter is both literal
                    and figurative. It is, in short, literary. Not only this, but the letter is
                    poetic. It produces the system that will enable digital humanities. The
                    resulting conditions for codes (for Unicode, in the case of my essay), for
                    storage, for processing, and so on, are produced poetically from the literary,
                    that is, from the letter as the given-ness of a category, as an announcement
                    that extends itself and exhausts itself in doing so.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> The Idiocy of the Digital Literary (and what does it have to do with digital
                    humanities?) </head>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">... literature begins at the moment when
                            literature becomes a question.</quote>
                        <bibl>Maurice Blanchot</bibl>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Literature is debugged.</quote>
                        <bibl>Ted Nelson</bibl>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">I can't seem to speak / the
                            language.</quote>
                        <bibl>Iggy Pop</bibl>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p>How can we discuss the literary in digital humanities? I will do so in three
                    ways. </p>
                <p>First, through an <soCalled>idiotic</soCalled> text. By this, I mean a
                    speculative meditation, setting out questions and propositions on the relation
                    of digital humanities to the concept of the literary.</p>
                <p>Second, through a more explicit reading of the place of literature in the current
                    state of the field of digital humanities. I survey digital humanities projects,
                    the place of digital humanities in the press, and the way the field defines
                    itself.</p>
                <p>Third, through an examination of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) as a site of
                    what I call the idiocy of the digital literary. I argue that text encoding
                    engages in the problematic, non-conceptual, differentiating momentum of the
                    literary through the literal mark of character rendering.</p>

                <div>
                    <head> I. Idiocy </head>

                    <p>I almost wrote <q>the idiot of digital literature</q> in the title of this
                        essay. Idiot that I am, I ask: is not such a slip of the pen, the wrong word
                        on the page, or the wrong fingers on the wrong keys, is not such an
                            <emph>almost written</emph> and <emph>almost taking place</emph>
                        precisely the domain of the literary? Or equally literary: the right words
                        and the right keys, the pen in exactly the right place, and yet still a
                        slippage in precisely this, <emph>an almost not taking place yet written
                            down</emph>. How can you know? What is the <emph>literary
                            literally</emph>? The otherness of the literary is inextricable from
                            <q>it could be otherwise,</q> subject to Theodor Adorno's judgment in
                        the essay <title rend="quotes">Commitment</title> on the work of art as
                        entirely artificial and constructed artifact, as <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#adorno1992">instructions for the praxis
                                they refrain from: the production of life lived as it ought to
                                be</quote>
                            <ptr target="#adorno1992" loc="93"/>
                        </cit>. </p>
                    <p>(I wonder: how can digital humanities deal with the <emph>almost
                            written</emph> and the <emph>almost taking place</emph> or <emph>almost
                            not taking place yet written down</emph>? I find nothing in digital
                        humanities – even amidst the poetic turns and explorations of figurality –
                        that engages with this potentiality of the literary.)</p>
                    <p>The idiot of digital literature: would this not be a way of entitling myself?
                        Are not all titles, of and in whatever genre, to a greater or lesser degree
                            <soCalled>signed</soCalled> by the author? As in <title rend="italic"
                            >TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange by the
                            TEI Consortium Originally edited by C.M. Sperberg-McQueen and Lou
                            Burnard for the ACH-ALLC-ACL Text Encoding Initiative Now entirely
                            revised and expanded under the supervision of the Technical Council of
                            the TEI Consortium</title>? All this appears on the front matter of the
                        TEI P5 Guidelines. I admit that I am unclear and cannot discern or read
                        whether this is a single title, a title with authorship attributions, or if
                        it is several titles, or partially not a title (or something else)? Or is
                        such a question of the author's name really only the case within a certain
                        kind of very literary author function? Is this only the case for literary
                        works, where a title adheres to the writer's name? As in: Shakespeare's
                            <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> or Mark Twain's <title rend="italic"
                            >Huck Finn</title>? But it is this very particular and very literary
                        effect that interests me when it comes to examining the literary in digital
                        humanities: this stickiness of the name, this effect of reference in the
                        formal feature of the title. The most unreadable scrap of text is signed by
                        its author, and this is part of what qualifies it as literary. </p>
                    <p>In this sense, <soCalled>the idiocy of digital
                            literature</soCalled> is named for me; I am announcing myself as the idiot.
                        Such abjection is strategic, of course. Here are my strategies: I mean to
                        use <soCalled>idiot</soCalled> in the ancient Greek sense of an individual,
                        an ordinary person, a non-professional person, a private person. Towards
                        this, my inquiry poses simplistic and particular questions about digital
                        humanities projects, about popular accounts of digital humanities, about
                        historical affinities between digital humanities and literary studies, and
                        about core protocols of digital humanities. </p>
                    <p>But also, I mean to bring to digital humanities a sense of the idiot in the
                        Dostoyevskian or Sartrean sense of saintliness through naive questioning. Or
                        even the Iggy Poppian sense of the idiot, bringing a bit of snarling
                        punkiness to digital humanities. At the least, this is a question of style,
                        of an inquiry wandering in and out of the space of academic discourse. </p>
                    <p>Finally, and most particularly, I mean idiocy in the sense that Clément
                        Rosset wrote of <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#rosset1989">the idiocy of the real</quote>
                            <ptr target="#rosset1989" loc="111"/>
                        </cit>. Idiocy as inescapable and yet obdurate; as singular, immediate, and
                        useless. Idiocy as a <emph>passion</emph> for reality. I find this passion
                        in characters on the screen, in the literalness of what the computers
                        displays, and in the way this literal is played out in digital humanities
                        practices. Is this passion not a description of the literary?</p>
                    <p>In what follows, I ask idiotic questions of digital humanities, seeking the
                        occluded but productive literary core of this field. At first glance, this
                        still-emerging field is systematized around <foreign>a priori</foreign> sets
                        of categories for objects and discourses that presume literature without the
                        literary. By this, I mean <emph>the literary</emph> to signify a domain of
                        excess and difference that is institutionalized as creativity or innovation.
                        At the least, digital humanities is uncomfortable with this sense of the
                        literary. Digital humanities handles and presents this domain but, at least
                        explicitly, does not participate in it. It assumes the productivity or
                        poetics of the literary, and builds on this assumption. One might say: it
                        follows the trajectory of the literary but is not literary itself. It
                        insists that it is methodological. Such insistence lets digital humanities
                        operate on and make a <emph>project</emph> out of the literary. </p>
                    <p>By literary, I also refer to the legal norms of an archivable work with an
                        author, as well as the modern profession that this work implies. Digital
                        humanities is expert at dealing with the literary in this sense. It employs
                        diverse, complex methods and means of studying literature. To be clear:
                        literature is not (and never was) literary, and for this reason literature
                        can be a subject of digital humanities. Literature is a noun, literary an
                        adjective. Literature is a work and an archive, literary an activity and
                        process. <emph>Literature is not literary</emph> first means that the
                        institution of literature is bereft of the literary. Every work of
                        literature can be said to cite the literary but any account of it (the
                        literary) falls short: it locates it in this or that feature, this or that
                        theory, which is not the literary but a particular formalism, a form that is
                        repeatable and extractable from the text (by definition). </p>
                    <p>
                        <emph>Literature is bereft of the literary</emph> means literature refers
                        to, tells the story of the literary. Literature is the institutional memory
                        of the literary. Literature means the literary has left the building.
                        Literature can be a subject of digital humanities for this reason, but the
                        literary cannot. The many monuments of the digital humanities canon already
                        include archives and tools built around literature but not around the
                        literary. Can we imagine a meta-digital humanities on the literary? We
                        cannot. Not in any current imagining of digital humanities, not without
                        rethinking both the digital and the humanities. </p>
                    <p>This is demonstrably true both in the large scale configuration of the
                        digital humanities — such as the mission and practice of the National
                        Endowment for the Humanities Office of Digital Humanities — and in
                        paradigmatic digital humanities literature projects, such as those developed
                        and exhibited at sites such as Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                        Humanities at University of Virginia (IATH) and the Maryland Institute for
                        Technology in the Humanities at University of Maryland (MITH). My strategy
                        is to invert the problematic to ask: what is literary about digital
                        humanities? What if digital humanities is a <soCalled>field</soCalled> only
                        in that it is literary?<note>The discourse field of the digital text is
                            operational and methodological (terms I see as consonant with the
                            pragmatic claims of digital humanities), or closed and functional (in a
                            more <soCalled>systems-like</soCalled> terminology), through flows of
                            materiality and interiority — or more strictly, through the interior of
                            bodies — that are neither included nor excluded but maintained, held,
                            surviving in the discrete sign of the text, surviving as a kind of
                            pseudo-reference or <q>overextended
                                transcendence</q> (in Benjaminian terms) —
                                <emph>overextended</emph> because we are always left with the ruins
                            and not the transcendence. Such a survival text is one way of thinking
                            about the literary. </note> Digital humanities may take on or remediate
                        a poetic function in its premises and claims, but this function is the
                        outcome of the literary and not literary itself. Models of a discrete domain
                        of <emph>the literary</emph>, particularly Jakobson’s <q>defamiliarization</q> – though Fry’s <q>non-construction</q> would be equally
                        applicable – repeat and extend rather than resolve the problem of situating
                        the literary vis a vis digital humanities.<note>The conjunction of
                            Jakobson’s <q>poetic</q> and its
                            relation to information theory is nothing new, and is in fact explicit
                            on Jakobson’s part. My point is simply the way this function reacts to
                            the literary, handles and contains it without addressing it. This legacy
                            of the literary as defamiliarization continues in critics of electronic
                            literature such as Nick Montfort and Scott Rettberg. </note> In the end,
                        I turn to text and character encoding as fictional sites of the trajectory
                        of the <soCalled>character</soCalled> and the mis-directed wandering of the
                        literary mark. The character is one direction for reading the singularity of
                        the literary in the digital humanities. I return to the digital humanities
                        with an understanding of the literary in its projects, but — unfortunately —
                        with no proposal for reconciling the system of digital humanities with the
                        singularity of the literary.</p>
                    <p>A bit more on the <emph>passion</emph> of the digital literary. It is a
                        matter of characters on the screen. My problem is: should I read or should I
                        look? I look at the screen — which one? this one, every one? — and see
                        characters turning to images, characters destined for figural and literary,
                        and not communicative, ends. In short, I see only mojibake. If you read in
                        Wikipedia or elsewhere you learn that mojibake refers to incorrectly
                        rendered characters, a case where the characters in a computer document are
                        incorrectly tagged, or where the system displaying the characters does not
                        support the encoding, and the resulting display or rendering is described as
                        incorrect and as gibberish. Similar terms deal with the concept in other
                        languages, but the Japanese <soCalled>mojibake</soCalled> sticks, seemingly
                        for the proximity of the pictoriality of the problem and of Japanese
                        graphemes; and for the exoticism involved, the suggestion of the problem as
                        fundamentally other. Mojibake is a problem of interoperability, a breakdown
                        of a system intended to encode, decode, represent, and display every
                        possible character. A breakdown, therefore, in a universal system of
                        communication based on direct and correct presentation of characters. In the
                        breakdown, the display does something else. It fails in its universality and
                        interoperability, and in failing produces an image or set of images.</p>
                    <p>I feel unclear and idiotic on the notion of incorrect character encoding. I
                        look at a screen and it may appear beautiful, it may appear horrendous, it
                        appears in many ways, and — idiot that I am — I find it difficult or
                        impossible to insist that a display is <emph>correct</emph> or not. I insist
                        that no method can account for what the screen displays. Let me add: I
                        worked hard to arrive at this insistence. It is the same way that I find (or
                        seek to find) it impossible to distinguish any writing on the net from
                            spam.<note>I do not see this problematic as specific to writing on the
                            net, but I would say that the net involves a different or new protocol
                            for recognition, a different culture of the discrete sign. Writing
                            implies networking. Even more: any <soCalled>literary</soCalled>
                            perspective on writing cannot distinguish print or digital writing; such
                            perspective is idiotic, addressing the body and the other in the
                            writing, in the discrete text, without regard to the medium and the
                            message (the <soCalled>literary</soCalled> is the flow, the light
                            writing McLuhan describes that is a medium without a message, or that is
                                <q>to read what was never
                                written</q> in Benjamin’s sense). </note> In the face of a
                        universal and interoperable technics of the written character, all writing
                        is spam and all characters mojibake. It seems to me that correctness in
                        rendering is not self-evident but partakes of the same desires for universal
                        interoperability as digital humanities: to move from displays and images to
                        abstraction and knowledge, to make everything into <emph>projects</emph>
                        (fundable, publishable, tenurable, etc.).<note>Consider Roland Barthes on
                                <title rend="quotes">Typos</title>: <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#barthes1977">To type: no traces:
                                    nothing exists, and then all of a sudden the word is there: no
                                    approximation, no <emph>production</emph>; there is no birth of
                                    the letter, but the expulsion of a little scrap of code. Typos
                                    are therefore very special: faults of essence: mistaking the
                                    keys, I attack the system at its heart; the typo is never vague,
                                    indecipherable, but a legible mistake, a meaning. However, my
                                    whole body enters into these code mistakes.</quote>
                                <ptr target="#barthes1977" loc="96–97"/>
                            </cit>. </note> Is any project possible without correct character
                        rendering?</p>
                    <p>I started with the question of <q>should I read.</q> I could add,
                            <emph>should I write</emph>: What if characters displayed or rendered on
                        screen are not read; instead, they matter, precisely in the way literature
                        matters? Every <emph>should I?</emph> and every <emph>I should</emph> is a
                        literary question, a question of permission and of otherness. <soCalled>The
                            literary</soCalled> is and must be asserted and discovered. The ethical
                            <emph>should</emph> is inextricable from the literary and remains
                        secreted in the digital. The matter of characters displayed or rendered on
                        screen is intensely human and humanistic, an intensity that goes to that
                        last paragraph of Adorno's <title rend="italic">Aesthetic Theory</title>,
                        which tells of the suffering that is art’s <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#adorno1997">expression and which forms its
                                substance. This suffering is the humane content that unfreedom
                                counterfeits as positivity</quote>
                            <ptr loc="260" target="#adorno1997"/>
                        </cit>. What if the positivity of the character displayed or rendered, their
                        thingness, is the intensification of the world's suffering? Even in the most
                        incorrectly rendered characters? <emph>The literariness of the digital as
                            this expression</emph>. What if? Keep in mind that every <q>what if</q>
                        is also a literary question, a question of latency of the world, and of the
                        poetics or productive latency of the world’s narrativity. </p>
                    <p>I should write of <emph>rendering</emph>, as in rendering characters on the
                        screen. To <soCalled>render</soCalled> is to express, to represent, to give,
                        to produce, to surrender, to narrate, to vomit, to melt down and clarify the
                        fat from an animal, and to extract by means of heating. The last brings us
                        back to the phenomenology of characters, as inscribed intentional glyphs,
                        however technically occluded the agency and pragmatics of intentionality; as
                        surfaces intensified through graphematic marking; and as necessarily given
                        to the eyes for reading subjects, however distant and mechanized those
                        readers may be. In other words, rendering brings me to an organic
                        continuity, an epigenetic landscape of the organism within the technical
                        display, a flesh infrastructure. And to narrate: every rendering is a tale,
                        a story of the flesh. All this is found in the <emph>problem</emph> of
                        literature.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>II. Digital and Literary </head>
                    <p>The passion and problem of the literary takes place today in digital
                        humanities. If digital humanities exists — I am not sure it does, though I
                        wish it did for the possibility of what it might be but is not yet — if it
                        exists, it is as a miasma or screen covering deep desires and even deeper
                        problems. It certainly would not be what it purports to be now: a set of
                        tutorials for the latest tools. If it existed, it would deepen the desire
                        and the problematic, and name both clearly: the name of the desire and the
                        problem is <emph>literature</emph>.</p>
                    <p>First the miasma. <soCalled>Digital</soCalled> is a widely used term that
                        remains loosely defined in principle and clarified as needed in practice.
                        Since digital humanities claims to be a method or set of methods, it implies
                        clarity and definition (just look at the many articles staking positions on
                            <q>what is digital humanities</q>). Fortunately, there is a clear one:
                            <soCalled>digital</soCalled> is defined as dealing with discrete
                        information and the processes around the storage, transmission, and
                        reception of such information. The definition is self-referential, since the
                        modern understanding of information following Claude Shannon is premised on
                        the discrete. To write <soCalled>information</soCalled> is necessarily to
                        engage with the digital.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately, the vast majority of digital humanities projects in no way
                        require digital information. They are not digital in any significant or
                        necessary way. I will make this case with several arguments, some better and
                        some worse. I see these arguments as obvious, even idiotic. Let me be clear:
                        as I claim below, protocols and standards such as the Text Encoding
                        Initiative (TEI) do engage with the digitalization of text, and do so
                        precisely as a displaced engagement with the literary, but in ways intended
                        to lead to projects that, as <soCalled>projects</soCalled> (or intentional
                        works), are not digital. I argue idiotically, two incompatible positions:
                        digital humanities is not at all digital and only exists as a warmed over
                        version of the institution of literary criticism; and if digital humanities
                        is in fact digital, it is only because it is focused on the problem of the
                        literary (and not on the institution of literary criticism). A program is at
                        work here, a tropology of inscription and displacement. The several
                        arguments I offer separate <emph>projects</emph> from <emph>encoding
                            practices</emph> to focus on the poetic core of digital humanities, a
                        core that is the contained and muted (discrete) problematic of the
                            literary.<note>I should add that others offer better articulations of
                            this critique (for example, see Alan Sondheim on the digital, and
                            Florian Cramer's writings in general). </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As a start, you must admit that the broad field of visualization and
                        multimedia presentations — undoubtedly useful re-imaginings of humanities
                        work beyond the page and book, and the examples most vividly invoked in
                        popular accounts of digital humanities in the <title rend="italic">New York
                            Times</title> or elsewhere — do not <emph>require</emph> a computer. Or,
                        if we (you and I) insist on the computer in this case, it is for its ability
                        to display many media forms, no doubt an ability enhanced by flexible
                        digital storage and processing, but an enhancement and ability not in any
                        way impossible without such storage and processing. If I create a humanities
                        project with paper, with images cut out of magazines, with film, with
                        cassette tapes, the result may be retro but is not in any substantial way
                        different from what appears on my computer. Digital humanities projects are
                        undeniably prettier and more exciting than the paper and scotch tape project
                        I described. (Is that what we mean when we say it is an exciting new field?
                        Digital humanities is pretty humanities?) Let me add: I see nothing wrong
                        with this, as long as we come clean and admit it.</p>
                    <p>Social media or crowdsourced or semantic web projects are no better. If we
                        grant that such Web 2.0 concepts differ from Web 1.0, and this is not
                        self-evident, it must also be granted and truly self-evident that these
                        again do not require digital information. Crowdsourcing is perfectly
                        implementable outside of and prior to digital encoding, as are
                            <soCalled>friends</soCalled> of various sorts. Even more: the very
                        impulse to recreate a social network in <soCalled>digital media</soCalled>
                        seeks out and leverages not <soCalled>the digital</soCalled> but the hiding
                        of the digital aspects of the medium. Visualizing a social network uses the
                        computer as a medium to picture relationships that are not digital. Such
                        applications go to great effort <emph>not</emph> to be
                            <soCalled>digital.</soCalled>
                    </p>
                    <p>Things are equally vague with the seemingly similar notion that digital
                        humanities involve humanities <soCalled>beyond print.</soCalled> This is a
                        repetition of arguments such as Marshall McLuhan's in <title rend="italic"
                            >The Gutenberg Galaxy</title> and also does not relate to digital
                        encoding. This <soCalled>beyond</soCalled> could be addressed in terms of
                        radio, film, and so on. This is not to say that computers do not fit in the
                        sequence of media moving beyond the printed page, but the computer fits in a
                        sequence of <emph>media</emph> and not of analog to digital encoding. Or
                        rather: the new threshold of media using digital encoding would be part of
                        the trajectory of media described by McLuhan. We should talk of media
                        humanities.</p>
                    <p>What exactly do we get in insisting that this work is digital? The work under
                        consideration is certainly displayed on computers and using new media
                        devices, but such devices are not <soCalled>digital.</soCalled> The phrase
                            <soCalled>digital media</soCalled> seems to describe the computer, but
                        that object is plastic and wires, glass and tubing, and only the data stored
                        in it can be called digital. Digital data could just as well be stored and
                        computed in other devices, including abacuses and fingers (i.e. digits).
                            <emph>Digital</emph> refers to the domain of the discrete and
                        computable, but it does not equal a computer. Discrete computation can be on
                        paper, and indeed the characters we use for writing and enumeration are
                        already discrete elements. A computer can just as well be implemented out of
                        Twinkies or rocks, Lincoln Logs or atomic particles. To speak of
                            <soCalled>digital media</soCalled> or <soCalled>digital
                            technologies</soCalled> is to refer to the fact that such media or
                        technologies encode or carry digitally encoded information. We easily move
                        from this to the medium itself through a synecdochal rhetorical trick, the
                        encoding extended to the whole, moving from digitally-processed information
                        to the content and semantics of that information, as if the fact of the
                        encoding spread across the whole, allowing for a marketing style boosterism
                        of the all that takes place on the computer as <soCalled>digital,</soCalled>
                        a labeling that suggest a novelty and innovation that is not evident but is
                        everywhere.</p>
                    <p>At this point, you may be annoyed or even infuriated, and you may insist that
                        it is clear that the powers of display, transmission, storage, and so on,
                        associated with these media only became possible with the development of
                        digital information processing. Perhaps, but such a counter-argument means
                        we deal with by-products of media using digital encoding, and not with
                        discrete digital processing. The speed, storage, and so on are part of a
                        lengthy history of speeding up, a <q>logistics
                            of perception,</q> in Paul Virilio's useful phrase, of which
                        computers with their digital encodings are only the latest version. Such a
                        history could be centered on the discrete mark, on the digital as a
                        long-range phenomenon. Any such explanation must recognize a shift in
                        literacy that includes the impact of television, film, paperbacks, the
                        printed book, and — why not — papyrus. We might be better to speak of modern
                        humanities or faster humanities, or anything but digital humanities. Perhaps
                        we should talk simply of <emph>humanities</emph>, since this speeding up is
                        part of the era of knowledge that makes humanities possible. Or, in a
                        rigorous move, cast the digital back into the fundamentals of discrete
                        elements (e.g. Stiegler 2009). This is a persuasive but complex argument,
                        and destroys <soCalled>digital humanities</soCalled> as an emerging field.
                        Television, film, print, papyrus, all are digital, taking us into the very
                        fact of the graphic mark as digital, to arrive at the question of the
                        letter, that is, of the literary. </p>
                    <p>If the majority of digital humanities projects are not digital, arguably what
                        remains is a minority of projects that are digital but are not humanistic.
                        The use of computational models such as hidden Markov chains, Backus-Naur
                        forms, rewriting systems, and so on, can treat humanities materials as
                        formal languages in the computer science sense. The premise of discrete
                        alphabets of digital characters is precisely the condition of such
                        languages. </p>
                    <p>I will deal with these models elsewhere, but I argue that encoding practices
                        such as TEI are ways of treating text as aggregates of discrete characters.
                        Character encoding builds on the already discrete qualities of written
                        traces, and in a way that poetically extends the non-identity of these
                        qualities and the literariness of the inscribed mark. Early discussions of
                        the roots or fundaments of language focused on
                            <soCalled>stochoie,</soCalled> which Max Müller described as degrees or
                        steps making up a whole. The term came from physics, naming basic elements
                        of nature, but was applied to the letter of the alphabet by the Greeks. In
                        Latin it was translated as <soCalled>littera</soCalled> or letter. As I will
                        elaborate below and elsewhere, formal languages and encoding are engaged
                        with that long history of the literal, a history inextricable from a
                        material and prosthetic exteriorization. At which point the humanities no
                        longer deal with human utterance and expression, even if such applications
                        are applied to the archived traces of natural language. </p>
                    <p>Let me consider, secondly, in what ways digital humanities <emph>is</emph>
                        literary. It is hard to know how to begin to answer this question, given the
                        still uncertain status of digital humanities. The 2011 conference at
                        Stanford billed itself as <soCalled>Big Tent Digital Humanities,</soCalled>
                        emphasizing heterogeneity and lack of a single method or view. I began
                        earlier with the literariness of the act of naming, and <soCalled>Big Tent
                            Digital Humanities</soCalled> said almost too much by publicly airing
                        the problem and poetics at the core of digital humanities. As a phrase
                        referring to political gatherings where participants forsake their
                        philosophies for the sake of the overall movement, the ideological
                        concealment of <soCalled>big tent</soCalled> is perfect. (Think of the
                        connotations: the carnival, the religious gathering, the Sunday picnic, and
                        so on.) The fuzziness at the core is both a problem and the true method of
                        digital humanities. A program is at work, or is executed, in the broadly
                        sketched opposition between the chatter and glamour of digital media as
                        faster and pretty forms of humanities projects, on the one hand, and the
                        inhuman calculability of formal language, on the other. The digital is a
                        poetic tropology posited at the core of digital humanities: on the one hand,
                        encoded information paratactically referenced in screen outcomes; on the
                        other, deep computational structures beyond human comprehension. This
                        spectrum is the occluded problematic of the literary. There appears to be a
                            <soCalled>field</soCalled> of digital humanities, given the availability
                        of project and infrastructure funding, such as the vanguard NEH program of
                        Digital Humanities Start-Up grants; the establishment of an essential
                        journal such as <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>;
                        and the many job offerings now featured in the Chronicle of Higher Education
                        (at the same time as openings in other fields dwindle). Of course, remarking
                        on this rapidly developing yet unclarified and uncodified state of digital
                        humanities is itself part of the self-understanding and heroic emergence
                        narrative of the field: to discuss it is to comment on its newness and
                        innovation.</p>
                    <p>At first glance, there is little literature in digital humanities. Consider
                        the showcase NEH Start-Up grants. A search done in early October 2011 of
                        grants awarded by this program finds that out of 251 funded projects, the
                        keyword <soCalled>literature</soCalled> appears less than ten percent of the
                        time (16 times) and <soCalled>literary</soCalled> even more seldom (13
                        times). When these terms are used, literature refers to a disciplinary
                        rubric (a project might appeal to <soCalled>literary scholars</soCalled>) or
                        to generic distinctions for identifying certain types of texts as literary
                        texts, (e.g. as verse or as a novel). These distinctions are then typically
                        opposed to other clearly demarcated classes of scholar and text, such as
                            <soCalled>historians</soCalled> and <soCalled>historical
                            texts.</soCalled> To broaden the search to uses of terms such as
                            <soCalled>narrative</soCalled> includes a wider range of projects but
                        also deepens the question. </p>
                    <p>In general, no digital humanities project directly deals with literature as a
                        topic, or with literariness. Based on the descriptions in the NEH library of
                        funded projects, the only project that directly engages with the
                            <soCalled>literary</soCalled> as a research question is the <title
                            rend="quotes">Electronic Literature Directory: Collaborative Knowledge
                            Management for the Literary Humanities.</title> This project asks what
                        role literature, in its specificity and as against other forms and
                        practices, can play in the digital humanities. The project concludes that
                        literature can play a critical role in the traditional sense of literary
                        criticism as humanistic discernment. I will address the question of
                            <soCalled>electronic literature</soCalled> at length elsewhere. It
                        stands in its own problematic and troubled relation to digital humanities,
                        or to <soCalled>digital</soCalled> and <soCalled>humanities.</soCalled>
                    </p>
                    <p>What is clear is that all projects in the grant program, and indeed all
                        projects appearing under the rubric of the humanities, are concerned with
                        textuality in some way. All the projects are proposed in a document and lead
                        to a variety of texts, most typically a <soCalled>white paper.</soCalled> At
                        one extreme, <soCalled>literature</soCalled> means <soCalled>it is
                            written.</soCalled> At this second glance, digital humanities seems
                        deeply literary. It is clear that the crucial monuments of digital
                        humanities are built on literature. IATH, undoubtedly the template for
                        digital humanities centers nationwide, incubated well-known
                        literature-oriented projects such as <title rend="quotes">The World of
                            Dante,</title>
                        <title rend="quotes">Uncle Tom's Cabin and American Culture,</title>
                        <title rend="quotes">The Walt Whitman Archive,</title>
                        <title rend="quotes">The William Blake Archive,</title>
                        <title rend="quotes">The Rossetti Archive,</title> and <title rend="quotes"
                            >The Dickinson Electronic Archive.</title> All are famous examples of
                        digital humanities. Projects such as the Rosetti Archive are not simply
                        excellent examples of digital humanities projects but function as paradigms.
                        The application of digital humanities to these canonical literary works
                        produced canonical digital humanities projects. The Rossetti Archive is an
                        exemplary and long-lived digital humanities project — begun in the pre-web
                        days of 1992 and conceptualized even earlier — and now functions as a
                        touchstone for scholarly discussion of the development of digital
                        humanities. Jerome McGann uses it to frame his consideration of <title
                            rend="italic">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide
                            Web</title>. If the project is at some level <soCalled>simply</soCalled>
                        a place for storing and retrieving documents by and about Rossetti, it is
                        understood as far more: a prototype and reference point, an argument in the
                        form of an archive. <title rend="quotes">The Dickinson Electronic
                            Archive</title> is the same, and also notable for its role as a
                        switchpoint of energy and interest from Virginia to Maryland, where its
                        creator and curator Martha Nell Smith built on the success of the IATH
                        project to found the Maryland Institute for the Humanities. Inseparable from
                        the archival is the foundational, institution-building quality of these
                        literary projects. Of course, I could go on and list other projects at other
                        centers, many of which are paradigms of digital humanities scholarship. </p>
                    <p>The visibility of this paradigm is displayed or staged even more intensely as
                        digital humanities becomes the star of the humanities in public discourse.
                        Take a look at the <title rend="quotes">Humanities 2.0,</title> a series of
                        articles by Patricia Cohen in the New York Times, begun in November 2010,
                        where literature plays a crucial but somewhat mysterious role. Cohen states: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2011">A history of the humanities in
                                the 20th century could be chronicled in <q>isms</q> ― formalism,
                                Freudianism, structuralism, postcolonialism ― grand intellectual
                                cathedrals from which assorted interpretations of literature,
                                politics and culture spread.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#cohen2011"/>
                        </cit> She then adds her claim: <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2011">The next
                            big idea in language, history and the arts? Data.</quote> While Cohen
                        introduces digital humanities as a whole, the majority of her examples are
                        projects dealing with literature, and the status of literature in these
                        projects is troubling for all concerned: it is an exemplary display of the
                        success and danger of the method. One researcher describes being <q>excited and terrified</q> by the way
                        digital humanities is <q>actually shaping the
                            kind of questions someone in literature might even ask.</q> The
                            <q>potential of electronic tools to reduce
                            literature and history to a series of numbers, squeezing out important
                            subjects that cannot be easily quantified</q> hovers over these
                        articles. </p>
                    <p>At the same time, we are repeatedly told that literature remains beyond the
                        method of digital humanities, despite re-shaping and reduction to
                        quantities. Anthony Grafton declares to Cohen: <q>I don’t believe quantification can do everything. So much of
                            humanistic scholarship is about interpretation.</q> The exemplary
                        status of literature as the unclarified core of the humanities is never
                        clearer: it is the text that digital humanities never tires of, it is the
                        perfect crash text dummy for the new methodology that always emerges
                        unscathed. </p>
                    <p>My point is that Cohen's suggestion that digital humanities replaces the
                        humanistic focus on interpretation with data processing methodology is too
                        simple, or rather too little as an explanation. Instead, you should
                        recognize the literary tropism of digital humanities: on the one hand, it
                        re-energizes the study of literature in a way that goes beyond the various
                            <soCalled>isms</soCalled> of theory and is rigorously grounded in
                        method. Of course, digital humanities does this for a variety of fields, not
                        just literature; but literature surely was and remains the apex of debates
                        about <soCalled>isms.</soCalled> The bloodiest battles of the
                            <soCalled>ism</soCalled> wars were fought in literature departments.</p>
                    <p>On the other hand, and more than this: literature is not just one case among
                        others. If it is returned to again and again as exemplary, this repetition
                        goes beyond the fact that literature is resistant to data-driven methods.
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2011">New digital tools are bringing new ways
                            to teach humanities courses, even Shakespeare</quote> writes Cohen. The
                            <q>even</q> is supposed to indicate
                        both the supposedly transgressive move entailed in applying digital
                        humanities to the Bard, but also to indicate the expected and inevitable
                        place of Shakespeare in this argument, where <q>even Shakespeare</q> means that the argument could not
                        be complete without Shakespeare. Cohen's examples belong to an existing
                        motif of understanding media through the lens of re-situated literature
                        monuments, a motif that includes <title rend="quotes">Shakespeare on
                            Film</title> — in all its configurations, from books to films such as
                            <title rend="italic">Shakespeare in Love</title> or the recent <title
                            rend="italic">Anonymous</title>, a film that cloaks pseudo-questions of
                        Shakespearean authorship in a core re-assertion and intensification of the
                        survival and of humanities through interest in literature — or similar
                        versions of this motif, such as Jay Clayton's <title rend="italic">Charles
                            Dickens in Cyberspace </title>or Jerry Flieger's <title rend="italic">Is
                            Oedipus Online?</title> (testifying to Freud as literary author). In
                        such works, the literary functions as a topos mobilizing well-read cultural
                        materials to understand new forms. The anxiety around the danger of the new
                        is a way of re-asserting the literariness of literature. Indeed, the
                        exemplarity of literature rubs off on the other projects Cohen looks at, so
                        that history or art become equally rich but also inexhaustible subject for
                        digital humanities. Literariness circulates in the description of other
                        fields, without any clear conceptualization or without even being named (no
                        need to state that digital humanities treats history and the rest as
                        literary).</p>
                    <p>In all this, there is no need on Cohen's part to read literature, no
                        requirement to cite texts by Shakespeare (or other authors). I would argue
                        that the projects at IATH and elsewhere discussed above possess similar
                        citational value. Literature <soCalled>itself</soCalled> is the citation, an
                        invocation that adds literariness to the digital humanities overall. What is
                        the point of this citation? Firstly, proof of the survival value of
                        literature, <soCalled>even</soCalled> in the digital era. Literature is the
                        survival value of texts, it is the name of what lives on in texts, in this
                        and every era. Literature is stored up and hidden in every digital
                        humanities project. </p>
                    <p>And so, secondly, the renaissance of digital humanities is a literary
                        renaissance, a renewal through the <soCalled>project</soCalled> (through
                        every digital humanities project) that finds its paradigms in self-declared
                        literature projects such as the Rossetti Archive. Moreover, the citation of
                        literature implies <soCalled>depth</soCalled> in digital humanities
                        projects, a deepening of projects that ensure their value and return on
                        investment. Literary texts bear repeated reading, including repeated
                        critical readings. (How many books are there on <title rend="italic"
                            >Hamlet</title>?) So too digital humanities projects will bear re-use
                        and add something, some specific <soCalled>digital</soCalled> something to
                        the work. The point is not what is added but that literariness provides a
                        place for this value. Does it matter if the projects are used or is the
                        point simply that they exist? Surely the frantic desire to build or
                            <soCalled>start up</soCalled> monuments of digital humanities exceeds
                        any possible <emph>use</emph> of the projects? Unreadability is the point,
                        unreadability of a literary <soCalled>core</soCalled> or
                            <soCalled>origin</soCalled> to all products, unreadability as the
                        guarantee that we need new projects.</p>
                    <p>What can we make of this unreadability? How do we take it? Perhaps the deep
                        ambiguous unreadability of the literary is the name for the
                            <emph>satisfaction</emph> of the digital humanities project. Is this
                        really so? How can we tell? It is troubling to say that literature, with all
                        its fictionality and delusiveness, stands for the satisfaction of the desire
                        named digital humanities. Literature is necessary to the humanities — if the
                        humanities is not literary it is nothing else. Literature is the promise of
                        the humanities' survival. But is the survival of the humanities anything but
                        this promise? Is the survival anything but a story told, a figure of
                        language, a bit of writing? The literary in digital humanities is an
                        occluded tropology promising monuments and <soCalled>projects.</soCalled>
                        What is a <emph>project</emph>, that core object of digital humanities,
                        other than a version of the literary <emph>work</emph>? At the same time,
                        the literary in digital humanities is a productive, or more precisely, a
                        poetic momentum.</p>
                    <p>
                        <emph>The project is a monument built on the momentum of poetics.</emph>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>III. The Literary in Digital Humanities</head>
                    <p>It is remarkably difficult to distinguish literary texts from other texts.
                        Close scrutiny of so-called non-literary texts always brings to the
                        foreground problems of the poetic turn, authorial voice, or figural
                        language. Where text declares itself to be literature, announces its
                        literariness, it remains equally difficult to define the literariness given
                        in the text, beyond the fact of this announcement. No end of definitions are
                        possible, but the sheer ongoing existence of literary criticism is a tribute
                        to the non-conclusion of this project. You can decide that a text is
                        literary because of metaphor or tropological play, but the only clear thing
                        is that such a decision guarantees that anything other than these qualities
                        determine the literariness of the text. The distinguishing characteristic of
                        the literary is our inability to distinguish its character. Literature is
                        always something other than itself. </p>
                    <p>I will not rehearse the complex history of the discourse on <soCalled>the
                            literary.</soCalled> Instead, I will briefly examine TEI, the Text
                        Encoding Initiative, surely one of digital humanities' great
                        accomplishments. My argument is in three parts. </p>
                    <p>First, literature functions as the core example for TEI. By
                            <soCalled>core,</soCalled> I mean to highlight that TEI begins its
                        self-definition by invoking literary texts. Literature is necessary to the
                        definition of TEI.</p>
                    <p>Second, digital humanities scholars already recognize the literary potential
                        of TEI. I focus on Julia Flanders’ provocative arguments about text encoding
                        as a <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011">world-generating</quote> performance
                        that opens the possibility for <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011"
                            >poetic</quote> markup. </p>
                    <p>Third and finally, TEI builds its momentum on the poetics of the letter, on
                        the literary mark. Character rendering is a literary performance, and we
                        follow the figural turns of this performance when we speak with and engage
                        with the computer and its displays. </p>
                    <p>Literature functions as the core example of TEI. As originally set out in
                        1987 and formulated over the following years, TEI principles are oriented
                        towards humanities texts. The principles are well known: they make <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#tei2011">recommendations about suitable ways of
                            representing those features of textual resources which need to be
                            identified explicitly in order to facilitate processing by computer
                            programs.</quote> Specifically, TEI provides tags added to text to
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#tei2011">to mark the text structure and other
                            features of interest.</quote> Encoding text leaves the text in place but
                        adds a surplus coding of marks. The monuments of digital humanities I
                        described above are variously enabled by TEI tagging.</p>
                    <p>The primary examples in the TEI guidelines are drawn from literary texts,
                        both hypothetical and actual. The guidelines begin with a markup of William
                        Blake's <title rend="quotes">The Sick Rose.</title> The example
                        concludes:</p>
<eg>&lt;!-- more poems go here -- &gt;</eg>
                    <p>The standard adds that this <quote rend="inline" source="#tei2011">is an XML
                                <term>comment </term>and is not treated as part of the text.</quote>
                        The example of the boundary between TEI and text is exemplified by the
                        boundaries of a poem — in this case the canonical Blake poem familiar from
                        Norton anthologies — and the larger unit of a hypothetical anthology of
                        poems. The burden of marking <quote rend="inline" source="#tei2011">text structure
                            and other features of interest</quote> is carried by the example of a
                        poetry anthology. For our purposes: poetry is the analog boundary of
                        discrete digital tags.</p>
                    <p>The guidelines continue with many more literary examples. Of course, the
                        presence of these examples no doubt indicates the preference and background
                        of the authors. Guidelines such as TEI are protocols, in the sense of the
                        Internet Request for Comments (RFCs) that provide recommendations for the
                        operation of the Internet. Such protocols describe the behaviors of a
                        community. They are prescriptive and binding but not absolute. They
                        constitute a crowd. In this case, the crowd of digital humanities is again a
                        community of poetry readers, who agree in principle on recommendations for
                        marking up. Once again, a program is executed and at work. </p>
                    <p>Digital humanities scholars already recognize the literary potential of TEI.
                        Julia Flanders and Jacqueline Wernimont, in a presentation given at the
                        Digital Humanities 2011 conference at Stanford, proposed approaching TEI
                        markup as a practice of poetics <ptr target="#flanders2011"/>. Flanders and
                        Wernimont proposed to adopt the concept of <soCalled>possible
                            worlds</soCalled> from philosophy, and from its deployment in
                        narratology, to <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011">describe how
                            authorial markup might leverage the formal tools of a structural model
                            in order to enact a generative or poetic mode of markup.</quote> My
                        short summary will not do justice to their argument. To define what they
                        mean by <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011">authorial</quote>
                        markup, they begin from <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011"
                            >long-standing conceptual tension within the markup (and especially the
                            TEI) community between two models of markup.</quote> The first is rooted
                        in <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011">mimesis and
                            surrogacy,</quote> while the second is <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#flanders2011">is more concerned with meaning creation and the
                            domain of annotation, interpretation, authoring.</quote> The authors
                        focus on the second model, which they propose is suspended between
                        representation and production. <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011"
                            >The most common examples in the present day include annotation,
                            interpretive markup such as the association of themes and keywords with
                            spans of text (e.g. using the TEI @ana and <gi>interp</gi> mechanism),
                            and the creation of new documents such as articles using an XML markup
                            language as an authoring system.</quote> Flanders and Wernimont conclude
                        that <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011">the markup itself becomes
                            a world-generating mode of knowing that must carry several registers of
                            meaning arising from different kinds of scholarly agency.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>While Flanders and Wernimont set out an argument about two different forms of
                        markup, the ground of their claim is the <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2011"
                            >performative and illocutionary qualities of markup.</quote> Which is to
                        say: all markup is performative, all markup must be authorial and
                        world-generating. The most <soCalled>mimetic</soCalled> markup, devoted to
                        the straightforward representation of the text would surely be a great
                        achievement of authorship, where the registers of meaning would be cunning,
                        almost ironic in their silent overlay. The momentum of this poetics is such
                        that there can be no way to determine whether markup is a representation of
                        the text or in a fictional relation to the text. </p>
                    <p>TEI builds its momentum on the poetics of the letter, of the literary mark.
                        It is not that the text turns poetic and thus digital humanities is large
                        enough to accommodate this turn. No, the computer is not textual, or rather
                        is only textual after the fact. It is not that we read the screen and
                        possibly discover literary texts in our reading. On the contrary, we read
                        the screen <emph>because it is literary from the first</emph>. The
                        literariness of the computer is the condition of our reading.</p>
                    <p>Much more could be said. There is always more idiocy. What do you make of
                        Saussure’s remarks on the written sign that the <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#saussure1983">actual mode of inscription
                                is irrelevant, because it does not affect the system. […] Whether I
                                write in black or white, in incised characters or relief, with a pen
                                or a chisel — none of that is of any importance for the
                                meaning</quote>
                            <ptr target="#saussure1983" loc="118"/>
                        </cit>? Or for that matter Freud's remark that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#freud1965">the single letters of the
                                alphabet […] do not occur in pure nature</quote>
                            <ptr loc="261" target="#freud1965"/>
                        </cit>? The trajectory of the problem of the literary as digital can be
                        unread, tracked, allegorized, and lost through a much more complex history
                        that casts the discrete back into text encodings that include Morse and
                        ASCII and FIELDATA, but also Viète and Bacon's ciphers. Still, you want the
                        literary. You want me to address the literary in digital humanities, whereas
                        all I do in this essay is speak to its absent efficacy. </p>
                    <p>Anthony Wilden, in his short essay on <title rend="quotes">Analog and Digital
                            Communication,</title> which after forty years still remains little-read
                        and yet one of the few useful texts on the topic, respects the complication
                        of distinguishing the analog and digital. In fact, he sees such
                        distinction-making as itself implicated in the boundaries of the analog and
                        digital. For Wilden, the negation of the literal <emph>is</emph> what orders
                        the analog and digital. In short, any communicational
                            <soCalled>ensemble</soCalled> may be understood as analog or digital
                        depending on the boundary drawn and the position of the observer vis a vis
                        the communication. In terms of character encoding, Wilden's argument about
                        negation is important: he argues that there is only negation in the digital
                        order, and that negation corresponds to relational meta-organization of
                        information. The presence of zero as the simple flip of the digit is enough
                        to negate the letter. </p>
                    <p>Encoding sites the letter. Encoding grants the letter presence, while a
                        different encoding negates it and puts another letter in its place. For
                        Wilden, this structural fact is introduced into the analog in a way that
                        negates the material substrate bearing or carrying a mark, and poetically
                        and punctually produces the digital mark. The digital mark is information
                        only as it negates or re-marks what bears it (178-188).</p>
                    <p>The informational and energetic actuality of the discrete mark is a problem
                        of boundaries and systems. It is, in short, the problem of the literal,
                        which itself is another name for the problem of the literary. (The literary:
                        a problem with multiple names, already a story at work, a story of the
                        letter and its literary literalness.) We deal with the remainders of
                        system-generating literary inscription, with the guarantee of a narrative
                        resting on the meaning and sense-making around sites of literal inscription.
                            <emph>It is written</emph>: literature specifies topics of contention
                        and debate, including specifying conditions of authorship and of the nature
                        of the work, and of topics that are carried out as discourses identified as
                        digital. Open source or file sharing are examples of such topics: part of
                        the institution of literature that programs in advance the debates and
                        contentions. Literature names the discreteness — the digitalization, if you
                        want — left by the literary. Discreet and discrete: literature’s fictional
                        narrative is poetic, productive, but not at all truthful, and can tell us
                        nothing of the literary except that it is written.<note>On the discreet in
                            the discrete, see Stiegler on <title rend="quotes">The Discrete
                                Image</title>
                            <ptr target="#stiegler2002"/>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Let me stick close to the concerns of TEI and digital humanities to focus on
                        the literal inscription on the screen and in the computer. As an XML
                        document, TEI-encoded text relies on the Unicode standard. Unicode
                        guarantees that all XML documents, and thus all TEI markup, <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#unicode">whatever languages or writing systems they
                            employ, use the same underlying character encoding (that is, the same
                            method of representing as binary data those graphic forms making up a
                            particular writing system).</quote> The guidelines continue: <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#unicode">Unicode provides a standardized way of
                            representing any of the many thousands of discrete symbols making up the
                            world's writing systems, past and present.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Following this statement of the importance of Unicode, the TEI Guidelines
                        immediately turn to <quote rend="inline" source="#tei2011">textual
                            structures,</quote> stating: </p>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#tei2011">A text is not an undifferentiated sequence of
                        words, much less of bytes. For different purposes, it may be divided into
                        many different units, of different types or sizes. A prose text such as this
                        one might be divided into sections, chapters, paragraphs, and sentences. A
                        verse text might be divided into cantos, stanzas, and lines. Once printed,
                        sequences of prose and verse might be divided into volumes, gatherings, and
                        pages.</quote>
                    <p>While TEI will foster an awareness and understanding of the complex relation
                        between text and its units, the fact of this differentiation is fundamental
                        and unquestioned, a fact that is given literally as a datum through the
                        literalness of Unicode.</p>
                    <p>The story I am telling you might climax here, here is my climax: Unicode as
                        the literal, defining digital writing. On the Unicode Consortium's <title
                            rend="quotes">Acclaim for Unicode</title> page, James J. O’Donnell, the
                        classicist, digital humanist, and provost of Georgetown University declared:
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Unicode marks the most significant
                            advance in writing systems since the Phoenicians.</quote> The
                        significance and advance need to be followed and understood. There is only
                        one code on the net and it is Unicode. Read the following carefully: it is
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">the universal character encoding
                            standard for written characters and text.</quote> The Unicode
                        Consortium’s <title rend="quotes">What is Unicode?</title> webpage,
                        providing their central definition, begins with the following mantra: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#unicode">Unicode provides a unique number
                                for every character, no matter what the platform, no matter what the
                                program, no matter what the language</quote>
                            <ptr target="#unicode"/>
                        </cit>. From most points of view, the capacity of Unicode is enormous.
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#unicode">The majority of the common characters
                            used in the major languages of the world are encoded in the first 65,536
                            code points,</quote> but the sixteen-bit encoding has the capability to
                        encode up to 1,114,112 code points. Unicode even encodes fictional writing
                        systems such as Elvish or Klingon. Its codespace includes any writing system
                        whatsoever, without regard to whether this writing was ever employed by
                        human culture. <quote rend="inline" source="#unicode">It provides the capacity to
                            encode all characters used for the written languages of the
                            world.</quote> What an achievement! To encode all humanities writing
                        systems, past, present, and fictional! More than this: since streams of
                        ASCII are the basis of all file transfers on the net, since ASCII is now a
                        subset of Unicode, and since Unicode provides a structure for exchange and
                        storage of data, then we must recognize that this encoding is the
                        fundamental writing of all that is on the net. </p>
                    <p>Brian Lennon's excellent discussion of Unicode focuses on the limits of its
                        claims to totality: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#lennon2010">As a system defining
                                universally efficient transmission, it must emit redundant waste in
                                the form of merely local variation, precisely to claim its place
                                    <emph>as</emph> system</quote>
                            <ptr target="#lennon2010" loc="170"/>
                        </cit>. As with the ASCII standard, Unicode is easily critiqued for the way
                        it inevitably re-maps geopolitical concerns and contentions. But it is the
                        distinction between character and glyph, central to the logic of Unicode,
                        which accounts for the literariness involved. The enormous range of
                        encodings, on the one hand, and the flexibility in transmission, storage,
                        and display of characters, on the other, all come down to this distinction.
                        Joe Becker’s original 1988 draft proposal for the Unicode standard states
                        that a <q>clear and all-important distinction
                            is made between <emph>characters</emph>, which are abstract text
                            content-bearing entities, and <emph>glyphs</emph>, which are visible
                            graphic forms.</q> This distinction is carried on in the Unicode
                        standard as implemented and maintained to this day. The distinction is in
                        operation within all encodings and implies a philosophy of the screen and of
                        the object. The current standard Unicode 2.0 Core Specification released on
                        February 17, 2011, states: <quote rend="inline" source="#unicode">Characters are
                            the abstract representations of the smallest components of written
                            language that have semantic value.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>What is meant by <q>abstract</q>? Character
                        refers to the <q>abstract meaning and/or
                            shape, rather than a specific shape.</q> What is meant by <q>semantic</q> here? Not that a given
                        character is meaningful. The character <q>a</q> may or may not be
                        meaningful. Rather, as Korpela’s <title rend="italic">Unicode
                            Explained</title> argues, it <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#korpela2006">would be better to say that a
                                character has a <emph>recognized identity</emph> and it may be
                                sometimes used as meaningful in itself</quote>
                            <ptr loc="11" target="#korpela2006"/>
                        </cit>. Meaning and semantics are part of the recognizable identity of the
                        character within the system of Unicode. <q>The
                            character identified by a Unicode code point is an abstract entity, such
                            as <q>latin capital letter a</q> or <q>bengali digit five.</q> The mark
                            made on screen or paper, called a glyph, is a visual representation of
                            the character</q> (5). </p>
                    <p>What is a glyph? A glyph is perceived. <q>Glyphs represent the shapes that characters can have when they are
                            rendered or displayed.</q> A glyph is also technically produced. It
                        is an outcome of technology. <q>In contrast to
                            characters, glyphs appear on the screen or paper as particular
                            representations of one or more characters.</q> Glyph and character
                        are part of a single writing technology, the one side abstract, encoded and
                        conceptual; the other side, material, perceived, and undefined.</p>
                    <p>Obviously, glyphs outnumber characters. There are multiple possible
                        renderings for a character: many sizes, many resolutions, and many forms of
                        visibility, any of which may be recognizable as characters. There is no
                        comparison with glyphs: they are fundamentally unnumbered. They appear and
                        are seen, but are not and cannot be defined by Unicode. Glyphs are
                        recognized for the encoding that they render. Codes are set out in tables
                        and carefully controlled. Appearances are disordered and without accounting.
                        The difference is between wild phenomena and specific forms or characters.
                        The character on the screen, the text that I see and read, is not a body.
                        There is no character there but only an encoding that I read through the
                        appearance. What I see, but not what I read, is an innumerable disordering
                        of appearances. Characters are the logistical construction of
                            <soCalled>reading</soCalled> and <soCalled>seeing</soCalled> through a
                        systematic technical distribution of the visual and symbolic. </p>
                    <p>The subjectivity of the writer and reader of character codes is not a
                        function of the so-called gaze of psychoanalysis, a concept that involves
                        the problematization of the object in relation to the eye. Unicode empties
                        out appearances of any subject-object relations. There are no relations in
                        the visible, no subjects and no objects, only a vast and innumerable field
                        of appearances. Code is the truth that appearance is not: all that appears
                        is nothing but the negated world of matter, nothing but flows of intensity,
                        outside the abstraction of code. The gaze, the site of the subject and of
                        all of our anxieties and traumas, is an undefined surplus effect left on the
                        screen, never penetrating or seeping into the code. </p>
                    <p>Of course, I recognize that code is visible too. Gaze seeps across code and
                        smears its surface. Therefore, the visible field must be controlled. It is
                        paradoxical that Unicode must be represented in charts, not to mention in
                        books and other writings: tables, guides, diagrams, and so on, all
                        displaying what is not possible to make visible. What are these charts? They
                        are depictions of <soCalled>character</soCalled> as the gaze on the encoded
                        character. The charts come with a disclaimer: <q>Character images shown in the code charts are not
                            prescriptive.</q> Not prescriptive but narrative and poetic. For
                        this there is the <q>representative
                            glyph,</q> which is <q>not a
                            prescriptive form of the character,</q> and yet <q>enables recognition of the intended character to a
                            knowledgeable user and facilitates lookup of the character in the code
                            charts.</q> It is a paradoxical appearance through which the symbol
                        is recognized. The representative glyph is immediately false, not to be
                        taken as the abstract character but as its perfect fiction. </p>
                    <p>The visual and symbolic churn and turn within this mess of glyph, character,
                        and representative glyph, a mess of allegorical narratives of the literary,
                        narratives that go by the name digital humanities, are all built on markup
                        and method as the poetic turning and returning to (and in relation to)
                        literary inscription. It is a return leaving not the literary but literature
                        as the wayward trajectory of marking. I tell you: the entwined source of the
                        literary and digital humanities is here.</p>
                    <p>The history of character and glyph are similar. The earliest English usages
                        of both refer to a carving, a cutting, or a marking. In short, usage refers
                        to the problem of rendering. By the seventeenth century, character came to
                        refer to the mental and moral qualities of an individual, while glyph
                        continued to refer to the material and physical engraving. As Marshall
                        McLuhan detailed in the <title rend="italic">Gutenberg Galaxy</title>, the
                        emergence and dominance of print led to the perceived equivalence of the
                        qualities of individuals and printed characters. I tell you: not just a
                        letter but also <emph>any</emph> appearance on the screen is a glyph etched
                        or inscribed on that surface. Every screen is a glyph; every screen is the
                            <term>stochoie</term> or <term>littera</term>. The literal is always
                        being screened. Character encoding means <emph>I write it, it writes
                            me</emph>. To screen is to touch, is to contact the other. Such a
                            <emph>terminal screen</emph> is never touched by the other; it is never
                        smearing the same fluid on my fingers, on my tongue. How rigid is this
                            <soCalled>never touched</soCalled>? What relation exists through this
                        rigidity? </p>
                    <p>Much more could be told of the theater of the screen, of character armoring,
                        of the gender of the letter, and the satisfaction found through rendering
                        and display. I remind you: the computer is not digital. Computers melt,
                        overheat, shed light and lose data.<note>I recognize the awareness of the
                            computer as <emph>object</emph> in recent work on object-oriented
                            ontologies, but I do not recognize an awareness of the radiating,
                            ecstatic, and harrowing aspect of the object. Perhaps Graham Harman’s
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#harman2005">allure</quote> gestures
                            towards this sense of the <quote rend="inline" source="#harman2005"
                                >radioactive</quote> state of the object <ptr target="#harman2005"
                                loc="160–168"/>. </note> They exist in a narrowly-controlled thermal
                        range. The website for Intel Corporation, producer of many of the world’s
                        microprocessors, states that <q>thermal
                            management</q> refers to <q>two major
                            elements: a heat sink properly mounted to the processor, and effective
                            airflow through the system chassis. The ultimate goal of thermal
                            management is to keep the processor at or below its maximum operating
                            temperature.</q> The computer is not discrete and differentiated,
                        not an archive of texts, not an enclosure of circumscribed inscriptions, but
                        a radiating sun in a constant state of decay. Using a computer is handling
                        the decay and dispersal of thermal management — not to mention managing
                        hardware interrupts, breakpoints, and quantum tunneling. </p>
                    <p>On any given day the amount of energy used to power Facebook pages, recipe
                        searches, news sites and all that the internet entails is about 20 or 30
                        gigawatts. In terms of greenhouse gas emissions, power consumed daily by the
                        internet is roughly the same as the airline industry.</p>
                    <p>And yet you say the computer is digital. By <soCalled>you,</soCalled> I
                        imagine Julia Flanders, because I admire her work and her argument:
                        cogently, persuasively, correctly, arguing for the world-generating poetics
                        of markup. By <soCalled>you,</soCalled> I address digital humanities. The
                        digital is this narrative: deceptive, fictional, a narrative of the
                        otherness of the world, a narrative of project management as management of
                        otherness. Digital means a narrative imagining the other through
                        information. A delirium of data as absence of the world, as mourning this
                        absence, as telling the closure of data. Unicode turns every project into
                        narrated knowledge that can be handled and managed.<note>In <title
                                rend="italic">Aesthetic Theory</title>, Adorno writes: <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#adorno1997">Suffering remains foreign
                                    to knowledge; though knowledge can subordinate it conceptually
                                    and provide means for its amelioration, knowledge can scarcely
                                    express it through its own means of experience without itself
                                    becoming irrational</quote>
                                <ptr loc="24" target="#adorno1997"/>
                            </cit>. </note>
                    </p>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->
                <bibl label="Adorno 1997" xml:id="adorno1997" key="adorno1997">Adorno, Theodor.
                        <title rend="italic">Aesthetic Theory</title>. Minneapolis: University of
                    Minnesota Press, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Adorno 1992" xml:id="adorno1992" key="adorno1992">Adorno, Theodor.
                        <title rend="quotes">Commitment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Notes to Literature, Volume 2. </title>New York: Columbia
                    University Press, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Barthes 1977" xml:id="barthes1977" key="barthes1977">Barthes, Roland.
                        <title rend="italic">Roland Barthes on Roland Barthes</title>. New York:
                    MacMillan, 1977.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Becker 2011" xml:id="becker2011" key="becker2011">Becker, Joe. <title
                        rend="quotes">Unicode 88.</title> Unicode.org. Web. Accessed October 14,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Cohen 2011" xml:id="cohen2011" key="cohen2011">Cohen, Patricia. <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities 2.0.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>. Web. Accessed October 14,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Saussure 1983" xml:id="saussure1983" key="saussure1983">de Saussure,
                    Ferdinand. <title rend="italic">Course in General Linguistics</title>. New York:
                    Open Court Publishing, 1983.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Flanders and Wernimont 2011" xml:id="flanders2011" key="flanders2011a"
                    >Flanders, Julia and Jacqueline Wernimont. <title rend="quotes">Possible Worlds:
                        Authorial Markup and Digital Scholarship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2011 Online Abstract.</title> Web.
                    Accessed October 14, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Freud 1965" xml:id="freud1965" key="freud1965">Freud, Sigmund. <title
                        rend="italic">The Interpretation of Dreams</title>. New York: Avon,
                    1965.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Harman 2005" xml:id="harman2005" key="harman2005">Harman, Graham.
                        <title rend="italic">Guerilla Metaphysics</title>. New York: Open Court,
                    2005.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hayles 2008" xml:id="hayles2008" key="hayles2008a">Hayles, N.
                    Katherine. <title rend="italic">Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the
                        Literary</title>. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Jakobson 1987" xml:id="jakobson1987" key="jakobson1987a">Jakobson,
                    Roman. <title rend="italic">Language in Literature</title>. Cambridge: Harvard
                    University Press, 1987.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Korpela 2006" xml:id="korpela2006" key="korpela2006">Korpela, Jukka K.
                        <title rend="italic">Unicode Explained</title>. O'Reilly Media, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Lennon 2010" xml:id="lennon2010" key="lennon2010">Lennon, Brian. <title
                        rend="italic">In Babel's Shadow</title>. Minneapolis: University of
                    Minnesota, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="McLuhan 2011" xml:id="mcluhan2011" key="mcluhan2011">McLuhan, Marshall.
                        <title rend="italic">The Gutenberg Galaxy</title>. Toronto: University of
                    Toronto Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rosset 1989" xml:id="rosset1989" key="rosset1989">Rosset, Clément.
                        <title rend="quotes">Reality and the Untheorizable,</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">The Limits of Theory</title>. Palo Alto: Stanford University
                    Press, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Shklovsky 2004" xml:id="shklovsky2004" key="shklovsky2004">Shklovsky,
                    Viktor. <title rend="quotes">Art as Technique</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Literary Theory</title>: An Anthology. Malden, MA: Blackwell Pub, 2004. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Stiegler 2009" xml:id="stiegler2009" key="stiegler2009">Stiegler,
                    Bernard. <title rend="italic">Technics and Time, 2: Disorientation</title>.
                    Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Stiegler 2002" xml:id="stiegler2002" key="stiegler2002">Stiegler,
                    Bernard. In Jacques Derrida and Bernard Stiegler, <title rend="italic"
                        >Echographies of Television: Filmed Interviews. </title>Cambridge: Polity
                    Press, 2002. </bibl>
                <bibl label="TEI 2011" xml:id="tei2011" key="tei2011">The Text Encoding Initiative.
                        <title rend="italic">The Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines for Electronic
                        Text Encoding and Interchange.</title> Web. Accessed October 14,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Unicode" xml:id="unicode" key="unicode">The Unicode Consortium.
                    Unicode.org. Web. Accessed October 14, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wilden 1972" xml:id="wilden1972" key="wilden1972">Wilden, Anthony.
                        <title rend="italic">System and Structure</title>. London: Tavistock,
                    1972.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
