<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Textual Artifacts and their Digital
                    Representations: Teaching Graduate Students to Build Online
                    Archives</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Deena
                        <dhq:family>Engel</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences,
                        New York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>deena.engel@nyu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Deena Engel is a Clinical Professor as well as the
                            Associate Director of Undergraduate Studies for the
                            Computer Science Minors programs in the Department
                            of Computer Science at the Courant Institute of
                            Mathematical Sciences of New York University. She
                            teaches undergraduate computer science courses on
                            web and database technologies, as well as courses
                            for undergraduate and graduate students in the
                            Digital Humanities. Ms. Engel also conducts research
                            and supervises undergraduate and graduate student
                            research projects in the Digital Humanities. She
                            holds Master’s degrees in both Comparative
                            Literature and Computer Science</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Marion
                        <dhq:family>Thain</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>New York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>marion.thain@nyu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Marion Thain teaches literature and the liberal
                            arts at New York University, and is Associate
                            Director for Digital Humanities for the Faculty of
                            Arts and Sciences (website: <ref target="https://sites.google.com/a/nyu.edu/marion-thain/">https://sites.google.com/a/nyu.edu/marion-thain/</ref>).
                            Her research is primarily in the areas of:
                            aestheticism and Decadence; British poetry and
                            poetics; the Digital Humanities. She has published
                            five books and many essays and journal articles,
                            including: <title rend="italic">The Lyric Poem:
                                Formations and Transformations</title>
                            (Cambridge University Press, 2013); <title rend="quotes">Michael Field</title> (1880-1914):
                                <title rend="italic">Poetry, Aestheticism, and
                                the Fin de Siècle</title> (Cambridge University
                            Press, 2007). She is currently a director of The
                            Victorian Lives and Letters Consortium (<ref target="http://tundra.csd.sc.edu/vllc/">http://tundra.csd.sc.edu/vllc/</ref>), a
                            collaborator on The Affect Project (<ref target="https://affectproject.ca/index.php/home/common">https://affectproject.ca/index.php/home/common</ref>
                            — funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities
                            Research Council of Canada), and a participant in A
                            History of Distributed Cognition (<ref target="http://eidyn.ppls.ed.ac.uk/history-distributed-cognition-2014-18">http://eidyn.ppls.ed.ac.uk/history-distributed-cognition-2014-18</ref>
                            — funded by the Arts and Humanities Research
                            Council, U.K.)</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000199</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2015-02-28">28 February 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled
                        vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Digital pedagogy</item>
                        <item>computer science</item>
                        <item>online archives</item>
                        <item>graduate DH</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2015-01-18" who="EH">Encoded article</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Co-teaching a digital archives course (ENGL-GA.2971) for
                    graduate students in the English Department allowed us to
                    bring together our expertise in both research and pedagogy
                    from two fields: English Literature and Computer Science.
                    The course built on a core pedagogical principle in Computer
                    Science of teaching through projects rather than from
                    unrelated one-off programming or web development
                    assignments. Teaching the Text Encoding Initiative after
                    students had completed hands-on projects (using xHTML, CSS,
                    and a digital archive working in a standard content
                    management system) enabled the building of technological
                    skill sets in a logical and complementary manner. From a
                    literary perspective, building a digital archive — and
                    teaching text encoding — enabled an in-depth consideration
                    of textual materiality, the processes through which literary
                    scholarship must inform technological building decisions,
                    and the ways in which the act of digitization can be used to
                    ask new questions of the text (or to prompt the text to ask
                    new questions of itself). This paper will survey our
                    techniques and approaches to interdisciplinary teaching,
                    culminating in our usage of text encoding for exploring
                    issues of textuality through digital presentation.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Techniques and approaches to interdisciplinary teaching for a
                    graduate digital archives course.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This article reflects on the practice of designing and
                    implementing a course that aimed to teach graduate students
                    in English the skills to build a scholarly online digital
                    archive from primary source materials. A founding principle
                    of our pedagogical practice is the integration of CS and DH
                    methods. As a still fairly young pedagogical field,
                    discussion and sharing on this topic might, we hope, be
                    timely and useful to others. This course was part of an
                    evolving response to the key current pedagogical challenge
                    of teaching graduate students in English how to synthesize a
                    new set of technological skills with literary expertise to
                    discover new ways of working and new questions to ask of
                    their texts.</p>
                <p>The ultimate ambition of our course was for each student to
                    digitize text otherwise inaccessible beyond the material
                    archive. As such the focus was on dealing with manuscript
                    materials, marginalia and other editorial markings on
                    typescripts, and materials that had a particular material
                    instantiation. The students were free to choose their focal
                    materials to reflect their own interests, and had access to
                    the manuscripts collections and Fales’ special collections
                    in the Bobst Library at New York University. The resulting
                    digital archives included, for example, collections of
                    nineteenth- or twentieth-century letters by well-known
                    writers; manuscript drafts of what went on to become
                    well-known literary texts; type-script drafts of literary
                    essays; and even a collection of contemporary hand-made
                    ‘zines’. Each archive included images of the documents,
                    transcriptions, TEI encodings, contextualization through
                    further reading lists, and prose narratives about their
                    materials and their digital archival practice.</p>
                <p>New York University’s Department of English first offered a
                    course on creating online archives from primary source
                    materials in the fall, 2011 semester under the course number
                    and title <title rend="italic">ENGL-GA.2957-001 Special
                        Topics in Literary Theory: Literary Archives and Web
                        Development. </title>(The course home page, hosted by
                    the Department of Computer Science at New York University
                    can be found at <ref target="http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall11/ENGL-GA.2957-001/DT_openingPage.html">http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall11/ENGL-GA.2957-001/DT_openingPage.html</ref>).
                    This course built on earlier experience in the Computer
                    Science Department on teaching topics in the Digital
                    Humanities through an undergraduate Special Topics course
                        <title rend="italic">CSCI-UA.380</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computing in the Humanities and the
                        Arts</title>. (CSCI-UA.380 <title rend="italic">Computing in the Humanities and the Arts</title> has
                    been offered five times from the fall, 2007 semester through
                    the fall, 2014. semester; see <ref target="http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall14/CSCI-UA.0380-002/HC_index_fa14.php">http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall14/CSCI-UA.0380-002/HC_index_fa14.php</ref>).
                    The undergraduate Computer Science course is taught within
                    the context of the Computer Science Department Web
                    Programming minor (<ref target="http://cs.nyu.edu/webapps/content/academic/undergrad/minors">http://cs.nyu.edu/webapps/content/academic/undergrad/minors</ref>)
                    and has two pre-requisites (one semester each in computer
                    programming and in web design) <ptr target="#engel2013"/>.
                    In each iteration of the undergraduate course, the capstone
                    project included building an online digital archive from
                    primary source materials; some of the results of this
                    collaboration between the New York University Library and
                    Archives and the Department of Computer Science are
                    described in published essays. <ptr target="#mitchell2012"/>; <ptr target="#bunde2010a"/>; <ptr target="#bunde2010b"/>.</p>
                <p>The course under discussion in this article, <title rend="italic">ENGL-GA.2971</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Practicum in Digital Humanities</title>
                    was given in the fall, 2013 semester in a new format in
                    which it was designed and co-taught collaboratively by two
                    faculty members, one each from the English and Computer
                    Science departments. (The course home page, hosted by the
                    Department of Computer Science at New York University can be
                    found at <ref target="http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall13/ENGL-GA.2971-001/DT_index_fa13.php">http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall13/ENGL-GA.2971-001/DT_index_fa13.php</ref>)
                    As computer systems become more integrated into and integral
                    to studies in many fields, the development of courses that
                    offer training in technology is becoming more and more
                    relevant outside of Computer Science departments. <ptr target="#guzdial2005"/>. In addition, the role of web
                    development in current Computer Science pedagogy is widely
                    studied and discussed <ptr target="#park2011"/>; <ptr target="#wang2009"/>; <ptr target="#yue2004"/>. From a
                    pedagogical standpoint, this course offered the Computer
                    Science department an opportunity to devise materials and a
                    curriculum to best meet the needs of our growing student
                    body in the Humanities who wish to augment their studies
                    with computational and technological skills. As it ran in
                    2011 the course was very successful in bringing humanities
                    computing skills to students in the English department.
                    Building on this success, the introduction of a literature
                    professor (with expertise in editing, and creating online
                    archives of manuscript materials) as a co-teacher was
                    designed to help expand the remit by forging greater
                    connection with current debates within the humanities, and
                    particularly within literary studies. The syllabus for the
                    course can be found in the appendix. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Aims of the Course</head>
                <p>From a Computer Science perspective this course sought to
                    implement and contextualize four current goals and trends in
                    Computer Science education. Following is a brief description
                    of each of these goals with references for further
                    reading.</p>
                <p>(1) Project-Based Learning (“PBL”):</p>
                <p><cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#richards2009">Project-based courses are common in
                            computing education. As a method within the
                            problem-based learning toolkit, projects can be used
                            at any stage within a degree program to explore
                            alternative and often more complete solutions to a
                            given problem allowing the theory to emerge as
                            necessary.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#richards2009"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p><cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#guzdial2010">Students who drop out from a course
                            do not have the opportunity to learn all the
                            material and transfer it. If students understand the
                            usefulness of what they are learning, they are less
                            likely to give up.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#guzdial2010"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>There is a current trend in Computer Science pedagogy to
                    encourage <q>project-based learning</q> (PBL) in place of
                        <q>traditional</q> one-off programming or development
                    assignments. <ptr target="#chang2010"/>; <ptr target="#gülbahar2006"/>; <ptr target="#richards2009"/>.
                    We found that all of the technical skills and technology
                    infrastructure that we taught could be related to the main
                    project in this course, which is the online digital archive.
                    This approach appeared to incentivize the students to tackle
                    topics outside of their areas of expertise as the results
                    were immediately apparent (e.g. the ability to manipulate a
                    variety of images of a manuscript within the context of a
                    webpage) and moved them closer to their end goal of the
                    course project.</p>
                <p>(2) The Role of Web Development in Computer Science
                    Pedagogy:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#park2011">Web development can provide a rich
                        context for exploring computer science concepts and
                        practicing computational creativity.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#park2011"/>
                </cit>
                <p>Web development has become a serious area of study for
                    undergraduate Computer Science majors <ptr target="#adams2007"/>; <ptr target="#connolly2011"/>;
                        <ptr target="#liu2011"/>; <ptr target="#mendes2012"/>;
                        <ptr target="#schaub2009"/> and for undergraduate
                    non-majors <ptr target="#gousie2006"/>; <ptr target="#greenberg2012"/>; <ptr target="#guzdial2005"/>;
                        <ptr target="#kurkovsky2007"/>. Web development offers
                    instructors and students both a granular approach to
                    teaching technologies by focusing a lesson or assignment on
                    a single technology (e.g. xHTML/CSS; PHP; using Photoshop to
                    manipulate images, etc.) as well as the opportunity to study
                    and work with the many-faceted technological structure of
                    web implementation (e.g. the underlying relationship between
                    xHTML, CSS, PHP and a database in the context of modifying
                    and manipulating a content management system (CMS) site). </p>
                <p>(3) Inclusion and Computer Science Pedagogy:</p>
                <p><cit><quote rend="block" source="#pulimood2008">Supporting a workforce that can create, not simply consume,
                    computing technology requires a shift in pedagogy toward
                    problem solving in a gender neutral, culturally and
                    ethnically diverse community.</quote> <ptr target="#pulimood2008"/></cit>.</p>
                <p>There is an acute awareness within the Computer Science
                    pedagogy field that education in Computer Science and
                    technology must consciously and deliberately address issues
                    of inclusion so that women and minority students as well as
                    disabled students should have full access and encouragement
                    to participate on a <soCalled>level playing
                    field</soCalled>. As female students are well represented in
                    the discipline of English, the issues of gender and computer
                    technology were particularly relevant for the course. The
                    recent research into inclusivity within Computer Science
                    education <ptr target="#guzdial2012"/>; <ptr target="#pulimood2008"/>; <ptr target="#stephenson2007"/> helps to inform practices and approaches to teaching
                    technology skills to Humanities students. Open discussion of
                    discomfort with technology appeared to ameliorate some of
                    the concern. Furthermore, imposing a rule in classroom
                    discussion that <q>there is no such thing
                        as a dumb question</q> and that <q>web technology is constantly evolving and the trick is
                        to learn how to frame the question</q> helped to
                    assuage the students’ fears.</p>
                <p>(4) The Development of Computer Science Pedagogy Within
                    Inter-disciplinary and Cross-disciplinary Areas of
                    Education:</p>
                <p><cit><quote rend="block" source="#leblanc2010">Computer science holds a unique position to craft
                    multidisciplinary curricula for the new generation of
                    faculty and students across the academy who increasingly
                    rely on computing for their scholarship.</quote> <ptr target="#leblanc2010"/></cit></p>
                <p>Computer Science departments must continue to meet the needs
                    of other departments and collaborate both on University
                    pedagogy goals and with research <ptr target="#bills2007"/>;
                        <ptr target="#leblanc2010"/>. Teaching collaboration
                    between Computer Science and literature faculty aids the
                    development of more radically interdisciplinary courses,
                    which can offer something different from literature courses
                    that use technologically-enhanced learning or web
                    development courses that utilize literary texts. </p>
                <p>Our course was structured so as to begin with connected but
                    distinct issues in literature and technology that ran in
                    tandem, but to work towards the integration of the two sets
                    of considerations. This integration culminated in the final
                    section of the course on the Text Encoding Initiative (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</ref>). From the
                    perspective of the literature professor, then, the overall
                    pedagogical aim was to provide a layer of commentary on the
                    course activities that encouraged students to reflect on all
                    the technical decisions they made in building their sites as
                    themselves potentially acts of interpretation of the text
                    they were representing. Through looking at recent debates
                    around textual interpretation in literary studies, it was
                    possible to make connections that enabled students to
                    consider how their own practice in digital reproduction
                    might be intersecting fundamentally and significantly with
                    issues of textuality. This goal was one of teaching the
                    students how to think in ways that confront the deepest
                    issues of interdisciplinarity, and to avoid the natural
                    compartmentalization of skill sets. We maintained the
                    specificity of the issues within each disciplinary field
                    while showing the points of intersection by role-modeling
                    debates between the two teachers. With the main outcome of
                    the course being the online digital archive, we decided not
                    to ask the students to write a separate reflective
                    essay-commentary on their building of those sites, but to
                    ensure that this reflection was built into the site through
                    their layout, the choices they made, and through the prose
                    in their <q>About</q> sections.</p>
                <p>Also from a literary perspective, it was crucial to the
                    course that there was the potential not just for a growth in
                    technological skills informed by considerations drawn from
                    the humanities, but a growth in awareness of textual
                    features through attending to the literature in a new way.
                    In other words, the act of digitization became within the
                    course a new way of being sensitive to the features of the
                    text for literary, critical, and interpretative purposes.
                    The potential for this process to work in two disciplinary
                    directions simultaneously was particularly interesting
                    pedagogically because the students came to the course with
                    varied levels of expertise in technology and in literary
                    study. The humanities skills the students developed through
                    the course were those of the literary critic (particularly
                    in relation to textual materiality), the literary-historical
                    scholar, and the editor. Depending on each student’s
                    previous experience and their comfort with literature and
                    technology, respectively, the opportunities were different,
                    but for every student the objective was a symbiotic
                    relationship between the two, with the digitization process
                    prompting new engagement with the texts they had chosen, and
                    for the resulting considerations to then go on to inflect
                    the way they used the technology within their site. </p>
                <p>While this article focuses around the collaboration of the
                    two professors who designed and taught the course, it should
                    be noted from the outset that the course benefitted
                    enormously from the involvement of a broader team. The
                    librarians at the Bobst Library, and particularly those
                    working within Fales (Charlotte Priddle, Lisa Darms, and
                    Amanda Watson), provided a session for our students teaching
                    them how to use special collections and how to handle its
                    materials. Melitte Buchman from the Bobst Digital Studio
                        (<ref target="http://dlib.nyu.edu/dlts/">http://dlib.nyu.edu/dlts/</ref>) worked with our
                    students both as a group and individually to help them
                    photograph their materials and understand the principles and
                    practices of imaging. The Systems Group within the Courant
                    Institute of Mathematical Sciences (CIMS) provided the
                    technological resources required to host and support the
                    students’ projects. Working within this broader term not
                    only helped better support our students but also offered
                    something in return, as our students provided the library
                    with high resolution tiff images of the materials they had
                    scanned.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Course Syllabus and Structure: Technology</head>
                <p>This course met twice each week: once in a traditional
                    classroom lecture and discussion format; and a second time
                    in a multi-media lab for hands-on work. Both instructors
                    attended all of the lecture classes; in addition, the
                    Computer Science faculty member provided lab sessions, and
                    the English faculty member offered consultation hours
                    immediately following each lab session (in practice, there
                    was much collaboration between the two professors in each of
                    these additional strands).</p>
                <p>Every student was given an account on a production webserver
                        (<ref target="http://cims.nyu.edu/webapps/content/systems/resources/i6">http://cims.nyu.edu/webapps/content/systems/resources/i6</ref>).
                    The Courant Institute provides two servers dedicated to
                    teaching purposes that are used throughout the Computer
                    Science department: a web-server for students to host their
                    sites and a database server running MySQL so that students
                    learn to create and manage their own databases. Students
                    also worked in the Digital Studio (<ref target="http://nyu.libguides.com/digitalstudio">http://nyu.libguides.com/digitalstudio</ref>) and ITS
                    Multi-media lab which provided scanning equipment and
                    appropriate software for image manipulation and web
                    development.</p>
                <p>The course was divided into four units. A list of the
                    technical skills which were taught in each unit is followed
                    by an overview of the pedagogical practices. The first three
                    units each entailed a project-based assignment which is
                    described below as well.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Unit I - Basic web development skills </head>
                <p>In this unit of the course, we covered skills and topics
                    typically taught in a standard introductory course to web
                    design. These topics include:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Mark-up languages: Students were introduced to mark-up
                        languages using HTML5 and CSS3 for rendering basic
                        webpages. </item>
                    <item>Working with images: Students learned to scan objects
                        to specification; with discussion on image resolution
                        and image file types (.tiff, .psd, .jpg, and .gif in
                        particular) in order to understand how to best implement
                        the process from scanning a manuscript through rendering
                        that image for web viewing at appropriate sizes and
                        resolution. Melitte Buchman, the Digital Content Manager
                        at NYU’s Division of Libraries, provided a guest lecture
                        for the class on meta-data standards for image files as
                        well as on accepted scholarly standards for images used
                        for scholarly purposes. </item>
                    <item>File management skills for working on a Unix web
                        server: Students learned to upload files for
                        publication; manage file folders; download files; assess
                        file sizes and permissions; set up .htaccess files to
                        restrict access to portions of their sites when
                        appropriate; and other file management skills. </item>
                </list>
                <p>The project assignment for this unit consisted of a website
                    of a minimum of two pages rendered in HTML5 and CSS3 to
                    describe an author of the student’s choice and publish two
                    or three selections of his or her work.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Unit II - Content Management System (CMS)</head>
                <p>In this unit of the course, each student installed his/her
                    own WordPress (<ref target="http://wordpress.org/">http://wordpress.org</ref>) site to the teaching
                    webserver. The Computer Science faculty member, in
                    consultation with the English Department, decided to use
                    WordPress in this case as Omeka was not supported on the
                    server we used and we believed Drupal is too complex for an
                    introductory class taught within one semester for this
                    student population. As each student installed his or her own
                    WordPress site, they had the opportunity to learn
                    aboutWordPress as an example of a CMS and will be able to
                    carry this knowledge to future CMS projects.</p>
                <p>Specific topics in this unit included:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Themes (<ref target="http://wordpress.org/themes/">http://wordpress.org/themes/</ref>) and
                        child-themes (<ref target="http://codex.wordpress.org/Child_Themes">http://codex.wordpress.org/Child_Themes</ref>) for
                        customization: Each student was expected to select and
                        install a WordPress theme of his or her choice based on
                        the content needs of the site. In addition, each student
                        was required to create a child-theme for further
                        customization; one result is that none of the original
                        themes were recognizable in the final sites.</item>
                    <item>The students explored additional topics in xHTML and
                        CSS to facilitate their site development including the
                        debugging process such as with Firefox Firebug (<ref target="https://getfirebug.com/">https://getfirebug.com/</ref>); implementing
                        external style sheets such as Google Fonts (<ref target="https://www.google.com/fonts">https://www.google.com/fonts</ref>) and
                        understanding and implementing responsive design (the
                        way that a site might change configuration depending on
                        whether the user is viewing the site on a desktop,
                        tablet or mobile phone for example).</item>
                    <item>We taught a brief introduction to PHP where all
                        students were required to modify the source code in at
                        least one PHP script (e.g. all students were required to
                        modify the default footnote to credit the Fales Archives
                        for their materials; this typically required a PHP
                        script modification.)</item>
                    <item>A CMS uses a database “behind the scenes”: Students
                        were introduced to MySQL during lectures. The students
                        were not required to make changes to their data within
                        MySQL but in several instances they required assistance
                        from the Computer Science instructor to do so and these
                        events resulted in positive learning experiences for the
                        class.</item>
                    <item>Throughout this unit, we discussed the underlying
                        structure of a CMS and at the end of this unit, we
                        discussed the differences and similarities among the
                        most commonly used CMS’ in the Digital Humanities
                        (WordPress, Drupal and Omeka; with a brief explanation
                        of Django). We also discussed the role of JavaScript in
                        a CMS but the students did not study or modify
                        JavaScript in this project.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The assignment for this unit of the course consisted of their
                    first draft of an online digital archive based on primary
                    source materials; content included text and images.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Unit III: – XML and the Text Encoding Initiative </head>
                <p>Based on the principle in Computer Science pedagogy of
                    building skills on a strong foundation, we introduced XML in
                    the final development unit of the course. In this unit of
                    the course, we sought to build on the students’
                    understanding and experience with HTML5 as a mark-up
                    language in order to contextualize and introduce XML <ptr target="#mackellar2012"/>; <ptr target="#patterson2005"/> in general and the TEI application of XML in particular. </p>
                <p>Students were introduced to the syntax and structure of XML
                    as it is used in its narrative form for descriptive
                    meta-data; students in this course did not use XML to
                    generate stand-alone datasets. There are significant
                    differences between XML and HTML; the significantly greater
                    flexibility of XML was presented to the students as a means
                    to better annotate and analyze their literary texts.
                    Students already understood that HTML and CSS separate the
                    content of a text from the infinite variety of possible
                    output formats. In this course, we discussed XML
                    implementation to further describe and define the underlying
                    literary structure of a text (e.g. a play consists of acts;
                    and each act may consist of one or more scenes while a novel
                    containing chapters would be encoded differently in order to
                    capture the underlying structure of prose). We further
                    introduced the flexibility and variability available in XML
                    languages to capture meta-data; specifically using XML tags
                    standardized in the literary scholarly community through the
                    international efforts of the TEI Consortium and related
                    projects. The two professors worked closely together to pick
                    a series of examples for the first lectures on TEI/XML in
                    order for the students to make the transition and see the
                    value of XML over plain text or HTML.</p>
                <p>For web presentation of the TEI documents to accompany their
                    websites, students were offered the choice to use CSS or
                    TEI-Boilerplate (<ref target="http://dcl.slis.indiana.edu/teibp/index.html">http://dcl.slis.indiana.edu/teibp/index.html</ref>).
                    XSLT was not taught formally in this class due to the
                    concern that this is a more advanced topic which could
                    intimidate students at this level, especially in light of
                    the complex literary texts that they selected. However, the
                    Computer Science instructor introduced XSLT briefly at this
                    time in the course so that the students would understand the
                    importance of it in web publishing and its wide usage in the
                    TEI community. Several students expressed an interest in
                    XSLT workshops such as those conducted by the Women Writers
                    Project (<ref target="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/outreach/seminars/">http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/outreach/seminars/</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Unit IV: Site Preservation</head>
                <p>Preservation is a very important topic with respect to
                    digital archives from both a literary and a technical
                    perspective. In the final class, we discussed technological
                    aspects of the students’ sites which would require
                    modification for permanent online publication; and how to
                    render a finished CMS site into a static HTML/CSS site for
                    permanent publication (this discussion centered on a plug-in
                    currently available at <ref target="http://wordpress.org/plugins/static-html-output-plugin/">http://wordpress.org/plugins/static-html-output-plugin/</ref>.
                    Note that this plug-in required modification by the
                    instructor in order for the students to use it.). The
                    students understood that such a transition would eliminate
                    any future issues of upgrades to PHP running on the
                    webserver in general and to future versions of WordPress in
                    particular; as well as the value of rendering the site
                    easier for the Systems administrators to support as MySQL
                    would no longer be needed to keep their sites running after
                    such a transition. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Course Syllabus and Structure: Literature</head>
                <p>Interwoven with this technology syllabus was a set of
                    considerations led by the literature professor. This process
                    began at the start of the semester through a discussion
                    about why we might want to digitize texts and what might be
                    gained; what our priorities should be in deciding which
                    texts to digitize; which texts might be most at risk of
                    being lost to us or inaccessible if not digitized; and what
                    might be the consequences of digitizing text. This class
                    discussion generated a humanities agenda (of aims and
                    concerns) to which we returned throughout the course in
                    relation to our practice. The following two weeks were
                    devoted to analyzing existing online literary archives:
                    first a few chosen for collective group attention,<note> For
                            example,<title rend="italic">The Rossetti
                            Web</title> (<ref target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/">http://www.rossettiarchive.org/</ref>); <title rend="italic">The Carlyle Letters Online</title>
                            (<ref target="http://carlyleletters.dukejournals.org/">http://carlyleletters.dukejournals.org/</ref>);
                            <title rend="italic">The Shelley-Godwin
                            Archive</title> (<ref target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/</ref>). </note>
                    and then those chosen by the students which they analyzed in
                    ten minute presentations to the class. Students were given a
                    list of criteria for the scholarly evaluation of such sites,
                    but also asked to think more generally about what the online
                    presentation of the material adds (what it might enable the
                    user to do with the text that they couldn’t otherwise do)
                    and how it might change our reading of the material
                    presented. It is through this discussion that one of the key
                    practices of the course, from a humanities perspective, was
                    introduced: analyzing how site-building and presentational
                    decisions are also in key part interpretative decisions that
                    determine how the material is read. The lessons learned from
                    this analysis fed into their own project development in
                    various ways, particularly in relation to their design of
                    site architecture and navigations. For one student working
                    with a nineteenth-century manuscript of a novella, for
                    example, a key opportunity arose from the author’s practice
                    of dating his work on the manuscript. The student designed
                    menu options that allowed the user to access the manuscript
                    according either to date of composition or chapter
                    structure. This enabled the correlation of the work the
                    author was doing on the manuscript on a particular day with
                    the concerns he expressed in letters written on or around
                    the same day.</p>
                <p>For the literary component of this first section of the
                    course, essays such as Kenneth M. Price’s piece on
                        <q>Electronic Scholarly Editions</q> were used to
                    introduce many of the key concerns <ptr target="#price2013"/>. However, students were also asked to engage with
                    thoughts about the practice of textual editing more
                    generally and to consider the kinds of benefits the online
                    environment might offer over the traditional paper-based
                    environment. The issues discussed here ranged from the
                    ability to rectify mistakes relatively easily in digital
                    editions as opposed to runs of printed texts, to the kind of
                    high-level interactivity and hypertextuality that online
                    archives might offer. </p>
                <p>Teaching the students about metadata was a crucial part of
                    the first half of this course and the topic was introduced,
                    from the literary-studies perspective, through the scholarly
                    debate around textual materiality. The technical information
                    about metadata standards was provided through the online
                    pamphlet — <title rend="quotes">Understanding
                        Metadata</title> – published by the National Information
                    Standards Organization (<ref target="http://www.niso.org/publications/press/UnderstandingMetadata.pdf">http://www.niso.org/publications/press/UnderstandingMetadata.pdf</ref>),
                    but that was really secondary to getting students to first
                    consider <emph>why</emph> it might be important to record
                    and represent certain types of information about the texts
                    they were digitizing, and <emph>what</emph> they would want
                    to record in order to capture various different aspects of
                    the textual object. To bring this issue alive from the
                    perspective of literary scholarship, the students were given
                    some relevant literary scholarship in advance of the class.
                    For example, Nicholas Frankel has written about the
                    significance of reading text within the context of the book
                    as a material object, using as his example Oscar Wilde’s
                        <title rend="italic">Poems</title> – a beautiful and
                    elaborately-designed book shown to them in the University’s
                    special collections the following week <ptr target="#frankel2000"/>. This scholarly work gave an
                    agenda to thinking about textual materiality and provided a
                    powerful example of the kinds of interests humanities
                    researchers might have in a book’s extra-textual features,
                    and how those features might be considered necessary for the
                    interpretation of a text. For the class itself, the
                    literature professor brought in some examples of books that
                    raised interesting issues of materiality, and discussed with
                    the students which aspects they would want to represent in a
                    digital rendition and how they would go about giving that
                    information in the form of metadata. These examples included
                    not only texts that are elaborate or unusual in their
                    material instantiation but, for example, a fairly plain
                    mid-twentieth-century book that had an old photo tucked
                    inside the front cover; it was not clear the photo had any
                    relevance to the book other than through the life of a
                    previous owner, and the students were asked to discuss what
                    they would do with it in their digitization process. The
                    students were also asked to bring in any textual-object of
                    their choice and talk briefly — and in light of the kinds of
                    issues they had seen explored in the set reading — about
                    what and how they would want to represent it in addition to
                    its text. </p>
                <p>The benefit of approaching the issue of metadata through
                    literary scholarship around textual materiality was that it
                    enabled a much deeper engagement with the issues of creating
                    a digital representation. These would not have emerged had
                    we simply instructed the students of the need to record, for
                    example, the particularities of the place, date, and
                    publication of the particular edition they were digitizing,
                    or the physical location and call number of the manuscript
                    they might be working with. The discussion around the
                    importance of issues of materiality to the interpretation of
                    text brought to light all kinds of other aspects of the
                    physical text that might be important in representing it in
                    a digital format: both through metadata and through the
                    photographs and scans they were to create. For example, we
                    discussed the importance of giving the online reader images
                    of the cover and front-pages and end-pages of a text, and
                    considered the ways in which sites that had not done so
                    might limit the questions scholars could ask of the texts
                    they represent. In light of recent scholarship on the
                    history of paper, we also considered the potential
                    importance of giving information such as the type and weight
                    of paper used as part of the metadata, and the significance
                    of such information to certain kinds of scholarly questions
                    (see <ptr target="#price2012"/>). </p>
                <p>Issues of materiality central to the course were given an
                    interesting twist through one student’s focus on
                    contemporary <q>zines</q>. Often created by hand rather than
                    on a computer, and exploiting a rawness that appeared to
                    oppose the aesthetics of new technologies, the students were
                    encouraged to think about how these pieces posed interesting
                    theoretical, and sometimes practical, questions for the
                    process of digitization. One zine in particular, which was
                    folded in such a way as to give the potential for many
                    different views of its content depending on how it was
                    unfolded, exploited the three-dimensional possibilities of
                    paper in space. Although with enough separate images from
                    different angles (or within a video or animation), these
                    possibilities could be captured and uploaded to the digital
                    archive, the zine was clearly designed to challenge the
                    two-dimensional textuality of both the traditional codex
                    technology and digital textuality. The introduction of
                    literary-theoretical frames for thinking about the insistent
                    materiality of these items led the student to write to the
                    authors with questions both about their intentions and to
                    ask permission to digitize the zines. The replies were often
                    revealing of a reaction against digital culture and can be
                    summarized with reference to the <title rend="quotes">8
                        ball</title> collective website, where they insist on
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">MORE ZINING, LESS BLOGGING</quote>
                        (<ref target="http://8ballzinefair.com/ABOUT">http://8ballzinefair.com/ABOUT</ref>). By encouraging
                    the group to think about what it means to digitize items
                    that were created (in part, at least) in opposition to
                    digital culture, we were able to provide a particularly
                    interesting and challenging perspective on the processes the
                    students were undertaking.</p>
                <p>This discussion about the material instantiation of text (in
                    relation to very varied examples from the nineteenth to the
                    twenty-first century) led by the literature professor was
                    part of the preparation for students to go into the
                    university library’s special collections department to
                    choose the materials they wanted to digitize. Attending a
                    session organized by the library staff, the students learned
                    about the collection, and how to handle its materials. The
                    library staff also covered copyright issues that continued
                    to play an important role in class discussions throughout
                    the course as permissions were clarified, sought and
                    granted. The following weeks of the course focused, from the
                    literature perspective, on helping the students to choose
                    their texts; and culminated in using one of the classes to
                    present their materials and discuss them with the other
                    students in the class. At the presentation the students were
                    asked to give a rationale for their choices, including
                    thoughts on the textual, critical/historical and technical
                    significance of their selection. This discussion, in a
                    roundtable format, was particularly useful because the
                    students had chosen very different kinds of materials to
                    digitize: sharing their work with each other enabled them to
                    learn from the very different challenges they were each
                    facing, and to broaden their understanding beyond the issues
                    their own materials posed. Over the next couple of weeks,
                    when the class time was devoted primarily to the technical
                    issues of building their sites, it was possible to ensure
                    the <soCalled>literary</soCalled> considerations stayed with
                    them by asking them all the time to think about and develop
                    that connection between the building decisions they were
                    making in their archives and the issues of textuality and
                    materiality introduced earlier. This was something the
                    literature professor took up with students particularly
                    during the lab sessions when there was the opportunity to
                    address these issues individually and to encourage them to
                    think about the particular problems and possibilities their
                    own materials offered. </p>
                <p>We brought all of this back into class again in week eight,
                    when almost the whole session was devoted to another
                    literature-led roundtable with each student presenting their
                    site under construction and explaining in ten minutes why
                    they had chosen the proposed site architecture and to give a
                    rationale, from a literary and scholarly perspective, for
                    the technical choices they had made. They were asked to
                    consider not just how their materials could best be
                    presented, but also who their intended audience was and how
                    a desire to be useful and relevant to a broad audience might
                    inflect the design of their sites. At this point the
                    students were asked to consider what kind of interest their
                    texts might hold within current scholarly fields of enquiry
                    and how to connect with and aid those users, but also how
                    they might make their sites sustainable in a literary,
                    rather than a technological sense, by keeping their
                    materials open as far as possible to the kinds of questions
                    future users might want to ask of them that we cannot now
                    necessarily predict. As an example, introducing archives
                    that had not digitized the advertisements at the back of the
                    nineteenth-century periodicals they represented, we
                    discussed how such materials were now considered of great
                    interest to scholars both in their own right and as context
                    for the articles that had been digitized. All the students
                    reported making changes to their sites as a result of the
                    reflective process they undertook in presenting their
                    rationale to others. Listening to each others’ presentations
                    and discussing them afterwards also helped significantly in
                    sharing good practice and introducing new possibilities for
                    each project. At the end of each presentation the student
                    was asked what they might enable through their digitization
                    of the text that could not be done before. Here they were
                    asked to go beyond the more obvious answers that related to
                    preservation and access to think about how their
                    digitization strategy enabled the texts to ask new questions
                    of themselves; the ensuing discussion was particularly
                    formative for shaping the next phase of site building the
                    students undertook in the course.</p>
                <p>The second half of this session was devoted to a round-up of
                    the challenges students were facing with their projects from
                    a literary, rather than technological, perspective. The
                    agenda here was determined in key part by the problems, and
                    solutions, that had arisen with students individually in the
                    lab sessions (which often highlighted more general issues
                    they should all consider). The agenda included a discussion
                    of issues around the principles of manuscript transcription.
                    Here the students were invited to consider the well-worked
                    out transcription statement represented in a site such as
                    the Bentham letters (given there in full to aid
                    crowd-sourced transcription) and how it might help them
                    develop principles for their own transcription (<ref target="http://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/">http://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/</ref>).
                    Editorial experience was also used to encourage the students
                    to think about the significance of recording uncertainty,
                    introducing the need to balance a natural desire for
                    definitive and interpretative transcriptions with a strategy
                    that left open possibilities for other meanings that might
                    become relevant in the future. Also raised here was the
                    general, and related, issue of fidelity versus
                    clarity/usability, and clutter versus functionality, to help
                    the students think about the challenges they were all facing
                    in deciding how much detail to present and how many
                    different functions to build into their sites. The
                    possibility of offering different views of the material, so
                    a reader could choose either a simple or more complex view
                    and functionality, was a particularly useful point around
                    which the professors could role-model the interplay of
                    technical and scholarly considerations. Another major topic
                    at this point was the use of visualization and mapping to
                    enable the students to present data in new ways. With one
                    student using a map to locate manuscripts geographically, we
                    were able to introduce the idea of using visualizing more
                    generally in other, non-geographical, ways to help get more
                    out of their data. For example, another student had been
                    wondering which of the many and varied published editions of
                    her novella to provide alongside the manuscript version she
                    was digitizing; one solution discussed with her was to use
                    the software tool Juxta (<ref target="http://www.juxtasoftware.org/">http://www.juxtasoftware.org/</ref>) to show the
                    relationship between the manuscript and various different
                    published editions, showing visually the areas of greatest
                    similarly and difference between them. </p>
                <p>This process of reflecting on the literary issues at stake in
                    their building procedures ended with the students being
                    asked to imagine what they might enable their users to do
                    with their materials in an ideal world — and what the
                    literary or scholarly value of those digital experiments
                    might be. This was the basis for a discussion of how the
                    course instructors might be able to help the students
                    implement some of those ideas in a realistic form within the
                    time and resources available. For example, a student who was
                    interested in large-scale crowd-sourced transcription
                    created a game-inspired transcription quiz in the form of a
                    WordPress blog. She used this to address some of the
                    challenges of legibility posed by the author’s hand-written
                    marginal comments in the type-written manuscript she was
                    digitizing. Another student who was digitizing an archive of
                    mid-twentieth-century letters written from New York City
                    plotted the addresses from which they were sent on a
                    historically accurate map of the city. She used KML (a
                    mark-up language based on XML for use with Google Maps) to
                    identify the geographical positions, and then superimposed a
                    map from the archives of the New York Public Library over
                    the Google map to make the mapping historically relevant.
                    Adding a geographical component to her work enabled her to
                    analyze the importance of the location of writing to its
                    content — a process that revealed interesting
                    connections.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Text Encoding: Further Integrating Technological and
                    Literary Considerations </head>
                <p>The course culminated in teaching encoding to the students so
                    that they could add a further layer of information to their
                    sites, experimenting with what the TEI might be able to
                    offer their projects. First we used the <title rend="quotes">The Red Wheelbarrow</title> by William Carlos Williams
                    in order to introduce mark-up of basic metadata and poetic
                    structure from a technical perspective. Then we turned to a
                    passage from <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> and a
                    chapter from <title rend="italic">Huckleberry Finn</title>
                    to teach the TEI conventions for encoding drama and prose.
                    We taught this collaboratively, going through the literary
                    passages with the students identifying which features one
                    might want to encode, and showing how those features would
                    be rendered in the XML. The Shakespeare example enabled us
                    initially to introduce the idea of the TEI header and the
                    kind of metadata that could be recorded there: both in
                    relation to the creation of the electronic edition, and in
                    relation to the specificities of the edition drawn on for
                    digitization. It also enabled us to show some of the key
                    tags and attributes for working with dramatic text. Chapter
                    twenty-one from the Mark Twain novel was chosen to enable a
                    more complex engagement with TEI through its playfulness
                    with genre: here the characters engage in a muddled and
                    half-remembered enactment of a Shakespeare play. The
                    play-acting within the text enabled us to show how one might
                    mix prose and drama tags to render the text in interesting
                    and useful ways. In addition, the text invited a series of
                    notes in the encoding disentangling the lines from different
                    Shakespeare plays that were muddled together in a single
                    soliloquy. The chapter also has instances of southern
                    dialect that could be translated in the text encoding (thus
                    rendering it searchable in standard English), and other
                    textual features (such as a playbill centered in the middle
                    of a page) that raised interesting questions about encoding
                    practice. </p>
                <p>Following on from this class teaching the language of the
                    TEI, the literature faculty member led another session
                    focusing on the literary and critical significance of
                    encoding. The chapter <title rend="italic">The Text Encoding
                        Initiative and the Study of Literature</title> by James
                    Cummings provided a good starting point for the students to
                    think about the history of the initiative and its more
                    theoretical and critical implications <ptr target="#cummings2013"/>. The students had read this
                    chapter in advance of the class, and had also prepared their
                    own notes towards the encoding of the first textual example
                    we looked at in this session: Shakespeare’s Sonnet no. 116.
                    Working through the sonnet with them gave a chance to think
                    about a different genre through TEI. Starting with a
                    literary critical reading of the sonnet, the students were
                    asked to think about the rhyme scheme and meter. Noting the
                    possibility of rendering the overall meter and rhyme scheme
                    in the header, we also discussed, for example, the
                    implications of the fact that the rhyme scheme does not in
                    fact appear to comply to this scheme in modern English, and
                    how we might reflect on that in the TEI. Similarly the
                    opening lines of the poem (which invoke the liturgy of the
                    marriage ceremony) are not in the standard iambic meter, and
                    this enabled us to discuss what kind of metrical mark-up and
                    interpretation might be noted through the TEI. The goal here
                    was to begin to think about the variety of purposes for
                    which encoding might be used, and to start to show the
                    variety of ways one can note a particular feature of the
                    text through the TEI depending on what one wants to achieve. </p>
                <p>Having worked through the sonnet in detail, we then gave them
                    the poem <title rend="quotes">Love Sonnet</title> by John
                    Updike and asked them how they would encode it <ptr target="#updike1969" loc="66"/>. The poem has one
                    complete first line (<q>In Love’s rubber
                        armor I come to you</q>’) but the subsequent
                    thirteen <q>lines</q> of the sonnet are indicated purely by
                    a letter marking the position on the page where each line
                    would end. The letter given to mark each line ending
                    crucially also represents the strict rhyme scheme of the
                    sonnet. From a technological perspective, the aim of this
                    exercise was to get the student to produce an XML encoding,
                    but from a literary perspective it was also to ask students
                    to think about the act of encoding and to recognize the poem
                    as itself in some ways a challenge to some of the
                    structuralist assumptions upon which TEI is founded. The
                    poem is a post-modern parody of the conventional nature of
                    love poetry, gesturing towards the generic, iterable and
                    predictable nature of the romantic sonnet. As such, the poem
                    is a gesture towards a sonnet rather than a sonnet itself,
                    and in this way it raises questions about the kinds of
                    classifications on which encoding is based. The poem has
                    fourteen lines, and the rhyme scheme one would expect from a
                    Shakespearian sonnet, but does that make it a sonnet, and
                    should it be identified in that way in the TEI? What happens
                    if we try to encode this poem in the way we tagged the
                    Shakespeare sonnet? What questions does this ask of the
                    poem, and what might it miss or misrepresent? To encode this
                    poem as a sonnet is to explain its own joke in a rather
                    heavy-handed way, but the joke is also in some sense on the
                    process of encoding, which the playfulness of the poem seems
                    to evade. Looking at this poem with the students aimed,
                    then, to explore and question in practice some of the issues
                    that Jerome McGann identified when he wrote that because the
                    TEI <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann2001">treats the humanities corpus –
                        typically works of imagination – as informational
                        structures, it ipso facto violates some of the most
                        basic reading practices of the humanities community,
                        scholarly as well as popular</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mcgann2001" loc="139"/></cit>. Overall, then, the
                    seminar introduced a theoretical engagement with the TEI as
                    well as teaching students how to use XML. </p>
                <p>It was in light of this reflective engagement with the TEI —
                    on its possible limitations and problems as well as its
                    benefits — that we asked the students to consider TEI in
                    relation to their own projects. The key question was what
                    problems could TEI solve for them, and what could it offer
                    the user of the site that was currently not otherwise
                    possible. The work we did in class on encoding various
                    genres of literary text complemented the work we did with
                    the students in the lab session which focused primarily
                    around their own project work with manuscripts. One key area
                    for discussion here was the potential for the TEI to render
                    searchable the textual-content captured and presented
                    primarily through images. The students’ work with
                    hand-written manuscripts presented particularly interesting
                    possibilities here, in relation to providing options for the
                    interpretation of complex and problematic script, and for
                    presenting issues of manuscript materiality. For example, a
                    project digitizing nineteenth-century hand-written letters,
                    in which additions were often placed in the gaps on the
                    page, prompted class debate on how best to render this text
                    and useful discussion about the complementarity of
                    manuscript image and text encoding. In addition to
                    transcription, the students also used the TEI to note
                    additional contextual information as well as the usual
                    metadata. For example, the student who digitized letters
                    written from various locations in New York City used the TEI
                    to encode the geographical data. Another used the TEI to add
                    information about the hand-drawn images that appeared in her
                    text, thus enabling a further explanatory and interpretative
                    commentary that altered the way the text would be read.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Assessment</head>
                <p>The structure of the assessment reflected the structure of
                    the course more generally in that we began with smaller
                    separate technical and literary assignments and then brought
                    the two together in the main project. The first two
                    assignments (building a small website for the purposes of
                    studying HTML and CSS; and evaluating existing on-line
                    text-archive sites) were assessed by the Computer Science
                    and English faculty members respectively. The final online
                    digital archive and the TEI-encoded literary texts were
                    assessed by the two faculty members together. The course
                    ended with the students formally presenting their sites to
                    the group for the final assessment in order to maintain the
                    group dynamic and the sense of peer-sharing which had been
                    so important throughout the course.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>Just as the Digital Humanities is an emerging field, so is
                    the pedagogy associated with it. Case studies such as those
                    described in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Pedagogy: Practices, Principles, and Politics</title>
                    <ptr target="#hirsch2012"/> show a variety of pedagogical
                    goals both within and between different disciplinary areas
                    in the Humanities. Lists of competencies such as those cited
                    in <title rend="italic">Specification 3</title> in <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#burdick2012" loc="132–133"/> offer a different
                    approach: documenting specific technical skills required for
                    humanities students and scholars to successfully create and
                    implement computational and digitally-based research and
                    publications. Our collaborative approach — of building on
                    principles of Computer Science pedagogy in combination with
                    teaching principles of digital literary scholarship — aimed
                    to provide our students with the best of both worlds.</p>
                <p>The principles of our collaboration might be summarized under
                    four points. The first being the preparation we did before
                    the course: planning how we would interconnect the concerns
                    of our respective disciplines conceptually and practically
                    in relation to the structure of each class. The second being
                    the weekly meetings we had to monitor and adjust the course
                    content and pedagogical approach. The third category relates
                    to the differences in disciplinary teaching methods. Our
                    collaboration involved an integration, or alternation, of
                    the seminar — or roundtable — discursive style of the
                    humanities with the more lecture-driven style of Computer
                    Science complemented with lab sessions. Fourth, and finally,
                    we sought to role-model interdisciplinary collaboration in
                    various ways throughout the class, showing the students that
                    the same question might have two different answers: one
                    technical and one from a scholarly humanities perspective;
                    we then pursued the connections through discussion with the
                    class, and through discussion with each other in front of
                    the class. While at the start of the course we presented the
                    introductory technological skills and the key humanities
                    questions separately, the goal was to achieve convergence of
                    these perspectives over the length of the course by teaching
                    the students to see every technical decision they made in
                    building their sites as an interpretative gesture (and to
                    see their interpretative and critical analyses as having a
                    technical embodiment). </p>
                <p>Various problems and challenges arose as we taught the
                    course. For example, the imaging of the primary materials
                    occurred early on in the semester and generated a great deal
                    of enthusiasm that resulted in students imaging more
                    material than they could reasonably work with; in the future
                    we would ask students to think more carefully at this stage
                    to limit the focus and give more scope for the qualitative
                    rather than quantitative work. We also ran into problems
                    with the ever-changing technological environment. For
                    example, Google was phasing out support for KML, which
                    required a new solution to be found for one student’s
                    mapping work; and TEI-Boilerplate turned out to serve our
                    purposes less well than expected in the CMS environment. In
                    terms of pedagogical approaches, we adapted the course as it
                    progressed to fit the needs of the students; in particular,
                    we worked to build in greater opportunities for discussion
                    and sharing information between the students and their
                    respective projects. In addition, once we began working with
                    the students on their individual projects, we decided to use
                    the particular challenges they were facing with their
                    materials as our examples in the class lectures. </p>
                <p>We have engaged with other departments to see how the course
                    might be modified to become suitable for a broader range of
                    humanities students. Our initial assessment suggests there
                    would be ways to develop the course to cater to students
                    from a range of disciplines in Literature and History. For
                    example, introducing EAD (Encoded Archival Description: <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/ead/">http://www.loc.gov/ead/</ref>) along with TEI as
                    examples of XML languages would be useful for history
                    students and complement work done by literature students and
                    history students using TEI with manuscripts and documents.
                    The addition of an historian to our teaching team would be
                    essential in enabling us to expand our interdisciplinary
                    conceptualization and theorization of the online archive in
                    conjunction with this expanded technological syllabus.
                    Having taught the course once we are also considering the
                    following changes for the second iteration: the addition of
                    a lecture on XSLT formatting the TEI examples used earlier
                    in the class; and the addition of more reading and
                    discussion on the theory of TEI.</p>
                <p>Finally, we have found that teaching collaboratively enabled
                    us to think about new research practices. This connection
                    has not always been obvious:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#leblanc2010">From the outset, it was clear that
                        teaching together in connected courses would be good for
                        our students. What was not so clear was how good it
                        would be for the faculty’s professional development and
                        research output.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#leblanc2010"/>
                </cit>
                <p>Yet, as we worked together, we better appreciated the overlay
                    of our fields of study, and ideas for new research
                    collaborations emerged. Digital Humanities is an area in
                    which collaboration can be particularly valuable to ensure a
                    depth and breadth of both technical and conceptual
                    knowledge, and through our collaboration we felt able to
                    explore profound methodological intersections between the
                    fields of technology and the humanities. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix I: Course Description and Syllabus</head>
                <p>(<ref target="http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall13/ENGL-GA.2971-001/DT_index_fa13.php">http://cs.nyu.edu/courses/fall13/ENGL-GA.2971-001/DT_index_fa13.php</ref>)</p>
                <p>The interface of technology and the humanities represents a
                    key to the future, yet many students feel they lack the
                    skills to access this potential. This course offers an
                    introduction to web development and digital publication
                    especially created for students in the Humanities, with a
                    view to equipping you with knowledge foundational for
                    reflective engagement with the new media of literary
                    creation and dissemination. Students will survey the
                    principles of current technologies and apply them through
                    practice as they learn the skills and techniques for
                    formatting and publishing archival materials in a web-based
                    environment. The course builds towards the creation of a
                    digital edition, giving you the opportunity to work with
                    primary source materials available through NYU's rich
                    archival collections (these include a wide variety of
                    printed texts, manuscripts and images from which to select
                    according to your interests).</p>
                <p>The course will consist of a traditional classroom lecture
                    and discussion format as well as computer lab sessions to
                    promote and assist students as they work on each of their
                    three projects in this course. Each student will have an
                    account on a production webserver to post their work and
                    learn to install and configure a WordPress site specifically
                    tailored to his or her primary source materials. Topics and
                    assigned projects will begin with an introduction to mark-up
                    languages and building a site of related web pages followed
                    by a project centered on encoding and annotating digital
                    texts for scholarly purposes. The final project involves
                    photographing or scanning, transcribing, and encoding
                    digital texts to build an online archive.</p>
                <table>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Week</cell>
                        <cell>Topics Covered</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour
                                –Literature: introduction to digitization /
                                literary projects</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour – Technology: Introduction to
                                web design, mark-up languages and related
                                technologies.</p><p>Lab - Hands-on: Project #1 -
                                Unix; HTML, xHTML, CSS </p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour –
                                Technology: Advanced CSS; Web-authoring
                                software; Integration of text and graphics on
                                the web</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>
                                hour – Literature: Introduction to selected
                                scholarly literary archival sites and critical
                                discussion.</p><p>Lab: Hands-on: Project #1
                                continued</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour –
                                Literature: Students present the scholarly
                                literary sites to the class which they have
                                prepared in assignment #1followed by
                                discussion.</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour – Technology: Advanced
                                CSS</p><p>Lab: Hands-on: Project #1 - Advanced
                                CSS</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour –
                                Technology: Working with image files: file types
                                and how to use them (GIF, JPG, PNG for use on
                                the web as well as RAW, TIFF, PSD for archival
                                purposes); discussion on image compression,
                                digitization standards, and related topics;
                                instructions on scanning images using a flat-bed
                                scanner as well as working with cameras to
                                capture images of archival materials.</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour –
                                Literature: Introduction to concepts in Metadata
                                and building their collection; preparation for
                                session in the archives on the next
                                day.</p><p>Lab: Guest Lecture: Meeting with
                                Library and Fales Archives staff to discuss
                                working with primary source materials,
                                instructions on handling the materials, and
                                copyright issues.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour –
                                Technology: Guest Lecture in the digital imaging
                                lab. </p><p>The students worked in the imaging
                                lab with both professors present to accomplish
                                the following in the second hour: </p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour -
                                Technology: hands-on training on scanning and
                                photographing primary source materials; review
                                of Library of Congress and related standards;
                                overview of file management practices.
                                    </p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour
                                – Literature: approval of the primary source
                                materials selected. </p><p>Lab: Project #2.
                                Students are requested to set up a web page
                                hosting sample images for review.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Part 1 (1.5 hours): Technology – Introduction
                                to working with a CMS; in-class demonstration of
                                a WordPress installation, configuration and
                                implementation; as well as themes modification
                                and downloading themes appropriate the students’
                                selected archival materials. </p><p>Part 2 –
                                Literature: ½ hour: Round table discussion as
                                each student describes his/her content selection
                                and literary/scholarly focus.</p><p>Lab: Project
                                #2 – Install the CMS and start building the
                                webpages for the contextualization
                                (introduction, bibliography and related pages);
                                configure the “child-theme”; continue working
                                with images </p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Technology Class – 2 hours: WordPress and CMS
                                concepts; in-class demonstration of site
                                customization; integration of text and
                                images.</p><p>Lab: Project #2 Students begin
                                building the cataloguing section of the
                                site.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Literature Class – 2 hours: discussion on
                                problems and possibilities that students
                                encounter with their selected texts (including
                                discussion of the principles of manuscript
                                transcription).</p><p>Lab: Project #2 – Students
                                continue work on their project.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Technology – 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                                hour: ½ hour each on technical problems and
                                questions students have about their individual
                                sites; and a summary on the contents expected
                                for the technical “about” page on the
                                site.</p><p>Technology 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour: Introduction to XML, encoding
                                text and XML-TEI.</p><p>Literature: poems by
                                William Carlos Williams.</p><p>Lab: Hands-on:
                                Completion of Project #2; Students begin work on
                                Project #3 (XML-TEI)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1st hour: Technology: Class lecture and
                                discussion on XML-TEI.</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour:
                                Technology/Literature: Encoding Hamlet’s <hi rend="italic">Soliloquy</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Soliloquy</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Huck Finn</hi> (Chapter 21,
                                excerpt) in XML-TEI. Students are asked to
                                encode Shakespeare’s Sonnet 116 for the
                                following week.</p><p>Lab: Project #3 – XML-TEI,
                                continued</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1.5 hours: Literature - Case study on
                                sonnets.</p><p>Last ½ hour: Technology -
                                introduction to XSL/ XSLT</p><p>Lab: Project #3
                                – XML-TEI, continued</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour:
                                Technology Site sustainability (e.g. creating a
                                static HTML/CSS site from a CMS site for
                                preservation purposes and permanent
                                installations and technical questions that came
                                up.</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour:
                                Literature – Discussion on the “about”
                                statements from a literary
                                perspective.</p><p>Lab: Completion of materials
                                and preparation for class
                            presentations.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> hour: Student
                                Presentations in lieu of a final exam</p><p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> hour: Technology
                                – Additional requested topics included WordPress
                                for blogging and considerations in
                                crowd-sourcing; using Oxygen for editing XML;
                                and other technical questions and topics that
                                arose as students worked on their
                            sites.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Student Presentations in lieu of a final
                                exam.</p><p>Discussion on future projects and
                                where to go from here.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Assessment and Grade Distribution:</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Assignment #1 (Humanities site evaluation) – 10% of
                        the final grade</item>
                    <item>Assignment #2 (Proposal for project #2 – selection of
                        Fales materials, including rationale) – included in the
                        project #2 grade</item>
                    <item>Project #1 – Build a unified site on an author of the
                        student’s choice - 20% of the final grade</item>
                    <item>Project #2 – Online digital archive based on primary
                        source materials using WordPress - 40% of the final
                        grade. </item>
                    <item>Project #3 – Use TEI to encode several representative
                        samples of literary texts in the student’s archival site
                        - 30% of the final grade</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>

                <bibl label="Adams 2007" xml:id="adams2007">Adams, D. Robert.
                        <title rend="quotes">Integration early: a new approach
                        to teaching web application development.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">J. Comput. Sci. Coll.</title> 23, 1
                    (October 2007), 97-104.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bills and Canosa 2007" xml:id="bills2007"> Dianne
                    P. Bills and Roxanne L. Canosa. <title rend="quotes">Sharing
                        introductory programming curriculum across
                        disciplines.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings
                        of the 8th ACM SIGITE conference on Information
                        technology education</title> (SIGITE 2007). ACM, New
                    York, NY, USA, 99-106. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Bunde and Engel 2010a" xml:id="bunde2010a">
                    <title rend="quotes">Computing in the Humanities: An
                        Interdisciplinary Partnership in Undergraduate
                        Education.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Archival
                        Organization</title>, 1533-2756, Volume 8, Issue 2,
                    2010, 149–159</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bunde and Engel 2010b" xml:id="bunde2010b">Bunde,
                    Janet and Deena Engel. <title rend="quotes">An
                        Inter-Disciplinary Approach to Web Programming: A
                        Collaboration Between the University Archives and the
                        Department of Computer Science,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Conference</title>,
                    London.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Burdick et al 2012" xml:id="burdick2012"> Burdick,
                    Anne, Johanna Drucker, Peter Lunenfield, Todd Presner,
                    Jeffrey Schnapp. <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts:
                    MIT Press (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Chang and Lee 2010" xml:id="chang2010">Chang,
                    Ling-Chian and Greg C. Lee. <title rend="quotes">A
                        team-teaching model for practicing project-based
                        learning in high school: Collaboration between computer
                        and subject teachers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Comput. Educ.</title> 55, 3 (November
                    2010), 961-969. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Connolly, 2011" xml:id="connolly2011"> Connolly,
                    Randy W. <title rend="quotes">Awakening Rip Van Winkle:
                        modernizing the computer science web curriculum.</title>
                    In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 16th annual joint
                        conference on Innovation and technology in computer
                        science education</title> (ITiCSE 2011). ACM, New York,
                    NY, USA, 18-22. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Cummings 2013" xml:id="cummings2013"> Cummings,
                    James. <title rend="quotes">The Text Encoding Initiative and
                        the Study of Literature.</title> In <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title>, ed.
                    Ray Siemens and Susan Schreibman. Chichester, West Sussex:
                    Blackwell. 451-457.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Engel 2013" xml:id="engel2013"> Engel, Deena.
                        <title rend="italic">Embracing the Digital Humanities: A
                        Course on Computing in the Humanities for Undergraduate
                        Computer Science Minor Students</title>
                    <ref target="http://db.grinnell.edu/sigcse/sigcse2013/Program/viewAcceptedProposal.pdf?sessionType=poster&amp;sessionNumber=2">http://db.grinnell.edu/sigcse/sigcse2013/Program/viewAcceptedProposal.pdf?sessionType=poster&amp;sessionNumber=2</ref>
                    SIGCSE 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Frankel 2000" xml:id="frankel2000"> Frankel,
                    Nicholas. <title rend="italic">Oscar Wilde’s Decorated
                        Books</title>. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.
                    2000.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gousie 2006" xml:id="gousie2006"> Gousie, Michael
                    B. <title rend="quotes">A robust web programming and
                        graphics course for non-majors.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SIGCSE Bull.</title> 38, 1 (March
                    2006), 72-76. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Greenberg et al 2012" xml:id="greenberg2012">
                    Greenberg, Ira, Deepak Kumar, and Dianna Xu. <title rend="quotes">Creative coding and visual portfolios for
                        CS1.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        43rd ACM technical symposium on Computer Science
                        Education</title> (SIGCSE 2012). ACM, New York, NY, USA,
                    247-252. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Gülbahar and Tinmaz 2006" xml:id="gülbahar2006">
                    Gülbahar, Yasemin and Hasan Tinmaz. <ref target="http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ728907.pdf">http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ728907.pdf</ref>.
                        <title rend="italic">Implementing Project-Based
                        Learning</title>, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Guzdial and Forte 2005" xml:id="guzdial2005">
                    Guzdial, Mark and Andrea Forte. <title rend="quotes">Design
                        process for a non-majors computing course.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SIGCSE Bull.</title> 37, 1 (February
                    2005), 361-365. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Guzdial 2010" xml:id="guzdial2010"> Guzdial, Mark.
                        <title rend="quotes">Does contextualized computing
                        education help?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ACM Inroads</title> 1, 4 (December
                    2010), 4-6. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Guzdial et al 2012" xml:id="guzdial2012"> Guzdial,
                    Mark, Barbara J. Ericson, Tom McKlin, and Shelly Engelman.
                        <title rend="quotes">A statewide survey on computing
                        education pathways and influences: factors in broadening
                        participation in computing.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ninth annual
                        international conference on International computing
                        education research</title> (ICER 2012). ACM, New York,
                    NY, USA, 143-150. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Hirsch 2012" xml:id="hirsch2012"> Hirsch, Brett D.,
                    Ed. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy:
                        Practices, Principles and Politics</title>, Cambridge,
                    UK: OpenBook Publishers (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Kurkovsky 2007" xml:id="kurkovsky2007"> Kurkovsky,
                    Stan. <title rend="quotes">Making computing attractive for
                        non-majors: a course design.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">J. Comput. Small Coll.</title> 22, 3
                    (January 2007), 90-97.</bibl>
                <bibl label="LeBlanc et al 2010" xml:id="leblanc2010"> LeBlanc,
                    Mark D., Tom Armstrong, and Michael B. Gousie. <title rend="quotes">Connecting across campus.</title> In
                        <title rend="quotes">Proceedings of the 41st ACM
                        technical symposium on Computer science
                        education</title> (SIGCSE 2010). ACM, New York, NY, USA,
                    52-56. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Liu and Phelps 2011" xml:id="liu2011"> Liu, Yi and
                    Gita Phelps. <title rend="quotes">Challenges and
                        professional tools used when teaching web
                        programming.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">J. Comput. Sci. Coll.</title> 26, 5
                    (May 2011), 116-121.</bibl>
                <bibl label="MacKellar 2012" xml:id="mackellar2012"> MacKellar,
                    Bonnie K. <title rend="quotes">An XML course as a
                        springboard for teaching fundamental computer science
                        ideas.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">J. Comput. Sci. Coll.</title> 27, 3
                    (January 2012), 15-21. </bibl>
                <bibl label="McGann 2001" xml:id="mcgann2001"> McGann, Jerome.
                        <title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality: Literature
                        after the World Wide Web</title>. New York, Palgrave:
                    2001.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Mendes et al 2012" xml:id="mendes2012"> Mendes,
                    Antonio Jose, Anabela Gomes, Amilcar Cardoso, and Luis
                    Paquete. <title rend="quotes">Increasing student commitment
                        in introductory programming learning.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2012 IEEE Frontiers in
                        Education Conference (FIE)</title> (FIE 2012). IEEE
                    Computer Society, Washington, DC, USA, 1-6. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Mitchell et al 2012" xml:id="mitchell2012">
                    Mitchell, Eleanor, Peggy Seiden, and Suzy Taraba, Eds.
                        <title rend="italic">Past or Portal? Enhancing
                        Undergraduate Learning through Special Collections and
                        Archives</title>. American Library Association. Chapter
                    7 in "Pedagogy": <title rend="italic">New York University:
                        Computing in the Humanities @ NYU Libraries</title> by
                    Janet Bunde, Deena Engel and Paula Feid.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Park and Wiedenbeck 2011" xml:id="park2011"> Park,
                    Thomas H. and Susan Wiedenbeck. <title rend="quotes">Learning web development: challenges at an earlier
                        stage of computing education.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the seventh international
                        workshop on Computing education research</title> (ICER
                    2011). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 125-132. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Paterson et al 2005" xml:id="patterson2005">
                    Paterson, James H., Frances McCormick, and Gerry Creechan.
                        <title rend="quotes">Teaching XML in a web development
                        context.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the 10th annual SIGCSE conference on Innovation and
                        technology in computer science education</title> (ITiCSE
                    2005). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 359-359. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Price 2012" xml:id="price2012"> Price, Leah. 2012.
                        <title rend="italic">How to Do Things with Books in
                        Victorian Britain</title>. Princeton: Princeton
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Price 2013" xml:id="price2013"> Price, Kenneth M.
                        <title rend="quotes">Electronic Scholarly
                        Editions.</title> In <title rend="italic">A Companion to
                        Digital Literary Studies</title>, ed. Ray Siemens and
                    Susan Schreibman. Chichester, West Sussex: Blackwell, 2013.
                    434-450</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pulimood and Wolz 2008" xml:id="pulimood2008">
                    Pulimood, Sarah Monisha and Ursula Wolz. <title rend="quotes">Problem solving in community: a necessary
                        shift in cs pedagogy.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SIGCSE Bull.</title> 40, 1 (March
                    2008), 210-214. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Richards 2009" xml:id="richards2009"> Richards,
                    Debbie. <title rend="quotes">Designing Project-Based Courses
                        with a Focus on Group Formation and Assessment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Trans. Comput. Educ.</title> 9, 1,
                    Article 2 (March 2009), 40 pages. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Schaub 2009" xml:id="schaub2009"> Schaub, Stephen.
                        <title rend="quotes">Teaching CS1 with web applications
                        and test-driven development.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SIGCSE Bull.</title> 41, 2 (June 2009),
                    113-117. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Stephenson et al 2007" xml:id="stephenson2007">
                    Stephenson, Peter, L. Miguel, Joan Peckham, Jean-Yves Hervé,
                    and Ron Hutt. <title rend="quotes">Using undergraduate
                        interdisciplinary research to promote computer
                        science.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">J. Comput. Sci. Coll.</title> 22, 3
                    (January 2007), 98-104. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Updike 1969" xml:id="updike1969"> Updike, John.
                        <title rend="italic">Midpoint</title>. New York: Knopf,
                    1969.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wang and Zahadat 2009" xml:id="wang2009"> Wang, Ye
                    Diana and Nima Zahadat. <title rend="quotes">Teaching web
                        development in the web 2.0 era.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 10th ACM conference on
                        SIG-information technology education</title> (SIGITE
                    2009). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 80-86. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Yue and Ding 2004" xml:id="yue2004"> Yue, Kwok-Bun
                    and Wei Ding. <title rend="quotes">Design and evolution of
                        an undergraduate course on web application
                        development.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings
                        of the 9th annual SIGCSE conference on Innovation and
                        technology in computer science education</title> (ITiCSE
                    2004). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 22-26. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>