<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Towards a Richer Sense of Digital Annotation: 
                    Moving Beyond a "Media" Orientation of the Annotation of Digital Objects</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>John <dhq:family>Bradley</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Kings College London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>john.bradley@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                    
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>John Bradley has been a member of the Department of Digital Humanities (formally Center for Computing in the Humanities), King’s College London since 1997, where he has worked on many multi-year collaborative research projects, carried out his own research, and taught in various programs offered by the department.  In September 2011 he was appointed into an academic post at King’s, and still finds himself sometimes trying to figure out that this means.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000121</idno>
                <idno type="volume">006</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2012-10-12">12 October 2012</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born Digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>.</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>annotation, software tools</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>annotation</item>
                        <item>software tools</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2012-06-26" who="MCC">Encoded file</change>
            <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Digital technology often gives us the chance to re-conceive common scholarly practices with the humanities, and one of these is the practice of annotation.  Whereas many in the digital humanities look at annotation through the lens of social media, in this paper we consider annotation’s already established function in scholarship: to support the development of an interpretation of a body of material.  It begins by applying a “software application” perspective to annotation and it notes that personal annotation sits at the nexus between the publishing application of the material being annotated, and an interpretation development application that aims to support the reader’s thinking. Once this application orientation is taken up, it becomes evident that it is useful to re-conceptualise aspects of annotation beyond the annotation-of-media focus which the World Wide Web has encouraged in all of us. The paper does this by considering annotation in an application that is not media oriented in nature, Northwestern University’s WordHoard, and it explores some of the significance of annotation where the application’s data model – with its inherent semantic significance – is available to be annotated. There is a growing interest in thinking of the WWW as a delivery mechanism for software applications rather than merely for documents, and thus many of the issues that this paper raises could apply to the work of web-oriented developers too.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>An application-oriented perspective opens up new ways to think about digital annotation.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>One characteristic of new technology is that it takes time to understand all the new
                affordances the technology provides. The earliest printers tried first to produce
                books that looked as much like manuscripts as possible but later discovered that
                print had both possibilities and requirements that were not conceived of in the
                pre-print era. The digital revolution, particularly the internet, has brought us the
                evident potential for a substantial transformation in scholarly communication.
                Goodness knows, we in the digital humanities (DH) are well aware that the new
                digital technologies in which we are engaged are bringing new things to the
                Humanities! However, it is possible – even likely – that we are still not seeing all
                the new kinds of potential that digital technology has opened to us.</p>
            <p>My work has taken up issues around digital annotation, and this is a topic that is of
                interest to a number of people in the digital humanities. Indeed, there is an active
                community of researchers in the DH who are exploring the annotation of digital
                resources such as WWW pages. Drew University's DM project is described by its
                developers as <quote rend="inline" source="#DM2012">a tool for linking media,</quote> and supports the annotation of images,
                texts and fragments of images or texts <ptr target="#DM2012"/>. The
                University of Basel's Salsah project is described as <quote rend="inline" source="#Salsah2012">a system for annotation and
                linkage of sources in the Arts and Humanities</quote> that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#Salsah2012">allows the annotation and
                linkage of arbitrary digital sources such as digital texts, still and moving images
                and sound</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#Salsah2012"/>
               </cit>. The TILE website claims that the TILE software is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#TILE2011">a web-based tool
                for creating and editing image-based electronic editions and digital archives of
                humanities texts</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#TILE2011"/>
               </cit>. Here the annotation links lines of text in an image of a
                manuscript to corresponding lines in a transcript, but TILE also features an <term>Image
                Markup Tool</term> that allows one to <quote rend="inline" source="#TILE2011">annotate regions of an image.</quote> The Open Annotation
                Collaboration recognises that annotating <quote rend="inline" source="#TILE2011">is
                a pervasive element of scholarly practice for both the humanist and the scientist,</quote>
                and that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#OAC2011">it is a method by which scholars organize existing knowledge and
                facilitate the creation and sharing of new knowledge</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#OAC2011"/>
               </cit>. A parallel initiative, called
                AO: Annotation Ontology provides a formal
                annotation model that works well in a domain ontology-rich context (here, seemingly
                the Life Sciences). <note>See <ref target="#CiccareseEtAl2010">Ciccarese <foreign>et
                    al</foreign> 2010</ref> for details. Work by Signer and Norrie (<ref target="#SignerAndNorrie2009">2009</ref>) presents 
                a model for <term>cross-media annotations</term>. There are other initiatives hosted by
                institutions as diverse as the University of Queensland to the Digital Emblematica
                Online project.</note>
            </p> 
            <p>Almost all of the interest in digital annotation with our community has been from the
                perspective of the WWW, in particular in the context of Web 2.0: its public and
                social context. See, for example, Jane Hunter's excellent encyclopaedic overview of
                work on digital annotation in the web context <ptr target="#hunter2009"/>. Indeed, Hunter directly
                acknowledges this focus in the <title rend="quotes">Scope and Definitions</title> part of her paper where she
                states that she has placed this work directly at the centre of where much of the
                recent thinking on annotation has been: the WWW, and she therefore focuses on the
                potential of the internet to enable annotation as a collaborative and social
                activity.</p>
            <p>Much of our understanding of annotation within the WWW has grown out of work in the
                context of web-accessible digital libraries. For this, the highly influential work
                of Maristella Agnosti and colleagues and, in particular, her seminal work on a formal
                definition of annotation as presented in Angosti and Ferro has been important <ptr target="#AgnostiAndFerro2007"/>.
                This work, in turn, has influenced the Open Annotation Collaboration project, an
                initiative which intends to <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#OAC2011">facilitate to emergence of a Web and resource-centric
                interoperable annotation environment</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#OAC2011"/>
               </cit>. Here again, the
                thinking about annotation has been driven by the concerns of the World Wide Web, and
                therefore assumes that all objects that it supports for annotation will be
                web-accessible and web-based objects.</p>
            <p>This way of viewing annotation – in the light of the WWW – is seductive not only
                because of the pervasive nature of the WWW in our thinking about digital things, but
                also because the continuing document-oriented nature of much of the web. As this
                paper will hopefully reveal, this document-orientation happens to fit well with
                characteristics of pre-digital technologies such as print, and means that we don't
                see other aspects of digital objects that are <emph>not</emph> shared by pre-digital
                ones, and which, as a consequence are barely explored through the lens of the WWW.
                Furthermore, I believe that, even within the web-centric perspective of software
                developers in the DH, certain assumptions about the nature of digital things on the
                WWW are changing: in particular one can see a shift in thinking of the WWW as the
                deliverer of resources to the deliverer of tools and applications. However, our
                focus as a community, so far, has been primarily on the document-centred WWW and
                annotation in this context. This has limited our understanding of the potential of,
                and the issues that arise from, annotation, and, perhaps even of digital objects
                more generally.</p>
            <p>I intend in this paper, then, to encourage a somewhat broader perspective, derived
                from my work on the <ref target="#Pliny2009">
                  <emph>Pliny</emph>
               </ref> project, and to work on the significance of
                digital annotation that is at least a bit outside the conventional WWW digital world
                    view.<note>Some of what is reported here grew out of work funded by the Mellon
                    Foundation's MATC award for Pliny. Parts of it were first reported in a poster
                    displayed at the DH2011 conference by Timothy Hill and myself <ptr target="#BradleyHill2011"/>.</note> To the extent that the web-oriented DH development community is
                thinking about the still-emerging more interactive- and application-oriented WWW
                environments such as those enabled by HTML5 and AJAX, perhaps it will have useful
                things to say to them as well.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Any Place for Personal Annotation?</head>
                <p>Because of the fascination within the DH community with the WWW we as a community
                    have chosen to focus on the new potentially highly collaborative and community
                    nature of scholarship that the WWW makes possible. Indeed, much recent work
                    focuses so tightly on collaboration that it seems to ignores the role of
                    individual reflection in scholarship. We see, for instance, the well-deserved
                    excitement within the DH community generated by the emergence of the Zotero
                    software developed by Georgetown's Center for History and New Media <ptr target="#Zotero2012"/>. As Dan Cohen notes, Zotero's success has emerged from the
                    effort put in by the developers to ensure that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#Cohen2008">the tool connects with the
                    digital ecosystem</quote> 
                  <ptr target="#Cohen2008"/>
               </cit>. In this article Cohen goes on to drive home this aspect of
                    Zotero by pointing out that it is about <quote rend="inline" source="#Zotero2012">Building Bridges, Not Islands.</quote>
                    However, this is a telling statement – surely the islands are important too. The
                    bridges are only needed if the islands contain something of importance. What
                    would the islands be in humanities scholarship?</p>
                <p>In spite of this excitement in building bridges of collaboration and digital
                    sharing, surely all social scholarly interaction had better be driven by the
                    <soCalled>islands</soCalled> of personal reflections and understanding of its participants. This
                    is, after all, where each individual's contribution to the whole comes from. The
                    individual's contribution is, of course, developed out of the interaction with
                    others in the field, but it is still based on further personal reflection that
                    grows out of this interaction. Otherwise, each individual in the social network
                    can have nothing original to contribute.</p>
                <p>Pliny (<ref target="#Pliny2009">2009</ref>) was software written to explore some of the new potential for
                    annotation in the digital world and was created to focus attention on the
                    potential role for computing in supporting not so much social scholarly
                    interaction but personal research. Current work by this author with colleagues
                    here at King's is now focusing on the implications of sharing of Pliny-based
                    personal data in the computing <soCalled>cloud</soCalled>, but it is necessary to understand that,
                    nonetheless, Pliny has been initially grounded in the scholarship of the
                    individual. For this reason Pliny is based on a different set of assumptions
                    about the role of annotation in scholarship from pretty well all of the
                    annotation-oriented WWW-based work mentioned earlier. Indeed, my original
                    intention with Pliny was to remind the DH development community that personal,
                    rather than collaborative/shared, annotation taps into some fundamental elements
                    of humanities scholarship. It too was worthy of study by the DH community,
                    rather than being simply ignored as a result of the focus on the significance of
                    collaboration that online-scholarship makes possible.</p>
                <p>What is meant, within Pliny, about annotation for personal research? The primary
                    starting point for understanding annotation there is to think about traditional
                    pre-digital annotation: some material added by the reader to a printed text for
                    the purpose of enriching the reader’s experience of reading that text. In fact,
                    Pliny is derived from thinking about what writing in a book is for, and to
                    explore how doing this kind of annotation in a digital instead of print context
                    affects or enhances this goal or purpose. At first glance one might think that,
                    after all, <soCalled>annotation is annotation</soCalled> – that all forms of annotation share the
                    same base principles and that there is no need for something different – at
                    least at the technical level – for personal and public/shared annotation.
                    However, there has been research done in computer science that suggests
                    otherwise <ptr target="#Marshall1998" loc="41"/>.<note>See <ptr target="#Marshall1998"/> for some early, but still insightful, observations
                    about different kinds of annotation, and some of the significance of the
                    differences (described as <q>dimensions of annotation</q>) – in particular the
                    dimensions of <q>published vs. private</q> and <q>Global vs. institutional vs.
                    workgroup vs. personal</q>, and further discussion on the distinction
                    between private and public annotation, and what happens when going from private
                    notes to public ones in <ref target="#MarshallAndBush2004">Marshall and Brush 2004</ref>.</note> Indeed, I believe that much of
                    the Pliny-related work, as described in the original papers about Pliny (<ref target="#Bradley2008">Bradley
                    2008</ref> and <ref target="#Bradley2008a">2008a</ref>), and extended in a particular direction in 
                    <ref target="#Bradley2008b">Bradley 2008b</ref> and further still in this paper, shows that there a rather fundamental differences
                    between personal and web-oriented annotation that can transform much of how we
                    think about how one might best apply digital technology to support the
                    activity.</p>
                <p>Since even in the Web 2.0 context much of the thinking about annotation is
                    derived from the long-standing practice of annotation on paper, let us start
                    there (see figure 1). Most of the time annotation on paper is a personal
                    activity – what Marshall would consider at the private end of her published
                        <foreign>versus</foreign> private dimension. This kind of annotation acts as
                    a central activity for many scholars <ptr target="#BrockmanEtAl2001"/>.
                    But what is this kind of private annotation for? Of course, at the moment in
                    which readers write annotations, they do it to enhance their immediate
                    understanding and retention of the material that they are reading. Does it have
                    any longer-lasting purpose or use? My conjecture (supported by, among others,
                    Brockman <foreign>et al</foreign> and Marshall), and expressed in how
                    Pliny works, is that in fact this kind of annotation, indeed notetaking more
                    generally, provides one of the bases for much scholarly research in the
                    humanities. In this view notetaking fits into the activity of developing a
                    personal interpretation of the materials the reader is interested in. <note>See
                    discussion of this with regard to previous Pliny work in <ref target="#Bradley2008">Bradley 2008</ref> pp 265-6,
                    and <ref target="#Bradley2008a">Bradley 2008a</ref>, section <title rend="quotes">So, What Is Humanities Research, Really?</title>
               </note>
            </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>A printed page as the nexus between
                     applications</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Thus, when the book reader writes a note on the page s/he creates a situation
                    where two rather different applications must co-exist there: the
                    print media represented by the printed word and his/her annotation shown by the
                    handwritten note. The owner, the technology and purpose of these two co-existing
                    texts – the annotation and the print material – are quite different.
                    Furthermore, there is a temporal side to this: whereas the printed text
                    represents an endpoint in the <soCalled>publishing application</soCalled> that put it there, the
                    hand-written annotation represents the beginning of an act of interpretation
                    that is likely to continue into the future. When the reader writes something in
                    a book, she or he intends to use this note in the process of developing his/her
                    own ideas about the material that will continue after the writing of the note is
                    over. Although in print the note is of necessity tied to the page onto which it
                    was written, its value grows to the extent that it represents a thought that
                    remains in the reader's mind after she is finished with the article or book
                    where the note was written, and this moves the note from its original context in
                    the printed page to a larger context for it that is almost certainly going to
                    transcend any particular page.</p>
                <p>In some senses, then, a printed page with an annotation on it represents both a
                    physical and temporal nexus between these two quite different applications: (i)
                    the presentation of the print, and (ii) the support for the annotation made by
                    the individual reader. Although the annotation is on the same page as the print,
                    it is quite a separate kind of thing from the print. Indeed, if handwritten
                    annotation on a printed page worked in the way that many annotation services on
                    websites operate – provided as a service of the book’s publisher – it would in
                    fact seem very peculiar, and, indeed perhaps strikingly inappropriate. Why
                    should personal notes attached to material served via a website be made
                    available through facilities provided by the website's owner, and thus
                    apparently owned by him or her? The ownership of the individual printed copy of
                    a book where the notes are written provides a personal context for the note that
                    a website, by itself, cannot immediately provide.</p>
                <p>As initially installed Pliny supports annotation for web pages, images and PDF
                    documents. Separate software components within Pliny have been written for each
                    of these media types, and each of them support, simultaneously, mechanisms to
                    display the object (web page, image or PDF) and to support annotation of these
                    objects. However, although the annotation items appear initially with the web or
                    PDF page or image to which they are attached, they also became also objects that
                    work in the larger Pliny context as independent objects in their own right.
                    Thus, in some ways like the printed book, the Pliny screen becomes the nexus
                    between the <emph>display application</emph> of the image, web or PDF page and
                    the separate-but-linked <emph>annotation/notetaking application</emph> (see
                    Figure 2). Furthermore, the Eclipse platform in which Pliny
                    operates already supports the dynamic addition of new components into an
                    existing installation. Pliny could thus be relatively straightforwardly extended
                    to add support for annotation for other media such as video or audio. The
                    integration between these media and Pliny notes would be similar to that
                    provided in base Pliny – annotations made on these media could also
                    automatically fit into the separate interpretation development environment that
                    Pliny supports.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Pliny as the nexus between applications</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Figures 1 and 2, then, emphasise the <soCalled>nexus</soCalled> nature of annotation on the printed
                    and digital page, but don't adequately illustrate how these objects work within
                    Pliny in the notetaking context (the application identified in the box to the
                    top right in both figures 1 and 2). Figure 3 presents schematically a
                    representation of the role of annotations in Pliny's more-general notetaking
                    application: what I have described above as interpretation building. The
                    material in figure 3 is organised into three areas. The annotations (shown in
                    the left-most area) sit as transition points between the digital objects they
                    annotate, and the digital model of his/her personal interpretation that the user
                    builds in Pliny. This is where the <soCalled>nexus</soCalled> nature of annotation is
                    represented.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Pliny objects in its <soCalled>notetaking</soCalled> application</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The remaining two areas focus on the role of these annotations in notetaking and
                    interpretation building. In the middle area we see someone using Pliny to
                    discover and record concepts of interest to him/her. Although any real use of
                    Pliny would likely result in many hundreds of concepts being identified and
                    organised there, for the purposes of simplifying this diagram we only show two
                    of them, labelled <title rend="quotes">Concept 1</title> and <title rend="quotes">Concept 2</title> –  although a real Pliny user would
                    give these object representing his or her concepts significant names, of course.
                    Within each of these concept-objects we see notes describing the concept, and
                    links (through previously created annotations) to resources that relate to them.
                    Finally, the third area to the right shows the user assembling the concepts and
                    references to the original sources that have been stored in Pliny as s/he plans
                    for two papers.</p>
                <p>It is important to note that the central area in figure 3 represents
                        <emph>personal</emph> materials. The concepts recorded there would reflect
                    the reader’s personal and particular interests. Thus these connections, although
                    often bound to specific annotations in the material the researcher has worked
                    with, take on their own structure that is quite different from the structure
                    implied by a collection of notes in books. Although the task of interpretation
                    started with the writing of annotations about what one is reading, its focus
                    must shift in time towards the construction of objects that represent one’s own
                    interpretation, with its own independent structure and connections between its
                    parts. The annotations still have a role in this, because they ground the
                    interpretation in the sources that have been read – however, they operate now in
                    the context of the reader’s interpretation rather than the source’s context. I
                    have taken the liberty of calling this shift in significance of the annotations
                    from their original target to having a role in the user’s own emerging
                    interpretation building as a re-contextualising of the notes. By showing the
                    integration between annotation and interpretation development, Pliny draws our
                    attention away from a focus on the building of annotation components added to,
                    say, websites that support shared annotation, and towards the purpose that
                    drives most acts of annotation in the first place: to support personal
                    scholarship by (a) recording original thoughts (as original annotations) that
                    arise in the mind of the reader as these objects are studied, and then (b) by
                    providing a way of incorporating these thoughts into a structure of
                    interpretation that will almost always blend personal insights with references
                    to ideas that arose from a range of separate documents.</p>
                <p>Note, as well, that the various objects shown in figure 3 form a web of
                    connections that to some extent tracks the web of connections in the Pliny
                    user's mind as she creates the various objects represented there. Pliny then
                    provides a kind of glue that connects references to documents of various media
                    to the user’s own set of ideas that are also stored as a network.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Annotation in the Context of Applications</head>
                <p>As is perhaps clear by now, Pliny is not a website but an
                        <emph>application</emph> that runs on its user’s machine. This allows it to
                    be more flexible about the kinds and range of resources it can work with and (by
                    not being itself served from the web) allows these materials from different
                    resources and scattered across different places on the Internet to be brought
                    together, including even personal objects not served over the internet at all.
                    Furthermore, being an application that someone runs on their own machine
                    emphasises its personal nature, and clearly reflects the personal ownership of
                    any personal annotations its user creates.</p>
                <p>Although Pliny is a software application, it is built on top of the Eclipse
                    framework which provides a conceptual model for application development that is
                    particularly well suited to the development of collaborating peer related
                    components such as what is implied in the <soCalled>nexus</soCalled> understanding that I have just
                    described<note>See <ptr target="#Birsan2005"/> for a now rather dated, but still solid
                        introduction to Eclipse's plugin-in architecture that is relevant to the
                        discussion that follows here. A more recent, but much more formal
                        computer science-oriented discussion of Eclipse's plugin architecture and
                        some of its implications can be found at <ref target="#WermelingerAndYu2008">Wermelinger and Yu 2008</ref>.</note>.
                    This is because the Eclipse framework has a richer understanding of software
                    modularity than one finds in other conventional Java frameworks such as Swing,
                    or, indeed in other non-Java environments too. With conventional Java
                    applications a developer can indeed include components that come from other
                    developers – a central idea of software modularity. Database engines like MySQL
                    or XSLT transformation tools like Saxon are examples of software developed by
                    one team of people, but often used by other projects as building blocks within
                    their own application, even though they are then components that disappear
                    inside this larger packaging. The developers in my department, for example, use
                    MySQL in our Prosopography of Anglo-Saxon England (PASE) project, but MySQL's
                    use inside PASE is virtually invisible to the PASE user. Thus, a main
                    application like PASE's becomes a <q>Borg application</q>, reusing software
                    development work from others as a way to efficiently implement aspects of the
                    software that they need. Like the Borg on <title rend="italic">Star Trek</title> the enveloping
                    software projects take over these applications to serve their needs, but then to
                    a large extent hide them inside their own packaging. Although the master project
                    becomes a big tent containing many different components that help support it,
                    from the user's point of view these components have been swallowed up, and users
                    will only see the enveloping application as the thing they are using.</p>
                <p>Not all modular software development operates in a way that hides the constituent
                    modules. The need for different applications to share a workspace so that they
                    can all interact on their shared data is common in data- and text-mining
                    toolkits, and the approach used there is often characterised as a kind of
                    modularity called the data-flow model. One uses the data flow approach by
                    connecting separate tools together – the data being processing is first passed
                    into one tool which transforms it in some way and generates output that is
                    passed (flowed) as input into the second, and so forth. Although data-flow does,
                    indeed, enable a framework where different pieces of software can co-exist and
                    remain evident to the user, this paradigm is insufficient for annotation, since
                    annotations have not so much the need to share data that they <soCalled>process</soCalled> (what
                    data-flow enables), as to share the screen with the materials that they
                    decorate. The sharing of the screen as well as the data makes the nature of
                    their co-operation of necessity more intimate than what the data-flow model
                    imagines.</p>
                <p>Having drawn our attention to the intimate nature of the interaction between
                    components in Pliny’s annotation framework, we now look at figure 4, which
                    redrafts the ideas in figure 3 into an application-oriented perspective. Here,
                    the different applications (browser, PDF viewer, WordHoard and an application
                    called <title rend="quotes">A</title>) operate as peers – each visible to the user and clearly providing
                    different and complementary functions for him/her. Furthermore, the yellow boxes
                    – which represent the annotations, sit at the boundary (by sharing the screen)
                    and are hence shown here as sitting between the application in which they are
                    displayed, and the Pliny framework in which they are stored. This ability to
                    combine data from two different applications on a resource as intimate as a
                    computer screen window is made possible through Eclipse’s software environment
                    in which Pliny is built.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Pliny notes glue together separate
                     applications</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The top three applications in figure 4 (shown here in orange and already
                    incorporated into basic Pliny) simply present PDF and web pages. They are really
                    media players, but, by being <soCalled>Pliny aware</soCalled>, are also able to support personal
                    annotation (the small yellow boxes) of the different media they present. Once we
                    notice the application nature of these components, however, we are in a position
                    to take the application idea still further. We have already pointed out that
                    Pliny is extendable to support annotation to different media by the addition of
                    new Pliny-aware applications that displayed these other media. However,
                    applications are not always simply media-players. Thus, Pliny’s support for
                    annotation did not need to be limited to relatively static <emph>media</emph>
                    objects such as web pages or PDF files or digital video, but could extend to the
                    displays generated by potentially more complex, interactive, and independently
                    developed applications, as long as the developer of each of these applications
                    wrote it in such a way that they were Pliny-aware.</p>
                <p>This is implied in figure 4, where the two Pliny-aware software applications (an
                    imaginary <name>App A</name>, and the real <name>WordHoard</name>) support Pliny
                    annotation too. They are not simply pieces of software to display media object
                    like PDF documents. Instead, they represent dynamic applications that someone
                    uses to explore dynamically other kinds of data. In this way of thinking any
                    display that these applications generated from their data could also be
                    annotated and these annotations could also be integrated into the user’s set of
                    ideas that are represented within Pliny. We have, then, Pliny acting not only as
                    a tool to model a network of interconnections between media data (as suggested
                    in figure 3), but also a tool to interconnect pretty well any kind of software
                    applications as well – as long as the application is written to accommodate
                    Pliny annotation.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Exploring Annotation Beyond Media</head>
                <p>Although application-thinking recognises that not all applications that might
                    support annotation need to be merely presenters of media, digital annotation has
                    been almost universally thought of as an activity connecting things to parts of
                    media files. The reason for this orientation, of course, might well be that
                    thinking about annotation has come from thinking about annotation on paper, and
                    paper is a kind of media. Furthermore, much of the thinking about annotation has
                    grown out of the digital library and WWW research community, where the objects
                    of interest have been almost exclusively media-oriented "documents", rather than
                    as a more diverse set of digital objects that can actually be represented in
                    software. Indeed, much of WWW terminology, centered as it is still primarily on
                    the conception of the web being made up of a large collection of documents,
                    encourages one to recognise only media-like digital objects as the kind of
                    objects involved in things like annotation. One sees this assumption everywhere.
                    Note the definition for annotation, for example, in OntoText’s widely quoted
                    glossary of definitions of terms related to ontologies as <quote rend="inline" source="#OntoText2011">a form of meta-data
                    attached to a particular section of document content,</quote> where
                    <soCalled>document</soCalled> is evidently thought of as a kind of media object – and this from a
                    company that is working with ontology technologies that themselves are
                    emphatically not document-like in nature <ptr target="#OntoText2011"/>. We see it again in the largely
                    unconscious use of the word <q>media</q> as the things that might be annotated in the
                    Open Annotations Collaboration’s data model’s <name>Guiding Principles</name>
                    <ptr target="#SandersonAndVanDeSompel2011"/>. Even Agnosti’s formal model of
                    annotation mentioned earlier seems to be based on this kind of orientation,
                    since her formal model builds towards its definition of annotation through a
                    definition of a data stream (<ref target="#AgnostiAndFerro2007">Agnosti and Ferro 2007</ref>, section 6.2) and a segment
                    in the stream (section 6.3) to the point where the anchoring point is defined as
                    a segment of a stream (section 9). This <soCalled>stream</soCalled> view of digital data seems to
                    me to be clearly one that is derived from a media-oriented orientation.</p>
                <p>Viewing annotation as an activity that connects material from separate
                    applications rather than media together is a more general one, and a better fit
                    to the fuller potential of digital technology than the more static media
                    perspective. It has the potential of liberating us from confining our thinking
                    to things that are conventionally rendered over the WWW: largely static objects
                    such as textual documents, images, 3D objects and even video and audio, and
                    opens our thinking to deal with annotation in the context of the
                    application-oriented perspective of the WWW that is still emerging. Indeed, this
                    shift in thinking is in line with what is clearly a current trend in the digital
                    humanities: towards thinking of the web as a place where applications (things
                    like, say, tools for text analysis, textual data mining or network analysis) can
                    work on materials rather than merely presenting them. These tools when delivered
                    over the web also do not exhibit a kind of “media orientation”, and assumptions
                    such as those mentioned above about annotation do not serve them well
                    either.</p>
                <p>The Mellon MATC prize awarded in 2008 for Pliny allowed the idea of annotation in
                    the broader application-oriented context I have just described to be explored
                    within Pliny. Was the integration of a complex application, with Pliny to handle
                    notetaking within that application, really practical? How did the act of
                    supporting annotation in the Pliny context affect how the application had to be
                    written? What, if any, were the technical constraints under which such an
                    application would have to be written if it was to support personal annotation,
                    and how onerous was it for developers to meet them? Before we started planning
                    to try out Pliny integration with a large application we had already explored
                    the development of small applications that co-operated with Pliny as test cases.
                    We built a small application, for example, to allow someone to annotate a
                    GoogleMap, and we did another to work with images from the image archive
                    provided through the Victoria and Albert’s public API. Both these applications implemented parts of the
                    Pliny approach to annotation handling, and allowed Google Maps, or collections
                    of VA materials, to integrate in the <soCalled>Pliny way</soCalled> with other materials;
                    exactly as suggested by figure 4. However, as experiments, these applications
                    were really prototype applications: pieces of software that were in some ways
                    rudimentary in nature, and hence both relatively small and based on only a
                    subset of the full potential of the mechanisms which they might have exploited.
                    Could this idea really work when the application was more complex?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>WordHoard with Pliny</head>
                <p>I was aware of Martin Mueller and Northwestern University’s
                    <name>WordHoard</name> project before the MATC aware had
                    been granted, and had wanted even then to try out integrating WordHoard with
                    Pliny. Here was software that, instead of running as a web application in a
                    browser, ran as a Java application. Its orientation towards allowing the user to
                    browse and search documents, and to perform various kinds of word-oriented
                    analyses on them, plus its host of different kinds of presentations that could
                    arise from this word-oriented work made it an excellent trial application for
                    the views on annotation that had then emerged in my mind. Although WordHoard
                    worked with text, it could not be thought of as a media-presentation application
                    in the way that a PDF viewer would be. Furthermore, it already supported
                    annotation to some extent, albeit in a way that was, at least from a personal
                    annotation perspective, more modest than what I wanted to explore with Pliny. As
                    a result, I proposed to Mellon that the money that they had awarded for Pliny
                    would fund a developer half-time for about two years to take the WordHoard code
                    and gradually adapt it so that it could run in the context in which Pliny ran,
                    and that could thus support the Pliny-supported annotation of its displays.
                    Martin Mueller, and indeed the whole Northwestern development team, were happy
                    with the idea and provided some guidance here and there although they were,
                    naturally enough, unable to take part in the daily development work. I am
                    thankful, however, for their generous support of the experiment.</p>
                <p>The Mellon MATC funding has allowed us to explore this approach more
                    substantially by applying the strategy used by Pliny as a real example of
                    substantial integration between two independently developed substantial tools.
                    The questions were:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>How difficult was it to re-express WordHoard's user interface in this new
                        Eclipse/plugin framework?</item>
                    <item>How difficult was it to integrate Pliny annotation into the user interface
                        for WordHoard?</item>
                    <item>Pliny provides a broader context in which annotation operates than
                        WordHoard does. Whereas annotation in standard WordHoard was thought of as a
                        way to add commentary to WordHoard's texts that stays within WordHoard
                        itself, Pliny annotation is thought of as a note-taking application that
                        creeps into potentially all aspects of all the applications that integrate
                        with it. Furthermore, the Pliny environment, with its potential for the
                        re-contextualisation of its data (as described above) allows WordHoard
                        objects to be referenced in contexts outside of WordHoard itself. How did
                        this connection of WordHoard with Pliny change the way the WordHoard
                        software had to operate?</item>
                    <item>Work is being done in by the larger Digital Humanities and other scholarly
                        technologies community to think about individual annotation of webpages –
                        see the OAC initiative, for example. By being based on Semantic Web
                        technologies such as RDF and 
                        URIs, it is extendable into a range of media-oriented
                        web-delivered objects, but it is not so clear how it fits with data which is
                        not available as media through a browser/web frontend <ptr target="#LassilaAndSwick1999"/> 
                  <ptr target="#JacobsAndWalsh2004"/>. What happens when the
                        digital resource (like WordHoard) is not a web application?</item>
                </list>
                <p>This list of concerns, and of things learned from them is, of course, of interest
                    to several different communities. In this article I focus on topics related to
                    issues 3 and 4, but the other issues need to be discussed in the forums
                    appropriate to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>What Was Built</head>
                <p>As it turned out, the task of building a complete version of WordHoard that
                    co-existed with Pliny and allowed for the kind of intimacy of interaction
                    implied in this article proved out to be a task that was too large for the
                    funding provided for it. This was in part due to the challenge of getting our
                    excellent Java programmers familiar enough with the Eclipse plugin way of doing
                    things to allow them to be efficient in their development work – and this was
                    compounded by the fact that our original programmer had to leave the project
                    partway through, and as a result we had to change programmer midstream –
                    requiring the training process to be carried out twice.</p>
                <p>The initial aim was to, as much as possible, mirror the original WordHoard
                    interface and integrate into it annotation components from Pliny, and we tried
                    to do this by leaving the <soCalled>business logic</soCalled> part of WordHoard entirely alone –
                    simply using the code that the Northwestern developers had written for it
                    exactly as it stood, while re-expressing WordHoard’s original interface in the
                    new User Interface frameworks of Eclipse and Pliny so that we could add
                    facilities for Pliny annotation to them. Figure 5 shows part of the original
                    WordHoard interface as created by Northwestern University, and Figure 6 shows
                    our implementation of WordHoard working in the Pliny/Eclipse environment.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Original WordHoard Displays</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>WordHoard in the Pliny environment.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Two of WordHoard’s displays are visible in the screenshot of our Pliny-compatible
                    interface for WordHoard shown in figure 6. In the lower left corner we can see
                    the WordHoard <title rend="quotes">Table of Contents</title> display which, as in the original WordHoard
                    application (shown in figure 5 in the left window), allows you to select a text
                    from the various ones available through WordHoard. As one might expect from the
                    Eclipse framework in which Pliny and our version of WordHoard was created, this
                    display, along with the other displays we implemented, can co-exist with
                    non-WordHoard materials. The top left area in Figure 6 shows, for example,
                    Pliny’s standard Resource Explorer. Annotations from different applications can
                    share the screen too: here we see a reference to a web page placed as an
                    annotation into the text display. Furthermore, in this screen shot the user has
                    installed into their version of Pliny not only WordHoard, but also tools for
                    annotating other objects: in this case, our prototype Google and V&amp;A
                    annotation tools. By having loaded the WordHoard, Google annotator and V&amp;A
                    annotation tools into Pliny the user is now able to annotate not only Pliny’s
                    standard media objects (Web pages, PDF files and images), but can also annotate
                    Google maps, material from WordHoard and images fetched through the Victoria and
                    Albert Museum’s public API (V&amp;A undated), and use Pliny’s
                    re-contextualisation tools to bring them together.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most obvious place to start thinking about integration between
                    WordHoard and Pliny was WordHoard's text display, where the texts within the
                    WordHoard corpus can be viewed. Indeed, WordHoard itself supported an annotation
                    component there already. We thought of Pliny's annotation paradigm as one
                    centered on the provision of a 2-D space were notes can be laid out (there is a
                    discussion of in what way this is central to the conception of Pliny in <ptr target="#bradley2008" loc="271"/>). Thus, for the text display – shown in figure 6 – we built the 2D
                    annotation space to tightly integrate with the display of the rather linear
                    display of text itself which comes from WordHoard. Pliny annotation objects
                    float in the two-dimensional space of the text area above WordHoard's linear text
                    presentation so that the user could integrate Pliny objects in the same space
                    that the text inhabits. Of course, this close integration between the linear
                    presentation of the text and the 2D nature of the annotation makes it work in
                    ways very similar to annotation on paper. Neither on paper, nor in our version
                    of Pliny, is the user constrained by the way the text is displayed when deciding
                    how to place their annotations. We think that the combining of WordHoard's text
                    display with Pliny's 2D way of doing annotation, and the ability to anchor a
                    Pliny object to a fragment of text, works quite well, and parallels to some
                    significant extent the way in which annotation in books are actually done –
                    closer, in fact, to what had been provided in the original WordHoard
                    implementation.</p>
                <p>An important part of our task with integrating Pliny into WordHoard centred 
                    around our recognition that a software user might want to annotation anything 
                    the application showed him/her: an idea that we have started to call the 
                    <soCalled>annotation anything</soCalled> principle. Not only the text display, but indeed all 
                    the displays that WordHoard could generate might create new ideas in the mind of 
                    the WordHoard user that he or she might want to annotate and record. Hence, 
                    we wanted to support annotation not only in WordHoard's text display, but in 
                    the other displays that it could generate too.</p>
                <p>In the interest of software development expediency, we added Pliny annotation to
                    other WordHoard displays by means of a technically simpler approach than what we
                    used in the text display by providing a separate 2D annotation area to the right
                    of the main WordHoard display where notes and reference to other Pliny materials
                    could be put. The degree of integration between the annotations and the display
                    that triggered them in the mind of the user was, then, substantially less than
                    it had been for the text display, but it still at least allowed users to add
                    comments about what they are seeing in the displays whenever they wished. You
                    can see Pliny's annotation area for WordHoard's word information display on the
                    right in figure 7.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>WordHoard word information display with Pliny annotation</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>We also did some work to render the WordHoard concordance tool with Pliny annotation support. 
                    Figure 8 shows a screenshot of the WordHoard concordance display centred on Shakespeare's 
                    use of the lemma <soCalled>house</soCalled>.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>WordHoard Concordance display with Pliny annotations</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In this case, perhaps because a KWIC concordance is both highly structured and
                    can contain many entries, Northwestern's original developers chose to display it
                    hierarchically. Within this display the user could choose among several
                    different ways to group and order the KWIC entries, and could use the hierarchy
                    to selectively open only certain of the categories thus created. In Figure 8,
                    the user has chosen to group the lemmas by the work in which they appear, and we
                    can see various Shakespeare plays with the number of occurrences of the word
                    <q>house</q> displayed (gray background). Two notes have been added to the display
                    already, but here we see the display at the moment that the user had chosen to
                    open two of the work entries (<title rend="italic">Anthony and Cleopatra</title> and <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>) so they can see
                    the actual occurrences of <emph>house</emph> as items in a KWIC concordance (white
                    background) for these two works.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Annotation's Standard Model and its Semantic Deficit</head>
                <p>Between Agnosti and Ferro's formal definition of annotation, and the more recent
                    and ongoing development of the Open Annotation Collaboration's initiative
                    we find an emerging understanding of annotation that I call here the <term>standard
                    model</term>. One thing that is perhaps surprising in this standard model is that it
                    naturally incorporates what I call a <term>semantic deficit</term> that is inherent in
                    annotation on paper, and in media-oriented annotation as well.</p>
                <p>Consider a situation when I am reading, say, Kierkegaard's <title rend="italic">Fear and Trembling</title> in
                    a printed copy, and I come across Kierkegaard's observation, and subsequent
                    challenge, to what he claims to be the commonly accepted statement <q>Only one who
                    works gets bread.</q> This passage triggers a personal reaction that I want to
                    record. In my particular print edition this happens to be on page 57. So, I
                    circle the part of the text on that page that talks about this and add a note
                    beside it with my reaction.</p>
                <p>There is, of course, a <term>semantic deficit</term> that arises here. I have written on
                    page 57 of my copy to record a personal response to the issue that Kierkegaard
                    is discussing, but I think of the link as being between my idea and
                    Kierkegaard's point, not to the spot on this page in my book. There is a
                    distinction between what I have done (made marks on page 57) and what I mean
                    (comment on this part of Kierkegaard's discussion).</p>
                <p>For personal annotations written into a printed book, this distinction does not really
                    matter very much – page 57 in my copy always has been, and always will be about
                    this proverb, and the fact is that when I see this annotation any time in the
                    future I will think about its connection to the proverb rather than to where it
                    is on the page. However, it is useful to note the incompleteness in the formal
                    semantics from an outsider's point of view. Someone talking about my note to a
                    third party is more likely to say that it was linked to the place in the text
                    where Kierkegaard is writing about this proverb, rather than that <q>John linked
                    his note to the text 7 centimetres from the top of page 57</q>. Indeed, she might
                    well say, <q>in my edition, this passage is on page 63</q>, making it clear that she
                    thinks of the link being to the idea represented on page 57 in my copy, rather
                    than to a spot on the page.</p>
                <p>Indeed, in Pliny the method used to attach an annotation to an area in a PDF file
                    works in a way that is very similarly to what happens on the printed page. The
                    anchoring spot is recorded as an area on the printed page rather than linked to
                    the objects the area on the page is showing. Indeed, Pliny is not aware of the
                    link-to-the-idea at all. However, since PDF processors work hard to always place
                    the text on the same place on each electronic page, this works fine. A display of
                    a PDF of <title rend="italic">Fear and Trembling</title> that reproduced my edition of the text would always
                    show this proverb on the same spot on page 57 too. Nonetheless, there is a kind
                    of semantic gap between what is needed to allow Pliny to display the annotation,
                    and what the user thinks of when he or she sees the anchor. Furthermore, almost
                    no user viewing my annotations in this PDF file will notice this semantic gap
                    because the context for display of the annotation (page 57, with all the text
                    always displayed in the place) is always the same.</p>
                <p>The issue is the same with media that operate in real time such as video or
                    audio. Although we may not think of video or audio as static, they both have a
                    kind of fixeded-ness about them too. Take as an example the period of time from
                    19 minutes 45 seconds to 20 minutes in Stanley Kubrick’s <title rend="italic">2001</title>. This segment
                    always represents the same sequence of image frames and therefore presents the
                    same spot in the script no matter which digital version of the video one is
                    looking at. From the viewer's perspective the same thing is always "going on",
                    and if someone attaches a comment to <title rend="italic">2001</title> for this time period it will always
                    appear at the right semantic moment. However, the semantic deficit still exists:
                    until we know what is going on in this time period we don’t know what the
                    comment might be about. As it turns out, 19.45 to 20.00 is the time when the
                    prehistoric ape figure throws a bone into the air, and the scene abruptly shifts
                    to the 21st century in near-Earth space. Although there is a semantic deficit
                    between the specification of the annotation's anchor as an interval of time in
                    the movie, the user seeing the comment in the context of the movie will not need
                    to notice it.</p>
                <p>This deficit between what is digitally recorded and what is <soCalled>meant</soCalled> is often
                    implicit in thinking about digital annotation and, indeed, like the annotation
                    to paper, often it does not matter given the fixed context in which the
                    annotation will be displayed. However, anchoring the annotation not to a spot in
                    a media file, but to something that is semantically meaningful reduces the
                    deficit and improves the semantics of the anchor. Take an example outside of
                    Pliny: from the OAC's Hubble example, where an image taken by the Hubble space
                    telescope of deep space shows what appears to be a tightly packed area in space
                    where there are many galaxies
                    (<ref target="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/examples/hubble.html">http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/examples/hubble.html</ref> – section 2.7).
                    All the annotation examples shown there identify this area in terms of an area
                    on the picture in the computer file that contains the Hubble image. The semantic
                    deficit here in these examples is that even though a different photograph of the
                    same area of space might show the same apparent cluster of galaxies, the
                    annotation's target for the Hubble image is specified only in terms of a
                    particular image file and cannot automatically be transferred to another
                    image.</p>
                <p>How could this semantic deficit be reduced, so that this comment about this area
                    of space as shown from earth could be connected to all of them? An obvious
                    answer would be to define the target of the comment to something that more
                    satisfactorily links semantically to this region of space – perhaps the actual
                    astronomical co-ordinates relative to the Celestial Sphere, for example. By
                    attaching the annotation to something that connects to the <soCalled>real world</soCalled> rather
                    than to an area in a piece of media that happened to capture it, we reduce the
                    semantic deficit that separates the annotation from the thing being annotated,
                    and improve the computer's ability to use the link in a way that is more
                    general.</p>
                <p>The approach of locating a segment of a file as the anchor for an annotation
                    works well enough for media-playing applications, even with the semantic deficit
                    it entails. However, not all computer applications are media players. What might
                    happen for them?</p>
                <p>One of the potentially important differences is connected to the way that data
                    that an application works with is represented. Most software developers call the
                    set of digital objects that represent their program's data its model. Usually
                    best development practice has the model objects kept separate from the surrogate
                    objects that display the model’s content on the screen. If one added annotation
                    to an environment that had a backing data model, what would one formally attach
                    the annotations to? One would expect annotations to link to objects in the model
                    rather than the corresponding display surrogates. Since these model/anchor
                    objects would represent the things the software is actually working with one
                    might believe that this would end up reducing the <term>semantic deficit</term> that
                    applies to the standard model of annotation. The model object the annotation
                    attached to would indeed be much more likely to closely represent the thing a
                    user thought the annotation was actually about.</p>
                <p>This perspective of connecting annotation to an actual model representation of
                    the object being discussed in the annotation does not appear to be present in
                    either Agnosti and Ferro or in the OAC data model. Surprisingly, however, Jane
                    Hunter touches briefly on it. Even though Hunter’s article
                    focuses on "document annotation practices" (revealing from the start a strong
                    document/resource/media orientation), she does note that annotation
                    could also mean something that is not attached to a <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2009">document about something,</quote>
                    but to the <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2009">something itself</quote> when she recognises the meaning of <soCalled>annotation</soCalled> in
                    computational biology <ptr target="#hunter2009" loc="4–1"/>. According to Hunter, apparently in this field annotation
                    is understood to actually attach information to particular <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2009">genes or proteins</quote>
                    themselves rather than merely to the pages describing them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Separating Anchor from Target</head>
                <p>In exactly the way that Hunter makes this distinction, Pliny annotation in
                    WordHoard comes close to exploring <q>annotation of the thing itself</q> because
                    WordHoard exhibits the classic model approach to managing its data, with its
                    data model representing the words in its text as linguistic objects. In
                    WordHoard's data model, then, there exists instances of an entity called <soCalled>word</soCalled>
                    that represent words in the text from a linguistic perspective. The word <q>shamest</q>
                    in line 322 from Act 5 Scene 1 in <title rend="italic">Comedy of Errors</title> (shown as highlighted in
                    Figure 6), for example, is an instance of the entity <soCalled>Word</soCalled> in WordHoard's
                    model. Because we are working with model objects in WordHoard, we are in the
                    position to actually attach comments to the things – the actual words – that the
                    comments are about.</p>
                <p>In a practical sense, digital annotation of model objects in a piece of software
                    can only be done when the digital model object it is being attached to is
                    accessible to the user – usually though some sort of display that the
                    application can create. Here, however, we run up against the issue we mentioned
                    briefly earlier that arises out of one of the basic principles of modern
                    software applications – the separation of the <term>model</term> from the <term>display</term>.
                    WordHoard’s words are a part of its <q>model</q>. However, any display of the model
                    data that WordHoard can generate is built out of display surrogates for the
                    model objects – graphical elements that can display on the screen and act as
                    intermediaries between the data itself in the model and the window on the
                    screen. This recognition of the separation between the model objects and its
                    representation to the user is widely acknowledged among developers, and is a key
                    element in the widely used Model-View-Controller (MVC) paradigm of software
                    development.</p>
                <p>This aspect of contemporary software design is relevant to our discussion here
                    because it brings to the foreground the idea of “context” for the display of
                    model data. In fact, displays for any particular piece of the model are
                    generally created by displaying data from several closely-related pieces of the
                    model, and thus the display is not exactly the same thing as the entity it is
                    displaying. Because the display of model data is separate from the model data
                    itself it is possible to show the same piece of model data in different
                    displays, and therefore different contexts. Indeed, the three displays we have
                    seen for WordHoard in the figures above all say something about its word
                    entities such as <q>shamest</q> in Act 5 Scene 1 of <title rend="italic">Errors</title>, but none of them are
                    actually the same as the word itself.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>A WordHoard user can select a word in the text display. WordHoard
                        recognises that the selection is a word and shows, at the bottom of the
                        screen, a brief summary of the PoS for that word. Furthermore, the user can
                        attach an annotation to that word, as we can see in figure 6, where a
                        comment is attached to the word <q>shamest</q>.</item>
                    <item>The WordHoard user can then request the display of the <title rend="quotes">Word Information
                        Panel</title> which displays various kinds of linguistic information about the
                        word. Figure 7 shows the Word Information display (but for a different
                        word).</item>
                    <item>The WordHoard user can select words for display in a KWIC concordance.
                        Perhaps the KWIC display, similar to that shown in figure 8) would display
                        the KWIC item for the word <q>shamest</q>. Although our current implementation of
                        annotation in WordHoard’s KWIC concordance does not, in fact, allow an
                        annotation to be attached to a particular KWIC instance, this could be
                        added.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In these three cases the WordHoard word is presented in different contexts with,
                    therefore, different kinds of information pulled from the data model and
                    provided to the user. For the text display the user sees the word in the
                    extended context of the text that surrounds it. For the Word Information Panel
                    s/he sees it with its linguistic information, and with the concordance the word
                    is displayed in the context of nearby words and other instances of the same
                    word. Any annotation attached to the particular word such as <q>shamest</q> is actually
                    attached to the same semantic object in any of these three display contexts.
                    However the different context in which the word appears may cause the user to
                    make quite different notes about it. Does it make sense, then, to say that the
                    annotations are all attached to this same semantic thing? It wouldn’t appear to
                    be so since the things an annotator might want to say about a word in the
                    context of the text in which it appears might well be different from what he or
                    she would want to say when it appears (as it does in WordHoard’s Word
                    Information display) with its linguistic and morphological information presented
                    about it.</p>
                <p>Thinking about this a little more, then, the different contexts in which the
                    WordHoard word appears can change the situation sufficiently to begin to affect
                    the meaning of the annotation as well – for annotation purposes the meaningful
                    anchor is not only dependent on the anchor object, but also the context in which
                    it is displayed:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>In context of text display, an annotation could discuss a word in its textual context.</item>
                    <item>In context of Info display, it could discuss the word and its morphology.</item>
                    <item>In context of Concordance: it could discuss the word in context of other usage 
                        of the same word in the text.</item>
                    <item>On other hand, some of the annotations might be purely about the word in its own right 
                        (how it is spelled, say), and apply comfortably to all three contexts.</item>
                </list>
                <p>By planning to attach annotations to the WordHoard word itself we thought we had
                    been reducing the <term>semantic deficit</term> that occurs when some text is used as an
                    anchor for an annotation in a printed book. However, it turns out that for an
                    annotation attached to a WordHoard word to have its full significance, the
                    <q>word</q> as anchor for an annotation only a part of the story. The word's context
                    in its display is seemingly also a significant element.</p>
                <p>This clear distinction between the semantic anchor for an annotation and the
                    context in which it appears is not explicitly made in the standard annotation
                    model. Agnosti and Ferro come close when they distinguish between a stream (as
                    context) and a segment (as anchor) in that stream, but a stream segment is
                    always a part of only one particular stream which contains it, and is thus
                    always assumed to appear in the same context. The OAC data model does not
                    recognise this situation well either, blurring the distinction between the
                    display in which the annotated object appears and the portion of it to which it
                    applies, and suggesting using of the W3C's Media Fragment specification
                    to identify a portion of the
                    target document where possible and what they call a "constrained target" if not
                    <ptr target="#SandersonAndVanDeSompel2011" loc="sections 3.7.2 and 3.7.3"/>. Furthermore, the developments in the Semantic Web have muddied
                    the water here too: between a document <emph>about</emph> an object, a real-world object with
                    its digital surrogate, and the context – a document – in which the surrogate
                    appears. See, for example, Jeni Tennison's attempt to clarify URIs for documents
                    <emph>about</emph> things versus URIs <emph>for</emph> real-world things in <ref target="#Tennison2011">Tennison 2011</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Annotation in a Dynamic Display Environment</head>
                <p>And there is more to say yet. As it turns out the role of context in annotation
                    becomes more striking when we consider WordHoard's concordance display (Figure
                    8) because the visual display (the context for notes) can vary so much within
                    it. Recall that in figure 8 we see a screenshot of the WordHoard concordance
                    display centred on Shakespeare's use of the lemma <q>house</q>, with two KWIC
                    displays opened by the user, for <title rend="italic">Anthony and Cleopatra</title> and <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>). The two
                    notes comment on the different meanings for <q>house</q> that Shakespeare has
                    exploiting in the different plays. Note, however that they were probably added
                    when the user had particular KWIC displays open that drew her attention to the
                    different meanings for <q>house</q> in the different plays. If the KWIC displays for
                    other plays are open instead it may not be so obvious that the two annotations
                    are talking about. Although the notes were clearly created as a result of the
                    user working with the KWIC entries, their appearance here, when KWIC entries for
                    only two of the plays are visible, could seem a little odd, since we can no
                    longer directly see what motivated them.</p>
                <p>The problem becomes even more evident if the user changes the ordering option for
                    this display to group usages of <q>house</q> in a different way. Figure 9 shows the
                    beginning of the display now grouped and ordered by date of publication.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>WordHoard concordance ordered by date</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Here one can see the frequency of use of the word <q>house</q> varying substantially
                    over the years, and indeed, perhaps this observation might be the cause for
                    another Pliny note to be added to the two that are already there. Note, however,
                    what has happened to the perceived relevance of the two pre-existing annotations
                    (about the different meanings for <q>house</q>) made earlier when the concordance was
                    ordered by the work. They are less evidently relevant to what WordHoard's
                    concordance display is showing us when the instances are grouped and ordered by
                    Publication date. Similarly, any note made about Shakespeare's varying use of
                    the word <q>house</q> over time that might arise when the user works with this
                    concordance order – although relevant when occurrences are displayed in this way
                    again in the future – will seem out of place if the concordance is displayed
                    again by Work.</p>
                <p>The problem arose, of course, out of our assumption when building Pliny/WordHoard
                    that the targets for annotation could simply be based on the particular display
                    the user was looking at, and this error grew out of our experience of supporting
                    annotation for Pliny’s supported digital media; where this problem did not
                    exist. There, thinking of an annotation as simply linked to a part of a display
                    seemed to present no problems because the media files, such as image files, web
                    pages, PDF documents, that drove the display were relatively static. The <emph>context</emph>
                    in which the annotation was anchored (what comes before, what comes after, and
                    what is actually visible) was always going to be the same. An annotation
                    attached to a media file of this kind, then, gets some part of its meaning from
                    the surrounding visual context in which it is displayed, and this surrounding
                    context is always the same in media-like data. For this reason, the context for
                    the annotation of media objects can be simply ignored in thinking about its
                    formal representation. This was simply not true in the dynamic KWIC display that
                    WordHoard provided.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Summary and Conclusions</head>
                <p>The focus on digital libraries and on the World Wide Web has encouraged a view of
                    digital objects primarily as documents, or perhaps more generally as media
                    objects. Although much work has been done exploring environments for presenting
                    these media objects and exploring various strategies for putting them together
                    into larger objects such as collections, the focus on only media files as
                    digital objects has constrained the thinking about the possible range of
                    interactions and their semantics that a human being might have with them.</p>
                <p>Digital annotation, as one of these kinds of interactions, has been thought of by
                    many solely in this document/media context: primarily as an act carried out on
                    static digital media formats such as those seen in a PDF or video file. This has
                    been perhaps understandable, not only because of its origins in the
                    media-oriented WWW, but also because the non-digital inspiration for digital
                    annotation has primarily been annotation in printed (and therefore static)
                    books. The publically available version of Pliny, in its basic distributed form,
                    supported annotation for media objects, and did not seem to disturb the model of
                    a <soCalled>static</soCalled> object being annotated either, even though, of course, a digital
                    object needn’t be simply a holder for static media content.</p>
                <p>In spite of the strong presence of the WWW and media in our thinking about
                    annotation, digital objects are not always pieces of media, and some of the
                    strategies we have for exploring the potential of digital methods for the
                    humanities do not suit them. Northwestern’s <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> is a tool for supporting
                    certain kinds of traditional scholarly activities – but its operation is not
                    captured by thinking of it as a kind of media viewer. Instead, the user is given
                    access to a set of mechanisms to explore and interact with a complex set of
                    textual objects for themselves. Annotation can be useful in a tool like
                    WordHoard since while working with it a user may well notice something which
                    provides some new insight for which an annotation would be useful. Thus,
                    annotation is a useful adjunct to what WordHoard does, even though annotation
                    there does not fit comfortably with the digital media driven "standard model" of
                    annotation. Although WordHoard is a particular application, it is certainly not
                    the only application that cannot be well categorised as a piece of media display
                    software. Tool kits such as text mining environments or network analysis
                    environments (to take two examples of strategies in vogue within the digital
                    humanities at present) also do not work with a media orientation, and annotation
                    frameworks that are media-oriented do not sit well with them either. Rethinking
                    of annotation to encompass annotation outside of a media context is necessary to
                    fit annotation properly into these new tools.</p>
                <p>Perhaps if you are not a digital annotation enthusiast you are wondering why this
                    issue might apply to you. Why should you care? Perhaps annotation has a place to
                    play in the broader evangelical nature of the digital humanities – the desire by
                    many in the DH community to promote the new tools as a new way to do the
                    humanities. These new tools such as text mining often have appeared to be a hard
                    sell in the humanities, and proponents of them have often found that
                    traditionally-oriented researchers seem uninterested. Of course, trying to
                    squeeze a scholarly interest <q>A</q> through a tool <q>B</q> which is manifestly not
                    related to it provides, by itself, a good reason perhaps why sometimes these new
                    tools have not penetrated the consciousness of mainstream humanities scholars.
                    However, one can sometimes find situations where even when a particular new tool <emph>does</emph>
                    seem to do something relevant to a scholar’s interest it still is not being
                    taken up. Perhaps this is because these more conservative colleagues don't see
                    how to incorporate the results from these tools into the rest of their
                    research.</p>
                <p>Perhaps annotation helps in this situation, particular when done in the way that
                    Pliny does it. If these new tools had Pliny annotation incorporated into them,
                    it would be possible for humanists to use annotation to note things in the
                    results from these new tools that struck them as interesting and to <soCalled>bind</soCalled> these
                    results with what they are finding from their more conventional research work
                    (arising from the reading of, say, a scholarly article presented in a PDF file
                    format). If <title rend="quotes">App A</title> in figure 4 was one of these new tools, the ability of run
                    it within the Pliny context would make it possible to integrate its results with
                    material from other traditional digital and even non-digital sources – WordHoard
                    in Pliny allows a user's observations that arise in WordHoard to be linked to
                    the observations he or she has made while reading an journal article in PDF. In
                    this way one might, through annotation, move a step towards binding these new
                    tools within the framework of traditional humanities research practice.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, this need to integrate new tool results with material from older
                    scholarly practices does not only affect our more cautious colleagues who may be
                    uncomfortable with these new research paradigms. Even a researcher who
                    enthusiastically uses these new tools still needs to take the materials s/he
                    finds there and to integrate them with references to traditional scholarship in
                    order to present results to the public. Franco Moretti, for instance, developed
                    his ideas about distant reading through using tools that treated his materials
                    of study in highly original ways. However, he chose to present these ideas in
                    the form of a narrative argument in the traditional way: through a printed book
                    (e.g., <ptr target="#Moretti2005"/>), and in that narrative he needed to combine results from
                    his new way of doing research with material that came out of traditional
                    methods, exhibited by references to mainstream scholarship. Annotation inside
                    new digital tools such as those that support the tools Moretti used for, say,
                    text mining could provide a mechanism that allows these new research tools to
                    better integrate with traditional scholarly practice – something even leading
                    edge digital scholars still need to do as well.</p>
                <p>In the work reported here <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> was taken up as an representative of the new
                    kind of tools. By supporting Pliny-style notetaking within <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> we allowed
                    its user to both record something s/he has noticed in a <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> display and
                    then to integrate this with observations that arose from the conventional
                    reading of other materials. By allows insights that arise in WordHoard to mix
                    with insights developed from traditional scholarship, Pliny allows <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> to
                    integrate more readily into the traditional activities of scholarship. The
                    scholar when writing an article could draw on notes that arose from insights
                    that happened when s/he was using <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title>, as well as when s/he was reading
                    print or digital documents. In this way, annotation and notetaking become
                    central acts both of traditional, print oriented or web, scholarship, but also
                    as acts that can be associated comfortably with the newer, more dynamic, digital
                    applications.</p>
                <p>Pliny’s working environment provides a powerful model for integration of not just
                    media-presenting tools such as its (already existing) image and PDF annotation
                    tools and potentially other media such as 3D, video or audio objects, but also
                    as an environment which encourages newer, much more broadly conceived,
                    applications to co-exist and even potentially interoperate in complex ways. Our
                    work with the integration of <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> with Pliny both demonstrated the
                    plausible, practical, nature of this kind of integration, but also revealed the
                    need for some new thinking about the relationship between annotation and these
                    more general, digital but non media-oriented, objects with which applications
                    like <title rend="italic">WordHoard</title> operate.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>The work reported on here came from research that was funded in large part by The
                    Mellon Foundation through their MATC award program. The author is particularly
                    grateful to the Foundation for the recognition that made this work possible. I
                    am also grateful to Prof. Martin Mueller and the team who developed WordHoard at
                    Northwestern University for their interest and support for this experiment.
                    Finally, I am very grateful for the work contributed by my two DDH colleagues
                    who did a significant amount of the development work for the WordHoard/Pliny
                    software, and in spite of the technical challenges it represented worked at it
                    very professionally and with good insights and good spirit: Payman Labbaff
                    first, and subsequently Timothy Hill.</p>
                <p>
               <emph>Pliny</emph>’s development and the thinking about annotation and notetaking that it
                    represents was made possible by the provision of research leave for me at King’s
                    College London, and the continued provision of some research time after it was
                    over. I am deeply grateful to KCL, and in particular to the head of (then) CCH
                    (now DDH), Harold Short, and my colleague Willard McCarty for their support for
                    this work over a number of years.</p>
                <p>I am also grateful to DHQ's anonymous reviewers who encouraged me to somewhat
                    recast this paper's original presentation to hopefully make the relevance of the
                    work it describes evident to a larger readership.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="AgnostiAndFerro2007" label="Agnosti and Ferro 2007" key="AgnostiAndFerro2007">Agnosti, Maristella and
                    Nicola Ferro. <title rend="quotes">A Formal Model of Annotations of Digital Content.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">ACM
                        Transactions on Information Systems</title>. 26.1: 2007. Article 3, 57 pages. <ref target="http://doi.acm/org/10.1145/1292591.1292594">
                    http://doi.acm/org/10.1145/1292591.1292594</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="AO2012" label="AO 2012" key="AO2012">
               <title rend="italic">annotation-ontology</title> project website. 
                    <ref target="http://code.google.com/p/annotation-ontology/">http://code.google.com/p/annotation-ontology/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Birsan2005" label="Birsan 2005" key="Birsan2005">Birsan, Dorian. <title rend="quotes">On Plug-ins and Extensible Architectures</title>. <title rend="italic">Queue</title> (ACM), 
                    3.2. <ref target="http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=1053345">http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=1053345</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley2008" label="Bradley 2008" key="bradley2008a">Bradley, John. <title rend="quotes">Thinking about Interpretation: 
                    Pliny and Scholarship in the Humanities</title>. 
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 23.3: 2008, pp. 263-79. 
                    doi: 10.1093/llc/fqn021.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley2008c" label="Bradley 2008c" key="bradley2008c">Bradley, John. <title rend="quotes">Pliny: A model for digital support 
                    of scholarship</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Information</title> (JoDI). 9.1: 2008 
                    (formally No. 26). <ref target="http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/view/209/198">http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/view/209/198</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Bradley2008b" label="Bradley 2008b" key="Bradley2008b">Bradley, John. <title rend="quotes">Playing together:
                    modular tools and Pliny</title>. draft of paper, given at <emph>DH 2008</emph> (University of Oulu,
                    Finland), June 2008. <ref target="http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/docs/oulu-paper.html">http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/docs/oulu-paper.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="BradleyHill2011" label="Bradley and Hill 2011" key="BradleyHill2011">Bradley, John and
                    Timothy Hill. <title rend="italic">When WordHoard met Pliny: breaking down of interaction silos
                        between applications</title>. Poster presented at <title rend="italic">DH 2011</title> conference, Stanford
                    University, June 19-22, 2011. Draft available online at
                    <ref target="http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/docs/Stanford-Poster.pdf">http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/docs/Stanford-Poster.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="BrockmanEtAl2001" label="Brockman et al 2001" key="BrockmanEtAl2001">Brockman, William S.,
                    Laura Neumann, Carole L. Palmer, Tonyia J. Tidline. <title rend="italic">Scholarly Work in the
                        Humanities and the Evolving Information Environment</title>, a report from the Council
                    on Library and Information Resources (Washington DC: Digital Library Federation,
                    Council on Library and Information Resources). (2001). 
                    <ref target="http://www.diglib.org/pubs/dlf095/">http://www.diglib.org/pubs/dlf095/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="CiccareseEtAl2010" label="Ciccarese et al 2010" key="CiccareseEtAl2010">Ciccarese, Paolo,
                    Marco Ocana, Leyla Jael Garcia Castro, Sudeshna Das and Tim Clark. <title rend="quotes">An open
                    annotation ontology for science on web 3.0</title>. in <title rend="italic">Journal of Biomedical Semantics</title>,
                    Vol 2 (Suppl):S4 2011. 
                    <ref target="http://www.jbiomedsem.com/content/2/S2/S4/abstract">http://www.jbiomedsem.com/content/2/S2/S4/abstract</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Cohen2008" label="Cohen 2008" key="Cohen2008b">Cohan, Daniel J. <title rend="quotes">Creating Scholarly
                    Tools and Resources for the Digital Ecosystem: Building Connections in the Zotero
                    Project</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 13.8: 2008. 
                    <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DM2012" label="DM 2012" key="DM2012">
               <title rend="italic">DM</title> website. <ref target="http://ada.drew.edu/dmproject/">http://ada.drew.edu/dmproject/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Eclipse2011" label="Eclipse 2011" key="Eclipse2011">
               <title rend="italic">Eclipse</title> home website. <ref target="http://www.eclipse.org/">http://www.eclipse.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hunter2009" label="Hunter 2009" key="hunter2009b">Hunter, Jane. <title rend="quotes">Collaborative semantic
                    tagging and annotation systems</title>. <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Information Science and
                        Technology</title>. 43.1: 2009. pp.1-84. DOI: 10.1002/aris.2009.1440430111. 
                    <ref target="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aris.2009.1440430111/full">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aris.2009.1440430111/full</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="JacobsAndWalsh2004" label="Jacobs and Walsh 2004" key="JacobsAndWalsh2004">Jacobs, Ian and
                    Norman Walsh, (Eds). <title rend="italic">Architecture of the World Wide Web, Volume One</title>, W3C
                    Recommendation 15 December 2004. <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="LassilaAndSwick1999" label="Lassila and Swick 1999" key="LassilaAndSwick1999">Lassila, Ora and
                    Ralph R. Swick (eds). <title rend="italic">Resource Description Framework (RDF) Model and Syntax
                        Specification</title>. W3C (1999). 
                    <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-rdf-syntax-19990222/">http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-rdf-syntax-19990222/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Marshall1998" label="Marshall 1998" key="Marshall1998">Marshall, Catherine C. <title rend="quotes">Toward an
                    ecology of hypertext annotation</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of HyperText 98</title>. Pittsburgh, PA.
                    ACM Press. pp. 40-49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="MarshallAndBush2004" label="Marshall and Bush 2004" key="MarshallAndBush2004">Marshall,
                    Catherine C and A.J. Bernheim Brush. <title rend="quotes">Exploring the relationship between
                    personal and public annotations</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of JCDL ’04</title> conference. Tucson
                    AZ. ACM Press. pp. 349-357</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Moretti2005" label="Moretti 2005" key="moretti2005">Moretti, Franco. <title rend="italic">Graphs, Maps,
                    Trees: abstract models for a literary theory</title>. London: Verso Books, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="OAC2011" label="OAC 2011" key="OAC2011">
               <title rend="italic">Open Annotation Collaboration</title>. 
                    <ref target="http://www.openannotation.org/">http://www.openannotation.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="OntoText2011" label="OntoText 2011" key="OntoText2011">
               <title rend="quotes">Glossary</title>. Webpage for OntoText AD corporation. <ref target="http://www.ontotext.com/kim/getting-started/glossary">http://www.ontotext.com/kim/getting-started/glossary</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Bradley2006" label="Bradley 2006" key="Bradley2006">
               <title rend="italic">Pliny: A Note Manager</title>. <ref target="http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/">http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Salsah2012" label="Salsah 2012" key="Salsah2012">
               <title rend="italic">Salsah</title>. Basel University Research Database website. <ref target="https://forschdb2.unibas.ch/inf2/rm_projects/object_view.php?r=291028type=5">https://forschdb2.unibas.ch/inf2/rm_projects/object_view.php?r=291028type=5</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="SandersonAndVanDeSompel2011" label="Sanderson and Van de Sompel 2011" key="SandersonAndVanDeSompel2011">
                    Sanderson, Robert and Herbert Van de Sompel (eds). <title rend="italic">Open Annotation: Beta Data
                        Model Guide</title>. <ref target="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/">http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="SignerAndNorrie2009" label="Signer and Norrie 2009" key="SignerAndNorrie2009">Signer, Beat and Noira C. Norrie. 
                    <title rend="quotes">An Architecture for Open Cross-Media Annotation Services</title>. In <title rend="italic">WISE '09: Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on Web Information Systems Engineering</title>. 
                    Berlin: Springer-Verlag. ISBN: 978-3-642-04408-3, doi: 10.1007/978-3-642-04409-0_39. pp. 387-400.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Tennison2011" label="Tennison 2011" key="Tennison2011">Tennison, Jeni. <title rend="quotes">What Do URIs Mean Anyway?</title>. 
                    In blog Jeni’s Musings. <ref target="http://www.jenitennison.com/blog/node/159">http://www.jenitennison.com/blog/node/159</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TILE2011" label="TILE 2011" key="TILE2011">
               <title rend="italic">Tile: text-image linking environment</title>. 
                    <ref target="http://mith.umd.edu/tile/">http://mith.umd.edu/tile/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="VictoriaAndAlbert" label="Victoria and Albert (no date)" key="VictoriaAndAlbert">
               <title rend="italic">Victoria and Albert Museum 
                    API Documentation</title>. <ref target="http://www.vam.ac.uk/api">http://www.vam.ac.uk/api</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="WermelingerAndYu2008" label="Wermelinger and Yu 2008" key="WermelingerAndYu2008">Wermelinger, Michel and Yijun Yu. 
                    <title rend="quotes">Analyzing the evolution of eclipse plugins</title>. 
                    In <title rend="italic">MRS '08: Proceedings of the 2008 international working conference on Mining software repositories</title>. 
                    New York: ACM. pp. 133-36. doi: 10.1145/1370750.1370783</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="WordHoard2004-11" label="WordHoard 2004-11" key="WordHoard2004-11">
               <title rend="italic">WordHoard: An Application for the close 
                    reading and scholarly analysis of deeply tagged text</title>. 
                    <ref target="http://wordhoard.northwestern.edu/userman/index.html">http://wordhoard.northwestern.edu/userman/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Zotero2012" label="Zotero 2012" key="zotero2012">
               <title rend="italic">Zotero</title> website. <ref target="http://www.zotero.org/">http://www.zotero.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>