<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Beyond Gutenberg: Transcending the Document Paradigm in
                    Digital Humanities</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Schloen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dschloen@uchicago.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David Schloen is Associate Professor of Archaeology in the Oriental
                            Institute and Department of Near Eastern Languages and Civilizations of
                            the University of Chicago. He studies the material and textual evidence
                            of society and economy in the ancient Levant and directs excavation
                            projects in Turkey and Israel. Prior to entering academia, he earned a
                            degree in computer science and worked professionally as a software
                            developer for a large corporation. He is currently the faculty chair of
                            the University of Chicago’s Digital Humanities Oversight Committee and
                            is director of the Center for Jewish Studies.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Sandra <dhq:family>Schloen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Chicago</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sschloen@uchicago.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sandra Schloen is a software engineer and the head of the OCHRE Data
                            Service at the University of Chicago. She has a degree in computer
                            science and a graduate degree in education. She has worked
                            professionally as a software developer since the 1980s in both business
                            and academic settings, with an emphasis on complex database systems and
                            scholarly research applications. She develops software in close
                            consultation with academic projects that span a wide range of
                            fields.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000196</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2014-12-20">20 December 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Computer-aided research in the humanities has been inhibited by the prevailing
                    paradigm of software design in humanities computing, namely, the document
                    paradigm. This article discusses the limitations of the document paradigm and
                    contrasts it with the database paradigm. It describes a database-oriented
                    approach that provides a better way to create digital representations of
                    scholarly knowledge, allowing individual observations and interpretations to be
                    shared more widely, analyzed more effectively, and preserved indefinitely.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A discussion of the limitations of the document paradigm vs. the database
                    paradigm.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Computer-aided research in the humanities has been inhibited by the prevailing
                    paradigm of software design in humanities computing (or, as it is now called,
                    digital humanities). The prevailing paradigm is so pervasive and has been
                    entrenched for so long that many people have difficulty imagining an
                    alternative. We are referring to the document paradigm of software design, in
                    which the structure of pre-digital documents is the basis for the data
                    structures in which information is represented digitally. In the document
                    paradigm, the digital representation of information depends on the relative
                    position of units of information in one or two dimensions. Information is
                    represented by linear character strings or by tables consisting of rows and
                    columns, as on a flat printed page.</p>
                <p>These position-dependent data structures are familiar to people who have been
                    trained to read books, which accounts for their popularity. But they fail to
                    meet the needs of scholars if they are used, not simply as intuitive display
                    formats, but as the basic organizing structures for the digital representation
                    of scholarly information. We pay a steep price for clinging to convenient
                    analogies like <q>line,</q>
                    <q>ledger,</q>
                    <q>page,</q>
                    <q>book,</q> and <q>library</q> insofar as we treat them as basic structures in
                    our software rather than merely convenient ways to present information to
                    end-users. By organizing information within position-dependent data structures
                    limited to one or two dimensions, such as strings and tables, we fail to
                    represent the full range of scholarly observations and interpretations in a
                    predictable and semantically rich digital form that permits powerful automated
                    comparisons and analyses.<note> We are referring here to logical data structures
                        that an application programmer manipulates by means of a high-level
                        programming language. Some of the simplest logical structures are
                        one-dimensional arrays that represent character strings and two-dimensional
                        arrays that represent tables. We do not claim that programmers can dispense
                        with these simple structures as components of more complex data structures;
                        rather, we are emphasizing the limitations of using a one- or
                        two-dimensional structure not just as a building block but as the
                        overarching way of organizing information, which is what is commonly done in
                        humanities computing.</note></p>
                <p>For example, in the document paradigm a text will be represented as a long
                    sequence of numeric codes in which each code represents a character in a writing
                    system (e.g., the standard ASCII numbers used for characters in the Latin
                    alphabet). Some of the characters may constitute annotations or <q>markup
                        tags</q> interspersed among characters that represent the text itself, but
                    both the text and its markup will be represented by a single string of character
                    codes. A character string with embedded markup tags can be interpreted as a
                    hierarchical <q>tree</q> of textual components, yielding a more complex data
                    structure. However, the semantic potential of the tree structure will be limited
                    by the fact that the markup tags occur at particular positions within what is,
                    ultimately, just a one-dimensional sequence of character codes.</p>
                <p>This widely used method of text encoding is sufficient for many purposes in daily
                    life and in research outside the humanities. But it has been borrowed
                    inappropriately from non-scholarly domains to be used for literary and
                    historical texts that are objects of study in their own right. Some kinds of
                    scholarly work can be done using this method, but it imposes unnecessary limits
                    if it is used as the primary means of representing a text. It deprives scholars
                    of the power to express in digital form many of the conceptual distinctions they
                    employ routinely in the course of their work. They end up imitating the
                    position-dependent structure of a pre-digital medium rather than exploiting the
                    potential of the digital medium to represent their information in a more
                    effective way. As a result, they fail to capture in an explicit, searchable form
                    the different ways a given text has been read and annotated, making it difficult
                    to use computational methods to compare and analyze the various interpretations.
                    And it is precisely those texts which are open to many different readings that
                    are of greatest interest to scholars in the humanities, who spend considerable
                    time tracing the history of textual interpretation and the interconnections
                    within and among texts — tasks that could be greatly facilitated by the
                    appropriate digital tools.</p>
                <p>The alternative to the document paradigm is the database paradigm, which is
                    characterized by data structures that transcend the position-dependent structure
                    of pre-digital documents. Database systems make use of unique
                        <soCalled>keys</soCalled> and internal indexes to retrieve and recombine
                    atomized units of information in a flexible manner. The database paradigm has
                    been wrongly neglected in the humanities because it is thought to be unsuitable
                    for free-form texts. Databases are thought to be suitable only for highly
                    structured tables of data, which is what many people think of when they hear the
                    word <q>database.</q> But there is a great deal of predictable structure both
                    within texts themselves and within scholarly analyses of them — structure of a
                    kind that is best represented digitally by means of a properly atomized and
                    keyed database.</p>
                <p>Moreover, a data table is itself a document and not a database. Even if we were
                    to aggregate separate tables into a collection of tables, we would not thereby
                    create a database, properly speaking, regardless of whether we use database
                    software to manage the various tables. According to the document-versus-database
                    distinction employed in this article, a collection of tables would constitute a
                    database only if the tables were linked via key fields and were
                        <soCalled>normalized</soCalled> to minimize the duplication of information,
                    necessitating <soCalled>joins</soCalled> among two or more tables to produce a
                    dynamic view of the atomized information in response to a particular
                        query.<note> For explanations of database <q>normalization,</q>
                        <q>keys,</q>
                        <q>joins</q> and other technical details, see <title rend="italic">Database
                            Systems: The Complete Book</title> by Hector Garcia-Molina, Jeffrey D.
                        Ullman, and Jennifer Widom <ptr target="#garcia2009"/>.</note> Thus, the
                    distinction between documents and databases is not a distinction between
                    unstructured textual information and structured tables. Rather, it is a
                    distinction between position-dependent data structures that mimic pre-digital
                    documents — be they one-dimensional character strings or two-dimensional tables
                    — and the atomized, flexible, and hence multi-dimensional structure of a true
                    database.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, because of the pervasiveness of the document paradigm, which has
                    become a deeply engrained tradition in humanities computing, scholarly software
                    development has focused on digital documents. There are a few exceptions but on
                    the whole there has been very little effort expended to develop database systems
                    for research in the humanities, even though there has been no insuperable
                    technical barrier to doing so in the past forty years, since the advent of the
                    relational data model and general-purpose database querying languages. Moreover,
                    in the last ten years, non-relational data models and querying languages have
                    emerged that make possible the creation of powerful database systems that
                    preserve the best features of relational systems but can more easily accommodate
                        texts.<note> We are referring here to atomized and normalized database
                        systems with semantically rich schemas suitable for comprehensive querying
                        in a finely grained manner, as opposed to document-oriented
                            <soCalled>content-management</soCalled> systems. See <ptr
                            target="#garcia2009"/> for an explanation of the relational data model
                        and the SQL querying language, as well as an overview of the newer
                        semistructured (XML) data model and XQuery querying language. Either or both
                        of these data models can now be employed when building high-performance
                        multi-user systems using <soCalled>enterprise-level</soCalled> database
                        management software such as Oracle, IBM’s DB2, and MarkLogic. A third model,
                        the graph data model — so called because it is based on mathematical graph
                        theory — actually predates the relational data model in its use within
                        database systems and is currently enjoying a revival (in the 1960s and
                        1970s, a graph-oriented approach was used in <soCalled>network</soCalled>
                        databases). For an introduction to the graph data model, see Chapter 9 in
                            <title rend="italic">Foundations of Computer Science</title> by Aho and
                        Ullman <ptr target="#aho1995"/>. The semistructured XML model is itself a
                        type of graph data model that is particularly well-suited for hierarchically
                        organized data, though it is by no means limited to hierarchies; however,
                        the term <q>graph database</q> has come to be used primarily for more
                        loosely structured non-hierarchical networks of data elements.</note> It is
                    time to embrace the database paradigm in digital humanities and invest more
                    effort in developing software within that paradigm instead of within the
                    document paradigm. This is the best way to create digital representations of
                    scholarly knowledge that can store individual observations and interpretations
                    in a manner that allows them to be shared more widely, analyzed more
                    effectively, and preserved indefinitely.</p>
                <p>In the remainder of this six-part article we will explain in more detail why the
                    database paradigm is better for digital research in the humanities than the
                    document paradigm. We will start in Part One by discussing the nature of digital
                    texts and the <soCalled>problem of overlapping hierarchies</soCalled> that
                    plagues the widely used linear-character-sequence method of digitizing texts.
                    This text-encoding method conforms to the document paradigm but it cannot cope
                    with multiple readings of the same text, which are best represented digitally as
                    overlapping hierarchies consisting of the same textual components. The inability
                    of this method to represent overlapping hierarchies limits its usefulness for
                    scholarly research.</p>
                <p>In Part Two, we examine how it was that the document paradigm came to dominate
                    software design in the humanities, despite its limitations. We will summarize
                    the parallel histories of the document paradigm and the database paradigm since
                    they emerged in the 1960s in order to understand the difference between them.
                    And we will see how, in recent years, the document paradigm has enriched the
                    database paradigm and made it even more suitable for computational work in the
                    humanities.</p>
                <p>In Part Three, looking forward, we discuss in general terms how to transcend the
                    document paradigm and work within the database paradigm in a way that enables
                    scholars to represent all the entities, properties, and relationships of
                    interest to them, including multiple readings of the same text that are
                    represented by means of overlapping hierarchies. This requires an
                        <soCalled>item-based</soCalled> atomization of information. A suitably
                    designed database system that implements an item-based ontology<note> In
                        philosophy, ontology is the study of being and of the basic categories of
                        being, but we are using the term in the way it has come to be used in
                        information science, ever since it was borrowed by artificial-intelligence
                        researchers in the 1980s. Tom Gruber, then at Stanford University, defined
                        it this way: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#gruber1993">A body of formally
                            represented knowledge is based on a <emph>conceptualization</emph>: the
                            objects, concepts, and other entities that are presumed to exist in some
                            area of interest and the relationships that hold among them. . . . An
                                <emph>ontology</emph> is an explicit specification of a
                            conceptualization</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gruber1993"/></cit>. Note that an ontology is merely a description
                        of concepts and relationships; it is not a technical specification for any
                        particular data-retrieval system. An ontology must be implemented in a
                        working system by means of a <soCalled>schema</soCalled> that defines
                        logical data structures that represent what is described in the ontology
                        (e.g., the interlinked table structures of a relational system).</note> can
                    allow us to represent scholarly knowledge in a highly flexible but still
                    predictable form — a digital form of knowledge whose schema is sufficiently
                    rich, semantically, to permit efficient automated searches, while still making
                    it easy for researchers to reconfigure their data and to integrate it tightly
                    both within and across individual research projects.</p>
                <p>In Part Four, we describe a specific example of how this atomized item-based
                    ontology has been implemented in a working database system in use at the
                    University of Chicago. This is a multi-user, multi-project, and highly scalable
                    non-relational database system that takes advantage of recent innovations in
                    database software. It relies on a standardized data format (XML) and
                    corresponding querying language (XQuery) that have been incorporated into
                    high-performance database software over the past decade as an alternative to
                    relational tables and the SQL querying language. We have therefore been able to
                    borrow many of the best features of older relational database systems while
                    working more easily with the complex overlapping hierarchies that characterize
                    data in the humanities.</p>
                <p>In Part Five, we explain how a hierarchical, item-based ontology implemented in a
                    database system allows us to go beyond isolated data silos to a sustainable
                    online research environment that encompasses and integrates a vast array of
                    information of interest to scholars — information that can be rigorously
                    searched and analyzed, in the spirit of the Semantic Web, overcoming the
                    limitations of the traditional document-oriented (and semantically impoverished)
                    World Wide Web. Texts and the many ways of reading them are only one example of
                    the information we need to search and analyze. The same generic ontology can be
                    used for other kinds of information pertaining to persons, places, artifacts,
                    and events. This enables interoperability and economies of scale among a wide
                    range of users. To realize the full benefits of digitization in the humanities,
                    our software tools should allow us to capture explicitly, in a reproducible
                    digital form, all the distinctions and relationships we wish to make, not just
                    in textual studies but also in archaeology, history, and many other cultural and
                    social disciplines. This raises the important issue of <soCalled>data
                        integration</soCalled> and how it can best be achieved, which is dealt with
                    in Part Six.</p>
                <p>In Part Six of this article, we conclude by exploring the implications of the
                    digital ontology we are advocating with respect to the question of whether
                    digitization necessarily forces us to standardize our modes of description or
                    whether we can obtain the benefits of structured data and powerful automated
                    queries without conceding semantic authority to the designers and sponsors of
                    the software we use. We argue that standardization of terminologies and
                    classifications is not necessary for data integration and large-scale querying.
                    A suitably designed item-based system allows us to safeguard the ontological
                    heterogeneity that is the hallmark of critical scholarship in the humanities.
                    Overlapping textual hierarchies are just one example of this heterogeneity,
                    which permeates scholarly work and should not be suppressed by standardized
                    document-tagging schemes or rigid database table formats.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>1. The problem of overlapping hierarchies</head>
                <p>In order to understand why the document paradigm leads to inadequate digital
                    representations of scholarly texts, we must first define what we mean by a
                        <soCalled>digital text.</soCalled> One way of digitizing a text is to make a
                    facsimile image of it — for example, scanning it to produce a bitmapped
                    photograph — for the purpose of displaying it to human readers. However, a great
                    deal of work in digital humanities is based, not on facsimile images, but on the
                    digitizing of texts in a form that allows automated searching and analysis of
                    their contents. Yet, when we go beyond making a visual facsimile of a text and
                    try to represent its meaningful content, then what we are actually digitizing is
                    not the text per se but a particular reading of it.</p>
                <p>The standard method of creating a digital text from a non-digital original
                    involves the character-by-character encoding of the text as a sequence of
                    numbers using one number per character. But this kind of encoding represents
                    just one potentially debatable interpretation of the physical marks on an
                    inscribed medium. Even in the simplest character-by-character encoding of a
                    text, without any editorial annotations in the form of embedded markup, choices
                    are being made about how to map the marks of inscription onto standard numeric
                    codes that represent characters in a particular writing system. Moreover, all
                    character-encoding schemes, such as ASCII and Unicode, themselves embody prior
                    interpretive choices about how to represent a given writing system and,
                    crucially, what to leave out of the representation. These choices were not
                    inevitable but must be understood historically with respect to particular
                    individuals and institutional settings. There is a historically contingent
                    tradition of encoding characters electronically that began long ago with Samuel
                    Morse and the telegraph, with the long and short signals of the Morse
                        code.<note> The ASCII and Unicode character-encoding systems ubiquitous in
                        computers today are descendants of the telegraphic coding systems that
                        originated in the 1830s with Samuel Morse’s quite reductive encoding of the
                        characters used in English-language texts. Morse and his successors were, of
                        course, mainly concerned with encoding the Latin alphabetic characters used
                        in modern American and European orthography. As a result, these were the
                        only universally standardized electronic characters for many years, until
                        quite recently, making it difficult to encode non-Western texts.</note> When
                    we speak of digital texts we should remember that every encoding of a
                    non-digital work is a reductive sampling of a more complex phenomenon. The
                    original work is represented by sequences of binary digits according to some
                    humanly produced and potentially debatable encoding scheme.<note> Indeed, the
                        0’s and 1’s of individual binary digits are themselves just conventionalized
                        human interpretations of measurable physical differences in analogue
                        phenomena such as electrical current, or magnetic polarity, or surface depth
                        in a pitted metallic film encased in plastic, whose depth is measured by a
                        laser in a CD- or DVD-player. The numeric value of what we interpret as a
                        sequence of binary digits (abbreviated by the term <q>bits</q>) is then a
                        further interpretation in terms of the base-2 positional numeral system; and
                        the correspondence of that number to a written character involves yet
                        another step of interpretation. For example, the eight-bit sequence 01000001
                        has the numeric value sixty-five, which is the standard ASCII code for the
                        Latin capital letter A, by computing in base-2 as follows: 0×2<hi
                            rend="superscript">7</hi> + 1×2<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> + 0×2<hi
                            rend="superscript">5</hi> + 0×2<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> + 0×2<hi
                            rend="superscript">3</hi> + 0×2<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 0×2<hi
                            rend="superscript">1</hi> + 1×2<hi rend="superscript">0</hi> = 65 (as we
                        would write it in the more familiar base-10 positional system, i.e., 6×10<hi
                            rend="superscript">1</hi> + 5×10<hi rend="superscript">0</hi> =
                        65).</note></p>
                <p>For example, the Unicode Consortium makes debatable choices about what to include
                    in its now ubiquitous character-encoding standard [<ref
                        target="http://www.unicode.org">http://www.unicode.org</ref>]. Even though
                    it gives codes for many thousands of characters, it does not attempt to capture
                    every graphic variant, or allograph, of every character in every human writing
                    system. This is understandable as a practical matter but it creates problems for
                    researchers for whom such variations are themselves an important object of study
                    because they indicate scribal style, networks of education and cultural
                    influence, diachronic trends, and so on. So we should start by acknowledging
                    that digitally representing a text as a sequence of standard character codes
                    really represents just one possible reading of the text; and, furthermore, this
                    representation is encoded in a way that reflects a particular interpretation of
                    the writing system used to create the text in the first place.</p>
                <p>The problem is that many texts are open to multiple readings, both on the
                    epigraphic level and on the grammatical or discourse level, and yet the dominant
                    text-encoding method in use today, which is characterized by linear
                    character-code sequences with embedded markup, is not capable of representing
                    multiple readings of the same text in a workable manner. This is a serious
                    problem for scholars in the humanities, in particular, for whom the whole point
                    of studying a text is to come up with a new or improved interpretation of it. It
                    is an especially pressing concern in fields of research in which divergent
                    readings occur at quite low levels of grammatical interpretation or epigraphic
                    decipherment. For example, when working with writing systems that do not have
                    word dividers, as is common in ancient texts, we often face ambiguous word
                    segmentations. And many texts have suffered physical damage or are inscribed in
                    an ambiguous way, giving rise not only to debatable word segmentations on the
                    grammatical level but also to debatable epigraphic readings.</p>
                <p>The problem is perhaps obvious in the case of philological work on manuscripts,
                    in which we need to record the decisions made by editors and commentators in
                    such a way that we can efficiently display and compare different readings of a
                    text whose physical condition, language, or writing system make it difficult to
                    understand. However, the problem arises also with modern printed texts and even
                    with <soCalled>born digital</soCalled> texts. Useful work on such texts can of
                    course be done with simple linear character encodings (with or without markup
                    tags) by means of string-matching searches and other software manipulations that
                    conform to the document paradigm. But a one-dimensional encoding cannot capture,
                    in a way that is amenable to automated querying, the decisions made by different
                    scholars as they come up with different ways of analyzing a text and of relating
                    its components to one another or to another text entirely.</p>
                <p>With the wealth of software tools at our disposal today, scholars should not have
                    to settle for a method of digitizing texts that cannot easily accommodate
                    multiple readings of the same text. They ought to be able to represent in
                    digital form various ways of reading a text while capturing the fact that these
                    are interpretations of the same text. Computers should help scholars debate
                    their different readings by making it easy to compare variations without
                    suppressing the very diversity of readings that motivates their scholarly work.
                    But the only way to do this is by abandoning the deeply engrained tradition of
                    treating digital texts as documents, that is, as data objects which are
                    configured in one or two dimensions. Scholarly texts should instead be
                    represented in a multi-dimensional fashion by means of a suitably designed
                    database system.</p>
                <p>To understand the limitations of the document-oriented approach, it is worth
                    examining the scholarly markup standard promulgated by the Text Encoding
                    Initiative (TEI), an international consortium founded in 1987 (see <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"
                    >http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</ref>; <ptr target="#cummings2007"/>). As we
                    have said, the dominant method of text-encoding for scholarly purposes is not
                    capable of representing multiple readings of the same text in a workable manner.
                    The TEI markup scheme is the best-known example of this method. We cite it here
                    simply as one example among others, noting that most other encoding schemes for
                    textual corpora work in a similar way and have the same limitations. We note
                    also that a number of scholars involved in the TEI consortium are well aware of
                    these limitations and do not claim to have overcome them.</p>
                <p>A digital text representation that follows the TEI standard contains not just
                    character codes that comprise the text itself but also codes that represent
                    markup tags interspersed within the text. The creators of the TEI scheme and
                    similar text-encoding schemes have assumed that embedding annotations within
                    character sequences in the form of markup tags yields a text-representation that
                    is rich enough for scholarly work. However, as Dino Buzzetti has emphasized, the
                    markup method has significant disadvantages <ptr target="#buzzetti2002"/>
                    <ptr target="#buzzetti2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#buzzetti2006"/>. As Buzzetti says, drawing on the Danish linguist
                    Louis Hjelmslev’s distinction between <q>expression</q> and <q>content,</q> and
                    citing Jerome McGann’s book <title rend="italic">The Textual Condition</title>
                    <ptr target="#mcgann1991"/>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#buzzetti2009">From a semiotic point of view the
                            text is intrinsically and primarily an indeterminate system. To put it
                            briefly, there are many ways of expressing the same content just as
                            there are many ways of assigning content to the same expression.
                            Synonymy and polysemy are two well-known and mutually related linguistic
                            phenomena.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#buzzetti2009" loc="50"/>
                    </cit> Thus, in an essay that Buzzetti co-authored with McGann, the following
                    question is raised: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#buzzetti2006">Since text is dynamic and mobile
                            and textual structures are essentially indeterminate, how can markup
                            properly deal with the phenomena of structural instability? Neither the
                            expression nor the content of a text are given once and for all. Text is
                            not self-identical. The structure of its content very much depends on
                            some act of interpretation by an interpreter, nor is its expression
                            absolutely stable. Textual variants are not simply the result of faulty
                            textual transmission. Text is unsteady, and both its content and
                            expression keep constantly quivering.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#buzzetti2006" loc="64"/>
                    </cit> The same point could no doubt be expressed in a less structuralist way,
                    but we are not concerned here with the particular literary theory that underlies
                    this way of stating the problem. Regardless of how they express it, Buzzetti and
                    McGann are surely right to say that the difficulties encountered in representing
                    multiple readings of the same text constitute a major deficiency in the
                    markup-based technique commonly used to digitize scholarly texts (see also <ptr
                        target="#mcgann2004"/>).</p>
                <p>Moreover, as they acknowledge, this deficiency was recognized very early in the
                    history of the Text Encoding Initiative and has been discussed repeatedly over
                    the years (see, e.g., <ptr target="#barnard1988"/>; <ptr target="#renear1993"
                    />). Almost twenty years ago, Claus Huitfeldt published a perceptive and
                    philosophically well-informed critique of the TEI encoding method, entitled
                        <title rend="quotes">Multi-Dimensional Texts in a One-Dimensional
                        Medium</title>
                    <ptr target="#huitfeldt1995"/>. He described the conventional method of
                    text-encoding in which <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#huitfeldt1995">a computer represents a text as
                            a long string of characters, which in turn will be represented by a
                            series of numbers, which in turn will be represented by a series of
                            binary digits, which in turn will be represented by variations in the
                            physical properties of the data carrier</quote>
                        <ptr target="#huitfeldt1995" loc="236"/>
                    </cit> as an attempt to represent multi-dimensional texts in a one-dimensional
                    medium.</p>
                <p>However, despite his accurate diagnosis of the problems inherent in reducing many
                    dimensions to just one, for some reason Huitfeldt did not challenge the basic
                    assumption that <soCalled>a long string of
                        characters</soCalled> is the only data structure available for the digital
                    representation of texts. As he no doubt knew, computer programmers are not
                    limited to using one-dimensional structures. The fact that all digital data is
                    ultimately represented by one-dimensional sequences of binary digits is
                    irrelevant in this context. We are dealing here with the logical data structures
                    used by application programmers and by high-level programming languages, not the
                    underlying structures dealt with by operating systems and compilers (a compiler
                    is a computer program that translates source code written in a high-level
                    programming language into lower level <soCalled>machine code</soCalled>). As a
                    computer scientist would put it, the power of digital computers stems from the
                    fact that a <q>Turing machine,</q> defined mathematically in terms of primitive
                    computations on a one-dimensional sequence of binary digits, is capable of
                    emulating more complex data structures and algorithms that can represent and
                    manipulate information in many different dimensions.</p>
                <p>Thus, in spite of the deeply entrenched habit of encoding texts as long character
                    strings, scholars should pay more attention to the fact that a digital computer
                    is not necessarily a one-dimensional medium when it comes to the representation
                    of texts — indeed, they will not obtain the full benefits of digitization until
                    they take advantage of this fact. The failure to adopt a multi-dimensional data
                    model explains why, after the passage of more than twenty-five years, no widely
                    accepted way of representing multiple readings of the same text has emerged in
                    the scholarly text-encoding community. By and large, even the sharpest critics
                    of the TEI markup scheme and its limitations have themselves remained within the
                    document paradigm. They have not abandoned the one-dimensional character-string
                    method of representing scholarly texts in favor of the multi-dimensional
                    structures available in a database system.</p>
                <p>To understand why no workable way of representing multiple readings has emerged,
                    we must examine more closely the TEI Consortium’s text-encoding method. The TEI
                    markup scheme encodes an <soCalled>ordered
                        hierarchy of content objects</soCalled> (OHCO), where a <soCalled>content object</soCalled> is a textual component defined
                    with respect to some mode of analysis at the level either of textual expression
                    or of textual content (see <ptr target="#renear2004" loc="224–225"/>). Quite
                    rightly, the OHCO model exploits the power of hierarchies to represent
                    efficiently the relationships of parts to a larger whole. For example, a text
                    might be broken down into pages, paragraphs, lines, and words, in a descending
                    hierarchy, or it might be broken down into component parts in some other way,
                    depending on the mode of analysis being employed. Regardless of how they are
                    defined, a text’s components can be separated from one another within a long
                    sequence of characters and related to one another in a hierarchical fashion by
                    means of markup tags.</p>
                <p>The problem with this method is that any one digital text is limited to a single
                    hierarchy, that is, one primary configuration of the text’s components. Using
                    standardized markup techniques, a linear sequence of characters can easily
                    represent a single hierarchy but it cannot easily represent multiple overlapping
                    hierarchies that reflect different ways of reading the same text. The TEI
                    Consortium itself provides some simple examples to illustrate this problem in
                    its <title rend="italic">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interchange</title>, including the following excerpt from the poem <title
                        rend="quotes">Scorn not the sonnet</title> by William Wordsworth <ptr
                        target="#TEIP52013" loc="Chapter 20"/><note> As we noted above, members of
                        the TEI Consortium are well aware of the limitations of the markup
                        technique. The 2013 TEI <title rend="italic">Guidelines</title> express it
                        this way: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">Non-nesting information
                            poses fundamental problems for any XML-based encoding scheme, and it
                            must be stated at the outset that no current solution combines all the
                            desirable attributes of formal simplicity, capacity to represent all
                            occurring or imaginable kinds of structures, [and] suitability for
                            formal or mechanical validation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#TEIP52013" loc="629"/></cit>.</note>: <lg>
                        <l>Scorn not the sonnet; critic, you have frowned,</l>
                        <l>Mindless of its just honours; with this key</l>
                        <l>Shakespeare unlocked his heart; the melody</l>
                        <l>Of this small lute gave ease to Petrarch’s wound.</l>
                    </lg> This poem could be represented by a hierarchy based on its metrical
                    features, with components that represent the poem’s lines, stanzas, and so on.
                    But the same poem could equally well be represented by a hierarchy based on its
                    grammatical features, with components that represent words, phrases, clauses,
                    and sentences.</p>
                <p>If we survey literary, linguistic, and philological scholarship more broadly, we
                    find many different ways of constructing hierarchical representations of texts,
                    each of which might be useful for computer-aided research on textual corpora.
                    Our different ways of analyzing texts produce different logical hierarchies and
                    we cannot claim that any one hierarchy is dominant, especially if we are trying
                    to create a digital representation of the text that can be used in many
                    different ways.<note> Often it is not necessary to encode each hierarchy
                        manually in a laborious fashion because aspects of a reader’s competence can
                        be captured in text-processing algorithms that automatically encode
                        distinctions and relationships a human reader would see. It is irrelevant
                        for our purposes whether analytical hierarchies are created manually or
                        automatically.</note> The choice of which analytic hierarchy to use and how
                    the hierarchy should be constructed will depend on the kinds of questions we are
                    asking about a text. For this reason, a fully adequate digital representation
                    would allow us to capture many different ways of reading a text without losing
                    sight of the fact that they are all readings of the same text. Moreover, a fully
                    adequate digital representation would make full use of the expressive power of
                    hierarchies wherever appropriate, but it would not be limited to hierarchies and
                    it would also allow non-hierarchical configurations of the same textual
                    components, without duplicating any textual content.</p>
                <p>A brute-force solution to the <soCalled>problem of overlapping
                        hierarchies,</soCalled> as it has been called, is to maintain multiple
                    copies of identical textual content, tagging each copy in a different way. Here
                    is a TEI encoding of the metrical view of the Wordsworth excerpt using the
                        <gi>l</gi> tag (one of the standard TEI tags) for each metrical line and
                    using the <gi>lg</gi> tag to indicate a <q>line group</q>: <dhq:example>
                        <p>
                            <gi>lg</gi></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>l</gi>Scorn not the sonnet; critic, you have
                                frowned,<code>&lt;/l&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>l</gi>Mindless of its just honours; with this
                                key<code>&lt;/l&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>l</gi>Shakespeare unlocked his heart; the
                                melody<code>&lt;/l&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>l</gi>Of this small lute gave ease to Petrarch's
                                wound.<code>&lt;/l&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <code>&lt;/lg&gt;</code></p>
                    </dhq:example> The grammatical view of the same text would be encoded by
                    replacing the metrical tags with tags that indicate its sentence structure,
                    using the <gi>p</gi> tag to indicate a paragraph and the <gi>seg</gi> tag for
                    grammatical <soCalled>segments</soCalled>: <dhq:example>
                        <p>
                            <gi>p</gi></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>seg</gi>Scorn not the sonnet;<code>&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>seg</gi>critic, you have frowned, Mindless of its just
                                honours;<code>&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>seg</gi>with this key Shakespeare unlocked his
                                heart;<code>&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <gi>seg</gi>the melody Of this small lute gave ease to Petrarch's
                                wound.<code>&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                        <p>
                            <code>&lt;/p&gt;</code></p>
                    </dhq:example></p>
                <p>However, as the authors of the TEI <title rend="italic">Guidelines</title> point
                    out, maintaining multiple copies of the same textual content is an invitation to
                    inconsistency and error. What is worse, there is no way of indicating that the
                    various copies are related to one other, so it is impossible to combine in a
                    single framework the different views of a text that are contained in its various
                    copies — for example, if one wanted to use an automated algorithm to examine the
                    interplay between a poem’s metrical and grammatical structures in comparison to
                    many other poems.</p>
                <p>Three other solutions to the problem of overlapping hierarchies are suggested in
                    the TEI <title rend="italic">Guidelines</title> but they are all quite difficult
                    to implement by means of textual markup using the standards-based software tools
                    currently available for processing linear character strings. In addition to
                        <soCalled>redundant encoding of information in
                        multiple forms,</soCalled> as in the example given above, the following
                    solutions are discussed: <list type="ordered">
                        <item><quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">Boundary marking with empty
                                elements,</quote> which <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">involves marking the start
                                    and end points of the non-nesting material. . . . The
                                    disadvantage of this method is that no single XML element
                                    represents the non-nesting material and, as a result, processing
                                    with XML technologies is significantly more difficult</quote>
                                <ptr target="#TEIP52013" loc="631–634"/>
                            </cit>. A further disadvantage of this method — indeed, a crippling
                            limitation — is that it cannot cope with analytical hierarchies in which
                            textual components are ordered differently within different hierarchies,
                            as often happens in linguistic analyses.</item>
                        <item><quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">Fragmentation and reconstitution of
                                virtual elements,</quote> which <quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013"
                                >involves breaking what might be considered a single logical (but
                                non-nesting) element into multiple smaller structural elements that
                                fit within the dominant hierarchy but can be reconstituted
                                virtually.</quote> However, this creates problems that <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">can make automatic analysis
                                    of the fragmented features difficult</quote>
                                <ptr target="#TEIP52013" loc="634–638"/>
                            </cit>.</item>
                        <item><quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">Stand-off markup,</quote> which <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#TEIP52013">separates the text and the
                                    elements used to describe it . . . It establishes a new
                                    hierarchy by building a new tree whose nodes are XML elements
                                    that do not contain textual content but rather links to another
                                    layer: a node in another XML document or a span of text</quote>
                                <ptr target="#TEIP52013" loc="638–639"/>
                            </cit>.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The last option, stand-off markup, is the most elegant solution but it is not
                    easy to implement using generally available software based on current markup
                    standards — and it is not, in fact, included in the TEI’s official encoding
                    method but requires an extension of it. Many people who are troubled by the
                    problem of overlapping hierarchies favor some form of stand-off markup instead
                    of ordinary <soCalled>embedded</soCalled> or <soCalled>in-line</soCalled>
                    markup. However, stand-off markup deviates so much from the original markup
                    metaphor that it no longer belongs within the document paradigm at all and is
                    best implemented within the database paradigm. Stand-off markup involves the
                    digital representation of multiple readings of a text by means of separate data
                    objects, one for each reading, with a system of pointers that explicitly connect
                    the various readings to the text’s components. But this amounts to a database
                    solution to the problem. The best way to implement this solution is to abandon
                    the use of a single long character sequence to represent a scholarly text — the
                    document approach — in order to take advantage of the atomized data models and
                    querying languages characteristic of database systems. Otherwise, the complex
                    linkages among separate data objects must be laboriously managed without the
                    benefit of the software tools that are best suited to the task. The database
                    approach we describe below is functionally equivalent to stand-off markup but is
                    implemented by means of an atomized and keyed database.<note> Chapter 16 of the
                        TEI <title rend="italic">Guidelines</title>
                        <ptr target="#TEIP52013" loc="495–545"/> discusses <title rend="quotes"
                            >Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment,</title> with a section at the end
                        of the chapter devoted to stand-off markup. The linking of textual
                        components within and across TEI-encoded documents is meant to be done by
                        means of the XML <q>id</q> attribute and the standardized XML Linking
                        Language (XLink), together with the XML Pointing Language (XPointer) and,
                        for stand-off markup, XML Inclusions (XInclude). But very little software
                        has ever actually implemented the XLink standard because after it was
                        initially proposed, early in the history of XML, it was quickly supplanted
                        by the Resource Description Framework (RDF) mechanism for expressing complex
                        links. Likewise, XInclude has rarely been implemented, and XPointer was
                        replaced by XPath, which forms part of the XQuery querying language. Many
                        software tools now implement the RDF and XQuery standards to accomplish the
                        functions for which XLink and XPointer were intended. This is an example of
                        the shift from a document-oriented approach to a database approach because
                        XLink, which grows out of the document model — being an extension of the
                        simple linking mechanism found in HTML documents intended for the navigation
                        of information by human readers — is limited by virtue of its embedding
                        within non-atomized document structures and so did not catch on, whereas the
                        widely used RDF standard prescribes a highly atomized format of the kind
                        used in databases and is much better suited for automated
                    querying.</note></p>
                <p>Other solutions to the problem of overlapping hierarchies continue to be
                    proposed, some of them quite sophisticated.<note> See, e.g., <ptr
                            target="#schmidt2009"/> and references to other work cited therein. See
                        also Chapter 20.5 of the TEI <title rend="italic">Guidelines</title> on
                            <title rend="quotes">Non-XML-based Approaches.</title></note> However,
                    the complex relationships among distinct data objects that underlie these
                    proposed solutions can best be implemented in a database system that does not
                    represent a text by means of a single character string. Such strings should be
                    secondary and ephemeral rather than primary and permanent. Nothing is lost by
                    adopting a database approach because a properly designed database system will
                    allow the automated conversion of its internal text representation to and from
                    linear character sequences, which can be dynamically generated from the database
                    as needed.</p>
                <p>With respect to the limitations of the TEI encoding method, some have argued that
                    the fault lies with the Extensible Markup Language (XML) standard that
                    prescribes how markup tags may be formatted [<ref
                        target="http://www.w3.org/standards/xml"
                        >http://www.w3.org/standards/xml</ref>]. The TEI method conforms to the XML
                    standard so that XML-based software tools, of which there are many, can be used
                    with TEI-encoded texts. But there is a good reason why standardized markup
                    grammars like XML allow only one strict hierarchy of nested textual components.
                    Accommodating overlapping pairs of markup tags within a single character string
                    would create a more complicated standard that demands more complicated software,
                    losing the main benefit provided by the markup technique, which is that it is
                    intuitive and easy to use, even by people who have modest programming skills. If
                    we are going to work with more complex data structures and software, it would be
                    better to abandon the single-character-string representation of a text
                    altogether in favor of a more atomized, and hence more flexible, database
                        representation.<note> Along these lines, an interesting foray has been made
                        in the direction of converting TEI documents into atomized RDF triples that
                        can be queried, database-style, using the SPARQL querying language (see <ptr
                            target="#tummarello2008"/>). We discuss RDF databases below.</note></p>
                <p>Thus, in our view, the TEI markup scheme and other similar text-encoding schemes
                    are useful as secondary formats for communicating a particular reading of a text
                    that has been generated from a richer underlying representation, but they are
                    not suitable for the primary digital representation of a text. For this one
                    needs a suitably designed database system, keeping in mind that with the right
                    kind of internal database representation it is a simple matter to import or
                    export a <soCalled>flattened</soCalled> representation of a given text — or,
                    more precisely, of one reading of the text — as a single character string in a
                    form that can be used by markup-based text-processing software. An existing
                    text-reading stored in digital form as a single sequence of characters (with or
                    without markup tags) can be imported by automatically parsing it in order to
                    populate the database’s internal structures. In the other direction, a character
                    string that represents a particular reading can easily be generated when needed
                    from internal database structures, incorporating whatever kind of markup may be
                    desired in a particular context (e.g., TEI tags or HTML formatting tags).</p>
                <p>In summary, we argue that document-markup solutions to the problem of overlapping
                    textual hierarchies are awkward workarounds that are at odds with the basic
                    markup model of a single hierarchy of textual components. Solving the problem
                    will require abandoning a digital representation of texts in the form of long
                    linear character sequences. That approach may suffice for many kinds of digital
                    texts, especially in non-academic domains, but it is not the best method for the
                    primary representation of texts that are objects of scholarly study and will be
                    read in different ways. Digital documents do not transcend the structure of the
                    flat printed page but rely on relative position in one or two dimensions to
                    distinguish entities and to represent their relationships to one another,
                    instead of making those distinctions and relationships explicit in
                    multi-dimensional structures of the kind found in a well-designed database. What
                    is needed is a database that can explicitly distinguish each entity and
                    relationship of interest, enabling us to capture all the conceptual distinctions
                    and particular observations that scholars may wish to record and discuss.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. The history of the document paradigm versus the database paradigm</head>
                <p>In light of the limitations imposed by the document-markup method of scholarly
                    text encoding, we may ask why this method took root and became so widely
                    accepted instead of the database alternative. To answer this question, it is
                    worth examining the history of the document paradigm of software design in
                    contrast to the parallel history of the database paradigm. The diagram below
                    summarizes the key developments in the emergence of these two paradigms, leading
                    up to the software environment in which we work today.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"> </graphic>
                </figure>
                <p>It is remarkable that current approaches to software design for both documents
                    and databases emerged in the United States in the same year, 1969, and in the
                    same institution, namely the International Business Machines Corporation (IBM),
                    although on opposite sides of the country. At the IBM lab in Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts, Charles Goldfarb and his colleagues came up with the first widely
                    adopted markup method for digital texts. This was eventually canonized as SGML,
                    the Standard Generalized Markup Language, which became an ISO standard in 1986
                    and a few years later gave birth to HTML, the HyperText Markup Language, and
                    thus to the World Wide Web (see <ptr target="#goldfarb1990"/> on SGML; the
                    relationship between SGML and HTML, and subsequently XML, is described in <ptr
                        target="#ducharme1999" loc="3–24"/>).</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, at the IBM lab in San Jose, California, an Englishman named Ted Codd
                    was writing a paper entitled <title rend="quotes">A Relational Model of Data for
                        Large Shared Data Banks</title>
                    <ptr target="#codd1970"/>, which changed the world of databases forever. Codd’s
                    relational data model subsequently became the basis for the majority of database
                    systems in use today. Beyond the relational model itself, the approach to
                    database design that flowed from Codd’s conceptual innovations informs many
                    aspects of recent non-relational systems and querying languages.</p>
                <p>The intellectual contrast between these two IBM employees could not have been
                    greater. Codd was a mathematician who received a Ph.D. from the University of
                    Michigan in 1965 with a thesis that focused on a difficult problem in the theory
                    of computation (self-replication in cellular automata). Goldfarb was an attorney
                    who graduated from Harvard Law School in 1964 and then practiced law in Boston.
                    He did not join IBM until November 1967, at which point, as he says in a memoir,
                    he knew nothing about computers (see <ptr target="#goldfarb1996"/>). He was
                    given the task of applying computers to the needs of law firms, in order to help
                    IBM expand its presence in that market. In particular, he was asked to work with
                    IBM programmers to integrate a simple text-editing program with an
                    information-retrieval system and a text-formatting program to make it easier to
                    manage and distribute legal documents and other structured documents used in
                    business enterprises and governmental settings, such as catalogues and
                    procedural manuals.</p>
                <p>Given his background, it is not surprising that Goldfarb’s solution to the
                    problem was non-theoretical and ad hoc. Quite understandably, he decided to
                    imitate what he knew about the preparation of printed documents and he latched
                    onto the concept of markup, as many others were doing around the same time,
                    transferring the blue pencil-marks of pre-digital editors to special sequences
                    of digitally encoded characters embedded in the main text. These embedded markup
                        <soCalled>tags</soCalled> could provide formatting instructions that told a
                    computer program how to print or display a text, or they could provide semantic
                    information about the structure and contents of the text. Goldfarb’s innovation
                    was to come up with a standard method for defining new markup tags in a
                    generalized way, allowing anyone to create a set of tags suitable for a
                    particular kind of document and making it easy to write software that could work
                    with a wide range of tagging schemes. His Standard Generalized Markup Language
                    is, strictly speaking, not itself a markup language (i.e., a document tagging
                    scheme) but rather a formal grammar for the design and specification of markup
                    languages.</p>
                <p>In addition to this standard tagging mechanism, the writing of general-purpose
                    software for text processing was greatly aided by adopting a simple hierarchical
                    model in which tags were used to group textual components into larger
                    configurations in a nested fashion, so that lines of text were grouped within
                    paragraphs, and paragraphs within sections, and sections within chapters, and so
                    on. This simple and intuitive approach to digital documents has proved to be
                    very popular, precisely because of its simplicity. For example, the HyperText
                    Markup Language on which the World Wide Web is based is one such tagging scheme,
                    and it took off like wildfire in the early 1990s in part because it required
                    very little technical expertise to use it.</p>
                <p>But Goldfarb made a fateful limiting assumption about the nature of texts that
                    has affected digital text-processing ever since. He assumed that the structure
                    of any text that was being digitally encoded would be determined in advance by
                    assigning it to a particular predefined genre (<soCalled>document
                        type</soCalled>). This would determine which markup tags could be used and
                    the way in which separately tagged components of the text could be nested within
                    one another to form a single hierarchy. In other words, Goldfarb assumed that
                    someone would decide in advance how the text ought to be read and this way of
                    reading would be fundamental to the text’s digital representation. This limiting
                    assumption is not usually a problem in the corporate world in which digital
                    markup emerged, where textual structures are determined from the top down by a
                    central semantic authority. However, this assumption creates severe problems for
                    scholars who lack a central semantic authority and thus work with texts in a
                    different way.<note> This limiting assumption was discussed already in a 1988
                        article by David Barnard et al. and was taken up again in 1993 by Allen
                        Renear and some TEI colleagues in an online paper entitled <title
                            rend="quotes">Refining Our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of
                            Overlapping Hierarchies,</title> as they reflected on the problematic
                        inheritance they had received from SGML, of which the TEI encoding scheme
                        was a particular application. As they said: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#renear1993">During the initial development
                                of descriptive markup systems . . . each document was seen as having
                                a single natural representation as a <soCalled>logical</soCalled>
                                hierarchy of objects, as determined by the genre of the document.
                                What text objects might occur in a document on this view is a
                                function of the genre or category of text that that document
                                belonged to . . . Although representations of a particular document
                                might differ when there was some uncertainty about the structure of
                                the document being represented, and the specificity or granularity
                                of a representation could vary, there was a sense that a single
                                document structure was being encoded</quote>
                            <ptr target="#renear1993"/>
                        </cit>.</note></p>
                <p>Turning now to the database paradigm, we can contrast the ad hoc and
                    non-theoretical character of Goldfarb’s approach with Codd’s theoretically
                    sophisticated approach to the digital representation of information. Codd’s
                    abstract relational model was initially resisted by IBM itself, his own
                    employer, which had recently adopted a quite different model.<note> IBM had
                        invested a great deal of money to develop and market a hierarchical database
                        system called IMS (Information Management System), which was soon made
                        obsolete by relational database systems. IBM’s reluctance to capitalize on
                        Codd’s innovation allowed Larry Ellison’s Oracle Corporation to grab a large
                        share of the relational database market, which it retains to this day. IBM
                        itself belatedly marketed a relational system called DB2, which has now
                        largely replaced IMS, although the latter is still used in some
                        settings.</note> But the relational model eventually won out and displaced
                    all its rivals. It did so because it is firmly rooted in mathematical theory,
                    enabling the creation of general-purpose software that can search and manipulate
                    relationally organized information with great efficiency. As is often the case
                    in computing, abstract theoretical elegance yielded optimal real-world
                    performance in the long run.</p>
                <p>Codd’s solution to the problem of managing digital information involved a leap of
                    abstraction to the mathematical concepts of <q>set</q> and <q>relation</q> and
                    the algebraic operations that can be performed on relations (for a concise
                    introduction to the relational data model and relational algebra, see <ptr
                        target="#garcia2009" loc="17–65"/>). Codd gave a mathematical basis to the
                    idea of database <soCalled>keys,</soCalled> that is, pieces of information that
                    uniquely identify other pieces of information and can be used to mix and match
                    the information in a database in any number of different ways. By finding the
                    right level of abstraction, he also guaranteed universality, meaning that
                    digital information of all kinds, regardless of which conceptual ontology is
                    used to organize it, can be manipulated and retrieved in a relational database
                    system.</p>
                <p>Goldfarb failed to make a similar leap of abstraction with the consequence that
                    his method of text representation is not universal but only partial and does not
                    meet the needs of textual scholars in particular. His digital texts mimic the
                    structure of pre-digital documents, conveying information implicitly by means of
                    sequential position, as in a printed work, which conveys information by the
                    relative placement of characters in a line, of lines in a page, and of pages in
                    a book. The information is implicit in the positioning of discrete entities — in
                    their before-and-after juxtapositions with other entities — rather than being
                    made explicit in independently addressable entities that can be related to one
                    another in any number of different ways, as in a keyed and indexed database.</p>
                <p>In other words, if we rely on data structures that conform to the document
                    paradigm, such as linear sequences of character codes, then our information is
                    imprisoned in the straitjacket of sequential position rather than being free to
                    be configured flexibly in many different dimensions, as can be done in a modern
                    database. This would not matter if all we were trying to do is display a
                    predetermined view of the text to a human reader. But the whole point of the
                    kind of digitization we are talking about is to encode information in a way that
                    enables not just a visual display of the text but automated analyses of its
                    contents. And, as we have seen, what we are actually encoding in that case is
                    not the text per se but one or more interpretations of it. So, if what we want
                    to represent digitally are the ways that one or more readers have understood the
                    text from different perspectives, we must transcend sequential position, which
                    limits our ability to configure a text’s components, and adopt a more flexible,
                    multi-dimensional method of representing a text.</p>
                <p>It is true that the markup tags embedded in a Goldfarbian digital text allow us
                    to go beyond a representation of the text as a simple unmarked sequence of
                    characters by making explicit some aspects of a reader’s interpretation of the
                    text. But markup tags are limited in what they can do by the very fact that they
                    are embedded in a specific location within a sequence of characters just as
                    pre-digital markup written in blue pencil exists at a certain place on the
                        page.<note> Parsing algorithms scan the linear character sequence of a
                        marked-up text to construct a more atomized digital representation (a
                            <soCalled>document object model</soCalled>) in which components of the
                        text are distinguished and explicitly interrelated, but these algorithms
                        cannot create a more complex model than can be expressed in the original
                        character string. Markup tags embedded in a one-dimensional character
                        sequence can be used to represent not only a hierarchical tree structure but
                        also two-dimensional tables, which is why XML documents have become an
                        important way of transmitting structured data between computing devices. But
                        a single character string, even with markup, is not designed to represent
                        the more complex multi-dimensional configurations possible in a database —
                        except in the trivial case in which a group of independent database objects
                        (e.g., relational tuples) are serialized and combined into a single omnibus
                        string for purposes of transmission over the Internet via HTTP.</note> This
                    limitation is tolerable when the structure of the text and thus the possible
                    ways of analyzing it are ordained in advance, as in the world of business and
                    government. But that is not the case in the world of scholarship.</p>
                <p>The lesson here is that humanists should not be parasitic on the impoverished
                    ontology of digital texts that flourishes in an environment of top-down semantic
                    authority but should draw upon the intellectual tradition of critical
                    scholarship to devise their own richer and more effective ontology. It is
                    unfortunate, in our view, that scholars became reconciled to the limitations of
                    the document-markup approach and neglected the database alternative. However, to
                    be fair, we concede that the relational database software that dominated in the
                    1980s and 1990s presented some practical barriers for textual applications
                    (e.g., the need for many inefficient table joins). It is only in recent years
                    that these barriers have been eliminated with the emergence of non-relational
                    database systems and querying languages, which themselves have borrowed
                    substantially from SGML and document-processing techniques while remaining
                    within the database paradigm. Thanks to these enhancements, we are at the point
                    where we can stop trying to solve what is actually a database problem by means
                    of a document-oriented method that lacks the powerful techniques implemented in
                    database systems. We can solve the problem of overlapping hierarchies by
                    breaking free of the constraints of the document paradigm and moving firmly to
                    the database paradigm. And we can do so while bringing with us the best features
                    of the document paradigm, which in recent years has greatly enriched the
                    database paradigm and has made it more capable of dealing with relatively
                    unstructured texts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Transcending the document paradigm via item-based atomization of
                    information</head>
                <p>We turn now from the document paradigm and its history to a database approach
                    that can transcend the limitations of digital documents. But first we must
                    emphasize that the problem we are trying to solve goes beyond the representation
                    of texts, so the best solution will be one that is applicable to other kinds of
                    scholarly data and permits both relatively unstructured texts and more highly
                    structured information to be stored, managed, and queried in the same way. By
                    generalizing the problem, we can reach the right level of abstraction and
                    develop a common computational framework for many kinds of scholarly research.
                    This allows the same database structure and software to be used for different
                    purposes, yielding financial economies of scale. And the motivation to create a
                    common computational framework is not simply pragmatic. It is also intellectual,
                    because the problem of overlapping hierarchies is not confined to textual
                    studies but emerges in many kinds of research in which multiple configurations
                    and interpretations of the same data must be represented and managed
                    efficiently.</p>
                <p>The problem we are trying to solve goes beyond text-encoding because the
                    pervasive document paradigm has fostered analogous limitations in humanities
                    software applications developed to manage structured data. Structured data is
                    usually displayed, not as lines of text, but in tabular form, with one row for
                    each entity of interest and one column for each property of those entities.
                    Tables provide a convenient way to display structured data but are not the best
                    way to organize scholarly information in its primary digital representation. A
                    rigid tabular structure imposes predetermined limits on what can be recorded and
                    how the information can be analyzed. In the humanities, there is often a high
                    degree of variability in what needs to be described and a lack of agreement
                    about the terms to be used and how entities should be classified. Software
                    developers who try to cope with this variability by using tables as primary
                    structures will end up creating many idiosyncratic tables which require equally
                    idiosyncratic (and unsustainable) software to be written for each research
                    project, and with no way to integrate information derived from different
                    projects. The alternative we advocate is to exploit the ability of an atomized
                    keyed-and-indexed database system to represent the full range of scholarly
                    observations and conceptual distinctions in a more flexible manner, allowing
                    many different views of a large body of shared information to be generated from
                    a common underlying database structure that does not predetermine what can be
                    recorded and how it can be analyzed.</p>
                <p>To do this, we must embrace a high degree of atomization in our database design.
                    We can design data objects and the linkages among them in a way that is less
                    atomized or more atomized, depending on the nature of the data and how it will
                    be used. In many database applications, compromises are made to reduce the
                    number of linkages required between distinct data objects (e.g., to reduce the
                    number of table joins needed in a relational system). Information about a class
                    of entities and their properties will often be embedded in a single table (e.g.,
                    data about the customers of a business enterprise). This kind of database table
                    therefore resembles a digital document, even though the entities in the table
                    may be linked to other entities in the database via unique keys, allowing the
                    database to transcend the document paradigm, at least in some respects. Many
                    commercial databases are <soCalled>class-based</soCalled> in this way; in other
                    words, their table structures depend on a predetermined classification of the
                    entities of interest. A class-based database uses two-dimensional tables to
                    represent predefined classes of entities that have predefined common properties
                    (i.e., predefined by the database designer). Typically, each class of entities
                    is represented by a single table; each entity in the class is represented by a
                    row in the table; and each property of that class of entities is represented by
                    a column in the table.</p>
                <p>In an academic domain such as the humanities, however, a class-based database is
                    often inadequate. A higher degree of atomization is needed to permit the
                    flexibility in description and analysis that critical scholarship demands. The
                    alternative to a class-based database is a highly atomized
                        <soCalled>item-based</soCalled> database in which not just each entity of
                    interest but each property of an entity and each value of a property is
                    represented as a separately addressable data object. This enables many different
                    dynamically generated classifications of entities, which are determined by the
                    end-users of the system and are not predetermined by the database designer. It
                    is important to note that even though relational databases use tables, they are
                    not necessarily class-based but can be designed to be item-based. Likewise,
                    non-relational databases can be item-based or class-based, depending on their
                        design.<note> The fundamental data objects in a relational database are
                        tuples. A set of tuples (called a <q>relation</q>) is conventionally
                        displayed as a table with one row per tuple. However, the relational data
                        model does not require information to be embedded in tabular rows and
                        columns in a document-oriented fashion, that is, in such a way that each
                        table corresponds to a particular class of entities possessing common
                        properties, with one entity per row and one property per column, mimicking
                        the structure of human-readable documents in which all of the information
                        about a group of entities is stored together in a single two-dimensional
                        configuration. Relational database systems often use class-based tables as a
                        matter of convenience because a more highly atomized design is not
                        necessary. But such tables do not take advantage of the ability of a
                        relational system to store and retrieve information in a more atomized and
                        flexible manner. The class-based approach is easy and intuitive and may be
                        adequate in non-scholarly contexts in which modes of description are
                        standardized in advance, as happens in a business enterprise; thus tables
                        that correspond to predefined classes of similar entities (e.g., employees,
                        products, customers, etc.) are frequently used as primary data structures in
                        commercial settings. But this is an application-level design choice. The
                        data models and querying languages that underlie general-purpose database
                        software, both relational and non-relational, do not require class-based
                        tables but can be used to implement a highly atomized item-based database
                        that is not structured around predefined classes of entities but treats each
                        unit of information, no matter how small, as a separately addressable data
                        object that can be combined with other atomic data objects in a highly
                        flexible way.</note></p>
                <p>A highly atomized item-based database of the kind we advocate does not eliminate
                    the need for strings and tables as a means of presenting information to
                    end-users. Computer programmers distinguish the secondary presentation of
                    information to human beings from the primary representation of this information
                    within a computer. One-dimensional character strings displayed as lines of text
                    on a computer screen are necessary for presenting information to human readers,
                    and there is no question that a two-dimensional table is an effective way of
                    presenting highly structured information. But one-dimensional strings and
                    two-dimensional tables are not the best structures to use internally for the
                    primary digital representation of scholarly information. These structures make
                    it difficult to manage a large number of distinct but interrelated units of
                    information — in our case, units that reflect the wide range of entities,
                    properties, and relationships distinguished by scholars — in a way that allows
                    the information to be easily combined in new configurations.<note> Computer
                        programmers make a further distinction between high-level data structures,
                        such as strings and tables, which are manipulated by application programs,
                        and the lower-level structures by which the high-level structures are
                        themselves implemented in a particular computer system. These lower-level
                        structures are even more primary, in a sense, but they are invisible to
                        application programmers, who work with standardized logical structures. We
                        are concerned here with data structures that are primary from the point of
                        view of a database developer or a text-processing application developer, as
                        opposed to what is primary to developers of the underlying system software
                        on which application programs rest.</note></p>
                <p>We contend that a highly atomized item-based database can provide a common
                    solution for scholarly work both with unstructured texts and with more highly
                    structured data, allowing the same underlying database structure and algorithms
                    to be used for both kinds of data. In such a database, individual data objects
                    may be linked together by end-users in different ways without imposing a single
                    standardized terminology or classification scheme. By virtue of being highly
                    atomized and readily reconfigurable, data objects that represent individual
                    entities and properties and the relationships among them are able to represent
                    the many idiosyncratic interpretations that characterize critical scholarship
                    much better than traditional digital documents. They can do so because there is
                    no requirement that the entities and properties of interest be defined in
                    advance or grouped together structurally in a way that inhibits other ways of
                    configuring them.<note> An item-based database design bears some similarity to
                        the object-oriented approach in software development and is well suited to
                        object-oriented programming techniques. However, an item-based design does
                        not have to be implemented in an object-oriented or object-relational
                        database system but can be implemented in other kinds of systems. Moreover,
                        the technical term <q>object-oriented</q> implies more than we intend by the
                        term <q>item-based</q> (e.g., it implies polymorphism, encapsulation, etc.).
                        For this reason, we have adopted the term <q>item-based</q> in contrast to
                            <q>class-based.</q></note></p>
                <p>With respect to texts, in particular, we can solve the problem of overlapping
                    hierarchies by using an item-based database to separate the representation of
                    each hierarchy of textual components from the representation of those components
                    themselves, while also separating the representation of each textual component
                    from the representations of all the others. If we separate the representation of
                    a hierarchy of textual components from the representations of each individual
                    component we obtain an atomized structure in which each textual component is
                    stored and retrieved separately from the hierarchies in which it participates,
                    no matter how small it may be and no matter how it may be defined. For example,
                    a database item may represent a unit of analysis on the epigraphic level, like a
                    character or line; or it may represent a unit of analysis on the linguistic or
                    discourse level, like a morpheme, word, clause, or sentence. It is up to the
                    end-user to define the scope of the items that make up a text and how they are
                    related to one another hierarchically and non-hierarchically.</p>
                <p>We call this an item-based database because it treats each textual component as
                    an individually addressable item of information. It is also a hierarchical
                    database, insofar as it makes full use of the expressive power of hierarchies —
                    as many as are needed — to represent efficiently the relationships of parts to a
                    larger whole. Indeed, each hierarchy is itself a database item. And because this
                    kind of database is highly atomized and item-based, it readily allows
                    non-hierarchical configurations of items, if those are necessary to express the
                    relationships of interest. This database design has been implemented in a
                    working system in use at the University of Chicago <ptr target="#schloen2012"/>,
                    which is described below in more detail. The same database structure has proved
                    to be applicable to many kinds of scholarly information other than texts.</p>
                <p>We are aware that this way of thinking about texts as databases and not as
                    documents will seem strange to many people. Some will no doubt react by
                    insisting that a text is intrinsically a sequential phenomenon with a beginning,
                    middle, and end, and is therefore well suited to digital representation by means
                    of a linear character sequence (i.e., a document). It is true, of course, that a
                    text is sequential. However, as we noted above, what we are representing is not
                    the text per se but various readers’ understandings of the text; and anyone who
                    understands what he or she is reading forms a mental representation that
                    encompasses many parts of the text at once. A human reader’s way of
                    comprehending (literally, <soCalled>grasping together</soCalled>) the
                    sequentially inscribed components of a text will necessarily transcend the
                    sequence itself. Thus, we need digital data structures that preserve the text’s
                    linearity while also being able to capture the many ways scholarly readers might
                    conceptualize the text’s components and simultaneously relate them to one
                    another.</p>
                <p>This way of thinking about texts requires a leap of abstraction of a kind
                    familiar to database designers. It is a matter of going beyond the concrete form
                    that information may take in a particular situation in order to discern
                    fundamental entities and relationships that a database system can work with to
                    generate many different (and perhaps unexpected) views of the data, depending on
                    the questions being asked, without error-prone duplication of information. Some
                    may object that operating at this level of abstraction — abandoning the simple
                    and intuitive document paradigm in favor of the more complex database paradigm —
                    creates obstacles for software development. It is true that it calls for
                    properly trained programmers rather than do-it-yourself coding, but this is
                    hardly an argument against developing more powerful systems that can more
                    effectively meet the needs of researchers. Scholars rely on complex
                    professionally written software every day for all sorts of data management and
                    retrieval (e.g., for social media, shopping, banking, etc.). We should not be
                    surprised if they need similarly complex software for their own research data.
                    As end-users they do not need to see or understand the underlying software and
                    data structures as long as the database entities, relationships, and algorithms
                    they are working with are understood at a conceptual level. Thus the complexity
                    of the software should be irrelevant to them.</p>
                <p>Moreover, poverty is not an excuse for failing to develop suitable software for
                    the humanities, whose practitioners usually have little or no money to hire
                    programmers. To the extent that a database system meets common needs within a
                    research community whose members use similar methods and materials (literary,
                    historical, etc.), the cost of developing and maintaining the software can be
                    spread over many researchers. Front-end user interfaces for the same system can
                    be customized for different projects without losing economies of scale, which
                    depend on having a single codebase for the back-end database software, where the
                    complexity lies. Indeed, if some of the resources expended over the years on
                    document-oriented software for the humanities had been spent on designing and
                    building suitable back-end database software, we would have better tools at our
                    disposal today. In our view, universities can support digital humanities in a
                    better and more cost-effective way by discouraging the development of
                    idiosyncratic project-specific tools and giving researchers and students access
                    to larger shared systems that are professionally developed and maintained,
                    together with the necessary training and technical support.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. XML, the CHOIR ontology, and the OCHRE database system</head>
                <p>We need now to give some indication of how, in practice, one can work within the
                    database paradigm using currently available software techniques to overcome the
                    limitations of the document paradigm. For a long time, the barrier between
                    textual scholarship and database systems seemed insurmountable because it was
                    cumbersome (though not impossible) to represent free-form texts and their
                    flexible hierarchies within relational databases, which have been the dominant
                    type of database since the 1980s. For this reason, in spite of its limitations,
                    the document-markup approach often seemed to be the best way to handle digital
                    texts. However, in the last ten years the database paradigm has itself been
                    greatly enriched by the document paradigm. This has enabled the creation of
                    non-relational database systems that can more easily handle flexible textual
                    hierarchies as well as highly structured data.</p>
                <p>This came about because of the Extensible Markup Language (XML), which was
                    adopted as a universal data-formatting standard by the World Wide Web Consortium
                    in 1998 and was followed in subsequent years by other widely used standards,
                    such as XQuery, a querying language specifically designed to work with XML
                    documents, and the Resource Description Framework (RDF) and its SPARQL querying
                    language, which are the basis of the so-called Semantic Web.<note> XML defines a
                        universal tagged-text format for transmitting structured information on the
                        Internet among diverse computing platforms and operating systems [<ref
                            target="http://www.w3.org/standards/xml"
                            >http://www.w3.org/standards/xml</ref>]. RDF represents information in
                        terms of subject-predicate-object <q>triples</q> [<ref
                            target="http://www.w3.org/rdf">http://www.w3.org/rdf</ref>]. SPARQL is a
                        querying language designed for retrieving information from large collections
                        of RDF triples. XML, XQuery, RDF, and SPARQL are all non-proprietary
                        standardized specifications published by the World Wide Web Consortium,
                        which was originally formed to take responsibility for the HyperText Markup
                        Language (HTML) standard on which the Web itself is based.</note> XML is
                    itself simply a streamlined and Web-oriented version of SGML that was developed
                    to remedy the semantic ambiguity of the HyperText Markup Language (HTML) on
                    which the Web is based. XML makes it easy to define semantic tagging schemes and
                    share them on the Internet.<note> Like HTML files, XML files are digital
                        documents that can be displayed as human-readable text because they are
                        encoded at the level of binary digits according to a known standard for
                        representing textual characters — usually the Unicode UTF-8 variable-width
                        encoding format, of which the older ASCII standard is now a subset (see <ref
                            target="http://www.unicode.org">http://www.unicode.org</ref>). All
                        recent computers support the UTF-8 standard; thus XML files can be readily
                        transmitted from one computer to another regardless of the computer’s
                        operating system. For this reason, XML has become an important vehicle for
                        transmitting structured information over the Internet. For example, the TEI
                        Consortium’s markup scheme is currently implemented by means of XML
                        documents.</note></p>
                <p>Database specialists quickly realized that XML transcends the world of document
                    markup and provides a formal notation for what has been called the <soCalled>semistructured data model,</soCalled> in distinction
                    from Codd’s relational data model. XML accordingly became the basis of a new
                    kind of non-relational database system that can work equally well with
                    structured tables and more loosely structured texts.<note> For an early
                        description of the semistructured data model and how it differs from the
                        relational model, see <ptr target="#abiteboul2000"/>. For a more recent
                        treatment, see <ptr target="#garcia2009" loc="483–515"/>.</note> It provides
                    a bridge between the document paradigm and the database paradigm. The keyed and
                    indexed data objects in an XML database conform to the XML markup standard and
                    thus may be considered documents, but they function quite differently from
                    traditional marked-up documents within the document paradigm. Like any other XML
                    documents, the data objects in an XML database each consist of a sequence of
                    character codes and so can be displayed as plain text, but they are not
                    necessarily correlated one-for-one to ordinary documents or texts in the real
                    world. Instead, they function as digital representations of potentially quite
                    atomized pieces of interlinked information, as in any other database
                        system.<note> The fact that an XML database is composed of
                            <soCalled>documents</soCalled> does not make it any less a database and
                        does not erase the clear distinction between the document paradigm and the
                        database paradigm. A document consists of a single character string whereas
                        a database consists of many distinct data objects. An XML document’s
                        character string can be parsed into a <q>document object model</q> and its
                        components can be isolated and retrieved via the XPath language, but a
                        document (or a concatenation of documents) is limited in what it can
                        represent, in comparison to a database. XPath is a powerful document
                        querying language but it locates the individually tagged components in a
                        document via their relative positions and thus remains within the document
                        paradigm. An XML database, on the other hand, consists of many different XML
                        documents that can be queried and updated as distinct data objects, both
                        individually and collectively, via the XQuery language, which subsumes XPath
                        but has many other features, being analogous to the SQL language used with
                        relational databases. XQuery enables not just searching within individual
                        documents but also <soCalled>joins</soCalled> that link different documents
                        to one another via unique keys, in a manner analogous to the database joins
                        among tuples (table rows) that are characteristic of a relational system.
                        Collectively, the separate keyed documents in an XML database can, like
                        relational tuples, represent much more complex configurations of information
                        than would be possible in a single document. In general, a database system
                        transcends simple document-processing because it implements an atomized data
                        model and corresponding querying language, which are necessary for the
                        efficient multi-dimensional representation and manipulation of information;
                        e.g., the relational data model with SQL, the semistructured (XML) data
                        model with XQuery, or the network-graph (RDF) data model with
                    SPARQL.</note></p>
                <p>For our purposes, the most important feature of the semistructured data model is
                    its close congruence to item-based ontologies characterized by recursive
                    hierarchies of unpredictable depth, for which the relational data model is not
                    well suited. As we have said, an item-based ontology defined at the right level
                    of abstraction can represent overlapping textual hierarchies without duplicating
                    any textual content, enabling digital text representations that capture
                    different ways of reading a text without losing sight of the fact that they are
                    all readings of the same text. And the same ontology can represent highly
                    structured information without embedding units of scholarly analysis in
                    two-dimensional tables of the kind prescribed by the document paradigm. Instead,
                    each entity of interest, and each property of an entity, can be stored as a
                    separately addressable unit of information that can be combined with other units
                    and presented in many different ways.</p>
                <p>We have demonstrated this in practice by developing and testing an item-based
                    ontology we have called CHOIR, which stands for <q>Comprehensive Hierarchical
                        Ontology for Integrative Research.</q> But an ontology is not itself a
                    working data-retrieval system; it is just a conceptual description of entities
                    and relationships in a given domain of knowledge. To demonstrate its utility for
                    scholarly research, we have implemented the CHOIR ontology in an XML database
                    system called OCHRE, which stands for <q>Online Cultural and Historical Research
                        Environment.</q> This multi-user system has been extensively tested for the
                    past several years by twenty academic projects in different branches of textual
                    study, archaeology, and history. In 2012 it was made more widely available via
                    the University of Chicago’s OCHRE Data Service [<ref
                        target="http://ochre.uchicago.edu">http://ochre.uchicago.edu</ref>].<note>
                        OCHRE is a transactional multi-user system implemented in an
                        enterprise-class DBMS. It makes use of record-locking in order to meet the
                            <q>ACID</q> requirements of atomicity, consistency, isolation, and
                        durability. It serves both as an active database system for entering and
                        modifying information during the data-collection phase of a project and as
                        an archival system for preserving and viewing the project’s data over the
                        long term.</note></p>
                <p>Although we have implemented the CHOIR ontology in an XML database system, we are
                    not using XML documents as a vehicle for marked-up texts in the manner
                    prescribed by the TEI text-encoding method. In an OCHRE database, XML documents
                    do not correspond to real-world documents but are highly atomized and
                    interlinked data objects, analogous to the <soCalled>tuples</soCalled> (table
                    rows) that are the basic structural units in a relational database. Each XML
                    document represents an individual entity or a property of an entity, however
                    these may be defined in a given scholarly project; or an XML document might
                    represent a particular configuration of entities or properties in a hierarchy or
                    set. For example, in the case of a text, each textual component, down to the
                    level of graphemes and morphemes if desired, would be represented by a different
                    XML document, and each hierarchical analysis of the text would be represented by
                    its own XML document that would contain pointers to the various textual
                    components.</p>
                <p>In contrast to conventional text-encoding methods, OCHRE’s representation of a
                    text is not limited to a single hierarchy of textual components. If overlapping
                    hierarchies are needed to represent alternate ways of reading the same text,
                    OCHRE does not duplicate textual content within multiple, disconnected
                    hierarchies. Instead, the same textual components can be reused in any number of
                    quite different hierarchical configurations, none of which is structurally
                    primary. Moreover, an OCHRE hierarchy that represents an overall mode of textual
                    analysis (e.g., metrical, grammatical, topical, etc.) can accommodate smaller
                    textual or editorial variants within the same mode of analysis as overlapping
                    branches in the same hierarchy. OCHRE also permits non-hierarchical
                    configurations of textual components, if these are needed.</p>
                <p>In terms of Hjelmslev’s expression-versus-content distinction, which was
                    mentioned above in connection with Dino Buzzetti’s critique of embedded markup,
                    a text is represented in OCHRE by means of recursive hierarchies of uniquely
                    keyed text-expression items (physical epigraphic units) and separate recursive
                    hierarchies of uniquely keyed text-content items (linguistically meaningful
                    discourse units). There is one hierarchy for each epigraphic analysis and one
                    hierarchy for each discourse analysis. To connect the hierarchies that make up
                    the text, each epigraphic unit is linked in a cross-hierarchical fashion to one
                    or more discourse units that represent interpretations of the epigraphic signs
                    by one or more editors. Each epigraphic unit and each discourse unit is a
                    separately addressable database item that can have its own descriptive
                    properties and can in turn contain other epigraphic units or discourse units,
                    respectively, allowing for recursion within each hierarchy.</p>
                <p>A recursive hierarchy is one in which the same structure is repeated at
                    successive levels of hierarchical nesting. Many linguists, following Noam
                    Chomsky, believe that recursion is a fundamental property of human language and,
                    indeed, is what distinguishes human language from other kinds of animal
                    communication (see <ptr target="#hauser2002"/>; <ptr target="#nevins2009"/>;
                        <ptr target="#corballis2011"/>). Whether or not this is true, it is clear
                    that recursive hierarchies are easily understood by most people and serve as an
                    intuitive mechanism for organizing information, as well as being easy to work
                    with computationally because they lend themselves to an iterative
                        <soCalled>divide and conquer</soCalled> approach. For this reason, recursion
                    plays a major role in the CHOIR ontology and the OCHRE database system that
                    implements it.</p>
                <p>The units of analysis within a given recursive hierarchy are defined by the
                    text’s editor according to his or her chosen method of analysis and they are
                    ramified to whatever level of detail is required. For example, a scholar might
                    distinguish pages, sections, lines, and individual signs, in the case of
                    epigraphic-expression hierarchies, and might distinguish paragraphs, sentences,
                    clauses, phrases, words, and morphemes, in the case of discourse-content
                    hierarchies. But note that the nature of the textual components and the degree
                    of nesting in each hierarchy are not predetermined by the software; they are
                    determined by the scholars who are using the software.</p>
                <p>Finally, OCHRE is not dependent on existing character-encoding standards for its
                    representation of writing systems. These standards may be inadequate for
                    scholarly research in certain cases. As we observed at the beginning of this
                    paper, the Unicode character-encoding standard, large as it is, does not include
                    every allograph of every sign in every human writing system. It embodies someone
                    else’s prior choices about how to encode characters and what to leave out of the
                    encoding. With this in mind, OCHRE safeguards the semantic authority of the
                    individual scholar, even at this most basic level, by abstracting the digital
                    representation of texts in a way that allows the explicit representation, not
                    just of texts themselves, but also of the writing systems that are instantiated
                    in the texts. If necessary, a scholar can go beyond existing standardized
                    character codes and can represent the components and structure of a particular
                    writing system in terms of hierarchies of idealized signs constituted by one or
                    more allographs (e.g., the first letter in the Latin alphabet is constituted by
                    the allographs <q>A</q> and <q>a</q> and various other ways of writing this
                    sign). The allographs of a writing system can then be linked individually,
                    usually in an automated fashion, to a text’s epigraphic-expression units, and
                    the text can be displayed visually via the drawings or images associated with
                    the allographs.</p>
                <p>In other words, scholars are able to make explicit in the database not just their
                    interpretations of a text but also their understandings of the writing system
                    used to inscribe the text. The epigraphic expression of a text can be
                    represented as a particular configuration of individually addressable allographs
                    that constitute signs in one or more writing systems — or, from another
                    perspective, a writing system can be represented as a configuration of ideal
                    signs derived from each sign’s allographic instantiations in a corpus of texts.
                    This is implemented internally by means of pointers from database items that
                    represent the text’s epigraphic units to database items that represent signs in
                    a writing system. Moreover, overlapping hierarchies can be used to represent
                    different understandings of a given writing system, reconfiguring the same signs
                    in different ways, just as overlapping hierarchies represent different readings
                    of a given text, reconfiguring the same textual components in different
                    ways.</p>
                <p>We can now say with some confidence, having developed and tested the CHOIR
                    ontology over a period of more than ten years in consultation with a diverse
                    group of researchers, that this ontology is an effective solution to complex
                    problems of scholarly data representation and analysis, including the
                    longstanding problem of overlapping hierarchies. To be sure, writing the
                    software to implement this ontology in a working database system such as OCHRE
                    requires a high level of programming skill and a considerable investment of time
                    and effort. However, the generic design of the underlying ontology ensures that
                    the same software can be used by many people for a wide range of projects,
                    making the system financially sustainable.</p>
                <p>Professionally maintained and well-supported multi-project systems like this are
                    much too scarce in the humanities, which have tended toward idiosyncratic
                    project-specific software that is not adequately documented, supported, or
                    updated over time. This tendency is not simply caused by a lack of resources. At
                    its heart, the problem is ontological, so to speak. Scholars have lacked a
                    comprehensive abstract ontology suitable for the full range of information with
                    which they deal, including both free-form texts and highly structured data. A
                    comprehensive ontology is needed as the basis for any widely shared database
                    system intended for use by humanities scholars. Moreover, widely shared systems
                    are highly desirable — both intellectually, because they make it easy to search
                    and analyze large amounts of information of diverse origins, and also
                    practically, because they can be sustained and enhanced over the long term as
                    scholars at different institutions pool their resources to support the same
                    system, achieving economies of scale.</p>
                <p>This does not mean putting all of our digital eggs in one basket. An ontology is
                    distinct from its implementations, so scholars who share a common abstract
                    ontology do not all have to use the same database system. If they can muster the
                    resources to do so, they are free to create different implementations of the
                    same ontology while still retaining interoperability, because converting data
                    from one database schema to another is relatively easy if the different database
                    systems employ the same underlying ontology. Note the distinction here between
                    conceptual ontologies and database schemas. A schema is an implementation of an
                    ontology in data structures designed for a working data-retrieval system in
                    accordance with a particular data model (e.g., the table schemas of relational
                    databases and the XML document schemas of semistructured databases).</p>
                <p>In the case of CHOIR, we have implemented the ontology in an XML database system
                    based on the semistructured data model; however, it does not depend on XML. The
                    same ontology could also be implemented (albeit less efficiently, in our view)
                    in a system predicated on a quite different data model — for example, a system
                    based on the well-known relational data model or one based on the graph data
                    model currently advocated by proponents of the Semantic Web. The CHOIR ontology
                    is, in fact, highly compatible with the basic design of the Semantic Web.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. A comprehensive ontology enables interoperability in the Semantic Web of
                    data</head>
                <p>Obtaining the benefits of a comprehensive ontology — not just intellectually,
                    with respect to a fuller representation of scholarly knowledge, but also
                    practically, with respect to economies of scale, interoperability, and
                    sustainability — will require working within the database paradigm to create
                    multi-project database systems that have a broad base of support. In contrast,
                    most humanities software development has been trapped in the document paradigm
                    exemplified by the TEI markup scheme and, more generally, by the reliance on Web
                    documents as primary repositories of scholarly information.<note> We include
                        within the document paradigm textual <soCalled>databases</soCalled> that may
                        well be implemented by means of general-purpose database software but do not
                        decompose and atomize texts in a true database fashion (i.e., in a way that
                        reflects the distinctions scholars routinely make when studying the texts)
                        and so do not allow flexible reconfigurations of textual components in
                        multiple overlapping hierarchies and non-hierarchical networks. Textual
                        databases may decompose texts into separate lines, storing each line in a
                        separate database record, but this imposes one particular analytical
                        structure on a text, inhibiting other ways of analyzing the same text. And
                        within each line there still remain long character sequences that are used
                        as the text’s primary digital representation. Software is occasionally
                        created that uses a more atomized design for particular textual corpora or
                        for particular analytical purposes but we are not aware of any other
                        comprehensive item-based ontology like CHOIR.</note></p>
                <p>However, a major effort to reshape the Web — the Semantic Web initiative of the
                    World Wide Web Consortium — has increasingly come to the attention of people
                    working in digital humanities [<ref
                        target="http://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb"
                        >http://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb</ref>]. The Semantic Web can be
                    regarded as an attempt to move the Web itself from the document paradigm toward
                    the database paradigm. It builds upon the technical standards that underlie the
                    document-oriented Web in order to implement what are, in effect, large databases
                    that can be easily distributed on many different computers connected via the
                    Internet.</p>
                <p>It will be useful at this point to explain why this attempt is being made, that
                    is, what deficiency of the traditional Web the Semantic Web is meant to address.
                    This will help us to explain why in designing our own system we have rejected
                    traditional documents as a means of primary knowledge representation for
                    scholars. The design of our database system predates the Semantic Web and we
                    have implemented it using the semistructured data model and XML rather than the
                    graph data model and RDF, but it is nonetheless compatible with the architecture
                    of Internet-mediated knowledge dissemination currently being encouraged by Tim
                    Berners-Lee as founder and director of the World Wide Web Consortium. In fact,
                    our system design, which involves implementing a hierarchical item-based
                    ontology in an atomized and keyed database, which we first did in the 1990s
                    using a relational database, has become much easier to implement in recent years
                    because the best features of the document paradigm have now been incorporated
                    into the database paradigm thanks to the non-proprietary standards published by
                    the World Wide Web Consortium — namely, XML and XQuery, as well as Semantic Web
                    standards such as RDF, the RDF-based Web Ontology Language (OWL), and the SPARQL
                    querying language.</p>
                <p>As we have said, the Semantic Web can be viewed as an attempt to move the Web
                    itself from the document paradigm, in which it originated, toward the database
                    paradigm — to go beyond a <soCalled>Web of documents</soCalled> to a
                        <soCalled>Web of data,</soCalled> as its proponents have put it. They hope
                    to achieve this through a revival of the graph data model for database design,
                    which had been neglected for many years in favor of the relational data model.
                    The heart of the Semantic Web is RDF (Resource Description Framework), which
                    prescribes a standardized way of representing knowledge in the form of
                    subject-predicate-object <soCalled>triples.</soCalled> In terms of mathematical
                    graph theory, a set of RDF triples represents a graph structure that consists of
                        <soCalled>nodes</soCalled> and <soCalled>arcs</soCalled> (also called
                        <q>vertices</q> and <q>edges</q>) which can be displayed visually in a
                    network diagram and analyzed by algorithms designed to traverse graphs (for an
                    introduction to the graph data model and graph theory, see <ptr
                        target="#aho1995" loc="451–528"/>). The graph data model is universal, like
                    the relational data model, which means that the concepts and relationships of
                    any ontology, no matter how complex, can be represented by means of atomized RDF
                    triples within a graph database.</p>
                <p>The emergence of RDF as a database format constitutes a challenge to the
                    practice, common in the humanities, of using digital documents as primary
                    repositories of scholarly information, as opposed to using them simply as
                    ephemeral secondary vehicles for presenting to human readers particular views of
                    information that have been dynamically generated from an underlying atomized
                    database (i.e., via HTML documents or via tabular displays of structured data).
                    Since the advent of the World Wide Web in the early 1990s, a great deal of
                    digital information produced by scholars has been stored in the form of tagged
                    documents and other digital resources to which such documents are linked.
                    Encoding texts in TEI-XML documents is an example of this strategy. But the
                    Semantic Web calls into question this way of storing scholarly data.</p>
                <p>We should keep in mind that the World Wide Web was not originally designed for
                    the primary storage of research data, even though it has come to be used that
                    way in the humanities. The Web was designed to present information to human
                    readers, as is indicated by its basic metaphor of <soCalled>pages</soCalled> of
                    information that an end-user can <soCalled>browse</soCalled> and from which a
                    user can jump to other pages via <soCalled>hyperlinks.</soCalled> It is not
                    surprising, therefore, that HTML documents are difficult to search and
                    manipulate as data objects using database techniques. Neither the meaning of the
                    data objects nor the meaning of the linkages among them is explicitly specified.
                    Databases with specified meanings are of course accessible on the Web via links
                    from static Web pages or via dynamic Web pages that the databases themselves
                    have generated, but these databases are not part of the World Wide Web itself.
                    They have no universal predictable structure and so require special-purpose
                    software in each case to interpret them. The Web per se, regarded as a
                    predictably structured database based on a common standard, is extremely simple,
                    consisting of interlinked HTML documents and other data objects whose type and
                    location (but not contents) can be described in HTML.<note> From the perspective
                        of graph theory, Web pages are nodes and Web hyperlinks are arcs, so the
                        World Wide Web as a whole can be regarded as a vast database predicated on
                        the graph data model. But it is difficult to query the Web effectively as a
                        database because it has an extremely simple ontology consisting of an
                        amorphous network of semantically undefined units of information
                            (<soCalled>pages</soCalled>) linked in an undefined way to other units
                        of information. This ontology is implemented in a very simple graph schema
                        defined by HTML in contrast to the more complex graph schemas that can be
                        defined by sets of RDF triples.</note> Because HTML was originally designed
                    to enable human browsing of information on the Internet and was not designed for
                    automated querying, it specifies how information should be displayed but does
                    not specify its meaning except to say that certain units of information are
                    linked to other units in some fashion.</p>
                <p>The simplicity of the Web’s schema has made it easy for people to share
                    information on the Internet. Scholars in the humanities have benefited because
                    the Web has encouraged the digitization and dissemination of vast quantities of
                    primary research material — literary texts, historical archives, maps,
                    photographs, audio and video clips, architectural and artifactual descriptions,
                    etc. — as well as secondary literature in the form of monographs, dictionaries,
                    and journal articles. However, the Web’s simplicity means that it lacks a
                    predefined semantic structure that could allow scholars to disseminate detailed
                    analyses of their sources in a way that is conducive to automated retrieval and
                    analysis, as opposed to human browsing and reading.<note> Querying by means of a
                        Web search engine such as Google is not an adequate solution to this
                        problem. A search engine returns a list of Web pages ranked in order of
                        their presumed relevance to what the user wants to find. This is helpful as
                        a rough-and-ready way to locate information but, as every Web user knows,
                        search engines often return irrelevant information or fail to find relevant
                        information.</note> The internal semantic structure of a Web page is not
                    predictable and the links between pages are semantically ambiguous, thus the
                    complex conceptual distinctions scholars employ as they study and discuss their
                    sources are not represented in a predictable digital form. This makes it
                    difficult to find and compare specific observations and interpretations in a
                    comprehensive way. Human readers can supply the semantics of the information
                    presented to them in a Web page but no semantic constraints are contained in the
                    internal, machine-readable representation of the information, preventing
                    automated querying and comparison.</p>
                <p>This limitation results from the Web’s reliance on the document paradigm of
                    software design, which is exemplified in the HTML markup scheme and the Web
                        <soCalled>page</soCalled> concept. The Web has used the document paradigm to
                    great effect, popularizing a simple technique for disseminating information on
                    the Internet in the form of marked-up character sequences. But this technique by
                    itself is not sufficient to allow the Web to be used as a database. For this
                    reason, the World Wide Web Consortium has built upon the XML and RDF data
                    standards by sponsoring the creation of two new querying languages analogous to
                    the SQL language used in relational database systems. These languages are
                    XQuery, for use with XML documents, and SPARQL, for use with RDF triples. The
                    advent of these new querying languages and their implementation in recent years
                    in high-performance database software (e.g., Oracle, IBM’s DB2, MarkLogic) has
                    made it possible to create non-relational systems capable of representing
                    complex scholarly conceptualizations in a form that can be easily disseminated
                    on the Internet and can also be efficiently searched and manipulated in the same
                    way as relational databases.</p>
                <p>XML itself was originally designed not as a database format but to represent the
                    semantic structure of documents in a way that could be shared on the
                    old-fashioned Web via browsers and other document-oriented software. Similarly,
                    RDF was originally intended simply to describe Web documents and other digital
                        <soCalled>resources</soCalled> so they would be easier to find — hence the
                    name <title>Resource Description Framework.</title> But when XML documents or
                    RDF triples are used in a database system with a powerful querying language,
                    they transcend the document paradigm within which they emerged. Their character
                    sequences are used within a database to represent atomized multi-dimensional
                    structures that go beyond the one- and two-dimensional structures prescribed by
                    the document paradigm.</p>
                <p>The markup method is here detached from its origins as a means of representing a
                    text via a long sequence of characters. Marked-up character sequences function
                    simply as a convenient way to serialize complex data structures — including the
                    atomized, interconnected, and thus multi-dimensional structures used in
                    databases — for the purpose of transmitting them across the Internet in a
                    standardized <soCalled>cross-platform</soCalled> way, without having to worry
                    about which operating system is used by the computing devices that are receiving
                    them. A scholarly text, in particular, will be represented in a properly
                    designed XML database or RDF database by many different character strings that
                    do not comprise a single sequential data object but constitute a collection of
                    interrelated data objects.</p>
                <p>We have used the XML Schema standard and the XQuery language to implement the
                    CHOIR ontology in a multi-project, multi-user, password-protected system — an
                    Online Cultural and Historical Research Environment — which can be distributed
                    widely on the Internet on many different database servers. The information
                    stored in the OCHRE system is highly atomized. It is contained in individually
                    addressable data objects, each of which has a universally unique identifier.
                    This is in keeping with the architectural design of the Semantic Web, even
                    though we are using XML documents rather than RDF triples as the basic
                    structural components.<note> A distributed database architecture is possible
                        because each XML document in the OCHRE system is an atomic data object that
                        has its own universally unique identifier which serves as a key field for
                        retrieving the object and for performing database joins. This is analogous
                        to the universally unique identifier (normally a Web URI) found in each
                        member of an RDF triple. XML documents in the OCHRE database contain
                        identifiers that point to other documents on the same database server or on
                        different database servers elsewhere on the Internet. The number and types
                        of other documents to which a given document can point will depend on its
                        own document type. Every document is an instance of one of several possible
                        document types, which collectively prescribe the schema of the database.
                        Each document type is defined by means of an XML Schema
                        specification.</note></p>
                <p>However, like any conceptual ontology, CHOIR is not restricted to a single
                    implementation. It could also be implemented in an RDF system based on the graph
                    model currently promoted by advocates of the Semantic Web — or, for that matter,
                    it could be implemented in a relational system using SQL. The decision about how
                    best to implement a conceptual ontology is a matter of software engineering and
                    depends on the software tools and standards available at the time. We have
                    chosen to use XML documents with XQuery rather than RDF triples with SPARQL
                    because CHOIR makes extensive use of recursive hierarchies, and XQuery, unlike
                    SPARQL, can deal with hierarchies very efficiently while still making it easy to
                    search and update non-hierarchical networks, on the one hand, and highly
                    structured data, on the other.<note> XML systems and RDF systems both depend on
                        mathematical graph theory rather than the set theory that underlies
                        relational database systems, but XML systems are optimized to work with a
                        particular kind of graph structure consisting of nodes and arcs that
                        represent hierarchies of data elements and attributes. In addition, the
                        XQuery language used with XML documents is <q>Turing complete,</q> whereas
                        the SPARQL language used with RDF triples is not. This means that XQuery can
                        perform any query performed by SPARQL but not vice versa. It also means that
                        any query or update performed by SQL, which is the standard querying
                        language for relational databases, can be translated into XQuery. Support
                        for the XQuery and SPARQL standards has recently been incorporated into
                        high-performance DBMS software sold by leading vendors such as Oracle and
                        IBM, whose database platforms are no longer purely relational but now
                        support the semistructured-graph data model (via XML) and the network-graph
                        data model (via RDF). Likewise, MarkLogic, a leading XML DBMS, now supports
                        SQL for querying relational tuples and SPARQL for querying RDF triples, as
                        well as providing a highly efficient mechanism for indexing and querying XML
                        documents via XQuery. MarkLogic also has built-in support for Apache Hadoop,
                        allowing it to use the MapReduce technique to distribute data and processing
                        among many computing nodes, ensuring scalability in the face of large
                        amounts of data and large numbers of simultaneous users.</note> But what
                    matters most in the long run is the ontology, not the implementation. Converting
                    data from one database schema to another — from an XML schema to an RDF schema
                    or a relational schema — is a relatively simple matter provided that the
                    underlying ontology remains the same. Moreover, the database need not be a
                    closed <soCalled>silo</soCalled> of information. Regardless of which data model
                    and querying language are used, a properly designed item-based system can be
                    made accessible online and the information it manages can be widely distributed
                    on multiple servers hosted by different institutions, in the spirit of the
                    Semantic Web.</p>
                <p>We argue that computer-aided research in the humanities would be greatly enhanced
                    by the widespread use of a comprehensive ontology of scholarly knowledge.
                    Accordingly, we have designed the CHOIR ontology to be a stable and sustainable
                    basis for storing and integrating diverse kinds of information over the long
                    term even as database software and schemas change. We offer this ontology as an
                    example of a comprehensive conceptualization of scholarly knowledge that can be
                    implemented in quite different kinds of database systems while serving as a
                    widely shared conceptual framework for the digital representation of scholarly
                    information. By means of database systems and APIs (application programming
                    interfaces) that implement the ontology, any and all scholarly observations and
                    interpretations, no matter how idiosyncratic, can be distributed on the Internet
                    in a predictable digital form, allowing them to be searched and edited by
                    interoperable software applications in a highly granular fashion with the aid of
                    powerful querying languages. And the Semantic Web standards make it easy to
                    disseminate the underlying ontology itself because the subject-predicate-object
                    triples of RDF are not just a data format for a particular kind of database
                    implementation but also provide a standardized way to express and share
                    conceptual ontologies in an implementation-independent manner.</p>
                <p>The CHOIR ontology is described in considerable detail in our OCHRE manual (<ptr
                        target="#schloen2012"/>, which is available as a printed book or online at
                        <ref target="http://ochre.uchicago.edu">http://ochre.uchicago.edu</ref>).
                    The ontology is currently expressed as a set of interrelated XML document types,
                    which are the basis of the OCHRE database system.<note> See <title rend="italic"
                            >OCHRE</title> by Schloen and Schloen (2012), pp. 372–375. Previously,
                        we called these document types the <title rend="quotes">Archaeological
                            Markup Language,</title> abbreviated as ArchaeoML, reflecting our
                        initial focus on archaeological data. However, these XML document types and
                        the upper ontology they express have proved to be applicable to a wide range
                        of research data beyond archaeology. Moreover, the designation <q>markup
                            language</q> was confusing for people who assumed that our XML document
                        types merely define metadata tags for marking up existing documents and data
                        tables rather than representing scholarly data of all kinds, including texts
                        and tables, in a more fundamental and atomized fashion. Thus, we have
                        adopted the name CHOIR for the ontology (<title>Comprehensive Hierarchical
                            Ontology for Integrative Research</title>) and CHOIR-XML for the
                        implementation of this ontology as an XML database schema in the form of a
                        set of interrelated XML document types, whose structure is specified via the
                        XML Schema language.</note> To complement the CHOIR-XML version of the
                    ontology, we are in the process of creating a CHOIR-RDF version, employing the
                    Web Ontology Language (OWL) to prescribe RDF subject-predicate-object triples
                    that express the ontology [<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview"
                        >http://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview</ref>]. This will provide a standardized
                    archival and exchange format that can be used by any CHOIR-based system,
                    regardless of its own data model and schema, because each system can use the
                    CHOIR-RDF format to export data in a way that preserves all the atomized
                    entities and relationships it contains, allowing them to be imported
                    subsequently into a different system in the form of RDF triples without any loss
                    of information.<note> In addition to CHOIR-RDF, OCHRE has its own archival
                        export format consisting of XML documents generated from the database that
                        are much larger and <soCalled>flatter</soCalled> than the highly atomized
                        CHOIR-XML data objects used within the database system itself. These
                        exported XML documents also contain XSLT stylesheets to format the
                        information as HTML for display in Web browsers. This
                            <soCalled>denormalized</soCalled> archival format is intended for use
                        with simple searching and viewing applications that dispense with a complex
                        database querying mechanism.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Data integration without forced standardization</head>
                <p>Earlier in this article we stressed the limitations of traditional digital
                    documents as a means of representing scholarly texts. But the vision of
                    scholarly computing that has shaped the CHOIR ontology and has been implemented
                    in the OCHRE database system goes far beyond representing multiple readings of
                    an individual text. As we explain in our OCHRE manual <ptr target="#schloen2012"
                    />, large textual corpora can be densely interrelated within the OCHRE database
                    by means of cross-cutting links from one text to another, and also by means of
                    synthetic works like dictionaries and bibliographies, which are themselves
                    modeled as hierarchies of entities that are cross-linked to selected textual
                    components. For example, a dictionary entry that cites a textual excerpt to
                    explain a meaning or sub-meaning of a word can be linked to a text in a way that
                    avoids any repetition of textual content. In other words, the same textual
                    components can participate, not just in multiple overlapping hierarchies of
                    textual analysis, but also in multiple dictionary entries, providing live links
                    from a dictionary to its underlying texts without any error-prone duplication of
                    data.</p>
                <p>And, going beyond texts, the CHOIR ontology encompasses units of space, time, and
                    agency as distinct entities, allowing not just texts but their authors and
                    editors, and the places and periods of textual production, to be represented as
                    individual database items that can be interlinked in many different ways. The
                    goal is to capture explicitly, in a reproducible digital form, any and all
                    distinctions and relationships a scholar might detect and discuss — and not just
                    in textual studies but also in archaeology, history, and many other cultural and
                    social disciplines.<note> The original impetus for the development of the OCHRE
                        database system and the ontology it implements was the need to manage large
                        amounts of heterogeneous archaeological information. But it quickly became
                        apparent that the same data structures, and thus the same software, could be
                        used equally well for the representation of texts and other phenomena. The
                        basic idea behind our hierarchical, item-based approach is described in an
                        article by David Schloen entitled <ref
                            target="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1023%2FA%3A1002471112790"
                                ><title rend="quotes">Archaeological Data Models and Web Publication
                                Using XML</title></ref>
                        <ptr target="#schloen2001"/>. This article is out of date in some respects —
                        it was written before the OCHRE project was begun and before XML databases
                        were widely available — but it explains the basic design principle that
                        underlies the CHOIR ontology and the OCHRE system.</note> Doing so will
                    facilitate powerful automated analyses that span many different research
                    projects, allowing scholars to explore the interconnections among texts and
                    their larger worlds, however these may be defined.</p>
                <p>This brings us to a central issue in scholarly computing and in many other kinds
                    of computing: namely, the need to integrate large quantities of diverse digital
                    information that has been recorded using different software applications based
                    on different schemas that are based in turn on different ontologies (see <ptr
                        target="#doan2012"/>). Scholars encode texts using heterogeneous markup
                    schemes; they create data tables using heterogeneous table structures; and they
                    describe digital resources using heterogeneous metadata formats. The OCHRE
                    system was designed from the beginning to facilitate the integration of
                    heterogeneous information, whether it be digitized originally in the form of
                    marked-up character sequences or in the rows and columns of structured tables.
                    OCHRE can do this because the CHOIR ontology on which it is based is a highly
                    generic <soCalled>upper</soCalled> ontology. An upper (or foundation) ontology
                    is one that has been defined on a very general level of abstraction in order to
                    subsume more specific local ontologies — e.g., particular nomenclatures and
                    classifications of entities — and thus to integrate data across separate domains
                    of knowledge. A database system that implements the CHOIR ontology can integrate
                    information from many different researchers and research projects while
                    preserving the terminology and conceptual distinctions of each. There is no need
                    for a universal standardized terminology because CHOIR provides a common
                    integrative structure at the level of the fundamental spatial, temporal,
                    linguistic, and logical entities and relationships that are used by all
                    scholars.</p>
                <p>In practice, this entails importing into a central database a diverse array of
                    existing scholarly data in the form of heterogeneously tagged text files and
                    heterogeneously structured data tables, automatically parsing the existing data
                    in order to decompose each text or table into a highly atomized collection of
                    individual items, and then populating the database with these items while
                    creating explicit links among them that replicate the entities, properties, and
                    relationships inherent in the original text files and data tables. This is made
                    possible by adopting an item-based organization of information rather than a
                    class-based organization. In a class-based database, the number and types of the
                    entity-classes, represented as two-dimensional tables, vary from one database to
                    the next. Even when there are similar classes in two different databases, the
                    predefined properties of the entities in each class, represented as table
                    columns, usually do not match. Integrating such databases requires
                    special-purpose software that is laboriously programmed to take account of the
                    idiosyncrasies of each database. But in an item-based database that implements
                    the CHOIR ontology, this problem is avoided because the class-based tabular
                    structures — and sequential textual structures, for that matter — are decomposed
                    into smaller entities with their own properties. Classes comprised of entities
                    that have been imported from heterogeneous data sources may then be constructed
                    secondarily, as needed, by comparing the individual properties of the entities,
                    without requiring that each entity be pre-assigned to a group that is assumed to
                    have the same set of properties. And because spatial, temporal, linguistic, and
                    taxonomic relationships are represented by flexible hierarchies, the hierarchies
                    of one project can easily be merged with the hierarchies of another, resulting
                    in a larger database that contains the data from both projects while remaining
                    coherently organized in a predictable fashion.</p>
                <p>Most attempts at data integration in academic disciplines have involved the
                    imposition of a standardized terminology that is intended to be adopted by all
                    researchers in a given domain of knowledge, whether in the form of standardized
                    table columns, standardized markup schemes (e.g., TEI), or standardized metadata
                    attributes (e.g., Dublin Core). However, this often proves to be unworkable as
                    scholars chafe at the restrictions the standards impose and eventually extend
                    them or diverge from them in idiosyncratic ways. They do this, not simply
                    because they are wedded to their own familiar nomenclatures, but because their
                    divergent terminologies quite legitimately reflect disparate research traditions
                    and interpretive perspectives — not to mention the different languages spoken by
                    researchers from different countries. No standardized terminology contains every
                    meaningful distinction that scholars may wish to make, which means that
                    standards tend to grow over time and become ever more bloated and complex to
                    please everyone, requiring the software that implements them to keep changing,
                    which in turn diminishes the value of the standards as a basis for automated
                    data integration.</p>
                <p>However, a standardized terminology is not actually necessary. Integrating
                    heterogeneous information requires a standardized way of representing the
                    structure of knowledge — how entities are described with properties and how
                    entities are related to other entities and properties are related to other
                    properties — but it does not require standardization of the properties
                    themselves. Scholars may well find it convenient on occasion to adopt a widely
                    shared terminology, but they should not be forced to do so.</p>
                <p>For this reason, the CHOIR ontology does not impose a standardized terminology
                    but instead provides a generic framework within which different terminologies
                    can be expressed and compared. Property names (attributes) are not built into
                    the structure of the database as table column headings or as predefined markup
                    tags. Property names are themselves treated as user-defined data within a more
                    abstract structure in which taxonomic descriptors are manipulated by end-users
                    as individual database items in their own right. Scholars can define their own
                    descriptive property names and property values and can organize them into a
                    meaningful hierarchy, yielding a project-specific taxonomy. There is no
                    structural distinction between data and metadata because all information is
                    represented in the same way, in terms of individual items that are linked to
                    other items. Not just entities but properties of entities are user-defined
                    database items that are linked to the entities they describe and can themselves
                    be constructed and manipulated as individually addressable units of
                    information.</p>
                <p>In OCHRE, a hierarchy of items that represent descriptive properties and property
                    values forms a user-defined taxonomy, which could encompass linguistic,
                    literary, and philological properties of the kind represented in textual markup
                    schemes like the TEI tagging scheme, as well as properties that pertain to
                    entities other than texts, such as persons, places, periods, and things. Texts
                    and components of texts are entities that are represented in the database as
                    individually addressable items, like any other entities. Resources such as
                    images are also entities that are represented as individual database items in
                    the same way. All units of scholarly analysis — whether they be textual,
                    spatial, temporal, personal, or taxonomic — make use of the same data structures
                    and algorithms, which represent each unit of analysis as a distinct database
                    item that can be described with its own properties and related to other units by
                    means of hierarchies and non-hierarchical networks.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, database users can easily specify the semantic relationships between
                    the disparate property names and qualitative property values found in different
                    taxonomies; that is, they can specify thesaurus relationships indicating
                    synonyms, antonyms, broader terms, narrower terms, and related terms. These
                    user-created thesaurus relationships can then be saved and used in database
                    queries to find similar items that have been described by different projects
                    using different terms. Data imported into the database from heterogeneously
                    tagged texts and from heterogeneously structured tables can thus be integrated
                    automatically without abandoning the original terminology used to record the
                    information, which is retained permanently in the properties of the database
                    items.</p>
                <p>But just as there is no universal, standardized taxonomy that applies to all
                    projects, there is no universal, standardized thesaurus. A thesaurus is itself a
                    work of scholarship to be credited to a particular scholar and shared with other
                    scholars, who can decide whose thesaurus to use when querying the database or
                    whether to devise their own. This reflects the fact that meaning depends on
                    context. The meanings of terms and their relationships to other terms cannot be
                    formalized once and for all and then applied in an anonymous, automated fashion
                    without regard to the specific intellectual context in which the terms are being
                    used, especially in disciplines characterized by a wide range of scholarly
                    traditions and interpretive perspectives.</p>
                <p>As a matter of principle, then, we do not attempt to replace the scholarly
                    choices of individual researchers with a standardized terminology. In the OCHRE
                    system there are no predefined table columns or descriptive markup tags or
                    metadata attributes. There is no predefined taxonomy or thesaurus. To impose a
                    standardized terminology would be to deprive scholars of the ability, and the
                    responsibility, to distinguish and describe their sources in their own way — and
                    in a way that is exposed to scrutiny by other scholars so that interpretations
                    can be contested and discussed. Our database design is predicated on the belief
                    that many of the semantic distinctions important to scholars cannot be
                    adequately formalized in advance and therefore should not be built into the
                    internal structure of a database system but should be a matter of ongoing
                    debate. Scholarly software should be designed to facilitate this work of
                    interpretation, not to replace it, by making it easy to construct and to share
                    both taxonomies and taxonomy-integrating thesauruses. But no single taxonomy or
                    thesaurus should be assumed to be universal. These are human works that are
                    created in particular research settings and reflect the interpretive
                    perspectives of embodied human agents, who themselves are rooted in particular
                    historical and linguistic traditions.</p>
                <p>In other words, in the world of critical scholarship, above all, to embrace
                    digitization is not to embrace artificial intelligence as a substitute for human
                    judgment. In his book <title rend="italic">What Computers Can’t Do</title>, the
                    philosopher Hubert Dreyfus <ptr target="#dreyfus1992"/> discusses the dependence
                    of meaning on context in relation to what he sees as the limitations, in
                    principle, of artificial intelligence — or at least the <q>strong</q> version of
                    artificial intelligence championed by its early proponents. Following Heidegger,
                    Dreyfus argues that our understanding of the world emerges from the background
                    of our historically situated human embodiment. This background can never be
                    fully articulated; thus our understanding of the world (including our scholarly
                    judgments, in this case) cannot be adequately emulated in formal symbols and
                    algorithms of the kind used by digital computers. Steven Horst, writing on
                        <title rend="quotes">The Computational Theory of Mind</title> in the <title
                        rend="italic">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>, summarizes his
                    argument as follows: <quote rend="inline" source="#horst2009">Dreyfus argued
                        that most human knowledge and competence — particularly <emph>expert</emph>
                        knowledge — cannot in fact be reduced to an algorithmic procedure, and hence
                        is not computable in the relevant technical sense. Drawing upon insights
                        from Heidegger and existential phenomenology, Dreyfus pointed to a
                        principled difference between the kind of cognition one might employ when
                        learning a skill and the kind employed by the expert. . . . more often than
                        not, argues Dreyfus, it is not possible to capture expert knowledge in an
                        algorithm, particularly where it draws upon general background knowledge
                        outside the problem domain</quote> (<ptr target="#horst2009"/>; see also
                        <ptr target="#winograd1986"/>; <ptr target="#winograd1995"/>; <ptr
                        target="#winograd2006"/>).<note> In their 1986 book <title rend="italic"
                            >Understanding Computers and Cognition</title>, the computer scientists
                        Terry Winograd and Fernando Flores discuss the implications for software
                        design of Heidegger’s phenomenologically oriented ontology and the view of
                        human cognition that flows from it, which stands in radical opposition to <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#winograd1986">the rationalistic
                                orientation that pervades not only artificial intelligence and the
                                rest of computer science, but also much of linguistics, management
                                theory, and cognitive science</quote>
                            <ptr target="#winograd1986" loc="6"/>
                        </cit>. Twenty years later, Winograd noted that work in artificial
                        intelligence (AI) has largely moved away from the (failed) rationalistic
                        attempt to capture human thought in a formal symbolic representation and has
                        moved toward <quote rend="inline" source="#winograd2006">statistical, embodied, and
                            constructivist approaches</quote> that differ markedly from the original
                        AI paradigm and are compatible with a phenomenological <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#winograd2006">design-oriented</quote> approach: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#winograd2006">Rather than basing AI
                                competence on a logical [computer-based] representation of the
                                setting and the agent’s knowledge, there is an interplay between
                                general adaptive mechanisms and world experience, which leads over
                                time to intelligent behaviors, often as the outcome of extensive
                                examples and training. . . . Of course there is a major role for a
                                rationalistic approach in creating and understanding the adaptive
                                mechanisms. Work in statistical language understanding, neural
                                networks, or machine learning is based on deep analysis and
                                quantitative models of the different mechanisms and techniques that
                                form the basis of adaptation. But the researcher is not required (or
                                able) to explicitly represent the knowledge or rules of behavior for
                                the intelligent system</quote>
                            <ptr target="#winograd2006" loc="1257–1258"/>
                        </cit>.</note></p>
                <p>Accordingly, we have designed the OCHRE system in such a way that a scholar who
                    is searching the database can decide whose thesaurus to employ when retrieving
                    information from more than one project and can easily create new thesaurus
                    relationships, if necessary. The responsibility for correlating different terms
                    is in the hands of the person asking the question, not the person who recorded
                    the data, and certainly not the person who wrote the software, because semantic
                    relationships among different scholarly taxonomies cannot be established once
                    and for all and employed without regard to the current intellectual context.
                    This does not rule out semi-automated ontology alignment; that is, the use of
                    machine-learning algorithms to propose thesaurus relationships to a human
                    expert, who then makes the final decisions about how to relate one taxonomy to
                    another. But, even so, the semantics of the database are determined by its users
                    rather than by an anonymous semantic authority whose interpretations have been
                    embedded in the software. OCHRE makes it easy to scrutinize the interpretive
                    choices of the named scholars who created the taxonomies used when entering data
                    and the thesaurus relationships invoked when performing a query. Users of the
                    database are not constrained by someone else’s prior interpretations, nor are
                    they dependent on an automated search engine whose algorithm for matching
                    similar terms is hidden from them, usurping their semantic authority in a
                    different way.<note> Concerning semi-automated ontology alignment, Alon Halevy,
                        a computer scientist who is an expert on data integration, says: <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#halevy2005">Some argue that the way to resolve
                            semantic heterogeneity is through standard schemas. Experience has
                            shown, however, that standards have limited success and only in domains
                            where the incentives to agree on standards are very strong. . .
                            .Resolving schema heterogeneity is inherently a heuristic,
                            human-assisted process. Unless there are very strong constraints on how
                            the two schemas you are reconciling are different from each other, one
                            should not hope for a completely automated solution. The goal is to
                            reduce the time it takes human experts to create a mapping between a
                            pair of schemas, and enable them to focus on the hardest and most
                            ambiguous parts of the mapping</quote> (<ptr target="#halevy2005"
                            loc="54–55"/>; see also <ptr target="#doan2012" loc="124–127"
                    />).</note></p>
                <p>In its approach to data integration and to the representation of information in
                    general, the CHOIR ontology, and the OCHRE database system that implements it,
                    conform to long-established practices that characterize critical scholarship, in
                    which semantic authority rests with the individual scholar. In this regard,
                    OCHRE is different from systems that conform to practices of institutional
                    control and standardization which have emerged in commercial and governmental
                    contexts — in which, of course, the vast majority of existing database systems
                    and text-processing systems have been developed, with the result that most
                    software is designed to meet the needs of bureaucratic organizations in which
                    semantic authority is imposed from the top down. In contrast, most scholars
                    today would agree that how one describes an object of study and how one
                    determines whether it is similar to something else reflect a historically
                    situated understanding of the world. There is no absolute and universal way of
                    describing the cultural and social world, and many would argue that the same is
                    true for the natural world. For this reason, scholarly practices have been
                    developed to identify who said what, and when and where they said it, in order
                    to encourage individual interpretive autonomy and to discourage anonymous and
                    unquestioned semantic authority. This is done by crediting descriptions and
                    interpretations to particular named scholars and by providing mechanisms for
                    widely disseminating their work so it can be used, criticized, and perhaps
                    replaced by other scholars.</p>
                <p>Unlike many database systems whose design has been borrowed from non-academic
                    domains, OCHRE does not try to change these longstanding scholarly practices but
                    rather to facilitate them. It does so by means of a database which is
                    sufficiently well structured that it can be efficiently searched but which does
                    not impose a predefined taxonomy or hide from view the logic by which
                    information is retrieved. Instead, database users can construct their own
                    taxonomy (or can borrow a taxonomy created by another project) and each OCHRE
                    end-user can decide whose thesaurus to employ when matching terms in one
                    project’s taxonomy with those in another. Interpretive choices are exposed to
                    view, both in the description of particular items and in the retrieval of what
                    are deemed to be similar items. Scholars who use OCHRE are not forced to conform
                    to <soCalled>the computer</soCalled> but are themselves responsible for the
                    semantics of the database, which is not an interpretive agent in its own right
                    but merely a tool to facilitate the human work of interpretation.</p>
                <p>To put it another way: ontological heterogeneity is not a vice to be suppressed
                    but a defining virtue of critical scholarship. Digitization of scholarly
                    information should not be used as an excuse to suppress this heterogeneity,
                    imposing a false consensus by institutional fiat. Instead, software should be
                    designed to make it easy for scholars to disagree with others and defend their
                    own interpretations — or to reach agreement, as the case may be — thereby
                    facilitating a productive conflict of interpretations. We advocate, therefore, a
                    highly generalized upper ontology for scholarly information that does not depend
                    on standardizing the terms and conceptual distinctions to be used within a given
                    domain of knowledge but instead relativizes and subsumes disparate local
                    ontologies, including the more general but still domain-specific local
                    ontologies that are expressed in standardized text-encoding schemes like the TEI
                    tagging scheme, in standardized table structures that represent predefined
                    entity classes and properties, and in standardized metadata attributes.</p>
                <p>Of course, even the highly abstract CHOIR ontology that underlies the OCHRE
                    system is not timeless or absolute. Embedded in it are historically situated
                    assumptions about how to organize knowledge. But experience has shown that this
                    ontology, which relies on very general concepts such as space, time, and agency,
                    and which harnesses the expressive power of recursive hierarchies, can represent
                    a very wide range of scholarly descriptions and interpretations in many
                    different fields of study.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>At the beginning of this article we focused on a particular problem in the
                    digital representation of scholarly texts, namely, the problem of overlapping
                    hierarchies. It should now be apparent that this problem is simply a special
                    case of a much larger problem in the representation of scholarly knowledge.
                    Overlapping hierarchies occur in many areas of research in which there is a need
                    to represent multiple configurations of the same units of analysis, be they
                    spatial, temporal, textual, or defined in some other way. To achieve the full
                    benefits of digitization, scholars need to be able to record multiple
                    interpretations of the same entities in a predictable, reproducible digital
                    form; and they need to be able to do so without error-prone duplication of data,
                    without severing the complex interconnections among their various
                    interpretations, and without being forced to adopt a standardized terminology
                    that deprives them of semantic authority and limits the diversity of
                    conceptualizations that motivates their scholarly work in the first place.</p>
                <p>For digital texts, in particular, this will mean abandoning the document paradigm
                    in favor of the database paradigm. And within the database paradigm, it will
                    mean abandoning the class-based organization of information — itself a
                    reflection of the intuitive but overly restrictive document paradigm — in favor
                    of a more abstract and atomized item-based organization. Only then will we
                    obtain a digital ontology of scholarly knowledge that is not borrowed
                    uncritically from non-scholarly domains and is sufficient for our task.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>We are grateful to Drayton Benner, Charles Blair, Martin Mueller, and Miller
                    Prosser for reading drafts of this article and giving us their comments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="abiteboul2000" label="Abiteboul et al. 2000">Abiteboul, S., Buneman,
                    P., and Suciu, D. <title rend="italic">Data on the Web: From Relations to
                        Semistructured Data and XML</title>. Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco
                    (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aho1995" label="Aho and Ullman 1995">Aho, A. V. and Ullman, J. D.
                        <title rend="italic">Foundations of Computer Science: C Edition</title>.
                    Computer Science Press, New York (1995). <ref
                        target="http://i.stanford.edu/~ullman/focs.html"
                        >http://i.stanford.edu/~ullman/focs.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barnard1988" label="Barnard et al. 1988">Barnard, D., Hayter, R.,
                    Karababa, M., Logan, G., and McFadden, J. <title rend="quotes">SGML-Based Markup
                        for Literary Texts: Two Problems and Some Solutions</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>, 22 (1988):
                    265-276.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buzzetti2002" label="Buzzetti 2002">Buzzetti, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Representation and the Text Model</title>, <title rend="italic">New
                        Literary History</title>, 33 (2002): 61-88.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buzzetti2009" label="Buzzetti 2009">Buzzetti, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Editions and Text Processing</title>. In M. Deegan and K.
                    Sutherland (eds), <title rend="italic">Text Editing, Print and the Digital
                        World</title>, Ashgate, Farnham, England (2009), pp. 45-61.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buzzetti2006" label="Buzzetti and McGann 2006">Buzzetti, D. and
                    McGann, J. <title rend="quotes">Critical Editing in a Digital Horizon</title>.
                    In L. Burnard, K. O’Brien O’Keeffe, and J. Unsworth (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Textual Editing</title>, The Modern Language Association of
                    America, New York (2006), pp. 53-73.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="codd1970" label="Codd 1970">Codd, E. F. <title rend="quotes">A
                        Relational Model of Data for Large Shared Data Banks</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Communications of the Association for Computing
                        Machinery</title>, 13 (1970): 377-387.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="corballis2011" label="Corballis 2011">Corballis, M. C. <title
                        rend="italic">The Recursive Mind: The Origins of Human Language, Thought,
                        and Civilization</title>. Princeton University Press, Princeton, N.J.
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cummings2007" label="Cummings 2007">Cummings, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Text Encoding Initiative and the Study of Literature</title>. In S.
                    Schreibman and R. Siemens (eds), <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital
                        Literary Studies</title>, Blackwell, Malden, Massachusetts (2007), pp.
                    451-476.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doan2012" label="Doan et al. 2012">Doan, A., Halevy, A., and Ives, Z.
                        <title rend="italic">Principles of Data Integration.</title> Elsevier,
                    Waltham, Massachusetts (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dreyfus1992" label="Dreyfus 1992">Dreyfus, H. L. <ref
                        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Computers_Can%27t_Do"><title
                            rend="italic">What Computers Can’t Do</title></ref><title rend="italic"
                        >: A Critique of Artificial Reason</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts (2nd edition; 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ducharme1999" label="DuCharme 1999">DuCharme, B. <title rend="italic"
                        >XML: The Annotated Specification</title>. Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle
                    River, New Jersey (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="garcia2009" label="Garcia-Molina et al. 2009">Garcia-Molina, H.,
                    Ullman, J. D., and Widom, J. <title rend="italic">Database Systems: The Complete
                        Book</title>. Pearson Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, New Jersey (2nd
                    edition; 2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldfarb1990" label="Goldfarb 1990">Goldfarb, C. F. <title
                        rend="italic">The SGML Handbook</title>. Clarendon Press, Oxford
                    (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldfarb1996" label="Goldfarb 1996">Goldfarb, C. F. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Roots of SGML: A Personal Reflection</title>, <ref
                        target="http://www.sgmlsource.com/history/roots.htm"
                        >http://www.sgmlsource.com/history/roots.htm</ref> (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gruber1993" label="Gruber 1993">Gruber, T. R. <title rend="quotes">A
                        Translation Approach to Portable Ontology Specifications</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Knowledge Acquisition</title>, 5 (1993): 199-220.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="halevy2005" label="Halevy 2005">Halevy, A. <title rend="quotes">Why
                        Your Data Won’t Mix</title>, <title rend="italic">Queue</title>, 3/8 (2005):
                    50-58.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hauser2002" label="Hauser et al. 2002">Hauser, M. D., Chomsky, N., and
                    Fitch, W. T. <title rend="quotes">The Faculty of Language: What Is It, Who Has
                        It, and How Did It Evolve?</title>, <title rend="italic">Science</title>,
                    298 (2002): 1569-1579.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="horst2009" label="Horst 2009">Horst, S. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Computational Theory of Mind</title>, <title rend="italic">Stanford
                        Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>, Stanford University <ref
                        target="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/computational-mind/"
                        >http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/computational-mind</ref> (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huitfeldt1995" label="Huitfeldt 1995">Huitfeldt, C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Multi-Dimensional Texts in a One-Dimensional Medium</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>, 28 (1994/1995):
                    235-241.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann1991" label="McGann 1991">McGann, J. J. <title rend="italic">The
                        Textual Condition</title>. Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey
                    (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann2004" label="McGann 2004">McGann, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Marking Texts of Many Dimensions</title>. In S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and
                    J. Unsworth (eds), <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital
                        Humanities</title>, Blackwell, Malden, Massachusetts (2004), pp. 198-217.
                        <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nevins2009" label="Nevins et al. 2009">Nevins, A., Pesetsky, D., and
                    Rodrigues, C. <title rend="quotes">Evidence and Argumentation: A Reply to
                        Everett (2009)</title>, <title rend="italic">Language</title>, 85 (2009):
                    671-681.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="renear2004" label="Renear 2004">Renear, A. H. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Text Encoding</title>. In S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and J. Unsworth (eds),
                        <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, Blackwell,
                    Malden, Massachusetts (2004), pp. 218-239. <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="renear1993" label="Renear et al. 1993">Renear, A., Mylonas, E., and
                    Durand, D. <title rend="quotes">Refining Our Notion of What Text Really Is: The
                        Problem of Overlapping Hierarchies</title>, Brown University <ref
                        target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html"
                        >http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html</ref>
                    (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schloen2001" label="Schloen 2001">Schloen, J. D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Archaeological Data Models and Web Publication Using XML</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>, 35 (2001):
                    123-152.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schloen2012" label="Schloen and Schloen 2012">Schloen, J. D. and
                    Schloen, S. R. <title rend="italic">OCHRE: An Online Cultural and Historical
                        Research Environment</title>. Eisenbrauns, Winona Lake, Indiana (2012). <ref
                        target="http://ochre.uchicago.edu">http://ochre.uchicago.edu</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schmidt2009" label="Schmidt and Colomb 2009">Schmidt, D. and Colomb,
                    R. <title rend="quotes">A Data Structure for Representing Multi-version Texts
                        Online</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Human-Computer
                        Studies</title>, 67 (2009): 497-514.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TEIP52013" label="TEI P5 2013">Burnard, L. and Bauman, S. (eds),
                        <title rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interchange</title>, Text Encoding Initiative Consortium, Charlottesville,
                    Virginia (2013). <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tummarello2008" label="Tummarello et al. 2008">Tummarello, G.,
                    Morbidoni, C., Puliti, P., and Piazza, F. <title rend="quotes">A Proposal for
                        Text Encoding Based on Semantic Web Tools</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Online Information Review</title>, 32 (2008): 467-477.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winograd1995" label="Winograd 1995">Winograd, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Heidegger and the Design of Computer Systems</title>. In A. Feenberg and A.
                    Hannay (eds), <title rend="italic">Technology and the Politics of
                        Knowledge</title>, Indiana University Press, Bloomington, Indiana (1995),
                    pp. 108-127.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winograd2006" label="Winograd 2006">Winograd, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Shifting Viewpoints: Artificial Intelligence and Human-Computer
                        Interaction</title>. <title rend="italic">Artificial Intelligence</title>
                    170 (2006): 1256–1258.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winograd1986" label="Winograd and Flores 1986">Winograd, T. and
                    Flores, F. <title rend="italic">Understanding Computers and Cognition: A New
                        Foundation for Design</title>. Ablex Publishing, Norwood, New Jersey
                    (1986).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
