<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Xpos’re: A Tool for Rich Internet Publications</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Leen <dhq:family>Breure</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Utrecht University &amp; DANS (Dutch Data
                        Archive)</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>L.Breure@uu.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Leen Breure studied history at the University of Utrecht. Since mid-80s
                            he has worked in the intersection of information technology / the
                            humanities and cultural heritage studies. His current research is about
                            enhanced publications and rich internet publications, organized in close
                            collaboration with DANS (Data Archiving and Networked Services), an
                            institute of KNAW (Royal Dutch Academy of Arts and Sciences) and NWO
                            (Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research)</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Maarten <dhq:family>Hoogerwerf</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DANS (Dutch Data Archive)</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>maarten.hoogerwerf@dans.knaw.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p> Maarten Hoogerwerf studied computer science at Delft University of
                            Technology. Since 2006 he works for DANS (Data Archiving and Networked
                            Services) where he focuses on persistent identification and integration
                            of research information (researchers, publications, datasets, etc.).
                            Currently he is responsible for the technical infrastructure within DANS
                            and its integration with other national and international
                            infrastructures.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>René <dhq:family>van Horik </dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DANS (Dutch Data Archive)</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>rene.van.horik@dans.knaw.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p> René van Horik works as program manager and researcher at DANS, the
                            Dutch national data archive in the social sciences and humanities. He
                            received his Phd from Delft University of Technology (information
                            science). His research interests are in digital preservation and digital
                            humanities.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000169</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2014-04-30">30 April 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>scholarly publishing</item>
                        <item>rich internet publication</item>
                        <item>multimedia</item>
                        <item>authoring</item>
                        <item>Flash</item>
                        <item>HTML</item>
                        <item>RDF</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2014-02-17" who="EH">Encoded file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p> Internet technologies are gradually reshaping the function of traditional
                    scholarly publications. There is a growing tendency in some disciplines to
                    publish a digital paper together with supplements such as images, videos,
                    3D-models and underlying data. More information requires a better usability in
                    terms of overview and finding information, which has led to new features in
                    journals and thus to modifying and extending this genre. These so-called
                    enhanced publications or rich internet publications have various physical forms:
                    PDF documents with embedded interactive models, HTML files enriched with
                    hyperlinks to contextual information and with facilities to highlight
                    information in the text, or aggregations of documents and other resources linked
                    together through metadata which make them findable for semantic search
                    engines.</p>
                <p>However, many of the originally print-based journals, particularly in the
                    humanities and social sciences, are still rather conservative in format and
                    offer hardly any opportunities for enhanced publishing, which leaves room for
                    some form of self-publishing, perhaps as addition to a regular journal article.
                    In this paper we introduce the Xpos’re tools for authoring and displaying an
                    interactive multimedia scholarly publication, which may be created as a digital
                    companion to a regular journal paper and published, for example, on the author
                    or institution’s website in order to share related research products and to
                    achieve greater visibility. We also report about practical experiences with this
                    software in a few research projects.</p>
                <p>The Xpos’re software (see: <ref target="http://xposre.nl/software/">http://xposre.nl/software/</ref>) comprises a Flash-based document reader
                    and a set of extensions (plug-ins) that extend the basic functionality of this
                    text browser. The extensions are used to display specific types of multimedia
                    that provide additional functionality, such as viewing images, videos and
                    interactive maps. The input text is XML based, which not only guarantees a
                    durable and flexible encoding of content, but also allows automatic rendering in
                    different formats according to the preferences of users and the limitations of
                    their hardware. In addition, the XML source can be easily transformed to an RDF
                    resource map to meet the requirements of the semantic web. The document reader
                    generates output in HTML, in two flavors, namely a slide based version that uses
                    JavaScript, and a plain HTML text (single page), which is most suitable for
                    printing and which can be used to create e-books. This plain HTML text can also
                    be displayed in a format similar to that of scientific journals through the
                    Xpos’re HTML Reader, which has more features than the automatically generated
                    slides and which can be highly customized by the user. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Tools for authoring and displaying interactive multimedia scholarly
                    publications</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. From PDF to Rich Internet Publication and E-book</head>


                <div>
                    <head>Innovation in Scholarly Genres</head>
                    <p>The journal article is still the basis of scholarly communication in most
                        disciplines. For a long time, the available space in a printed publication
                        and the high production costs have put restrictions on adding supplementary
                        material such as pictures, maps and fragments from historical sources. The
                        change to web publishing has taken away these material impediments, but in
                        facing new media we are inclined to recreate the old genre by new means. The
                        form and layout of online publications are in general still dominated by
                        genre conventions based on printed journals and books. The capabilities of
                        the digital channel are often underutilized, which makes that scholarly
                        communications are currently at a <soCalled>horseless carriage</soCalled>
                        state, that lies somewhere between the world of print and paper and the
                        world of the web and computers, with the former still exercising
                        significantly more influence than the latter <ptr target="#force11"/>.</p>
                    <p>There are signs that point to profound changes coming to the system of
                        scholarly communication <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>; <ptr target="#wouters2012"/>. Research on digital curation deliver new
                        publishing models, social media plays a rapidly increasing role in the
                        exchange and discussion of scientific ideas, and some journals have already
                        deliberately changed track by adopting a new format with enhanced usability.
                        Moreover, scholarly blogs offer ample opportunity to experiment with new
                        media such as audio and video. These innovations are unevenly spread over
                        the scholarly landscape: most changes occur in the hard sciences,
                        particularly in physics, chemistry and the bio-medical field, while
                        humanities and social sciences are more reluctant in this respect.<note>See
                            for an preliminary inventory of the occurrence of new publication
                            features: <ref target="http://xposre.nl/epfeatures/index.html">
                                http://xposre.nl/epfeatures/index.html</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The downside of this transition has a practical problem: the technology
                        required for the novel forms of publishing is generally not yet embedded in
                        a smooth authoring process comparable with that for printed publications.
                        Adding multimedia to a blog may not be a big problem, but a scholarly
                        journal adheres to higher standards of long-term sustainable information
                        access and aesthetic layout, which also places demands on the authoring
                        process, and, therefore, on the tools and templates which authors have at
                        their disposal. Non-printable supplements are often stored in a separate
                        section of the publisher’s website and as such are not perceived as part of
                        the discourse itself. The Xpos’re software package discussed here addresses
                        this type of problem for online publications that contain interactive
                        multimedia closely connected with the text. The pros and cons are best
                        understood after a short overview of the upcoming digital genres (section
                        1.2 through 1.4) followed by a preliminary conclusion (section 1.5)
                        explaining why new tools are needed.</p>
                    <p>The innovative scholarly genres can be grouped into a few, not strictly
                        defined categories: (1) enhanced publications, (2) rich internet publication
                        and (3) ebooks. These new genres still reflect many features of the old ones
                        from which they are derived, but have in common a certain integration of the
                        scholarly discourse with interactive access to research material. This
                        integration varies greatly, from linked research data and spreadsheets to
                        embedded interactive statistical charts and maps with results of analysis
                        and computation, image galleries, animated models and videos. The
                        interactivity added to the linear reading allows for diversion from the main
                        line of discourse and enables the user to select the information in which
                        (s)he is particularly interested, to choose different perspectives and to
                        explore data with new questions. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Enhanced Publications </head>
                    <p>The less advanced category is the so-called <soCalled>enhanced
                            publication.</soCalled> The term refers to the old genre of printed
                        papers, which, in digital format, have been enhanced with additional
                        material such as research data, models, illustrative images, or
                        post-publication comments and rankings, all rather loosely linked to the
                        publication through metadata. The data enhancements enable the replication
                        of research as well as secondary analysis of the underlying data sets.</p>
                    <p>Relating digital content resources that are distributed over different
                        collections (e.g. in literature studies and historic research) can greatly
                        enhance their value provided this is done in an interoperable
                        machine-readable way, which makes that they can be indexed by semantic
                        search engines. The <title rend="italic">Open Archives Initiative – Object
                            Reuse and Exchange</title> (OAI-ORE) has provided a standard for this
                        purpose <ptr target="#lagoze2007"/>. The Australian LORE (Literature Object
                        Re-use and Exchange) software is one of the tools supporting this standard.
                        It consists of a lightweight Firefox extension for creating, labeling and
                        visualizing typed relationships between individual objects, and relies on a
                        backend repository <ptr target="#gerber2009"/>. The ESCAPE editor in
                        combination with the InContext visualizer (both of Dutch origin) has a
                        similar functionality and also allows to create and to display a semantic
                        overlay in the form of an OAI-ORE based resource map, encoded in RDF <ptr target="#bentum2009"/>. There are more projects working into the same
                        direction using RDF or the OAI-ORE protocol more specifically, such as
                            Foresite<note>Forsite: <ref target="http://foresite.cheshire3.org/">http://foresite.cheshire3.org/</ref>. Date accessed: August 13,
                            2013.</note> and eChemistry.<note>eChemistry: <ref target="http://www.rsc.org/chemistryworld/News/2008/January/29010803.asp">http://www.rsc.org/chemistryworld/News/2008/January/29010803.asp</ref>.
                            Date accessed: August 13, 2013. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The advantage of such a package that includes the publication plus loosely
                        coupled addenda which are accessible through hyperlinks, is that the
                        creation is relatively easy, because it does not affect the published
                        document itself; a layer of metadata is sufficient. However, it has a low
                        degree of integration and, therefore, is not particularly comfortable. The
                        display of these extras is usually spread over different windows, each
                        operating in isolation. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Rich Internet Publications</head>
                    <p>The more integrated publication formats cannot be adequately described as
                        simply <soCalled>enhanced publications</soCalled>. We have argued elsewhere
                            <ptr target="#breure2011"/>, that the term <term>rich internet
                            publication</term> (RIP) is to be preferred for this more advanced form,
                        which consists of seamless combination of text, data and illustrations.
                        Usually it has a higher degree of interactivity by the use of slideshows,
                        image galleries, maps, and query interfaces. Integration concerns a variety
                        of aspects, such as internal linking between information objects and the
                        functional combination of user interface components on the presentation
                        level. </p>
                    <p>Elsevier’s <title rend="italic">Article of the Future</title> is the most
                        well-known example. In 2009 this publisher initiated this project to improve
                        the electronic communication of research. In the new layout the article is
                        divided into three panes, one for navigation, one for the core text and one
                        for supplementary and contextual information. Interactive tables, graphs and
                        other discipline specific tools have been brought into the text and make
                        that readers can drill down to underlying data <ptr target="#aalbersberg2012"/>. </p>
                    <p>Since December 2009 Portland Press has been using Utopia
                            Documents<note>Utopia website: <ref target="http://getutopia.com">http://getutopia.com</ref>. Date accessed: September 4, 2013.
                        </note> to enhance the content of their <title rend="italic">Biochemical
                            Journal</title>.<note>Biochemical Journal: <ref target="http://www.biochemj.org/">http://www.biochemj.org/</ref>.
                            Date accessed: September 4, 2013. </note> A Utopia document is an
                        enhanced PDF file for which a special reader has to be downloaded. It
                        connects the static content of scientific articles to up-to-date online
                        information and allows a great variety of annotations made by the author or
                        publication editor. Currently, the publisher’s version of this software is
                        only available to Portland, but it is promised to be in time available more
                        widely <ptr target="#pettifer2011"/>. <title rend="italic">BMC
                            Medicine</title>, the flagship medical journal of the BioMed Central
                        series, has chosen a similar technological direction by including 3D models
                        in the PDF, benefiting from Acrobat options to embed interactive objects in
                        a PDF document. Because in this case standard technology is used, the
                        document is mostly accessible through regular PDF readers <ptr target="#ziegler2011"/> (unfortunately, the iPad does not support these
                        advanced features).</p>
                    <p>The creation of RIPs has far-reaching consequences for the authoring and
                        publishing process. The production system must support the enhancements in
                        storage and layout and many journals have not (yet) chosen to move into this
                        direction; the regular PDF is the ubiquitous standard. This means that
                        authors will have no free choice regarding media rich publishing. The
                        selection of a journal will be based, rather, on more ponderous reasons like
                        ranking and readership than on this presentation aspect. A double track
                        solution is feasible by doing both, publishing the article in a highly
                        ranked journal to earn credits, and providing a text with supplementary
                        material through a private or institutional website to serve the community
                        of peers and to enhance visibility. One may consider this as an alternative
                        form of co-publishing, in which the efforts rather than the expenses are
                        shared — but with which technical means, and can it be done within a
                        reasonable amount of time? An ordinary HTML page is not a good solution,
                        precisely because of all the extra material. Think of a large set of photos,
                        an interactive map for display of research data or an interactive
                        spreadsheet. One needs special components to avoid a messy layout and to
                        provide a decent reading experience, which will require more technical
                        skills than we may expect from the average author.</p>
                    <p>An obvious channel for alternative communication is the research blog. In
                        general, bloggers do not see their blogs as appropriate outlets for original
                        research <ptr target="#puschmann2012"/>; <ptr target="#kjellberg2010"/>,
                        which is also confirmed by a look at blogs in humanities studies. Scientific
                        blogging is often motivated by the need of sharing knowledge with a wider
                        public than the community of experts, to express opinions and start
                        discussions. Moreover, in terms of layout the blog genre is not geared to
                        extensive scientific discourse. However, the blogging software can be used
                        for other purposes as well. The popular WordPress package, which is used on
                        many blog sites, is also the basis of PressBooks <note>PressBooks' website:
                                <ref target="http://pressbooks.com/">http://pressbooks.com/</ref>.
                            Date accessed: September 4, 2013. </note>, a commercial website, which
                        presents itself as the simple way of web book publishing with PDF as extra
                        output option. WordPress itself has also themes (i.e. layout templates)
                        suitable for scholarly publishing as well as special components for
                        multimedia <ptr target="#jankowski2009"/>; <ptr target="#tatum2011"/>.
                        Installation of the software does not require much technical knowledge.
                        Authoring can be done online, however, a drawback is that WordPress adds
                        additional codes to the HTML, which makes the source text less standard and
                        therefore more difficult to re-use. </p>
                    <p>A new platform with interesting architecture is Scalar <ptr target="#dietrich2012"/>
                  <note>Scalar: <ref target="http://scalar.usc.edu/scalar/">http://scalar.usc.edu/scalar/</ref>. date accessed: October 16,
                            2013. </note>, created by the Alliance for Networking Visual Culture and
                        is now available. It is a free, open source authoring and publishing
                        platform that is designed to write text online (or to copy and paste it from
                        an existing source). Scalar enables users to assemble media from multiple
                        sources and juxtapose them with their own writing in a variety of ways, with
                        minimal technical expertise required. Comments and annotations are also
                        supported. A user can easily switch between different views such as text
                        emphasis, media emphasis, metadata and various visualizations. Content
                        consists of pages and media, which can be related to each other in different
                        ways, which results in non-linear structures. Media can be imported from
                        online archives like Critical Commons, the Internet Archive, Flickr and
                        Vimeo. Scalar is a semantic web authoring tool that brings a balance between
                        standardization and structural flexibility to all kinds of material. Authors
                        familiar with WordPress will feel comfortable with the online authoring
                        process; an export option to other formats is not directly available, but
                        seems to be possible through the API <note>See <title rend="quotes">Working
                                with the API</title> under advanced topics in the User’s Guide: <ref target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/guide/working-with-the-api?path=advanced-topics">http://scalar.usc.edu/works/guide/working-with-the-api?path=advanced-topics</ref>.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>E-books</head>
                    <p>An offline alternative to the RIP is the modern e-book. In contrast to what
                        its name suggests an e-book does not need to be of the same substantial size
                        of a printed book because of the lack of overhead printing costs. The first
                        generation of e-books consisted mainly of texts with a few gray-scale
                        illustrations, and e-readers based on <soCalled>electronic paper</soCalled>
                        technology (e-ink) like Amazon’s Kindle could hardly display more, but this
                        is changing. Recently, e-books can be enriched roughly in the same way as
                        RIPs and e-reader software can be downloaded for all computers.</p>
                    <p>In fall 2011 Epub 3 was approved as recommendation<note>International Digital
                            Publishing Forum – Epub 3: <ref target="http://idpf.org/epub/30">http://idpf.org/epub/30</ref>. Date accessed: September 4, 2013.
                        </note>, which allows the embedding of audio and video together with some
                        scripting and makes interactivity possible. The great plus is that an Epub 3
                        document is a ZIP-file with only standard code inside: HTML5, CSS and
                        Javascript, which guarantees the reusability of the content. There are two
                        types of layout. Reflowable layout is default, which gives users a high
                        degree of control of the look and feel of the page; however, for the same
                        reason, it is more difficult for authors to make sure that multimedia appear
                        on the right position in the text. The alternative is fixed layout, which
                        sounds good, but is not yet very successfully implemented by reader
                        software. </p>
                    <p>Currently, the Epub 3 standard is not widely supported by publishers and
                        e-reader manufacturers, which makes that in practice one may come across
                        some annoying hitches. Apple offers extensive and good-looking support in
                        the form of its proprietary iBooks format. The text can be interspersed with
                        interactive images, image galleries, video and audio. Touch Press
                            <note>Touch Press: <ref target="http://www.touchpress.com">http://www.touchpress.com</ref>. Date accessed: September 4,
                            2013.</note> has already produced a set of impressive titles on popular
                        subjects such as the pyramids of Egypt in 3D, the work of Leonardo da Vinci
                        about human anatomy, and the march of the dinosaurs. Apple created a nice
                        authoring program, iBooks Author, which runs only on Apple devices, and the
                        same applies to the iBooks, which require an iPad. Conversion to PDF is
                        possible, but then all interactivity gets lost. Moreover, Apple requires
                        that iBooks files are only distributed through its own iBookstore unless the
                        work is free.<note>iBooks Author: Publishing and distribution FAQ: <ref target="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT5071">http://support.apple.com/kb/HT5071</ref>. Date accessed: September
                            4, 2013. </note> So, the highly proprietary nature of this channel may
                        be an impediment to scholarly publishing, which is increasingly marked by
                        openness. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Verdict: No Royal Highway</head>
                    <p>Conventional publishing is rather straightforward: there is a well-defined
                        path starting from a Word file or Lateχ document based on templates to an
                        HTML page and PDF. Enhanced publications add a linkage layer on top of this
                        existing system and require users to hop from one piece of content to
                        another. On the other hand, publishing an article in a digital format with
                        integrated research data, a set of photos, videos, interactive maps or
                        animations as with RIPs affects structure and layout of the publication
                        itself and requires new technology. Making a choice one has to avoid at
                        least four basic technical pitfalls: </p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <emph>Cluttering</emph> of the added content and thus creating an
                            aesthetically unacceptable document. We know that aesthetics do matter,
                            also because it influences credibility. Experiments have shown that
                            users can judge a web site's credibility in as little as 3.42 seconds
                            merely on the basis of its aesthetic appeal <ptr target="#alsudani2009"/>; <ptr target="#phillips2009"/>. This may be mitigated in a scientific
                            context, but the factor should not be neglected.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Information overload</emph>, which is closely related to the
                            previous point. The reader may not attach the same importance to the
                            extra information as the author did. Aside from the main line of
                            discourse the user should be given a choice with regard to content, e.g.
                            to view or to skip a chart, a model, a set of images or a video.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Format-device mismatch</emph>. Nowadays this easily happens with
                            the great variety of mobiles and diversity in screen resolutions. In the
                            good old days we were safe if our content stayed inside an area of
                            800x600 pixels. However, now we have got wide screens, tablets, iPad
                            minis, phablets, smartphones and more. Text should not <soCalled>fall
                                off</soCalled> the screen or be displayed with uncomfortably long
                            line length. The answer is responsive design, a relatively new
                            technology that allows a document to resize and to restructure depending
                            on the size of the screen on which it is being viewed, similar to the
                            reflowable layout of epub.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Proprietary solutions</emph>, because of a lack of openness (for
                            example for commercial reasons) or not adhering to standards. Creating a
                            scholarly publication requires a great deal of effort. If we can do it
                            once, in a standard format like HTML or XML, we can re-use it in its
                            entirety or parts of it, and automatically reformat it by means of XSLT.
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Authors are lucky when their publisher has well organized the rich
                        publication route as for example Elsevier did. This implies more than
                        refreshing the journal system and providing updated templates. Careful
                        instructions are needed how to submit multimedia material and, in addition,
                        Elsevier offers a paid illustration service. Overlooking the various
                        alternatives for self-publishing as discussed in the foregoing sections one
                        must conclude that each of them has certain snags; there is no royal
                        highway. Most authors will either need technical assistance or have to
                        accept compromises; new, user-friendly tools are badly needed to fill the
                        gap between the low end of WYSIWYG HTML editors and blog publishing on the
                        one hand, and less flexible and less open full-fledged commercial systems on
                        the other.</p>
                </div>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>2. Xpos’re as Cross-platform Solution</head>



                <div>
                    <head>Background</head>
                    <p>The Xpos’re project has its roots in handcrafted multimedia web applications
                        for research purposes, mainly made in Flash.<note>See examples: <ref target="http://xposre.nl/rips.html">http://xposre.nl/rips.html</ref>.
                        </note> Just before Flash was banished from the tablet platform a wish
                        arose to make this kind of application more generic and author-friendly,
                        which resulted in the Xpos’re suite. The software does not solve all
                        problems identified above, but avoids at least most of the pitfalls
                        mentioned. Due to its background in multimedia applications the Xpos’re
                        suite allows the creation of publications with a well-structured aesthetic
                        layout. With regard to information overload: the layout concept encourages
                        (but not enforces) a style of writing that divides the text into small
                        sections, presenting essentials first followed by more detailed evidence.
                        The variety of hardware platforms and screen resolutions is addressed
                        through different output options, both fixed and more reflowable HTML
                        formats. Input and output is based on standards, XML, HTML and cascading
                        style sheets, which precludes any lock-in. </p>
                    <p>The Xpos’re software is free and is distributed under a non-commercial
                        Creative Commons license and can be downloaded from <ref target="http://xposre.nl">http://xposre.nl</ref> which contains also a
                        few examples of real publications (note, that the illustrations in this
                        paper are based on a simple demo with brief pseudo-text kept short for the
                        sake of clarity).</p>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Flash Text Browser with Extensions</head>
                    <p>The main component of the Xpos’re package is a text browser, a Flash program,
                        which primarily renders the text as a set of slides (see Figure 1) and which
                        delegates the display of specific, mostly multimedia content to external
                        components, the so-called extensions, which are similar to plug-ins of a web
                        browser. These enhancements (in Flash or HTML-Javascript) may vary from
                        zoomable images, image galleries, interactive maps, and videos to
                        interactive data tables and statistical charts. The extensions are different
                        in size, are launched through special event-hyperlinks and are displayed on
                        top of the main text. The native Xpos’re Flash extensions can also interact
                        through this type of links with the main text, for example, changing the
                        slide displayed. In this way an image gallery can be used as a pictorial
                        index through goto-event links in the captions of the gallery images; by
                        clicking on the event-link a user can go to the slide where the image is
                        discussed (see Figure 2). Xpos’re has been designed to work together with
                        other web tools. Particularly the statistical market segment has companion
                        software, which is worth to be used and, depending on the application
                        interface, can also be used with Xpos’re as a less integrated extension.</p>
                    <figure>

                        <head>The Xpos’re text browser showing a slide with one text column and an
                            image list (Flash, CSS).</head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of the text browser with two columns</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>The text browser showing a slide with the image gallery
                            extension.</head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of the text browser showing the image gallery
                            extension</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In the basic display format the publication is a series of slides, each
                        having a fixed layout of 950 x 720 pixels, which fits most common screens in
                        landscape mode. It is not responsive, but there are options for more
                        flexible HTML output, which we shall discuss later. A slide should
                        correspond with a piece of text that is internally coherent, such as a
                        section or subsection of an article. It may contain the full text or a
                        summary, for example, if the Xpos’re publication is mainly intended to make
                        supplementary material available. For this purpose each slide can be linked
                        to the related page in the PDF file with the full text; then the linked page
                        is displayed by a button click. </p>
                    <p>A slide can contain one or two text columns and images. Images are displayed
                        as a list outside the text blocks, unless, like in HTML, defined through an
                            <code>img</code> tag and thus embedded in the text itself. The number of
                        images that fit on a slide depends on the size and orientation of the image
                        list, horizontal or vertical. How physical text layout affects reading from
                        screen is a thorny debate, which has produced a large number of
                        unfortunately inconclusive and slightly contradictive studies <ptr target="#nimwegen1999"/>; <ptr target="#dyson2004"/>; <ptr target="#santosa2011"/>. Conclusions have mostly favored short to medium
                        lines (about 60 characters per line), because longer lengths require greater
                        lateral eye movements, which makes reading more tiring <ptr target="#bernard2002"/>. The Xpos’re slide format allows text columns in
                        this range. </p>
                    <p>The limited space does not necessarily restrict the amount of information
                        that can be displayed. If a text is larger than the predefined column, it is
                        scrollable, but choosing continuation text may be more user-friendly. A
                        slide can have one continuation text of unlimited length, in the Flash
                        version displayed in a popup window and in the HTML slide version as a new
                        screen. This helps to present main things first. Usability research has
                        shown that users prefer brief information before reading a full text and
                        appreciate facilities for rapid browsing <ptr target="#dillon1989"/>.</p>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>HTML Output and the HTML Reader</head>
                    <p>Flash was kept because of its robustness and high quality of accurate graphic
                        rendering, which has proven to be consistent on different platforms over a
                        long period of time. It should be emphasized that no content is embedded in
                        the Flash file itself (which is still a common misunderstanding with regard
                        to Flash applications): at startup all text and images are preloaded from
                        the web server to guarantee good performance. </p>
                    <p>However, the user is in no way bound to Flash and can easily switch to HTML
                        output. The Flash text browser contains a code generator, which
                        automatically creates a look-alike HTML version of the Flash slides with
                        similar functionality to serve platforms where Flash is not supported (such
                        as the iPad). In the same way it can produce a plain HTML version with a
                        minimum of formatting suitable for printing, conversion to PDF and further
                        processing such as the creation of e-books through software as
                            Calibre.<note>Calibre: <ref target="http://calibre-ebook.com/">http://calibre-ebook.com/</ref>. Date accessed: September 4, 2013.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This flexible HTML document can also be manipulated and displayed by other
                        reader software. For example, the Xpos’re suite also comprises a highly
                        customizable HTML Reader, which displays this text in a three column
                        reflowable format (table of contents, main text and sidebar), similar to the
                        layout of most digital scientific journals. It has more features than the
                        automatically generated HTML slides and is particularly tablet friendly (see
                        Figure 3). An additional advantage of this reader is that it accepts also
                        other HTML texts (non-native XML) provided that basic formatting rules have
                        been followed.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The same text as in Figure 1 displayed in the Xpos’re HTML Reader
                            (HTML, Javascript, CSS). Notes and literature references are displayed
                            next to the text in the sidebar. It has other convenience features, e.g.
                            concept highlighting, navigation by images, look up of selected words on
                            the internet. </head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of the Xps're HTML Reader</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The cross-platform concept also applies to extensions. An important principle
                        in the Xpos’re architecture is <soCalled>gentle fallback</soCalled>, which
                        guarantees that the content of Flash extensions is still displayed in the
                        HTML slide version if Flash is not supported on a certain hardware platform.
                        Although the HTML version can handle Flash extensions, the user may select
                        the fallback option to let the web browser use the XHTML source directly
                        (which is sufficiently formatted) instead of the better looking Flash
                        rendering.</p>
                </div>
            </div>



            <div>
                <head>3. Authoring a Publication</head>
                <p>An Xpos’re publication consists of two main files: one containing the structured
                    publication text and one with metadata and instructions for the Xpos’re
                    software. A cascading style sheet (CSS) defines the layout in terms of colors,
                    font family and font size. XML has been chosen for the mark-up of the content.
                    The input must comply with an XML schema, which makes it easy to control and to
                    validate text entry. In many respects the Xpos’re XML vocabulary is close to
                    XHTML, particularly on the level of paragraph mark-up, but it contains non-HTML
                    instructions, among others, for the control of the extensions mentioned. </p>
                <dhq:example xml:id="figure4">
                    <head>Beginning of a slide containing a text column and two images. The template
                            <term>vright</term> defines a vertical image list on the right side. The
                        result is shown in Figure 1.</head>

                    <eg>
                        
  &lt;slide id=”intro” template=”vright”&gt;
      &lt;pdfPage&gt;1&lt;/pdfPage&gt;&lt;!--Related page in the PDF --&gt;
      &lt;title&gt;Lorem ipsum&lt;/title&gt;
                            
  &lt;visual&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;Tulip_field.jpg&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;!--Link to an Xpos’re extension, in this case the image viewer:  --&gt;
      &lt;onClick href=”event:add#ImageViewer.swf#Tulip_field.jpg” /&gt;
          &lt;cap&gt;Phasellus dictum congue orci. &lt;i&gt;(Click on image to enlarge)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/cap&gt;
  &lt;/visual&gt;
  &lt;visual&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;Red_tulips.jpg&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;cap&gt;Sodales nisl quis.&lt;/cap&gt;
  &lt;/visual&gt;
                            
  &lt;text1&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;Pharetra arcu mi&lt;/h2&gt;
      &lt;!-- Summary: --&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. 
          Morbi et risus quis turpis volutpat blandit quis non lacus. Donec consequat, odio non adipiscing
          bibendum, diam libero lacinia ipsum, in tempor sapien libero non ligula.&lt;/b&gt;
          &lt;!--Start of core text: --&gt; 
          &lt;p&gt;Phasellus dictum congue orci, nec scelerisque risus laoreet non. Duis eget
              orci ipsum, vitae sagittis nunc. Aliquam venenatis iaculis felis, sit amet
              bibendum libero eleifend a.&lt;/p&gt;
           Etc. </eg>
                </dhq:example>

                <p>The most direct form of authoring boils down to alternating between an XML editor
                    and the Xpos’re text browser, which shows immediately how the document rendered
                    looks. If the XML document is created on the basis of an existing publication,
                    text entry will be a matter of copy and paste. Other, more (semi‑) automated
                    workflows, which start for example from a Word text, are feasible as well. A
                    Word document saved as a (filtered) HTML text can be further cleaned by
                    conversion tools <note>For example the well-known program Tidy (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/tidy/">http://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/tidy/</ref>) or an online tool as Word
                        to Clean HTML: <ref target="http://word2cleanhtml.com/">http://word2cleanhtml.com/</ref>. Date accessed: September 4, 2013.
                    </note> and worked up to XML. This may be a more convenient way if an existing
                    text contains much mark-up (bold, italic et cetera) that is to be preserved.
                    This preprocessing stage could be more automated. A dedicated, task-oriented XML
                    editor with a word processor-like view such as XMLmind <note>XMLmind: <ref target="http://www.xmlmind.com">http://www.xmlmind.com</ref>. Date
                        accessed: September 4, 2013.</note> could simplify the authoring and
                    tweaking for those authors who are less familiar with the nuts and bolts of
                    XML.</p>
                <p>The layout of each slide can fully meet the requirements of the particular
                    content. The author can choose on which level he defines the position and size
                    of the text and images. By default layout is controlled through user-defined
                    templates. The advantage of this template mechanism is that it allows global
                    changes for the entire text at once; modifying a template affects all the slides
                    that use it. In addition, fixed layout is not hard coded in the text itself and
                    may be even completely disregarded as, for example, with the reflowable HTML
                    output in the HTML reader. </p>
                <dhq:example>
                    <head>Example of a template. This template defines the layout for a slide with a
                        vertical list of images on the left, and two text blocks (text1 and text2)
                        on the right. </head>
                    <eg>
                        
  &lt;template id="vleft"&gt;
  &lt;text1 x="370" y="110" width="500" height="485"&gt;Maintext&lt;/text1&gt;
  &lt;text2 x="370" y="595" width="500" height="100"&gt;Used as secondary text or text block&lt;/text2&gt;
  &lt;visuals x="15" y="115" size="270" orientation="vertical"&gt;Vertical image list on the left side 
      with 'width' equal to 'size'&lt;/visual&gt;
  &lt;/template&gt;
                          
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example>
                <p>If required, the author can also locally specify precise size and position of
                    layout elements in the slide itself. A local specification precedes over the
                    template in use, in the same way as local style definitions have priority of a
                    linked style sheet in an HTML document. In this way images can also be
                        <soCalled>pulled out of the list</soCalled> and placed anywhere on the
                    slide. For this purpose the text reader contains a so-called measuring tool (see
                    Figure 4), a transparent rectangle which can be drawn and resized by mouse and
                    arrow keys to make positioning and resizing of text and images easy. Each time
                    when the rectangle changes, its x, y, width and height are displayed at the
                    bottom of the slide in a format that can be copied and directly pasted into the
                    XML text. Although simple, this facility proves to be an effective compensation
                    for the fact that the text editing is not WYSIWYG.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The measuring tool (green rectangle), with, at the bottom of the screen,
                        position and size in a format which can be directly copied and pasted into
                        the XML text.</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Slide text may contain two kinds of hyperlinks: (1) regular HTML-hyperlinks and
                    (2) internal event-links, which represent instructions for the text browser.
                    Documents linked to the publication text through the former type of links are
                    displayed in a target window (just like in HTML), but Xpos’re can also show them
                    as an overlay on a transparent background on top of the slide, which creates a
                    sense of unity in the user interface. The second type of link is used, among
                    others, for navigation: <code>&lt;a href="event:goto#intro"&gt;Lorem
                            ipsum&lt;/a&gt;</code> will display the slide with the id-attribute having
                    the value <q>intro</q>. Another use is calling an extension. For example, the
                    image viewer can be activated to show a larger, zoomable version of a picture by
                    adding the tag: <code>&lt;a
                            href="event:add#ImageViewer.swf#Tulip_field.jpg"</code>. Extensions linked through event links appear as pop-ups in the
                    Flash text browser, and as overlays in the HTML look-alike. </p>
                <p>When ready, the text with all depending files is copied to a webserver, which
                    completes the publishing process. There is no content management system or other
                    back-end required. When published, this RIP can be aggregated with other content
                    (e.g. related publications or data sets) into an enhanced publication. Xpos're
                    also supports the generation of an OAI-ORE resource map (see section 1.2), which
                    is automatically generated by means of an XSLT file, to be downloaded from the
                    Xpos're website.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Summary of the Xpos’re publication model. Symbols on the connecting lines:
                            <emph>diamond</emph>: composition; cardinality: <emph>circle</emph>:
                        zero; <emph>vertical bar</emph>: one; <emph>crow foot</emph>: many.</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>4. Pilots</head>
                <p>We did some small scale testing of the software in research projects. The
                    development of Xpos’re started as part of a larger collaboration project within
                    the Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences and got national attention in
                    the context of enhanced publications. The combination of both attracted some
                    volunteers, who wanted either to add an Xpos’re publication to an already
                    published paper or to use the package for a new, born-digital product. This
                    resulted in four <soCalled>showcases</soCalled> about a diversity of subjects:
                    gallows in late medieval Frisia, a textual analysis of a Dutch novel, a
                    prototype for a Berber dictionary, and a rather long text (of the size of a
                    book) about parks and country houses in the Netherlands (the products and more
                    details are on Xpos’re website <note>Xpos’re – Rich Internet Publications: <ref target="http://xposre.nl/rips.html">http://xposre.nl/rips.html</ref>.
                    </note>). In the first two cases the technical work was done by the developer of
                    Xpos’re; the Berber dictionary was implemented by a student in collaboration
                    with a computer scientist, and text about parks was converted to Xpos’re source
                    text by technical personnel of a university library, who had followed a short
                    XML course and got a workshop of two half days about Xpos’re. </p>
                <p>In all four cases the content production process went smoothly. The Berber
                    dictionary, however, used a special text font, which required recompilation of
                    the Flash text browser. During the encoding of the book about parks we offered
                    some support for minor questions about image processing and how to create the
                    best layout. Using Xpos’re for such a long text raised questions about search
                    facilities, which are currently lacking in the text browser, because it was
                    designed with texts of article size in mind. Furthermore, we could observe a
                    tendency to stick to the basics and that more advanced features, such as the
                    plugins, were not easily used.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Conclusions</head>
                <p>Scholarly communication is in a process of transition and has not yet arrived at
                    a steady state. Both users and publishers realize that the traditional genre of
                    printed papers, even in digital form, does not suffice any longer and feel the
                    need to publish supplements to the text. This has resulted in quite different
                    digital solutions, varying from a multimedia section on a journal web site to
                    enhanced PDF documents and semantic aggregations of articles plus other
                    resources, but for most authors the way is not yet paved. Given the current
                    state of scholarly publication, rich media publishing entails a set of
                    difficulties and inconveniences that have to be dealt with:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>
                        <emph>Lack of integration:</emph> Given the current state of scientific
                        publishing, multimedia material is often only loosely connected with the
                        publication itself. This will not be experienced as a problem by all authors
                        and readers, but it is to be considered as an issue against the background
                        of the rapidly increasing influence of visual and audio content in our
                        culture. The recent upswing of multimedia journalism is a good example of
                        this tendency. We are now easily able to show what for centuries could only
                        be described, but in practice there are still hurdles, particularly in the
                        publishing infrastructure itself. </item>
                    <item>
                        <emph>Information overload: </emph>More and diverse content requires
                        adequate composition skills in combination with optional selection by the
                        user. Next to the information push of the publication itself we should leave
                        room for information pull: let readers select the details they like, just as
                        we do with an extensive footnote apparatus in printed publications. This
                        requires a slightly different style of writing and technical support in the
                        publication format.</item>
                    <item>
                        <emph>High quality layout:</emph> The variety of media tends to make layout
                        more complex. Unless supported by a user-friendly authoring system or the
                        publisher’s design department, this may demand too much from the average
                        author.</item>
                    <item>
                        <emph>Format-device mismatch</emph>: A uniform and consistent layout across
                        different devices, which have a great variety of screen resolutions and
                        idiosyncratic browser behavior, is an enormous challenge. So far only PDF
                        publications have been really successful on this point. Flash was a second
                        winner, but lost the battle on the mobile platform.</item>
                    <item>
                        <emph>Proprietary solutions</emph>: The situation is certainly not hopeless;
                        however, some attractive solutions tend to be proprietary by not fully
                        adhering to standards and / or by vendor lock-in. </item>
                    <item>
                        <emph>Lack of skills</emph>: Even if the technology in this field becomes
                        more user-friendly, authors should have more global technical knowledge and
                        basic skills to create a multimedia publication or to guide and to manage
                        its production by assistants. </item>
                </list>
                <p>The architectural concept of software has usually a much longer life than the
                    implementation, which is highly sensitive to changes in technology and market
                    positions. We all know spreadsheets, but only a few of us will remember Lotus
                    1-2-3, a highly popular spreadsheet and <soCalled>killer application</soCalled>
                    in the mid-1980s. Although the few pilots we did <note>See <ref target="http://xposre.nl/rips.html">http://xposre.nl/rips.html</ref>.
                    </note> showed that that the software works well without hitches, the Xpos’re
                    tools may be best evaluated on basis of the architectural concept. </p>
                <p>A major goal has been a good-looking layout that integrates different types of
                    content, much better than with the <soCalled>content package</soCalled> of the
                    enhanced publication. Aesthetically, the Flash version is often found most
                    attractive, also because the high graphic quality allows a pleasant information
                    density in a relative small screen space. In the fixed layout slides, text and
                    images can be precisely positioned. Other media types like interactive maps,
                    spreadsheets and video are so different in size that the same juxtaposition is
                    not possible as a generic solution. Extensions have been used instead, which are
                    displayed on top of the text and keep the context visible as much as possible.
                    The template mechanism encourages the predefinition of a layout model, which can
                    be both globally changed and locally overridden. </p>
                <p>Information overload is discouraged by a combination of several features, which
                    leads to dividing the content into layers. The first layer is the text on the
                    slide, the next one the continuation text, and, if required, a third layer in
                    the form of a PDF page linked to the slide. In the HTML Reader the sidebar can
                    be used for digressions and short introductions of related subjects and videos
                    that do not fit in the main text. </p>
                <p>The variety of devices and screen resolutions has been addressed to a certain
                    extent by a fixed layout that fits normal tablets and larger screens, and by the
                    flexible layout of the HTML Reader. A future version should be more responsive,
                    but downsizing for lower resolutions has its limits; hotspots as on an
                    interactive map or timeline require a minimum size and spacing on touch
                    devices.</p>
                <p>The elements of the Xpos’re XML vocabulary are not standard, but the large
                    overlap with HTML for sentence and paragraph mark-up and the ease of
                    transformation of XML content make reuse relatively simple. A drawback is the
                    basic knowledge of HTML, XML and CSS required for authoring. This may be
                    inhibiting for scholars who want to stay far away from web technology; they will
                    need some technical assistance. The barrier is not as serious as it may appear.
                    In one of our pilots a large publication was rather easily encoded in XML by two
                    persons who had only attended a short basic XML workshop and got a one-day
                    instruction in Xpos’re software.</p>
                <p>The Xpos’re architectural concept can be positioned between RIPs on basis content
                    management systems as WordPress and modern e-books. Although quite different in
                    many respects, all three of them are HTML-based and can be used to create
                    publications with enhanced reading experience. Unlike WordPress Xpos’re is a
                    completely client-side solution. The optional scripting in Epub 3 makes these
                    e-books in principle more versatile and powerful (and also more complex!) than
                    Xpos’re publications with extensions only. With regard to flexibility Xpos’re
                    stands out by an easily reusable source text and a variety of output options.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alsudani2009" label="Alsudani 2009" key="alsudani2009"> Alsudani, F. and Casey, M. <title rend="quotes">The effect of aesthetics on web credibility</title>: <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 23rd British HCI Group Annual Conference on
                        People and Computers: Celebrating People and Technology</title> (BCS-HCI
                    '09). British Computer Society, Swinton, UK: 512-519 (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aalbersberg2012"
                  label="Aalbersberg 2012"
                  key="aalbersberg2012"> Aalbersberg, IJ. J.,
                    Heeman, F., Koers, H. and Zudilova-Seinstra, E. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier’s
                        Article of the Future: enhancing the user experience and integrating data
                        through applications</title>, <title rend="italic">Insights</title>, 25:1
                    (2012): 33–43, doi: 10.1629/2048-7754.25.1.33.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bentum2009" label="Bentum2009" key="bentum2009"> Bentum, M. van, Hogenaar, A. and
                    Vierkant, D. <title rend="quotes">Enhanced Scientific Communication by
                        Aggregated Publications Environments (ESCAPE)</title>, <title rend="italic">ELPUB 2009</title>, North America, April 2009. Available at: <ref target="http://conferences.aepic.it/index.php/elpub/elpub2009/paper/view/108/48">http://conferences.aepic.it/index.php/elpub/elpub2009/paper/view/108/48</ref>.
                    Date accessed: August 30, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bernard2002" label="Bernard 2002" key="bernard2002"> Bernard, M., Fernandez, M. and
                    Hull, S. <title rend="quotes">The Effects of Line Length on Children and Adults'
                        Online Reading Performance</title>, <title rend="italic"> Usability
                        News</title>, 4:2 (2002). Available at: <ref target="http://usabilitynews.org/the-effects-of-line-length-on-children-and-adults-online-reading-performance/">http://usabilitynews.org/the-effects-of-line-length-on-children-and-adults-online-reading-performance/</ref>.
                    Date accessed: August 30, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman2007" label="Borgman 2007" key="borgman2007"> Borgman, C. L. <title rend="italic">Scholarship in the Digital Age: Information, Infrastructure, and the
                        Internet</title>. Cambridge (MA.): MIT Press (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="breure2011" label="Breure 2011" key="breure2011"> Breure, L., Voorbij, H. and
                    Hoogerwerf, M. <title rend="quotes">Rich Internet Publications: <q>Show What You
                            Tell</q>
               </title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Information</title>, North America, 12:1 (2011). Available at: <ref target="http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/view/1606/1738">http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/view/1606/1738</ref>. Date accessed:
                    April 26, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dietrich2012" label="Dietrich 2012" key="dietrich2012"> Dietrich, C. and Sayers, J.
                        <title rend="quotes">After the Document Model for Scholarly Communication:
                        Some Considerations for Authoring with Rich Media</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Studies / Le champs numériqe</title>, 3:2
                    (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dillon1989" label="Dillon 1989" key="dillon1989"> Dillon, A., Richardson, J. and
                    McKnight, C. <title rend="quotes">The Human factors of journal usage and the
                        design of electronic text</title>, <title rend="italic">Interacting with
                        Computers</title> 1:2 (1989): 183-189.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dyson2004" label="Dyson 2004" key="dyson2004"> Dyson, M. C. <title rend="quotes">How
                        physical text layout affects reading from screen</title>, <title rend="italic">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</title>, 23:6 (2004):
                    377-393. Available at: <ref target="http://images3.wikia.nocookie.net/__cb20060729105544/psychology/images/e/eb/Dyson,_M_C_%282004%29.pdf">http://images3.wikia.nocookie.net/__cb20060729105544/psychology/images/e/eb/Dyson,_M_C_%282004%29.pdf</ref>.
                    Date accessed: August 30, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="force11" label="Force 11" key="force11">Bourne, P.E., Clark, T., Dale, R., Waard, A.
                    de, Herman, I., Hovy, E.H. and Shotton, D. (Eds.) <title rend="italic">Force11
                        White Paper: Improving The Future of Research Communications and
                        e-Scholarship.</title> Available at: <ref target="http://force11.org/sites/default/files/book_attachments/Force11Manifesto20120219.pdf">http://force11.org/sites/default/files/book_attachments/Force11Manifesto20120219.pdf</ref>.
                    Date accessed: January 21, 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gerber2009" label="Gerber 2009" key="gerber2009"> Gerber, A. and Hunter, J. <title rend="quotes">A Compound Object Authoring and Publishing Tool for Literary
                        Scholars Based on the IFLA-FRBR Model</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                        International Journal of Digital Curation</title> 4:2 (2009): 28-42.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/article/view/116/119">http://www.ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/article/view/116/119</ref>. Date
                    accessed: August 30, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hunter2007" label="Hunter 2007" key="hunter2007"> Hunter, J. and Cheung, K. <title rend="quotes">Provenance Explorer – a graphical interface for constructing
                        scientific publication packages from provenance trails</title>,<title rend="italic"> International Journal on Digital Libraries </title>7:1-2
                    (2007): 99-107. Available at: <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00799-007-0018-5">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00799-007-0018-5</ref>. Date accessed: August
                    30, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jankowski2009" label="Jankowski 2009" key="jankowski2009"> Jankowski, N. (Ed.) <title rend="italic">e-Research: Transformation in Scholarly Practice.
                        Routledge</title> (2009). Accompanying website: <ref target="http://scholarly-transformations.virtualknowledgestudio.nl/">http://scholarly-transformations.virtualknowledgestudio.nl/</ref>. Date
                    accessed: October 15, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kjellberg2010" label="Kjellberg 2010" key="kjellberg2010"> Kjellberg, S. <title rend="quotes">I am a blogging researcher: Motivations for blogging in a
                        scholarly context</title>, <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 15:8
                    (2010) August 2. Available at: <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580">http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580</ref>. Date
                    accessed: August 12, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lagoze2007" label="Lagoze 2007" key="lagoze2007"> Lagoze, C. and Sompel, H. van de
                        <title rend="quotes">Compound information objects: The OAI-ORE
                        perspective</title>. <title rend="italic">Open Archives Initiative – Object
                        Reuse and Exchange.</title> Available at: <ref target="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/documents/CompoundObjects-200705.html">http://www.openarchives.org/ore/documents/CompoundObjects-200705.html</ref>.
                    Date accessed: August 30, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nimwegen1999" label="Nimwegen 1999" key="nimwegen1999">Nimwegen, C. van, Pouw, M. and
                    Oostendorp, H. van <title rend="quotes">The influence of structure and
                        reading-manipulation on usability of hypertexts</title>, <title rend="italic">Interacting with Computers</title> 12 (1999): 7–21.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pettifer2011" label="Pettifer 2011" key="pettifer2011"> Pettifer, S., McDermott, P.,
                    Marsh, J., Thorne, D., Villeger, A. and Attwood, T.K. <title rend="quotes">Ceci
                        n’est pas un hamburger: modelling and representing the scholarly
                        article</title>, <title rend="italic">Learned Publishing</title>, 24
                    (2011):207–220. Available at: <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1087/20110309">http://dx.doi.org/10.1087/20110309</ref>. Date accessed: January 21, 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2009" label="Phillips 2009" key="phillips2009">Phillips, C. and Chaparro, B. S.
                        <title rend="quotes">Visual Appeal vs. Usability: Which One Influences User
                        Perceptions of a Website More?</title> October, 15, 2009. <title rend="italic">Software Usability Research Laboratory</title>, Wichita State
                    University. Available at: <ref target="http://usabilitynews.org/visual-appeal-vs-usability-which-one-influences-user-perceptions-of-a-website-more/">http://usabilitynews.org/visual-appeal-vs-usability-which-one-influences-user-perceptions-of-a-website-more/</ref>.
                    Date accessed: August 13, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="puschmann2012" label="Puschmann 2012" key="puschmann2012"> Puschmann, C. and Mahrt, M.
                        <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Blogging: A New Form of Publishing or Science
                        Journalism 2.0?</title> In A. Tokar et al. (Eds.) <title rend="italic">Science and the Internet</title>, Düsseldorf (2012): 171-181.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="santosa2011" label="Santosa 2011" key="santosa2011">Santosa, P. I. <title rend="quotes">User’s Preference of Web Page Length</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Research and Reviews in Computer Science (IJRRCS)
                    </title>2:1 (2011): 180-185.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tatum2011" label="Tatum 2011" key="tatum2011"> Tatum, C. <title rend="quotes">Augmenting WordPress for Enhanced Publication</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship</title>, 10 June 2011. Available at: <ref target="http://digital-scholarship.ehumanities.nl/epubs/augmenting-wordpress-for-enhanced-publication/">http://digital-scholarship.ehumanities.nl/epubs/augmenting-wordpress-for-enhanced-publication/</ref>.
                    Date accessed: October 15, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wouters2012" label="Wouters 2012" key="wouters2012"> Wouters, P., Beaulieu, A.,
                    Scharnhorst, A. and Wyatt, S. (Eds.) <title rend="italic">Virtual Knowledge:
                        Experimenting in the Humanities and the Social Sciences</title>. MIT Press
                    (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ziegler2011" label="Ziegler 2011" key="ziegler2011">Ziegler, A. et al. <title rend="quotes">Effectively incorporating selected multimedia content into
                        medical publications</title>”, <title rend="italic">BMC Medicine</title>
                    9:17 (2011). Available at: <ref target="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/9/17">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/9/17</ref>. Date accessed: August
                    30, 2013.</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
