<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Pertinent Discussions Toward Modeling the <emph>Social</emph>
               Edition: Annotated Bibliographies</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Ray <dhq:family>Siemens</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>siemens@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ray Siemens (<ref target="http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/">http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/</ref>) is Canada Research Chair in Humanities
                     Computing and Distinguished Professor in the Faculty of Humanities at the
                     University of Victoria, in English and Computer Science. He is founding editor
                     of the electronic scholarly journal Early Modern Literary Studies and his
                     publications include, among others, Blackwell's Companion to Digital Humanities
                     (with Schreibman and Unsworth), Blackwell's Companion to Digital Literary
                     Studies (with Schreibman) and Mind Technologies: Humanities Computing and the
                     Canadian Academic Community (with Moorman). He directs the Digital Humanities
                     Summer Institute and Vice President of the Canadian Association of Humanities
                     and Social Sciences, and recently served as Chair of the international Alliance
                     of Digital Humanities Organisations’ Steering Committee.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Meagan <dhq:family>Timney</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mbtimney@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Meagan Timney is an information architect and user experience designer in San
                     Francisco, CA. Previously, she was a Postdoctoral Fellow and Assistant
                     Professor for the SSHRC MCRI-funded Editing Modernism in Canada Project and the
                     Electronic Textual Cultures Laboratory at the University of Victoria.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Cara <dhq:family>Leitch</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cmleitch@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cara Leitch is a PhD candidate in English at the University of Victoria and a
                     Research Assistant at the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Corina <dhq:family>Koolen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>c.w.koolen@hum.leidenuniv.nl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Corina Koolen is lecturer at the Book and Digital Media studies programme of
                     Leiden University and a PhD candidate at the Institute for Logic, Language and
                     Computation (University of Amsterdam).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Alex <dhq:family>Garnett</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>axfelix@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Alex Garnett is a Data Curation and Digital Preservation specialist at Simon
                     Fraser University, and a Ph.D. Student in Information Science at the Universty
                     of British Columbia. He has experience loving and munging data big and small
                     (in the private and public sector, respectively), and has particular interests
                     in the fields of natural language parsing and network analysis.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000111</idno>
            <idno type="volume">006</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2012-10-25">25 October 2012</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>scholarly editing</item>
                  <item>editorial theory</item>
                  <item>social networking</item>
                  <item>social media</item>
                  <item>networks</item>
                  <item>community</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2012-07-11" who="MCC">Encoded file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>The two annotated bibliographies present in this publication document and feature
               pertinent discussions toward the activity of modeling the social edition, first
               exploring reading devices, tools and social media issues and, second, social
               networking tools for professional readers in the Humanities. In this work, which is
               published conjointly with the LLC piece <title rend="quotes">
                  <ref target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/content/27/4/445.full">Toward Modeling
                     the Social Edition: An Approach to Understanding the Electronic Scholarly
                     Edition in the Context of New and Emerging Social Media,</ref>
               </title> we consider a typology of electronic scholarly editions adjacent to
               activities common to humanities scholars who engage texts as expert readers, noting
               therein that many methods of engagement both reflect the interrelated nature of
               long-standing professional reading strategies and are social in nature; extending
               this framework, the next steps in the scholarly edition’s development in its
               incorporation of social media functionality reflect the importance of traditional
               humanistic activities and workflows, and include collaboration, incorporating
               contributions by its readers and re-visioning the role of the editor away from that
               of ultimate authority and more toward that of facilitator of reader involvement. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Web 2.0 meets the scholarly edition</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Pertinent Discussions Toward Modeling the <emph>Social</emph> Edition: Annotated
            Bibliographies</head>
         <div>
            <head>1. Extending Electronic Editorial Traditions</head>
            <p>In the very early days of the world wide web, but well into a period in which our
               community understood the positive and transformative impact that computational
               technique has had on scholarly editing, we were reminded that literary studies are,
               and always have been, focused on engagement with texts regardless of interpretive
               theoretical predisposition. In digital literary studies, that textual focus manifests
               in a number of theories about the nature of the text in general and the electronic
               scholarly edition in particular, and has developed to the point that we can begin to
               construct, in a relatively straightforward manner, a basic typology of electronic
               scholarly editions via the approach each type takes in handling and engaging with its
               textual materials: from edited electronic text plus analytical tools for its readers
               (dynamic text), to text plus a static set of additional supporting materials in
               digital form for reader navigation and subsequent analysis (hypertextual edition), to
               text augmented by both dynamic analytical means and hypertextually-linked access to
               fixed resources plus automated means of discovering and interrelating external
               resources (dynamic edition). Such a typology, reductive as it may be, allows us to
               look forward – as many leaders in our field have encouraged us to do, variously – to
               what lies ahead in our treatment of the texts, and the textual editions, that sit at
               the core of our contemplation in literary studies and similar disciplines.</p>
            <p>Well into what is often called the new age of the internet – becoming immersed as we
               are in a generation of online tools facilitating collaboration, information sharing,
               and interoperability; becoming immersed as we are by social media interaction on the
               web – it is worth noting that the types of electronic scholarly editions we see
               prominently today were largely developed before the ubiquity of the web that we now
               enjoy, and do not accurately reflect the full range of useful possibilities present
               for academic engagement and interaction around the textual materials that are our
               focus. While the electronic medium is most certainly a productive space in which to
               present and analyse editions, it is increasingly difficult to ignore the influence of
               new and emerging possibilities for the electronic scholarly edition in the current
               phase in the social formation of the web. As such, our understanding of the
               electronic scholarly edition in its current form requires reconsideration in light of
               the collaborative potential of already extant and newly-emerging digital
               technologies; put another way, we need to extend our understanding of the scholarly
               edition in light of new models of edition production that embrace social networking
               and its commensurate tools. Toward understanding the scholarly edition in the context
               of new and emerging social media, our work – which comprises the article <title rend="quotes">Toward Modeling the Social Edition: An Approach to Understanding the
                  Electronic Scholarly Edition in the Context of New and Emerging Social
                  Media</title> (conjointly published in <title rend="italic">LLC</title>) and these
               bibliographies – offer an early engagement of pertinent issues and, ultimately, a
               utility-based consideration in an academic context of the toolkit that allows us to
               consider the social edition as an extension of the traditions in which it is situated
               and which it has the potential to inform productively.</p>
            <p>In this work, we consider a typology of electronic scholarly editions adjacent to
               activities common to humanities scholars who engage texts as expert readers, noting
               therein that many methods of engagement both reflect the interrelated nature of
               long-standing professional reading strategies and are social in nature; extending
               this framework, the next steps in the scholarly edition’s development in its
               incorporation of social media functionality reflect the importance of traditional
               humanistic activities and workflows, and include collaboration, incorporating
               contributions by its readers and re-visioning the role of the editor away from that
               of ultimate authority and more toward that of facilitator of reader involvement. The
               two annotated bibliographies present in this publication work to document and feature
               pertinent discussions toward the activity of modeling the <emph>social</emph>
               edition, first exploring reading devices, tools and social media issues and, second,
               social networking tools for professional readers in the Humanities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Reading Devices, Tools, and Social Media Issues of Pertinence to the
               Development of the Scholarly Edition</head>
            <p>A selected, annotated bibliography carried out by Corina Koolen and Alex Garnett for
               the ETCL’s work independently and with INKE and PKP [-2011].</p>
            <div>
               <head>2.1. Scholarly Use of Social Media by Academics</head>
               <p>This survey supports those interested in exploring the development of
                  collaborative work in academics, leading up to and including the use of the
                  Internet and Social Media (SM). From a situation where the Internet had just
                  become open to the mainstream public, up until now, we have seen great changes in
                  the possibilities and ways of thinking that concern collaborative academic work.
                  In this list, the focus shifts from collaborative work mainly to support student
                  learning, to general collaborative work. This is perhaps logical, as collaboration
                  on a greater scale, including sharing of information online – as opposed to
                  in-university collaboration – has only begun to materialize fairly recently. The
                  materials will reflect the relative novelty of the application in academia and
                  offer a wide range of topics that can be explored further.</p>

               <p>From two sections that provide a base in the history of collaborative reading,
                  current practices are presented: reflecting on how often and in which fashion
                  Social Media are currently used and consecutively providing a number of
                  small-scale experiments and recommendations to engage more widespread use.
                  Referencing and soft peer-review are also included as these are important issues
                  in the changing world of academic scholarship because of the influence of Web 2.0. </p>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.1 Digital Annotation Before Web 2.0</head>
                  <p>Prior to the advent of online Social Media, several attempts have been made to
                     offer students, teachers and researchers digital environments to facilitate the
                     research workflow. These three – mostly theoretical – articles have been
                     influential in academic research on digital (shared) annotation. </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Ovsiannikov, Ilia A., Michael A. Arbib, and Thomas H. Mcneill.
                              (1999). <title rend="quotes">Annotation Technology</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of Human-Computer
                                 Studies</title> 50.4: 329-362.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>In this article, the authors first give an overview of the field of
                           annotation systems, starting with offline software such as MS Word. It
                           gives insight in a wide variety of annotation tools with different
                           underlying principles, most of which are now obsolete. A number of these
                           systems were meant for online use, and some of the systems described show
                           how the hyperlink was still a point of focus in academic research. The
                           authors then report a qualitative survey on paper annotation, one of the
                           findings of which is that scholars primarily highlight and write in
                           margins (as opposed to writing on top of the text or between the lines
                           for instance); another result was that reasons for annotation are to
                           remember, to think, to clarify and to share. Sharing is seen as least
                           important by the authors and is of secondary importance to their
                           research, as the authors claim is not typical of the academic environment
                           to do so and more of interest for business purposes. The authors suggest
                           a taxonomy which classifies annotations with respect to their content,
                           form and functionality. Consecutively, based on this taxonomy Annotation
                           Technology (AT) is developed, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ovsiannikov1999">a set of
                              recommendations for software design</quote>
                           <ptr target="#ovsiannikov1999" loc="340"/></cit>. Interesting features are:
                           non-local referencing, where annotations on a similar topic across
                           documents is recognized; a tight integration of note-taking and reader
                           ergonomics which includes a <term>non-menu approach</term>; the
                           importance of linking, which includes the use of URLs to point to
                           specific notes; the separate storage of annotations in a database — or
                           several databases, so the reader is able to choose which ones to publish;
                           intelligent automated search; format-independent anchors so readers can
                           annotate any type of document. The authors see automated annotation
                           search as the greatest benefit over paper annotation. In the last
                           section, the authors present Annotator, a tool built on AT, which is
                           described in detail. Further research is said to be directed at
                           annotation-driven search.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Marshall, Catherine C. <title rend="quotes">Annotation: From Paper
                                 Books to the Digital Library.</title> (1997). <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second ACM International Conference on Digital
                                 Libraries</title>. Philadelphia, PA: ACM. pp 131-40. Print. <ref target="http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/~marshall/dl97.pdf">http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/~marshall/dl97.pdf</ref> (accessed on
                              July 14, 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>An influential study on the annotation behavior of college students in
                           their (paper) university textbooks. The author studied used textbooks
                           from a campus bookstore, with as many samples of the same edition of a
                           textbook as possible. Student selection criteria concerning the
                           annotations as they bought used textbooks were also taken into account.
                           Annotations are generally seen as private, whereas in this case students
                           would sometimes select the books on the quality of the annotations. The
                           annotations in the selected books were then classified by form and
                           function. The author classifies a total of six functions, among which
                           aids to memory and records of interpretative activity. In the final
                           section implications for annotations in the digital library are
                           discussed, where the author notes that in the design of new facilities,
                           four conditions should be supported: annotation <emph>in</emph> the text,
                           but distinguishable from the original text; non-interpretive markings;
                           fluidity of form (freeform type of annotation) and informal codings
                           (being able to switch between colors or implement systems). </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Wolfe, Joanna. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Annotation
                                 Technologies: A Software and Research Review</title>. <title rend="italic">Computers and Compositions</title> 19.4:
                              471-97.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article is focused on annotation to aid student learning. In the
                           first section, the author provides a description of the use of annotation
                           in medieval manuscript culture, explaining how digital annotation can
                           provide these same functions and more. The goal of the article is to
                           provide a review of current tooling, but to prevent the information of
                           becoming outdated too soon, the author has described different groups of
                           annotation tools, discerning them through context: annotations readers
                           make to themselves; annotations readers make and are meant to be shared
                           with the author; annotations readers make and are meant to be shared with
                           other readers; annotations from the author, intended for readers. This
                           division is perhaps no longer as relevant as the social web has rendered
                           the distinction between these roles less important, but it is
                           nevertheless an interesting starting point to consider the different
                           functionalities tools provide. The author then describes seven factors in
                           which tools can vary, including input, anchor, storage and searching and
                           filtering. The four types of context are then analyzed, providing first
                           possible strategies of form and function by reviewing literature on the
                           topic, followed by examples of annotation tools. The author has included
                           a wide variety of tools. Examples in the first group are a dedicated
                           reader, XLibris (<ref target="http://www.fxpal.com/?p=xlibris">http://www.fxpal.com/?p=xlibris</ref>), that has flexible annotation
                           options, including linking of a single annotation to several text
                           fragments and Animal Landlord, a tool for classroom video annotation. In
                           the second group, MS Word 2000 and iMarkup are discussed. In the final
                           section, the author discusses difficulties for research groups and
                           companies in developing and maintaining their tools. An interesting
                           example is mentioned, ThirdVoice (1999), which gave readers the
                           opportunity to annotate web pages, resulting in law suits from companies
                           who did not care for unpermitted comments. The more recent Google
                           Sidewiki (<ref target="http://www.google.com/sidewiki/intl/nl/index.html">http://www.google.com/sidewiki/intl/nl/index.html</ref>) faced the
                           same problem. The author sees future possibilities in stylus-based
                           annotation and sharing and suggest that a reader/annotator might want to
                           be able to switch between interfaces, when either annotating themselves
                           or reading another person’s notes for instance.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.2 Collaborative Learning before Web 2.0</head>
                  <p>From academia, there have been (and still are) numerous attempts to build
                     social platforms for shared learning and reading, which has eventually
                     developed into a distinct discipline (Computer Supported Collaborative
                     Learning) — stressing the value of shared information processing through the
                     computer. Two influential earlier systems are described in this section, CoNote
                     which makes use of the web and CSILE which works on a local network. CSILE
                     eventually developed into the still available Knowledge Forum (<ref target="http://www.knowledgeforum.com">http://www.knowledgeforum.com</ref>).
                     Both make use of restricted groups in an educational setting.</p>
                  <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Davis, James R. and Daniel P. Huttenlocher. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Shared Annotation for Cooperative
                                 Learning</title>.<title rend="italic">The First International
                                 Conference on Computer Support for Collaborative Learning</title>.
                              Indiana University. Bloomington, Indiana, USA: L. Erlbaum Associates
                              Inc., pp 84-88.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article shows an interesting conceptual model for collaborative work
                           through annotation, offering anchored discussions in documents. The
                           authors present CoNote, a collaborative system that is based on shared
                           annotation. First the system is described. CoNote is an online system
                           that requires no additional client software, and functions on HTML and
                           ASCII text. The annotations are anchored — although horizontally
                           separated from the base text and thus interrupting the annotated text —
                           and comments upon comments can be made. The annotations function much
                           like a discussion forum: the annotations appear as links in a structured
                           tree; the links contain meta-data: the title, author and date of
                           creation; and creation of annotations is done by filling out a form. The
                           annotations took the shape of questions and answers. The authors then
                           briefly describe the conceptual model behind the system. The system can
                           for instance be used by a group with a shared set of documents and users
                           can have different roles. In the fourth section a trial during an
                           introductory college computer science course (Fall 2004) is discussed.
                           Findings were that students who performed less were helped by the
                           annotations, that the students could answer each others questions
                           correctly, that they expected fast responses because of the connection to
                           the Internet and that the students conducted much work at home. Future
                           research is said to be directed at refinement of the system and
                           implementation in other settings.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Scardamalia, Marlene and Carl Bereiter. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Technologies for Knowledge-Building
                              Discourse</title>. <title rend="italic">Communications of the
                                 ACM</title> 36.5: 37-41.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article shows nicely how education has been changing over the last
                           decades, due to the widespread adoption of digital media. The authors
                           first provide a theoretical background in education and software. They
                           sketch the current educational situation and stress the importance of
                           knowledge building over knowledge reproduction. They argue that the
                           desktop metaphor of the personal computer, because it is intended for
                           business use, hinders the educational possibilities of the machine.
                           Consecutively, a framework for knowledge building is sketched, according
                           to a constructivist view, where coherence and completeness are central
                           concepts, built through social activity. In this global perspective, six
                           features are added, such as source referencing in order to facilitate
                           situating of information. The authors then describe their implementation
                           of a second-order computing facility, computer-supported intentional
                           learning environments (CSILE). The system itself is not based on
                           documents provided, but allows students to make texts and comment on one
                           another. The process is not described (or shown) in much detail however.
                           CSILE was implemented in local networks of several grade schools and
                           proved to be successful for the goals the authors had formulated. Note:
                           CSILE eventually evolved into Knowledge Forum, which still exists: <ref target="http://www.knowledgeforum.com">http://www.knowledgeforum.com</ref>.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.3 Academic use of Web 2.0</head>
                  <p>In recent years, a number of articles and reports have been published on
                     scholars’ attitudes and practices towards Social Media and Web 2.0. Some
                     small-scale, others spanning five years of study, these show a largely coherent
                     and perhaps not surprising image: a small group of academics is experimenting
                     (in all academic disciplines), but most scholars are still apprehensive of the
                     possible downsides and prefer <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> academic
                     publishing and peer review as long as there is no sound alternative — and many
                     do not expect there to be one in the near future. Interestingly enough, the
                     younger scholars often appear the most rigid, but this can be easily explained
                     as they can (or will) take few risks in trying to obtain tenure or
                     recognition.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>CIBER (University College, London). (2010). Social Media Research
                              and Workflow. <ref target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/social-media-report.pdf">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/social-media-report.pdf</ref>
                              (accessed July 11, 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Report issued by Emerald Publishing Group to CIBER on Social Media use
                           among scholars of several disciplines. The researchers focused on
                           retrieving the survey from users of Social Media (n=1923) but compared it
                           to a set of non-users (n=491), all geographically dispersed and from
                           several disciplines. The findings suggest two broad kinds of Social Media
                           user: one who conjointly uses microblogging, social tagging/bookmarking
                           and blogging (and who is also likely to own an iPad); one who uses SM for
                           sharing documents, organizing meetings and their calenders. The former is
                           the least established; the newest Social Media are the least popular in
                           general. Findings are similar to that of the Research Information Network
                           (2011): interinstitutional collaboration is an important incentive
                           (reported as peer pressure outside of the institution); SM acts as a
                              <emph>complement</emph> to traditional publishing; lack of time and
                           lack of knowledge on the benefits are important barriers; personal
                           motivation is important. A difference with aforementioned report: users
                           under 35 appeared to be more prone to use of Social Media, although the
                           general use is not limited to that group. Other findings include: the
                           scholars did not use niche tools especially developed for their purposes,
                           but general tools like Skype, Wikipedia and Facebook; and a peculiar
                           outcome: uptake is smaller in Asia and North-America than the rest of the
                           world <ptr target="#ciber2010" loc="14"/>. The questioned users also gave
                           recommendations for publishers, they would like to have better access,
                           and articles linked with data; and from libraries they requested easy
                           full-text search. For a quick discussion see <bibl>Howard, Jennifer.
                                 <title rend="quotes">Social Media Lure Academics Frustrated by
                                 Traditional Publishing</title>. <title rend="italic">The Chronicle
                                 of Higher Education</title> 57.25: 2011. n. pag. <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/Leading-Humanities-Journal/123696/">http://chronicle.com/article/Leading-Humanities-Journal/123696/</ref>
                              (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Hartley, Diane et al. (2010). <title rend="italic">Assessing the
                                 Future Landscape of Scholarly Communication: An Exploration of
                                 Faculty Values and Needs in Seven Disciplines</title>. UC Berkeley
                              Center for Studies in Higher Education. <ref target="http://escholarship.org/uc/cshe_fsc">http://escholarship.org/uc/cshe_fsc</ref> (accessed 19 July
                              2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>700+ page report on a five-year qualitative research among scholars of
                           mostly North-American elite institutes in seven disciplines (seven case
                           studies in the report, chapter 2 through 8; reading chapter 1 is enough
                           for a general overview). The scholars were selected through snowball
                           sampling. The goal was to map scholars’ uses, wants and possible models
                           for (future) scholarly communication. Over all disciplines, according to
                           the authors, scholars tend to hold onto traditional publishing values,
                           looking onto peer review as Churchill’s democracy: it is seen as the
                           least worse measure of quality and a filter for the amount of research
                           available. Young scholars are the most rigid. The authors as a result
                           have identified five key areas that need attention according to the
                           interviewees <ptr target="#hartley2010" loc="V"/>, which after
                           realisation would lead to a situation close to current practices,
                           including peer-reviewed journals and tenure. Thus, Social Media are not
                           seen nor wanted as an important part of scholarly communication. The
                           discipline of Digital Humanities is mentioned as an exception several
                           times. For a longer summary see: Davis, Phil. <title rend="quotes">Culture Trumps Technology: The UC Berkeley Scholarly Communication
                              Report</title>. <title rend="italic">The Scholarly Kitchen</title>. 15
                           Feb 2010. <ref target="http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2010/02/15/culture-trumps-technology/">http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2010/02/15/culture-trumps-technology/</ref>
                           (accessed 9 July 2011).</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Maron, Nancy L. and K. Kirby Smith. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Current Models of Digital Scholarly Communication: Results of an
                                 Investigation Conducted by Ithaka for the Association of Research
                                 Libraries</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic
                                 Publishing</title>. 12.1: n. pag. <ref target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0012.105?rgn=main;view=fulltext">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0012.105?rgn=main;view=fulltext</ref>
                              (accessed 13 July 2011). </bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Association of Research Libraries research conducted by Ithaka on the use
                           of digital scholarly resources. It is based on in-depth interviews with
                           humanities, social sciences and STM scholars in the US and Canada. The
                           researchers identified resources of which scholars report use, but <q>limited to resources containing born-digital content by
                              and for a scholarly audience</q>, among which E-only journals,
                           preprints, blogs and discussion forums; social tools for the general
                           public like Facebook or Diigo were excluded. The article describes these
                           eight types of resource, their role in academics, providing description
                           and images of examples in all three academic areas. The scholars report
                           that the resources need to 1) give access to current research 2)
                           facilitate exchange among scholars and 3) supply useful co-location of
                           works. STM scholars focused on the first, humanities and social science
                           on the second. The authors draw several conclusions from the interviews,
                           including: digital innovations are taking place in all disciplines;
                           digital publishing in academia has a long tail (many niche publications);
                           for a digital publication establishing credibility is important — many of
                           the more frequently mentioned publications existed at least several
                           years; and sustainability is a general problem. The authors conclude with
                           a brief section on how librarians can use this information in their work
                           of selection of materials.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Procter, Rob et al. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Adoption and Use
                                 of Web 2.0 in Scholarly Communications</title>. <title rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society
                                 A</title> 368.1926: 4039-4056.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Findings of a report funded by the Research Information Network (RIN),
                           based on qualitative and quantitative research among UK academics on Web
                              2.0.<note> The full report is also included in this bibliography:
                              Research Information Network (2011).</note> The findings signal that
                           adoption is modest: 39% non-users, 13% frequent users and 45% occasional
                              users.<note>The definitions of ‘occasional’ and ‘frequent’ are given
                              in the original report.</note> There is greater use among older age
                           groups, more senior positions and males (although the last factor not
                           convincingly so). The authors identify nine factors influencing adoption,
                           many of which institutional. The most important are 1) local support,
                           i.e. encouragement from within the institution — unfamiliarity often
                           prohibits use and as researchers report lack of time as a reason for
                           adoption, making encouragement from within the institution crucial and 2)
                           bottom-up implementation instead of top-down, thus no imposition of
                           tooling but service providing and information exchange. Another finding
                           is that frequent and occasional users use Web 2.0 as a supplement rather
                           than a replacement of traditional media. Lack of trust in non-peer
                           reviewed resources is an important factor in this, among users and
                           non-users. Collaborative research activities are also often an incentive
                           for the uptake. </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Research Information Network. (2010). <title rend="italic">If You
                                 Build It, Will They Come? How Researchers Perceive and Use Web
                                 2.0</title>. <ref target="http://www.rin.ac.uk/our-work/communicating-and-disseminating-research/use-and-relevance-web-20-researchers">http://www.rin.ac.uk/our-work/communicating-and-disseminating-research/use-and-relevance-web-20-researchers</ref>
                              (accessed 9 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Full report on which Procter et al (2010) have published results.
                           Although conducted among UK researchers only, this report provides a
                           wealth of information on scholarly communication and Web 2.0. It is
                           well-structured and freely available online in a well-designed
                           screen-friendly version. The report first defines contours of adoption.
                           The authors signal that although scholars remain loyal to traditional
                           forms of publication, they are not hostile towards the digital
                           possibilities. Adaption is most likely when stimulated locally and when
                           needed for interinstitutional collaboration. Social Media are seen as a
                           supplement rather than a replacement for traditional research and
                           publishing. Then the authors describe five case studies, among which
                           arts-humanities.net (<ref target="http://arts-humanities.net/">http://arts-humanities.net/</ref>) and PLoS (Public Library of
                           Science, <ref target="http://www.plos.org/">http://www.plos.org/</ref>).
                           These indicate that their uptake is now in the hands of a small group of
                           enthusiasts. The authors signal that growth of these platforms is
                           important for their survival, but sustainability and stability need to be
                           safe-guarded beforehand. In the final chapter, the implications are
                           discussed for universities, funders and researchers, making
                           recommendations for further adoption. University computing and
                           information services are explicitly mentioned as important possible
                           stimulators for the uptake of Web 2.0 tools.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.4 Academic Use of Specific Social Media Platforms</head>
                  <p>As the general research reports on scholarship and Social Media and Web 2.0
                     show that uptake in universities is in its infancy, a perspective from the
                     tools that are available currently might provide insight on future
                     possibilities of supporting the academic workflow and communication. These
                     originate in academia (Zotero) but more often in the trade or non-profit sector
                     (Diigo, Twitter) or through collaborations (CommentPress). Trials have been
                     conducted and research has been performed within universities and libraries
                     that can unveil new opportunities for digitally supported research.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Cohen, Daniel J. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Creating Scholarly
                                 Tools and Resources for the Digital Ecosystem: Building Connections
                                 in the Zotero Project</title>. <title rend="italic">First
                                 Monday</title> 13.8: n. pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017 ">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017</ref>
                              (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Discusses the Zotero Project (<ref target="http://www.zotero.org/">http://www.zotero.org/</ref>) developed by the Center for History and
                           New Media (CHNM) at George Mason University. The author describes that
                           the goal of the project was to combine the benefits of stand-alone
                           applications with those of web applications in order to facilitate the
                           academic research workflow. The author then discusses the benefits of
                           Zotero and its development into the tool it currently is. He states that
                           Zotero is built on the principles of academic research in general,
                           integrative and part of a network of thought. The author stresses the
                           underlying principles of Zotero — open source and open to external
                           connections and intervention — as a facilitator of its success. </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Estelles, Enrique, Esther de Moral, and Fernando Gonzalez. (2010).
                                 <title rend="quotes">Social Bookmarking Tools as Facilitators of
                                 Learning and Research Collaborative Processes: The Diigo
                                 Case.</title>
                              <title>Interdisciplinary Journal of E-Learning and Learning
                                 Objects</title>. 6: 175-191. <ref target="http://www.ijello.org/Volume6/IJELLOv6p175-191Estelles683.pdf ">http://www.ijello.org/Volume6/IJELLOv6p175-191Estelles683.pdf</ref>
                              (accessed 19 June 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors start by describing general characteristics of Social
                           Bookmarking Systems (SBS), selecting Diigo (<ref target="http://www.diigo.com">http://www.diigo.com</ref>) as the best
                           tool to facilitate teaching and learning and to support academic
                           research. Diigo is an acronym for ‘Digest of Internet Information, Groups
                           and Other stuff’. It allows users to bookmark and tag websites, video’s
                           and other items, comment upon them and share this information with
                           specific groups. The authors describe how Diigo facilitates individual
                           and team work, its applications for learning and research; give examples
                           of academic use — including a table with a sample of case studies; and
                           compare Diigo to other SBS. The authors are extremely supportive of
                           Diigo, which makes one of the most interesting parts of this article a
                           SWOT-analysis <ptr target="#estelles2010" loc="188"/>.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. (2007). <title rend="quotes">CommentPress:
                                 New (Social) Structures for New (Networked) Texts</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>. 10.3: n.
                              pag. <ref target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0010.305?rgn=main;view=fulltext">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0010.305?rgn=main;view=fulltext</ref>
                              (accessed 14 July 2011). Available in MediaCommons (including
                              comments) through <ref target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/mcpress/cpfinal/">http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/mcpress/cpfinal/</ref>
                              (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The author discusses a different model for digital publishing. The
                           argument is built up from the perspective that experiments have relied
                           too often on the metaphor of the codex and the incorrect notion of the
                           single, isolated academic author and reader. Instead, the author states,
                           the metaphor of the network, allowing for dialogue, is more efficient,
                           with the blog as a good starting point. This has materialized in
                           CommentPress, an open source Wordpress theme and plugin. The author then
                           describes several experiments with the model, conducted with the
                           Institute for the Future of the Book: G4M3R 7TH30RY (the web version of
                           the book <title rend="italic">Gamer Theory</title> by McKenzie Wark, <ref target="http://www.futureofthebook.org/gamertheory/">http://www.futureofthebook.org/gamertheory/</ref>) which was the
                           basis for CommentPress; and consecutively two projects taken up to
                           develop CommentPress further: Mitchell Stephens’s article <title rend="quotes">Holy of Holies</title> and a commentable version of the
                           Iraq Study Group Report. The author then discusses the possibilities for
                           academic publishing, noting that the use can be a labor-intense process
                           for the author, for instance in keeping track of the comments.</p>
                        <p>The MediaCommons version of the article has not solicited many comments,
                           perhaps because for first-time commentators they were moderated before
                           being published; the comments are interesting however to scan: some are
                           content-related, others involve for instance practical problems in
                           installing CommentPress. Many are by the same author. An interesting
                           detail: an error which still resides in the published paper is commented
                           upon in the comments section of the MediaCommons version (Section <title rend="quotes">Operation Iraqi Quagmire</title>). </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Greenhow, Christine. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Social
                                 Scholarship: Applying Social Networking Technologies to Research
                                 Practices</title>. <title rend="italic">Knowledge Quest</title>
                              37.4: 42-47.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The article discusses the benefits and downsides of social bibliography
                           sites or social bookmarking sites for education purposes, specifically
                           CiteULike (<ref target="http://www.citeulike.org">http://www.citeulike.org</ref>) and Diigo (<ref target="http://www.diigo.com">http://www.diigo.com</ref>). Benefits
                           include a greater insight in one’s <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#greenhow2009">own scholarly
                              attitudes and practices</quote>
                           <ptr target="#greenhow2009" loc="43"/></cit>, students learning from
                           professors, connecting with them, getting a broader insight and being
                           able to contribute themselves. Soft peer review is mentioned as another
                           benefit: it shows (student) researchers which articles are popular and
                           thus probably more valuable. A downside according to the author is the
                           fact that because of a lack of peer review students need to read more
                           critically to assess the value of a text. In Diigo, there is the
                           possibility of annotation, making that assessment easier; another’s
                           annotations benefit critical thinking. The author concludes by stating
                           that methods and principles need to be defined and that further research
                           into the impact is necessary.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Hammond, Tony et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Social
                                 Bookmarking Tools (I): A General Review</title>. <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 11.4: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/hammond/04hammond.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/hammond/04hammond.html</ref>
                              (accessed 14 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>In 2005, a new class of social bookmarking tools was arising that catered
                           more to academic needs, which meant the inclusion of metadata. In this
                           article, such bookmarking tools are discussed. After a brief discussion
                           of the origin of links, including taxonomies and bookmarklets, the
                           authors describe the nature of tagging (participatory, bottom-up instead
                           of a top-down process, a flat structure instead of hierarchical) and the
                           reason for tagging — most tools discussed are bookmarking sites where
                           users tag content by others intended for personal use. The authors then
                           briefly identify benefits, such as being able to locate information in a
                           smaller pool than the whole web; and a few issues, among which privacy.
                           The authors have built link lists in Connotea (<ref target="http://www.connotea.org/">http://www.connotea.org/</ref>) to
                           demonstrate the usefulness of the tool. These provide invaluable
                           information by following them now — several years after publication. The
                           authors had used a complex tag to accompany the article to prevent others
                           using the same tag for different topic. However, the tag they have chosen
                           to accompany the article is not unique (anymore) and spamming appears to
                           be an issue. The most useful lists in the current day are those that
                           combine the tag with the references restricted by poster, in this case
                           the references that were tagged by one of the authors of the article.
                           This indicates the usefulness of a filter. The authors end with a summary
                           of elements usually present in social bookmarking tools. An accompanying
                           article focuses on one of the bookmarking tools mentioned, Connotea:
                              <bibl>Lund, Ben. et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Social
                                 Bookmarking Tools (II): A Case Study — Connotea</title>. <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 11.4: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/lund/04lund.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/lund/04lund.html</ref> (accessed
                              14 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Kjellberg, Sara. (2010). <title rend="quotes">I Am a Blogging
                                 Researcher: Motivations for Blogging in a Scholarly
                              Context</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 15.8: n.
                              pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580</ref>
                              (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The author first describes previous research on the motivation for
                           blogging, which is a small base of research, often auto-ethnographic. The
                           author states that it was possible to identify recurrent themes however,
                           among which information or knowledge management, social purposes and
                           expressing opinions. A qualitative research method was then employed, by
                           conducting in-depth semi-structured interviews with twelve Swedish, Dutch
                           and Danish blogging researchers in 2009, from a variety of disciplines,
                           including humanities and STM who were selected through snowball sampling.
                           The author has also used the blogs themselves in analyzing the
                           interviews. From the material, six functions were distilled:
                           disseminating content, expressing opinions, keeping up-to-date and
                           remembering, writing, interacting and creating relationships (although
                           not every blogger mentions them all). The author elaborates on these
                           functions, using ample quotes from the interviews. Motivations for
                           blogging were then extracted from the interviewees’ statements on the
                           functions: 1) sharing with others, 2) providing room for creativity and
                           3) feeling connected. Sharing (1) is not reserved for academic peers,
                           especially in the STM sector, where people from the industry also follow
                           the blogs. The mentioned creativity (2) originates from fact that the
                           bloggers can write with less restriction than in articles, and can thus
                           be used to develop and organize ideas. The bloggers mention strong
                           personal motivations for keeping their blogs, even though they are not
                           part of their academic publishing record and the researchers do not think
                           it will aid their careers in the near future. A table shows the interplay
                           of the functions and motivations and the intended audience (self or
                           others).</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Priem, Jason and Kaitlin Light Costello. (2010) <title rend="quotes">How and Why Scholars Cite on Twitter</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ASIS&amp;t Annual Meeting</title>.
                              Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, USA. <ref target="http://www.asis.org/asist2010/proceedings/proceedings/ASIST_AM10/submissions/201_Final_Submission.pdf">http://www.asis.org/asist2010/proceedings/proceedings/ASIST_AM10/submissions/201_Final_Submission.pdf</ref>
                              (accessed 8 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors conduct bibliometric analysis of Twitter (<ref target="http://twitter.com/">http://twitter.com/</ref>) feeds by a
                           sample of 28 academics (faculty, postdocs or doctoral students) from the
                           humanities, social sciences and sciences, selected through snowball
                           sampling. 2,322 Tweets that contained direct or indirect links to a
                           peer-reviewed scholarly article online were isolated and analyzed by both
                           authors using open coding. The direct citations are called first-order,
                           the citations which linked to an intermediary web page are second-order
                           citations. The authors also conducted qualitative research by doing
                           interviews. Reasons given for not citing directly are workflow and the
                           existence of a paywall, which was supported by the quantitative data.
                           Citing in Tweets is reported to be seen as part of an ongoing
                           conversation. The participants favored the speed with which articles
                           spread (also supported by the quantitative data). Moreover, the platform
                           aided their daily academic process: Twitter functions as a filter and
                           helps point to interesting articles. The authors conclude by stating that
                           Twitter citations could be a valuable part of bibliometrics to supplement
                           traditional citation analysis.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Ross, Claire et al. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Enabled
                                 Backchannel: Conference Twitter Use by Digital Humanities</title>.
                                 <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 67.2:
                              214-237.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors describe the possible benefits and downsides of using Twitter
                              (<ref target="http://twitter.com">http://twitter.com</ref>) as a
                           digital backchannel at conferences and show how the use of Twitter as a
                           platform can enable better participation and communication among
                           community members, thus to support communities of practice. As the
                           Digital Humanities (DH) community is known as an early adopter of such
                           technologies, tweets from three DH conferences from June through
                           September 2009 were used. The Tweets were collected and archived by
                           Twapper Keeper (<ref target="http://www.twapperkeeper.com">http://www.twapperkeeper.com</ref>). The database was analysed using
                           qualitative and quantitative methods. Automated analysis was hindered
                           because of the use of abbreviations, different spellings, etc. due to the
                           maximum length of a Tweet (140 characters). Tweets were categorized
                           manually according to types of <emph>user intention</emph> for which the
                           authors have developed their own categories: comments on presentations;
                           sharing resources; discussions and conversations; jotting down notes;
                           establishing an online presence; and asking organizational questions <ptr target="#ross2011" loc="219"/>. Most of the Tweets fell into the
                           category of <q>jotting down notes</q>, indicating that sharing is more
                           important than collaboration. The findings also suggest that a minority
                           of users generates a great proportion of the Tweets, whereas many users
                           produce none or only one Tweet during the conference, indicating an
                           unevenness of use. Regulation by the organizers of the conference
                           (communicating a hashtag up front for instance) could improve this
                           situation according to the authors. Consecutively, the users with the
                           highest amount of tweets were sent an online survey, resulting in 11
                           responses, where the aggregation of proceedings for other attendees
                           (through <q>jotting down notes</q>) was also mentioned as most important.
                           The authors conclude by stating, among other things, that the backchannel
                           of Tweets offer more than <q>whispering in class</q> but that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ross2011">new, dedicated methodologies for the analysis and
                              understanding of Tweet-based corpora are necessary.</quote><ptr target="#ross2011" loc="232"/></cit></p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Yang, Stephen J.A. et al. (2011). <title rend="quotes">A
                                 Collaborative Multimedia Annotation Tool for Enhancing Knowledge
                                 Sharing in CSCL</title>. <title rend="italic">Interactive Learning
                                 Environments</title> 19.1: 45-62.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article describes a Social Media tool that has been built in
                           academia (within the discipline of Computer Supported Collaborative
                           Learning) to support collaborative learning, PAMS 2.0. An overview of
                           earlier research in and outside CSCL is first given, including several
                           approaches to collaborative and cooperative learning. Then, PAMS 2.0 is
                           described. PAMS 1.0 was not Web-based whereas this version is. Some
                           features that are mentioned: PAMS 2.0 makes use of the Web Services
                           Resource Framework technology (WSRF), which is XML-based; readers can
                           annotate on document files and web pages — although they the latter have
                           to be imported; it allows for role assignment; and it provides
                           synchronous discussion possibilities next to the read/annotation space.
                           Consecutively, an experiment is discussed. Two groups of student
                           volunteers — one using PAMS, the other not — read, annotated and
                           discussed materials during a semester, which they were tested on in five
                           iterations. The students using PAMS performed equally to the other group
                           at the beginning of the trial, but performed better at the end. The
                           authors hope to implement the system on the Web. This article not only
                           shows the possible benefits of this system, it also provides an
                           indication of the possible benefit of using (semi-)commercial
                           applications in educational settings, for instance Diigo. Not much
                           research as yet has been done on such platforms. </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.5. Sidebar: Other Social Media Platforms</head>
                  <p>Some platforms have not been included in the previous list, but have
                     interesting features and are worth looking into. The articles — which all but
                     one originate from the trade sector — have been included separately in the
                     bibliography.</p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>Platform</cell>
                        <cell>URL</cell>
                        <cell>Further reading</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Copia</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://www.thecopia.com">http://www.thecopia.com</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Carmody, Tim. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Copia, Social Reading
                                 App/Network/Store, Comes Alive</title>. <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 18 Nov. <ref target="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/11/copia-social-reading-appnetworkstore-comes-alive/">http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/11/copia-social-reading-appnetworkstore-comes-alive/</ref>
                              (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>; <bibl>Watters, Audrey. (2010). <title rend="quotes">New Social E-Reading Platform Allows Real-Time
                                 Discussions, Right On the E-Book's Pages</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 22 Nov. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/new_social_e-reading_platform_allows_real-time_dis.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/new_social_e-reading_platform_allows_real-time_dis.php</ref>
                              (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Kobo reader</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://www.kobobooks.com">http://www.kobobooks.com</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Sorrel, Charlie. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Kobo Update Adds
                                 Social Features, Nerd-Friendly Stats</title>. <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 10 Dec. <ref target="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/12/kobo-update-adds-social-features-nerd-friendly-stats/">http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/12/kobo-update-adds-social-features-nerd-friendly-stats/</ref>
                              (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Mendeley</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://mendeley.com">http://www.mendeley.com</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Hopkins, Curt. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Mendeley Throws Open
                                 the Doors to Academic Data</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 29 Apr. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/mendeley_introduces_academic_catalog_search.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/mendeley_introduces_academic_catalog_search.php</ref>
                              (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Open Annotation Collaboration</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://www.openannotation.org">http://www.openannotation.org</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Hunter, Jane et al. (2010). <title rend="quotes">The Open
                                 Annotation Collaboration: A Data Model to Support Sharing and
                                 Interoperability of Scholarly Annotations</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2010: Conference
                              Abstracts</title>. London, United Kingdom: Office for Humanities
                              Communication; Centre for Computing in the Humanities. 175-178.</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Readum</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://www.readum.com">http://www.readum.com</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Watters, Audrey. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Long Live Marginalia!
                                 ReadSocial Brings Annotations to Digital Literature</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 24 Mar. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/love_live_marginalia_readsocial_brings_annotations.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/love_live_marginalia_readsocial_brings_annotations.php</ref>
                              (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Google Sidewiki and Reframe it</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <ref target="http://www.google.com/sidewiki">http://www.google.com/sidewiki</ref>
                           <ref target="http://reframeit.com">http://reframeit.com</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <bibl>Curtis, Benjamin. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Google's Sidewiki
                                 and the Real Innovations</title>. <title rend="italic">Medical
                                 Marketing and Media</title> 45.1: 31. <ref target="http://www.mmm-online.com/googles-sidewiki-and-the-real-innovations/article/160456/">http://www.mmm-online.com/googles-sidewiki-and-the-real-innovations/article/160456/</ref>
                              (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>;<bibl>Lardinois, Frederic. (2009).
                                 <title rend="quotes">Reframe It Brings Facebook, Twitter, &amp; Web
                                 Luminaries to Its Annotation Tool</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 30 Mar. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/reframe_integrates_facebook_and_twitter.php ">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/reframe_integrates_facebook_and_twitter.php</ref>
                              (accessed 7 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.6 Collaborative Reading Using e-Reading Devices</head>
                  <p>Much academic research has been done on the use of e-reading devices and their
                     merit for academic work, but the relative novelty of <emph>shared</emph>
                     annotation precludes interesting findings on that particular topic. On the
                     iPad, which offers many tools for collaboration, like iAnnotate, academic
                     research on the topic as yet is hard to find.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Weisberg, Mitchell. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Student Attitudes
                                 and Behaviors Towards Digital Textbooks</title>. <title rend="italic">Publishing Research Quarterly</title> 27.2:
                              188-196.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Report on a two-year study among students on e-reading devices. The study
                           was conducted at Sawyer Business School of Suffolk University in Boston,
                           Massachusetts. This research shows that when readers make long-term use
                           of a e-reading device, adoption becomes more likely. Annotation
                           possibilities were seen as an important aspect. Especially the tablet was
                           seen as an interesting option for reading — and these allow for
                           collaborative reading, although the study does not report on this
                           opportunity. Other researches mention the strain of annotation and
                           hightlighting — and thus never get to the social part of annotation — if
                           it was available at all in the chosen device at that time, see for
                           instance: <list>
                              <item>
                                 <bibl><title rend="quotes">E-Readers Advance in Academe: A <title rend="italic">Chronicle</title> Survey</title>. (2010).
                                       <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher
                                       Education</title>. 56.38: 2011. n. pag. <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/E-Readers-Advance-in-Academe-/65885/">http://chronicle.com/article/E-Readers-Advance-in-Academe-/65885/</ref>
                                    (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl></item>
                              <item><bibl>Gielen, Nina. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Handheld E-Book
                                       Readers and Scholarship: Report and Reader Survey</title>.
                                       <title rend="italic">ACLS Humanities E-book</title>: n. pag.
                                       <ref target="http://www.humanitiesebook.org/heb-whitepaper-3.html">http://www.humanitiesebook.org/heb-whitepaper-3.html</ref>
                                    (accessed 19 July 2011).</bibl></item>
                              <item><bibl>Stein, Scott. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Do Kindles (and
                                       Other E-readers) Need Better Ways to Annotate?</title>
                                    <title rend="italic">CNET News</title>. 30 Sept. <ref target="http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-10363642-1.html">http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-10363642-1.html</ref>
                                    (accessed 15 July 2011). (mentions <title rend="italic">The
                                       E-reader Pilot at Princeton</title>. New Jersey: Princeton
                                    University, 2009. <ref target="http://www.princeton.edu/ereaderpilot/">http://www.princeton.edu/ereaderpilot/</ref> [accessed 1
                                    July 2011.]).</bibl></item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>O'Donnell, James J. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Do You Like Your
                                 E-Reader?: Six Takes from Academics</title>. <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title> 56.38: n.pag. <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/Do-You-Like-Your-E-Reader-/65840/">http://chronicle.com/article/Do-You-Like-Your-E-Reader-/65840/</ref>
                              (accessed 14 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Six academics describe the use of their e-readers, which are in this case
                           Kindles and iPads. All describe the Kindle as no more than a possibility
                           to replace a stack of leisure reading with a single small device. The
                           iPad is mentioned as having more opportunities for scholarly work, but
                           still wants improvement. Collaboration or sharing is not mentioned. One
                           researcher remarked that a barrier in doing research with the iPad is the
                           impossibility to annotate copyrighted digital documents.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>
                              <title rend="quotes">The iPad for Professors: Evaluating a
                                 Productivity Tool after One Year</title>. (2011). <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>: n.pag.
                                 <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/article-content/126885/">http://chronicle.com/article/article-content/126885/</ref>.
                              (accessed 14 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Six scholars evaluate the use of the iPad (first version) for scholarly
                           purposes. Many mention note-taking and being able to synchronize
                           documents to several devices. Collaborative work or sharing is hardly
                           mentioned, although one scholar describes using Dropbox (<ref target="http://www.dropbox.com">http://www.dropbox.com</ref>) and
                           iAnnotate (<ref target="http://www.ajidev.com/iannotate/">http://www.ajidev.com/iannotate/</ref>) for receiving and grading
                           student work (and then returning them through Gmail).</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Wang, Tricia. (2010). <title rend="quotes">My New Academic Workflow
                                 with my iPad, iAnnotate, Mendleys &amp; Dropbox</title>. <title rend="italic">Cultural Bytes</title>. <ref target="http://culturalbyt.es/post/1125482840/workflow">http://culturalbyt.es/post/1125482840/workflow</ref> (accessed 11
                              July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This is a blog post by an academic, Tricia Wang, which provides a nice
                           case of the use of a device (the iPad) combined with several Social Media
                           tools for performing research. The article contains several images of the
                           author’s work process.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.1.7 Referencing and Soft Peer-Review</head>
                  <p>Peer review is central to academic recognition and it is one of the main
                     concerns when Social Media and online publishing are discussed: how does one
                     guarantee quality, that is to say filter information without it? This section
                     includes an essay confronting this issue and an article that proposes to
                     include Web-based metrics to obtain recognition.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Priem, Jason and Bradley M. Hemminger. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Scientometrics 2.0: Toward New Metrics of Scholarly Impact on the
                                 Social Web</title>. <title rend="italic">First Editions</title>
                              15.7: n. pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2874/2570">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2874/2570</ref>
                              (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>An alternative model for measuring academic impact is suggested,
                           including Social Media data but still built around single article
                           reference. First, the authors offer a quick discussion of existing
                           models, the most important of which is the Journal Impact Factor (JIF)
                           which is used by tenure committees but only measures the impact of
                           journals as a whole. In the third section, tables are presented with
                           practical overviews that can serve as a basis for scientometrics: 1) an
                           overview of several types of Social Media, aimed at the general and
                           specifically at the academic public (often in science); 2) an overview of
                           research recommending and discussing webmetrics. The authors
                           consecutively supply a list of data sources explaining why and how these
                           can be used for scientometrics and what the pitfalls are. This list
                           includes reference managers, comments on articles, microblogging and
                           blogging. In the conclusions, the application of scientometrics is
                           discussed cautiously. The main uses described are evaluation, filtering
                           and study and mapping of scholarship. The authors end with a discussion
                           of the limitations and opportunities, encouraging new research.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Peer-to-Peer
                                 Review and the Future of Scholarly Authority</title>. <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> 48.2: 124-129.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>In developing the online scholarly publishing network MediaCommons (see
                              <ref target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/">http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/</ref>) with the Institute of
                           the Future of the Book, the author was often questioned about peer
                           review, as the articles shared through this platform will not be
                           peer-reviewed in the traditional sense. The topic of digital scholarly
                           peer review is addressed in this essay. The author first notes that on
                           the Web in general, the shift in authority towards decentralization is
                           accepted, but that in academia scholars are not willing to consider such
                           a notion for intellectual authority, resulting in the risk of becoming
                           completely detached from the non-academic world. The downsides of peer
                           review are explained, for instance how the system sustains itself and the
                           author then offers online peer-to-peer review as an alternative, where
                           filtering replaces gatekeeping. The author concludes by stating her hopes
                           that a community surrounding projects like MediaCommons can set the
                           parameters for such a system in such a way that current systems can learn
                           to adhere to this type of review.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.2 Scholarly use of Social Media by non-academics</head>
               <p>Where in the use of the Web and Social Media many academics express concern,
                  another opportunity is recognized: the possibility to engage a wider audience. In
                  this second part of the bibliography, the possibilities of such an engagement are
                  explored. First there is a theoretical focus where researchers — for different
                  reasons — argue the benefit or even necessity of employing Web 2.0 strategies to
                  include the public in the academic knowledge system. In the second section,
                  examples of the employment of Social Media — thereby including the products and
                  help of a wider audience — are given, including discussion on the benefits and
                  downsides and possible strategies for improving these tools.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>2.2.1 Theoretical Background</head>
                  <p>The articles in this section have different backgrounds which the authors have
                     used as a base: industry, (global) education and university, but all have in
                     common that they advocate a university model based on the Web 2.0 model and/or
                     technologies in order for the university to survive as a knowledge producer in
                     a fast-changing world. </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Brown, John Seely and Richard P. Adler. <title rend="quotes">Minds
                                 of Fire: Open Education, the Long Tail, and Learning 2.0</title>.
                                 <title rend="italic">Educause Review</title> 43.1: 2008. 16-20, 22,
                              24, 26, 28, 30, 32. <ref target="http://webpages.csus.edu/~sac43949/PDFs/minds_on_fire.pdf ">http://webpages.csus.edu/~sac43949/PDFs/minds_on_fire.pdf </ref>
                              (accessed on 19 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors argue that because of the rising demand for higher education,
                           it is near impossible to meet the global demand in the future, at least
                           if this demand needs to be met by building brick-and-mortar institutions.
                           The solution is seen in access through the Internet, but more importantly
                           Web 2.0 technology: participatory resources that can support different
                           types of learning, according to the authors. The notion of social
                           learning is employed to support this claim, where 1) the way something is
                           learned — collaboratively — is becoming more important than what is
                           learned, countering the Cartesian view of knowledge and learning based on
                           knowledge transferal; 2) learning to be a <emph>participant</emph> in the
                           field is included in the learning process. The authors point to the open
                           source software community as an example of how new-comers learn through
                           participation and mention that this model is incorporated by other
                           communities such as Wikipedia, stressing the importance of the visibility
                           of the creation process. The authors then continue to describe some
                           examples of formal and informal social learning based on the first type
                           of social learning, using SecondLife and Social Media in general.
                           Consecutively some projects are described based on the second type of
                           social learning, where content and community are used as equal parts in
                           the learning process. On example is The Decameron Web by the Italian
                           Studies Department at Brown University, where students can find source
                           materials, but also can emulate on established researchers’ work and
                           submit their own contributions. The authors argue that learning will
                           develop into Learning 2.0, where students will not only learn in college,
                           but during their whole life according to a demand-pull principle instead
                           of supply-push, connecting to niche communities of people with the same
                           interest, where they will engage in informal learning. The Open
                           Educational Resources movement, together with eScience, eHumanities and
                           Web 2.0 resources provides a base for <term>Open Participatory Learning
                              Ecosystems</term> in which people can continue to take part, also from
                           outside an institution. The authors state that reflective practicums in
                           formal and informal learning institutions can help shape such ecosystems.
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Nikolov, Roumen. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Towards University
                                 2.0: A Space Where Academic Education Meets Corporate
                                 Training</title>. Arnhem, The Netherlands: IPROF-09: ICT
                              Professionalism: a Global Challenge. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10506/136">http://hdl.handle.net/10506/136</ref> (accessed 15 June
                              2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This (for many research universities daring) framework for institutional
                           change in university builds on Web 2.0 and Enterprise 2.0 strategies. The
                           author first sketches the environment of the developments: the economic
                           importance of knowledge, including the Lisbon strategy to forward Europe
                           in the global economy; the adaptation and integration of e-learning,
                           where the increase of ICT in higher eduction has led to new pedagogy
                           models and embedding of e-learning; current university models, where the
                           Corporate University is explained in more detail; and lastly, Web 2.0 and
                           Enterprise 2.0. Enterprises have acknowledged the importance of Web 2.0
                           technologies and have thus incorporated them, because these technologies
                           provide <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#nikolov2009">opportunities for company improvements in
                              the area of innovation, collaboration, knowledge sharing, using
                              collective intelligence and searching and discovering</quote>
                           <ptr target="#nikolov2009" loc="4"/></cit>. Part of these developments is the
                           emergence of <term>ideagoras</term>, Web 2.0 based environments where
                           researchers and developers can collaboratively innovate. On the bases of
                           these developments and models, the author builds a model of University
                           2.0. It means an adaptation of a large part of the principles of the
                           Enterprise 2.0 model and thus the integration of Web 2.0 technologies and
                           applications. An application is found in the concept of the Community of
                           Practice (see Wenger 1998), upon which the university should build and
                           maintain a community in order to collaborate with the industry. In the
                           final section, the implementation of such a strategy at the University of
                           Sofia is briefly explained, which is partially based on the European
                           e-Competence Framework (2008). </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Unsworth, John. (2008). <title rend="quotes">University
                              2.0</title>. <title rend="italic">The Tower and the Cloud: Higher
                                 Education in the Age of Cloud Computing</title>. Educause. pp
                              227-237. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/thetowerandthecloud">http://www.educause.edu/thetowerandthecloud</ref> (accessed 15
                              July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>In this essay, the author argues that universities need to rethink their
                           strategies to perform their core business of cultivating knowledge. Using
                           a nineteenth century article on the distribution of books through
                           railroads, the author distills the concept of <term>information
                              friction</term>, which — explained roughly — describes impeding
                           factors on the distribution of information and the positive effect of a
                           new technology. The author sees universities as monolithic, slow
                           organizations that impede innovation and need to learn from Web 2.0
                           strategies. He advocates <soCalled>seamy</soCalled> systems (as opposed
                           to seamless): top-down, small-scale, non-finalized tools that encourage
                           users to think about information processing. Examples he uses are BibApp
                           — for building publication networks based on one’s own faculty staff,
                           available through <ref target="http://bibapp.org/">http://bibapp.org/</ref> — and BRAIN, a <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth2008">peer
                              finder for institutional repositories</quote>, which is of his own
                           making <ptr target="#unsworth2008" loc="233"/>. The end user is crucial
                           in making the latter operable, as demander and supplier of content. The
                           author argues that if universities makes its information accessible
                           properly, users (including non-academic) will build upon this knowledge
                           by building tools to provide different kinds of access, through apps for
                           instance. In the conclusion the author repeats part of a fifteen-year-old
                           lecture in which he stated that the university should not wait for the
                           public to come, but to actively engage it by meeting in their own
                           environment — if it is not already too late. </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Wenger, Etienne. (1998). <title rend="quotes">Communities of
                                 Practice: Learning as a Social System</title>. <title rend="italic">Systems Thinker</title> 9.5: 1-10. <ref target="http://www.open.ac.uk/ldc08/sites/www.open.ac.uk.ldc08/files/Learningasasocialsystem.pdf                                  ">http://www.open.ac.uk/ldc08/sites/www.open.ac.uk.ldc08/files/Learningasasocialsystem.pdf
                              </ref> (accessed July 18, 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Theoretical article that describes the often-used concept of Community of
                           Practice (CoP). Although the concept was designed for use in business
                           practices, it is particularly useful in describing online communities;
                           the identity of the CoP is shaped by the contents of what the members
                           share, thus by knowledge, and not by the institution or other official
                           affiliations or even shared tasks. Although these communities grow
                           naturally, organizations can influence them. Five strategies of nurturing
                           the community are described.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Cambridge et al. (2005) have written a brief design guide to form and sustain
                     communities of practice in Higher Education:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Cambridge, Darren, Soren Kaplan and Vicki Suter. (2005).
                                 <title>Community of Practice Design Guide: A Step-by-Step Guide for
                                 Designing &amp; Cultivating Communities of Practice in Higher
                                 Education.</title> Educause. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/ELI/CommunityofPracticeDesignGuide/160068 ">http://www.educause.edu/ELI/CommunityofPracticeDesignGuide/160068</ref>
                              (accessed 18 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.2.2. Examples</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>von Ahn, Luis, et al. (2008). <title rend="quotes">reCAPTCHA:
                                 Human-Based Character Recognition via Web Security
                              Measures</title>. <title rend="italic">Science</title> 321.5895:
                              1465-1468. <ref target="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/reCAPTCHA_Science.pdf">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/reCAPTCHA_Science.pdf</ref>
                              (accessed on 18 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The prime author has done much research on the employment of <q>
                              <soCalled>wasted</soCalled> human processing power</q>. In this
                           article, reCAPTCHA (now acquired by Google: <ref target="http://www.google.com/recaptcha">http://www.google.com/recaptcha</ref>) is described, a system that
                           uses human processing power to help transcribe digitized textual archival
                           material where OCR has failed. CAPTCHAs (completely automated public
                           Turing-test to tell computers and humans apart) are used on websites to
                           prevent machines from automatically filling out forms. Computer-generated
                           strings of letters and digits, which are also distorted by the computer
                           to make them illegible for machines, are shown which the reader then
                           needs to replicate to prove she is human. In reCAPTCHA, next to one
                           string of computer-generated content, scanned words from archival
                           documents are inserted — which two OCR systems have failed to recognize.
                           Thus, free human transcription of words is provided. The workings of the
                           system are first explained in a clear and detailed fashion. Empirical
                           research proves that 1) archival documents can be transcribed with a
                           99.1% accuracy using reCAPTCHA; 2) reCAPTCHAs are better at preventing
                           computers to read their contents than (computer-generated) CAPTCHAs are.
                           This is a good example of the useful employment of non-expert knowledge
                           for problems that are generally solved by experts, but that can be
                           performed on a much larger scale than would have been possible without
                           such application.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Brumfiel, Geoff. <title rend="quotes">Breaking the
                                 Convention?</title>
                              <title rend="italic">Nature</title> 459.7250: 1050-1051.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>A brief discussion of the downside of direct digital publishing during
                           science conferences. The boundaries between researchers and journalists
                           blur, as often anyone can get access to streaming video during
                           conferences, Twitter feeds, etc and publish on this information. Raw data
                           might become publicly available before intended. The author discusses
                           means of prevention, but also points to the possible benefit.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Cohen, Daniel J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Engaging and Creating
                                 Virtual Communities</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                                 the Cultural Heritage Online Conference</title>. Florence, Italy.
                              28-32. <ref target="http://www.rinascimento-digitale.it/eventi/conference2009/proceedings-2009/Proceedings-part1.pdf ">http://www.rinascimento-digitale.it/eventi/conference2009/proceedings-2009/Proceedings-part1.pdf
                              </ref> (accessed 18 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>In this conference paper, the author describes the use of virtual
                           communities to aid scholars in conducting research. Some examples are
                           mentioned that allow for varied engagement of non-academics. Digital
                           Humanities Now (<ref target="http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/">http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/</ref>) for instance, is mentioned as
                           a platform where the social media buzz in Digital Humanities is
                           aggregated. More active engagement can be found in Galaxy Zoo (<ref target="http://www.galaxyzoo.org/">http://www.galaxyzoo.org/</ref>,
                           now the second version), where amateur astrologers identify galaxies and
                           planets. Steve (<ref target="http://www.steve.museum/">http://www.steve.museum/</ref>) is an amateur tagging tool used by
                           cultural heritage institutions for the tagging of art works. The author
                           mentions that communities develop without deliberate intention from
                           organizations themselves and that they can be very useful to research;
                           that is, for <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2009">secondary products of
                              scholarship</quote>, like classification and providing context <ptr target="#cohen2009" loc="31"/>. The author ends on the note that
                           cultural heritage institutions will need to learn to curate virtual
                           communities around the physical objects they normally curate.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Fernheimer, Janice W., Lisa Litterio, and James Hendler. (2011).
                                 <title rend="quotes">Transdisciplinary ITexts and the Future of
                                 Web-Scale Collaboration</title>. <title>Journal of Business and
                                 Technical Communication</title> 25.3: 322-337.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Through the concept of ITexts (<q>the blend of IT and texts</q>,
                           introduced in 2001), including for instance e-mail and reading on a
                           portable device, the authors suggest a transdisciplinary approach to
                           problem-solving. This article gives an interesting example of the
                           application of Web 2.0 to facilitate large-scale collaborative networks
                           that include the general public. The authors first discuss the importance
                           of transdisciplinary collaboration for societal problem-solving.
                           Consequently, a two-day workshop on web-scale collaboration is described,
                           where three groups (each discussing an issue in STM, humanities or social
                           science) discussed the conditions of such collaboration and gave examples
                           of ITexts that could be of use. CommentPress and Wikipedia were mentioned
                           for instance in a group focused on the topic of scholarly data. All
                           groups defined five heuristics for suitable platforms, among which
                           providing incentives to attract user participation and mechanisms for
                           ensuring privacy and dedicating ownership. Three examples of IText for
                           transdisciplinary collaboration are discussed: Wikipedia (<ref target="http://www.wikipedia.org/">http://www.wikipedia.org/</ref>),
                           Galaxy Zoo (for identifying galaxies, <ref target="http://www.galaxyzoo.org/">http://www.galaxyzoo.org/</ref>,
                           now the second version) and reCAPTCHA (which aids in deciphering words of
                           difficult to read archival material <ptr target="#vonahn2008"/>, <ref target="http://www.google.com/recaptcha">http://www.google.com/recaptcha</ref>). The authors conclude by
                           recommending the continuance of transdisciplinary workshops and further
                           development of heuristics.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Guy, Marieke and Emma Tonkin. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Folksonomies: Tidying up Tags?</title>. <title rend="italic">D-Lib
                                 Magazine</title> 12.1: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january06/guy/01guy.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january06/guy/01guy.html</ref> (accessed
                              11 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Although this article is not explicitly on academic and non-academic
                              <emph>scholarly</emph> use of Social Media, folksonomies are a good
                           example of how expert and non-expert users document objects of interest,
                           guiding access to information, as opposed to sole expert classification
                           in for instance libraries. The authors suggest opportunities to
                           ameliorate tagging, based on a research sample of delicious (<ref target="http://www.delicious.com/">http://www.delicious.com/</ref>)
                           and Flickr (<ref target="http://www.flickr.com/">http://www.flickr.com/</ref>), from the side of the user as well as
                           the system’s creator. They discuss the possible consequences of for
                           instance automated tag suggestion, opportunities for discussion among
                           users and offering a rule set to users, suggesting that too much
                           intervention might impoverish the tag set; thereby implicitly supporting
                           the possible benefit of using a system which includes non-experts.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Hendry, David G., J.R. Jenkins, and Joseph F. McCarthy. (2006).
                                 <title rend="quotes">Collaborative Bibliography</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Processing and Management</title> 42.3:
                              805-825.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors signal the potential wealth of Internet resources, which they
                           identify as bibliographies. They have indexed a number of resources,
                           including for instance Google Zeitgeist (<ref target="http://www.google.com/press/zeitgeist/">http://www.google.com/press/zeitgeist/</ref>) , Yahoo Groups (<ref target="http://groups.yahoo.com/">http://groups.yahoo.com/</ref>) and
                           Slashdot (<ref target="http://slashdot.org/">http://slashdot.org/</ref>)
                           upon which they have expanded a traditional conceptual model for
                           bibliographies to include participation. The authors suggest several new
                           research topics emerging from their work, including amateur
                           bibliographers and professional intermediation.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Mollet, Amy. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Taking a Leaf Out of
                                 Poliakoff's Book: Embracing New Online Platforms as Necessary for
                                 the Positive Survival of Academic Impact and Debate</title>. <title rend="italic">Impact of Social Sciences</title>. 9 June. <ref target="http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2011/06/09/poliakoff-gearty-online-academic-impac/                                  ">http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2011/06/09/
                                 poliakoff-gearty-online-academic-impac/ </ref> (accessed 15 July
                              2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The author briefly discusses two academic researchers, Martyn Poliakoff
                           (Professor of Chemistry at the University of Nottingham) and Conor Gearty
                           (Professor of Law at the London School of Economics) who have
                           successfully employed social media to extend their audience to the wider
                           public. The blog (Impact of Social Sciences by the London School of
                           Economics and Political Science) provides other examples of academics
                           reaching out to the public as well as discussions on the topic.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Purdy, James P. (2010). <title rend="quotes">The Changing Space of
                                 Research: Web 2.0 and the Integration of Research and Writing
                                 Environments</title>. <title rend="italic">Computers and
                                 Composition</title> 27.1: 48-58.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article is aimed at reforming student composition education, where
                           students generally are presented with an artificial distinction between
                           research and writing (and between doing research and Web 2.0). The author
                           uses a combination of four Web 2.0 platforms to show how students can be
                           taught a more realistic image of composition: Wikipedia (<ref target="http://www.wikipedia.org">http://www.wikipedia.org</ref>),
                           JSTOR (<ref target="http://www.jstor.org/">http://www.jstor.org/</ref>),
                           ARTSTOR (<ref target="http://www.artstor.org">http://www.artstor.org</ref>) and del.icio.us. (now called <title rend="quotes">delicious</title>, <ref target="http://www.delicious.com/">http://www.delicious.com/</ref>).
                           Each of these websites is explained as having affordances for either
                           research, writing or a combination of both and the author expands on the
                           teaching possibilities for each of them. The importance is stressed of
                           connecting Web 2.0, which students are familiar with, to academic
                           research, offering students — and non-academic researchers — an
                           opportunity to relate more easily to this type of research. Moreover, the
                           focus in teaching should shift from consumption (what have others written
                           on the subject?) to the production side (what do I have to say about
                           this?). The author also argues for students to be better taught how to
                           discern quality on the Internet, rather than forcing them to read only
                           materials that are available through the library. In the conclusion, the
                           author focuses on the academic Web 2.0 counterparts for providing — for
                           instance — annotation possibilities and urging composition teachers to
                           teach students how to become — and see themselves as — <q>capable
                              knowledge producers</q>, using the affordances of Web 2.0.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Santo, Avi and Christopher Lucas. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Engaging Academic and Nonacademic Communities Through Online
                                 Scholarly Work</title>. <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title>
                              48.2: 129-138.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors have conducted an informal online survey through the
                           MediaCommons e-mail list and the Cultural Studies listserv on practices
                           and attitudes towards engaging non-academic communities through online
                           scholarly work. Some of the outcomes are described, for instance the gap
                           between the interest in engaging non-academics and actual practices. Many
                           scholars prefer to engage other academics and students first and are not
                           completely comfortable with sharing unfinished work online, although 46%
                           of the respondents report maintaining blogs. In the final section,
                           possibilities for engaging the non-academic community are mentioned —
                           including existing examples — and the authors stress the importance of
                           making an effort to do so. The benefit of this engagement is mentioned
                           briefly: education and perhaps in the best case scenario, aid from the
                           non-academic community in knowledge construction. The authors find that
                           the Web is starting to be used to disperse scholarly discourse more
                           widely and encourage scholars to take risks.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Shanahan, Marie-Claire. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Changing the
                                 Meaning of Peer-to-peer? Exploring Online Comment Spaces as Sites
                                 of Negotiated Expertise</title>. <title rend="italic">JCOM: Journal
                                 of Science Communication</title> 9.1: n.pag. <ref target="http://jcom.sissa.it/archive/09/01/Jcom0901%282010%29A01/ ">http://jcom.sissa.it/archive/09/01/Jcom0901%282010%29A01/</ref>
                              (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The author has performed linguistic discourse analysis on the comments
                           section of three health science articles in a newspaper to find whether
                           experts, either personal or scientific, interact with one another. The
                           small sample indicates that the origin of personal experience needs to be
                           given or else is demanded, whereas scientific expertise is assumed with
                           the use of a certain type of discourse. The author notes that the
                           personal and scientific experts commented within their peer-groups and
                           where they did interact (in one case), the personal experts ‘scientised’
                           their language use. Since the origin of scientific expertise was rarely
                           explicitly mentioned, it is not certain whether the scientific experts
                           are academics or not. It is an interesting article however, as it points
                           to the notion that linguistic markers of (a lack of) academic education
                           have a great influence on the interaction between commentators; and
                           possibly disproves (although the sample is small) the fact that a shared
                           discussion space automatically allows for connection between different
                           communities of practice. </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.3 e-Reader Hardware and Related Electronic Reading Tools</head>
               <p>Supplementing the above, this review of electronic reading environments and tools
                  is meant to provide a baseline for understanding new e-Reader hardware and
                  software. Although it is striking in one sense how little seems to have changed in
                  a decade – for example, the vast majority of scholarly <soCalled>reading
                     tools</soCalled> that have been developed or theorized are either annotation
                  systems or lookup engines – new file formats and commercial testing grounds are
                  rapidly accelerating this work.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>2.3.1 e-Reader Hardware</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <title rend="italic">Sony Reader</title>
                        </label>
                        <p>The first <soCalled>modern</soCalled> dedicated e-Reader platform was the
                           Sony Reader, released through Borders booksellers in the United States in
                           September 2006. It featured a greyscale screen similar to that of the
                           first- and second-generation iPod and iPod Mini, and was a surprisingly
                           multi-functioned device, able to play MP3 audio and natively display PDF,
                           ePub, Mobipocket, and MS Office document formats. Of these, PDF support
                           was handicapped by the device’s low refresh rate, which made horizontal
                           scrolling of documents that did not conform to the screen width very
                           inconvenient. Sony also introduced their own proprietary eBook format,
                           called <title rend="italic">BBeB</title> (<title rend="quotes">Broadband
                              eBook</title>), though it was not very successful, probably due to an
                           inability to purchase content on-the-go without using a PC as an
                           intermediary. Newer revisions of the device are now on sale in the US,
                           UK, and Canada, but support is flagging.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <title rend="italic">Amazon Kindle</title>
                        </label>
                        <p>In November 2007, twelve years after they sold their first physical book
                           over the internet, Amazon.com gave the e-Book a gargantuan,
                           consumer-grade push, in the form of their Kindle. The device was only on
                           sale in the United States until late 2009, when it was gradually
                           introduced into hundreds of other markets worldwide. The Kindle's loudest
                           boast, and perhaps its entire raison d'etre, was a screen made from the
                           revolutionary Vizplex, brainchild of Cambridge, MA startup E-Ink. Without
                           a backlight, Vizplex is easier on the eyes; with the help of a technique
                           called electrophoresis, Vizplex displays can freeze, without any power
                           consumption, until a user presses the ‘next page’ button. Now, a revision
                           of Vizplex is used in every major commercial e-Reader, and is arguably
                           the single greatest advantage of using a dedicated device.</p>
                        <p>Its other greatest innovation, and almost certainly its financial
                           triumph, is the ease with which it allows users to download and purchase
                           content on-the-fly without the use of a tethered PC. Amazon’s Kindle is
                           still the only device to provide free wireless 3G access to all users for
                           the purpose, and the only device <emph>not</emph> to support the open
                              <title rend="italic">ePub</title> document format, in a relatively
                           transparent effort to push its own DRM-secured, proprietary
                              eBooks.<note>Although ePub was designed to support DRM, its security
                              was compromised by hackers in 2009 and the ePub consortium has not
                              made any attempt to circumvent their efforts since.</note> Despite
                           this, Amazon has been successful in part because their content library is
                           the undisputed largest, and with their considerable resources will likely
                           remain so. The Kindle is also the only dedicated e-Reader device to
                           include a full physical keyboard, which some users may prefer for text
                           entry when searching or annotating content.</p>
                        <p>Because the Kindle was for a good while the market leader, it was they
                           who addressed many of the growing pains of e-Readers, and in some cases –
                           such as the provision of page and line numbers for scholarly use of
                           texts, as would be present in physical editions – they still provide the
                           best solution. In early 2011, Amazon released an Application Development
                           Kit (ADK) for third-party developers to build software specifically for
                           its dedicated Kindle device, though it remains in closed beta. </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>Barnes &amp; Noble Nook</label>
                        <p>Barnes &amp; Noble booksellers’ <title rend="italic">Nook</title>,
                           released in November 2009, runs on a variant of Google’s Android
                           smartphone platform, thus alleviating the need for a proprietary
                           Application Development Kit. Unlike the Amazon Kindle, it supports <title rend="italic">ePub</title> content and does not have a full keyboard.
                           There is also a version of the Nook with a colour display – named,
                           appropriately, the <title rend="italic">Nook Color</title> – which is
                           unique among dedicated e-Readers and may be ideal for heavily illustrated
                           content. Beyond this, though, newer iterations of the device have made it
                           very similar, both ergonomically and feature-wise, to the Kindle, with
                           Barnes &amp; Noble’s selection of available content impressive in its own
                           right.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>Kobo</label>
                        <p>The Kobo, developed by an independent Toronto-based firm in 2010 and
                           marketed primarily through the US <title rend="italic">Borders</title>
                           bookstore chain and <title rend="italic">Chapters</title> in Canada until
                           the former’s recent bankruptcy, was initially much less expensive than
                           its competition (at $149 CAD), and served as a budget alternative to the
                           Nook and Kindle until it effectively drove down the cost of all three
                           devices. It, too, has become strikingly similar to its brethren on modern
                           revisions, offering a near-identical feature set to the Nook (including
                           ePub) and a notably better selection of Canadian content. The Kobo’s ADK
                           is expected to be released in mid-2011.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>Apple iPad and other mobile devices</label>
                        <p>Apple’s iPad is, of course, a multifunction device, and not a true
                           dedicated e-Reader insofar as it does not use Vizplex display technology
                           (as would be inappropriate for other content displayed on an iPad). It
                           has, however, garnered an extraordinary amount of developer interest for
                           its novel form factor, and in fact all of the manufacturers of dedicated
                           e-Reader hardware now provide an iPad app<note>Along with, it is worth
                              noting, applications for the iPhone, Android, and Windows/Mac OSX
                              desktop platforms.</note> which provides most or all of the
                           functionality of a dedicated device.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Per the current software market, supplemental reading tools such as annotation
                     are typically handled by third-party application developers<note>The apparent
                        leaders in annotation functionality as of Summer 2011 are <title rend="italic">iAnnotate</title> on iPhone or iPad and <title rend="italic">RepliGo</title> on Android or Blackberry. <title rend="italic">RepliGo</title> deserves further praise for its ability to
                        reformat PDF documents into a single-screen view for easier browsing on a
                        mobile device – a powerful and rare feature.</note>, and may not necessarily
                     be compatible with the more straightforward reading environments of the
                     Kindle/Nook/Kobo apps. For example, the Kobo iPad app has been criticized for
                     deleting all stored annotations whenever the software is updated and the user’s
                     library is refreshed, making it apparent that so-called <soCalled>active
                        reading</soCalled> has not been a priority for the application’s developers.
                     There has been a clear focus on the provision of reading statistics and other
                     metrics, as evidenced by the graphical breakdown below.</p>

                  <p>Google’s Android smartphones have generally received comparable development
                     attention, and benefit from Google’s comparatively relaxed stance on allowing
                     unlicensed content which need not originate from a trusted source. However,
                     still more novel eBook applications which would be not possible on dedicated
                     hardware are for the most part being developed only for the iPad, notably an
                     interactive <title rend="italic">Alice in Wonderland</title> Storybook (<ref target="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/alice-for-the-ipad/id354537426">http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/alice-for-the-ipad/id354537426</ref>) and
                     the <title rend="italic">LiquidText</title> reading environment (<ref target="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/alice-for-the-ipad/id354537426">http://liquidtext.net/</ref>), which is discussed at length elsewhere in
                     this document.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2.3.2 Related Electronic Reading Tools</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Graham, J. (1999). <title rend="quotes">The reader's helper: a
                                 personalized document reading environment</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI Conference</title>. ACM,
                              New York. <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/302979.303139">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/302979.303139</ref> (accessed 20 July
                              2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Documents a shift in reading styles over two centuries away from
                           sequential, complete reading and toward skimming and searching for
                           relevant information, with increasing demand for need of more efficient
                           methods of extracting relevant information from documents. Presents a new
                           document reading environment, Readers Helper, which supports the reading
                           of electronic and paper documents; it analyses documents and produces a
                           relevance score for topics of interest, to help the reader decide whether
                           the document is actually worth reading in full or skimming. Also
                           automatically highlights topic of interest phrases, and presents an
                           information visualization tool that presents a dynamic representation of
                           the document to aid in navigation.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Hornbæk, K. &amp; E. Frokjær. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Reading
                                 of Electronic Documents</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings
                                 of the ACM CHI Conference</title>.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>These two relatively early studies of electronic reading environments
                           have an interesting commonality: they are both designed to help the
                           reader get some information out of the way. Whereas Graham’s <title rend="quotes">Reader’s Helper</title> allows users to browse thumbnail
                           selections of other documents related to the one they are currently
                           viewing, Hornbæk and Frokjær’s prototype allows users to minimize
                           selections of the active text, performing a sort of reverse-highlighting
                           that they call a fisheye view. Modern readers should take note that
                           concerns about information overload have stood in opposition to our
                           striving for intextuality for at least a decade hence.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Cadiz, J.J., A. Gupta, &amp; J Grudin. (2000). <title rend="quotes">Using Web annotations for asynchronous collaboration around
                                 documents</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM
                                 Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work</title>.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This is among the earliest comprehensive work on asynchronous web
                           document annotation, reporting on the inter-office use of a Microsoft
                           Word 2000 plugin, and the majority of its points still hold up well
                           today. It is curious, however, to note that they claim <quote rend="inline" source="#cadiz2000">virtually all commercial document-processing packages
                              (e.g., Microsoft Word, Lotus Notes) support some form of
                              annotations</quote>. While this has indeed been true of word
                           processing software for the decade-plus that the authors claim, this only
                           serves to make more obvious the degree to which PDF and web annotation
                           have lagged behind. We have, however, hardly lacked for advancements in
                           eleven years. In a time before ubiquitous cloud server architecture, the
                           annotation environment described by the authors more closely resembles an
                           asynchronous chat log containing symbolic links to a particular document
                           than the <soCalled>living</soCalled> documents that have been theorized
                           since. What this may tell us, however, is that simple online chats are
                           officially of the <q>want to happen</q> persuasion – in the
                              <q>information wants to be free</q> sense – and any way that we can
                           sustain them is nevertheless useful. Indeed, the frequency with which
                           users annotated documents appeared to follow a common power law, as with
                           many other collaboration systems.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Dyson, M. (2001). <title rend="quotes">The Influence of Reading
                                 Speed and Line Length of the Effectiveness of Reading from
                                 Screen</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                                 Human-Computer Studies</title>. 54.4 (2001): 585-612.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>While not about electronic reading <emph>tools</emph> per se, this
                           landmark article from a decade ago still contains one of the most
                           comprehensive treatments of how digital document layouts affect reading
                           speed for a varied audience. The author begins by reviewing reading
                           research from the 1950s through the 1970s which assessed the tradeoff in
                           reading speed versus comprehension, and notes that a range of 55 to 70
                           characters per line was and remains something of a sweet spot for
                           monospace and variable-width fonts alike. Curiously, longer line lengths
                           of up to 100 characters seem to be better for the express purpose of
                           skimming, and, of course, the idea that there can be more than one
                           optimal document layout strongly reinforces the advantages of reflowable
                           text. In 2001, this finding stood in opposition to her participants’
                           apparent preference for paginated, rather than scrolling documents, as
                           the de facto paginated document, PDF, only supported a fixed document
                           layout. Now, new formats such as <title rend="italic">ePub</title> appear
                           to combine the best of both worlds.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Baumer, E., M. Sueyoshi, &amp; B. Tomlinson. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Role of the Reader in the Activity of
                                 Blogging</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceeding of the 26th ACM
                                 Chi Conference</title>.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article, while not about a reading tool or tools <emph>per
                           se</emph>, provides an excellent thinking-through of the affordances of
                           reader discourse in electronic documents. The authors begin by noting
                           that the shift in literary theory of the 1960s and 70s toward analyzing
                           the reader’s response to literature has not quite been carried through to
                           our study of digital media. In order to understand the behaviour and
                           expectations of blog readers, they conducted an ethnographic study of
                           fifteen participants, which revealed that blog reading is a deeply
                           habitual process – simultaneously productive and time-wasting – and that
                           blogs unsurprisingly command an enormous degree of authenticity relative
                           to other written media. The study also suggests that the
                              <term>non-chronicity</term> of blogs was somehow special, in that
                           posts have a clearly defined <emph>sequence</emph> of following one after
                           another, this is the full extent to which blogs have any relevant
                           temporality. The authors believe that these factors should be taken into
                           account in the design of new and novel reading tools.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Milne, D. &amp; I.H. Witten. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Learning
                                 to Link with Wikipedia</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                                 the 17th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge
                              Mining</title>.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This paper reports on an ongoing project in automatically parsing and
                           embedding noun-phrase links in web pages, using Wikipedia as a reference.
                           Linking with Wikipedia – or, as the authors say, <term>wikifying</term>
                           pages – has so far succeeded where similar projects have failed, thanks
                           to Wikipedia’s breadth and (supposed) impartiality. For example, where
                           similar lookup engines might require a great deal of editorial effort to
                           create a functional <soCalled>dictionary</soCalled> and attempt to use
                           the long-standing WordNet lexical database for disambiguating word
                           meanings, Wikification gets by on statistical relevance judgments, using
                           one of the largest such databases in existence (dwarfing WordNet’s
                           coverage of noun phrases). In this paper, the authors explain in detail
                           their method for making these relevance judgments, noting with amusement
                           that the overall machine-derived statistical relevance for their results
                           is somehow identical to that of the aggregate relevance judgment of their
                           user study participants – 79%.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Olive, T., J.-F. Rouet, E. Francois, &amp; V. Zampa. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Summarizing Digital Documents: Effects of Alternate
                                 or Simultaneous Window Display</title>. <title rend="italic">Applied Cognitive Psychology</title> 22.4: 541-558.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This curious paper is unlike the majority of reading environment design
                           studies in that it rejects the notion that an optimal reading environment
                           is likely to be <soCalled>designed</soCalled> at all. Rather, it supports
                           the notion of reading environments being assembled post-hoc by the user –
                           grouping various tools, in various different applications, wherever
                           happens to be most convenient – and in so doing, reinforces the
                           advantages of narrow, single-column document layouts that can be made to
                           accommodate as much marginalia as possible. Curiously, in the three
                           years’ eternity such this work was published, new dedicated devices have
                           begun to wrest back away users’ ability to multitask as they see fit,
                           though it is worth noting that most e-Reader applications (along with
                           many legacy Oxford journal reading environments) have opted for
                           smaller-than-A4 page layouts.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Qayyum, M.A. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Capturing the Online
                                 Academic Reading Process</title>. <title rend="italic">Information
                                 Processing &amp; Management</title> 44.2: 581-595.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article, an extension of the author’s dissertation work, reports on
                           the electronic document reading, sharing, and interaction habits of
                           graduate students. He found that the vast majority of annotations fall
                           into just two categories – underlined or highlighted text, and anchor
                           points for some marginalia. Either selection of text (in the first case,
                           the original author’s; in the second, the reader’s) could be indexed by a
                           sufficiently powerful reading environment and presented to the reader or
                           readers as a table of contents of notes. One finding from this study
                           which seems all too logical and subverts a key assumption of open online
                           annotation systems is that many individuals do <emph>not</emph> want to
                           inherit an already-annotated document, even less so if the prior
                           annotator is anonymous. While we can learn much from the wisdom of
                           crowds, we seldom sit out to read a self-contained document with these
                           crowds in mind, as doing so can be confusing or overwhelming. It is thus
                           a sensible assumption that the annotation layer should be secondary to
                           the original text in a well-designed reading environment – and worth
                           considering when this assumption may <emph>not</emph> hold true.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Siemens, R., C. Leitch, A. Blake, K. Armstrong, &amp; J. Willinsky.
                              (2009). <title rend="quotes">It May Change My Understanding of the
                                 Field: Understanding Reading Tools for Scholars and Professional
                                 Readers</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanitites
                                 Quarterly</title> 3.4.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>The authors report on a study of user opinions on using the scholarly
                           article reading tools embedded within the Public Knowledge Project’s
                              <title rend="italic">Open Journal Systems</title>. According to the
                           authors, the single most interesting finding from this research was that
                           the reading tools were overwhelmingly found to be better at locating
                           articles within their respective scholarly context than actually
                           assisting with individual readings. The most likely reason volunteered
                           for this is that there are simply not many productive ways that software
                           can intervene in readers’ variously idiosyncratic means of interacting
                           with isolated documents (with the exception of annotation, which not
                           well-supported by Open Journal Systems at the time of the study). Indeed,
                           their think-aloud protocol evinced almost as many descriptions of
                           individual reading processes than commentary on the tools themselves.
                           Among the tools that did work well was an engine for discovering authors’
                           related work, assisting in readers’ credibility judgments of authors whom
                           they had not previously been introduced to (and all the more so in the
                           context of Open Access). Among those that did not work well for many
                           readers were broader-scale <q>find more like this</q> options, usually
                           because the article metadata which was mined for search terms was
                           insufficient to compete with the relatively trivial alternative of
                           readers formulating their own Google Scholar search.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Kamil, M.L, &amp; E.B. Moje. (2011). <title rend="italic">The
                                 Handbook of Reading Research</title>. Taylor &amp; Francis. p.
                              1040.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This lengthy volume, while not about electronic reading per se, is a
                           comprehensive single source for much of what we currently know about the
                           reading process from the perspective of education. The book’s short first
                           chapter deals with how controlled reading studies are best conductive, in
                           both an ethnographic and computational context. After this, the book
                           turns to focus entirely on the reading process itself: in the second
                           chapter, through the life cycle; in the third, at various levels of
                           linguistic depth; and in the fourth, in the teaching and learning of
                           reading. The fifth and final chapter, also the most diverse, deals with
                           many sociocultural facets of reading – such as how popular culture has
                           altered our approach to language and literacy, how second languages are
                           learned, and how literacy can thrive in informal contexts. The lattermost
                           is perhaps of particular note for reading specifically non-academic
                           content on the web.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>MacFadyen, H. (2011). <title rend="quotes">The Reader's Devices:
                                 The Affordance of e-Book Readers</title>. <title rend="italic">Dalhousie Journal of Interdisciplinary Management</title>
                              7.1.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article, a polite lamentation of sorts on what it is we are gaining
                           and losing by migrating away from paper toward digital documents, begins
                           with a telling anecdote: a search of the Google Books corpus reveals that
                           there were relatively few published references to the wonderful smell of
                           books prior to 1990, after which mounting concerns about the
                           disappearance of this smell made them more and more prevalent. The author
                           reviews the abortive (and variously worrying, for still-relevant reasons
                           ranging from deprecated libraries to privacy concerns) attempts at
                           popularizing e-Books prior to Amazon’s Kindle, which is <quote rend="inline" source="#macfayden2011">as much a device used to buy books as it is a device
                              used to read books</quote>. She believes, however, that the somewhat
                           collapsed physical extension of e-Books – a <quote rend="inline" source="#macfayden2011">brown
                              paper wrapper</quote> on the bus, containing entire libraries – will
                           eventually speed the intellectual work of readers working across multiple
                           texts and wanting to copy and paste at will, though seems to believe
                           unequivocally that we are not there just yet.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Marshall, C.C. (2010). <title rend="italic">Reading and Writing the
                                 Electronic Book</title>. Morgan &amp; Claypool. pg. 185.</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>Cathy Marshall’s <title rend="italic">Reading and Writing the Electronic
                              Book</title>, from the excellent <title rend="italic">Synthesis
                              Lectures</title> (<title rend="quotes">on Information Concepts,
                              Retrieval, and Services</title>) series, is an exhaustive and readable
                           review of research on interacting with electronic documents over the past
                           two decades. The introduction is a retrospective approach to how reading
                           has changed with the advent of hypermedia. There is a review of the long
                           relationship between typography and reading behaviour, and entire
                           chapters on annotation and social reading. After a brief discussion of
                           how reading is best understood and studied, the book’s second half
                           focuses largely on metadata, text markup, and other issues concerning
                           file formats. Although the book’s relatively recent publication date
                           makes the absence of any discussion about modern platforms such as the
                           iPad or file formats such as <title rend="italic">ePub</title> all the
                           more disappointing, and there are some subjects (such as DRM) which the
                           author is unable and perhaps justifiably unwilling to give full
                           recognition in the allotted space, this is very probably the most
                           comprehensive review of electronic reading, as a process and a history,
                           currently available.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Tashman, C.S. &amp; W.K. Edwards. (2011). <title rend="quotes">LiquidText: A Flexible, Multitouch Environment to Support Active
                                 Reading</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI
                                 Conference</title>. <ref target="http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~keith/pubs/chi2011-liquidtext.pdf">http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~keith/pubs/chi2011-liquidtext.pdf</ref>
                              (accessed on 10 July 2011).</bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This very promising report on a prototype active reading system for
                           tablet devices was presented at the 2011 ACM <title rend="italic">CHI</title> (Computer-Human Interaction) conference in anticipation
                           of the software’s release later this year. The authors detail a user
                           study which was designed with the express purpose of determining which
                           components of active reading (annotation being the obvious long-standing
                           example) are still better-supported by pen and paper than they are in
                           electronic reading environments. Their findings, on which their system
                           design is predicated, are summarized as follows: the messiest and most
                           valuable insights are usually located in a cross-document context, not in
                           a single PDF or Word file but in the margins of Powerpoints and email
                           threads. As such, LiquidText is being built to preserve the context of
                           text snippets once they have been dragged and dropped (or, as per the
                           tablet paradigm, pinched or pulled) out of their original home, while
                           still allowing them to be dynamically re-formed elsewhere, and
                           highlighted or bookmarked accordingly. Some exemplar screenshots are
                           attached.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>
                           <bibl>Thayer, A., C.P. Lee, L.H. Hwang, H. Sales, P. Sen, and N. Dalal.
                              (2011). <title rend="quotes">The Imposition and Superimposition of
                                 Digital Reading Technology</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI Conference</title>. </bibl>
                        </label>
                        <p>This article recounts the trials and tribulations of the University of
                           Washington’s Amazon Kindle DX pilot program for students. Like many
                           articles reviewed here, it mentions the XLibris digital paper prototype
                           (Fuji-Xerox, Palo Alto) of years prior as the high bar to beat in the
                           field, despite the fact that it was never widely adopted. The authors of
                           this article are quite critical of the Kindle DX, noting that the degree
                           to which students expect to be able to skim physical textbooks is totally
                           unlike their expectations of speed-reading PDFs which are usually read on
                           screen, and the Kindle is not up to this task. In addition, the Kindle
                           was found to be poorly-suited to both horizontal scrolling and annotation
                           (both of which have been addressed in later revisions of the hardware).
                           Kinesthetic clues such as flipping to a dog-eared corner halfway through
                           a textbook were also badly missed, and some complex illustrations were
                           evidently not rendered properly. The researchers conclude somewhat
                           unequivocally that this incarnation of the Kindle is not nearly as
                           well-suited to multimodal academic reading as its consumer success might
                           suggest.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Social Networking Tools for Professional Readers in the Humanities</head>
            <p>A whitepaper survey, carried out by Cara Leitch for the ETCL [-2009].</p>
            <div>
               <head>3.1 Introduction: Responding to the Needs of Professional Readers in the
                  Humanities</head>
               <p>The key activities of professional readers in the humanities include: evaluating
                  the scholarly value of research material, communicating with other scholars, and
                  managing physical and electronic collections of research material. In our recent
                  study of expert readers and their experience with the Open Journal System, we
                  observed that participants were most satisfied with the online reading tools when
                  they modeled existing reading strategies. Participants expressed dissatisfaction
                  when the online reading tools proved less effective than their existing
                  strategies.</p>
               <p>As expert readers also become expert at using online tools, they will demand an
                  even higher level of sophistication from an online reading environment.
                  Professional readers are becoming increasingly aware of the potential of social
                  networking tools as scholarly research tools. A successful online reading
                  environment would integrate social networking tools in a way that extends readers’
                  existing strategies. The value of such an environment to the professional reader
                  would be that he or she would not have to use a variety of disjointed tools.
                  Instead, he or she would be able to perform the same tasks from within the reading
                  environment. To date, no one social networking tool models all three main aspects
                  of readers’ existing strategies. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.2 Social Networking Tools: An Overview</head>
               <p>
                  <term>Social software</term> refers to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#software2007">software which supports, extends, or derives added value
                        from human social behaviour</quote>
                     <ptr target="#software2007" loc="16"/>
                  </cit>. Donath and boyd write, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#software2007">underlying all the networking sites are a core set of
                        assumptions -- that there is a need for people to make more connections,
                        that using a network of existing connections is the best way to do so, and
                        that making this easy to do is a great benefit</quote>
                     <ptr target="#software2007" loc="71"/>
                  </cit>. The common factor among almost all social software is the idea of sharing
                     <ptr target="#gross2005" loc="71"/>. What exactly is being shared differs from
                  network to network but almost all provide tools to create and maintain an
                  identity, connect with other users, exchange information, and classify/sort that
                  information.</p>
               <p>Wellman et al. suggest <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#wellman2006">that on-line relationships are based more on shared
                        interests and less on shared social characteristics</quote>
                     <ptr target="#wellman2006" loc="231"/>
                  </cit> while Donath and boyd note <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#software2007">to turn an encounter into a connection, there generally
                        must be some common ground</quote>
                     <ptr target="#software2007" loc="77"/>
                  </cit>. The New Media Consortium refers to the internet as a <q>third place</q> after home and work where people <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#nmc2007">connect with friends, watch television, listen to music,
                        build a sense of togetherness with people across the world, and provide
                        expressions of ourselves . . .</quote>
                     <ptr target="#nmc2007" loc="3"/>
                  </cit>. According to Ellison, Steinfeld and Lampe, this <term>third place</term>
                  does not weaken offline social ties, rather <quote rend="inline" source="#ellison2007">may indeed be
                     used to support relationships and keep people in contact, even when life
                     changes move them away from each other. </quote> Ellison, Steinfeld and Lampe
                  also note, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ellison2007">in addition to helping student populations, this use of
                        technology could support a variety of populations, including professional
                        researchers, neighborhood and community members, employees of companies, or
                        others who benefit from maintained ties</quote>
                     <ptr target="#ellison2007"/>
                  </cit>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.3 Specific Social Networking Tools Relevant to Professional Readers' Existing
                  Strategies</head>
               <div>
                  <head>3.3.1 Evaluating: Identity Presentation Tools</head>
                  <p>The ability to create and maintain an online identity is one of the key
                     features common to social networking tools. Boyd writes <quote rend="block" source="#boyd2008a">
                        Social network sites are based around profiles, a form of individual (or,
                        less frequently, group) home page, which offers a description of each
                        member. In addition to text, images, and video created by the member, the
                        social network site profile also contains comments from other members and a
                        public list of the people that one identifies as Friends within the network
                           <ptr target="#boyd2008a" loc="123"/>.</quote> Pew Internet’s <title rend="quotes">Digital Footprints</title> study reports that <quote rend="inline" source="#madden2007">one in ten internet users have a job that requires them to
                        self-promote or market their name online</quote> and <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#madden2007">voluntarily posted text, images, audio, and video has
                           become a cornerstone of engagement with Web 2.0 applications. Indeed,
                           being <q>findable and knowable</q> online is often
                           considered an asset in participatory culture where one’s personal
                           reputation is increasingly influenced by information others encounter
                           online </quote>
                        <ptr target="#madden2007" loc="iii, 4"/>
                     </cit>. Girgensohn and Lee suggest that one of the benefits of creating an
                     maintaining a profile on a social networking site is the opportunity to create
                     a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#girgensohn2007">persistent and verifiable identity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#girgensohn2007" loc="127"/>
                     </cit>, while Boyd and Ellison note, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#boyd2007">what makes social network sites unique is not that they
                           allow individuals to meet strangers, but rather that they enable users to
                           articulate and make visible their social networks</quote>
                        <ptr target="#boyd2007"/>
                     </cit>. Given the importance expert readers place on markers of authority such
                     as credentials and past publications, it is in the individual’s best interest
                     to exert some control over his or her online identity. Creating and maintaining
                     an online profile would help give humanities scholars this control and would
                     allow them to include the kind of information expert readers use when
                     evaluating the value of research material. In their discussion of Peers, a
                     social networking application created and used by design and consulting firm
                     Avenue A | Razorfish, Cohen and Clemens focus on the ability of social
                     networking tools to foster collaboration. Like most social networking tools,
                     Peers gives users the ability to create profiles, share information, and
                     collaborate on projects. Users also have the ability to rate projects posted by
                     other members in the same discipline. Cohen and Clemens write, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2005">in this structure for presenting individual work, the
                           standard for quality work naturally becomes higher. Work deliverables
                           that were prior routine now become viewable, visible and available to a
                           highly critical audience</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cohen2005" loc="524"/>
                     </cit>. Cohen and Clemens emphasis is on the influence the peer-rating system
                     has on quality of work. A rating system in a reading environment for expert
                     readers would have a slightly different focus. At the site Faculty of 1000,
                     scientists rank research articles in order to highlight the best of new
                     research. For expert readers in the humanities, a rating system would help
                     readers evaluate the scholarly importance of an article and assess the
                     relevance and trustworthiness of its author. If ratings were incorporated into
                     an author’s online profile, readers would have ready access to information
                     about an author’s recent publication history and information about how well his
                     or her research has been received. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>3.3.2 Communicating: Commenting Tools</head>
                  <p>Expert readers learn about new ideas and develop existing ones by engaging in
                     scholarly communication with their peers and colleagues. Online, these readers
                     participate in online forums, email listservs, and use commenting tools on
                     blogs and other social networking sites. Kathleen Fitzpatrick writes <quote rend="block" source="#fitzpatrick2007">Scholars operate in a range of conversations, from classroom
                        conversations with students to conference conversations with colleagues;
                        scholars need to have available to them not simply the library model of
                        texts circulating amongst individual readers but also the coffee house model
                        of public reading and debate. This interconnection of individual nodes into
                        a collective fabric is, of course, the strength of the network, which not
                        only physically binds individual machines but also has the ability to bring
                        together the users of those machines, at their separate workstations, into
                        one communal whole. <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2007"/>
                     </quote> Hoadley and Kilner write, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hoadley2007">knowledge-building communities are a particular kind of
                           community of practice focused on learning. Based on scholarly
                           communities, knowledge-building communities take as an explicit goal the
                           development of individual and collective understanding</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hoadley2007" loc="32"/>
                     </cit>. They describe conversation as the method by which information becomes
                     knowledge <ptr target="#hoadley2007" loc="33"/>. An online community that
                     models a community of practice combines content with communication. Social
                     networking applications provide tools to facilitate both information sharing
                     and dialogue.</p>
                  <p>Noah Wardrip-Fruin recently participated in an experiment using CommentPress
                     and the blog <title rend="italic">Grand Text Auto</title> to explore how social
                     networking tools might be used in the peer-review process. In January 2008,
                     Wardrip-Fruin released the manuscript of his forthcoming book, <title rend="italic">Expressive Processing</title>, to members of the Grand Text
                     Auto community. Using CommentPress, community members were able to comment on
                     the text paragraph by paragraph. In his introduction to the experiment,
                     Wardrip-Fruin observes <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#wardripfruin2008">I soon realized that blogs . . . contain raw research,
                           early results and other useful information that never gets presented at
                           conferences</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wardripfruin2008"/>
                     </cit>. By using CommentPress to collect early reviews of his manuscript,
                     Wardrip-Fruin has been able to engage with the scholarly community in a new and
                     less formal way. The editorial suggestions made in the comments do not carry
                     the weight of traditional peer review, but they provide an interesting interim
                     step between private circulation of a manuscript in process and official
                     submission of a manuscript to a publisher for peer review.</p>
                  <p>In a follow-up conversation between Wardrip-Fruin, Ben Vershbow from the
                     institute for the Future of the Book (creators of CommentPress), Doug Sery of
                     MIT Press (publishers of Wardrip-Fruin’s book) and Don Waters of the Andrew W.
                     Mellon Foundation, there is an attempt made to clarify the role of open peer
                     review in the publishing process. Waters writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ifbook2008">there is a sense in which the experiment is not aimed
                           at <soCalled>peer review</soCalled> at all in the sense that peer review
                           assesses the qualities of a work to help the publisher determine whether
                           or not to publish it. What the exposure of the work-in-progress to the
                           community does, besides the extremely useful community-building activity,
                           is provide a mechanism for a function that is now all but lost in
                           scholarly publishing, namely <term>developmental editing</term>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr target="#ifbook2008"/>
                     </cit>.</p>
                  <p>The use of CommentPress as an editing tool suggests a number of applications
                     for an online reading tool. Larry Sanger writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sanger2007">strong collaboration – which is made possible on a wide
                           scale by the Internet – goes one step further. Not only are there
                           multiple authors, and not only are those people each others’ editors, but
                           there is no set group of people who are the authors and editors of the
                           work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sanger2007"/>
                     </cit>. Rather than being used only to leave notes or comments on material that
                     has already been published, readers could participate in the development of
                     works in progress and, in turn, benefit from the participation of other members
                     of the scholarly community.</p>
                  <p>The ability to leave a paragraph-specific comment rather than a comment at the
                     end of a text makes CommentPress a useful annotation tool. Authors could invite
                     community members to clarify aspects of his or her work that reflect their
                     field of expertise. This makes possible a fluid, up-to-date system of reference
                     that goes beyond the citation of published material. Readers could use
                     CommentPress to leave questions or comments that are tied to specific passages
                     in a text. Multiple users could engage in multiple conversations around
                     different points in the text rather than in one long, threaded conversation at
                     the end of the text. This kind of communication system combines the reach of
                     global community with the specificity of local conversation. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>3.3.3 Managing: Reference Management Tools</head>
                  <p>Searching, retrieving, classifying, and organizing research material is a
                     primary activity of professional readers. Expert readers employ a variety of
                     strategies ranging from simple filing systems to elaborate systems of
                     classification and storage. Reference management tools such as Zotero,
                     Citeulike, and Connotea allow users to find, store, and organize research
                     materials online. This kind of organization system has the benefit of giving
                     the user access to his or her research material from any computer connected to
                     the internet.</p>
                  <p>The use of folksonomy tagging in reference management tools can improve on a
                     reader’s existing research strategies by providing him or her with a flexible
                     and easily accessible way of organizing research according to his or her own
                     criteria. These tools also allow users to share research collections with
                     colleagues and find material relevant to their interests in other collections.
                     Alexander describes the role of social bookmarking in higher education as a
                     tool for <quote rend="inline" source="#alexander2006">collaborative information discovery</quote>. He
                     identifies a number of benefits to using social bookmarking: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#alexander2006">finding people with related interests can magnify one’s
                           work by learning from others or by leading to new collaborations. . .
                           [and] the practice of user-created tagging can offer new perspectives on
                           one’s research, as clusters of tags reveal patterns (or absences) not
                           immediately visible . . .</quote>
                        <ptr target="#alexander2006"/>
                     </cit>. User incentives for tagging include the ability to quickly retrieve
                     research material, to share relevant material with colleagues, and to express
                     an opinion or make a public statement about one’s interests <ptr target="#marlow2006" loc="34–35"/>. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conclusion</head>
               <p>One of the challenges faced by expert readers is that more and more of their
                  reading and research is being conducted online. Rather than replace expert
                  readers’ existing strategies, a successful online reading environment would extend
                  and improve those strategies. The use of social networking tools would contribute
                  to this extension and improvement, particularly in the key areas of evaluation,
                  communication, and management of resources.</p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Guide to Selected Social Networking Sites and Tools</head>
            <p>
               <label>CiteULike</label> (<ref target="http://www.citeulike.org">http://www.citeulike.org</ref>) is a tool based on the principle of social
               bookmarking, aiming to promote and develop the sharing of scientific references
               amongst researchers. In the same way that it is possible to catalog web pages (with
               Furl and del.icio.us) or photographs (with Flickr), scientists can share information
               on academic papers with specific tools (like CiteULike) developed for that purpose.
               The website is sponsored by the publisher Springer Science+Business Media. Richard
               Cameron developed CiteULike in November 2004 and in 2006 Oversity Ltd. was
               established to develop and support CiteULike. When browsing issues of research
               journals, small scripts stored in bookmarks (bookmarklets) allow one to import
               articles from repositories like PubMed, and CiteULike supports many more. Then the
               system attempts to determine the article metadata (title, authors, journal name, etc)
               automatically. Users can organize their libraries with freely chosen tags and this
               produces a folksonomy of academic interests. (From Wikipedia).</p>
            <p>
               <label>Faculty of 1000</label> (<ref target="http://www.f1000.com">http://www.f1000.com</ref>) is a research tool designed to help scientists find
               and assess scholarly articles. Individual scientists select, rate, and classify
               research articles. Those ratings are published alongside comments from the reviewers.
               Users of Faculty of 1000 can browse highly-rated articles, search using specific
               criteria, and sign up to be notified by email when new research is published.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Flickr</label> (<ref target="http://www.flickr.com">http://www.flickr.com</ref>) allows users to upload, store, classify, and share
               photos. Photos are classified using tags that make it possible for other users to
               search photo collections. Community is encouraged through the formation of interest
               groups.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Flock</label> (<ref target="http://www.flock.com">http://www.flock.com</ref>)
               is a web browser that integrates features of social networking tools. From within the
               browser, users can access information from a number of social networking sites,
               including Facebook, flickr, Twitter, blogger, and WordPress blogs. While using Flock,
               the user is connected to his or her social network without having to visit each site
               individually. The user receives constantly updated information about his or her
               contacts. In addition, Flock facilitates information sharing by allowing the user to
               email or message contacts, update a blog, and upload material from the browser
               toolbar. Flock is highly customizable; every user determines what information is
               displayed in his or her social browser.</p>
            <p>
               <label>H20 Playlist</label> (<ref target="h2obeta.law.harvard.edu/home.do">h2obeta.law.harvard.edu/home.do</ref>) is a service hosted by the Berkman Center
               for Internet and Society at Harvard Law School. The purpose of H2O Playlist is to
               facilitate the sharing of information in the form of course syllabi and reading
               lists. Educators and students using the site are encouraged to communicate with
               others in order to learn more about their field of study. Users categorize their
               ‘playlists’ using tags in order to facilitate searching.</p>
            <p>
               <label>iLeonardo</label> (<ref target="http://www.ileonardo.com">http://www.ileonardo.com</ref>) allows users to create online collections called
               Notebooks where they can store information in a variety of forms. Notebooks can be
               shared with other users and users can help create large, public repositories of
               information. Users can create and maintain profiles that show the user’s recent
               activity alongside personal information. iLeonardo is currently in private Beta. </p>
            <p>
               <label>Linkedin</label> (<ref target="http://www.linkedin.com">http://www.linkedin.com</ref>) is a social networking site geared to
               professionals. It provides an opportunity for networking within a structured
               environment. Users create a profile and a network made up of their business and
               personal connections.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Lyceum</label> (<ref target="http://lyceum.ibiblio.org">lyceum.ibiblio.org</ref>) works with the WordPress publishing platform to create
               stand-alone, multiuser blogs. A multi-user blog facilitates communication within
               groups and with those outside the group. Each user can create his or her own
               individual page and contribute to the group blog.</p>
            <p>
               <label>MySpace</label> (<ref target="http://www.myspace.com">http://www.myspace.com</ref>) is popular with young adults, and resembles
               Facebook in that it is a social networking site used primarily for personal
               expression and communicating with a social group.</p>
            <p>
               <label>NatureNetwork</label> (<ref target="http://network.nature.com">network.nature.com</ref>) connects scientists from around the world in an online
               environment that facilitates information sharing and collaboration. Users can create
               and maintain an individual or group profile, create connections to other users,
               communicate with other users through blogs, and access information about upcoming
               events. In addition to fostering global communication, Nature Network also focuses on
               creating local networks. Currently, there are local networks for Boston and
               London.</p>
            <p>
               <label>NoseRub</label> (<ref target="http://www.noserub.com">http://www.noserub.com</ref>) allows users to combine information from a number
               of social networking sites into one application. Rather than a service or
               application, NoseRub is a protocol that can be adapted by the individual user and run
               on his or her own server. An example of what can be done with NoseRub is available on
               their website.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pownce</label> (<ref target="http://www.pownce.com">http://www.pownce.com</ref>) is a social networking tool that allows users to
               share information, including images, text, and links. Unlike other social networking
               tools, Pownce is a desktop application. Users do not have to be using a web browser
               in order to use Pownce.</p>
            <p>
               <label>PulseWire</label> (<ref target="www.worldpulsemagazine.com/pulsewire">www.worldpulsemagazine.com/pulsewire</ref>) is currently in development, and will
               provide an interactive community for women around the world. It is designed to
               facilitate information sharing and communication.</p>
            <p>
               <label>RentAThing</label> (<ref target="http://www.rentathing.org">www.rentathing.org</ref>) is designed to facilitate resource sharing by measuring
               and communicating information about a user’s reputation. A high reputation score
               tells lenders that the borrower is considered trustworthy. Users build reputation
               scores by providing collateral and references from other users.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Twitter</label> (<ref target="http://www.twitter.com">www.twitter.com</ref>)
               is a ‘micro-blogging’ service that facilitates social networking through the exchange
               of short status messages. Twitter has been adopted as a communication tool by
               political candidates, demonstrating that a social networking tool can be expanded
               beyond its original purpose. Rather than sharing personal updates (<q>I am
               hungry</q>), some Twitter users are now using the tool to share information about
               upcoming events (<q>Meeting Monday at 11:30</q>) and as a reminder service (<q>Don’t
                  forget to attend Monday’s meeting</q>).</p>
            <p>
               <label>Writeboard</label> (<ref target="http://www.writeboard.com">www.writeboard.com</ref>) is an online writing environment that allows users to
               create, edit, and share web-based documents. Invitations to collaborators are sent
               through email. Users can track changes to a text as they edit as well as compare two
               versions of the same text.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Zotero</label> (<ref target="http://www.zotero.org">www.zotero.org</ref>) is
               an extension for Firefox that allows users to manage research collections from within
               their browser. One of Zotero’s most important features is its ability to
               automatically identify and capture citation information on a web page. Users can then
               capture citation information, classify it using tags, and generate citations. Future
               developments of Zotero will include the ability to share collections with other users
               and to receive information about new material as it becomes available.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <div>
               <head>Background and History</head>
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Backstrom, Lars et al. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Group Formation in
                           Large Social Networks: Membership, Growth, and Evolution</title>.
                        Proceedings of KDD’06, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, 20-23, 2006. New
                        York: ACM.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Beer, David and Roger Burrows. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Sociology
                           and, of, and in Web 2.0: Some Initial Considerations</title>. <title rend="italic">Sociological Research Online</title> 12.5. <ref target="http:// www.socresonline.org.uk/12/5/17.html">http://
                           www.socresonline.org.uk/12/5/17.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Boase, Jeffrey. (2006). <title rend="italic">The Strength of Internet
                           Ties</title>. Washington, DC: Pew Intenret and American Life
                        Project.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Friends, Friendsters, and Top
                           8: Writing Community into Being on Social Network Sites</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 11.12. 25 Jan. <ref target="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_12/boyd/index.html">http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_12/boyd/index.html</ref>
                        (accessed Jan 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">None of This is Real: Identity
                           and Participation in Friendster</title>. <title rend="italic">Structures
                           of Participation</title>. Ed. Joe Karaganis. <ref target="www.danah.org/papers/NoneOfThisIsReal.pdf">www.danah.org/papers/NoneOfThisIsReal.pdf</ref> (accessed 23 Jan
                        2007.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>
                        <title rend="quotes">The Significance of Social Software</title>. (2007).
                        BlogTalks Reloaded: Social Software Research &amp; Cases. Ed. Thomas N. Berg
                        and Jan Schmidt. Norderstedt. 15-30.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah michele. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Friendster and Publicly
                           Articulated Social Networking</title>. Proceedings of CHI 2004, Vienna,
                        Austria, 24-29. April 2004. New York: ACM. 1279-82.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah michele and N.B. Ellison (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social
                           Network Sites: Definition, History, and Scholarship</title>. <title rend="italic">. Journal of Computer-Meditated Communication 13.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/boyd.ellison.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/boyd.ellison.html</ref>
                        </title> (accessed 25 Jan 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Donath, J. and d. boyd. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Public Displays of
                           Connection</title>. <title rend="italic">BT Technology Journal</title>
                        22.4: 71-82.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Ellison, Nicole B., Charles Steinfeld and Cliff Lampe. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Benefits of Facebook <soCalled>Friends</soCalled>:
                           Social Capital and College Students' Use of Social Network Sites</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Meditated Communication</title>
                        12.4 <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol12/issue4/ellison.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol12/issue4/ellison.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Garton, Laura, Caroline Haythornthwaite and Barry Wellman. (1997). <title rend="quotes">Studying Online Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Meditated Communication</title> 3.1.
                           <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue1/garton.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue1/garton.html</ref> (accessed 23 Jan
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Gips, Jonathan et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">SNIF: Social
                           Networking in Fur</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                           CHI</title>, 2005. Portland, OR, USA. 2-7 April. New York: ACM.
                        1391-94.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Girgensohn, Andreas and Alison Lee. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Making
                           Web Sites Be Places for Social Interaction</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CSCW 2002</title>. New Orleans, LA. USA. New York: ACM,
                        2002. 136-45.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Golbeck, Jennifer and Michael M. Wasser. (2007). <title rend="quotes">SocialBrowsing: Integrating Social Networks and Web Browsing</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI 2007</title>. San Jose, CA, USA:
                        28 April–3 May 2007. New York: ACM. 2381-86.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Golder, Scott A., Dennis Wilkinson and Bernardo A. Huberman. (2007).
                           <title rend="quotes">Rhythms of Social Interaction: Messaging with a
                           Massive Online Network</title>. <title rend="italic">3rd International
                           Conference on Communities and Technologies</title>. (CT2007). East
                        Lansing, MI, USA. June 28-30. <ref target="http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl/papers/facebook/facebook.pdf">http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl/papers/facebook/facebook.pdf</ref>
                        (accessed 23 Jan 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Humphreys, Lee. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Mobile Social Networks and
                           Social Practice: A Case Study of Dodgeball</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title> 13.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/humphreys.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/humphreys.html</ref> (accessed 25
                        Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Kumar, Ravi, Jasmine Novak and Andrew Tomkins. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Structure and Evolution of Online Social Networks</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Proceedings KDD ’06</title>. Philadelphia, PA. 20-23
                        Aug. 2006. New York: ACM. 611-17.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Lampe, Cliff, Nicole Ellison and Charles Steinfeld. (2007). <title rend="quotes">A Familiar Face(book): Profile Elements as Signals in on
                           Online Social Network</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                           2007 Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>. San Jose,
                        CA. New York: ACM Press. 435-44.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Mayer, Adalbert and Steven L. Puller. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The
                           Old Boy (and Girl) Network: Social Network Formation on University
                           Campuses</title>. Journal of Public Economics 92: 329-47.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Mislove, Alan et al. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Measurement and
                           Analysis of Online Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of IMC’07</title>. San Diego, CA, USA. 24-26 Oct. 2007. New
                        York: AMC. 29-42.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>New Media Consortium. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social Networking, the
                              <soCalled>Third Place</soCalled>, and the Evolution of
                           Communication</title>. New Media Consortium. <ref target="www.nmc.org/evolution-communication">www.nmc.org/evolution-communication</ref> (accessed 23 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Parks, Malcolm R. (1996). <title rend="quotes">Making Friends in
                           Cyberspace</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated
                           Communication</title> 1.4. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol1/issue4/parks.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol1/issue4/parks.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Perer, Adam. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Making Sense of Social
                           Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI 2006</title>.
                        Montreal, PQ. 22-27 April 2006. New York: ACM. 1779-82.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Ridings, Catherine M. and David Gefen. (2004). <title>Virtual Community
                           Attraction: Why People Hang Out Online</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title> 10.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol10/issue1/ridings_gefen.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol10/issue1/ridings_gefen.html</ref> (accessed
                        23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Tyler, Tom R. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Is the Internet Changing
                           Social Life? It Seems the More Things Change, the More They Stay the
                           Same</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Social Issues</title> 58.1:
                        195-205.</bibl>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Collaboration</head>
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Cachia, Romina, Ramón Compañó and Olivier Da Costa. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Grasping the Potential of Online Social Networks for
                           Foresight</title>. <title rend="italic">Technological Forecasting and
                           Social Change</title> 74: 1179-1203.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Cohen, Tracy and Ben Clemens. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Social
                           Networks for Creative Collaboration</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of C&amp;C ’05.</title> London, UK. 12-15 April, 2005. New
                        York: ACM. 252-55.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Dugan, Casey et al. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Dogear Game: A
                           Social Bookmark Recommender System</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP ’07</title>. Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 4-7 Nov.
                        2007. New York: ACM. 387-390.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Ehrlich, Kate, Ching-Yung Lin and Vicky Griffiths-Fisher. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Searching for Experts in the Enterprise: Combining Text and
                           Social Network Analysis</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                           GROUP ’07</title>. Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 4-7 Nov. 2007. New York:
                        ACM. 117-126.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. (2007). <title rend="quotes">CommentPress: New
                           (Social) Structures for New (Networked) Texts</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic Publishing</title> 10.3. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.3336451.0010.305">http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.3336451.0010.305</ref> (accessed 11 Jan.
                        2007).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Hoadley, Christopher M. and Peter G. Kilner. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Using Technology to Transform Communities of Practice into
                           Knowledge-Building Communities</title>. SIGGROUP Bulletin 25.1: 31-40.
                     </bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>if:book. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Developing Books in Networked
                           Communities: A Conversation with Don Waters</title>. <title rend="italic">if:book</title> Blog 4 Feb. 2008. <ref target="http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/2008/02/developing_books_with_networked_communities.html">http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/2008/02/developing_books_with_networked_communities.html</ref>
                        (accessed 4 Feb. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Licamele, Louis et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Capital and Benefit
                           in Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                           LinkKDD’05</title>. Chicago, IL. 21 Aug. 2005. New York: AMC.
                        44-51.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Marlow, Cameron et al. (2006). <title rend="quotes">HT06, Tagging Paper,
                           Taxonomy, Flickr, Academic Article, To Read</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings for HT’06</title>. Odense, Denmark. 22-25 Aug. 2006. New
                        York: ACM. 31-39.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>McDonald, David W. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Recommending
                           Collaboration with Social Networks: A Comparative Evaluation</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI 2003</title>. Ft. Lauderdale, FL.
                        5-10 April, 2003. New York: ACM. 593-600.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Mori, Junichiro, Tatsuhiko Sugiyama and Yutaka Matsuo. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Real-world Oriented Information Sharing Using Social
                           Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP’05</title>.
                        Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 6-9 Nov. 2005. New York: ACM. 81-84.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Sanger, Larry. (2007). <title rend="quotes">How to Think about Strong
                           Collaboration among Professionals</title>. Keynote address. Handelsblatt
                        IT Congress. Bonn, Germany. 30 Jan. 2007. <ref target="http://www.citizendium.org/collab_prof.html">http://www.citizendium.org/collab_prof.html</ref> (accessed 17 Dec.
                        2007).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Shami, N. Sadat et al. (2007). <title rend="quotes">That’s What Friends
                           are for: Facilitating <soCalled>Who Knows What</soCalled> Across Group
                           Boundaries</title>. Proceedings of GROUP ’07, Sanibel Islands, FL, USA.
                        4-7 Nov. 2007. New York: ACM. 379-382.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Shevade, Bageshree, Hari Sundaram and Lexing Xie. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Modeling Personal and Social Network Context for Event
                           Annotation in Images</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of JCDL
                           ’07</title>. Vancouver, BC. 18-23 June, 2007. New York: ACM. 127-34.
                     </bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Wardrip-Fruin, Noah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Expressive Processing:
                           An Experiment in Blog-Based Peer Review</title>. <title rend="italic">Grand Text Auto</title> 22 Jan. 2008.
                        http://grandtextauto.org/2008/01/22/expressive-processing-an-experiment-in-blog-based-peer-review/
                        (accessed 28 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Wellman, Barry et al. (1996). <title rend="quotes">Computer Networks as
                           Social Networks: Collaborative Work, Telework, and Virtual
                           Community</title>. <title rend="italic">Annual Review of
                           Sociology</title> 22: 213-38.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Zhang, Jun and Mark S. Ackerman. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Searching
                           for Expertise in Social Networks: A Simulation of Potential
                           Strategies</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP’05</title>.
                        Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 6-9 Nov. 2005. New York: ACM. 71-80.</bibl>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Education &amp; Libraries</head>
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Johnson, Shelley Henson, Justin Ball and David Wiley. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Folksemantic: Web 2.0 Tools for Teaching and
                           Learning</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2007 New Media
                           Consortium Summer Conference</title>. New Media Consortium, 2007. <ref target="http://www.nmc.org/2007-proceedings">http://www.nmc.org/2007-proceedings</ref>. (accessed 23 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Landis, Cliff. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social Networking Sites:
                           Getting Friendly With our Users</title>. <title rend="italic">College and
                           Research Libraries News</title> 68.11. 21 May 2007. <ref target="http://www.ala.org/ala/acrl/acrlpubs/crlnews/backissues2007/december07/socialnetwrkg.cfm">http://www.ala.org/ala/acrl/acrlpubs/crlnews/backissues2007/december07/socialnetwrkg.cfm</ref>
                        (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>New Media Consortium and Educause Learning Initiative. (2007). <title rend="italic">The Horizon Report: 2007 Edition</title>. New Media
                        Consortium. <ref target="http://www.nmc.org/horizon/2007/report">http://www.nmc.org/horizon/2007/report</ref> (accessed 23 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Secker, Jane and Gwyneth Price. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Libraries,
                           Social Software and Distance Learners: Blog It, Tag It, Share
                        It!</title>. New Review of Information Networking 13.1: 39-52.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Stephens, Michael and Maria Collins. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Web
                           2.0, Library 2.0, and the Hyperlinked Library</title>. <title rend="italic">Serials Review</title> 33.4: 253-56.</bibl>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Identity, Privacy &amp; Trust</head>
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Alexander, Bryan. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Web 2.0: A New Wave of
                           Innovation for Teaching and Learning?</title>
                        <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title> 41.2: 32-44. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/ero/article/web-20-new-wave-innovation-teaching-and-learning">http://www.educause.edu/ero/article/web-20-new-wave-innovation-teaching-and-learning</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Bargh, John A., Katelyn Y. A. McKenna and Grainne M. Fitzsimons. (2002)
                           <title rend="quotes">Can You See the Real Me? Activation and Expression
                           of the <soCalled>True Self</soCalled> on the Internet</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Social Issues</title> 58.1: 33-48.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Barnes, Susan B. (2006) <title rend="quotes">A Privacy Paradox: Social
                           Networking in the United States</title>. <title rend="italic">First
                           Monday</title> 11.9. <ref target="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_9/barnes/index.html">http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_9/barnes/index.html</ref>
                        (accessed 25 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social Network Sites: Public,
                           Private, or What?</title>
                        <title rend="italic">Knowledge Tree</title> 13. <ref target="http://kt.flexiblelearning.net.au/tkt2007/?page_id=28">http://kt.flexiblelearning.net.au/tkt2007/?page_id=28</ref> (accessed 25
                        Jan 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>boyd, danah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Why Youth ♥ Social Network
                           Sites: The Role of Networked Publics in Teenage Social Life</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Youth, Identity, and Digital Media</title>. Ed.
                        David Buckingham. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. 119-142. <ref target="www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf">www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf</ref> (accessed 23 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl> Christopherson, Kimberly M. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Positive
                           and Negative Implications of Anonymity in Internet Social Interactions:
                              <q>On the Internet, Nobody Knows You’re a Dog</q>
                        </title>. <title rend="italic">Computers in Human Behaviour</title> 23:
                        3038-56.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Davies, Julia. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Display, Identity and the
                           Everyday: Self-Presentation Through Online Image Sharing</title>. <title rend="italic">Discourse: Studies in the Cultural Politics of
                           Education</title> 28.4: 549-64.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Dwyer, Cathy. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Digital Relationships in the
                              <title rend="quotes">MySpace</title> Generation: Results From a
                           Qualitative Study</title>. 40th Hawaii International Conference on System
                        Sciences (HICSS), Waikoloa, HI.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Dwyer, Catherine, Starr Roxanne Hiltz and Katia Passerini. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Trust and Privacy Concern Within Social Networking Sites: A
                           Comparison of Facebook and MySpace</title>. Proceedings of the Thirteenth
                        Americas Conference on Information Systems, Keystone, Colorado, 9-12
                        August.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Golbeck, Jennifer and James Hendler. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Inferring Binary Trust Relationships in Web-Based Social
                           Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">ACM Transactions on Internet
                           Technology</title> 6.4: 497-529.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Gross, Ralph and Alessandro Acquisti. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Information Revelation and Privacy in Online Social Networks</title>.
                           <title rend="italic">Proceedings of WPES’05</title>. Alexandria,
                        Virginia. 7 Nov. 2005. New York: ACM. 71-80.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Lange, Patricia G. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Publicly Private and
                           Privately Public: Social Networking on YouTube</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title> 13.1.
                           <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/lange.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/lange.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan.
                        2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Madden, Mary et al. <title rend="italic">Digital Footprints: Online
                           Identity Management and Search in the Age of Transparency</title>.
                        (2007). Washington, DC: Pew Internet and American Life Project. <ref target="http://www.pewinternet.org/pdfs/PIP_Digital_Footprints.pdf">http://www.pewinternet.org/pdfs/PIP_Digital_Footprints.pdf</ref>
                        (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl> Mathieson, S. A. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Face-off in
                        Oxford</title>. Info Security October 2007 32-35. Online Computer Library
                        Center. <title rend="italic">Sharing, Privacy and Trust in Our Networked
                           World: A Report to the OCLC Membership</title>. Dublin, Ohio:
                        OCLC.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Tidwell, Lisa Collins and Joseph B. Walther. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Computer-Mediated Communication Effects on Disclosure, Impressions, and
                           Interpersonal Evaluations: Getting to Know One Another a Bit at a
                           Time</title>. <title rend="italic">Human Communication Research</title>
                        28.3: 317-48.</bibl>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <bibl>Tufekci, Zeynep. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Can You See Me Now?
                           Audience and Disclosure Regulation in Online Social Network
                        Sites</title>. <title rend="italic">Bulletin of Science, Technology and
                           Society</title>. <ref target="http://userpages.umbc.edu/~zeynep/papers/ZeynepCanYouSeeMeNowBSTS.pdf">http://userpages.umbc.edu/~zeynep/papers/ZeynepCanYouSeeMeNowBSTS.pdf</ref>.
                        (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Alexander 2006" xml:id="alexander2006" key="alexander2006">Alexander,
               Bryan. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Web 2.0: A New Wave of Innovation for Teaching
                  and Learning?</title>
               <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review</title> 41.2: 32-44. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/ero/article/web-20-new-wave-innovation-teaching-and-learning">http://www.educause.edu/ero/article/web-20-new-wave-innovation-teaching-and-learning</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Backstrom et al. 2006" xml:id="backstrom2006" key="backstrom2006">Backstrom, Lars et al. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Group Formation in Large Social
                  Networks: Membership, Growth, and Evolution</title>. Proceedings of KDD’06,
               Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, 20-23, 2006. New York: ACM.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bargh et al 2002" xml:id="bargh2002" key="bargh2002">Bargh, John A.,
               Katelyn Y. A. McKenna and Grainne M. Fitzsimons. (2002) <title rend="quotes">Can You
                  See the Real Me? Activation and Expression of the <soCalled>True Self</soCalled>
                  on the Internet</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Social Issues</title>
               58.1: 33-48.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Barnes 2006" xml:id="barnes2006" key="barnes2006">Barnes, Susan B. (2006)
                  <title rend="quotes">A Privacy Paradox: Social Networking in the United
                  States</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 11.9. <ref target="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_9/barnes/index.html">http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_9/barnes/index.html</ref> (accessed 25
               Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Baumer et al. 2008" xml:id="baumer2008" key="baumer2008">Baumer, E., M.
               Sueyoshi, &amp; B. Tomlinson. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Role of the
                  Reader in the Activity of Blogging</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceeding of the
                  26th ACM Chi Conference</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Beer and Burrows 2007" xml:id="beer2007" key="beer2007">Beer, David and
               Roger Burrows. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Sociology and, of, and in Web 2.0: Some
                  Initial Considerations</title>. <title rend="italic">Sociological Research
                  Online</title> 12.5. <ref target="http:// www.socresonline.org.uk/12/5/17.html">http:// www.socresonline.org.uk/12/5/17.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Boase 2006" xml:id="boase2006" key="boase2006">Boase, Jeffrey. (2006).
                  <title rend="italic">The Strength of Internet Ties</title>. Washington, DC: Pew
               Intenret and American Life Project.</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd 2004" xml:id="boyd2004" key="boyd2004a">boyd, danah michele. (2004).
                  <title rend="quotes">Friendster and Publicly Articulated Social
               Networking</title>. Proceedings of CHI 2004, Vienna, Austria, 24-29. April 2004. New
               York: ACM. 1279-82.</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd 2006" xml:id="boyd2006" key="boyd2006">boyd, danah. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Friends, Friendsters, and Top 8: Writing Community into Being on
                  Social Network Sites</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 11.12. 25
               Jan. <ref target="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_12/boyd/index.html">http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue11_12/boyd/index.html</ref> (accessed Jan
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd 2007a" xml:id="boyd2007a" key="boyd2007a">boyd, danah. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social Network Sites: Public, Private, or What?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Knowledge Tree</title> 13. <ref target="http://kt.flexiblelearning.net.au/tkt2007/?page_id=28">http://kt.flexiblelearning.net.au/tkt2007/?page_id=28</ref> (accessed 25 Jan
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd 2008" xml:id="boyd2008" key="boyd2008b">boyd, danah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">None of This is Real: Identity and Participation in
                  Friendster</title>. <title rend="italic">Structures of Participation</title>. Ed.
               Joe Karaganis. <ref target="www.danah.org/papers/NoneOfThisIsReal.pdf">www.danah.org/papers/NoneOfThisIsReal.pdf</ref> (accessed 23 Jan 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd 2008a" xml:id="boyd2008a" key="boyd2008a">boyd, danah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Why Youth ♥ Social Network Sites: The Role of Networked Publics in
                  Teenage Social Life</title>. <title rend="italic">Youth, Identity, and Digital
                  Media</title>. Ed. David Buckingham. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. 119-142. <ref target="www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf">www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf</ref> (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="boyd and Ellison 2007" xml:id="boyd2007" key="boyd2007b">boyd, danah
               michele and N.B. Ellison (2007). <title rend="quotes">Social Network Sites:
                  Definition, History, and Scholarship</title>. <title rend="italic">. Journal of
                  Computer-Meditated Communication 13.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/boyd.ellison.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/boyd.ellison.html</ref>
               </title> (accessed 25 Jan 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Brown and Adler 2008" xml:id="brown2008" key="brown2008">Brown, John Seely
               and Richard P. Adler. <title rend="quotes">Minds of Fire: Open Education, the Long
                  Tail, and Learning 2.0</title>. <title rend="italic">Educause Review</title> 43.1:
               2008. 16-20, 22, 24, 26, 28, 30, 32. <ref target="http://webpages.csus.edu/~sac43949/PDFs/minds_on_fire.pdf ">http://webpages.csus.edu/~sac43949/PDFs/minds_on_fire.pdf </ref> (accessed on 19
               July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Brumfiel n.d." xml:id="brumfiel" key="brumfiel">Brumfiel, Geoff. <title rend="quotes">Breaking the Convention?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Nature</title> 459.7250: 1050-1051.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cachia, Compañó, and Da Costa 2007" xml:id="cachia2007" key="cachia2007">Cachia, Romina, Ramón Compañó and Olivier Da Costa. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Grasping the Potential of Online Social Networks for Foresight</title>. <title rend="italic">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title> 74:
               1179-1203.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cadiz et al. 2000" xml:id="cadiz2000" key="cadiz2000">Cadiz, J.J., A.
               Gupta, &amp; J Grudin. (2000). <title rend="quotes">Using Web annotations for
                  asynchronous collaboration around documents</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative
               Work</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cambridge et al. 2005" xml:id="cambridge2005" key="cambridge2005">Cambridge, Darren, Soren Kaplan and Vicki Suter. (2005). <title>Community of
                  Practice Design Guide: A Step-by-Step Guide for Designing &amp; Cultivating
                  Communities of Practice in Higher Education.</title> Educause. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/ELI/CommunityofPracticeDesignGuide/160068 ">http://www.educause.edu/ELI/CommunityofPracticeDesignGuide/160068</ref> (accessed
               18 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Carmody 2010" xml:id="carmody2010" key="carmody2010">Carmody, Tim. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">Copia, Social Reading App/Network/Store, Comes Alive</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 18 Nov. <ref target="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/11/copia-social-reading-appnetworkstore-comes-alive/">http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/11/copia-social-reading-appnetworkstore-comes-alive/</ref>
               (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Christopherson 2007" xml:id="christopherson2007" key="christopherson2007">
               Christopherson, Kimberly M. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Positive and Negative
                  Implications of Anonymity in Internet Social Interactions: <q>On the Internet,
                     Nobody Knows You’re a Dog</q>
               </title>. <title rend="italic">Computers in Human Behaviour</title> 23:
               3038-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ciber2010" label="CIBER 2010" key="ciber2010">CIBER (University College,
               London). (2010). Social Media Research and Workflow. <ref target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/social-media-report.pdf">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/social-media-report.pdf</ref>
               (accessed July 11, 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cohen and Clements 2005" xml:id="cohen2005" key="cohen2005a">Cohen, Tracy
               and Ben Clemens. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Social Networks for Creative
                  Collaboration</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of C&amp;C ’05.</title>
               London, UK. 12-15 April, 2005. New York: ACM. 252-55.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cohen 2008" xml:id="cohen2008" key="Cohen2008b">Cohen, Daniel J. (2008).
                  <title rend="quotes">Creating Scholarly Tools and Resources for the Digital
                  Ecosystem: Building Connections in the Zotero Project</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 13.8: n. pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017 ">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2233/2017</ref>
               (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2009" label="Cohen 2009" key="cohen2009">Cohen, Daniel J. (2009).
                  <title rend="quotes">Engaging and Creating Virtual Communities</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Cultural Heritage Online Conference</title>.
               Florence, Italy. 28-32. <ref target="http://www.rinascimento-digitale.it/eventi/conference2009/proceedings-2009/Proceedings-part1.pdf ">http://www.rinascimento-digitale.it/eventi/conference2009/proceedings-2009/Proceedings-part1.pdf
               </ref> (accessed 18 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Curtis 2010" xml:id="curtis2010" key="curtis2010">Curtis, Benjamin. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">Google's Sidewiki and the Real Innovations</title>. <title rend="italic">Medical Marketing and Media</title> 45.1: 31. <ref target="http://www.mmm-online.com/googles-sidewiki-and-the-real-innovations/article/160456/">http://www.mmm-online.com/googles-sidewiki-and-the-real-innovations/article/160456/</ref>
               (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Davies 2007a" xml:id="davies2007a" key="davies2007a">Davies, Julia. (2007)
                  <title rend="quotes">Display, Identity and the Everyday: Self-Presentation Through
                  Online Image Sharing</title>. <title rend="italic">Discourse: Studies in the
                  Cultural Politics of Education</title> 28.4: 549-64.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Davis and Huttenlocher 1995" xml:id="davis1995" key="davis1995">Davis,
               James R. and Daniel P. Huttenlocher. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Shared Annotation
                  for Cooperative Learning</title>.<title rend="italic">The First International
                  Conference on Computer Support for Collaborative Learning</title>. Indiana
               University. Bloomington, Indiana, USA: L. Erlbaum Associates Inc., pp 84-88.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Donath and boyd 2004" xml:id="donath2004" key="donath2004">Donath, J. and
               d. boyd. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Public Displays of Connection</title>. <title rend="italic">BT Technology Journal</title> 22.4: 71-82.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dugan et al. 2007" xml:id="dugan2007" key="dugan2007">Dugan, Casey et al.
               (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Dogear Game: A Social Bookmark Recommender
                  System</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP ’07</title>. Sanibel
               Islands, FL, USA. 4-7 Nov. 2007. New York: ACM. 387-390.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dwyer 2007" xml:id="dwyer2007" key="dwyer2007">Dwyer, Cathy. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Digital Relationships in the <title rend="quotes">MySpace</title>
                  Generation: Results From a Qualitative Study</title>. 40th Hawaii International
               Conference on System Sciences (HICSS), Waikoloa, HI.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dwyer et al 2007" xml:id="dwyeretal2007" key="Dwyeretal2007">Dwyer,
               Catherine, Starr Roxanne Hiltz and Katia Passerini. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Trust and Privacy Concern Within Social Networking Sites: A Comparison of
                  Facebook and MySpace</title>. Proceedings of the Thirteenth Americas Conference on
               Information Systems, Keystone, Colorado, 9-12 August.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dyson 2001" xml:id="dyson2001" key="dyson2001">Dyson, M. (2001). <title rend="quotes">The Influence of Reading Speed and Line Length of the Effectiveness
                  of Reading from Screen</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                  Human-Computer Studies</title>. 54.4 (2001): 585-612.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ehrlich, Lin, and Griffiths-Fisher 2007" xml:id="ehrlich2007" key="ehrlich2007">Ehrlich, Kate, Ching-Yung Lin and Vicky Griffiths-Fisher. (2007).
                  <title rend="quotes">Searching for Experts in the Enterprise: Combining Text and
                  Social Network Analysis</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP
                  ’07</title>. Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 4-7 Nov. 2007. New York: ACM.
               117-126.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ellison, Steinfeld and Lampe 2007" xml:id="ellison2007" key="ellison2007">Ellison, Nicole B., Charles Steinfeld and Cliff Lampe. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The Benefits of Facebook <soCalled>Friends</soCalled>: Social Capital and College
                  Students' Use of Social Network Sites</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                  Computer-Meditated Communication</title> 12.4 <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol12/issue4/ellison.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol12/issue4/ellison.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="estelles2010" label="Estelles 2010" key="estelles2010">Estelles, Enrique,
               Esther de Moral, and Fernando Gonzalez. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Social
                  Bookmarking Tools as Facilitators of Learning and Research Collaborative
                  Processes: The Diigo Case.</title>
               <title>Interdisciplinary Journal of E-Learning and Learning Objects</title>. 6:
               175-191. <ref target="http://www.ijello.org/Volume6/IJELLOv6p175-191Estelles683.pdf ">http://www.ijello.org/Volume6/IJELLOv6p175-191Estelles683.pdf</ref> (accessed 19
               June 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Fernheimer et al. 2011" xml:id="fernheimer2011" key="fernheimer2011">Fernheimer, Janice W., Lisa Litterio, and James Hendler. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Transdisciplinary ITexts and the Future of Web-Scale
                  Collaboration</title>. <title>Journal of Business and Technical
                  Communication</title> 25.3: 322-337.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Fitzpatrick 2007" xml:id="fitzpatrick2007" key="fitzpatrick2007">Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. (2007). <title rend="quotes">CommentPress: New (Social)
                  Structures for New (Networked) Texts</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                  Electronic Publishing</title> 10.3. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.3336451.0010.305">http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.3336451.0010.305</ref> (accessed 11 Jan.
               2007).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Fitzpatrick 2009" xml:id="fitzpatrick2009" key="fitzpatrick2009a">Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Peer-to-Peer Review and the
                  Future of Scholarly Authority</title>. <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title>
               48.2: 124-129.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Garton, Haythornthwaite and Wellman 1997" xml:id="garton1997" key="garton1997">Garton, Laura, Caroline Haythornthwaite and Barry Wellman. (1997).
                  <title rend="quotes">Studying Online Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Meditated Communication</title> 3.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue1/garton.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue1/garton.html</ref> (accessed 23 Jan
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gielen 2010" xml:id="gielen2010" key="gielen2010">Gielen, Nina. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">Handheld E-Book Readers and Scholarship: Report and Reader
                  Survey</title>. <title rend="italic">ACLS Humanities E-book</title>: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.humanitiesebook.org/heb-whitepaper-3.html">http://www.humanitiesebook.org/heb-whitepaper-3.html</ref> (accessed 19 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gips 2005" xml:id="gips2005" key="gips2005">Gips, Jonathan et al. (2005).
                  <title rend="quotes">SNIF: Social Networking in Fur</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI</title>, 2005. Portland, OR, USA. 2-7 April. New York: ACM.
               1391-94.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Girgensohn and Lee 2007" xml:id="girgensohn2007" key="girgensohn2007">Girgensohn, Andreas and Alison Lee. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Making Web Sites Be
                  Places for Social Interaction</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CSCW
                  2002</title>. New Orleans, LA. USA. New York: ACM, 2002. 136-45.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Golbeck and Hendler 2006" xml:id="golbeck2006" key="golbeck2006">Golbeck,
               Jennifer and James Hendler. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Inferring Binary Trust
                  Relationships in Web-Based Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">ACM
                  Transactions on Internet Technology</title> 6.4: 497-529.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Golbeck and Wasser 2007" xml:id="golbeck2007" key="goldbeck2007">Golbeck,
               Jennifer and Michael M. Wasser. (2007). <title rend="quotes">SocialBrowsing:
                  Integrating Social Networks and Web Browsing</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI 2007</title>. San Jose, CA, USA: 28 April–3 May 2007. New
               York: ACM. 2381-86.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Golder, Wilkinson and Huberman 2007" xml:id="golder2007" key="golder2007">Golder, Scott A., Dennis Wilkinson and Bernardo A. Huberman. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Rhythms of Social Interaction: Messaging with a Massive Online
                  Network</title>. <title rend="italic">3rd International Conference on Communities
                  and Technologies</title>. (CT2007). East Lansing, MI, USA. June 28-30. <ref target="http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl/papers/facebook/facebook.pdf">http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl/papers/facebook/facebook.pdf</ref> (accessed
               23 Jan 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Graham 1999" xml:id="graham1999" key="graham1999">Graham, J. (1999). <title rend="quotes">The reader's helper: a personalized document reading
                  environment</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI
                  Conference</title>. ACM, New York. <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/302979.303139">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/302979.303139</ref> (accessed 20 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greenhow2009" label="Greenhow 2009" key="greenhow2009">Greenhow,
               Christine. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Social Scholarship: Applying Social
                  Networking Technologies to Research Practices</title>. <title rend="italic">Knowledge Quest</title> 37.4: 42-47.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gross and Acquisti 2005" xml:id="gross2005" key="gross2005">Gross, Ralph
               and Alessandro Acquisti. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Information Revelation and
                  Privacy in Online Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                  WPES’05</title>. Alexandria, Virginia. 7 Nov. 2005. New York: ACM. 71-80.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Guy and Tonkin 2006" xml:id="guy2006" key="guy2006">Guy, Marieke and Emma
               Tonkin. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Folksonomies: Tidying up Tags?</title>. <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 12.1: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january06/guy/01guy.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january06/guy/01guy.html</ref> (accessed 11 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hammond et al. 2005" xml:id="hammond2005" key="hammond2005">Hammond, Tony
               et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Social Bookmarking Tools (I): A General
                  Review</title>. <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 11.4: n. pag. <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/hammond/04hammond.html">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/hammond/04hammond.html</ref> (accessed 14 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hartley2010" label="Hartley 2010" key="hartley2010">Hartley, Diane et al.
               (2010). <title rend="italic">Assessing the Future Landscape of Scholarly
                  Communication: An Exploration of Faculty Values and Needs in Seven
                  Disciplines</title>. UC Berkeley Center for Studies in Higher Education. <ref target="http://escholarship.org/uc/cshe_fsc">http://escholarship.org/uc/cshe_fsc</ref> (accessed 19 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hendry et al. 2006" xml:id="hendry2006" key="hendry2006">Hendry, David G.,
               J.R. Jenkins, and Joseph F. McCarthy. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Collaborative
                  Bibliography</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Processing and
                  Management</title> 42.3: 805-825.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hoadley and Kilner 2007" xml:id="hoadley2007" key="hoadley2007">Hoadley,
               Christopher M. and Peter G. Kilner. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Using Technology to
                  Transform Communities of Practice into Knowledge-Building Communities</title>.
               SIGGROUP Bulletin 25.1: 31-40. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Hopkins 2010" xml:id="hopkins2010" key="hopkins2010">Hopkins, Curt. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">Mendeley Throws Open the Doors to Academic Data</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 29 Apr. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/mendeley_introduces_academic_catalog_search.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/mendeley_introduces_academic_catalog_search.php</ref>
               (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hornbæk and Frokjær 2001" xml:id="hornbaek2001" key="hornbaek2001">Hornbæk,
               K. &amp; E. Frokjær. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Reading of Electronic
                  Documents</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI
                  Conference</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Humphreys 2007" xml:id="humphreys2007" key="humphreys2007">Humphreys, Lee.
               (2007). <title rend="quotes">Mobile Social Networks and Social Practice: A Case Study
                  of Dodgeball</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated
                  Communication</title> 13.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/humphreys.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/humphreys.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan.
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hunter et al. 2010" xml:id="hunter2010" key="hunter2010">Hunter, Jane et
               al. (2010). <title rend="quotes">The Open Annotation Collaboration: A Data Model to
                  Support Sharing and Interoperability of Scholarly Annotations</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2010: Conference Abstracts</title>. London,
               United Kingdom: Office for Humanities Communication; Centre for Computing in the
               Humanities. 175-178.</bibl>
            <bibl label="if:book 2008" xml:id="ifbook2008" key="ifbook2008">if:book. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Developing Books in Networked Communities: A Conversation with Don
                  Waters</title>. <title rend="italic">if:book</title> Blog 4 Feb. 2008. <ref target="http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/2008/02/developing_books_with_networked_communities.html">http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/2008/02/developing_books_with_networked_communities.html</ref>
               (accessed 4 Feb. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Johnson et al 2007" xml:id="johnson2007" key="johnson2007a">Johnson,
               Shelley Henson, Justin Ball and David Wiley. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Folksemantic: Web 2.0 Tools for Teaching and Learning</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2007 New Media Consortium Summer
                  Conference</title>. New Media Consortium, 2007. <ref target="http://www.nmc.org/2007-proceedings">http://www.nmc.org/2007-proceedings</ref>. (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kamil and Moje 2011" xml:id="kamil2011" key="kamil2011">Kamil, M.L, &amp;
               E.B. Moje. (2011). <title rend="italic">The Handbook of Reading Research</title>.
               Taylor &amp; Francis. p. 1040.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kjellberg 2010" xml:id="kjellberg2010" key="kjellberg2010">Kjellberg, Sara.
               (2010). <title rend="quotes">I Am a Blogging Researcher: Motivations for Blogging in
                  a Scholarly Context</title>. <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 15.8: n.
               pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2962/2580</ref>
               (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kumar, Novak and Tomkins 2006" xml:id="kumar2006" key="kumar2006">Kumar,
               Ravi, Jasmine Novak and Andrew Tomkins. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Structure and
                  Evolution of Online Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings KDD
                  ’06</title>. Philadelphia, PA. 20-23 Aug. 2006. New York: ACM. 611-17.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lampe, Ellison and Steinfeld 2007" xml:id="lampe2007" key="lampe2007">Lampe, Cliff, Nicole Ellison and Charles Steinfeld. (2007). <title rend="quotes">A
                  Familiar Face(book): Profile Elements as Signals in on Online Social
                  Network</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2007 Conference on Human
                  Factors in Computing Systems</title>. San Jose, CA. New York: ACM Press.
               435-44.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Landis 2007" xml:id="landis2007" key="landis2007">Landis, Cliff. (2007).
                  <title rend="quotes">Social Networking Sites: Getting Friendly With our
                  Users</title>. <title rend="italic">College and Research Libraries News</title>
               68.11. 21 May 2007. <ref target="http://www.ala.org/ala/acrl/acrlpubs/crlnews/backissues2007/december07/socialnetwrkg.cfm">http://www.ala.org/ala/acrl/acrlpubs/crlnews/backissues2007/december07/socialnetwrkg.cfm</ref>
               (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lange 2007" xml:id="lange2007" key="lange2007">Lange, Patricia G. (2007).
                  <title rend="quotes">Publicly Private and Privately Public: Social Networking on
                  YouTube</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated
                  Communication</title> 13.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/lange.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/lange.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan.
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lardinois 2009" xml:id="lardinois2009" key="lardinois2009">Lardinois,
               Frederic. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Reframe It Brings Facebook, Twitter, &amp; Web
                  Luminaries to Its Annotation Tool</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 30 Mar. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/reframe_integrates_facebook_and_twitter.php ">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/reframe_integrates_facebook_and_twitter.php</ref>
               (accessed 7 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Licamele et al 2005" xml:id="licamele2005" key="licamele2005">Licamele,
               Louis et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Capital and Benefit in Social
                  Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of LinkKDD’05</title>. Chicago,
               IL. 21 Aug. 2005. New York: AMC. 44-51.</bibl>
            <bibl label="MacFadyen 2011" xml:id="macfadyen2011" key="macfadyen2011">MacFadyen, H.
               (2011). <title rend="quotes">The Reader's Devices: The Affordance of e-Book
                  Readers</title>. <title rend="italic">Dalhousie Journal of Interdisciplinary
                  Management</title> 7.1.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Madden et al 2007" xml:id="madden2007" key="madden2007">Madden, Mary et al.
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Footprints: Online Identity Management and Search in
                  the Age of Transparency</title>. (2007). Washington, DC: Pew Internet and American
               Life Project. <ref target="http://www.pewinternet.org/pdfs/PIP_Digital_Footprints.pdf">http://www.pewinternet.org/pdfs/PIP_Digital_Footprints.pdf</ref> (accessed 23
               Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Marlow et al 2006" xml:id="marlow2006" key="marlow2006">Marlow, Cameron et
               al. (2006). <title rend="quotes">HT06, Tagging Paper, Taxonomy, Flickr, Academic
                  Article, To Read</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings for HT’06</title>.
               Odense, Denmark. 22-25 Aug. 2006. New York: ACM. 31-39.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Maron and Smith 2009" xml:id="maron2009" key="maron2009">Maron, Nancy L.
               and K. Kirby Smith. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Current Models of Digital Scholarly
                  Communication: Results of an Investigation Conducted by Ithaka for the Association
                  of Research Libraries</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic
                  Publishing</title>. 12.1: n. pag. <ref target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0012.105?rgn=main;view=fulltext">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/j/jep/3336451.0012.105?rgn=main;view=fulltext</ref>
               (accessed 13 July 2011). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marshall1997" label="Marshall 1997" key="marshall1997a">Marshall,
               Catherine C. <title rend="quotes">Annotation: From Paper Books to the Digital
                  Library.</title> (1997). <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second ACM
                  International Conference on Digital Libraries</title>. Philadelphia, PA: ACM. pp
               131-40. Print. <ref target="http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/~marshall/dl97.pdf">http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/~marshall/dl97.pdf</ref> (accessed on July 14,
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Marshall 2010" xml:id="marshall2010" key="marshall2010">Marshall, C.C.
               (2010). <title rend="italic">Reading and Writing the Electronic Book</title>. Morgan
               &amp; Claypool. pg. 185.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mathieson 2007" xml:id="mathieson2007" key="mathieson2007"> Mathieson, S.
               A. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Face-off in Oxford</title>. Info Security October
               2007 32-35. Online Computer Library Center. <title rend="italic">Sharing, Privacy and
                  Trust in Our Networked World: A Report to the OCLC Membership</title>. Dublin,
               Ohio: OCLC.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mayer and Puller 2008" xml:id="mayer2008" key="mayer2008">Mayer, Adalbert
               and Steven L. Puller. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The Old Boy (and Girl) Network:
                  Social Network Formation on University Campuses</title>. Journal of Public
               Economics 92: 329-47.</bibl>
            <bibl label="McDonald 2003" xml:id="mcdonald2003" key="mcdonald2003">McDonald, David W.
               (2003). <title rend="quotes">Recommending Collaboration with Social Networks: A
                  Comparative Evaluation</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI
                  2003</title>. Ft. Lauderdale, FL. 5-10 April, 2003. New York: ACM. 593-600.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Milne and Witten 2008" xml:id="milne2008" key="milne2008">Milne, D. &amp;
               I.H. Witten. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Learning to Link with Wikipedia</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Information and
                  Knowledge Mining</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mislove 2007" xml:id="mislove2007" key="mislove2007">Mislove, Alan et al.
               (2007). <title rend="quotes">Measurement and Analysis of Online Social
                  Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of IMC’07</title>. San Diego,
               CA, USA. 24-26 Oct. 2007. New York: AMC. 29-42.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mollet 2011" xml:id="mollet2011" key="mollet2011">Mollet, Amy. (2011).
                  <title rend="quotes">Taking a Leaf Out of Poliakoff's Book: Embracing New Online
                  Platforms as Necessary for the Positive Survival of Academic Impact and
                  Debate</title>. <title rend="italic">Impact of Social Sciences</title>. 9 June.
                  <ref target="http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2011/06/09/poliakoff-gearty-online-academic-impac/                                  ">http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2011/06/09/
                  poliakoff-gearty-online-academic-impac/ </ref> (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mori, Sugiyama, and Matsuo 2005" xml:id="mori2005">Mori, Junichiro,
               Tatsuhiko Sugiyama and Yutaka Matsuo. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Real-world
                  Oriented Information Sharing Using Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP’05</title>. Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 6-9 Nov. 2005. New
               York: ACM. 81-84.</bibl>
            <bibl label="New Media Consortium 2007" xml:id="nmc2007">New Media Consortium. (2007).
                  <title rend="quotes">Social Networking, the <soCalled>Third Place</soCalled>, and
                  the Evolution of Communication</title>. New Media Consortium. <ref target="www.nmc.org/evolution-communication">www.nmc.org/evolution-communication</ref> (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nikolov2009" label="Nikolov 2009" key="nikolov2009">Nikolov, Roumen.
               (2009). <title rend="quotes">Towards University 2.0: A Space Where Academic Education
                  Meets Corporate Training</title>. Arnhem, The Netherlands: IPROF-09: ICT
               Professionalism: a Global Challenge. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10506/136">http://hdl.handle.net/10506/136</ref> (accessed 15 June 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="O'Donnell 2010" xml:id="odonnell2010" key="odonnell2010">O'Donnell, James
               J. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Do You Like Your E-Reader?: Six Takes from
                  Academics</title>. <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>
               56.38: n.pag. <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/Do-You-Like-Your-E-Reader-/65840/">http://chronicle.com/article/Do-You-Like-Your-E-Reader-/65840/</ref> (accessed 14
               July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Olive et al. 2008" xml:id="olive2008" key="olive2008">Olive, T., J.-F.
               Rouet, E. Francois, &amp; V. Zampa. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Summarizing Digital
                  Documents: Effects of Alternate or Simultaneous Window Display</title>. <title rend="italic">Applied Cognitive Psychology</title> 22.4: 541-558.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ovsiannikov1999" label="Ovsiannikov 1999" key="ovsiannikov1999">Ovsiannikov, Ilia A., Michael A. Arbib, and Thomas H. Mcneill. (1999). <title rend="quotes">Annotation Technology</title>. <title rend="italic">International
                  Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title> 50.4: 329-362.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Parks 1996" xml:id="parks1996" key="parks1996">Parks, Malcolm R. (1996).
                  <title rend="quotes">Making Friends in Cyberspace</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title> 1.4. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol1/issue4/parks.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol1/issue4/parks.html</ref> (accessed 25 Jan.
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Perer 2006" xml:id="perer2006" key="perer2006">Perer, Adam. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Making Sense of Social Networks</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CHI 2006</title>. Montreal, PQ. 22-27 April 2006. New York: ACM.
               1779-82.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Priem and Costello 2010" xml:id="priem2010" key="priem2010">Priem, Jason
               and Kaitlin Light Costello. (2010) <title rend="quotes">How and Why Scholars Cite on
                  Twitter</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ASIS&amp;t Annual
                  Meeting</title>. Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, USA. <ref target="http://www.asis.org/asist2010/proceedings/proceedings/ASIST_AM10/submissions/201_Final_Submission.pdf">http://www.asis.org/asist2010/proceedings/proceedings/ASIST_AM10/submissions/201_Final_Submission.pdf</ref>
               (accessed 8 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Priem and Hemminger 2010" xml:id="priem2010a" key="priem2010a">Priem, Jason
               and Bradley M. Hemminger. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Scientometrics 2.0: Toward New
                  Metrics of Scholarly Impact on the Social Web</title>. <title rend="italic">First
                  Editions</title> 15.7: n. pag. <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2874/2570">http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2874/2570</ref>
               (accessed 13 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Procter et al. 2010" xml:id="procter2010" key="procter2010">Procter, Rob et
               al. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Adoption and Use of Web 2.0 in Scholarly
                  Communications</title>. <title rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the
                  Royal Society A</title> 368.1926: 4039-4056.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Purdy 2010" xml:id="purdy2010" key="purdy2010">Purdy, James P. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">The Changing Space of Research: Web 2.0 and the Integration
                  of Research and Writing Environments</title>. <title rend="italic">Computers and
                  Composition</title> 27.1: 48-58.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Qayyum 2008" xml:id="qayyum2008" key="qayyum2008">Qayyum, M.A. (2008).
                  <title rend="quotes">Capturing the Online Academic Reading Process</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Processing &amp; Management</title> 44.2:
               581-595.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Research Information Network 2010" xml:id="rin2010" key="network2010">Research Information Network. (2010). <title rend="italic">If You Build It, Will
                  They Come? How Researchers Perceive and Use Web 2.0</title>. <ref target="http://www.rin.ac.uk/our-work/communicating-and-disseminating-research/use-and-relevance-web-20-researchers">http://www.rin.ac.uk/our-work/communicating-and-disseminating-research/use-and-relevance-web-20-researchers</ref>
               (accessed 9 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ridings 2004" xml:id="ridings2004" key="ridings2004">Ridings, Catherine M.
               and David Gefen. (2004). <title>Virtual Community Attraction: Why People Hang Out
                  Online</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Computer-Mediated
                  Communication</title> 10.1. <ref target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol10/issue1/ridings_gefen.html">http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol10/issue1/ridings_gefen.html</ref> (accessed 23 Jan.
               2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ross2011" label="Ross 2011" key="ross2011">Ross, Claire et al. (2011).
                  <title rend="quotes">Enabled Backchannel: Conference Twitter Use by Digital
                  Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 67.2:
               214-237.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sanger 2007" xml:id="sanger2007" key="sanger2007">Sanger, Larry. (2007).
                  <title rend="quotes">How to Think about Strong Collaboration among
                  Professionals</title>. Keynote address. Handelsblatt IT Congress. Bonn, Germany.
               30 Jan. 2007. <ref target="http://www.citizendium.org/collab_prof.html">http://www.citizendium.org/collab_prof.html</ref> (accessed 17 Dec. 2007).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Santo and Lucas 2009" xml:id="santo2009" key="santo2009">Santo, Avi and
               Christopher Lucas. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Engaging Academic and Nonacademic
                  Communities Through Online Scholarly Work</title>. <title rend="italic">Cinema
                  Journal</title> 48.2: 129-138.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Scardamalia and Bereiter 1995" xml:id="scardamalia1995" key="scardamalia1995">Scardamalia, Marlene and Carl Bereiter. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Technologies for Knowledge-Building Discourse</title>. <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title> 36.5: 37-41.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Secker and Price 2007" xml:id="secker2007" key="secker2007">Secker, Jane
               and Gwyneth Price. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Libraries, Social Software and
                  Distance Learners: Blog It, Tag It, Share It!</title>. New Review of Information
               Networking 13.1: 39-52.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Shami et al 2007" xml:id="shami2007" key="shami2007">Shami, N. Sadat et al.
               (2007). <title rend="quotes">That’s What Friends are for: Facilitating <soCalled>Who
                     Knows What</soCalled> Across Group Boundaries</title>. Proceedings of GROUP
               ’07, Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 4-7 Nov. 2007. New York: ACM. 379-382.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Shanahan 2010" xml:id="shanahan2010" key="shanahan2010">Shanahan,
               Marie-Claire. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Changing the Meaning of Peer-to-peer?
                  Exploring Online Comment Spaces as Sites of Negotiated Expertise</title>. <title rend="italic">JCOM: Journal of Science Communication</title> 9.1: n.pag. <ref target="http://jcom.sissa.it/archive/09/01/Jcom0901%282010%29A01/ ">http://jcom.sissa.it/archive/09/01/Jcom0901%282010%29A01/</ref> (accessed 15 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Shevade, Sundaram, and Xie 2007" xml:id="shevade2007">Shevade, Bageshree,
               Hari Sundaram and Lexing Xie. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Modeling Personal and
                  Social Network Context for Event Annotation in Images</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of JCDL ’07</title>. Vancouver, BC. 18-23 June, 2007.
               New York: ACM. 127-34. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Siemens et al. 2009" xml:id="siemens2009" key="siemens2009">Siemens, R., C.
               Leitch, A. Blake, K. Armstrong, &amp; J. Willinsky. (2009). <title rend="quotes">It
                  May Change My Understanding of the Field: Understanding Reading Tools for Scholars
                  and Professional Readers</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanitites
                  Quarterly</title> 3.4.</bibl>
            <bibl label="The Significance of Social Software 2007" xml:id="software2007">
               <title rend="quotes">The Significance of Social Software</title>. (2007). BlogTalks
               Reloaded: Social Software Research &amp; Cases. Ed. Thomas N. Berg and Jan Schmidt.
               Norderstedt. 15-30.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sorrel 2010" xml:id="sorrel2010" key="sorrel2010">Sorrel, Charlie. (2010).
                  <title rend="quotes">Kobo Update Adds Social Features, Nerd-Friendly
               Stats</title>. <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 10 Dec. <ref target="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/12/kobo-update-adds-social-features-nerd-friendly-stats/">http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/12/kobo-update-adds-social-features-nerd-friendly-stats/</ref>
               (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Stein 2009" xml:id="stein2009" key="stein2009">Stein, Scott. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Do Kindles (and Other E-readers) Need Better Ways to
                  Annotate?</title>
               <title rend="italic">CNET News</title>. 30 Sept. <ref target="http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-10363642-1.html">http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-10363642-1.html</ref> (accessed 15 July
               2011). (mentions <title rend="italic">The E-reader Pilot at Princeton</title>. New
               Jersey: Princeton University, 2009. <ref target="http://www.princeton.edu/ereaderpilot/">http://www.princeton.edu/ereaderpilot/</ref> [accessed 1 July 2011.]).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Stephens and Collins 2007" xml:id="stephens2007" key="stephens2007">Stephens, Michael and Maria Collins. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Web 2.0, Library
                  2.0, and the Hyperlinked Library</title>. <title rend="italic">Serials
                  Review</title> 33.4: 253-56.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tashman and Edwards 2011" xml:id="tashman2011" key="tashman2011">Tashman,
               C.S. &amp; W.K. Edwards. (2011). <title rend="quotes">LiquidText: A Flexible,
                  Multitouch Environment to Support Active Reading</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI Conference</title>. <ref target="http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~keith/pubs/chi2011-liquidtext.pdf">http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~keith/pubs/chi2011-liquidtext.pdf</ref> (accessed on 10
               July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Thayer et al. 2011" xml:id="thayer2011" key="thayer2011">Thayer, A., C.P.
               Lee, L.H. Hwang, H. Sales, P. Sen, and N. Dalal. (2011). <title rend="quotes">The
                  Imposition and Superimposition of Digital Reading Technology</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM CHI Conference</title>. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Tidwell et al 2002" xml:id="tidwell2002" key="tidwell2002">Tidwell, Lisa
               Collins and Joseph B. Walther. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Computer-Mediated
                  Communication Effects on Disclosure, Impressions, and Interpersonal Evaluations:
                  Getting to Know One Another a Bit at a Time</title>. <title rend="italic">Human
                  Communication Research</title> 28.3: 317-48.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tufekci 2008" xml:id="tufekci2008" key="tufekci2008">Tufekci, Zeynep.
               (2008). <title rend="quotes">Can You See Me Now? Audience and Disclosure Regulation
                  in Online Social Network Sites</title>. <title rend="italic">Bulletin of Science,
                  Technology and Society</title>. <ref target="http://userpages.umbc.edu/~zeynep/papers/ZeynepCanYouSeeMeNowBSTS.pdf">http://userpages.umbc.edu/~zeynep/papers/ZeynepCanYouSeeMeNowBSTS.pdf</ref>.
               (accessed 23 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tyler 2002" xml:id="tyler2002" key="tyler2002">Tyler, Tom R. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Is the Internet Changing Social Life? It Seems the More Things
                  Change, the More They Stay the Same</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                  Social Issues</title> 58.1: 195-205.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2008" label="Unsworth 2008" key="unsworth2008">Unsworth, John.
               (2008). <title rend="quotes">University 2.0</title>. <title rend="italic">The Tower
                  and the Cloud: Higher Education in the Age of Cloud Computing</title>. Educause.
               pp 227-237. <ref target="http://www.educause.edu/thetowerandthecloud">http://www.educause.edu/thetowerandthecloud</ref> (accessed 15 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vonahn2008" label="von Ahn et al 2008" key="vonahn2008">von Ahn, Luis, et
               al. (2008). <title rend="quotes">reCAPTCHA: Human-Based Character Recognition via Web
                  Security Measures</title>. <title rend="italic">Science</title> 321.5895:
               1465-1468. <ref target="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/reCAPTCHA_Science.pdf">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/reCAPTCHA_Science.pdf</ref> (accessed on 18 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wang 2010" xml:id="wang2010" key="wang2010">Wang, Tricia. (2010). <title rend="quotes">My New Academic Workflow with my iPad, iAnnotate, Mendleys &amp;
                  Dropbox</title>. <title rend="italic">Cultural Bytes</title>. <ref target="http://culturalbyt.es/post/1125482840/workflow">http://culturalbyt.es/post/1125482840/workflow</ref> (accessed 11 July
               2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wardtrip-Fruin 2008" xml:id="wardripfruin2008" key="wardrip2008a">Wardrip-Fruin, Noah. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Expressive Processing: An
                  Experiment in Blog-Based Peer Review</title>. <title rend="italic">Grand Text
                  Auto</title> 22 Jan. 2008.
               http://grandtextauto.org/2008/01/22/expressive-processing-an-experiment-in-blog-based-peer-review/
               (accessed 28 Jan. 2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Watters 2010" xml:id="watters2010" key="watters2010">Watters, Audrey.
               (2010). <title rend="quotes">New Social E-Reading Platform Allows Real-Time
                  Discussions, Right On the E-Book's Pages</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 22 Nov. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/new_social_e-reading_platform_allows_real-time_dis.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/new_social_e-reading_platform_allows_real-time_dis.php</ref>
               (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Watters 2011" xml:id="watters2011" key="watters2011">Watters, Audrey.
               (2011). <title rend="quotes">Long Live Marginalia! ReadSocial Brings Annotations to
                  Digital Literature</title>. <title rend="italic">ReadWriteWeb</title> 24 Mar. <ref target="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/love_live_marginalia_readsocial_brings_annotations.php">http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/love_live_marginalia_readsocial_brings_annotations.php</ref>
               (accessed 5 July 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Weisberg 2011" xml:id="weisberg2011" key="weisberg2011">Weisberg, Mitchell.
               (2011). <title rend="quotes">Student Attitudes and Behaviors Towards Digital
                  Textbooks</title>. <title rend="italic">Publishing Research Quarterly</title>
               27.2: 188-196.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wellman et al 1996" xml:id="wellman2006" key="wellman1996">Wellman, Barry
               et al. (1996). <title rend="quotes">Computer Networks as Social Networks:
                  Collaborative Work, Telework, and Virtual Community</title>. <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Sociology</title> 22: 213-38.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wenger 1998" xml:id="wenger1998" key="wenger1998">Wenger, Etienne. (1998).
                  <title rend="quotes">Communities of Practice: Learning as a Social System</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Systems Thinker</title> 9.5: 1-10. <ref target="http://www.open.ac.uk/ldc08/sites/www.open.ac.uk.ldc08/files/Learningasasocialsystem.pdf                                  ">http://www.open.ac.uk/ldc08/sites/www.open.ac.uk.ldc08/files/Learningasasocialsystem.pdf
               </ref> (accessed July 18, 2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wolfe 2002" xml:id="wolfe2002" key="wolfe2002">Wolfe, Joanna. (2002).
                  <title rend="quotes">Annotation Technologies: A Software and Research
                  Review</title>. <title rend="italic">Computers and Compositions</title> 19.4:
               471-97.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Yang et al. 2011" xml:id="yang2011" key="yang2011a">Yang, Stephen J.A. et
               al. (2011). <title rend="quotes">A Collaborative Multimedia Annotation Tool for
                  Enhancing Knowledge Sharing in CSCL</title>. <title rend="italic">Interactive
                  Learning Environments</title> 19.1: 45-62.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Zhang and Ackerman 2005" xml:id="zhang2005" key="zhang2005c">Zhang, Jun and
               Mark S. Ackerman. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Searching for Expertise in Social
                  Networks: A Simulation of Potential Strategies</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of GROUP’05</title>. Sanibel Islands, FL, USA. 6-9 Nov. 2005. New
               York: ACM. 71-80.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>