<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Escaping the Shallows: Deep Reading’s Revival in the Digital
                    Age</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Dowling</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Iowa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>david-dowling@uiowa.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David Dowling is an assistant professor in the department of Journalism
                            and Mass Communication at the University of Iowa.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000180</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2014-07-18">18 July 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Among the many reactions against the digital revolution is a humanitarian
                    movement toward long form online reading in collective and social networks. This
                    movement — visible in online book clubs such as <title rend="quotes">Infinite
                        Summer</title> and 1book140, websites such as longreads.com, and the trend
                    of blogs-to-books publication — is a reaction against superficial increasingly
                    brief headline-driven Internet news. Called to action by the threat of what
                    critic Jessica Helfand has diagnosed as digital culture’s <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#helfand2001">narrative depravation,</quote> the deep reading revival has
                    reclaimed narrative and returned it to the populace, transforming reading into
                    an act of mass collaboration on an unprecedented scale. Despite studies
                    corroborating Nicholas Carr’s claim in <title rend="italic">The Shallows</title>
                    (2011) that the distractions of the digital environment are anathema to
                    immersive linear deep reading, online culture has actually enhanced and
                    accelerated the appreciation of longer richer works through its support of
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">radial reading</quote> as described by
                    Jerome McGann. This essay argues that while the intrinsically distracting
                    virtual geography of the Internet has threatened to diminish the role of
                    textured narrative in our intellectual and social lives, the Web has ironically
                    provided the media for the most salient movements in support of the deep reading
                    it threatens to obliterate. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Deeps and shallows of reading</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#konstantinou2012">The great virtue of
                            collective reading projects is that they give us an occasion to work
                            together to help us sustain our attention, to achieve goals we might
                            have thought too difficult to attain working on our own. So let’s get
                            going — with a chaos of connections, a blizzard of studied silence, a
                            whirling vortex of intense, collective focus. #OccupyGaddis, Lee
                            Konstantinou, June 2012.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#konstantinou2012"/>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p>A movement in long form and literary journalism is currently gaining traction on
                    the Internet, representing a revival in deep reading whose roots were barely
                    visible in Internet culture just ten years ago. The advent of platforms such as
                        <title rend="italic">Longform.org</title> in 2010 just after the release of
                    the iPad that same year, followed by <title rend="italic">Atavist</title> and
                        <title rend="italic">Byliner</title> in 2011, has inspired a host of vibrant
                    online reading communities. The collaborative mass movement seeking longer more
                    textured writing has risen in direct opposition to the shrinking attention spans
                    associated with the digital revolution that have threatened to diminish, if not
                    utterly annihilate, the status of narrative as the transmitter of core values
                    shared and contested in the culture. Ironically, this crusade to rescue
                    narrative from the distracting ecosystem of the Internet not only has adopted
                    the very medium blamed for its demise, it has done so with a robust <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#konstantinou2012">chaos of connections, a
                            blizzard of studied silence, a whirling vortex of intense, collective
                            focus</quote>
                        <ptr target="#konstantinou2012"/>
                    </cit>. Testifying to the rich diversity of digital culture and its ubiquitous
                    reach, the Internet has provided both the setting and tools for the
                    counter-revolution to reclaim narrative from the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#briggs2011">attention economy</quote> and the commercial
                    distractions of its infrastructure, from Google searches to social media <ptr
                        target="#briggs2011" loc="15"/>.</p>
                <p>This essay tracks the most effective responses to the digital revolution’s
                    marginalization of print books signaled by the rapid decline since 2002 in all
                    forms of print reading, according to a 2012 Pew study, and the attendant rise of
                    online reading <ptr target="#kohut2012"/>. The shift away from print has
                    suggested for some critics the loss of the literary mind associated with it, as
                    deep immersive reading would appear to have yielded to highly distracting
                    hyperlinked e-book alternatives and increasingly superficial online reading. But
                    deep reading and online reading are not mutually exclusive pursuits; the
                    Internet provides fertile ground for critical immersion in a wide variety of
                    media texts. Surging demand for those digital texts is buoying rather than
                    sinking the publishing industry, as sales rose to twenty-three percent of book
                    publishers’ revenue in 2012 for a six percent gain reaching $7.1 billion in
                    revenue that year <ptr target="#boynton2013" loc="129"/>. </p>
                <p>Speed and access to rich stores of data characteristic of digital reading, I
                    argue, do not signal the inevitable decline and extinction of serious reflective
                    reading. Indeed, the latest wave of online reading communities has harnessed
                    hypersocial participatory Internet culture for sustained focus on long immersive
                    works. Whereas digital reading has been previously criticized for the haste and
                    superficiality it encourages, the movement toward deep reading has given rise to
                    a new premium on media products’ <soCalled>stickiness,</soCalled> a measure
                    based on how much time a reader spends with a digital text. Platforms such as
                    Longform.org operate according to this model. In 2012, for example, sixty-five
                    percent of <title rend="italic">Longform</title>’s readers completed every 2,000
                    plus-word story they read <ptr target="#boynton2013" loc="130"/>. Among the
                    diverse reading communities now populating the digital ecosystem from Harlequin
                    and fantasy serial fiction to classical literature groups, Longform’s young
                    mobile and well-educated readers represent a demographic Robert S. Boynton has
                    called <quote rend="inline" source="#boynton2013">the envy of any
                        advertiser,</quote> as fifty percent are under 34, thirty percent read
                    mainly on phones and tablets, and forty-two percent have attended graduate
                    school <ptr target="#boynton2013" loc="130"/>. </p>
                <p>This study begins by situating deep reading within the larger critical debate
                    about the impact of digital culture, followed by a segment defining deep and
                    immersive online reading practices. Focus then turns to how deep and immersive
                    reading play out in particular digital reading communities, with emphasis on the
                    signature moves that characterize their social function to support deep
                    immersive reading and foster an appreciation for narrative. Consideration then
                    turns to how such groups constitute social reading as mass collaboration, a
                    process made possible by nature of its deinstitutionalized participatory
                    culture, the subject of the next section. The conclusion argues for the crucial
                    role of narrative immersion in the formation of conscientious moral judgment. </p>
                <div>
                    <head> Reading in the Digital Age: The Critical Debate </head>
                    <p>If Herman Melville’s <title rend="italic">Moby-Dick</title> (1852) stands as
                        one of the literary world’s great monuments to narrative achievement, the
                            <title rend="italic">Moby-Dick</title> Marathon Reading became a major
                        occasion in popular literary culture to safeguard that achievement along
                        with its print and oratorical origins from the distractions of the digital
                        age. The annual New Bedford, Massachusetts live non-stop relay reading of
                        Melville’s novel functioned in 2009 as a <soCalled>sit-in protest</soCalled> against electronic media
                        saturation according to Mayor Scott Lange. Although Lange accurately
                        predicted that <q>You won’t hear
                            or see a cell phone,</q> 2009 would actually be the last anti-tech
                        year for the reading, which then transformed from a tacit luddite rite to a
                        full-blown technological feast, complete with giant screens displaying
                        texts, tweets, and forum posts from virtual participants throughout the
                        world discussing live streaming video of readers delivering passages of
                        Melville’s epic narrative <ptr target="#dowling2010" loc="38"/>. In only one
                        year — from 2009 to 2010 — the event went from print-only to a multimedia
                        extravaganza that ironically sacrificed nothing of its original intention:
                        to reaffirm the power of complex narrative and the sanctity of the reader’s
                        full immersion in it. Once digital, the novel’s global reach expanded the
                        reading community of an event previously limited to its live participants
                        and reported by a few bloggers and local reporters. That reading community
                        has since grown with the proliferation of social media channels in each
                        successive year. Fear of technology’s stultifying effects in 2009 proved
                        moot in 2010, as the novel would build new significance through its widening
                        readership.</p>
                    <p>The spread of live Melville readings online is just one of many examples of
                        the deep reading renaissance now taking place in digital culture. The now
                        thoroughly digitized literary marathon readings reveal how online
                        communities have seized the tools of social media for deep reading,
                        effectively refuting skeptics such as Nicholas Carr (2011) and Jessica
                        Helfand (2001), who insist that new media necessarily has a deleterious
                        effect on narrative, perhaps the most crucial link to our humanity. But old
                        media do not die; they converge, according to Henry Jenkins (2006). In his
                        recent study of Melville in participatory digital culture, Jenkins points
                        out that <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2013">it is simplistic to
                            assume that technologies can support only one mindset</quote> associated
                        with scanning and skimming. It is also <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#jenkins2013">wrong-headed to assume the Internet’s
                            intellectual ethic is in direct and total opposition to that associated
                            with books</quote> because, as the history of media suggests, <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#jenkins2013">one medium does not displace
                            another, but rather, each adds a new cultural layer, supporting more
                            diverse ways of communicating, thinking, feeling, and creating than
                            existed before</quote>
                        <ptr target="#jenkins2013" loc="11"/></cit>. Convergence culture, therefore, is at
                        the core of the latest online movement for deep reading, as it embodies
                        media merging together in an ongoing process at the intersection of
                        technologies, industries, content, and audiences <ptr target="#jenkins2013"
                            loc="13"/>. Indeed, the online movement in deep reading illustrates
                        precisely how communities can respond to the disruption of an old pattern of
                        consumption — the solitary reading of print — by establishing new
                        participatory cultures across media platforms. </p>
                    <p>The debate over the fate of deep reading in digital culture has drawn
                        considerable attention recently. The January 2013 issue of the <title
                            rend="italic">Publication of the Modern Language Association</title>,
                        for example, dedicated its department of <title rend="quotes">The Changing
                            Profession</title> to research on <title rend="quotes">Reading in the
                            Digital Age.</title> In it one study concluded that online reading
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#baron2013">privileges locating
                            information over deciphering and analyzing more complex text,</quote>
                        necessarily making <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#baron2013">deep and
                            sustained reading (for work or pleasure) run second to information
                            gathering and short-term distraction</quote>
                        <ptr target="#baron2013" loc="200"/></cit>. Yet such arguments, as Jim Collins
                        notes, <quote rend="inline" source="#collins2013">remain an exercise in
                            nostalgia, grounded in a discourse of inevitable loss.</quote> The
                        hypersocialization of online readers, I concur, is not <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#collins2013">merely a distraction</quote> but <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#collins2013">an entryway into an endless
                            variety of reading communities,</quote> a point made stronger in light
                        of how they engage in archiving, sharing, and discussing texts, all edifying
                        behaviors that cultivate both individuality and community <ptr
                            target="#collins2013" loc="212"/>. </p>
                    <p>Within the wider public debate on the impact of the digital revolution, deep
                        reading’s fate plays a central role in several highly visible works
                        expressing dissent toward online culture <ptr target="#carr2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#harkaway2012"/>
                        <ptr target="#lanier2010"/>
                        <ptr target="#bauerlein2008"/>
                        <ptr target="#turkle2011"/>. The virulent effects of Internet culture on
                        news media, cognitive function, privacy, retail, and democracy have been
                        cause for alarm from a variety of sectors <ptr target="#ophiretal2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#levy2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#jeongandfishbein2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#longform2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#dretzin2010"/>. Others have defended the democratic <ptr
                            target="#shirky2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#gillmor2006"/>), cognitive <ptr target="#johnson2006"/>, and
                        commercial benefits <ptr target="#briggs2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#howe2009"/> of electronic media. Luddite arguments lament the
                        loss of human idiosyncrasy, intimacy, and sympathy though the
                        marginalization of print as witnessed by the disappearance of brick and
                        mortar bookstores, particularly independent ones, seemingly rendered
                        obsolete by mammoth online superstores such as Amazon <ptr
                            target="#miller2007"/>. Utopians instead extol the virtue of the new
                        avenues for group formation <ptr target="#shirky2009"/> and participatory
                        culture <ptr target="#jenkins2006"/> that have opened up on the Internet. </p>
                    <p>The web would appear the least likely environment to host the revival of deep
                        reading given the findings of several studies of online reading. A 2005
                        survey of the influence of hypertext on comprehension concluded that <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#destefanoandlefevre2007">the increased demands
                            of decision-making and visual processing in hypertext impaired reading
                            performance</quote> unlike <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#destefanoandlefevre2007">traditional linear
                            presentation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#destefanoandlefevre2007" loc="1639"/></cit>. Jakob Nielsen’s
                        eye-tracking study of web users revealed that the eye follows a pattern
                        resembling the letter F when reading text on websites compared to
                        line-by-line reading encouraged by printed material <ptr
                            target="#nielsen2006"/>. Nielsen’s further experiments found that web
                        users actually read in the traditional linear sense very little, spending
                        instead the majority of their time skimming webpages in haste <ptr
                            target="#nielsen2008"/>. Such browsing was indicative of the desire to
                        scan and absorb material quickly, a factor of speed concomitant to the
                        distracting nature of digital culture’s new premium placed on
                            <soCalled>multitasking</soCalled>. Research at Stanford University
                        conducted by Clifford Nass <ptr target="#ophiretal2009"/> has contributed
                        convincing scientific data supporting the cognitive losses incurred from
                        multitasking compared to work performed without distraction. His lab’s
                        findings have since been verified with alarming implications that suggest a
                        profound blindness to otherwise obvious elements — <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#chabrisandsimons2009">invisible gorillas</quote> as Chabris
                        and Simons call them — in our environment when attention is divided <ptr
                            target="#chabrisandsimons2009"/>. </p>
                    <p>The most successful movements averting such liabilities transcend the
                        unhelpful assumption that digital media is anathema to deep reading by
                        embracing new technology to spark a humanitarian revival in long form and
                        book reading. Technology has not deterministically prevented the formation
                        of deep reading communities while only shrinking units of interpersonal
                        communication and news stories in the online environment. Counter-movements
                        to these trends have gained traction with digital technologies that would
                        otherwise seem capable of only dividing our attention and preventing
                        sustained reading. Indeed, the tools and practices at the heart of that
                        digital culture, particularly tweeting, texting, and following hyperlinks
                        that gloss media texts, are instrumental to the new movement toward sharing
                        and discussing books and long form works. Paradoxically, the core of this
                        countermovement therefore exists primarily online <ptr target="#staley2003"
                            loc="4"/>
                        <ptr target="#phamandsarno2010" loc="A1"/>. Whereas the Internet has been
                        blamed for marginalizing and neglecting narrative in obvious ways, it has
                        also nonetheless provided the media for its revival, proving that computer
                        mediated communication (CMC) and short messaging service (SMS) are inert
                        value-free tools that can have either corrosive or revitalizing effects on
                        the culture depending on their use <ptr target="#harkaway2012"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Deep Immersive Reading Defined</head>
                    <p>Nicholas Carr argues in <title rend="italic">The Shallows</title> that linear
                        narrative stripped clean of hypertext and embedded links makes for a more
                        personal and absorbed mode of reading <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="128"/>.
                        But narrative free of hypertext is not always causally linked to deep,
                        focused reading. In many instances, narrative does not require or even
                        solicit deep reading. Guy Montag’s wife Mildred in Ray Bradbury’s novel
                            <title rend="italic">Fahrenheit 451</title>, for example, is addicted to
                        her daytime TV series she watches on <soCalled>the parlor walls</soCalled> precisely because it
                        intellectually anesthetizes her, providing her with a pacifying substitute
                        for books, which her government systematically suppresses by burning any
                        volumes that leak into the culture. Although free of the distractions of
                        hyperlinked data and easy access to social media, her media text is designed
                        for passive consumption. She is drawn to the linear narrative of television
                        soap operas precisely because they do not demand deep complex interpretation
                        and/or inspire discourse with her community. She is immersed, in this sense,
                        but not engaged critically in her subject in a way characterizing deep
                        reading. Marshall McLuhan described such immersion as a feature of <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1965">hot</quote> media that encourages
                        emotional rather than intellectual — and thus potentially political —
                        engagement. A high-definition medium like the one that absorbs Bradbury’s
                        character represents McLuhan’s sense that new media technology could furnish
                        an overabundance of the imaginative stimulus (usually through escapist
                        fantasy) for the reader without challenging them to exercise their own
                        imaginations or grapple with provocative ideological scenarios and
                        propositions <ptr target="#kovarik2011" loc="10"/>
                        <ptr target="#mcluhan1965"/>. Thus narrative can be not only shallow, as the
                        facile episodes of electronic home entertainment in Bradbury’s dystopia
                        suggest. Narrative can also be socially corrosive since <q>Millie</q> Montag
                        has in effect substituted the fictional figures on her parlor wall for the
                        real ones who actually populate her life. </p>
                    <p>The neutralizing asocial effects of the media immersion envisioned by
                        Bradbury and McLuhan are symptomatic of a culture deprived of online social
                        media. The digital ecology has enabled immersive reading — in which the
                        consumer is fully absorbed in a work’s characters, scenes and narrative — to
                        be intellectually empowering. My use of <soCalled>deep reading</soCalled>
                        here denotes analysis and critique, whereas <soCalled>immersion</soCalled>
                        suggests a completeness of experience. Depth does not necessitate immersion;
                        deep reading can occur with simple texts and vice-versa. These are not
                        always mutually dependent categories, as many instances illustrate. Indeed,
                        what readers actually do in their participation with texts reflects an
                        expansive heterogeneous range of online practices marked by a willingness to
                        dive deeply into a wide array of texts. </p>
                    <p>The online reading communities I examine tend to engage in both deep reading
                        and immersion in the extreme. Internet readers of immersive narrative
                        reflect a completeness of experience that inspires rather than silences
                        discussion, draws out rather than erases the individual reading experience,
                        and socializes rather than isolates the pastime of media consumption. This
                        socializing tendency renders a morally conscientious reading experience.
                        Narrative is particularly effective in driving that social exchange of
                        analysis and critique because it humanizes online news media’s notoriously
                        brief, abstract, and impersonal standard mode of expression. Set in the
                        context of long form narrative, deep immersive reading becomes more
                        provocative for readers, inspiring more nuanced and serious consideration of
                        any given set of events or ideological circumstances superficially skimmed
                        by traditional headline-driven news. As discussed in the conclusion,
                        narrative becomes necessary for making moral judgments. </p>
                    <p>The concept of the <soCalled>linear</soCalled> text bears directly on
                        critical presumptions about deep and immersive reading. A key assumption in
                        Carr’s <ptr target="#carr2011"/> argument, for example, privileges linear
                        narrative of the sort associated with cause-effect realistic fiction of the
                        Victorian era, as his favorite examples in <title rend="italic">The
                            Shallows</title> tend to be Charles Dickens and Nathaniel Hawthorne. Yet
                        he also includes modernist James Joyce, noting that <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#carr2011">nonlinear narrative</quote> by writers like William
                        Burroughs <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">would have been
                            unthinkable without the artists’ presumption of attentive patient
                            readers.</quote> Privileging print, he argues that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">when transcribed to a page, a
                                stream of consciousness becomes literary and linear</quote>
                            <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="76"/>
                        </cit>. But Burroughs in print is just as nonlinear as Burroughs online.
                        Hypertextual links would enable rather than disable fluent readings of his
                        enigmatic and densely allusive idiosyncratic texts. Thus print does not
                        automatically make all texts more linear and thus more literary and deep.
                        Indeed, what distinguishes so many texts embraced by online reading
                        communities is precisely their nonlinearity, their narrative tendency to
                        yield to enriching diversions or downright distractions and their capacity
                        to shatter artificial distinctions between high and low cultural products.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Surges in Reader Demand for Digital Texts</head>
                    <p>Efforts to establish and integrate long form works into the digital world
                        abound. Social media directly serves the revival of deep reading in the area
                        of politics. Social media mitigated by SMS are tools primarily concerned
                        with expressing opinions; when users aggregate opinions they create public
                        opinion. Traditionally public opinion has been measured by surveys (online,
                        telephone, face-to-face), but now social media provides a new way to learn
                        about politics, read the news and connect with others through a process now
                        referred to as social reading available in forms such as Facebook’s
                        News-Apps Center <ptr target="#facebook2012"/>. It enables users to select
                        from options and share news videos and stories with Facebook friends while
                        also seeing what those friends are reading and watching. <title
                            rend="italic">The Washington Post</title> and NBC News have applications
                        with hundreds of thousands of followers. The Huffington Post Social Reading
                        App socializes the reading experience by enabling readers to share stories,
                        start conversations, and keep abreast of their friends’ reading. Mashable’s
                        mission is to empower people by spreading knowledge of social media and
                        technology, and has become the largest independent news source dedicated to
                        covering digital culture, social media and technology. The Hill Social
                        Reader provides news inside the beltway and is created by The Hill, a
                        congressional newspaper that publishes daily when Congress is in session,
                        with a special focus on business and lobbying, political campaigns and
                        events on Capitol Hill. </p>
                    <p> The most spectacular illustration of online political news consumers
                        demanding in-depth reading followed the November 2012 presidential election.
                        Sales skyrocketed for Nate Silver’s <title rend="italic">The Signal and the
                            Noise</title> (2012) based on his <title rend="italic">New York Times
                        </title> blog, <title rend="italic">fivethirtyeight</title>, which predicted
                        an Obama landslide months before it occurred. Sales of Silver’s book
                        increased 850% in one day, making it the second bestselling title on Amazon
                        at the time <ptr target="#silver2012"/>
                        <ptr target="#isidore2012"/>. As with Curt Brown, long complex works by
                        journalists and bloggers such as Silver go viral when readers can access and
                        recommend these titles easily through social media. Bloggers are
                        increasingly motivated by the desire to publish their entire blogs as books
                            <ptr target="#pedersen2009"/>. </p>
                    <p>As Silvers’s success illustrates, the way to create demand for <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#lessig2008">after broadcast sales</quote> of
                        blogs as books and television shows as DVDs is <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#lessig2008">through complexity,</quote> according to Lawrence
                        Lessig <ptr target="#lessig2008" loc="94"/>. Complexity in visual media
                        trafficking in narrative has also been steadily rising for the last half
                        century. Plots of television shows have become increasingly complex and
                        demanding, not simpler, since the 1950s <ptr target="#johnson2006" loc="27"
                        />. Because viewers are not likely to grasp in one viewing the full range of
                        critical and narrative complexity of today’s television shows, viewers thus
                        have reason to watch them again by purchasing the DVD for repeated viewing.
                        David Foster Wallace was a notorious <title rend="italic">X-Files</title>
                        fan for precisely this reason and <title rend="italic">The Wire</title> has
                        won scholarly praise for the current generation just as <title rend="italic"
                            >Twin Peaks </title>did for the prior one. Many narratively rich
                        cultural products warrant such <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#lessig2008">follow-on consumption</quote>
                            <ptr target="#lessig2008" loc="94"/>
                        </cit>. Most who attend the aforementioned New Bedford <title rend="italic"
                            >Moby-Dick </title>Marathon reading, for example, are savoring in a live
                        format a work they have read many times as with a Beethoven symphony <ptr
                            target="#dowling2010" loc="121"/>. Serial fiction writers such as James
                        Fenimore Cooper and Harriet Beecher Stowe published their stories in weekly
                        segments one chapter at a time to an audience that expected it to be
                        available for purchase to re-reread after its periodical run in bound novel
                        form. Time bound, one-time reading was not enough for mid-nineteenth century
                        readers. The same principle holds true in today’s market. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Online Readers as Radial Readers</head>
                    <p>Long form journalism’s resurgence through both blogs and social media (which
                        feed into print and e-books) enriches and deepens the culture of digital
                        identity, particularly the conventions of personal expression in social
                        media. As social reading increasingly becomes a means of shaping online
                        identity, it provides a more sophisticated extension of self-presentation
                        commonly found on Facebook. The sharing of reading can raise the stakes of
                        personal profiling beyond how <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#papacharissi2009">social networking site users typically
                            interpret cues deposited in member profiles, such as messages on
                            Facebook <soCalled>walls</soCalled> or messages or pictures of member
                            friends to make inferences about the member’s character</quote>
                        <ptr target="#papacharissi2009" loc="203"/>
                        <ptr target="#walther2008" loc="28–49"/>. So while social reading serves
                        user demand for the circulation of readings, it also has the effect of
                        showcasing reading tastes as a richer more sophisticated expression of one’s
                        personal profile. Prior to social reading the construction of identity on
                        Facebook has been rigidly confined to a set of conventions that purport to
                        express individuality, but only on a superficial and often pretentious
                        level. Social reading, furthermore, offers the online world a profile more
                        reflective of one’s bookshelf — providing a portrait through intellectual,
                        political, and aesthetic interests — reaching well beyond the limited milieu
                        of requisite photos showcasing one’s children, spouse, and vacation along
                        with humorous links or witty quotes that have become the social norm for
                        Facebook users. Recent research indicates the <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#papacharissi2009">most popular features of
                                Facebook include its photo-sharing abilities</quote>
                            <ptr target="#papacharissi2009" loc="204"/>
                        </cit>, a feature now used for book-sharing and social reading. Indeed, the
                        development of social reading has been fueled by its adaptability to the
                        contributions of <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#papacharissi2009">applications that work
                                with the open source foundation of the website, constantly
                                refreshing and rejuvenating content</quote>
                            <ptr target="#papacharissi2009" loc="204"/>
                        </cit> which now increasingly includes e-books and long form journalism. The
                        Facebook community is currently embracing the once isolated factions of long
                        form aficionados and bibliophiles. Although self-presentation online and
                        impression management form a common point of interest in recent research,
                        social reading as a measure of the surging demand for long form reading has
                        received less attention.</p>
                    <p>Due to the ease with which such social reading networks can be formed online,
                        works of 2,000 or more words that engage in learned controversy or delve
                        into historical topics relevant to contemporary issues actually lend
                        themselves well to the Internet. With its abundance of easily accessed data
                        through hyperlinks, the Internet enhances <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#mcgann1991">radial reading,</quote> Jerome McGann’s concept
                        which he contrasts with <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">linear
                            reading</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>. Linear reading, particularly the sort
                        that disempowers the reader as noted by Moody <ptr target="#moody2012"/>, is
                        at odds with varieties of spatial and radial reading that instead are more
                        in tune with current notions of narrative characterized by fragmented
                        diverse genres alluding to and intersecting with interior consciousness of
                        self and community. McGann explains that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">radial reading involves
                                decoding one or more of the contexts that interpenetrate the
                                scripted and physical text</quote>
                            <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>
                        </cit>. In this sense, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">the reading eye does not move
                                only in a linear direction</quote>
                            <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>
                        </cit>. Complex material encourages radial reading because it <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">necessitates some kind of
                            abstraction from what appears most immediately,</quote> as McGann
                        observes <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>. <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">The person who temporarily
                                stops <soCalled>reading</soCalled> to look up the meaning of a word
                                is properly an <emph>emblem</emph> of radial reading because that
                                kind of <soCalled>radial</soCalled> operation is repeatedly taking
                                place even while one remains absorbed with a text</quote>
                            <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>
                        </cit>. Radial reading has never been so rich and rewarding as in the
                        context of the online ecosystem, with its readily available search engines
                        and social media tools. SMS drives such radial reading in an apparent
                        paradox in which brief messaging can aid rather than truncate deep
                        understandings and experiences of longer texts, leading to further
                        interaction among readers through tools such as email that allow for longer
                        nuanced expression. </p>
                    <p>Works that encourage online debate and civic dialogue enact precisely this
                        pattern, as readers delve deep within the text while also moving outward
                        into now readily available online data networks. <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">Emily Dickinson tells us that
                                    <q>there is no frigate like a
                                    book</q> in order to remind us that reading sends us away
                                from and within the books we enter</quote>
                            <ptr target="#mcgann1991" loc="113"/>
                        </cit>. It is important to note that deep reading that sends us away from
                        the text in order to burrow deeper into it, as McGann explains, is far more
                        critically engaged than the escapist experience of Bradbury’s Mildred Montag
                        of <title rend="italic">Fahrenheit 451</title>. Interestingly, Harlequin
                        romance readers, today’s corollary to Mildred, are hardly so escapist, but
                        are increasingly active in reading community forums of exchange that not
                        only invite socially and politically engaged online discussions, but also
                        encourage professional development, catering directly to this active digital
                        generation of the formerly passive audience personified by Bradbury’s
                        Mildred. Indeed, Harlequin’s <title rend="quotes">Community Home</title>
                        offered in early 2014 <quote rend="inline" source="#harlequin2014">some
                            great reading challenges</quote> for <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#harlequin2014">aspiring authors</quote> who are encouraged to
                        utilize <quote rend="inline" source="#harlequin2014">the information,
                            support, and advice to be found on our writing forums.</quote>
                        Harlequin’s rebranding, <title rend="quotes">Entertain, Enrich,
                            Inspire,</title> is consonant with the active social nature of its
                        thriving online reading community countering older tendencies toward
                        isolation and passivity associated with paperback romance consumption. The
                        publisher encourages readers to enter this personalized community through a
                        link suggesting, <title rend="quotes">Introduce Yourself Here</title>
                        <ptr target="#harlequin2014"/>. This participatory culture that fosters
                        critical engagement is ideally suited to the online world because it
                        encourages and enables not only the <soCalled>radial</soCalled> consultation with other outside
                        data — <quote rend="inline" source="#harlequin2014">information, support,
                            advice</quote> — in support of the reading, but utilizes that basis of
                        enhanced knowledge for informed and learned dialogue <ptr
                            target="#harlequin2014"/>. Both popular romance fiction and literary
                        polyvalent texts are not only <quote rend="inline" source="#redman1997"
                            >linguistic and spatial, but multiple and interactive as well</quote>;
                        they are hypertextual, just as the richest poetry and prose tend be <ptr
                            target="#redman1997" loc="142"/>. Such works demand explication and
                        interrogation now easily accessible on the Internet through the ready
                        consultation with others willing to share their knowledge and expertise. </p>
                    <p>Internet culture has spawned this new form of immersive radial reading as
                        witnessed in the heterogeneity of readership on such platforms as <title
                            rend="italic">BookTalk.org</title>, <title rend="italic">LitLovers: A
                            Well-Read Online Community</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                            >onlinebookclub.org</title>. <title rend="italic">Shelfari</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">LibraryThing</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                            >Goodreads</title> that emphasize archiving, connecting readers based on
                        shared titles on their virtual bookshelves. <title rend="italic"
                            >LibraryThing</title>’s forum system, Talk, enables users to see
                        conversations occurring in all groups or just their own. Discussion here can
                        be intensely specialized, as in one thread about Charles Darwin’s <title
                            rend="italic">Origin of Species</title>, which freely dovetails into
                        contemporary scientific books, as seen in the contribution of a reader
                        called southernbooklady. In response to the assertion that <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#librarything2013">the genetic clock can be
                            tracked to show the split between the two species ca. 3 million years
                            ago,</quote> she references the contemporary book, <title rend="italic"
                            >Spillover: Animal Infections and the Next Human Pandemic</title>, for
                        its treatment of how <quote rend="inline" source="#librarything2013"
                            >genetics are used to trace the evolution of not just pathogens, but the
                            way pathogens become integrated into the lifecycle of hosts,</quote>
                        particularly in <quote rend="inline" source="#librarything2013">different
                            strains of HIV,</quote> a pattern evocative of <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#librarything2013">the genetic history of various flu
                            viruses</quote> which she notes places evolution into proper perspective
                            <ptr target="#librarything2013"/>. Far from becoming untethered by
                        unsupported assertions and doctrinaire soap-box rants one might expect from
                        an online discussion of evolution, this discussion and others like it remain
                        steeped in such useful data and allusions, all of which serves the purpose
                        of illuminating the core meanings and contexts of the text at hand, in this
                        case, Darwin. Talk on <title rend="italic">LibraryThing</title> thus
                        represents complex movement back and forth between the text, other texts,
                        SMS with other readers (texting, tweeting, social networking, and emailing),
                        and Web searches. The key is that engaged critical readers truly immersed in
                        the process will return to the text, rather than exiting into an endless
                        series of distractions, one begetting the next, which the Internet has been
                        notorious for encouraging. Thus Internet culture has extended the dialogic
                        nature of critical reading. This revises Carr’s binary expressed in his
                        metaphor for deep reading as deep sea diving and Internet reading as
                        frenetic jet skiing <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="7"/>). The immersive radial
                        reading of expressive texts dives deeper into subjects with tools of
                        illumination retrieved at the surface rather than flitting mindlessly only
                        on the surface, the very nature of <emph>surf</emph>ing, according to more
                        common Internet reading practices.</p>
                    <p>In an online discussion of <title rend="italic">Outlander</title> in
                        #1book140, such radial reading was on display. Twitter, in this case, served
                        as the medium through which to share a revealing link to a <title
                            rend="italic">Books and Writers Community</title> post, offering data on
                        how the original marketing plan for the text impacted its genre, especially
                        its use of conventions typically found in romances. <q>Melissa</q> tweeted,
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">Any thoughts on the
                            wedding? A romance starting with a forced marriage didn’t sit well but
                            maybe was historically accurate?</quote> to which <q>Sandy</q> replied:
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">Marriage is a practical
                            solution — protects Claire [the protagonist] from BJR, keeps Jamie from
                            leading the clan. Not a traditional romance.</quote> Melissa registered
                        her disappointment, <quote rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">True, but
                            was hoping for something more romantic in a romance novel. I’m enjoying
                            their post-wedding courtship more.</quote> This tweet inspired Sandy to
                        share the link to the <title rend="italic">Books and Writers
                            Community</title> forum detailing how marketing plans for the book
                        shaped its blending of genre conventions, a contextual clue tapping into the
                        book trade’s larger industrial motives as an explanation for the author’s
                        aesthetic choice. Sandy’s tweet, <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#outlander2014">Here’s an explanation from @Writer_DG on why
                            Outlander was originally marketed as a romance,</quote> offered the link
                        to data that, Melissa acknowledged, had enriched her reading experience:
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">Thanks for the info about
                            Outlander. Didn’t know much about it until I decided to do
                            #1book140</quote>
                        <ptr target="#outlander2014"/>. The Twitter exchange was fruitful and indeed
                        drove directly at the heart of what makes <title rend="italic">Outlander
                        </title>author Diana Gabaldon so interesting: her willingness to blend
                        genres from historical fiction to mystery to science fiction to fantasy.
                        This source of knowledge about the text enlightened the reader, while
                        spreading the conversation to a separate but related online reading
                        community. Elsewhere on #1book140, readers credit their community for
                        encouraging them for concentrating their attention. On 11 February 2014,
                        jompoi, for example, tweeted that <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#outlander2014">#1book140 helps me learn 2 appreciate
                            different genres, books’ merits and flaws,</quote> thanking the reading
                        community for helping to sustain his attention and interest. <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">I’ve completed every #1book140
                            selection, and will do so with this one as well,</quote> he said,
                        allowing that <quote rend="inline" source="#outlander2014">otherwise I
                            would have quit after 100 pages or so</quote>
                        <ptr target="#outlander2014"/>. </p>
                    <p>Such discussions reveal how reading communities can use the web to increase
                        users’ intelligence through speed and efficiency without neglecting a more
                        time-honored understanding of intelligence measured by depth of thought.
                        Collaboration among <title rend="italic">Outlander</title> readers places
                        into proper perspective findings suggesting cognitive effects of the massive
                        increase in Internet use in the last decade include a decline in <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#greenfield2009">deep processing</quote> that underpins <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#greenfield2009">mindful knowledge
                                acquisition, inductive analysis, critical thinking, imagination, and
                                reflection</quote>
                            <ptr target="#greenfield2009" loc="70"/>
                        </cit>. Such reading communities dispel fears that browsing, scanning and
                        skimming would eliminate the capacity to immerse oneself in a longer work of
                        writing, and commit a level of concentration that exerts control over the
                        text rather than succumbing to the whim of clicking on the next attractive
                        hyperlink or banner advertisement. With each new media product, the Internet
                        will continue to spawn <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2005">new forms of
                                <soCalled>reading</soCalled>…as users <soCalled>power
                                browse</soCalled> horizontally through titles, contents pages and
                            abstracts going for quick wins</quote> in order to adapt to those new
                        modalities <ptr target="#liu2005" loc="700–12"/>. Such browsing and scanning
                        can co-exist with deep reading and even enhance it, as the speed with which
                        the reader’s shared link about <title rend="italic">Outlander</title>’s
                        genre conventions attests. Ironically, the culture of distraction in which
                        newspaper sections like the <title rend="italic">Boston Globe</title>’s
                            <title rend="quotes">Short Takes</title> have become staples in most
                        daily print and online formats has only encouraged readers to share such
                        material through CMC and SMS to enrich their collective deep reading. The
                        power of the Internet to scatter attention becomes the very resource
                        providing the tools for this counter-revolution. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Online Social Reading as Mass Collaboration</head>
                    <p>#OccupyGaddis is a reading group whose stated purpose is to discuss William
                        Gaddis’s <title rend="italic">J.R.</title>, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#konstantinou2012">a book about our
                                fragmented attention and a book designed to tax our capacity to pay
                                attention — to demand higher and deeper levels of attention from us
                                — in a world imagined to be (both in 1975 and today) a kind of
                                conspiracy to keep us from focusing on what is right in front of
                                us</quote>
                            <ptr target="#konstantinou2012"/>
                        </cit>. The large online reading group recently assembled through Twitter
                        and message boards to peruse Gaddis’s exceptionally difficult and complex
                        novel. Lee Konstantinou <ptr target="#konstantinou2012"/>, the group’s
                        founder, called the project #OccupyGaddis invoking a spirit of protest
                        against the fragmentation and alienation of digital culture. His project was
                        inspired by the <title rend="italic">New Yorker </title>article on Gaddis by
                        Jonathan Franzen, <title rend="quotes">Mr. Difficult,</title> which alerted
                        him to the unsalable yet brilliant 976-page narrative sprawl. Konstantinou’s
                        hypothesis was that, confined to the medium of print and offline discussion,
                        the novel’s value remained hidden from readers. They lacked what the
                        Internet would provide: access to each other and rich stores of data to
                        gloss the text and unleash its full significance. Once the online public had
                        disintermediated access to it, the success of the group would represent a
                        form of protest against the most distracting reading environment in media
                        history, ironically proving that digital ecosystem conducive to collective
                        deep reading. Exhorting the readers, he wrote, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#konstantinou2012">the great virtue of
                                collective reading projects is that they give us occasion to work
                                together to help us sustain our attention, to achieve goals we might
                                have thought too difficult to attain working on our own</quote>
                            <ptr target="#konstantinou2012"/>
                        </cit>.</p>
                    <p>The inspiration to launch the project on the web came from the online reading
                        of David Foster Wallace’s <title rend="italic">Infinite Jest</title> by a
                        group who called their undertaking of his unwieldy and profound novel from
                        June through August of the year the author passed away <title rend="quotes"
                            >Infinite Summer</title>
                        <ptr target="#coscarelli2009"/>. This movement’s taking place online and not
                        live and in print suggests the compatibility of serious reading discussions
                        with popular social media. Jim Collins (2010) asks why serious literary work
                        should be understood as <emph>competing</emph> with the Internet and popular
                        entertainment. Instead, he suggests reframing the question in a way that
                        does not pit literary reading against popular reading in an antagonist
                        relation, considering instead <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#collins2010"
                            >how the experience of serious literary work [has] become popular visual
                            entertainment</quote>
                        <ptr target="#collins2010" loc="17"/></cit>. Konstantinou’s experiment illustrates
                        precisely the interdependence of mass media and literary reading
                        illuminating the <quote rend="inline" source="#collins2010">crucial
                            associated tastes</quote> conjoining <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#collins2010">literary experiences…no longer restricted to the
                            solitary act of reading a book</quote>
                        <ptr target="#collins2010" loc="17"/></cit>. <title rend="quotes">Infinite
                            Summer,</title> which took place summer of 2009, has found a lively
                        following, further indicating the type of interest in more sustained reading
                        experiences than the Internet typically offers, while also capitalizing on
                        the networking capacity of social media. </p>
                    <p> When entering the <title rend="quotes">Infinite Summer</title> message
                        board, one is immediately struck by a sense that reading passively for
                        escapist entertainment is anathema to the objective of this online
                        community, signified by the notice at the top of the screen in red: <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#infinitesummer2009">There are NO spoiler
                            restrictions in this forum</quote>
                        <ptr target="#infinitesummer2009"/></cit>. <title rend="quotes">Infinite
                            Summer</title> readers were unleashed from such concerns about spoiling
                        the entertainment of the uninitiated, and thus could delve into the full
                        scale of interconnected scene sequences and foreshadowing in <title
                            rend="italic">Infinite Jest</title>’s sophisticated narrative structure.
                        Online Wallace readers were thus not only analytically inclined on the
                        forum, their critical impulse had them thinking in terms of the book within
                        the context of its convergence across multiple media platforms. One of the
                        154 topics introduced by readers on the forum, for example, received 41
                        replies to a post on <title rend="quotes">Movie Adaptations of <title
                                rend="italic">Infinite Jest.</title>
                        </title> The critical discussion that ensued ranged from speculation about
                        which directors could possibly pull off such a feat — David Lynch, Terry
                        Gilliam, and the Coen Brothers topped the list — in terms of the resonance
                        of their aesthetic with that of Wallace’s, a concern problematized by the
                        translation of his seemingly unfilmable and unwieldy narrative into a motion
                        picture. The difficulty of such a project raised the question of what
                        specifically in Wallace’s novel could speak to its essence on film,
                        releasing a tide of suggestions on which parts of the novel were
                        indispensible and which could be omitted. Indeed, the seemingly profound and
                        intractable incompatibility between Wallace’s work and the medium of film
                        presented readers with a conceptual challenge they embraced as an occasion
                        to immerse themselves in the finer points of the novel. One discussant,
                            <q>Doubtful Geste,</q> for example noted, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#infinitesummer2009">Lynch seems to find
                                his greatest pleasure and/or solace in rushing towards a certain
                                extreme surrealism and individual obsession that DFW is trying to
                                make sure (his characters) are NOT lost in, to make sure (his
                                characters) find ways to reconnect/remain invested in community and
                                personal connection</quote>
                            <ptr target="#infinitesummer2009"/>
                        </cit>. </p>
                    <p>The <title rend="quotes">Infinite Summer</title> forum not only engaged
                        readers in broader critical considerations of the translation of Wallace’s
                        aesthetic across media and in the hands of other cultural producers. It also
                        featured discussion reflecting an appreciation for Wallace’s linguistic
                        brushstrokes at the sentence level. Those puzzling over the tone of a scene
                        or the logic of the novel’s discordant plot sequencing received feedback
                        clarifying the text and drawing them into the conversation’s broader
                        concerns. One reader, <q>TIBBIT,</q> wonders why Wallace mocks the AA
                        gathering and men’s meetings the character Hal attends, and learns from
                        another reader that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#infinitesummer2009">This scene is
                                hilarious and painful at the same time, like so much of the novel. I
                                think the book is a tragedy, so [it is tragic] that Hal almost makes
                                it to a meeting where he can connect with others, but ends up in the
                                wrong place at the wrong time, which turns out to be a big unhelpful
                                joke</quote>
                            <ptr target="#infinitesummer2009"/>
                        </cit>. The irony of this comment is that <emph>it</emph> comes in the
                        context of a group discussion among participants conjoined by a common
                        interest who would otherwise be strangers, not unlike the meetings Hal
                        attends. Only this online gathering, as the post and its response
                        demonstrate, is both functional and mutually edifying. The forum’s own
                        eccentric posts tending toward inadvertent self-parody or disruption of the
                        community’s analytic bent are met with the democratic process known as the
                        non-reply. </p>
                    <p>The default behavior of <title rend="quotes">Infinite Summer</title> members
                        is the facilitation of deeper understandings of Wallace’s work and its
                        broader significance. Discussion may be sprawling, but it touches base with
                        keynotes from the text with regularity. Retyping passages for readers who do
                        not have immediate access to the text is common practice. For example, one
                        reader’s request for <q>the text of the
                            section where Himself reminisces about <q>how [he] first became interested in annulation</q>
                        </q> was met by another, Robbi60, who dutifully retyped the lengthy
                        multi-paragraph excerpt and posted it immediately from Italy. Such
                        facilitation of material simultaneously breaks down the isolating barriers
                        of reading alone on print, and opens channels of discussion driven by a
                        shared desire to engage critically with Wallace’s novel. </p>
                    <p>The free flow between print and digital media in online book communities such
                        as <title rend="quotes">Infinite Summer</title> illustrates Jeff Howe’s
                        assertion that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#howe2012">conventions, like
                            the <q>novel,</q> the <q>book</q> and even the very act of reading are
                            no more immutable than language itself</quote>
                        <ptr target="#howe2012"/></cit>. Not only is deep reading and the book thriving in
                        our culture, the very engine driving their renaissance ironically is the web
                        itself. <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#howe2012">A book club that meets virtually
                                on the Internet represents something wholly new in literary culture:
                                reading as an act of mass collaboration</quote>
                            <ptr target="#howe2012"/>
                        </cit>. To communicate one’s thoughts on difficult and richly crafted works
                        through a truncated medium like Twitter would appear to defeat the purpose.
                        Yet Twitter is just one step in an elaborate transmedia chain in which
                            <soCalled>bookies</soCalled>
                        <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#howe2012">copy passages off their iPads,
                                Nooks and Kindles and then paste them into tweets before toggling
                                back to their texts. They post longer comments to their Facebook
                                accounts. They create Google maps that display the GPS coordinates
                                of where individual members are reading</quote>
                            <ptr target="#howe2012"/>
                        </cit>. CMC and SMS typical of such reading groups embodies a <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#soffer2012">language and media ideology that
                            emphasizes the fluidity and instability</quote> of typographic
                        expression <ptr target="#soffer2012" loc="1105"/>. The wider cultural
                        movement toward deep reading and long form texts paradoxically <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#soffer2012">is well-integrated in the
                                postmodern trends that provide ideological justification for
                                undermining rigid, modernist linguistic rules</quote>
                            <ptr target="#soffer2012" loc="1105"/>
                        </cit>. 1book140, a month-long meeting of readers who collectively choose a
                        book to read from one announced genre, has brought new life to <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#howe2012">reading, the original
                                    <soCalled>lean back</soCalled> occupation</quote>
                            <ptr target="#howe2012"/>
                        </cit>. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Deinstitutionalization and Participatory Culture</head>
                    <p>This dynamic of reading as an act of mass collaboration suggests a grass
                        roots movement like those defined in Clay Shirky’s defense of the Internet’s
                        democratic function to offer a space for organization without the hegemonic
                        bureaucratic features of formal organizations <ptr target="#shirky2009"/>.
                        The movement away from institutionalization, he argues, has enabled a
                        greater degree of such mass collaboration in which <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#shirky2009">we can do things for strangers
                                who do things for us at low enough cost to make that kind of
                                behavior attractive</quote>
                            <ptr target="#shirky2009" loc="127"/>
                        </cit>. Jurgen Habermas’s comments are helpful here in describing the
                        processes of deinstitutionalization, which help explain this as a type of
                        romantic reaction against the development of capitalism. Indeed, the
                        proliferation of online commerce has accelerated, reduced, and dehumanized
                        interpersonal communication during the digital revolution, just as the
                        mechanization of culture during the nineteenth century increasingly
                        calibrated and automated everyday labor and leisure life. Romantic thinkers
                        such as Ralph Waldo Emerson and Thomas Carlyle rebelled against the
                        mechanization of culture to defend and retrieve humanity they felt was lost
                        in rigid Lockean rationality. Habermas argues that the public sphere is
                        incapable of providing meaningful concrete confirmation of social structures
                        and their subjective identities within them <ptr target="#habermas1974"/>.
                        The anthropological protest against modernity is inclined toward that which
                        is presumably more real. For Andrew Jackson, this was specie, or hard
                        currency. For Ralph Waldo Emerson, this was intuition and nature. For the
                        rising mass of online deep readers, this is textured narrative. </p>
                    <p>Social theorist Arnold Gehlen has also argued that deinstitutionalization
                        occurs when normative codes for social behavior lose their plausibility <ptr
                            target="#turner2001" loc="95"/>. We are in an era in which the
                        conventions of online communication are no longer agreeable with a populace
                        demanding more sophisticated material. This brings the taken-for-granted
                        background structure into the foreground, where institutions are
                        self-consciously rearranged. Nineteenth century collectives such as Brook
                        Farm represented precisely such a gesture, in which normative codes of
                        acquisitive behavior were radically reconceived in communal living. Emerson
                        did the same with conventional codes of vocational expectations. Today, the
                        online collectivization of intellectuals offers an escape from the shallows
                        of Internet culture. Gehlen identifies a salient feature of modernity in
                        that the foreground of choice is growing, while the background pattern of
                        stable, reliable institutions diminishes <ptr target="#turner2001" loc="95"
                        />. The Internet — with its unlimited number of reading communities now
                        making themselves known to each other — has radically proliferated choice
                        and in the process has unleashed the culture from the institutions that
                        formerly regulated intellectual exchange. </p>
                    <p>Rebellion against the institutionalization of technology works to liberate
                        the culture to use the technology for its own self-determined aims. In
                            <title rend="italic">The Blind Giant: Being Human in the Digital World
                        </title>(2012), Nick Harkaway voices a similar optimistic view of new media,
                        and the future of digital reading. Although he expresses his disdain for
                        Google, describing it as <quote rend="inline" source="#harkaway2012">a
                            faith-based technocapitalist entry,</quote> a point Carr also expands on
                        convincingly, Harkaway concludes that we are responsible for the world that
                        technology helps us create: technology is an instrument, not an agent. The
                        enemy, he assures us, is our ignorance, not software. Harkaway is
                        particularly critical, however, of Google’s insistence on digitizing the
                        world’s books, a concern which intersects significantly with the pattern of
                        the Internet’s development into the medium that subsumes all other media
                            <ptr target="#harkaway2012"/>. The effect on books, once digitized,
                        directly bears an effect on narrative. Texts become broken up, mixed and
                        spread around, in a realization of the precepts of mashup theory. Once
                        digitized, books become subjected to <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#sonvilla-weiss2010">Collage, montage, sampling or remix
                            practices</quote> that borrow fragments <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#sonvilla-weiss2010">through alteration, manipulation, [and]
                            recombination</quote> to make a whole new piece, in which <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#sonvilla-weiss2010">the sources of origin may
                            still be identifiable yet not perceived as the original version</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sonvilla-weiss2010" loc="9"/></cit>. This is a process by which
                        different information is recombined without changing the original source of
                        information, one evolving as a unique combination of the conversational
                        media known as user-generated content and mass media platforms. Will remix
                        culture destroy narrative as we know it? </p>
                    <p>Twentieth century authors Jorge Luis Borges and Ray Bradbury have argued
                        through their imaginative writing that, although under the significant
                        pressure of the changing media climate, the books and their libraries will
                        survive. Before them, Washington Irving makes precisely this claim in <title
                            rend="quotes">The Mutability of Literature,</title> a story in his
                        famous <title rend="italic">Sketch Book</title> published in 1820 in which
                        the protagonist snooping through a library of dusty old tomes is accosted by
                        one particular volume that speaks back to him. The book tells of his concern
                        for being lost into obsolescence at the hands of the popular presses and
                        cheap literature at the dawning of the dime novel and the penny press in
                        publishing history. In Borges’s <title rend="quotes">Library of
                            Babel,</title> books are lost in their exponential proliferation in an
                        endless archive; in Ray Bradbury’s <title rend="italic">Fahrenheit
                            451</title>, books undergo a stripping down to factoids and an ultimate
                        replacement by screens. Both are prophetic of our current situation with the
                        Web’s limitless capacity to create more text than anyone could ever
                        assimilate in a lifetime and in today’s culture’s inclination not to
                        preserve but to break down, scatter and recombine text. However, the Web’s
                        unlimited size leaves enough room for both the sacred and the profane, for
                        both superficial diversion and serious long form works. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Restoring Narrative through the Internet</head>
                    <p>The replacement of print books with e-books has raised questions of the
                        electronic text’s impact on narrative. E-books render the reader, according
                        to Rick Moody, <quote rend="inline" source="#moody2012">the passive
                            recipient of some narrative bludgeoning,</quote> making devices such as
                        the Kindle <quote rend="inline" source="#moody2012">seem as heart-warming
                            as an electro-stimulator</quote> because they disincline users from
                        moving back and forth through the text <ptr target="#moody2012"/>. The print
                        book, he contends, instead radically empowers the reader because it
                        constitutes <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#moody2012">a physical object you can come
                                at in completely different ways</quote>
                            <ptr target="#moody2012"/>
                        </cit>. Similarly, Ted Striphas rejects the argument that print books are
                        anachronistic artifacts <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#striphas2009">whose longevity only hampers
                                our achieving a divine digital future</quote>
                            <ptr target="#striphas2009" loc="4"/>
                        </cit>. According to Jenkins’s concept of convergence in which new media do
                        not replace old media but coalesce with and interdepend on them, print books
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#striphas2009">hold a deep and abiding
                            history that belong in and to our own age</quote> every bit as much as
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#striphas2009">so-called cutting edge
                            technologies</quote> such as iPad and Kindle <ptr target="#striphas2009"
                            loc="4"/>. Critics have concurred that the publishing industry is
                        undergoing an e-revolution, but the question of its effect on narrative and
                        reading experience is subject to debate. If <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#carreiro2010">it will do society little
                                good to waste time lamenting, because e-books are here to
                                stay</quote>
                            <ptr target="#carreiro2010" loc="220"/>
                        </cit>, how have readers responded to the social dimension of digital
                        reading’s new interactive potential? The counter-revolution under way is not
                        just technological, but a very human movement to recapture what the digital
                        age has threatened to rob readers of: the power of the immersive deep
                        reading in long form narrative. Because its dialectic is rich enough to
                        accommodate such a humanitarian movement, the Internet can provide the
                        medium to inspire its own counter-revolution. </p>
                    <p>A new appreciation for narrative has developed in response to the loss of
                        sustained reading on the Internet. Alexander Chee’s <title rend="quotes">I,
                            Reader,</title> a 2010 personal essay in the <title rend="italic"
                            >Morning News</title>, laments the deterioration of deep reading in our
                        culture. He particularly regrets the moral detachment that comes of brief,
                        quick-hitting news stories, which for him developed into a malaise of civic
                        apathy. He finds a remedy for this moral conundrum of consuming news in vast
                        quantities but so superficially and quickly as to inspire apathy rather than
                        compassion and civic activism. Immersion in longer works made Chee <ptr
                            target="#chee2010"/>, as it does for many others now visible online,
                        care again about the social consequences of the news. Susan Sontag has
                        similarly found that <quote rend="inline" source="#sontag2007">By presenting
                            us with a limitless number of nonstop stories,</quote> a symptom of
                        their increasing brevity and superficiality, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#sontag2007">the narratives that the media
                                relate — the consumption of which has so dramatically cut into the
                                time the educated public once devoted to reading — offer a lesson in
                                amorality and detachment that is antithetical to the one embodied by
                                the enterprise of the novel</quote>
                            <ptr target="#sontag2007" loc="217"/>
                        </cit>. The loss of immersion in narrative comes with the loss of morality. </p>
                    <p>The need to reclaim the conscientious moral frame of mind deep reading
                        encourages has indeed been a source of motivation behind the movement for
                        longer and more sophisticated material on the Internet. Carr’s measure of
                        the maladies brought by Internet culture serves as a method of understanding
                        the source of discontent with superficial content that has sparked the
                        current deep reading movement. McGann’s more nuanced sense of reading proves
                        a digital humanities culture is indeed viable. But if the message shapes the
                        medium, radial reading online must necessarily be different from its print
                        counterpart. If so, then how has narrative changed in this new media
                        environment? Has digital deep reading altered narrative as we know it? The
                        online revolt against narrative depravation had been brewing since 2001,
                        roughly five years after the Internet rose to prominence. At that stage,
                        long reading online itself was entirely nascent or embryonic at best, as
                        early signs of backlash and sharp criticism prevailed ahead of the concerted
                        mass collaborative social reading movements currently under way. Like most
                        social movements, its beginnings were marked by protest and followed by
                        organization and mobilization. Among the first questions raised at this time
                        addressed the fate of narrative in the digital age. Design critic Jessica
                        Helfand, for example, asked, <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2006"
                            >what happens when a story becomes infinitely changeable?</quote> How
                        can <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">we design for such perpetual
                                unpredictable interruption in a culture in which linear parameters
                                are gone?</quote>
                            <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="122"/>
                        </cit>. If, as McGann has argued, the reading of poetry and literary prose
                        has always been radial rather than linear long before the Internet, it
                        certainly has become more externally referential and polyvalent through
                        online hypertext. We see this not only in literary texts, but also in
                        mainstream popular fiction, music, gaming, film, and graphic novel forums on
                        the Internet. Television shows, like <title rend="italic">American
                            Idol</title>, as Jenkins <ptr target="#jenkins2006"/> demonstrates, have
                        engendered online followings that have outpaced their own producers (and
                        even reviewers as in the case of the <title rend="italic">Twin Peaks
                        </title>series) with their capacity to critically interpret the shows with
                        context and analysis that has enabled them to predict and thus
                            <soCalled>spoil</soCalled> upcoming episodes. McGann’s formula should
                        apply not only to the literary text, but to any media text — from Melville
                        to the World Wrestling Entertainment — whose audience has the appetite and
                        intensity to make it the focal point of serious online discussion. Here we
                        might learn from Chee that what is needed in such a text ideal for deep
                        immersive reading is not necessarily high art, or canonized literature, but
                        one that lends itself to exploration unlike the facile Internet news
                        snippets designed to deflect and diffuse serious reflection, much less
                        foster it. Horse_ebooks gives a sense of the diversity of media texts
                        capable of inspiring thoughtful, extensive conversation on its strangely
                        poetic non sequiturs, a wildly popular platform that emerged from attempts
                        to avoid spam while marketing e-books through the unlikely medium of
                        Twitter. Equal parts online prank and cryptic digital performance art,
                        Horse_ebooks has inspired extensive witty self-reflexive philosophical
                        commentary in blogs and forums. The inspiration for fan art and fiction,
                        Horse_ebooks has amassed 200,000 followers in 2013, signaling a milestone in
                        participatory culture on the web. It also signals a landmark in the
                        diversity of media texts — in this case Tweets — that can function like
                        literary texts for discussion. </p>
                    <p>When the Internet was in its infancy in 2001, there was concern that computer
                        culture would disenfranchise not only written but visual narrative. The
                        advent of the consumer electronics industry, Helfand argued, led to a
                        neglect of <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">filmic
                            storytelling</quote> and the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#helfand2001">power of visual narrative,</quote> which had
                        yielded to an <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">interactive
                            screen-based media</quote> characterized by a <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#helfand2001">reductive pictorial syntax</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="120"/></cit>. Such compromised syntax hampered the
                        storytelling power that Michael S. Malone now promotes as the engine of
                        success in the era of new media. <quote rend="inline" source="#malone2012"
                            >The edge will go to those institutions,</quote> he argues, <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#malone2012">that can effectively employ
                            imagination, metaphor, and most of all, storytelling</quote>
                        <ptr target="#malone2012"/></cit>. This is not storytelling in the sense of
                        creative writing, although his purview is inclusive of that form, but <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#malone2012">Twenty-first century story
                                telling: multimedia, mass customizable, portable and scalable,
                                drawing upon the myths and archetypes of the ancient world, on
                                ethics, and upon a deep understanding of human nature and even
                                religious faith</quote>
                            <ptr target="#malone2012"/>
                        </cit>. Helfand similarly understood that successful <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">interaction design is not
                                only information design</quote>
                            <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="121"/>
                        </cit>. Writing in 2001, she accurately predicted more than a decade ago
                        that <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">as richer more complex
                            content finds its way into the electronic sphere</quote> design will
                        demand <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">more comprehensive thinking
                                that involves cognitive, spatial, and ergonomic
                                considerations</quote>
                            <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="121"/>
                        </cit>. But even beyond more attention to graphic and directional clarity,
                        the demand will only truly be met through the force of narrative. <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">Like the filmic model,</quote>
                        according to Helfand, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001"
                            >successful visual communication will become critically dependent on our
                            understanding of narrative, of audience, and of drama</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="121"/></cit>. Eleven years later Malone would draw
                        precisely the same conclusion. <quote rend="inline" source="#malone2012"
                            >The demand</quote> for narrative excellence is there, but the <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#malone2012">question is whether the traditional
                            humanities can furnish the supply,</quote> he urges, invoking the
                        economic forces driving this current trend <ptr target="#malone2012"/>. As
                        code writing and hardware engineering become more insular and less
                        accessible, the challenge now lies in making a product’s storytelling
                        capacity robust and indispensible. As Steven Jobs remarked, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#dediu2012">It is in Apple’s DNA that
                                technology alone is not enough — it’s technology married with
                                liberal arts, married with the humanities, that yields us the result
                                that makes our heart sing</quote>
                            <ptr target="#dediu2012"/>
                        </cit>. </p>
                    <p>At the heart of the humanities, of course, is Aristotle, the figure of
                        ancient philosophy, whose own notion of storytelling is now in radical flux
                        given the demands placed upon it from online media. This is a situation in
                        which <quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">each viewer becomes the
                                <term xml:lang="la">de facto </term>storyteller,</quote> which
                        raises the question: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">how do we
                            maintain the integrity of authorship, the focus of plot, the lyrical
                            cadences of a storyteller’s voice and vision and point of view?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="122"/></cit> Has this fragmentation eventuated in
                        our narrative depravation, the malady Helfand identifies with shortening
                        attention spans and online news stories? Conversely, can this pattern be
                        understood as enriching diversification, an opening of the process of
                        production of mass media to the populace? Instead of lamenting <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">the emergence of a kind of shared
                            authorship in which the linear parameters of classical narrative
                            structure no longer apply</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="122"/></cit>, an opportunity for a narrative
                        renaissance has been seized and is currently under way. Indeed, this is an
                        opportunity to transform the benefits of radial reading into a richer more
                        immersive experience. The challenge is to devise new methods for <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#helfand2001">visualizing stories in multiple
                            layers, for designing with multiple points of entry</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="123"/></cit>. For film, that challenge has been
                        met by such companies as Media Storm, Brian Storm’s platform for multimedia
                        long form documentary investigative journalism. </p>
                    <p>The Internet has proven to be a large enough environment to both threaten and
                        provide the means of support for a thriving narrative culture. According to
                        Henry Jenkins’s formulation, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2010">participatory culture is one
                                where there are relatively low barriers to artistic expression and
                                civic engagement, where there is strong support for creating and
                                sharing one’s creations with others, where there is some form of
                                informal mentorship whereby what is known by experienced community
                                members is passed on to novices</quote>
                            <ptr target="#jenkins2010" loc="98"/>
                        </cit>, a feature typical of the best and most vibrant online social
                        dynamics. At its most powerful, participatory culture is one in which <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#jenkins2010">each member believes their
                            contributions matter</quote> making <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#jenkins2010">each member feel some degree of social
                            connection to each other</quote>
                        <ptr target="#jenkins2010" loc="98"/></cit>. Indeed, this online environment
                        encourages commentary from readers who do not belittle or abridge narratives
                        such as Wallace’s <title rend="italic">Infinite Jest</title> and Gaddis’s
                            <title rend="italic">J.R.</title> but diversify and democratize them.
                        Longer works are enjoying a resurgence of interest precisely because readers
                        are now more capable than ever to participate in the narratives themselves
                        by demonstrating through online social reading culture precisely how they
                        intersect with and make meaning of their own life stories. Of course, this
                        is no utopia, and strands of the coarse underside of such unrestrained
                        access remain in those who indulge in an <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#helfand2001">ill-defined, anything goes
                            expressionism,</quote> as Helfand describes it, <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#helfand2001">messy and myopic, part stand-up comedy and part
                            soapbox-proselytizing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="91"/></cit>. But most online readers, whether
                        formally assembled in an announced discussion of one text, or informally
                        engaging in an organic exchange over a long narrative work, are not merely
                        solipsistic and ignorant of public issues. To the contrary, there is a
                        considerable standard for accuracy and mutual support in the social matrix
                        of online reading discussion. Any <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#helfand2001">outpouring of unedited thoughts</quote> in
                        serious long form online discussions tends to receive direction support and
                        focus from others <ptr target="#helfand2001" loc="92"/>
                        <ptr target="#jenkins2006"/>. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Toward a Digital Reading Class</head>
                    <p>The increasing interest in deep reading of such long form works online calls
                        into question the pessimism of some critics who have proclaimed the death of
                        the book in the digital age. As Mark Twain would say, reports of its death
                        have been greatly exaggerated. Witness Carr’s apocalyptic bent that fears a
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">narrowing of expressiveness
                            and a loss of eloquence</quote> due to <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#carr2011">our indulgence in the pleasures of informality and
                            immediacy</quote> with the replacement of the formal letter with email
                        and Twitter <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="108"/>. Writing in advance of the
                        deep reading counter-revolution illustrated by 1book140 and Infinite Summer,
                        his rhetoric is unremittingly bleak. He fears the cost of digitization will
                        be <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">a further weakening, if not a
                            final severing, of the intimate intellectual attachment between the lone
                            writer and the lone reader</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="108"/></cit>. Reading, as recent digital book clubs
                        have dramatically demonstrated, has never been more social, convivial, and
                        intellectually vibrant. Serious readers have never been content to remain
                        solitary and silent in their reading practice, but historically have sought
                        out each other by first forming informal circles, then coteries and clubs,
                        before finally becoming institutionalized in colleges of higher education.
                        Margaret Fuller, for example, spearheaded a series of literary
                            <soCalled>conversations</soCalled> in the Boston bookshop with her
                        friend Elizabeth Peabody in the 1830s to provide the outlet for discussion
                        craved by the followers of Emersonian transcendentalism. They would have
                        certainly made use of online media if it were available at the time, given
                        Fuller’s belief in the powers of mass communication, the most potent of
                        which during the antebellum era was the periodical press which she promoted
                        as <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#caneandalves2001">the only efficient
                            instrument for the education of the people</quote>
                        <ptr target="#caneandalves2001"/></cit>. Thus Carr’s nostalgia for isolated
                        reading and isolated authorship appears suspect to harkening back to a
                        golden age of print culture that never really existed. His indictment of
                        online book clubs complains that they are merely symptoms of <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#carr2011">the Web’s tendency to turn all media
                            into social media</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="106"/></cit>. He mistakenly assumes that online book
                        clubs make <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">social concerns
                            override literary ones</quote> in which <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#carr2011">writing becomes a means of recording
                            chatter.</quote> To the contrary, such groups typically reveal an
                        astonishing depth of immersion of a collective whole that can number in the
                        thousands, a remarkable feat in intellectual history that was never remotely
                        possible before 1995. Carr fears writing will be shaped by the ever-present
                        social buzz of email, texting, Twitter, and Facebook to the extent that it
                        will betray a <q>groupiness,</q>
                        as Caleb Crain describes it, all but suffocating the solitary author
                        distilling his or her own unique voice <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="107"/>.
                        But authorship was never such a solitary endeavor, even in the nineteenth
                        century <ptr target="#dowling2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#okker2003"/>. </p>
                    <p> As Henry Jenkins points out in Douglas Rushkoff’s recent PBS documentary
                        film <title rend="italic">Digital Nation</title>, every era in history has
                        always been challenged with the advent of new media that in fact has placed
                        at times tremendous pressure on the culture to reinvent itself. But the
                        culture, Jenkins urges, has proven perennially adaptive when it maintains an
                        open-minded spirit of exploration <ptr target="#dretzin2010"/>. Speculation
                        about technology’s encroachment upon the fate of books and reading ranges
                        from Bradbury’s dystopic vision of nomadic renegade infidels guarding their
                        secret archive of printed material from government book burners in <title
                            rend="italic">Fahrenheit 451 </title>to the 2005 <title rend="italic"
                            >Annual Review of Sociology</title> that made a strikingly similar bleak
                        prediction. Changes in reading habits, as one study claimed, meant the
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#griswoldetal2005">era of mass [book]
                            reading</quote> was a brief <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#griswoldetal2005">anomaly</quote> in intellectual history.
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#griswoldetal2005">We are now seeing such
                            reading return to its former social base: a self-perpetuating minority
                            that we shall call the reading class.</quote> The study then speculates
                        as to whether this reading class will enjoy an exalted privileged status in
                        the future, or whether it will be cast aside and relegated to living on the
                        margins like Bradbury’s nomadic bibliophile hermits, practitioners of <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#griswoldetal2005">an increasingly arcane
                            hobby</quote>
                        <ptr target="#griswoldetal2005" loc="137"/></cit>. The <soCalled>reading
                            class</soCalled> has emerged from the shadows and onto the Internet,
                        where the media now serves to bring them together more efficiently and in
                        greater numbers than ever. Bradbury’s renegade outlaw readers have found one
                        another through the Web and are expanding their ranks as the appetite for
                        serious reading surges into a large and vigorous mass. This is hardly the
                        dwindling marginalized offspring of a superannuated pastime, but the
                        forefront of a renaissance that is taking on all the features of a religious
                        revival. Sustained intense reading is possible and indeed flourishing in the
                        online environment, which has proven electronic media fertile rather than
                        sterile. Such a movement toward online group readings calls into question
                        the anxiety over digital media’s isolating effects. But with GPS regularly
                        in use during the 1book140 readings to locate and bring readers together in
                        physical space, and with events such as the <title rend="italic">Moby-Dick
                        </title>Marathon readings that have recently spread in popularity from New
                        Bedford and Mystic to Nantucket and Manhattan, there is abundant evidence of
                        the Web’s use as a conduit for collegiality and association. Of course there
                        are cases where individuals hide behind their screen identities and squander
                        their lives in online gaming or chat rooms as detailed by Turkle <ptr
                            target="#turkle2011"/>. But the characterization of online use as
                        exclusively isolating and socially alienating breaks down in light of the
                        millions currently discovering new likeminded readers they would never have
                        known prior to the digital revolution. </p>
                    <p>If journalism has begun to collapse under what is now <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#carr2011">an Internet age, a headline age,</quote> and the
                            <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#carr2011">the gray text page, once a
                            magazine staple, has been all but banished</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carr2011" loc="95"/></cit>, its long form offspring are thriving.
                        The culture has rediscovered a world beyond the easy-to-browse blurbs and
                        captions that have come to dominate magazine and newspaper formatting. Now
                        that consumers can talk back to the performances they witness through online
                        media, they can also consume products of intellectual culture, readings that
                        inspire not superficial but profound commentary, in this same dialogic way.
                        The conversation has grown, as the design of electronic products beyond long
                        form written works now encourages social networking. The Blu-ray version of
                        Disney’s <title rend="italic">Snow White</title> enables viewers to chat
                        with each other while watching the film. The <title rend="italic"
                            >Watchmen</title> disc links directly to Facebook to allow live
                        commentary on friends’ pages. Film aficionados now have the equivalent
                        social viewing experience of the <soCalled>bookies.</soCalled> Novels, as
                        Clay Shirky contends, may have been <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#shirky2009">a side effect of living in an environment of
                            impoverished access</quote> when they came into popularity with the rise
                        of the middle class at the dawn of the industrial revolution <ptr
                            target="#shirky2009" loc="111"/>. But now, in the twenty-first century,
                        at the apex of the digital revolution, the revival of demanding and deep
                        long form works have left us with an embarrassment of riches not only in
                        data, but more importantly, the richness of contact with each other. McGann
                        had the foresight in 2001 to observe that digital technology is a boon to
                        the humanities and the richness of deep narrative reading, warning that
                            <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann2001">the general field of
                            humanities education and scholarship will not take the use of digital
                            technology seriously until one demonstrates how its tools improve the
                            ways we explore and explain aesthetic works</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcgann2001" loc="xii"/></cit>. As Douglas Rushkoff reminds us in the
                        coda of <title rend="italic">Digital Nation</title>, technology <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#dretzin2010">challenges us to serve our human
                            values, but we must first learn what those values are</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dretzin2010"/>. As the online deep reading revival has shown,
                        narrative — and all its media manifestations — continues to be the vehicle
                        through which those values are expressed.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bauerlein2008" label="Bauerlein 2008" key="bauerlein2008">Bauerlein,
                    M. (2008). <title rend="italic">The Dumbest Generation: How the Digital Age
                        Stupefies Young Americans and Jeopardizes the Future.</title> New York:
                    Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baron2013" label="Baron 2013" key="baron2013">Baron, N. (2013). <title
                        rend="quotes">Redefining reading: The impact of digital communication
                        media.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publication of the Modern Language Association
                    </title>128.1 (January 2013): 193-200.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boynton2013" label="Boynton 2013" key="boynton2013">Boynton, Robert S.
                        <title rend="quotes">Notes toward a supreme nonfiction: Teaching literary
                        reportage in the twenty-first century.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary Journalism Studies </title>5.2 (Fall 2013):
                    125-131.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="briggs2011" label="Briggs 2011" key="briggs2011">Briggs, M. (2011).
                        <title rend="italic">Entrepreneurial Journalism. </title>New York: CQ
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2012" label="Brown 2012" key="brown2012">Brown, C. (2012). <title
                        rend="italic">In the Footsteps of Little Crow: 150 Years After the U.S.
                        Dakota War of 1862.</title>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="star" label="Star Tribune" key="[unlisted]">Minneapolis: Star Tribune
                    Media Company, LLC, eBook. Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.startribune.com/local/166467906.html"
                        >http://www.startribune.com/local/166467906.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caneandalves2001" label="Cane and Alves 2001" key="caneandalves2001"
                    >Cane, A.F. and Alves, S., eds. (2001) <title rend="italic">The Only Efficient
                        Instrument: American Women Writers and the Periodical.</title> Iowa City:
                    University of Iowa Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carreiro2010" label="Carreiro 2010" key="carreiro2010">Carreiro, E.
                    (2010). <title rend="quotes">Electronic books: How digital devices and new
                        technologies are changing the face of the publishing industry.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publishing Research Quarterly </title>26(4):
                    219-235.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carr2011" label="Carr 2011" key="carr2011b">Carr, N. (2011). <title
                        rend="italic">The Shallows: What the Internet is Doing to Our
                    Brains</title>. New York: Norton.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chabrisandsimons2009" label="Chabris and Simons 2009"
                    key="chabrisandsimons2009">Chabris, C. and D. Simons (2009). <title
                        rend="italic">The Invisible Gorilla: How Our Intuitions Deceive Us.
                    </title>New York: Random House.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chee2010" label="Chee 2010" key="chee2010">Chee, A. (2010). <title
                        rend="quotes">I, Reader.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Morning News</title> (29 November). Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.themorningnews.org/article/i-reader"
                        >http://www.themorningnews.org/article/i-reader</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="collins2010" label="Collins 2010" key="collins2010">Collins, J.
                    (2010). <title rend="italic">Bring on the Books for Everybody: How Literary
                        Culture Became Popular Culture</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="collins2013" label="Collins 2013" key="collins2013">Collins, J.
                    (2013). <title rend="quotes">Reading, in a digital archive of one’s own.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publication of the Modern Language Association
                    </title>128.1 (January 2013): 207-12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coscarelli2009" label="Coscarelli 2009" key="coscarelli2009"
                    >Coscarelli, J. (2009). <title rend="quotes">David Foster Wallace lives on for
                        an infinite summer.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Salon</title> (14 July). Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.salon.com/2009/07/14/infinite_summer/"
                        >http://www.salon.com/2009/07/14/infinite_summer/</ref>. See also <ref
                        target="hhtp://infinitesummer.org">infinitesummer.org</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dediu2012" label="Dediu 2012" key="dediu2012">Dediu, H. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">Steve Jobs’s ultimate lesson for companies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Harvard Business Review</title> (25 August). Available at
                        <ref target="http://hbr.org">hbr.org</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="destefanoandlefevre2007" label="DeStefano and LeFevre 2007"
                    key="destefanoandlefevre2007">DeStefano D. and J. LeFevre (2007). <title
                        rend="quotes">Cognitive load in hypertext reading: A review.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computers in Human Behavior</title> 23(3): 1616-1641. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dowling2010" label="Dowling 2010" key="dowling2010">Dowling, D.
                    (2010). <title rend="italic">Chasing the White Whale: The Moby-Dick Marathon;
                        or, What Melville Means Today</title>. Iowa City: University of Iowa
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dowling2011" label="Dowling 2011" key="dowling2011">Dowling, D.
                    (2011). <title rend="italic">The Business of Literary Circles in Nineteenth
                        Century America </title>. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dretzin2010" label="Dretzin 2010" key="dretzin2010">Dretzin, R. (dir.)
                    (2010). <title rend="italic">Digital Nation</title>. Public Broadcasting
                    Service, video.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gillmor2006" label="Gillmor 2006" key="gillmor2006">Gillmor, D.
                    (2006). <title rend="italic">We the Media: Grassroots Journalism By the People
                        For the People. </title> Sebastapol, CA: O’Reilly Media.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greenfield2009" label="Greenfield 2009" key="greenfield2009"
                    >Greenfield, P. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Technology and informal education:
                        What is taught, what is learned.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science</title> 323(5910): 69-71. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="griswoldetal2005" label="Griswold et al. 2005" key="griswoldetal2005"
                    >Griswold, W. and McDonnell, T., et al. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Reading and
                        the reading class in the twenty-first Century.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Sociology</title> 31: 127-41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="habermas1974" label="Habermas 1974" key="habermas1974">Habermas, J.
                    (1974). <title rend="quotes">The public sphere.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New German Critique</title> 3: 18-34.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harkaway2012" label="Harkaway 2012" key="harkaway2012">Harkaway, N.
                    (2012). <title rend="italic">The Blind Giant: Being Human in a Digital
                        World.</title> London: John Murray.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="helfand2001" label="Helfand and Maeda 2001" key="helfand2001">Helfand,
                    J. and Maeda, J. (2001). <title rend="italic">Screen: Essays on Graphic Design,
                        New Media and Visual Culture</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton Architectural
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howe2012" label="Howe 2012" key="howe2012">Howe, J. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">Books with 140 characters.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New York Times Review of Books </title>(20 May): 35.
                    Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/20/books/review/books-with-140-characters.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0"
                        >http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/20/books/review/books-with-140-characters.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howe2009" label="Howe 2009" key="howe2009">Howe, J. (2009). <title
                        rend="italic">Crowdsourcing: Why the Power of the Crowd is Driving the
                        Future of Business. </title>New York: Random House. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="isidore2012" label="Isidore 2012" key="isidore2012">Isidore, C.
                    (2012). <title rend="quotes">Nate Silver gets a big boost from the
                        election.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">CNN Money</title> (7 November). Available at <ref
                        target="http://money.cnn.com/2012/11/07/news/companies/nate-silver-"
                        >http://money.cnn.com/2012/11/07/news/companies/nate-silver-election/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="infinitesummer2009" label="Infinite Summer 2009"
                    key="infinitesummer2009">
                    <title rend="italic">Infinite Summer: Formed in Summer 2009 to Read David Foster
                        Wallace’s Masterwork <title rend="italic">“Infinite Jest.”</title>
                    </title> Available at <ref target="http://infinitesummer.org/forums/index.php"
                        >http://infinitesummer.org/forums/index.php</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jenkins2010" label="Jenkins 2010" key="jenkins2010">Jenkins, H.
                    (2010). <title rend="quotes">Multiculturalism, appropriation, and the new media
                        literacies: Remixing <title rend="italic">Moby-Dick</title>.</title> In:
                    Stefan Sonvilla-Weiss (ed) <title rend="italic">Mashup Cultures.</title> New
                    York: Springer, pp. 98-119.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jenkins2006" label="Jenkins 2006" key="jenkins2006">Jenkins, H.
                    (2006). <title rend="italic">Convergence Culture: Where Old and New Media
                        Collide.</title> New York: New York University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jenkins2013" label="Jenkins 2013" key="jenkins2013">Jenkins, H.
                    (2013). <title rend="italic">Reading in a Participatory Culture: Remixing
                        Moby-Dick in the English Classroom</title>. New York: Columbia University
                    Teachers College Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jeongandfishbein2007" label="Jeong and Fishbein 2007"
                    key="jeongandfishbein2007">Jeong, S.J. and Fishbein, M. (2007). <title
                        rend="quotes">Predictors of multitasking with media: Media factors and
                        audience factors.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Media Psychology</title> 10(3): 363-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="johnson2006" label="Johnson 2006" key="johnson2006">Johnson, S.
                    (2006). <title rend="italic">Everything Bad is Good For You: How Today’s Popular
                        Culture is Actually Making Us Smarter. </title>New York: Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kohut2012" label="Kohut 2012" key="kohut2012">Kohut, A. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">In changing news landscape, even television is
                        vulnerable.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Pew Research Center</title>. 27 September. Available at
                        <ref target="http://www.people-press.org/files/legacy-"
                        >http://www.people-press.org/files/legacy-pdf/2012%20News%20Consumption%20Report.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="konstantinou2012" label="Konstantinou 2012" key="konstantinou2012"
                    >Konstantinou, L. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Too big to succeed: On William
                        Gaddis’s <title rend="italic">J.R.</title>
                    </title>
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title> (28 October). Available
                    at <ref target="http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1024&amp;fulltext=1"
                        >http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1024&amp;fulltext=1</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kovarik2011" label="Kovarik 2011" key="kovarik2011">Kovarik, B.
                    (2011). <title rend="italic">Revolutions in Communication: Media History from
                        Gutenberg to the Digital Age</title>. New York: Bloomsbury.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="peters2012" label="Peters 2012" key="peters2012">Peters, C. (2012).
                        <title rend="quotes">Journalism to go.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journalism Studies </title>13.5-6(2012): 695-705.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lanier2010" label="Lanier 2010" key="lanier2010">Lanier, J.
                        (2010).<title rend="italic"> You are Not a Gadget: A Manifesto. </title>New
                    York: Knopf.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lessig2008" label="Lessig 2008" key="lessig2008">Lessig, L. (2008).
                        <title rend="italic">Remix: Making Art and Commerce Thrive in the Hybrid
                        Economy.</title> New York: Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="levy2007" label="Levy 2007" key="levy2007b">Levy, D. (2007). <title
                        rend="quotes">No time to think: Reflections on information technology and
                        contemplative scholarship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Ethics and Information Technology</title> 9(4):
                    237-249.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="librarything2013" label="LibraryThing 2013" key="librarything2013"
                    >LibraryThing. (2013). <title rend="italic">Talk</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.librarything.com/topic/168986"
                        >http://www.librarything.com/topic/168986</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2005" label="Liu 2005" key="liu2005b">Liu, Z. (2005). <title
                        rend="quotes">Reading behavior in the digital environment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 61(6): 700-12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="longform2011" label="Long Form 2011" key="propublica2011">Long Form
                    Storytelling in a Short Attention Span World. (2011). ProPublica Forum (17
                    March), The New School, NY, New York, video. Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.propublica.org/atpropublica/item/watch-the-propublica-long-form-"
                        >http://www.propublica.org/atpropublica/item/watch-the-propublica-long-form-storytelling-event</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malone2012" label="Malone 2012" key="malone2012">Malone, M.S. (2012).
                        <title rend="quotes">How to avoid a bonfire of the vanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</title> (25 October): A17.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="many1996" label="Many 1996" key="many1996">Many, P. (1996). <title
                        rend="quotes">Literary journalism: Newspapers’ last best hope.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Connecticut Review</title> (1): 59-69. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1965" label="McLuhan 1965" key="mcluhan1965">McLuhan, M.
                    (1965). <title rend="italic">Understanding Media</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                    Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann1991" label="McGann 1991" key="mcgann1991">McGann. J. (1991).
                        <title rend="italic">The Textual Condition. </title>Princeton, NJ: Princeton
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgann2001" label="McGann 2001" key="mcgann2001a">McGann, J. (2001).
                        <title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide
                        Web.</title> New York: Palgrave.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="miller2007" label="Miller 2007" key="miller2007">Miller, L. (2007).
                        <title rend="italic">Reluctant Capitalists: Bookselling and the Culture of
                        Consumption</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moody2012" label="Moody 2012" key="moody2012">Moody, R. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">Fugue for centrifuges: On Chris Ware’s Building
                        Stories.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title> (25 October). Available
                    at <ref
                        target="http://lareviewofbooks.org/review/fugue-for-centrifuges-on-chris-wares-building-stories"
                        >http://lareviewofbooks.org/review/fugue-for-centrifuges-on-chris-wares-building-stories</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nakamura2012" label="Nakamura 2013" key="nakamura2012">Nakamura, N.
                        <title rend="quotes">
                        <title rend="quotes">Words with friends</title>: Socially networked reading
                        on <title rend="italic">Goodreads</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Publication of the Modern Language Association
                    </title>128.1 (January 2013): 238-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="facebook2012" label="Facebook 2012" key="facebook2012">News-Apps
                    Center. (2012). Facebook (26 October). Available at <ref
                        target="https://email.uiowa.edu/owa/redir.aspx?C=tKmgWnqEXEiIp2sTfLytcsHWiYk_fM8IkSPeO7IuCqWJ5LOjE5q6xhcoqOwgErHJ5aUz-hsPeQ8.&amp;URL=http%3a%2f%2fwww.facebook.com%2fappcenter%2fcategory%2fnews%2f%3fplatform%3dallplatforms"
                        >http://www.facebook.com/appcenter/category/news/?platform=allplatforms
                    </ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nielsen2006" label="Nielsen 2006" key="nielsen2006">Nielsen, J.
                    (2006). <title rend="quotes">F-Shaped pattern for reading web content.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Alertbox </title>(17 April). Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/reading_pattern.html"
                        >www.useit.com/alertbox/reading_pattern.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nielsen2008" label="Nielsen 2008" key="nielsen2008">Nielsen, J.
                    (2008). <title rend="quotes">How little do users read?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Alertbox </title>(6 May). Available at <ref
                        target="www.useit.com/alertbox/percent-text-read.html"
                        >www.useit.com/alertbox/percent-text-read.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="okker2003" label="Okker 2003" key="okker2003">Okker, P. (2003). <title
                        rend="italic">Social Stories: The Magazine Novel in Nineteenth-Century
                        America. </title> Charlottesville, VA: University of Virginia Press.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ophiretal2009" label="Ophir, Nass, and Wagner 2009"
                    key="ophiretal2009">Ophir, E., C. Nass, and A. Wagner. (2009). <title
                        rend="quotes">Cognitive control in media multitaskers,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (24 August
                        2009)</title> 106.37 (2009): 15583-7. Available at <ref
                        target="www.pnas.org/content/early/2009/08/21/0903620106.full.pdf"
                        >www.pnas.org/content/early/2009/08/21/0903620106.full.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="papacharissi2009" label="Papacharissi 2009" key="papacharissi2009"
                    >Papacharissi, Z. (2009). <title rend="quotes">The virtual geographies of social
                        networks: A comparative analysis of Facebook, LinkedIn, and
                        ASmallWorld.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Media &amp; Society</title> 11(1-2): 199-220.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pedersen2009" label="Pedersen 2009" key="pedersen2009a">Pedersen, S.
                    (2009). <title rend="quotes">Have you got a Blook in you? Bloggers moving into
                        print.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The International Journal of the Book </title>6(2):
                    96-100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perlmutteranddowling2012" label="Perlmutter and Dowling 2012"
                    key="perlmutteranddowling2012">Perlmutter, D. and Dowling, D. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">How the humanities and journalism can save each other.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, (12 November).
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://chronicle.com/article/How-the-Humanities-and/135604/"
                        >https://chronicle.com/article/How-the-Humanities-and/135604/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phamandsarno2010" label="Pham and Sarno 2010" key="phamandsarno2010"
                    >Pham, A. and Sarno, D. (2010). <title rend="quotes">The future of reading;
                        beyond the words; on electronic devices; books talk to readers, play videos,
                        and connect them to authors and other fans.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Times</title> (July 18): Sect. AI. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="redman1997" label="Redman 1997" key="redman1997">Redman, T. (1997).
                        <title rend="quotes">An epic is a hypertext containing poetry.</title> In:
                    Rainey LS (ed) <title rend="italic">A Poem Containing History: Textual Studies
                        in the Cantos</title>. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press,
                    pp.142-56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shirky2009" label="Shirky 2009" key="shirky2009">Shirky, C. (2009).
                        <title rend="italic">Here Comes Everybody: The Power of Organizing without
                        Organizations</title>. New York: Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="silver2012" label="Silver 2012" key="silver2012">Silver, N. (2012).
                        <title rend="italic">The Signal and the Noise: Why So Many Predictions Fail
                        — But Some Don’t.</title> New York: Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="soffer2012" label="Soffer 2012" key="soffer2012">Soffer, O. (2012).
                        <title rend="quotes">Liquid language? On the personalization of discourse in
                        the digital era.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Media and Society </title>14(10): 1092-1110.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sontag2007" label="Sontag 2007" key="sontag2007">Sontag, S. (2007).
                        <title rend="italic">At the Same Time: Essays and Speeches</title>, eds.
                    Dilonardo P and Jump A. New York: Farrar, Strauss, and Giroux.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sonvilla-weiss2010" label="Sonvilla-Weiss 2010"
                    key="sonvilla-weiss2010">Sonvilla-Weiss, S., ed. (2010). <title rend="italic"
                        >Mashup Cultures</title>. New York: Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="staley2003" label="Staley 2003" key="staley2003">Staley, D.J. (2003)
                        <title rend="quotes">The future of the book in the digital age.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Futurist</title> 37(5): 18-22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="striphas2009" label="Striphas 2009" key="striphas2009">Striphas, T.
                    (2009) <title rend="italic">The Late Age of Print: Everyday Book Culture from
                        Consumerism to Control</title>. New York: Columbia University Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="npr2012" label="NPR 2012" key="npr2012">
                    <title rend="quotes">The future of short attention span theatre.</title> (2012).
                    National Public Radio (26 October). Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.npr.org/2012/10/26/163649283/the-future-of-short-attention-span-theater"
                        >http://www.npr.org/2012/10/26/163649283/the-future-of-short-attention-span-theater</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turkle2011" label="Turkle 2011" key="turkle2011">Turkle, S. (2011).
                        <title rend="italic">Alone Together: Why We Expect More From Our Technology
                        and Less From Each Other.</title> New York: Basic Books.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turner2001" label="Turner 2001" key="turner2001">Turner, B.S. (2001).
                        <title rend="quotes">Social systems and complexity theory.</title> In:
                    Trevino AJ (ed) <title rend="italic">Talcott Parsons Today: His Theory and
                        Legacy in Contemporary Sociology</title>. Lanham, MD: Rowan and Littlefield,
                    pp. 85-100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="walther2008" label="Walther 2008" key="walther2008">Walther, J.B. et
                    al. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The role of friends’ appearance and behavior on
                        evaluations of individuals on Facebook: Are we known by the company we
                        keep?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Human Communication Research</title> 34(1): 28-49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harlequin2014" label="Harlequin 2014" key="harlequin2014">Welcome
                    message. (2014). <title rend="italic">Harlequin Community</title>. Available at
                        <ref target="http://community.harlequin.com"
                        >http://community.harlequin.com</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="outlander2014" label="#1book140 2014" key="outlander2014">#1book140
                    (2014). #Outlander. 10 February. Available at <ref
                        target="https://twitter.com/search?q=%231book140&amp;src=hash"
                        >https://twitter.com/search?q=%231book140&amp;src=hash</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
