<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">An Agent-based Model for the Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Belinda <dhq:family>Roman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>St. Mary's University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>belinda.roman@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Belinda Roman presently teaches International Economics in the Department of
                     Economics at St. Mary’s University. Her other local teaching affiliations are
                     with the Alamo Colleges in San Antonio. She received her PhD from the
                     University of Western Ontario in Canada and holds an MPhil from the London
                     School of Economics and Political Science. Both her Bachelors and MA are from
                     Texas Christian University. Prior to teaching Dr. Román served as Managing
                     Editor of <title rend="italic">Intensive Care World – The Official Publication
                        of the World Society of Intensive Care Specialists</title> - and Senior
                     Information Officer for the American Chamber of Commerce in London. She also
                     worked for the U.S. Department of State/USAID in South America as
                     Administrative Director of the Electrification for Sustainable Development
                     project.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000142</idno>
            <idno type="volume">007</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2013-07-01">1 July 2013</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2013-02-04" who="MCC">Encoded article</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>The Humanities now confront a new era in cultural representations — the digital age.
               As a consequence, our approach to culture may be modified because technology allows
               us to now visualize our thoughts and theories using digital and computing techniques.
               This research focuses on merging humanities research with computational sciences to
               explore the processes involved in culture dynamics. We present an interdisciplinary
               approach that combines literary studies, economics, and agent-based modeling (ABM)
               and give details of how literature maybe used as a data set that can be translated
               into a dynamic Java-based simulation of human interactions constructed around Game
               Theory. Our model of Cross-Cultural Cooperation is designed to study culture at
               various levels of granularity simultaneously in order to show how micro-behaviors
               might lead to macro outcomes such as cultural group formation. We present one
               experiment based on the literature of discovery and conquest in the U.S. Southwest
               translated into the language of ABM. Additionally, we explore the role of space,
               time, and population-size in this process and offer a discussion of possible future
               directions for this type of research. The creation of our simulator of cultural
               exchange between individuals of differing cultures allows researchers to experiment
               with ideas about first and ongoing contact and speculate with “What if?”
               scenarios.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Hispanic diversity in the virtual world. DHQ publishes research on a multi-agent
               simulation of the U.S. Southwest melting pot.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>An Agent-based Model for the Humanities</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The humanities now confront a new era in cultural representations — the digital age.
               As a consequence, our approach to culture may be modified because technology allows
               us to now visualize our thoughts and theories using digital and computing techniques
                  <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="1"/>. For this, we need an analytical framework that
               integrates various disciplines synergistically. In this research, we offer the
               possibility of complexity science and computer simulation as a means of accomplishing
               this goal in the humanities.</p>
            <p>This work focuses on merging humanities research with computational sciences to
               explore the processes involved in culture dynamics. We present an interdisciplinary
               approach that combines literary studies and agent-based modeling (ABM). The article
               divides into five sections. In the first, we describe our approach to culture. Next,
               we explain our <q>computational turn</q> by presenting the idea of agent-based
               modeling in the humanities. In section three, we give details of how literature may
               be used as a data set. We present our model and the results from one experiment using
               our own ABM simulation in section four. And finally, we conclude with a discussion
               and possible future directions for this type of research.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Hispanic Culture in ABM Perspective</head>
            <p>The intent of our work is to better understand what behaviors give rise to diversity
               within a cultural group, specifically the Hispanic culture as our area of research
               interest. Dawkins (1978, 1999), Cavalli-Sforza and Feldman (1981), Cavalli-Sforza
               (2000), and Sperber (2006, 2007) and others hold that that culture<note> E.
                  Slingerland suggests the humanities have much to offer natural sciences as
                  discoveries possess new challenges to our understanding of us, each other, and
                  life <ptr target="#slingerland2008"/>. He also writes that the humanities can
                  benefit from science such that the two may be integrated. Human experiences are
                  part of human existence and must be studied as an integrated whole. Consequently,
                  bringing the two branches of knowledge together is a goal of this
                  interdisciplinary work.</note> is a second process marching in step with
               biological evolution. The evidence of this process might be viewed from a
               materialistic position (Gabora 2007) such that, artifacts in the form of tools are
               taken to indicate the existence of a <q>culture.</q> Consequently, if we follow the
               evolution of <q>tools</q> in terms of their nature, number, and complexity, we have a
               materialistic approach to culture and its development over time. Alternatively, we
               might focus on the intangible aspects of culture such as the abstract systems of
               language and behaviors (institutions) that transmit information between individuals
               and groups of individuals, leading to learning over generations (Cavalli-Sforza and
               Feldman 1981). These abstractions depend on mind processes such as awareness,
               perception, judgment, and problem-solving <ptr target="#wilson2001"/>. In this view, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wilson2001">Culture is the mental equipment that
                     society members use in orientating, transacting, discussing, defining,
                     categorizing, and interpreting actual social behavior in their society</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wilson2001"/>
               </cit>.<note> Taken from <title rend="italic">MIT Encyclopedia of Cognitive
                     Sciences</title>, ed. Robert A. Wilson and Frank Keil. Boston, MA, MIT Press,
                  2001, p. 120. This definition is attributed to the goals of cognitive
                  anthropology.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When we add <q>Hispanic</q> to culture, we are limiting the view of culture to some
               extent; however, there are diverse views on what Hispanic culture means. For some,
               the Southwestern United States Borderlands embody the Hispanic, but why? Is it as
               simple as the presence of the Spanish at some point? This simplification obscures the
               fact that more complex processes have taken place over time between numerous
               individuals and groups including but not limited to Anglo, Hispanic and Native
               American. The complexity of the process is manifest in the definitions for the term
                  <q>Hispanic.</q> For example, the Real Academia Española notes that it often
               refers to the populations of Hispania, the Roman name for the Iberian peninsula,
               although the dictionary also notes that the term applies to the countries of
                  <term>hispanoamérica</term> and more specifically to individuals in the United
               States whose origin is hispanoamérica <ptr target="#academia2001"/>. Across the
               Atlantic, in the late nineteenth century the term <q>hispanic</q> referred to the
               Spanish-speaking New World <ptr target="#harper"/>. More recently, Hispanic is the
               term used by U.S. government for census purposes to identify members of certain
               groups (Cuban, Mexican, Puerto Rican, Central and South American <ptr
                  target="#census"/>). The tag arises from a process of <q>self-identification</q>
               based on a set of prompts such as <quote rend="inline" source="#census">Mexican,
                  Puerto Rican, Cuban, Central or South American, or some other Hispanic
                  origin</quote> (U.S. Bureau of the Census 1993). However, this Hispanic label
               concerns various groups who feel that it does not adequately reflect the totality of
               their experiences. Hence, we now see Latinos, Chicanos, Hispanos and other
               identities. This diversity of self-identification and its expression as a group-level
               phenomenon known as <q>culture</q> is at the very heart of our research. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The <q>Computational Turn</q>
            </head>
            <p>Complexity or complex systems analysis is concerned with how the <q>simple</q>
               organizes to become the complex. For example, how does a single cell become a brain?
               How is it that a number of individuals acting in an individual way give rise to
               larger social structures such as cultural groups, economies, financial or political
               systems that span the globe? These systems seem to act in ways that are difficult to
               perceive at certain levels of disaggregation (granularity). Additionally, their
               emergence over time is equally difficult to predict, although from the perspective of
               complexity science we can understand the possible systemic outcomes if we can
               understand the nature of individual interactions within a certain context.</p>
            <p>The starting point for this research is based on complexity; that is, to identify the
               overarching system and then to further disaggregate this entity into its individual
               parts such that we understand the correlation in the behaviors of individuals that
               lead to a higher-order system. Individuals and their behaviors are the focus rather
               than simply the individual as a unit in a linear system that adds two and two to
               result in four. The rules of behavior between individuals are about the transmission
               of information and are in fact very simple and limited. However, the emergent system,
               as the interplay of individual behaviors is called, is believed to differ from the
               sum of its parts, and the system itself changes over time. Mitchell offers as
               examples of these types of systems a solar system, the brain, a stock market, and
               global climate change <ptr target="#mitchell2009" loc="16"/>. These are extremely
               complex systems but when disaggregated into their parts planets, cells, individual
               equity traders, and simple molecules are interacting with each other in a way not
               clear to us if we take a systemic view. This is where complexity science differs from
               traditional reductionist scientific analysis in its methodology and view. That is to
               say, complexity science acknowledges there is no clear way to reduce a complex whole
               into the sum of its parts because other forces must be at play between the parts.
               However, we can take a small segment of this complexity and break it down into its
               parts and rules that govern the behavior of these parts in order to better understand
               how a dynamic system emerges with sometimes difficult to predict outcomes.</p>
            <p>For our research, we consider <q>culture</q> a macro-level phenomenon that may be
               visualized as a dynamic process using ideas from complexity in combination with new
               computational technology. In order to arrive at this end, we combine <q>data</q> from
               a set of cultural artifacts — written artifacts to be precise; (2) the concepts of
               evolution and emergence from complexity; (3) a behavioral mechanism consistent with
               culture but translatable to computer code — Game Theory; and (4) a method of encoding
               and visualizing these ideas. In our case, the process of self-identification by
               individuals is recast in terms of game theory in order to better understand how
               individual choice leads to group-level diversity. This, we believe, means that a
               group as it is broadly interpreted contains individuals that share a common process
               of self-identification; however, when the level of granularity for
               self-identification changes, suddenly not everyone in the group fits into the
               previously clear-cut category as was once thought. This we believe approximates
               emergence because it is an inevitable consequence of the expansion of simple rules
               governing individual self-identification. By studying these ideas using complexity,
               we hope to better understand how cultures emerge or evolve, rather than simply accept
               their existence.<note> Determining how an individual came to recognize the need or
                  the ability to dominate the external world is not the purpose of this work
                     <foreign>per se</foreign>. However, the idea that a group-level behavior such
                  as <q>culture</q> emerged from individual decisions, is the foundation. In order
                  to pursue this line of investigation, an interdisciplinary approach is needed.
                  Therefore, extensive use is made of concepts normally found in the natural,
                  social, and computational sciences, in order to study the emergence of a specific
                  culture — in this case a cultural system labeled Hispanic.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Literature as Data</head>
            <p>Literary objects such as written texts are cultural objects that represent cultural
               information. In this respect they might be viewed as material evidence of a culture’s
               existence. In other words, they may be considered as either data points or sets
               relating to a culture. For example, one could count the number of books (data points)
               produced in a given space of time and assign a meaning to the output such that it
               becomes a measure of cultural development expressed through book production. In fact,
               the United Nations Education, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) has taken
               on the task of measuring culture through data such as book publications on a yearly
               basis as one means of measuring the standard of living in a country <ptr
                  target="#unitednations"/>.</p>
            <p>Another view of texts might be that the books themselves contain information about
               the relationships and interactions between individuals within a culture or multiple
               cultures at the time the work was produced. On one level, they represent information
               that may be fact or fiction. On another they contain information that has meaning in
               a cultural context and <q>reproduce</q> in the histories of cultural systems. In this
               respect, Dawkins’ concept of cultural <term>memes</term> as a counterpart to genes in
               evolutionary biology might be used to suggest that a book possesses a meme or its
               content a number of memes that are somehow translated to whomever interacts with the
               book. However, unlike genes, memes undergo continuous mutations <ptr
                  target="#dawkins1978" loc="208–209"/> because each individual experience differs,
               making the fidelity of a given meme ambiguous in terms of the process of culture. In
               other words, the interpretation of the information in the book constantly changes
               through individual experience. Notwithstanding, this Darwinian analogy of cultural
               evolution has found favor with some researchers because it structures the idea of
               culture as an evolutionary process such that new techniques might be used to explore
               the process<note>Whilst for Dan Sperber and Nicolas Claidière, culture spreads like
                  an addiction through individuals, but the transmission mechanism of cultural
                  information is more akin to that of epidemiology (virus) instead of natural
                  selection <ptr target="#sperber2006"/>.</note>. However, as researchers at the
               London School of Economics point out, memes have no constant physical representation
               making them <emph>per se</emph> difficult to substantiate and study <ptr
                  target="#howlett2011"/>. </p>
            <p>Fortunately or not, when studying culture, we are left with cultural products such as
               books and their ambiguous content as sources of information on the past, making
               research difficult. For our study, we suggest that the ambiguity of interpretations
               arising out of historical texts should not eliminate them as a viable source for
               historical research into culture. In fact, we take the view that individuals interact
               with each other through a process of encounter and self-identification, and that
               through a number of different processes, these encounters impact on individuals
               leading to a group-level dynamic <ptr target="#sperber2007"/>. The key point is that
               we are not seeking to identify a specific idea or meme and follow its evolution over
               time. Rather we focus on individual behaviors based on what we believe to be an
               original point of understanding based on a text. From here, our interest is, as
               Daniel Sperber writes, how <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#sperber2007">Cultural information spreads across
                     members of a population through their interactions, that is, through their
                     producing, in their common environment, events and objects that carry
                     information that others can pick up</quote>
                  <ptr target="#sperber2007"/>
               </cit>.<note>He also notes that, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#sperber2007">The state of a culture at a given
                        moment corresponds to the distribution of variants resulting from these
                        micro-events, and the evolution of culture is that of this
                        distribution</quote>
                     <ptr target="#sperber2007"/>
                  </cit>.</note> The cultural information we are interested in relates to
               self-identification.</p>
            <p>As noted above, our research interest is the Hispanic, more specifically the
               Southwestern U.S. and, to some extent, Northern Mexico. These are modern-labels
               placed on a landscape previously unencumbered by political divisions such as an
               international border between Mexico and the United States, and subdivisions such as
               California, Arizona, New Mexico and Texas, or Baja California, Sonora, Chihuahua,
               Coahuila Nuevo Leon, Tamaulipas. In fact, as Arias and Meléndez note, this mapping of
               the region begins with the exploration and conquest of these lands by numerous
               Europeans and their attempt to contextualize their own experiences <ptr
                  target="#arias2002"/>. This being the case we return to first contact between
               Europeans and the pre-existing indigenous groups in a specific area of the
               Mexico-U.S. Borderlands around present-day Santa Fe, New Mexico, because this area
               represents a region known to have been inhabited by Pueblo Indians prior to first
               contact and subsequently inhabited by the Spanish and later Hispanics. It is an area
               of continuous settlement that serves as a starting place for our research on the
               emergence of the Hispanic. We will use modern-day labels for consistency.</p>
            <p>Four Spanish Borderlands texts, or <foreign>crónicas</foreign>, were studied for
               their clues as to the possible decisions that Spaniards employed when encountering
               the Pueblo Indians of New Mexico. It is important to note that the Spanish writings
               were produced under very strict regulations governing these official reports to the
               Spanish monarchs from the New World. In fact, Valcárcel (2010) and Mignolo (1999,
               1995) maintain the <foreign>relación </foreign>(account), typical of writings between
               1505 and 1573,<note>See <ptr target="#insula1999"/>. The entire volume contains
                  analyses and commentaries on the crónicas, relaciones ,and other early colonial
                  writings.</note> operated under two sets of rules, the ones handed down by the
               Crown on the requirements for these reports and those issued by the local
                  governors.<note>In fact, in several secondary works the compendium of documents
                  and detailed analysis may be found in <ptr target="#vazquez2004"/>.</note> Since
               Native groups were an integral part of the process of first contact, where possible
               we attempted to find the Native American voice in these stories. In the Pueblo case,
               the vast majority of the written record stems from research and interests external to
               their world; that is, by non-Pueblo authors such as the early chroniclers working
               under strict guidelines. This presented a significant challenge to any attempt to
               evaluate the Native experience of first contact, given that so much has been written
               and documented by <q>outsiders.</q> Notwithstanding, one means of gauging the Pueblo
               view of their history was through their testimonies as contained in the
                  <foreign>crónicas</foreign>. The Spanish colonial records submitted by secular and
               religious groups recorded Native American belief systems, customs, social
               organization and economic activities but to find these same materials written by
               Native Americans themselves is another matter. Nevertheless, embedded within the
                  <foreign>crónicas</foreign> are fleeting glimpses of these groups. Any early
               Native view contained in the crónicas was mediated through the Spanish writer. We
               have also consulted a second source: works by modern-day members of the Pueblo, some
               of whom have endeavored to record and preserve their histories in writing.</p>
            <p>Two chronicles consulted deal with Francisco de Coronado’s (1540) expedition to
               modern day New Mexico and Kansas in search of Cíbolo and Quiviria. Captain Juan
               Jaramillo’s chronicle was written some 20 years after the expedition returned from
               its travels and is considered by historians as a useful primary source on the
               geography of the region <ptr target="#jaramillo2004"/>.<note>Scant information is
                  available on Juan Jaramillo, but <ptr target="#flint2012"/> offer similar
                  observations to those found in <ptr target="#thrapp1991"/>=, as well as other
                  works such as <ptr target="#winship2009"/>, Herbert Eugene Bolton, George P.
                  Hammond and Agapito Rey, as well as a relatively new entry in the <title
                     rend="italic">Cervantes Virtual Portal de la Cultural Chicana</title>.</note>
               Jaramillo’s text makes references to encounters with indigenous groups in terms of
               marching past <q>
                  <foreign>rancherias</foreign>
               </q> or staying near <q>indiezuelos</q> and <q>ranchos,</q> where Indians cultivated
               beans, maize, and squash (<quote rend="inline" source="#jaramillo2004">Fue ansí, y
                  todo lo que por allí vimos, fue unos indiezuelos en algunos valles poblados, como
                  en ranchería, tierra estéril…</quote>) <ptr target="#jaramillo2004"/>. Although
               fleeting in their representations, these references portray contact with indigenous
               groups that transpired without incident (<q>...llegamos a otro arroyo a donde estaban
                  unos indios poblados que tenían ranchos de paja y sementeras de maíz y frisoles y
                  calabazas…</q>). Jaramillo’s account also includes descriptions of tense even
               hostile encounters between the explorers and tribes in what is now the Great Plains
               of the U.S. (<q>Aquí donde hallamos los indios y nos vieron, se comenzaron de
                  alborotar con voces y muestras de huir, y aun tenían allí algunos sus mujeres
                  consigo, …</q>). There is evidence of cooperation as we noted the importance of
               translators or collaborators with the Spanish (<q>comenzoles a llamar el indio
                  Isopete en su lengua,…</q>). In fact, Adolphus Bandelier emphasized that the
               interpreters who travelled with the Spanish explorers were almost certainly from
               different indigenous groups, such as the Mexica or Tlaxcanas of Central Mexico — two
               of the many groups that accompanied the Spanish — were not always at hand when
               encounters occurred, and when they were, there was a question of competency as well
               as fidelity in the work of translation. Between Coronado’s <foreign>entrada</foreign>
               and the <foreign>reconquest</foreign>, modern surveys of the area suggest that very
               little Spanish entered into the native languages. That is, the Pueblo retained
               linguistic purity <ptr target="#bandelier1910" loc="3"/>. </p>
            <p>The second chronicle is Pedro de Castañeda’s narrative of the same Coronado
               expedition <ptr target="#winship2009"/>. Just as Jaramillo wrote some 20 years after
               the fact, Castañeda also recalls events two decades later, but his motivation for
               writing the chronicle is to correct the misleading accounts of the mythical land of
               Cíbolo. He wrote that the furthest reaches of the New Spain did not hold great wealth
               and populations like those in Mexico or Peru. His report tells us that in some
               instances the expedition encountered depopulated areas or relatively small
               settlements ranging from several hundred to perhaps one thousand inhabitants. This is
               significant because modern scholarship suggests that the population of the region was
               on the order of 50,000–60,000 at the time of first contact with the Spanish <ptr
                  target="#flint2012"/>. There is some continuity between Castañeda and Jaramillo,
               as both write that native populations are seen to live in
                  <foreign>rancherias</foreign> and sustain themselves from hunting and other
               activities. Castañeda’s narrative contains more detail on the landscape and distance
               between the indigenous communities and larger topographical features. As he explains,
               Cíbola was not unpopulated; indigenous populations lived in communities separated by
               several <foreign>leguas</foreign> but in the eyes of Spanish conquistadores were
               considered a single agglomeration of population. Modern-day researchers find the
               Castañeda account particularly important in terms human geography.</p>
            <p>The third Spanish chronicle is by Gaspar Castaño de Sosa,<note>See Schroeder and
                  Matson 1965. Schroeder and Matson include a complete English translation of the
                  Alonso de Leon chapter on Castaño de Soso. According to this version Castaño de
                  Sosa’s <q>talents</q> were greatly esteemed by Governor Gomez Perez de las Marinas
                  on the entrada to the Islanda of Moluccas <ptr target="#schroeder1965" loc="9"/>.
                  They write that Andres Perez de Verlanga’s first hand account is the only known
                  account of the expedition (<ptr target="#alessio1978"/>, <ptr
                     target="#chipman1992"/>, <ptr target="#weddle1985"/>). Luis Carvajal was
                  considered one of the first to enter Texas from Mexico. He was also born in
                  Portugal. He and his wife Guiomar de Ribera were Jews converted to Christianity.
                  His wife was the daughter of a royal slave factor and originally from Lisbon.
                  Archivo General de Indias, <title rend="italic">Archivo General de Indias de
                     Sevilla</title> (Madrid, 1958) (Duaine 1971, Toro 1944, Weddle and1985).</note>
               <foreign>alcalde mayor</foreign> of modern-day Monterrey, Nuevo León (Villa de San
               Luís), during the late sixteenth century. When the original governor of the region,
               Luis de Carvajal, was denounced as a crypto-Jew, Castaño de Sosa was elevated to
                  <foreign>teniente de gobernador</foreign> of Almadén (present day Monclova, Nuevo
                  León).<note>See <ptr target="#schroeder1965"/>. See also <ptr
                     target="#obregon1928"/>.</note> In 1590 Castaño de Sosa was forced to leave
               Almadén having been himself denounced before the Real Audencía by Juan Morlete as a
               slave trader and possible crypto-Jew. His flight from Monterrey to Santa Fe was
               published in 1592, and again in a collection of writings from the Archivo de Indias
               in 1871. Gaspar Castaño de Sosa’s <title rend="italic">Memoria</title> is an
               interesting document to the extent that it details the exploits and encounters of
               this unauthorized expedition to New Mexico some eight years ahead of Juan de Oñate,
               whose conquest would lead to a more permanent settlement of New Mexico <ptr
                  target="#castano2004"/>. The work itself has received relatively little critical
               attention when compared to the more known exploits such as those of Coronado or Juan
               de Oñate.<note>See <ptr target="#bancroft1889"/> and Dorothy Hulls’ summary. Matson
                  and Schroeder suggest that the journalist may have been Andres Perez, although
                  they are not certain <ptr target="#schroeder1965" loc="17"/>. Interestingly, they
                  note that two Indians who remained with the Pueblo after Castaño de Sosa’s case
                  was remanded into the custody of Spain’s representatives in 1593 also appear in
                  the record regarding Juan de Oñate’s activities in the region <ptr
                     target="#schroeder1965" loc="16"/>.</note> While the historical significance of
               this chronicle is not the focus of this research <foreign>per se</foreign>, it is
               interesting that Castaño de Sosa names and takes possession of lands as he makes his
               way to Santa Fe, following the norms established by the Spanish Crown. We read in his
               narrative that the first encounter with the indigenous populations, described as
                  <foreign>gente de paz</foreign> (literally <q>peaceful people</q>), is facilitated
               by a native identified as Miguel, who is familiar with Spanish, having served with an
               unidentified group of soldiers from whom he learned the language. He is welcomed into
               the Castaño de Sosa retinue as a translator <ptr target="#castano2004"/>. Another
               interesting aspect of Castaño de Sosa’s <title rend="italic">Memoria</title> is that
               encounters with Native Americans are almost a daily occurrence and seemingly friendly
               by all accounts <ptr target="#castano2004"/>. However, it is curious that in this
               time period, we find Indians who have already acquiesced to the will of the Spanish
               Monarchy and the Catholic Church. In the first one hundred years after Cortés, the
               north-western frontier was, according to Castañeda, at Culiacán in Sinaloa <ptr
                  target="#winship2009"/>. The northern frontier according to Matson and Schroeder
               was at the San Gregorio River in southern Chihuahua in 1581, although slave raids had
               reached beyond <ptr target="#schroeder1965" loc="6"/>. In fact, Capitan Lope de
               Aritit had reached the Concho River in search of slaves. Captain Mateo Gonzales had
               taken slaves from the junction of the Rio Grande and Rio Conchos, and Gaspar de Luxan
               also entered the region in 1581. The north-eastern frontier during this period would
               have been at Monterrey (present-day Mexico) at best. The fact that slaving raids were
               taking place indicates that this region was beyond Spanish control, which means it
               remained virtually impossible that as Castaño de Sosa moved across this region, he
               truly found native groups who had submitted to Spanish authority. Notwithstanding,
               the Castaño de Sosa report contains many references to encounters with indigenous
               groups that were mostly friendly but turned hostile once he reached modern-day Santa
               Fe <ptr target="#castano2004"/>. </p>
            <p>The last Spanish chronicle consulted discusses the travels of two Franciscan friars,
               Francisco Domínguez and Silvestre Vélez de Escalante, who set out from Santa Fe, New
               Mexico in 1776 to open a route to Monterey, California. Thanks to Father Escalante’s
               chronicling of the expedition, their attempt to link New Mexico with the Pacific
               coast could be considered a final point in the cycle of Spanish conquest and
               exploration of North America. Many U.S.-Mexico Borderlands scholars view the content
               of this record as an important contribution to knowledge on the Pueblo Indians and
               Hispanic life in the present-day U.S. Southwest. The Domínguez-Escalante
                  <foreign>Derrotero</foreign> y <foreign>diario</foreign> (route and diary)
               consists of documents not the least important of which is Father Escalante’s report
               (Vélez de Escalante and Domínguez 1777).<note>The copy utilized for this research was
                  found at the Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois.</note> Among the supporting
               documents in the archive is a 16-page analysis by Juan Augustín Morfí of the contents
               of the <foreign>Derrotero y</foreign>
               <foreign>diario</foreign> and its general relevance to the entire Spanish enterprise
               of conquest and discovery. Because Morfí’s analysis represents a consolidation of
               views held by authorities and scholars of the late-eighteenth century, it is
               revealing in terms of Spanish perceptions of European-Native encounters and views of
               a continuously ambiguous frontier region. Morfí is also known in the Borderlands for
               his work on the history of Texas, completed as part of the Teodore de Croix
               inspection (1777).<note> Among the publications that deal with this tour include
                     <foreign>Diario y derrotero, 1777-1781, Compendio del diario del viaje a las
                     Provincias Internas [de fray Juan Agustín Morfi]: Chihuahua, 26 abril
                     1778,</foreign> and <foreign>History of Texas, 1673-1779</foreign>
                  <ptr target="#morfi1967"/>. For his diary and travel routes in digital format, see
                     <ptr target="#morfi1967"/>.</note> The contents of Morfí’s comments are
               significant because they reveal a number of considerations. Firstly, as late as the
               end of the eighteenth century, communication between New Mexico and <q>old</q> Mexico
               was limited meaning the colonial seat at Santa Fe functioned in relative isolation.
               Morfi also writes that of all the indigenous groups in America (North, Central and
               South), the only ones to have actually declared <q>war</q> with the Spanish are the
               Apaches and Comanches in the north. This is significant because, if true, the fact
               highlights a great difference between the northern and other frontier-regions in
               Spanish America. Finally, his writings highlight that Native Americans were far from
               monolithic and their inter-relationships were as much a balancing act between
               themselves and their distinct cultures as their experiences with the Spanish. Morfi’s
               work also gives us a more concrete view of how the Spanish crown thought to delimit
               its boundaries, following geographic landmarks such as the Colorado River and the Red
               River. The urgency to label, define and delimit was sparked by French incursions in
               Texas and Louisiana, and Russian and British explorers in the Upper Pacific
               Northwest. Father Morfí’s analysis of the Domínguez-Escalante diaries serves as an
               excellent bookend to the reading of these chronicles because it truly represents an
               end to the cycles of conquest and discovery. Subsequent writers would increasingly
               address military and political considerations rather than the raw nature of the
               region, taking for granted that Spain had imprinted itself on the land and its
               people.</p>
            <p>In terms of what might have been said or written from the perspective of Native
               America during this early period, precious little survives. One source may be found
               in the documents of the Juan de Oñate expedition which ended with a pogrom against
               the Ácoma Pueblo in 1599. The details of this event have been well researched, most
               notably by historians such Marc Simmons (1993) as well as H.H. Bancroft (1889), G.
               Hammond and A. Rey (1953). An official enquiry into the reports of atrocities
               committed during the pogrom reached Mexico and Spain, leading to the trials,
               subsequent conviction, and banishment of Oñate from New Mexico. These records include
               statements from numerous eyewitnesses including natives of central Mexico who
               traveled with Oñate and a number of Ácoma.<note> Many thanks to the Research Center
                  for Romance Studies, International and Area Studies, University of California,
                  Berkeley; specifically, the generous help of Jerry R. Craddock, Director, who
                  kindly offered electronic copies of the center’s translation work which form part
                  of the Cíbola Project. Quotes for this section were taken with permission from
                  Jerry R. Craddock and John H. R. Polt (2008), specifically, as noted in the
                  document, the paleographic transcription of the primary text, collation with the
                  second text, and translation into English. This work is based on Archivo General
                  de Indias, Patronato, legajo, 22, ramo 13, ff. 1036r-1085r (94r-143r); ff.
                  1086r-1131v.</note> For example, a native from Tlatenango in the present-day state
               of Puebla is reported to have companied Oñate to New Mexcio.</p>
            <p> In the wake of the Pueblo Revolt, the Spanish, along with 317 Tiwas, retreated to
               Paso del Norte, leading to the establishment of Nuestra Señora de Corpus Christie
               mission and the first significant populating of present day C. Juárez, Chihuahua — El
               Paso, Texas.<note> Tiwa is part of the Tanoan-Kiowa language grouping. The members of
                  this tribe that retreated with the Spanish adopted Ysleta as part of their name
                  rather than Isleta, which was the name of their original settlement near
                  modern-day Albuquerque, New Mexico. Their modern name is Tigua.</note> John
               Kessell (1989) writes that the news of the Pueblo success against the Spanish
               encouraged other groups to test their possibilities. Although never brought to
               fruition, the rumblings of a revolt at Paso del Norte precipitated an enquiry into
               the plotting of a rebellion, which is another source of the Native voice.<note> The
                  documents associated with this case are entitled <foreign>Año de 1685 Numero 4
                     Autos sobre los socorros que pide [e]lgouernador de la Nueva Mexico y otras
                     noticias tocant[es] a la subleuazion de los yndios bar[ba]-ros de aquella
                     prouinzia y la mudanza del Puesto del Pa[so] [d]el Rio del Norte al de la
                     Ysleta a ynstanzias y pedimentos de los vezinos y Padre Procurador Fray Nicolas
                     Lopez, y la gente y demas socorros que pide para este efecto Testimonio sacado
                     a la letra de los autos criminales que se fulminaron contra los mansos
                     apostatas y sus aliados. Contiene quinze foxas escritas y una blanca. Año de
                     1684 años</foreign>.</note> The significance of this enquiry is the fact that
               whilst the Northern Pueblo were enjoying a long decade of cultural renaissance, the
               Southern Pueblo remained under Spanish control, albeit by choice given that they
               retreated with them to Paso del Norte. Still, this fact did not constitute a complete
               acquiesce to Spanish rule. In segments of testimony from the trails we read that the
               governor of the Tigua and his lieutenant, as well as representatives from the Piros,
               were called before a tribunal presided over by Domingo Jirona de Cruzate, governor
               and captain general of the Spanish at Yselta. The testimony begins by stating that
               the governor of the Tigua, his lieutenant, and two Piro Indians were brought before
               the tribunal to give testimony. We also learn that Manos Indians, already
               Christianized, are also in the area and friendly with the two other groups. One of
               the Piros, Ventura, understands the Manso language, thereby allowing the Piros and
               Tiguas to communicate about a potential uprising. In another interesting and very
               relevant segment in the testimony, we read of the inter-marriages. The point here,
               without reading too much into the primary texts, is that at every moment some form of
               individual cultural contact was taking place, whether this occurred intra- or
               extra-tribally, is to some extent unimportant. However, we can see that Pueblo, Piro,
               Manso, Apache, and others interacted with each other as well as with the Spanish.</p>
            <p>The work of Joe Sando,<note>Joe S. Sando was born into the Sun Clan at Jemez Pueblo,
                  New Mexico. He received his education at Eastern New Mexico University and
                  Vanderbilt University. His career includes teaching Pueblo history at the
                  University of New Mexico and ethnohistory at the Institute of American Indian Arts
                  in Sante Fe. Currently, Sando is Director of Archives, Pueblo Indian Study and
                  Research Center, at the Pueblo Cultural Center in Albuquerque, New Mexico. He also
                  serves as consultant to the National Museum of Indian History in Washington,
                  D.C.</note> a native of the present-day Jemez Pueblo,<note>This pueblo was one of
                  the largest at the time of first contact with the Coronado Expedition in 1541. The
                  records of the Antonio de Espejo Expedition indicate that the populations might
                  have been as much as 30,000 in 1583.</note> explains that considerable differences
               existed between and within native groups. He maintains that the Pueblo underwent
               fewer fundamental changes than other tribes who were subjected to forced relocation
               and even complete destruction. This perseverance is attributed by Sando to an
               attitude of <q>accommodation</q> toward European cultures. Of course, this notion of
                  <q>accommodation</q> is of great interest to this research because it suggests
               that beyond individual encounters or interactions, a broader strategy existed within
               the Pueblo that permitted the emergence of a cultural cohesiveness.<note>He has
                  published several volumes on the Pueblo including most recently, <title
                     rend="italic">Pueblo Nations: Eight Centuries of Pueblo Indian History</title>
                  <ptr target="#sando1992"/>, <title rend="italic">Nee Hemish, A History of the
                     Jemez Pueblo</title>
                  <ptr target="#sando1982"/> and <title rend="italic">The Pueblo Indians</title>
                  <ptr target="#sando1976"/>.</note> Another highly regarded Pueblo scholar, Alfonso
               Alex Ortiz, a member of the modern-day San Juan Pueblo, writing in 1994, frames the
               question of Pueblo culture in a more fundamental way: He asks if it makes sense to
               lump the Pueblos together in one group <ptr target="#ortiz1994" loc="296"
                  />.<note>Alfonso Alex Ortiz was born in San Juan Pueblo, New Mexico. He received
                  his B.A. from the University of New Mexico in 1961 and his M.A. and Ph.D. from the
                  University of Chicago in 1963 and 1967, respectively. Ortiz's career included
                  assistant professor at Pitzer College, Claremont, California; professor, Princeton
                  University, and professor of anthropology at the University of New Mexico. Ortiz's
                  interests included contemporary Indian affairs, religion and society, and oral
                  tradition. He also edited Native American writings. He was a Guggenheim Fellow,
                  1975–76; MacArthur Fellow, 1982–87; and awarded the Indian Achievement Award,
                  1982. His books include: <ref
                     target="http://www.ipl.org/div/natam/bin/browse.pl/B1135">
                     <title rend="italic">American Indian Myths and Legends</title>
                  </ref>
                  <ptr target="#ortiz1984"/>, <title rend="italic">New Perspectives on the
                     Pueblos</title>
                  <ptr target="#ortiz1972"/>, <title rend="italic">North American Indian
                     Anthropology: essays on society and culture</title>
                  <ptr target="#ortiz1994"/>, and <title rend="italic">The Tewa World: Space, Time,
                     Being and Becoming in a Pueblo Society</title> (Ortiz 1969). </note>
               <quote rend="inline" source="#ortiz1994">Does the term Pueblo, or Indian for that
                  matter, truly represent the relative or is it an artificial construct developed by
                  the Spaniards and perpetuated by later historians, anthropologists and the
                  like?</quote> This, Ortiz maintains, is the fundamental question at the heart of
               whether or not a <q>Pueblo</q> culture survives. That is, do the <q>Pueblo</q>
               themselves know if they are different from other groups they know or have known?
               Ortiz writes that he believes it can be demonstrated that the Pueblo people have
               believed themselves to share a common culture despite linguistic differences. In
               other words, their cultural cohesiveness is not based on language as is often
               considered key to this notion. Ortiz offers that there is no single institution that
               unifies the groups over the past 2,000 years <ptr target="#ortiz1994" loc="297"/>.
               However, a non-social structural and non-cultural factor is shared by all surviving
               Pueblos, and as Sando also noted, the Pueblo have never been displaced from their
               homeland. It is the sense of place that predominates and unifies the Pueblos <ptr
                  target="#ortiz1994" loc="297"/>. He writes that the Pueblo had a long history of
               contact well before the arrival of the Spanish, much of which is only subject to
               conjecture in modern day research <ptr target="#ortiz1994" loc="298"/>. There is a
               broad history of cross-cultural contact between the groups that encompasses material
               trade in food, wares, and clothing, religious contact, and repeated contact such that
               the Pueblo tribes have, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ortiz1994">touched each
                  other’s lives in the most fundamental of ways</quote>
               <ptr target="#ortiz1994" loc="299"/></cit>. Furthermore, the network of contacts extended
               into Meso-America. The experience with Coronado later served as a learning tool for
               future generations of Pueblos. Specifically, Ortiz writes that taking refuge in the
               ancestral mountains was known to happen on many occasions during the Spanish period
               and helped the groups survive <ptr target="#ortiz1994" loc="300"/>. He offers as
               examples the fact that the Tewa fled to the Hopi and the Jemez to the Navajo.</p>
            <p>With the writings of Alfonso Ortiz and Joe Sando, this research can formulate a more
               general picture of the Pueblo view of first encounters and ongoing contacts. Clearly,
               there were misunderstandings in terms of signals and their meanings despite the best
               effort of the Spanish to use non-Pueblo translators to infer and imply significance.
               It is clear that the pattern of individual and group contact resulted in exchanges
               that in turn resulted in cultural modifications, the extent of which is contentious
               at best. Nevertheless, we see that there is an element of ambivalence in the Pueblo
               view of their contact with the Spanish. For example, Ortiz in particular expresses
               animosity toward the European intrusion and its consequences for Pueblo life;
               however, he also notes that accommodation was instrumental to their resilience. Sando
               appears less reticent in his observations on the Spanish impact on natives, in
               general. Both agree that Native groups interacted with each other on a number of
               levels and that the Spanish and other European groups were not the only cultural
               factors influencing their way of life. It is interesting to note that neither author
               underscores the presence of Tlacaltecans, Méxica, nor other groups from the south as
               particularly influential; rather they are clear that regional contacts with each
               other and tribes from the Great Plains were more significant.</p>
            <p>We believe we have gleaned data from these texts on individual choices about
               self-identification as well as cultural group formation. We take the view that the
               literary record contains information about individual decision-making and that
               aggregations of these decisions are an appropriate analogy for cultural beginnings,
               transformations, and advancements that can be used to explore how behaviors lead to
               more complex systems such as culture. In this regard, our reading of the text has
               given us an idea of the individuals who participated in the cultural system, and the
               types of rules that governed their behaviors.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Agent-Based Modeling for the Humanities</head>
            <p>The process of self-identification contained in the chronicles is based on rules
               governing individual action within a context and includes a number of aspects, among
               them decision-making. We focus our efforts on decision-making because it is
               particularly well-suited to computer coding easily translatable to mathematics. Table
               1 presents examples of text-based references identified as behaviors manifested by
               Spanish and Pueblo individuals upon contact. These references were translated into a
               format more appropriate for game theory (GT), which is nothing more than a
               mathematical expression of different people interacting with each other, sometimes
               cooperatively, and other times in competition with each other, but certainly
               expressing both potential behaviors to varying degrees. John Holland notes, games,
               strategies, payoffs and other scientific metaphors are characterized by rules that
               are more readily converted to <q>mathematical</q> analysis <ptr target="#holland1998"
               />. He also stresses that this process is not absolute, in and of itself; however,
               the decisions of the two individuals is important within the context of other
               simultaneous decision-makers such that a blending of players’ mutual and conflicting
               interests makes the combination of multi-agent simulation and GT interesting for this
               research. While this world of games and their mathematical expression exhibits some
               explanatory powers, the important point is that a wide variety of outcomes may be
               considered. Furthermore, the human behaviors modeled take place outside a market
               construct: In other words, rather than using a market, pricing model, and utility
               theory, game theory centers on strategies and choices. </p>
            <table>
               <head>Table 1 - Select Text Analysis, Encounter, and Choice/Strategy</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Source</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Interpretation</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Choice/Strategy</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Juan Jaramillo’s Relación</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>..un camino todo poblado y en paz…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Already intermixing</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate always</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Pedro de Castañeda</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…diciendo que un hombre le había forzado a su mujer…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Violent encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Defect</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Gaspar Castaño de Sosa</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…y dos días antes, vino a la dicha villa, un indio, llamado
                           Miguel…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Friendly encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Analysis of Juan Morfí</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>Los Tarahumaras y algunos otros cuando quieren reducir el de la
                           obediencia hallan la misma protección en los Navajos y Lipánes.</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Inter-tribal cooperation</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Ácoma trials</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Al ser preguntado por qué este confesante y los demás indios de su
                        pueblo mataron al dicho [maestro] de campo y a otros diez españoles y a dos
                        [chicos], dijo que los dichos españoles hirieron a un indio del pueblo y que
                        por esto se enojaron y los mataron.</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Violent encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Defect</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Joe Sando</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…an attitude of <q>accommodation</q> toward
                        European cultures…</q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Alfonso Ortiz</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…the Pueblo tribes have, <q>touched each
                           other’s lives in the most fundamental of ways.</q>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Tolerance for ideas</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Ysleta del Sur</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…pues los dichos Pedro y Ventura eran de nación Piros y los indios
                           todos eran uno, y eran sus amigos los Tiguas del pueblo de la Isleta, les
                           fueron a hablar y a convocarlos para que todos juntos
                           ejecutasen…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Inter-tribal competition</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <note>An extended version of this table may be found in Appendix 1.</note>
            <p>Instead of counting the number of passages in which an encounter between Spanish and
               Native American was mentioned, we translated passages into game theory and computer
               code for multi-agent simulation. Table 1 also presents a short list of
               interpretations and translations of behaviors for encoding. The artificial world of
               ABMs allows us to imagine a virtual space in which individuals have a limited number
               of choices, fulfilling one of the fundamental criteria of complexity — that a limited
               set of simple rules govern individual behavior <ptr target="#aschenwald2002"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel A: Typical cellular automata grid and visualization after computational
                  instructions. This first image is a typical grid with one yellow cell encircled by
                  eight blue neighboring cells. Source: <title rend="italic">Introduction to the
                     Theory of Cellular Automata and One-Dimensional Traffic Simulation</title>
                  <ptr target="#cochinos2000"/>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel B: Typical cellular automata grid and visualization after computational
                  instructions. This second image represents a transformation of cells based on a
                  set of instructions by Richard Cochinos. Source: <title rend="italic">Introduction
                     to the Theory of Cellular Automata and One-Dimensional Traffic
                     Simulation</title>
                  <ptr target="#cochinos2000"/>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The cellular automata model is a common ABM because it incorporates numerous
                  individuals.<note>Not included in this work are network-based models in which the
                  relationship between entities is key. This method of complex system analysis
                  identifies nodes and linkages between the nodes. The goal is to understand the
                  interconnectedness of the nodes. Mitchell offers an excellent review of this
                  process in Chapter 15 of her book. She cites the hyperlinks between web pages, a
                  neural system, and social relationships as examples <ptr target="#mitchell2009"
                     loc="234"/>.</note> Each cell represents an individual — referred to as agents
               — that resides on a grid in a certain state, chosen from a small number of clearly
               defined possible states, such as <q>on</q>/<q>off</q> or <q>alive</q>/<q>dead.</q>
               The visualization (see Figures 1 and 2)<!-- was figure 1 --> is similar to a sheet of
               graph paper of arbitrary size, dimension, and geometry with a certain (randomized)
               initial setting. In a dynamic model, the future state of each agent is determined by
               its current state as well as the current states of its neighbors. This is important
               in complexity because the context of each individual influences his or her state. In
               Figure 1 we see one yellow cell surrounded by eight blue cells. This is understood as
               an individual surrounded by eight other individuals. In the simulations, the yellow
               cell selects one of its eight neighbors and communicates information based on a set
               of rules that are uniform for all cells <ptr target="#cochinos2000" loc="41"
                  />.<note>John Conway’s Game of Life is the most famous of simulations in this
                  class. See <ptr target="#cederman2005"/>.</note> The outcome of the information
               exchange is conditioned on the status of one or more of its neighbors.<note>John von
                  Neumann and Stanislaw Ulam (1940s) offered a model of life and
                  self-reproduction.</note> In this way, the model is set such that the rules
               governing an individual’s behavior may be simple, but the outcomes of each encounter
               by pairs of individuals when aggregated may become very complex, as shown in Figure
               2.</p>
            <p>Game theory figures into the simulations when individual actions are expressed in
               terms of choices based on a decision strategy. A number of researchers (<ptr
                  target="#page2007"/>, <ptr target="#boyd2005"/>, <ptr target="#axelrod2006"/>)
               have sought to understand phenomena such as culture through the lens of complexity .
               In these and other works some form of game theory and complexity have been combined.
               We are following their research models by opting to use decision-making strategies as
               proxies for cultural attitude, as these lend themselves to encoding. This means
               individuals of a particular culture possess a common attitude toward members of their
               own as well as toward other cultures. The result of each encounter between
               individuals can subsequently be expressed as a payout (cost or benefit). For example,
               two individuals — <hi rend="bold">A</hi>1 and <hi rend="bold">A</hi> — encounter each
               other. As they are pre-programmed with a behavior because of their culture, they
               identify the other based on a notion of self and make a decision to interact or not,
               as the case may be. This interaction is termed cooperate (C) or not cooperate (D). In
               code, this cooperate situation would be expressed as CC if both individuals
               cooperate. When one of the two differs, CD and DC are the possible combinations. In
               the case of both refusing to cooperate with each other, this produces DD. Table 2
               lists the possible behaviors of each individual, and Table 3 translates these into
               coded outcomes. </p>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Types of Behaviors Possible</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Always Cooperate</cell>
                  <cell>Individual always cooperates</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Alternate</cell>
                  <cell>Individual alternates behavior no matter what experience</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Tit-for-tat</cell>
                  <cell>Individual alternates depending on previous experience</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Grudger</cell>
                  <cell>Individual begins with cooperate and defects</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Always Defect</cell>
                  <cell>Defect agent always changes strategy </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Table 3</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Coded Outcomes</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>CC</cell>
                  <cell>Both Cooperate A1 and A2</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>CD</cell>
                  <cell>Agent A1 cooperates, Agent A2 does not</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>DC</cell>
                  <cell>Agent A2 cooperates, Agent A1 does not</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>DD</cell>
                  <cell>Agents never cooperate</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>What does each individual gain from each encounter? In our view, interactions between
               individuals do not simply end with a code. We have taken the position that
               individuals are impacted by contact since it involves an exchange of information.
               This requires additional thought on possible outcomes. As noted above, other
               researchers have used biological notions such as reproductive capabilities or life
               spans as features of social systems. This, we thought, would help incorporate a
               dynamic population that might approximate the Borderlands. Consequently, when the
               encounters resulted in an outcome of C, the ability to reproduce of an individual
               improves. On the other hand when the encounter generates a D, the individual and
               consequently the population experiences a decline in reproductive opportunities;
               stated another way: the possibility of death increases for any individual in the
               entire population.</p>
            <p>More importantly, as we are interested in showing that encounters between individuals
               of different cultures can impact on individual perceptions of self, we translated
               this into <q>tolerance,</q> here defined based on how each individual views his or
               her neighbor in terms of self. The idea is that a member of a cultural group has a
               predefined notion of self, but this may change as members of other cultures are
               encountered or even as members of own-culture who have experienced outsiders are
               encountered. In this way, we have attempted to incorporate the notion of self as one
               of perception and the question of cultural group membership as a question of scale or
               granularity from the perspective of the observer. This means that on one level there
               are the inter- and intra-cultural interactions, represented by individual agents and
               their interactions with each other. On another level, there is the cultural whole
               operating within a larger system of multiple cultures. The vision from above is one
               in which large cultural complexes can be seen as different, but from below, there is
               individual as well as subgroup-level diversity. As a general rule, we have taken the
               position that an individual’s tolerance for difference improves with positive
               encounters (C) with members of a different culture group. Conversely, an in encounter
               that produces a negative experience (D), the individual with D becomes more
               intolerant. The degree to which these changes take place are predetermined by the
               researcher. Referring back to Figure 1, we see that each individual cell has eight
               neighbors, and each of the other neighbors has eight neighbors. In other words, each
               pair of individuals is part of a larger system of pairs of individuals who are
               simultaneously making decisions based on their culture. However, because the process
               of decision-making is iterative and takes place simultaneously over multitudes of
               pairs of individuals, notions of self can change, and when they do, the summation of
               these individual interactions generates a group-level dynamic from which additional
               cultural groups emerge. </p>
            <p>We tested our ideas on group-level diversity using an ABM titled Borderlands5 in
               which the landscape is represented as a two-dimensional finite grid with each cell
                  <q>alive</q> (color) or <q>dead</q> (black).<note> This modeling simulation was
                  encoded with the close collaboration of Fernando Sancho Caparrini, University of
                  Sevilla, Department of Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence. His work on
                  this modeling project and others is part of a larger research project funded by
                  the Canadian government to investigate the impact of the Hispanic Baroque as a
                  cultural system, under the direction of Juan Luis Suárez, Professor of Spanish,
                  Department of Modern Languages at the University of Western Ontario.</note>
               Individuals may be alone or belong to groups (differentiated by color) meant to
               simulate the sharing of common characteristics. An important feature of our model is
               the fact that individuals are immobile, that is they do not move from the cell to
               which they have been assigned, but they will interact with one of the individuals
               occupying a neighboring cell (out of eight possible) giving the illusion of movement.
               Each original individual is born into the landscape with a culture that is
               represented by one color (vector). Each color corresponds to a decision-making
               strategy to be used when encountering an individual or culture. All individuals of
               the world work simultaneously over time, measured in terms of ticks of the ABM clock.
               Additionally, all individuals follow the rules of the world in a synchronous manner
               and modify their individual parameters accordingly. The process is as follows: </p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>At any given step in time (or tick of the clock), a cell will randomly select
                  one of its neighbors, forming a pair. </item>
               <item>The two individuals decide to cooperate or not based on a pre-determined
                  approach (culture group membership). </item>
               <item>Depending on the outcome of the decision because another individual is
                  involved, a number of additional variables adjust in order to capture a
                  population-wide impact or outcome. </item>
            </list>
            <p>Our actual focus is self-identification, consequently the agent does not move rather
               she perceives what is happening around her. In our experiment, self-identification is
               not static rather it is subject to change based on a change in <q>tolerance.</q> In
               Borderlands5 this factor is designed to approximate the process of
               self-identification based on cultural similarity. Tolerance is expressed as a value
               between zero (0) and (1) and is set by the researcher such that it may be very
               strictly defined or very flexible. In the best-case scenario, if both sides
               cooperate, both sides become more tolerant. In the worst-case scenario, neither is
               tolerant, and no one cooperates. In the two intermediate positions (A1 cooperates but
               A2 does not, <foreign>vice versa</foreign>) either Individual A1 or A2 will receive a
               positive benefit from cooperative behavior despite the fact that the other is
               uncooperative. At the beginning of the simulation, all individuals have a tolerance
               level of zero (0), although this changes as the model progresses. Zero tolerance
               means that there is no opportunity for cooperation based on similarity — agents must
               be exactly alike. When the tolerance level is increased (tolerance &gt; 0.0)
               cooperative behavior extends beyond those agents who are exactly alike to everyone
               who is the same. If the tolerance level is pushed to the other extreme (0), everyone
               is intolerant of all other agents and chaos ensues; each individual sees herself as
               unique. As long as individuals A1 and A2 determine that the color of the other is
               less than the pre-set tolerance factor, each individual recognizes the other as from
               the <q>same</q> culture and implements a strategy that corresponds to interactions
               with somebody of the <q>same</q> culture. On the other hand, if the distance is
               greater than stipulated by the system, an alternative strategy will be played. It is
               important to note that if one of the individuals is more tolerant than the other, it
               can transpire that one individual <q>interprets</q> that both are of the same
               culture, while the other <q>interprets</q> that the cultures are different. This is
               ambiguous yes, but it is this unexplained phenomenon that permits individuals to
               possess a more fluid self-identity within limits. By setting up the model as
               described, we are conforming to the guidelines of complexity, that a limited number
               of rules govern individual action and impact on a small number of parameters. And
               yet, there is a broader context that is capture by population-wide factors.</p>
            <figure>
               <!-- figure 3; was figure 2a -->
               <head>Borderlands5 — Panel A: This panel shows the three cultures with clearly demarcated
                  boundaries.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <!-- figure 4; was figure 2b -->
               <head>Panel B: This panel shows the same population covering only 50 percent of the
                  available space.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>In Borderlands5 we created a world with three cultures each occupying a different
               location in the space; however, the total population does not exceed 50 percent of
               available cells. We have deliberately created several <q>borders</q> between groups
               (see Figures 3 and 4<!-- was figure 2a and 2b -->). These are meant to simulate
               distinct separations between groups such as physical barriers — rivers or mountains.
               What does this all mean? In our abstraction, we are visualizing three cultural groups
               one of whom is Spanish and the other two distinct Native American groups — one larger
               than the other. These cultures possess cultural attributes expressed as strategies.
               The largest of the Native American groups will always alternate strategies as they
               encounter members of the two smaller groups. One of the smaller groups will always
               operate with the largest group (say a Spanish behavior), and the other will only use
               an alternating strategy with the smaller group (say Native-Spanish ambivalence). Each
               member of a cultural group always cooperates with those identified as from the same
               culture. This is one of our interpretations of how first and ongoing contact might
               have taken place between the Spanish and Native Americans.</p>
            <figure>
               <!-- was figure 3a -->
               <head>Panel A - Initial Groups for Borderlands5</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel B - 50% Population Density</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
               <!-- was figure 3b -->
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel C - 25% Population Density</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
               <!-- was figure 3c -->
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel D - 75% Population Density</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
               <!-- was figure 3d -->
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Panel E - 100% Population Density</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
               <!-- was figure 3e -->
            </figure>
            <p>Since our interest is the group-level experience, we grouped the individual cells in
               Figure 4 along color lines. Our baseline was the initial setting as seen in Figure 5.
               The images that follow (Figures 7 through 9) show how the original three groups have
               evolved over time, giving rise to additional groups — that a far more complex system
               of identities. The passage of time was simulated by allowing our model to run for a
               period of 6,000 ticks of the ABM clock (in our imagination something akin to 500
               years). The initial settings were not altered except in one specific way — density of
               population. This means that in a series of experiments, we altered the number of
               active cells along the following lines 25%, 50%, 75%, and 100%. Our intent was to
               explore in greater detail the role of population density in group formation. These
               variations were run 20 times in each case and results were essentially the same: an
               average of 10–11 new groups emerged from the initial settings governing individual
               actions. This is interesting to the extent that it suggests that population density
               may not be a determining factor in cultural group formation, rather the key component
               may be individual cooperative or uncooperative behavior. Whether or not this outcome
               reflects reality requires additional testing by us as well as researchers who might
               be interested in this methodology and process. Notwithstanding, the fact that our
               model does not actually incorporate geography possible thorough the use of digitized
               topography maps, does not invalidate our findings. Rather, we would like to suggest
               that self-identification contributes to group formation not only on land but may also
               be the case in cyberspace. In which case, our research only leads to more questions
               and applications.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>We have used literary studies as a broad guideline for translating historical texts
               into an agent-based modeling experiment on a small aspect of culture — how it might
               evolve over time into a diverse and complex system. The individual actors we have
               read about in the accounts of Spanish conquistadors and Native Americans have been
               transformed into computer-based agents operating in a virtual world. Their individual
               attributes have become colors, and each interacts using a game in which their
               decisions center on cooperation; that is, the choices are presented as a form of game
               theory in which any one individual may defect or cooperate with the outcome impacting
               on the tolerance of other cultures as well as their ability to reproduce. In other
               words, we have created an interdisciplinary view of culture: one that involves
               humanities, complexity and computational technology.</p>
            <p>We have used a great deal of imagination and creativity in our research — virtual
               studies require this of the researcher. And although there are limitations, we can
               see that culture may be visualized and studied in this new environment. That is to
               say, a humanistic background does not preclude researchers from attempting to use the
               latest technology to explore ideas common to the humanities. However, it does require
               that we consider how our ideas translate into methods outside our disciplinary
               boundaries. In this case we have used complexity science in conjunction with text
               analysis as methodological approach for studying the intricacies of human
               interactions. This is a bottom-up approach that focuses on the interactions of
               individuals and their role in generating larger and more complex structures that
               cannot be predicted in a linear fashion from the characteristics of the individual
               actors. Furthermore, we have shown how a small set of simple ideas can lead to a
               broader outcome. This is at the very heart of complexity and agent-based modeling.
               Our research suggests that this methodology introduces some interesting benefits for
               the study of culture and its emergence and transformation over time; however, much of
               this exploration is taking place outside the humanities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix 1</head>
            <table>
               <head>Table 1 - Extended Text Analysis, Encounter, and Choice/Strategy</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Source</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Interpretation</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">Choice/Strategy</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Juan Jaramillo’s Relación</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>..un camino todo poblado y en paz…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Already intermixing</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate always</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>… aquí vimos un indio y dos que parecieron ser después de la
                           primera población…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Sighting</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>... todos estos indios….nos recibieron bien</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Already intermixing</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate always</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Pedro de Castañeda</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>..parecía en otro tiempo haber sido casa fuerte en tiempo que fue poblada y
                     bien se conocía ser hecha por gentes extranjeras políticas y guerreras venidas
                     de lejos …</cell>
                  <cell>Inter-tribal warfare/politics</cell>
                  <cell>Grudger</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…en lugar de poblados, hallar grandes despoblados, y en lugar de
                           ciudades populosas, hallar pueblos de doscientos vecinos y el mayor de
                           ochocientos o mil;</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>groupings of natives</cell>
                  <cell>group vector</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…diciendo que un hombre le había forzado a su mujer…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Violent encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Grudger</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…hubo lugar que las lenguas hablasen con ellos y se les hiciese
                           requerimientos por ser gente bien entendida…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Linguistic contact - interpreter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperative</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…otro día fue Don Garcia López de Cárdenas a ver los pueblos y
                           tomar de ellos lengua</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Linguistic contact - interpreter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperative</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Gaspar Castaño de Sosa</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…y dos días antes, vino a la dicha villa, un indio, llamado
                           Miguel…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Friendly encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>… y que dio, acabo de tres días, con muy gran cantidad de gente de
                           nación despeguen, el cual fue de ellos muy bien recibido…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Grouping of natives, friendly</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…no dio lengua ninguna, de muchas que llevaba, que le entendiesen
                           persona…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Linguistic contact - Interpreter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…quedó el dicho Joan de Vega, indio; y visto que quedaba solo,
                           asieron del algunos indios, y lo echaron en el río y le quitaron unas
                           amarras, y le dieron tres flechazos…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Violent encounter - Natives</cell>
                  <cell>Defect</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Analysis of Juan Morfí</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>Los Tarahumaras y algunos otros cuando quieren reducir el de la
                           obediencia hallan la misma protección en los Navajos y Lipánes.</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Inter-tribal cooperation</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>Y no es increíble que algunos Comanches, de los que se califica más
                           fieles, se empeñasen, por algún premio, en acompañar a la expedición, en
                           calidad de guías, mientras sus Parientes se ocupan en la
                           guerra.</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Tribe joins Spanish</cell>
                  <cell>Defect</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Ácoma trials</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>En este dicho día luego incontinente el dicho señor gobernador hizo
                           [presentarse] ante si a un indio que mediante el dicho intérprete dijo
                           llamarse Caucachi.</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Linguistic contact - interpreter</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Al ser preguntado por qué este confesante y los demás indios de su
                        pueblo mataron al dicho [maestro] de campo y a otros diez españoles y a dos
                        [chicos], dijo que los dichos españoles hirieron a un indio del pueblo y que
                        por esto se enojaron y los mataron.</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Violent encounter</cell>
                  <cell>Defect</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Joe Sando</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>Thus, the Pueblos have common elements, but
                        are distinctive entities in their own right</q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Cultural Unity/Differentiation</cell>
                  <cell>Tit-for-tat</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…an attitude of <q>accommodation</q> toward
                        European cultures…</q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…the writings of Bartolomé de las Casas and
                        Francisco de Vitoria, were responsible for a change in Spanish attitudes
                        after the re-conquest of New Mexico in the 1690s. He suggests that their
                        writings lead to a policy of mutual accommodation…</q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Tolerance or accomodation</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Alfonso Ortiz</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>Ortiz writes that he believes it can be
                        demonstrated that the Pueblo people have believed themselves to share a
                        common culture despite linguistic differences.</q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Cultural Unity/Differentiation</cell>
                  <cell>Tit-for-tat</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…the Pueblo tribes have, <q>touched each
                           other’s lives in the most fundamental of ways.</q>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Tolerance for ideas</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>…the Pueblo tribes have, <q>touched each
                           other’s lives in the most fundamental of ways.</q>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Tolerance for ideas</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <foreign>Ysleta del Sur</foreign>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <q>
                        <foreign>…pues los dichos Pedro y Ventura eran de nación Piros y los indios
                           todos eran uno, y eran sus amigos los Tiguas del pueblo de la Isleta, les
                           fueron a hablar y a convocarlos para que todos juntos
                           ejecutasen…</foreign>
                     </q>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Inter-tribal competition</cell>
                  <cell>Cooperate</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Cervantes Visual Portal" xml:id="cervantes" key="cervantes">Cervantes
               Virtual Portal de la Cultural Chicana. <ref
                  target="http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/portal/Lchicana/"
                  >http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/portal/Lchicana/.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="United Nations" xml:id="unitednations" key="unitednations">United Nations.
               United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. <ref
                  target="http://www.unesco.org/new/en/unesco/"
                  >http://www.unesco.org/new/en/unesco/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="US Bureau of the Census 1970" xml:id="census" key="census">U.S. Bureau of
               the Census. 1970 Census. <ref target="http://www.census.gov/"
                  >http://www.census.gov/.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="academia2001" label="Real Academia Española 2001" key="academia2001">Real
               Academia Española. <title rend="italic">Diccionario de la Lengua Española</title>.
               22nd edition. 2001. <ref target="http://www.rae.es/rae.html"
                  >http://www.rae.es/rae.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Harper 2010–2012" xml:id="harper" key="harper">Harper, D., ed. <title
                  rend="italic">Online Dictionary of Etymology</title>. 2010–2012. <ref
                  target="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?l=a"
                  >http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?l=a</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="insula1999" label="Insula 1999" key="insula1999">Insula: Revista de
               Ciencias y Humanidades: No. 522, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Aschenwald 2002" xml:id="aschenwald2002" key="aschenwald2002">Aschenwald,
               Janette, Stefan Fin, and Gottfried Tappeiner. <title rend="quotes">Brave New
                  Modeling: Cellular Automata and Artificial Neural Networks for Mastering
                  Complexity in Economics.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Complexity</title> 7:1 (2002): 39–47.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Alessio Robles 1978" xml:id="alessio1978" key="alessio1978">Alessio Robles,
               Vito. <title rend="italic">Coahuila y Texas en la época colonial</title>. Mexico
               City: Editorial Cultura, 1938; 2nd ed., Mexico City: Editorial Porrúa, 1978. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Arias and Meléndez 2002" xml:id="arias2002" key="arias2002">Arias, Santa
               and Mariselle Meléndez<title rend="italic">, </title>eds. <title rend="italic"
                  >Mapping Colonial Spanish America: Places and Commonplaces of Identity, Culture,
                  and Experience.</title> Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Archivo General de Indias 1958" xml:id="archivo1958" key="archivo1958"
               >Archivo General de Indias, <title rend="italic">Archivo General de Indias de
                  Sevilla</title> (Madrid, 1958?)</bibl>
            <bibl label="Axelrod and Hammond 2006" xml:id="axelrod2006" key="axelrod2006">Axelrod,
               Robert and Ross Hammond. <title rend="quotes">The Evolution of Ethnocentrism.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Conflict Resolutions</title> 50:6 (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bandelier 1910" xml:id="bandelier1910" key="bandelier1910">Bandelier,
               Adolphus. <title rend="quotes">Documentary History of the Rio Grande Pueblos of New
                  Mexico.</title> Archeological Institute of America. 13:3 (1910).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Berry 2011" xml:id="berry2011" key="berry2011">Berry, David M. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Computational Turn: Thinking about the Digital
                  Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Culture Machine </title>12 (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bancroft 1889 " xml:id="bancroft1889" key="bancroft1889">Bancroft, H.H.
                  <title rend="italic">History of Arizona and New Mexico, 1530–1888. </title>San
               Francisco: History Co., 1889.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bolton 1916" xml:id="bolton1916" key="bolton1916">Bolton, Herbert Eugene.
                  <title rend="italic">Spanish Exploration in the Southwest, 1542–1706</title>. New
               York: C. Scribner's Sons, 1916. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Boyd and Richerson 2005" xml:id="boyd2005" key="boyd2005">Boyd, Robert and
               Peter J. Richerson. <title rend="italic">The Origin and Evolution of
               Cultures</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Castaño de Sosa 2004" xml:id="castano2004" key="castano2004">Castaño de
               Sosa, Gaspar. <title rend="italic">Memoria del descubrimento que Gaspar Castaño de
                  Sosa, hizo en el Nuevo México, siendo Teniente de Gobernador y Capitán General del
                  Nuevo Reino de León: (27 de Julio de 1590). </title>1864. Digital edition.
               Alicante: Biblioteca Virtual Miguel de Cervantes, 2004. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Cavalli-Sforza 2000" xml:id="cavalli2000" key="cavalli2000">Cavalli-Sforza,
               Luigi. <title rend="italic">Genes, Peoples, and Languages.</title> Trans. Mark
               Seielstad, New York: North Point Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cavalli-Sforza and Feldman 1981" xml:id="cavalli1981" key="cavalli1981"
               >Cavalli-Sforza, L. L. and M. Feldman. <title rend="italic">Cultural Transmission and
                  Evolution.</title> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1981.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Chipman 1992" xml:id="chipman1992" key="chipman1992">Chipman, Donald.
                  <title rend="italic">Spanish Texas, 1519–1821. </title>Austin: University of Texas
               Press, 1992. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Cochinos 2000" xml:id="cochinos2000" key="cochinos2000">Cochinos, Richard.
                  <title rend="quotes">Introduction to the Theory of Cellular Automata and
                  One-Dimensional Traffic Simulation.</title>
               <title rend="italic"> </title>Accessed January 20, 2012. <ref
                  target="http://theory.org/complexity/traffic/"
                  >http://theory.org/complexity/traffic/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Cederman 2005" xml:id="cederman2005" key="cederman2005">Cederman,
               Lars-Erik. <title rend="quotes">Computational Models of Social Forms: advancing
                  generative Process Theory.</title>
               <title rend="italic">AJS</title> 110:4 (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Craddock and Polt 2008" xml:id="craddock2008" key="craddock2008">Craddock,
               Jerry R. and John H. R. Polt. <title rend="quotes">The Trial of the Indians of Acoma,
                  1598–1599.</title> Berkeley: Cibola Project, Research Center for Romance Studies,
               UC Berkeley, 2008. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Dawkins 1978" xml:id="dawkins1978" key="dawkins1978">Dawkins, Richard.
                  <title rend="italic">The Selfish Gene</title>. Oxford: Oxford University of Press,
               1978 and 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dawkins 1999" xml:id="dawkins1999" key="dawkins1999">Dawkins, Richard.
                  <title rend="italic">The Extended Phenotype</title>. Afterward by Daniel Dennett.
               Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1999. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Duaine 1971" xml:id="duaine1971" key="duaine1971">Duaine, Carl L. <title
                  rend="italic">Caverns of Oblivion.</title> Manchaca, Texas: Packrat, 1971. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Flint and Flint 2012" xml:id="flint2012" key="flint2012">Flint, Richard and
               Shirley Flint. <title rend="italic">Documents of the Coronado Expedition, 1539–1542:
                  "They Were Not Familiar with His Majesty, nor Did They Wish to Be His
                  Subjects</title>. Albuequerque: University of New Mexico Press, 2012. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Gabora 1997a" xml:id="gabora1997a" key="gabora1997a">Gabora, Liane. <title
                  rend="quotes">Mind.</title> Handbook of Archaeological Theories eds. R. A.
               Bentley, H. D. G. Maschner, and C. Chippendale, 283–296. Walnut Creek, CA: Altamira
               Press, 1997. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Gabora 1997b" xml:id="gabora1997b" key="gabora1997b">Gabora, Liane. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Origin and Evolution of Culture and Creativity.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Memetics</title>: <title rend="italic">Evolutionary
                  Models of Information Transmission</title> 1:1 (1997).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hammond and Rey 1977" xml:id="hammond1977" key="hammond1977">Hammond,
               George P. and Agapito Rey, eds. <title rend="italic">Narratives of the Coronado
                  Expeditions</title>. Coronado Cuarto Centennial Publications, 1540–1542, v. 2. New
               York: AMS Press, 1977. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Hammond and Rey 1953" xml:id="hammond1953" key="hammond1953">Hammond,
               George P. and Agapito Rey. <title rend="italic">Don Juan De Oñate, Colonizer of New
                  Mexico, 1595–1628. </title>2 vols. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
               1953.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Holland 1998" xml:id="holland1998" key="holland1998">Holland, John. <title
                  rend="italic">Emergence: From Chaos To Order</title>. Cambridge, M.A.: Basic
               Books, 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Howlett 2011" xml:id="howlett2011" key="howlett2011">Howlett, Peter. <title
                  rend="quotes">A Toolkit for Travelling Facts.</title>
               <title rend="italic">London School of Economics and Political Sciences
                  website</title>, <title rend="quotes">How well do facts travel?</title> 2011. <ref
                  target="http://www2.lse.ac.uk/economicHistory/Research/facts/AboutTheProject.aspx"
                  >http://www2.lse.ac.uk/economicHistory/Research/facts/AboutTheProject.aspx</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Jaramillo 2004" xml:id="jaramillo2004" key="jaramillo2004">Jaramillo,
                  Juan<title rend="italic">. Relación hecha por el capitán Juan Jaramillo, de la
                  jornada que había hecho a la Tierra Nueva en Nueva España y al descubrimiento de
                  Cíbola, yendo por General, Francisco Vázquez Coronado (Año de 1537)</title>. 1864.
               Digital edition. Alicante: Biblioteca Virtual Miguel de Cervantes, 2004. <ref
                  target="http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/servlet/SirveObras/04705179799137228754480/p0000001.htm#I_0_"
                  >http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/servlet/SirveObras/04705179799137228754480/p0000001.htm#I_0_</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Kessell 1989" xml:id="kessell1989" key="kessell1989">Kessell, John</bibl>
            <bibl label="Morfí 1967" xml:id="morfi1967" key="morfi1967">Morfí, Juan Agustín
                  de.<title rend="italic"> Diario y derrotero, 1777–1781. Compendio del diario del
                  viaje a las Provincias Internas [de fray Juan Agustín Morfi]: Chihuahua, 26 Abril
                  1778, </title>and <title rend="italic">History of Texas, 1673–1779</title>. 2
               vols. Albuquerque: Quivira Society, 1935; rpt., New York: Arno, 1967. <ref
                  target="http://biblioteca.universia.net/autor/Morfi,%20Juan%20Agust%C3%ADn.html"
                  >http://biblioteca.universia.net/autor/Morfi,%20Juan%20Agust%C3%ADn.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Mignolo 1999" xml:id="mignolo1999" key="mignolo1999">Mignolo, Walter.
                  <title rend="italic">Local Histories/Global Designs: Coloniality, Subaltern
                  Knowledges and Border Thinking.</title> Princeton: Princeton University Press,
               1999.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mignolo 1995" xml:id="mignolo1995" key="mignolo1995">Mignolo, Walter.
                  <title rend="italic">The Darker Side of the Renaissance: Literacy, Territoriality,
                  Colonization. </title>Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mitchell 2009" xml:id="mitchell2009" key="mitchell2009b">Mitchell, Melanie.
                  <title rend="italic">Complexity: A Guided Tour</title>. Oxford, U.K.: Oxford
               University Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Obregón 1928" xml:id="obregon1928" key="obregon1928">Obregón, Baltasar.
                  <title rend="italic">Obregón’s History of 16th Century Explorations in Western
                  America: entitled Chronicle, commentary, or relation of the ancient and modern
                  discoveries in New Spain and New Mexico, Mexico, 1584</title>. Los Angeles: Wetzel
               Publishing Company, 1928.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ortiz 1984" xml:id="ortiz1984" key="ortiz1984">Ortiz, Alex. <title
                  rend="italic">American Indian Myths and Legends </title>. New York: Pantheon
               Books, 1984. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Ortiz 1972" xml:id="ortiz1972" key="ortiz1972">Ortiz, Alex. <title
                  rend="italic">New Perspectives on the Pueblos</title>. Albuquerque: University of
               New Mexico Press, 1972. <ref
                  target="http://www.ipl.org/div/natam/bin/browse.pl/B1378"
                  >http://www.ipl.org/div/natam/bin/browse.pl/B1378</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ortiz 1994" xml:id="ortiz1994" key="ortiz1994">Ortiz, Alex. <title
                  rend="italic">North American Indian anthropology: essays on society and
                  culture</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ortiz 1969" xml:id="ortiz1969" key="ortiz1969">Ortiz, Alex. <title
                  rend="italic">The Tewa World: Space, Time, Being and Becoming in a Pueblo
                  Society</title>
               <ref target="http://www.ipl.org/div/natam/bin/browse.pl/B1377"
                  >http://www.ipl.org/div/natam/bin/browse.pl/B1377</ref>. Chicago: University of
               Chicago Press, 1969. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Page and Bednar 2007" xml:id="page2007" key="page2007">Page, Scott and
               Jenna Bednar. <title rend="quotes">Can Game(s) Theory Explain Culture? The Emergence
                  of Cultural Behavior within Multiple Games.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Rationality and Society</title> 19:1 (2007), 65–97.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sando 1992" xml:id="sando1992" key="sando1992">Sando, Joe.<title
                  rend="italic"> Pueblo Nations: Eight Centuries of Pueblo Indian History</title>.
               Santa Fe: Clear Light Publishers, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sando 1982" xml:id="sando1982" key="sando1982">Sando, Joe.<title
                  rend="italic"> Nee Hemish: A History of the Jemez Pueblo</title>. Albuquerque:
               University of New Mexico Press, 1982.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sando 1976" xml:id="sando1976" key="sando1976">Sando, Joe.<title
                  rend="italic"> The Pueblo Indians</title>. San Francisco: Indian Historian,
               1976.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Schroeder and Matson 1965 " xml:id="schroeder1965" key="schroeder1965"
               >Schroeder, Albert H. and Dan S. Matson. <title rend="italic">A Colony on the Move:
                  Gaspar Castaño De Sosa's Journal, 1590–1591</title>. Santa Fe, New Mexico: School
               of American Research, 1965.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Simmons 1993" xml:id="simmons1993" key="simmons1993">Simmons, Marc.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Slingerland 2008" xml:id="slingerland2008" key="slingerland2008"
               >Slingerland, Edward. <title rend="italic">What Science Offers the Humanities:
                  Integrating Body and Culture. </title>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
               2008.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sperber and Claidière 2006" xml:id="sperber2006" key="sperber2006">Sperber,
               Dan and Nicolas Claidière. <title rend="quotes">Why Modeling Cultural Evolution Is
                  Still Such a Challenge.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Biological Theory</title> 1:1 (2006), 20–22.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sperber 2007" xml:id="sperber2007" key="sperber2007">Sperber, Dan. <title
                  rend="quotes">Seedless Grapes: Nature and Culture.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Creations of the Mind: Theories of Artifacts and their
                  Representations,</title> eds. Stephen Laurence and Eric Margolis. Oxford: Oxford
               University Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Thrapp 1991" xml:id="thrapp1991" key="thrapp1991">Thrapp, Dan, ed.<title
                  rend="italic"> Encyclopedia of Frontier Biography. </title>Lincoln: University of
               Nebraska Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Toro 1944" xml:id="toro1944" key="toro1944">Toro, Alfonso. <title
                  rend="italic">La familia Carvajal: Estudio histórico sobre los judíos y la
                  Inquisición de la Nueva España en el siglo XVI</title>. 2 vols. Mexico City:
               Patria, 1944.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Valcárcel 2010" xml:id="valcarcel2010" key="valcarcel2010">Valcárcel,
               Carmen del Mora. <title rend="quotes">Las Siete Ciudades de Cíbola: Utopía y Realidad
                  en la Expedición de Vázquez Coronado.</title>
               <title rend="italic">El Escritor y el Intelectual Entre Dos Mundos</title>. Madrid:
               Iberoamericana-Vervuert Verlag, 2010. 645–658.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Vázquez Coronado 2004" xml:id="vazquez2004" key="vazquez2004">Vázquez
               Coronado, Francisco. <title rend="italic">Carta de Francisco Vázquez Coronado al
                  Emperador, dándole cuenta de la expedición a la Provincia de Quivira y de la
                  inexactitud de lo referido a Fr. Marcos de Niza, acerca de aquel país.
               </title>1864. Digital edition. Alicante: Biblioteca Virtual Miguel de Cervantes,
               2004. <ref
                  target="http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/servlet/SirveObras/dhmex/78030620982381685354679/index.htm"
                  >http://bib.cervantesvirtual.com/servlet/SirveObras/dhmex/78030620982381685354679/index.htm</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Vélez de Escalante and Domínguez 1777" xml:id="velez1777" key="velez1777"
               >Vélez de Escalante, Silvestre, and Francisco Atanasio Domínguez. <title
                  rend="italic">Derrotero y diario</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wilson and Keil 2001" xml:id="wilson2001" key="wilson2001">Wilson, Robert
               A. and Frank Keil, eds. <title rend="italic">MIT Encyclopedia of Cognitive
                  Sciences</title>. Boston: MIT Press, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Weddle 1985" xml:id="weddle1985" key="weddle1985">Weddle, Robert S. <title
                  rend="italic">Spanish Sea: The Gulf of Mexico in North American Discovery,
                  1500–1685</title>. College Station: Texas AandM University Press, 1985.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Winship 2009" xml:id="winship2009" key="winship2009">Winship, George
               Parker, Pedro De Castañeda De Najera, Francisco Vásquez de Coronado, Antonio de
               Mendoza, and Juan Camilo Jaramillo. <title rend="italic">The Journey of Coronado,
                  1540–1542</title>. Santa Barbara: Greenwood Press, 2009.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
