<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Digital Humanities, Copyright Law, and the Literary</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Robin <dhq:family>Wharton</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>robin.s.wharton@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Robin Wharton (@rswharton on Twitter) holds a JD (1999) and a PhD (2009), both
                     from the University of Georgia. She is a co-founder and director of the
                     Calliope Initiative (www.calliopeinitiative.org), which develops open source
                     tools to facilitate student-centered, project-based, multimodal composition
                     pedagogy, and she is on the partner board of Hybrid Pedagogy
                     (www.hybridpedagogy.com), an open, peer-reviewed journal of teaching and
                     technology. Her research interests include medieval and early modern law and
                     literature, critical legal studies, and the digital humanities. She is working
                     on a book about the influence of common law poetics and the emergence of the
                     individual as a target of regulatory authority in Middle English
                     literature.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000147</idno>
            <idno type="volume">007</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2013-07-01">1 July 2013</date>

            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2013-05-01" who="MCC">encoded article</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>Embedded in the rich textual record of international copyright law, we often
               encounter a quaint, and perhaps naïve definition of the <soCalled>literary</soCalled>
               around which the law has crystallized and which has the potential to influence the
               work of all digital humanists, whether they think of themselves as literary scholars
               or not. The first part of this article explores how a relatively narrow definition of
               the <soCalled>literary</soCalled> as a category of <soCalled>high</soCalled> or
               belletristic cultural production has informed the contours of U.S. copyright law, in
               particular. Section 101, Title 17 of the United States Code expressly defines
                  <soCalled>literary works</soCalled> as any <cit><quote rend="inline"
                  source="#copyrighted2010">works, other than audiovisual works, expressed in
                  words, numbers, or other verbal or numerical symbols or indicia, regardless of the
                  nature of the material objects, such as books, periodicals, manuscripts,
                  phonorecords, film, tapes, disks, or cards, in which they are embodied</quote>
               <ptr target="#copyrighted2010"/></cit>. US courts have, however, often employed a narrower,
               more commonplace understanding of the <soCalled>literary</soCalled> as an aesthetic
               category when sorting artifacts or content into other legally more significant
               categories such as idea, expression, criticism, parody, and satire. The second
               section of the article considers some of the potential implications and consequences
               of the current regulatory structure for the work of digital humanists. Judges
               engaging in a fair use analysis more often than not expect scholarship to come
               packaged in print monographs written in academic language aimed at an audience of
               disciplinary specialists. When they encounter scholarly artifacts that depart from
               those formal expectations and draw from pre-existing work, judges are less likely to
               find the use of pre-existing work is fair and therefore non-infringing. Finally, the
               article examines whether the literary as a category should be abandoned altogether,
               or whether digital humanists might productively redefine the literary as part of a
               strategy for re-imagining the institutional and legal regulations that govern
               academic work.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Embedded in copyright law, we often encounter a quaint, perhaps naïve definition of
               the “literary”</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Digital Humanities, Copyright Law, and the Literary</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In his <title rend="quotes">An Attempt at a <q>Compositionist Manifesto,</q>
               </title> Bruno Latour advocates for a discursive practice he labels
                  <q>composition.</q> Composition involves assembly, construction, creation <ptr
                  target="#latour2010" loc="474"/>. It thus stands in contrast with <q>critique,</q>
               which, for Latour at least, involves a futile attempt to tear down facades in order
               to reveal the truth concealed beneath them: <quote rend="block" source="#latour2010"
                  >The difference is not moot, because what performs a critique cannot also compose.
                  It is really a mundane question of having the right tools for the right job. With
                  a hammer (or a sledge hammer) in hand you can do a lot of things: break down
                  walls, destroy idols, ridicule prejudices, but you cannot repair, take care,
                  assemble, reassemble, stitch together. <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="475"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Within the compositionist landscape Latour imagines, our attention would be drawn
                  <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#latour2010">away from the irrelevant difference
                  between what is constructed and what is not constructed, toward the crucial
                  difference between what is well or badly constructed, well or badly
                  composed</quote>
               <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="474"/></cit>. Composition as Latour defines it challenges
               and calls into question the conceptual boundaries that often separate literary
               things, e.g., things such as books and scholarly essays, from non-literary things,
               e.g., paintings, musical scores, and dance <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="473–74"
               />.</p>
            <p>Latour’s discussion of compositionism also seems to blur at least some of the
               distinctions we often make between literary <q>authorship</q> and literary
                  <q>scholarship</q> by suggesting the artist and the humanist ultimately draw upon
               many of the same tools and processes <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="474–75"/>. In
               this, composition as a mode of production seems particularly suited to the digital
               humanities, which as an inter- or trans-discipline challenges and calls into question
               some of these same conceptual boundaries. In a talk at the 2011 convention of the
               Modern Language Association that caused a stir because of what it potentially said
               about who is <q>in</q> and who is <q>out</q> of the digital humanities community,
               Steve Ramsay argued, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2011a">Personally, I think
                  Digital Humanities is about building things. [. . .] If you are not making
                  anything, you are not . . . a digital humanist</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay2011a"/></cit>. Ramsay’s discussion, in a subsequent blog post, of
               building as a <q>distinctive</q> scholarly mode in digital humanities <ptr
                  target="#ramsay2011b"/> suggests digital humanities scholarship is (or has the
               potential to be) formally and methodologically different from what we might think of
               as more traditional literary <q>criticism</q>.</p>
            <p>Even though it resists many of the rhetorical and formal conventions we have come to
               associate with literary scholarship, compositionism in Latour’s definition
               nevertheless engages processes of interpretation, deconstruction, and theoretical
               framing. Latour’s <q>manifesto</q> thus also provides insight into how those digital
               humanists who like Ramsay are interested in building things may also respond to Alan
               Liu’s call, in his own 2011 MLA address, for more engagement within digital
               humanities with the quintessentially humanistic endeavor of cultural criticism <ptr
                  target="#liu2011"/>. Ramsay and Liu understand building as an activity that
               engages critical intellectual processes, even though critique may not be its ultimate
               end <ptr target="#liu2011"/>. The debate about the relationship, or potential lack
               thereof, between composition and building, on the one hand, and criticism, on the
               other, has even found its way into the mainstream press in an essay by Adam Kirsch in
               the <title rend="italic">New York Times Sunday Book Review</title>. What I find
               particularly thought-provoking in Kirsch's account is his suggestion, which mirrors
               Latour’s, that a conceptual turn towards composition or building in the work of
               literary scholars has the potential to undo the distinction we often make between the
               objects of literary study and the objects produced by literary study: <cit><quote
                  rend="inline" source="#kirsch2010">The critic participates in the world of
                  literature not as a lawgiver or a team captain for this or that school of writing,
                  but as a writer, a colleague of the poet and the novelist</quote>
               <ptr target="#kirsch2010"/></cit>. </p>
            <p>As a digital humanist, I am persuaded by the assertions Latour, Ramsay, and Liu have
               made about how academic scholarship in general and digital humanities scholarship in
               particular can and should evolve in response to new technological and cultural
               pressures. As a lawyer and legal scholar, I am also intrigued by how that evolution
               might challenge the current regulatory framework in productive new ways. Copyright
               law has frequently imported and even codified prevailing academic ideas about what
               constitutes literature and literary scholarship <ptr target="#vaidhyanathan2001"
                  loc="35–37"/>. Digital humanists should, therefore, be prepared to confront a set
               of legal paradigms ill-designed to accommodate new modes of scholarly production that
               depart from those traditional formal expectations. Unraveling how the language of
               literary study has informed the language of the law, though, also provides a
               persuasive demonstration of the potential agency literary scholars can assert to
               influence jurists and legal decision-making. In order to change the way we work, we
               must also articulate new theoretical structures through which that work can be
               justified — both within our departments and within legal briefs and judicial opinions
               — <emph>as scholarship</emph>.</p>
            <p>In the following section, <title rend="quotes">U.S. Copyright Law and the
                  Literary,</title> I explore in more detail how the category of the <q>literary</q>
               evolved within and continues to inform the application of U.S. copyright law. The
               focus on the United States here results from both practical and strategic
               considerations. As a practical matter, a detailed examination of copyright law in
               multiple jurisdictions is beyond the scope of a single treatise, much less a single
               essay. Strategically, I want to continue what I see as a productive trend toward more
               granular studies of legal texts and legal history that add detail to broader
               international narratives such as the one Martha Woodmansee <ptr
                  target="#woodmansee1984"/> has constructed.<note>Such studies include detailed
                  examinations of how copyright was extended beyond the book trade in particular
                  jurisdictions <ptr target="#surwillo2007"/>, how concepts such as intellectual
                     <q>piracy</q> have evolved alongside that of the authorial genius <ptr
                     target="#johns2009"/>, and why the globalization of copyright has encountered
                  resistance in the developing world <ptr target="#boateng2011"/>. </note> This is
               not an attempt to explain how the literary as a category informs copyright law in
               every jurisdiction, in every case. Rather, by engaging with the central theme running
               through this issue, I hope to demonstrate how the ongoing conversation about
               copyright reform engages and enriches our discussion of how digital humanities will
               define itself as a discipline. The article then turns, in the section titled <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Humanities and Copyright Law,</title> to a consideration of
               some of the practical consequences for digital humanists working in the United
               States, or working with materials first published in the US, of the continued legal
               application of categorical distinctions between <q>high</q> and <q>low</q>
               literature, and between <q>original</q> authorship and <q>derivative</q> scholarship.
               That section also explores how, as digital humanists reconfigure the literary as a
               category by considering what place building or making things <emph>with</emph>
               literary objects has or should have in disciplines where scholarly work has consisted
               primarily of writing <emph>about</emph> literary objects, we may also need to think
               strategically beyond the lab and into the courtroom and legislative chamber. The
               final section, <title rend="quotes">Transformative Use, Joint Authorship, and More
                  Productive Relationships,</title> concludes by looking at the existing law as a
               source of authority upon which digital humanists might draw as we press for a
               re-examination of the institutional regulations that govern academic work.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>U.S. Copyright Law and the Literary</head>
            <p>As humanists, we confront an intellectual environment where we must constantly
               demonstrate what we do is relevant and necessary. The law governing our work,
               however, has been built around a presumption the literary objects we study (a
               category that has been extended by analogy to cover visual, cinematic, dramatic, and
               performing arts) are only <q>useful</q> when they look like technical manuals.
               Further, as digital humanists, we are engaged in a consideration of how new tools and
               methods might fundamentally alter the shape of humanistic inquiry. In this too, we
               are potentially confounded by jurisprudential use of the literary as a rather narrow
               category that segregates <q>high</q> from <q>low</q> culture. Judicial deployment of
               what I will refer to throughout as a <q>belletristic</q> definition of the literary
               places implicit aesthetic and formal limits on the acceptable artifacts of literary
               study, as well as the scholarship produced by such study.</p>
            <p>Ray Patterson <ptr target="#patterson1991" loc="47–55"/>, Ty Herrington <ptr
                  target="#herrington2001" loc="59–76"/>, Lawrence Lessig <ptr target="#lessig2004"
                  loc="7–13"/>, and James Boyle <ptr target="#boyle1996" loc="51–60"/> have all
               described how U.S. copyright jurisprudence is shaped by an internal tension between a
               desire to reward the creation and dissemination of all manner of cultural production
               on the one hand, and a belief economic monopolies stifle innovation and creativity on
               the other. Pursuant to the Intellectual Property Clause in the U.S. Constitution,
               copyright is a means to an end, promoting the <q>Progress of Science and useful
                  Arts</q>
               <ptr target="#constitution" loc="Article 1, Section 8"/>. In this passage, by
               including that revealing modifier <q>useful,</q> the Constitution’s framers appear to
               reject belletristic justifications of copyright grounded in appreciation of authorial
               genius or artistic merit. Instead, the Constitution casts the <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#herrington2001">the exclusive right</quote> granted to <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#herrington2001">authors and inventors</quote> as a sort
               of reward for rendering a civil service to the community <ptr
                  target="#herrington2001" loc="35–58"/>, as an incentive to disclose the patented
               invention or publish the copyrighted work. The ultimate end of granting private
               property rights is to expand the public domain; rewarding authors and inventors is
               just a means to that end. In addition, while the clause identifies <q>writings,</q>
               as the proper subject of copyright regulation, coverage under the original Copyright
               Act of 1790 for <quote rend="inline" source="#constitution">maps, charts, and
                  books,</quote> in that order, makes fairly clear the category <q>authors</q>
               included cartographers and technical writers, as well as novelists and poets. The
               current version of the law, which was substantially codified in 1976, now defines
                  <q>literary works</q> as any <quote rend="inline" source="#constitution">works,
                  other than audiovisual works, expressed in words, numbers, or other verbal or
                  numerical symbols or indicia, regardless of the nature of the material objects,
                  such as books, periodicals, manuscripts, phonorecords, film, tapes, disks, or
                  cards, in which they are embodied</quote>
               <ptr target="#constitution" loc="17 U.S.C. Section 101"/>.</p>
            <p> Although the statutory definition of the literary remains quite broad, statutes and
               legislative history provide, at best, only half the story. Putting together an
               accurate account of how the law employs the literary as a category requires a turn to
               case law, and a brief tour through significant cases where courts have defined key
               concepts such as <q>idea,</q>
               <q>expression,</q>
               <q>originality,</q> and <q>fair use.</q> In reading these cases, I want to highlight
               how judicial attempts to define other, legally significant categories often involve
               an unreflective application of a definition of the literary drawn, not from the
               Constitution or the copyright statute, but from somewhere else entirely. I am less
               concerned with the problem of where the courts get this implicit definition of the
               literary, than with the subsequent social and legal consequences of defining
                  <q>literature</q> as a relatively small subset of literary works that can be
               distinguished on the basis of their aesthetic appeal, or identifying critique as the
               primary mode of literary scholarship. Each of these cases is a historically specific
               response to a very complex set of circumstances. They are also the sources of
               important legal doctrines that have been shaped by unarticulated assumptions about
               the world the law is supposed to regulate. By understanding how judicial assumptions
               about literature and the work of literary studies have influenced judicial
               decision-making, I hope to provide some insight into how a reconfiguration within the
               academy of those categories and relationships might have the potential to effect
               substantial, beneficial change in the law.</p>
            <p>From the outset, the First Amendment and the underlying policy of the copyright law —
               to promote the progress of science, or knowledge, and the useful arts, or industry —
               have exerted pressure on courts to place inherent limitations upon or create
               exceptions to the exclusive rights of authors <ptr target="#leval1990" loc="1106–8"
               />, <ptr target="#shipley1986" loc="984–98"/>. The originality requirement [17 U.S.C.
               Section 102(a)] and the idea versus expression dichotomy [17 U.S.C. Section 102(b)]
               both limit what can be considered copyrightable subject matter. Fair use [17 U.S.C.
               Section 107], which I address in more detail in the section below, is the most
               significant exception to an author’s right to prevent unlicensed copying. These three
               concepts, which began as common law doctrine and have since been codified in Title 17
               of the United States Code, provide the underpinnings for our modern understanding of
               the public domain, also known as the intellectual commons <ptr target="#boyle1996"
                  loc="45"/>. They do so, however, through the implicit encoding of narrow
               definitions of literature and literary scholarship, both of which entered US
               copyright law during the late-nineteenth century.</p>
            <p> Thus, the modern formulation of the idea-expression dichotomy originates in the
               Supreme Court case of <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>, 101 U.S. 99
               [1879], in an opinion still routinely cited to justify judicial decision-making in
               copyright cases. The underlying action arose from Baker’s publication and use of
               accounting ledgers predicated on a system Charles Selden had invented and described
               in a prior publication. The evidence clearly demonstrated the words, charts, and
               forms Baker employed were similar to but still distinct from those Selden used, but
               Selden’s widow, the plaintiff in the original action, argued Selden’s copyright
               covered the ideas expressed in the work as well as the expression used to convey
               them. The Supreme Court, arguing from a set of hypothetical situations involving
               technical manuals on subjects such as medicine, perspective drawing, and mathematics,
               held expression is the purview of copyright and ideas are the purview of patent law:
                  <quote rend="block" source="#baker1879">The copyright of a book on perspective, no
                  matter how many drawings and illustrations it may contain, gives no exclusive
                  right to the modes of drawing described, though they may never have been known or
                  used before. By publishing the book without getting a patent for the art, the
                  latter is given to the public <ptr target="#baker1879" loc="102"/>.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Only copying of expression gives rise to copyright infringement; use of the ideas
               does not. In the process of reaching its holding, the Court begins to break down the
               broad, legislative category of <q>writings</q> — e.g., maps, charts, books, etc. —
               into literary expression that consists primarily of words and other forms of
               expression that comprise <quote rend="inline" source="#baker1879">illustrations of
                  lines and figures</quote> and <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#baker1879">diagrams
                  (which merely stand in the place of words)</quote>
               <ptr target="#baker1879" loc="102"/></cit>. Words, illustrations, lines, figures, and
               diagrams are all forms of expression that can embody ideas. Words, though, are the
               paradigmatic form of expression, the vehicle to which the Court returns repeatedly in
               drawing out an extended series of analogies to clarify its reasoning: <quote
                  rend="block" source="#baker1879">The fact that the art is described in the book by
                  illustrations of lines and figures which are reproduced in practice in the
                  application of the art makes no difference. Those illustrations are the mere
                  language employed by the author to convey his ideas more clearly. Had he used
                  words of description instead of diagrams (which merely stand in the place of
                  words), there could not be the slightest doubt that others, applying the art to
                  practical use, might lawfully draw the lines and diagrams which were in the
                  author’s mind, and which he thus described by words in his book <ptr
                     target="#baker1879" loc="102–103"/>.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Unlike words, which maintain a stable identity as expression throughout the Court’s
               discussion, the diagrams <q>which merely stand in the
                  place of words</q> and thus presumably constitute expression in one sentence
               become in the next ideas <q>which were in the author’s
                  mind, and which he thus described by words in his book.</q>
            </p>
            <p> In addition to the distinction between idea and expression, the Court thus ends up
               drawing a line between two different kinds of expression. We get expression in which
               the idea is separable from the form in which it has been embodied, which the Court
               repeatedly illustrates through resort to literary examples, and expression in which
               the idea has <q>merged,</q> which the Court always identifies with non-verbal,
               non-literary modes of representation: <quote rend="block" source="#baker1879">The
                  very object of publishing a book on science or the useful arts is to communicate
                  to the world the useful knowledge which it contains. But this object would be
                  frustrated if the knowledge could not be used without incurring the guilt of
                  piracy of the book. And where the art it teaches cannot be used without employing
                  the methods and diagrams used to illustrate the book, or such as are similar to
                  them, such methods and diagrams are to be considered as necessary incidents to the
                  art, and given therewith to the public — not given for the purpose of publication
                  in other works explanatory of the art, but for the purpose of practical
                  application. <ptr target="#baker1879" loc="102–103"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Although expression is generally subject to copyright protection, in some cases,
               pursuant to what has come to be called the <q>merger</q> doctrine, even that is given
               over to the public along with the ideas expressed where one must reproduce the
               expression not <q>in other works explanatory of the
                  art, but for the purpose of practical application.</q> The quoted passage
               further demonstrates how the circumstances of the case, which involved a technical
               manual, set the conceptual parameters the Court employed to think through the
               problem. In its analysis, the Court did not hold the abstractions behind images or
               words are never subject to copyright protection under any circumstances. It also did
               not conclude non-literary expression will never be separable from the ideas it
               embodies. Rather, it concluded the kinds of abstractions, the <q>methods</q> and
                  <q>knowledge</q> involved in the particular case of <title rend="italic">Baker v.
                  Selden</title>, were more appropriately treated as the subject of patent law, if
               they could be subject to regulation as property at all. Consequently, their public
               disclosure without making them the subject of a patent application gave them up into
               the public domain, if they were not part of it already. Similarly, the kinds of
               non-literary expression involved in the case, forms and diagrams, provided
               quintessential examples where idea and expression had merged.</p>
            <p> The Court’s reasoning, as quoted thus far, would have been entirely sufficient to
               justify its holding <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#baker1879">that blank account
                  books are not the subject of copyright, and that the mere copyright of Selden’s
                  book did not confer upon him the exclusive right to make and use account books,
                  ruled and arranged as designated by him and described and illustrated in said
                  book</quote>
               <ptr target="#baker1879" loc="107"/></cit>. The Court went on, however, to address
               hypothetical future cases involving <quote rend="inline" source="#baker1879"
                  >ornamental designs or pictorial illustrations addressed to the taste</quote>:
                  <cit><quote rend="block" source="#baker1879">Of course these observations are not
                  intended to apply to ornamental designs or pictorial illustrations addressed to
                  the taste. Of these it may be said that their form is their essence, and their
                  object, the production of pleasure in their contemplation. This is their final
                  end. They are as much the product of genius and the result of composition as are
                  the lines of the poet or the historian’s period. On the other hand, the teachings
                  of science and the rules and methods of useful art have their final end in
                  application and use, and this application and use are what the public derive from
                  the publication of a book which teaches them. But as embodied and taught in a
                  literary composition or book, their essence consists only in their statement. This
                  alone is what is secured by the copyright. The use by another of the same methods
                  of statement, whether in words or illustrations, in a book published for teaching
                  the art would undoubtedly be an infringement of the copyright.</quote><ptr
                     target="#baker1879" loc="103–104"/></cit>
               
            </p>
            <p>I quote at length here in order to demonstrate more clearly how the Court introduces
               extra-legal concepts regarding literature, literary production, and the various
               functions of different kinds of <q>writings</q> into its legal reasoning. <q>Ornamental designs or pictorial illustrations addressed
                  to the taste</q> are like <q>the lines of the
                  poet or the historian’s period,</q> in that the visual and written material
               both are <q>the product of genius and the result of
                  composition.</q> As such, the Court concludes, both can be distinguished from
               the <q>mere language</q> and instructional <q>diagrams</q> of the technical manual at
               issue in the case at hand, which are the more mundane vehicles through which
               knowledge is communicated. Although the Court is still concerned with untangling the
               distinctions between idea and expression, and between patent and copyright as
               outlined legislatively, its conclusions about what can and cannot be borrowed, what
               can and cannot be protected, are clearly influenced by more than just the letter of
               the law as it currently stood. The influence of extra-legal, primarily aesthetic
               considerations about the nature of art in general and literature in particular leads
               the Court to distinguish artistic creation from technological innovation, ornament
               from utility, and the <q>production of pleasure</q>
               from the communication of useful knowledge. These conceptual distinctions continue to
               permeate the academy and often trouble digital humanists and other scholars whose
               work ignores or transcends them, and they also continue to play a significant role in
               how courts interpret and apply the law.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title> was handed down in 1879, nearly a
               century after the first federal copyright statute was enacted, under the Copyright
               Act of 1831. The 1831 act extended the copyright term, made copyright a descendible
               property right that could be transferred to one’s heirs by will or through the laws
               of inheritance, and added sheet music to the list of copyrightable subject matter
                  <ptr target="#copyright1831"/>. In the passage from <title rend="italic">Baker v.
                  Selden </title>quoted above, though, we can read influence of the conceptual turn
               that produced the Copyright Act of 1870. Although the more recent law did not apply
               in the case because Selden wrote his treatise before it went into effect, its
               gravitational pull clearly shapes the Court’s opinion. The Copyright Act of 1870 was
               part of a legislative package that included an overhaul of the patent system and
               attempted to establish a federal regulatory structure for registering and protecting
               trademarks. Among a number of other substantial changes to the copyright law, the new
               legislation extended the list of works subject to copyright, and included an
               exclusive right to produce translations in the <q>bundle of rights</q> granted to the
               owners of copyrights in literary works <ptr target="#copyright1870"/>.</p>
            <p>By adding the translation right, Congress legislatively overruled the decision in
                  <title rend="italic">Stowe v. Thomas</title>, 23 F. Cas. 201 [1853]. In that case,
               the court held a German translation of Harriet Beecher Stowe’s <title rend="italic"
                  >Uncle Tom’s Cabin</title> did not infringe the copyright in her work. Denying
               Stowe’s copyright claim, the court, like the Supreme Court in the later decision of
                  <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>, distinguished <q>abstract</q> ideas
               from <q>concrete</q> expression. Unlike the Supreme Court, however, the lower court
               in <title rend="italic">Stowe v. Thomas</title> did not make what have since become
               conventional distinctions between literary creation and technological innovation:
                  <quote rend="block" source="#stowe1853">An author may be said to be the creator or
                  inventor, both of the ideas contained in his book, and the combination of words to
                  represent them. Before publication he has the exclusive possession of his
                  invention. His dominion is perfect. But when he has published his book, and given
                  his thoughts, sentiments, knowledge or discoveries to the world, he can have no
                  longer an exclusive possession of them. Such an appropriation becomes impossible,
                  and is inconsistent with the object of publication. The author’s conceptions have
                  become the common property of his readers, who cannot be deprived of the use of
                  them, nor of their right to communicate them to another clothed in their own
                  language, by lecture or by treatise. <ptr target="#stowe1853" loc="205–6"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Here, in a case involving a literary work in both the legal and the commonplace
               understanding, the court describes the author as the <q>creator or
                     <emph>inventor</emph>
               </q> of her book, who upon publication gives up her <q>conceptions</q> to her <q>readers, who cannot be deprived of the <emph>use</emph>
                  of them, nor of their right to communicate them to another clothed in their own
                  language, by lecture or by treatise</q> (emphasis added): <quote rend="block"
                  source="#stowe1853">The claim of literary property, therefore, after publication,
                  cannot be in the ideas, sentiments, or the creations of the imagination of the
                  poet or novelist as dissevered from the language, idiom, style, or the outward
                  semblance and exhibition of them. His exclusive property in the creation of his
                  mind, cannot be vested in the author as abstractions, but only in the concrete
                  form which he has given them, and the language in which he has clothed them. <ptr
                     target="#stowe1853" loc="206"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title> Court defined uncopyrightable
               abstractions, ideas, narrowly, as <q>knowledge</q> and <q>methods.</q> In this
               earlier case, the lower court takes a much more expansive approach, concluding <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#stowe1853">ideas, sentiments, or the creations of the
                  imagination of the poet or novelist as dissevered from the language, idiom, style,
                  or the outward semblance and exhibition of them,</quote> all resided outside the
               domain of copyright. The holding thus expressly rejected Stowe’s argument that as the
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#stowe1853">
                  <q>efficient cause</q> of a thing,</quote> the author <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#stowe1853">[i]n respect to a book . . . is the creator of the
                  ideas</quote> it contains and therefore is entitled, pursuant to copyright law, to
               the exclusive right to sell them. <ptr target="#stowe1853" loc="202"/>.</p>
            <p> In my analysis of these two cases, I am attempting, as Latour suggests, to draw
               attention <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#latour2010">away from the irrelevant
                  difference between what is constructed and what is not constructed, toward the
                  crucial difference between what is well or badly constructed, well or badly
                  composed</quote>
               <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="474"/></cit>. The law itself is a composition, built up,
               broken down and rebuilt over the years in response to historical circumstance. <title
                  rend="italic">Baker v. Selden </title>and <title rend="italic">Stowe v.
                  Thomas</title> can, of course, be read as judicial responses to historically
               specific social, political, and economic pressures. They may also — I would even
               argue must also — be read as judicial efforts to create an internally coherent legal
               epistemology that not only reacts to the world it is intended to regulate but also
               proactively creates the terms by which that world will subsequently be known and
               understood. These two cases represent two alternative means of constructing the idea
               v. expression dichotomy. One of them, <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>,
               constructs that dichotomy through reference to an extra-judicial understanding of the
               literary as a relatively narrow category of cultural production comprising writings
               whose artistic merit renders them, among other things, somehow less useful. The
               other, <title rend="italic">Stowe v. Thomas</title>, relies on a very different, but
               also extra-judicial understanding of literary authorship that depends upon drawing
               parallels, as opposed to distinctions between literary and technological
               invention.</p>
            <p>The Congressional decision effectively to overrule <title rend="italic">Stowe v.
                  Thomas</title> and include a translation right in the 1870 act might have been
               construed broadly as a statutory codification of Stowe’s position, one that
               effectively put an end to the idea-expression dichotomy in copyright law, at least as
               far as literary works were concerned. It certainly marks what many have argued was
               the beginning of a long legislative turn away from the original policy concerns of
               the Intellectual Property Clause, and a redefinition of authorship and copyrightable
               subject matter in accordance with more conventional notions of genius, creativity,
               and artistic merit. The Supreme Court, however, took the opportunity in <title
                  rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title> to breathe life back into the
               idea-expression dichotomy, or at least put it on life support. When we read <title
                  rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title> as a response to the 1870 act, we see how,
               in order to accommodate both the original intent behind the Intellectual Property
               Clause and to make room for the emerging definitions of authorship and creative
               production that helped to produce the new copyright legislation, the <title
                  rend="italic">Baker v. Selden </title>Court split the baby. It does so by
               conceptually dividing what began in the Intellectual Property Clause as an inclusive
               and undifferentiated category of <q>writings</q> into the sub-categories of writings
               that are <q>useful,</q> that is works whose <q>final end</q> is to teach the public
               about the useful arts, and writings that are literary in a conventional sense,
               writings whose <q>form is their essence,</q> and whose <q>final end</q> is in <cit><quote
                  rend="inline" source="#baker1879">the production of pleasure in their
                  contemplation</quote>
               <ptr target="#baker1879"/></cit>.</p>
            <p>This narrow definition of the literary is implicit in how the idea v. expression
               dichotomy is used today. To put it another way, in order to understand how
                  <q>ideas</q> and <q>expression</q> are distinguished under the law, we must read
               into the law a distinction between technological innovation and artistic creation,
               between technical and scientific literature and <q>literary</q> works like novels and
               plays. In scientific and technical literature, the distinction between idea and
               expression is relatively clear. The ideas themselves, furthermore, are of <q>use</q>
               to the public, and understanding <q>use</q> in this context also depends upon drawing
               fairly conventional distinctions between technological or scientific, and artistic
               endeavors. Hence the potential those <q>useful</q> ideas possess to become the
               subject of patent law and their availability for unlicensed reproduction if they are
               not patented. As codified in Title 17, Section 102(b) of the Copyright Act of 1976,
               the current version of the statute, the idea-expression dichotomy continues to
               associate <q>idea</q> with a utilitarian vocabulary: <q>In no case does copyright protection for an original work of authorship extend to
                  any idea, procedure, process, system, method of operation, concept, principle, or
                  discovery, regardless of the form in which it is described, explained,
                  illustrated, or embodied in such work</q> [17 U.S.C. Section 102(b)]. </p>
            <p>In the latter category of literary objects addressed by the Court in <title
                  rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>, which includes things like poems and
               novels, however, the distinction between idea and expression was and still remains
               less than clear. After the 1870 act, the copyrightable expression in these works
               clearly included more than the <q>mere language</q> in which an author’s ideas were
                  <q>clothed.</q> Indeed, after copyright was expanded yet again to incorporate an
               exclusive right to make <q>derivative</q> works, subsequent cases extended copyright
               protection to conceptual elements such as the story and the characters in a fictional
               work, bringing them under the umbrella of copyrightable expression <ptr
                  target="#kurtz1986" loc="429"/>. This extension of coverage provides the basis for
               precluding unlicensed creation of sequels to and adaptations of a literary work. Not
               surprisingly, though, courts have trouble drawing the line between artistic
               expression and the public domain, or perhaps the collective unconscious, in some
               cases. In two cases involving the Pixar animated film <title rend="italic">Monsters,
                  Inc.</title>, for example, judicial decision-making turned upon literary questions
               and the expert testimony of academics regarding whether certain thematic and even
               visual elements are fundamental components of monster stories as a genre and
               therefore not subject to protection under copyright law <ptr target="#price2008"
                  loc="188–195, 202–207"/>.</p>
            <p> By announcing copyright coverage is potentially broader for what we might, purely as
               a matter of convenience, call high, or creative literary works, <title rend="italic"
                  >Baker v. Selden</title> implied most of the ideas embodied in books from this
               category, although they may be the <q>product of genius
                  and the result of composition,</q> are to be valued for the pleasure they
               produce, rather than their utility. They are not subject to patent law, nor do they
               demand to be circulated as freely as the <q>useful</q> ideas we find in low, or
                  <q>practical</q> literary works like maps, charts, and technical manuals. The
               Court implicitly concluded the <q>Progress of Science
                  and the useful Arts</q> is not directly served by their circulation as
               material for use and application, rather than simple consumption. The Court’s
               reasoning also hinges on yet another implicit presumption works produced for
               instruction are not generally <q>addressed to the
                  taste.</q> They will not in the ordinary case <q>produce pleasure in their contemplation,</q> at least not in the same manner
               as belletristic literary works whose final end is to do so.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Digital Humanities and Copyright Law</head>
            <p>Like the idea-expression dichotomy, the fair use doctrine creates breathing room for
               the public domain in U.S. copyright law. In many cases, though, judicial descriptions
               of fair uses have effectively limited literary scholars to what Latour has identified
               as the tools of critique. The fair use analysis relies on a presumption the items
               enumerated in the fair use preamble — <q>criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching . . . , scholarship, or
                  research</q> [17 U.S.C. Section 107] — will not look like creative artifacts
                  <q>addressed to the taste,</q> that
               literary scholarship will not resemble, except in the most superficial way, the
               literary objects with which it engages. This presumption literary scholarship will
               not resemble its objects of study further reflects an implicit belief literary
               scholars will ordinarily direct their work to the study of <q>high</q> literature.
               These formal expectations operate hand in glove with a very narrow understanding of
               what literary scholars may do with the work they study. Rather than using
               pre-existing material to build or create, literary scholars are expected to limit
               their work to dissecting, examining, commenting, discussing. For those scholars who
               desire formal innovation, who would take up Latour’s challenge to create a scholarly
               discourse that shares as much with <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#latour2010">art,
                  painting, music, theater, dance,</quote>
               <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="473–74"/></cit> as it does with the technical manuals
               discussed by the Court in <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>, the fair use
               analysis works against them. The more literary scholars innovate with the form of
               their scholarship, the more likely they are to be limited in the scope of its
               coverage by a judicial definition of literary scholarship as a formalist critique
               that <q>make[s] war</q>
               <ptr target="#suntrust2001" loc="1271"/> against its objects of study. </p>
            <p>Digital humanists have already begun to reconfigure the literary as a category by
               considering whether using literary objects as building blocks for archives and
               exhibits designed to preserve, display, and study them can be considered an act of
               literary scholarship. When added to the fact many digital humanists already include
                  <q>non-traditional</q> texts such as code, video games, and social media, for
               example, in the list of objects that might be studied and used in ways similar to
               novels and plays, one gets the sense digital humanities may change substantially both
               our common understanding of the <q>literary</q> as a category and how we use it as a
               means of distinguishing one thing from another. Yet even as our working definitions
               of the literary are evolving, legal incorporation of prior definitions has resulted
               in a system that effectively limits the work of scholars who study artifacts that are
               literary, in the narrow, belletristic sense, to producing traditional academic
               criticism in the form of articles and books, at least those scholars who want to
               avoid getting sued and do not have the money to pay potentially exorbitant license or
               attorneys’ fees.</p>
            <p>In the nearly 150 years since <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title> was
               decided, continued application of the useful v. artistic, or low v. high distinction
               the Court drew in that case has evolved into a jurisprudence of <q>thin</q> v.
                  <q>thick</q> copyright <ptr target="#shipley2007"/>.<note>
                  <p> Others have used the thick v. thin distinction to describe the operation of
                     copyright more generally, observing how copyright has evolved from a relatively
                        <q>thin</q> right to prevent exact duplication for a limited time into a
                        <q>thick</q> bundle of rights that can be invoked to prevent many different
                     forms of reuse for a much longer term <ptr target="#vaidhyanathan2001"
                        loc="1–8"/>. I am using the thick v. thin distinction as the Supreme Court
                     used it in the case of <title rend="italic">Feist Publications, Inc. v. Rural
                        Telephone Service Co.</title>, 499 U.S. 340 [1991] to distinguish factual
                     works where, due to a relative lack of originality, copyrightable subject
                     matter is scant and protection therefore <q>thin</q> from creative works, where
                     originality and copyrightable subject matter are abundant and protection is
                        <q>thick.</q>
                  </p>
               </note> Although all <q>works of authorship</q> receive copyright protection, not all
               works are therefore created equal. Creative and artistic works, works that are
                  <q>literary</q> in the narrower, belletristic sense in that they can lay <cit><quote
                  rend="inline" source="#oed2012">claim to consideration on the ground of beauty
                  of form or emotional effect,</quote>
               <ptr target="#oed2012"/></cit> receive a great deal of legal protection from infringement,
               while historical, factual, or technical works get less, sometimes substantially less
               protection <ptr target="#shipley2007" loc="94–99"/>. This distinction comes into play
               perhaps most clearly in cases involving a fair use defense to a claim of copyright
               infringement. U.S. law requires courts to consider four factors when determining
               whether an allegedly infringing use is actually fair: <quote rend="block"
                  source="#constitution">Notwithstanding the provisions of sections 106 and 106A,
                  the fair use of a copyrighted work, including such use by reproduction in copies
                  or phonorecords or by any other means specified by that section, for purposes such
                  as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching (including multiple copies for
                  classroom use), scholarship, or research, is not an infringement of copyright. In
                  determining whether the use made of a work in any particular case is a fair use
                  the factors to be considered shall include — <list type="ordered">
                     <item>the purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a
                        commercial nature or is for nonprofit educational purposes;</item>
                     <item>the nature of the copyrighted work;</item>
                     <item>the amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the
                        copyrighted work as a whole; and</item>
                     <item>the effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the
                        copyrighted work.</item>
                  </list> The fact that a work is unpublished shall not itself bar a finding of fair
                  use if such finding is made upon consideration of all the above factors. <ptr
                     target="#constitution"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Section 107 codifies a long line of case law that originated in 1841 with <title
                  rend="italic">Folsom v. Marsh</title>, 9 F. Cas. 342 [1841]. Courts have made
               clear the <q>preamble</q> enumerating typical examples of fair use — <q>criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching (including
                  multiple copies for classroom use), scholarship, or research</q> [17 U.S.C.
               Section 107] — does not control whether something is or is not a fair use. In every
               case, courts must apply the four factors, along with any other factors they consider
               relevant to making a fair use determination. Nevertheless, in practice, the preamble
               sets a sort of aesthetic standard informing judicial application of the four-factor
               test. </p>
            <p> The first factor, regarding the <q>purpose and
                  character</q> of the allegedly infringing use, is supposed to cull thieves of
               creative expression from the herd of those who are simply borrowing facts, figures,
               and ideas, or who are treating creative expression like <q>facts</q> to be displayed,
               dissected, and discussed, i.e., critiqued. The second factor, concerning the <q>nature of the copyrighted work,</q> is designed to
               separate works that are really cobbled together out of facts, figures, and history —
               i.e., works where the copyright is <q>thin</q> — from those high literary works that
               comprise mostly creative expression and thus get <q>thicker</q> protection. Under the
               law as it has been interpreted and applied, creative, artistic works get a high level
               of copyright protection in the fair use analysis. They are also less likely to be
               viewed as fair uses. Consequently, if one authors a creative, artistic work that
               makes substantial use of pre-existing expression from another creative, artistic work
               that has not yet entered the public domain, the safest strategy would be to claim
               one’s work parodies the original.</p>
            <p> So, for example, in <title rend="italic">Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin</title>,
               286 F.3d 1257 [2001], the Court of Appeals for the Eleventh Circuit determined
               Margaret Mitchell’s heirs could not prove a likelihood of success on the merits in an
               infringement action involving Alice Randall’s <title rend="italic">The Wind Done
                  Gone</title> because it was more likely than not a parody, as opposed to a
               derivative sequel, of <title rend="italic">Gone With the Wind</title>. In reaching
               its decision, the court first had to <q>ensure that
                     <q>a parodic character may reasonably be perceived</q> in [Randall’s]
                  work</q>: <quote rend="block" source="#suntrust2001">The Supreme Court’s
                  definition of parody in Campbell [v. Acuff Rose], however, is somewhat vague. On
                  the one hand, the Court suggests that the aim of parody is <q>comic effect or ridicule,</q> but it then proceeds
                  to discuss parody more expansively in terms of its <q>commentary</q> on the
                  original. In light of the admonition in Campbell that courts should not judge the
                  quality of the work or the success of the attempted humor in discerning its
                  parodic character, we choose to take the broader view. <ptr target="#suntrust2001"
                     loc="1267"/> (citations omitted)</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Where engagement with a belletristic idea of the literary — its definition, its
               utility in defining legal concepts, its implicit presumptions about the relationship
               between art and utility — remains largely in the background in <title rend="italic"
                  >Baker v. Selden</title> and <title rend="italic">Stowe v. Thomas</title>, in
                  <title rend="italic">Suntrust v. Houghton Mifflin</title> we see the court engaged
               in an explicit attempt to define and apply literary terminology. The fair use
               determination turns upon how the court weighs in regarding an ongoing debate in
               literary studies and in copyright case law about the difference between parody and
               satire: <quote rend="block" source="#suntrust2001">For purposes of our fair-use
                  analysis, we will treat a work as a parody if its aim is to comment upon or
                  criticize a prior work by appropriating elements of the original in creating a new
                  artistic, as opposed to scholarly or journalistic, work. Under this definition,
                  the parodic character of TWDG is clear. TWDG is not a general commentary upon the
                  Civil-War-era American South, but a specific criticism of and rejoinder to the
                  depiction of slavery and the relationships between blacks and whites in GWTW. The
                  fact that Randall chose to convey her criticisms of GWTW through a work of
                  fiction, which she contends is a more powerful vehicle for her message than a
                  scholarly article, does not, in and of itself, deprive TWDG of fair-use
                  protection. We therefore proceed to an analysis of the four fair-use factors. <ptr
                     target="#suntrust2001" loc="1267"/> (citations omitted)</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Where parody is generally considered to be a fair use, satire is not. In this
               passage, the court struggles, as a number of courts have, with a literary distinction
               that has important legal consequences. As the <title rend="italic">Suntrust</title>
               court summarizes it, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#suntrust2001">Parody, which is
                  directed toward a particular literary or artistic work, is distinguishable from
                  satire, which more broadly addresses the institutions and mores of a slice of
                  society</quote>
               <ptr target="#suntrust2001"/></cit>. Thus, in order to find Randall’s work could be
               construed as a parody, the court necessarily had to determine first <title
                  rend="italic">The Wind Done Gone</title> offers a critique of <title rend="italic"
                  >Gone With the Wind</title> itself, rather than <q>a general commentary upon the Civil-War-era American
                  South.</q>
            </p>
            <p> The line courts draw between parody and satire is grounded in a presumption the work
               of literary criticism is to critique the author’s craft, rather than explore the
               broader socio-political circumstances that might have produced or might be reflected
               in the appropriated work. To the extent <title rend="italic">The Wind Done
                  Gone</title> pokes fun at the <q>formal</q> qualities of <title rend="italic">Gone
                  With the Wind</title> by demonstrating how far they deviate from reality in the
               Civil-War-era South, the <title rend="italic">Suntrust</title> court held it could be
               properly construed as operating like a <q>scholarly article</q> about the book. That
               narrow definition of literary scholarship only applies, however, when the allegedly
               infringing work itself looks suspiciously like a belletristic literary object. Had
               Randall chosen to write an academic <q>commentary upon
                  the Civil-War-era American South,</q> she very likely could have quoted
               extensively, word-for-word — and without fear of a copyright infringement action —
               from <title rend="italic">Gone With the Wind </title>in order to demonstrate how the
               ante-bellum period is romanticized in post-war fiction. By examining <title
                  rend="italic">The Wind Done Gone</title> for <q>parodic character</q> before
               engaging in the four-factor analysis, the <title rend="italic">Suntrust</title> court
               once again divided the broad, statutory category of literary objects into two
               categories. In the first category are literary things that are generally considered
               to be fair uses, things like scholarly articles. In the second, the court places
               things that are literary in the narrower, belletristic sense, such as <q>work[s] of
                  fiction</q> that will, under most circumstances not constitute fair use, that is
               unless they can be construed as <q>parody</q> engaged, like a more recognizable piece
               of literary criticism, in a formalist critique of the appropriated work.</p>
            <p> The court’s holding in <title rend="italic">Suntrust</title> demonstrates how
               unrealistically narrow and highly conventional definitions of both the literary and
               literary scholarship continue to inform judicial application of U.S. copyright law.
               Perhaps even more troubling, it describes the relationship between literary
               scholarship and its object as a fundamentally hostile one: <cit><quote rend="block"
                  source="#suntrust2001">A parody is a work that seeks to comment upon or criticize
                  another work by appropriating elements of the original. <q>Parody needs to mimic an original to make its point,
                     and so has some claim to use the creation of its <emph>victim’s (or collective
                        victims’)</emph> imagination.</q> Thus, Randall has fully employed those
                     <emph>conscripted</emph> elements from GWTW <emph>to make war against
                  it</emph></quote><ptr target="#suntrust2001" loc="1271"/></cit> (emphasis added).
            </p>
            <p>Some see in the digital humanities a potential to transform humanistic inquiry from a
               primarily critical enterprise into something that is still critical but in which
               critique is just one step in a longer process of something that might resemble
               Latour’s idea of composition. If this is the case, then digital humanists have a
               vested interest in the ongoing debate regarding the evolution of international
               copyright law. We need to ask ourselves whether or how we should reconfigure or even
               continue to deploy questionable aesthetic categories the law preserves like flies in
               amber when talking about the work we do as digital humanists. </p>
            <p>Perhaps one of the most important things we gain from understanding how courts have
               drawn upon and engaged with the literary as a category when interpreting and applying
               copyright law, is a better sense of just how much is riding upon the outcome of
               academic debates regarding the future of humanistic inquiry and scholarly
               communication. As a practical matter, preservation within the academy of traditional
               aesthetic and functional distinctions between literary objects and literary
               scholarship, between technological innovation and artistic creation, between
               composition and critique, will facilitate the continued preservation of those same
               distinctions within US copyright law. That in turn will mean that, under the law at
               least, all objects of study will not be available in the same way to the same kinds
               of activities. Perhaps that is a good thing. Because public domain materials are
               generally available to a wider range of scholarly activities involving building or
               composition, keeping the binary intact might ensure a continued interest in and
               engagement with older work in spite of external pressures to specialize in more
                  <q>relevant</q> areas such as new media studies rather than historical literary
               periods. Modern literary artifacts would continue to be amenable only to relatively
               traditional methods, though. Difficulty convincing our colleagues and institutions to
               value certain modes of scholarly production translates in the courtroom into judicial
               confusion over whether or not such work constitutes <q>scholarship</q> and fair use.
               Preserving the old categories in the law and within our disciplines would help to
               perpetuate a legal as well as a professional distinction between acceptable or legal
               uses of literary work in scholarly study and disfavored or illegal (unless licensed)
               uses.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Transformative Use, Joint Authorship, and More Productive Relationships</head>
            <p>Yet even as judicial interpretations of U.S. copyright law have incorporated narrow
               and confining definitions of both the literary and literary scholarship, some courts
               have also demonstrated how reconfiguring the literary as a category potentially opens
               up a more expansive space for humanistic inquiry. Just as digital and traditional
               humanists alike have called into question the criteria used to distinguish high from
               low or creative from technical literary artifacts, so too have U.S. courts begun to
               question the utility of such categories in analyzing the <q>purpose and character</q>
               of an allegedly infringing use in cases involving a fair use defense. Courts in a
               number of recent cases building upon the decisions in <title rend="italic">Kelly v.
                  Arriba Soft Corp.</title>
               <ptr target="#kelly2003"/>, and <title rend="italic">Bill Graham Archives v. Dorling
                  Kindersley Ltd.</title>
               <ptr target="#graham2006"/>, have turned to the concept of <q>transformative use</q>
               in order to determine whether a use is fair. Rather than relying on traditional
               aesthetic criteria to determine whether a given use is <q>critical</q> or merely
                  <q>derivative</q> of the pre-existing work, courts applying transformative use
               consider instead whether <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#castle1998">the secondary
                  use adds value to the original — if [copyrightable expression in the original
                  work] is used as raw material, transformed in the creation of new information, new
                  aesthetics, new insights and understanding</quote>
               <ptr target="#castle1998" loc="142"/></cit>.</p>
            <p>Thus, in the case of <title rend="italic">Blanch v. Koons</title>, 467 F.3d 244
               [2006], the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit upheld the district court’s
               grant of summary judgment in favor of Jeff Koons, who had reproduced in a painting an
               image drawn from one of the plaintiff’s photographs. Central to the circuit court’s
               holding was its conclusion Koons’s painting, <title rend="quotes">Niagara,</title>
               made <q>transformative</q> use of copyrightable subject matter from Blanch’s
               photograph, <q>Silk Sandals</q>:<quote rend="block" source="#blanch2006">Koons is, by
                  his own undisputed description, using Blanch’s image as fodder for his commentary
                  on the social and aesthetic consequences of mass media. His stated objective is
                  thus not to repackage Blanch’s <title rend="italic">Silk Sandals,</title> but to
                  employ it <q>in the creation of new information, new aesthetics, new insights and
                     understandings.</q> When, as here, the copyrighted work is used as <q>raw
                     material,</q> in the furtherance of distinct creative or communicative
                  objectives, the use is transformative. <ptr target="#blanch2006" loc="254"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The court’s discussion of transformative use, as an activity that creates <q>new information, new aesthetics, new insights
                  and understandings</q> from the <q>raw material</q> of copyrighted expression
               calls to mind Latour’s description of composition, in which the compositionist aims
               not (or at least not only) to <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2010">break down
                  walls, destroy idols, ridicule prejudices</quote> but to <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#latour2010">repair, take care, assemble, reassemble, stitch
                  together</quote> a set of <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2010">utterly
                  heterogeneous parts</quote> into something new and at least momentarily useful
                  <ptr target="#latour2010" loc="475"/>. </p>
            <p>The Second Circuit, unlike the Eleventh Circuit in <title rend="italic">Suntrust v.
                  Houghton Mifflin</title>, also concluded the consideration of whether something is
               parody or satire, while relevant to the fair use inquiry, is not dispositive: <cit><quote
                  rend="inline" source="#blanch2006">We have applied [the transformative use
                  doctrine] in too many non-parody cases to require citation for the proposition
                  that the broad principles of [transformative use] are not limited to cases
                  involving parody. But the satire/parody distinction may nevertheless be relevant
                  to the application of these principles</quote>
               <ptr target="#blanch2006" loc="255"/></cit>. The court further held the benefit accruing to
               the public from the exhibition for which <title rend="quotes">Niagara</title> was
               commissioned helped to balance the commercial nature of the overall enterprise and
               the private financial benefits derived by the defendants <ptr target="#blanch2006"
                  loc="256"/>. Perhaps even more surprising, the Koons court disagreed with the
               lower court’s determination, pursuant to the second fair use factor, that Blanch’s
               work was not <q>creative</q> or <q>artistic</q>: <cit><quote rend="inline"
                  source="#blanch2006">Accepting that <q>Silk Sandals</q> is a creative work,
                  though, it does not follow that the second fair-use factor. . . has significant
                  implications for our overall fair-use analysis. As we recently explained, . . .
                     <q>the second factor may be of limited usefulness where the creative work of
                     art is being used for a transformative purpose</q>
               </quote>
               <ptr target="#blanch2006" loc="257"/></cit>. Throughout its holding, the court in <title
                  rend="italic">Koons</title> implicitly reaffirms and recognizes the production of
               aesthetic pleasure is just one among the many important and useful social functions
               performed by art. </p>
            <p> The decision in <title rend="italic">Blanch v. Koons</title> has drawn both praise
               and criticism, and I do not want to suggest it represents, even seven years later, a
               normative standard guiding judicial application of U.S. copyright law. It does,
               however, provide substantial support for the proposition that courts of law have
               begun to accept the argument that transformative uses of pre-existing expression in
               songs, paintings, films, and the like may be classified as fair use alongside more
               recognizable forms of <q>criticism, comment, news
                  reporting, teaching . . . , scholarship, or research</q> [17 U.S.C. Section
               107]. The court’s reasoning also destabilizes the distinction U.S. copyright law has
               drawn for more than a century between works whose end is instruction, and works whose
               end lies in producing pleasure in the contemplation. <title rend="italic"
                  >Koons</title> rests on an understanding the abstractions conveyed in creative and
               artistic expression may not be the exclusive creations of the author, may often
               signify beyond the individual composition in which they appear, and, therefore, like
                  <q>knowledge</q> and <q>methods</q> should be available in the public domain for
               use as well as consumption. In <title rend="italic">Koons</title>, the court’s
               version of the creative or information economy is far more hospitable to both
               Latour’s idea of <q>composition</q> and digital humanists working in non-traditional
               scholarly modes and media.</p>
            <p> As digital humanists make the argument in promotion and tenure review that
               humanities scholarship does not have to look like traditional journal or book
               publication in order to do similar scholarly work or benefit the public in
               substantial and meaningful ways, a positive legal response to that argument would
               seem to provide yet another source of authority on which we can rely. After all, as a
               practical matter, the people making the argument and convincing judges are, in fact,
               often our colleagues in academia, filing briefs as friends of the court in
               significant cases, or working as expert witnesses hired by the parties or as special
               referees appointed by the court. One has to wonder why we have been relatively
               successful in making this argument outside of the academy in high-stakes copyright
               litigation, but still sometimes face substantial opposition within our own academic
               departments. In many cases, not only the judicial opinions, but also the parties’
               legal memoranda in which transformative use arguments have been articulated — and
               rebutted — are a matter of public record. We should consider whether we can
               productively mine these textual resources for vocabulary and conceptual framing as we
               create the standards we will apply in evaluating digital and non-traditional
               scholarship, standards such as the MLA’s <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for
                  Evaluating Work in Digital Humanities and Digital Media</title>
               <ptr target="#mla2012"/>. These same legal resources would unquestionably be of value
               as we attempt to refashion institutional policy regarding fair use and copyright
               matters.</p>
            <p> Speaking more broadly, I hope this discussion of U.S. copyright law and the literary
               demonstrates how what we do matters beyond the walls of the ivory tower. At times,
               the corporate economic interests that have shaped recent copyright legislation such
               as the Digital Millennium Copyright Act (the <q>DMCA</q>) and the Sonny Bono
               Copyright Term Extension, which legislation most scholars agree has created a more
               hostile environment for fair users of copyrighted content and decimated the public
               domain, can seem an almost overwhelming force. In 2010, however, in a round of
               federal rulemaking under the DMCA, libraries and producers of fan culture secured
               significant regulatory clarifications to facilitate their continued work <ptr
                  target="#schofield2010"/>
               <ptr target="#copyrighted2010"/>. The Creative Commons and Open Access movements have
               substantially raised public and institutional awareness of the importance of
               protecting the public domain and encouraging free circulation of content for use and
               reuse. During the time I have been working on this article, in 2012, an internet
                  <q>blackout</q> campaign against the Stop Online Piracy and Protect Intellectual
               Property Acts (<q>SOPA</q> and <q>PIPA,</q> respectively) helped to persuade US
               legislators to put the bills on hold indefinitely. Scholars of all disciplinary
               stripes have played an important role in each of these efforts. </p>
            <p>The language of literary scholarship and humanistic inquiry has done more than simply
               shape our own institutional practices. Through the integration of that language into
               case and even statutory law, certain strands of these discourses have in some
               situations acquired the force of law, for better or worse. We should therefore be
               careful as we call for reform of the academy. Law and policy makers do not regulate
               in a vacuum; they shape regulations to promote or discourage certain tendencies that
               already exist within the systems affected by the exercise of regulatory authority.
               Understanding the process reveals a potential opportunity to consider how, as we
               reconfigure the academic workplace, we might work more productively towards producing
               a regulatory framework more favorable to the public the academy ostensibly exists to
               serve, the policies to which we adhere, as well as the work we would like to do.</p>
            <p> Differences of opinion exist among digital humanists about how to define the digital
               humanities as a discipline. Many of the various definitions share in common a
               tendency to turn away from defining digital humanities in relation to the literary,
               both as a category that may apply to the objects we study, and as a category into
               which the work we produce might fall. One fairly prevalent and commonplace definition
               of the literary has been deployed in the copyright law context to define scholarship
               and teaching in relatively narrow and problematic ways. One might question,
               therefore, the continued effectiveness of the literary as a vehicle for
               conceptualizing the work of digital humanities, even for digital humanists working in
               traditional areas of literary studies. If digital humanists are to take advantage of
               the opportunity to affect public policy, however, by modeling at the disciplinary and
               institutional levels how we believe intellectual property regulation does and should
               work, then we must be able to articulate an alternative formulation of the literary
               that will prove useful inside the academy as well as the courtroom. The Second
               Circuit in <title rend="italic">Koons</title> and Latour in his <title rend="quotes"
                  >Compositionst Manifesto,</title> present strong arguments for reimagining
               scholarly work in terms of building new things that make use of instead of simply
               critique our objects of study. Along with the broad and inclusive definition of the
               literary as currently codified in the copyright statute itself, they also provide
               much-needed guidance regarding how we can justify building and digital humanities
               work with non-traditional texts as a scholarly activity within a more inclusive, more
               public-facing definition of literary scholarship. Lest copyright law prove an
               insurmountable barrier that stops digital humanists from experimenting with new forms
               of scholarship before we have even really begun, to accomplish the first goal
               requires giving due attention to the second.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Baker v. Selden 1879" xml:id="baker1879" key="baker1879">
               <title rend="italic">Baker v. Selden</title>. 101 U.S. 99 1879.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bill Graham Archives v. Dorling Kindersley Ltd. 2006" xml:id="graham2006"
               key="graham2006">
               <title rend="italic">Bill Graham Archives v. Dorling Kindersley Ltd.</title> 448 F.3d
               605. 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Blanch v. Koons 2006" xml:id="blanch2006" key="blanch2006">
               <title rend="italic">Blanch v. Koons</title>. 467 F.3d 244 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Boateng 2011" xml:id="boateng2011" key="boateng2011">Boateng, Boatema.
                  <title rend="italic">The Copyright Thing Doesn’t Work Here</title>. Minneapolis:
               University of Minnesota Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Boyle 1996" xml:id="boyle1996" key="boyle1996">Boyle, James. <title
                  rend="italic">Shamans, Software, and Spleen: Law and the Construction of the
                  Information Society.</title> Boston: Harvard University Press, 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Boyle 2008a" xml:id="boyle2008a" key="boyle2008a">Boyle, James. <title
                  rend="italic">The Public Domain: Enclosing the Commons of the Mind</title>. New
               Haven: Yale University Press, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Cambridge University Press v. Becker 2012" xml:id="cambridge2012"
               key="cambridge2012">
               <title rend="italic">Cambridge University Press v. Becker</title>. Civil Action No.
               1:08–CV–1425–ODE. 11 May 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Castle Rock Entertainment v. Carol Publishing Group 1998"
               xml:id="castle1998" key="castle1998">
               <title rend="italic">Castle Rock Entertainment v. Carol Publishing Group</title>. 150
               F.3d 132. 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Copyright Act of 1831" xml:id="copyright1831" key="copyright1831">
               <title rend="italic">Copyright Act of 1831</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Copyright Act of 1870" xml:id="copyright1870" key="copyright1870">
               <title rend="italic">Copyright Act of 1870</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Feist Publications, Inc. v. Rural Telephone Service Co. 1991"
               xml:id="feist1991" key="feist1991">
               <title rend="italic"> Feist Publications, Inc. v. Rural Telephone Service Co.</title>
               499 U.S. 340. 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Folsom v. Marsh 1841" xml:id="folsom1841" key="folsom1841">
               <title rend="italic">Folsom v. Marsh</title>. 9 F. Cas. 342. 1841.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Herrington 2001" xml:id="herrington2001" key="herrington2001a">Herrington,
               TyAnna K. <title rend="italic">Controlling Voices: Intellectual
                  Property, Humanistic Studies, and the Internet</title>. Carbondale, Illinois:
               2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Johns 2009" xml:id="johns2009" key="johns2009">Johns, Adrian. <title
                  rend="italic">Piracy: The Intellectual Property Wars From Gutenberg to
                  Gates</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp 2003" xml:id="kelly2003" key="kelly2003">
               <title rend="italic">Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</title> 336 F.3d 811. 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirsch 2010" xml:id="kirsch2010" key="kirsch2010">Kirsch, Adam. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Will Not to Power, but to Self-Understanding.</title>
               <title rend="italic">New York Times Sunday Book Review. </title>31 December
               2010.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kurtz 1986" xml:id="kurtz1986" key="kurtz1986">Kurtz, Leslie A. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Independent Legal Lives of Fictional Characters<title
                     rend="italic">.</title>
               </title>
               <title rend="italic">Wisconsin Law Review</title> 1 (May 1986): 429–525.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Latour 2010" xml:id="latour2010" key="latour2010a">Latour, Bruno. <title
                  rend="quotes">An Attempt at a <q>Compositionist Manifesto.</q>
               </title>
               <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 41.3 (Summer 2010): 471–90.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lessig 2004a" xml:id="lessig2004a" key="lessig2004a">Lessig, Lawrence.
                  <title rend="italic">Free Culture: How Big Media Uses Technology and the Law to
                  Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity.</title> New York: The Penguin Press,
               2004.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Leval 1990" xml:id="leval1990" key="leval1990">Leval, Pierre N. <title
                  rend="quotes">Toward a Fair Use Standard.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Harvard Law Review</title> 103 (1990): 1105–36.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Liu 2011" xml:id="liu2011" key="liu2011c">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Where is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities.</title> Paper presented to
               the 2011 Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Los Angeles, 7 January 2011.
                  <ref
                  target="http://liu.english.ucsb.edu/where-is-cultural-criticism-in-the-digital-humanities/"
                  >http://liu.english.ucsb.edu/where-is-cultural-criticism-in-the-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="MLA 2012" xml:id="mla2012" key="mla2012">Modern Language Association.
                  <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for Evaluating Work in Digital Humanities and
                  Digital Media.</title> April 25, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl label="OED 2012" xml:id="oed2012" key="oed2012">
               <title rend="quotes">literature, n.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford: Oxford
               University Press, 2012. <ref target="http://www.oed.com">http://www.oed.com</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Patterson and Lindberg 1991" xml:id="patterson1991" key="patterson1991"
               >Patterson, Lyman Ray and Stanley W. Lindberg. <title rend="italic">The Nature of
                  Copyright: A Law of Users’ Rights.</title> Athens, Georgia: University of Georgia
               Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Price 2008" xml:id="price2008" key="price2008">Price, David A. <title
                  rend="italic">The Pixar Touch: The Making of a Company.</title> New York: Vintage
               Books, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2011a" xml:id="ramsay2011a" key="ramsay2011a">Ramsay, Stephen.
                  <title rend="quotes">Who’s In and Who’s Out.</title> Paper presented to the 2011
               Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Los Angeles, 7 January 2011. <ref
                  target="http://lenz.unl.edu/papers/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out.html"
                  >http://lenz.unl.edu/papers/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2011b" xml:id="ramsay2011b" key="ramsay2011b">Ramsay, Stephen.
                  <title rend="quotes">On Building.</title> Blog post. 11 January 2011. <ref
                  target="http://lenz.unl.edu/papers/2011/01/11/on-building.html"
                  >http://lenz.unl.edu/papers/2011/01/11/on-building.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Schofield 2010" xml:id="schofield2010" key="schofield2010">Schofield, Jack.
                  <title rend="quotes">US says it's OK to jailbreak an iPhone, and take excerpts
                  from DVDs.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ZDNet UK. </title>26 July 2010. <ref
                  target="http://www.zdnet.co.uk/blogs/jacks-blog-10017212/us-says-its-ok-to-jailbreak-an-iphone-and-take-excerpts-from-dvds-10018104/"
                  >http://www.zdnet.co.uk/blogs/jacks-blog-10017212/us-says-its-ok-to-jailbreak-an-iphone-and-take-excerpts-from-dvds-10018104/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Shipley 1986" xml:id="shipley1986" key="shipley1986">Shipley, David E.
                  <title rend="quotes">Conflicts Between Copyright and the First Amendment After
                  Harper &amp; Row, Publishers v. Nation Enterprises.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Brigham Young University Law Review </title>4 (1986):
               983–1042.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Shipley 2007" xml:id="shipley2007" key="shipley2007">Shipley, David E.
                  <title rend="quotes">Thin But Not Anorexic: Copyright Protection for Compilations
                  and Other Fact Works.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Intellectual Property Law</title> 15 (2007):
               91–141.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Stowe v. Thomas 1853" xml:id="stowe1853" key="stowe1853">
               <title rend="italic">Stowe v. Thomas</title>. 23 F. Cas. 201. 1853.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin 2001" xml:id="suntrust2001"
               key="suntrust2001">
               <title rend="italic">Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin</title>. 286 F.3d 1257.
               2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Surwillo 2007" xml:id="surwillo2007" key="surwillo2007">Surwillo, Lisa.
                  <title rend="italic">The Stages of Property: Copyrighting Theatre in
               Spain</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Section 101, Title 17" xml:id="copyrighted2010" key="copyrighted2010">
               <title rend="quotes">Rulemaking on Exemptions from Prohibition on Circumvention of
                  Technological Measures that Control Access to Copyrighted Works</title> 2010.
               United States Register of Copyrights. <title rend="quotes">Recommendation of the
                  Register of Copyrights in RM 2008–8; Rulemaking on Exemptions from Prohibition on
                  Circumvention of Technological Measures that Control Access to Copyrighted
                  Works.</title> 11 June 2010. <ref
                  target="http://www.copyright.gov/1201/2010/initialed-registers-recommendation-june-11-2010.pdf"
                  >http://www.copyright.gov/1201/2010/initialed-registers-recommendation-june-11-2010.pdf</ref>.
                  <hi rend="bold">United States Code, Title 17.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="U.S. Constitution, Article 1, Section 8" xml:id="constitution"
               key="constitution">
               <title rend="italic">U.S. Constitution, Article 1, Section 8</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Vaidhyanathan 2001" xml:id="vaidhyanathan2001" key="vaidhyanathan2001"
               >Vaidhyanathan, Siva. <title rend="italic">Copyrights and Copywrongs: The Rise of
                  Intellectual Property and How It Threatens Creativity.</title> New York: New York
               University Press, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Woodmansee 1984" xml:id="woodmansee1984" key="woodmansee1984">Woodmansee,
               Martha. <title rend="quotes">The Genius and the Copyright: Economic and Legal
                  Conditions of the Emergence of the <q>Author.</q>
               </title>
               <title rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century Studies</title> 17.4 (1984): 425–48.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
