<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">Avatar Emergency</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Gregory L. <dhq:family>Ulmer</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Professor of English and Media Studies
            University of Florida, Gainesville</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>glue@ufl.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Gregory L. Ulmer is Professor of English and Media Studies at the University of
              Florida. He is affiliated with the European Graduate School, Saas-Fee, Switzerland,
              and is Coordinator of the Florida Research Ensemble, a collaboration experimenting
              with the invention of an image metaphysics for the apparatus of electracy. Recent
              books include <title rend="italic">Internet Invention</title> (2003), and <title rend="italic">Electronic Monuments</title> (2005). <title rend="quotes">Avatar
                Emergency</title> is from a work in progress.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000100</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2011-11-15">15 November 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2011-05-23" who="Alyssa">made corrections</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The original usage of <term>avatar</term> referred to the incarnation or human appearance
          of a deity, particularly Vishnu, in Hindu mythology. The term was adapted to cyberspace to
          name one’s online persona. This usage has come to include every aspect of one’s online
          representation, from the icon on a blog, or an email signature to the figure one plays in
          Second Life. <term>Avatar</term>, then, is a practical point of entry for theorizing the
          emergence of the new identity experience of electracy, that is supplementing and
          displacing <term>selfhood</term>, the identity formation of literacy. Playing one’s avatar
          is to electracy what writing an essay is to literacy. The point addressed in this essay is
          that an avatar is not merely the appearance of one’s representation, since through
          interactivity and even telepresence, I am t/here with my image. What is it to be/have an
          image? The answer begins with noting the literal meaning of the <term>avatar</term> in
          Sanskrit: <q>Descent.</q> Vishnu has descended (taken on embodiment)
          nine times, to correct a disordered world condition. This essay initiates a review of the
          cultural archive to see what is known already about our question (representations of
            <q>descent</q>). It is perhaps obvious, considering the prominence
          of Christianity in our heritage, that the West accumulated a huge amount of information
          about becoming body. Two examples are referenced in this introductory piece: Krishna and
          Orpheus.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>What counts in an emergency is not what your avatar looks like, but what it knows.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Avatar Emergency</head>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <p>This essay considers <term>avatar</term> from the point of view of the apparatus of
          electracy (the digital equivaltent of <term>literacy</term>). The concept, tradition, and
          practice of <term>avatar</term> are relevant to the invention of flash reason, a
          rhetorical practice for deliberative reason, for public policy formation, making
          democratically informed decisions in a moment, at light speed, against the threat of a
          General Accident that happens everywhere simultaneously. Any theorizing of
            <term>avatar</term> must at least acknowledge James Cameron’s dramatization in the
          blockbuster film. It is fortunate for my account (given the influence this film will have
          in shaping the discussion) that there is an important aspect of electrate
            <term>avatar</term> captured by Cameron’s treatment. Avatar as an experience is an event
          of counsel. It is an uncanny encounter with one’s own possibility (potential), as
          undergone in various wisdom traditions noted here as analogies for the flash reason made
          possible through avatar practice. Through avatar, players come to understand the General
          Economy of the universe, so to speak, represented as <term>nature</term> or the Gaia
          spirit of Pandora in Cameron’s film. The <soCalled>jar-head</soCalled> Sully, incarnated
          in his Na’vi simulation, transcends his Marine training as well as his limitations both
          physical and mental, to oppose the actions of the military-industrial complex corporation
          that are threatening the natural order. It is perhaps understandable, if not inevitable,
          that the screenplay uses the shorthand of the Frontier myth, in high-concept
          reconfiguration (genre hybrid), to express its values. Cameron’s <title rend="italic">Avatar</title> is a Western.</p>
            <p>Something is happening to us and through us that goes by the name <term>avatar</term>
          these days. Some of us are present in Second Life through an <term>avatar,</term> or have
          had our identities stolen digitally, for example, added a photograph to our Facebook
          account or branded our blog with an icon of some sort, even designed and sold T-Shirts,
          skateboards, coffee mugs and the like with our personal logos emblazoned. All of that is
          just learning the <term>alphabet</term> of avatar. We have not yet begun to avatar,
          although there are futuristic scenarios and scholarly histories, looking forward and back
          in time, to consider the possibilities. You need to meet avatar, that part of you
          inhabiting cyberspace (for lack of a better term). You and I need to meet the avatar that
          we already have, that we already are, now that it may be augmented within the digital
          apparatus (electracy) as a prosthesis of decision. Avatar knows more than you or I do, or
          rather, it knows better than you or I do about what to do now, or what you or I truly know
          and understand and value and wish in our various respective situations. This claim must be
          not only understood, but undergone. It is not only an idea, a theory, but an
          experience.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Internet Accident</head>
            <div>
               <head>Avatar Descends (the phrase is redundant) in Times of Crisis.</head>
               <p>The present crisis is represented by an exhibit, curated for the Museum of Accidents
            proposed by Paul Virilio. The Museum is an idea that hardly needs a space, since it is
            available <soCalled>without walls</soCalled> 24/7 on television. Nonetheless, it began
            its existence as an exhibition and catalogue, both entitled <title rend="quotes">Unknown
              Quantity,</title> presented at the Fondation Cartier pour l'art contemporain in Paris,
            from November 29, 2002, to March 30, 2003 (<ref target="http://www.onoci.net/virilio/pages_uk/accidents/liste.php">http://www.onoci.net/virilio/pages_uk/accidents/liste.php</ref>) <ptr target="#virilio1999" loc="45"/>. Having directed a television program on this
            project in Japan, Virilio collaborated with the Japanese on creating an actual museum
              <ptr loc="76" target="#virilio1999"/>. This Museum constitutes a paradigm, or
            exemplary problematic, which has the potential to gather all specialized academic
            disciplines around a single project, in order (despite Virilio's warning against this
            effect) to synchronize contemporary knowledge.</p>
               <p>The catalogue of the exhibit included Virilio's text, summarizing and expanding upon
            the thesis argued in a number of his published works, such as <title rend="italic">The
              Politics of the Very Worst</title>, <title rend="italic">Open Sky</title>, and <title rend="italic">The Original Accident</title>; an excerpt from the Chernobyl diary of
            Svetlana Aleksievich (Chernobyl is foregrounded as the emblem of the modern accident
            with global consequences); extensive illustrations — photographs representing a gallery
            of modern disasters both natural and man-made; reproductions of art works belonging to
            an eschatological genre, classical and contemporary, such as Jan Van Scorel, <title rend="quotes">The Universal Deluge,</title> and Walter de Maria, <title rend="quotes">Lightning Field.</title>
               </p>
               <p>Virilio's argument looks at the epoch of electracy from the perspective of the rise and
            fall of the ideology of progress. The extraordinary technological innovations of the
            industrial and post-industrial eras, including the invention of the recording
            technologies of the electrate apparatus, occurred within a shifting horizon of negative
            expectations. The eighteenth century introduced revolution; the nineteenth century added
            the expectation of war; the twentieth century culminated in the expectation of an
            integral accident, referring to an accident of knowledge itself. The basic insight
            derives from a glance at the history of progress — that every invention brought with it
            its own disaster: with the ship, train, car, plane, came their respective wrecks. There
            are no exceptions to this rule, hence, as we contemplate the possibilities of inventing
            life itself now (cloning, genetic engineering) we may anticipate corresponding disasters
            (the knowledge accident).</p>
               <p>The claim most directly relevant to electracy concerns the Internet accident, with the
              <soCalled>Internet</soCalled> serving as a metonym for the digital technologies of new
            media rapidly replacing the literate apparatus as the support for the language function
            in society. The Internet accident is a General Accident that occurs everywhere
            simultaneously, an event made possible by the light-speed connectivity and global reach
            of digital media, especially as these capacities are extended into such features as
            telepresence. Virilio posed the question: what is the integral accident that may be
            expected to follow upon the invention and general adoption of the Internet? In our
            context, he is asking: what are the consequences of electracy?</p>
               <p>Virilio introduces the neologism <term>dromosphere</term> (from <term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">dromos,</foreign>
                  </term> race) to name the conditions likely to
            produce the General Accident. The dromosphere refers to the pollution of dimensions that
            follows from electronic augmentation of human thought and language. Instant
            communication is constricting time, eliminating the past and the future, reducing human
            temporality to Now-time. If the oral apparatus ran on cyclical time, and literacy on
            linear time, electracy operates within the moment of Now. All trajectory disappears,
            eliminating the journey with its departure and passages, leaving us only with pure
            arrival. The mood of this condition is claustrophobic, a sense of being trapped. The
            human condition in the dromosphere is that of being caught and held within Now-time. The
            paradox of this confinement is that, augmented by the technologies of telepresence, the
            experience of Now is separated from place, even from being-there (<term>Dasein</term>). <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#virilio1999">It is now the immobility of all possible journeys or paths. The
                time-light barrier then blocks off — along with the horizon of appearances — the
                horizon of action, the very reality of a space where all succession dissolves, where
                it is as though hours and days had ceased to flow; surfaces ceased to extend; what
                cropped up yesterday, here or there, now happens everywhere at once. The accident to
                end all accidents spreads in a flash and the center of time — the endless present —
                leaves behind the center of fixed space for good. There is no longer any
                  <term>here</term>, everything is <term>now</term>.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#virilio1999" loc="85"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Virilio's argument is that teletechnologies through their instantaneous interactivity
            have produced a <soCalled>single time</soCalled> — Real Time — whose milieu is speed.
            This unprecedented immediacy and ubiquity makes democracy impossible, he argues. Public
            space in Real Time becomes an image in some medium — photography, cinema, television.
            These images replace the <soCalled>trajectories</soCalled> of the city, the face-to-face
            interaction of the public sphere and the encounter of subject with object in the agora,
            the forum. The question he raises is whether a virtual city is possible — whether it is
            possible to urbanize real time. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#virilio1997">If the answer is no, then a
                general accident is inevitable, the accident of history, the accident of accidents
                that Epicurus spoke of regarding history. If we are not capable of urbanizing the
                real time of exchange, in other words the live city-world, the city-world in real
                time, through the globalization of telecommunications, then both history and
                politics will be called into question. This is an extraordinary drama</quote>
                     <ptr target="#virilio1997" loc="40"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The conditions described by Virilio pose a challenge, calling for the invention of a
            new apparatus (social machine), that does for digital media what the invention of
            literacy in Classical Greece did for alphabetic writing. The creators of philosophy in
            the Academy and Lyceum invented the very institution of school, and within it the
            practices of logic, rhetoric, poetics to support ultimately scientific and democratic
            civilization. Plato warned in the first discourse on method in the Western tradition,
              <title rend="italic">Phaedrus</title>, that writing separated the speaker’s voice from
            embodied presence, allowing it to wander abroad without protection. The experience of
            one’s own voice returning in writing contributed to the formation of a new identity
            formation known as selfhood, as Eric Havelock demonstrated in several books. In
            electracy (the digital apparatus) the evolution of identity continues, this time through
            the phenomenon of avatar, of one’s image and reputation circulating through the
            Internet, subject to sampling and mixing, to return in the form of scandal, libel, fame,
            fortune. The invention of a logic adequate to the dromosphere (flash reason, a practice
            of epiphany for authoring on the fly in database environments functioning at light
            speed) begins with an investigation of the opportunity for further invention opened by
            the acceptance of <term>avatar</term> to name one’s representative in cyberspace. The
            implication is that avatar opens connectivity between you and techgnosis.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Dromosphere</head>
               <p>The guiding scene and proposed attunement for thought and action in electracy is
              <emph>player with avatar</emph>. <q>Play</q> is justified in
            this context not only because of the game analogy, but more properly in the ludic terms
            developed by Johan Huizinga, who argues that culture and even civilization emerges out
            of play <ptr target="#huizinga1950"/>. The historical or cultural source of this scene
            is the Sanskrit poem <title rend="italic">Bhagavadgita</title> (<title rend="quotes">Song of God,</title> Book VI of the <title rend="italic">Mahabharata</title>), a
            major work of the Hindu religion. The setting is the battlefield of Kuruksetra (a place
            of religious pilgrimage), with two armies in conditions of civil war in position to
            engage. Prince Arjuna is assisted in his battle chariot by Krishna, an incarnation of
            the god Vishnu. Arjuna, seeing many friends and family among both armies, expresses to
            his friend Krishna his ambivalence about the situation, and the decision he has to make.
            The poem records the subsequent conversation between the friends about dharma (duty,
            virtue), and the meaning of life in general, the metaphysics of the Hindu worldview.
            Krishna is one of nine avatars of Vishnu that have incarnated, appearing at times of
            crisis, whenever dharma is in decline. Vishnu’s avatars include fish, tortoise, boar,
            man-lion, dwarf, Rama the ax-wielder, Rama, Krishna, Buddha. A tenth avatar, Kalki, will
            appear in human form, riding a white horse, at the time of the crisis of our present
            age. The term <term>avatar</term> in Sanskrit literally means <term>descent</term>.</p>
               <p>The secular meaning of avatar refers to the personification in human form of abstract
            principles or intangible qualities. Aaron Britt surveyed the usage. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#britt2008">The proliferation of avatar’s second meaning can be traced to Second
                Life, a multiplayer online virtual world, where players fashion their own online
                personae called avatars. The popularity of the game has shot the term into the
                mainstream. Philip Rosedale, the creator of Second Life, defines avatar in the
                gaming sense as “the representation of your chosen embodied appearance to other
                people in a virtual world.” Considering that Second Life avatars may assume
                literally any guise — wings, a dragon’s head, gills and flippers — the key to
                avatarness, in Rosedale’s view, is user control. And insofar as a Second Life avatar
                does and is precisely what the player wants, not just a little Mario who can be made
                to run and jump or a shapely diva gyrating of her own programmed will, it comes far
                closer to being a full-fledged virtual persona.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#britt2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The value of <term>avatar</term> for us is that the name tags the site of electrate
            identity formation, and in its religious, secular, and literal senses indexes cultural
            resources that have yet to be explored for the insight they may offer into our question
            of deliberation in the dromosphere. Rosedale misunderstands avatar. It is indeed a
            relationship with self, but the power flows in exactly the reverse direction: the player
            is and does what avatar wants, to the extent that the player is prudent. Our point of
            entry into electracy is just this question of avatar: what it is, what it is for, how to
            do it (how to avatar, <emph>avatar as verb</emph>). A first lesson of our guiding scene
            for contemporary conduct – Arjuna with Krishna on the verge of battle – signals a shift
            in our approach to this usage, extending it to identify the site of subject formation
            itself in electracy. The scene shows us a relationship between self (player) and avatar.
            Self is Arjuna; avatar is Krishna. Here is a relay for understanding the status of one’s
            image (reputation, status, brand) in cyberspace. An online incarnation is not
              <soCalled>self</soCalled> or ego, but a dimension of identity emerging in the new
            apparatus that is unfamiliar to modern people, and for which the analogy, helping us to
            imagine what is happening and to guide the invention of this new formation, is
              <term>avatar</term>. The function of avatar is counsel in a situation of decision.
            Through avatar you go beyond the limits of <soCalled>self</soCalled> to understand
            action from the position of communal well-being.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Descent</head>
               <p>There is also a tradition of avatar in the West, whose terms help to locate a set-up
            for an invention. The tradition supplies the slots for a poetics of avatar. What are the
            elements, for which we will develop an upgrade path? <list type="ordered">
                     <item>Theory: Neoplatonism describes human being as a fall (a breaking off) from pure
                spirit into matter. The original descent is <soCalled>natural</soCalled> (birth).
                Embodied, one chooses between a vicious or virtuous descent (to embrace or reject
                sensory pleasure). Wisdom prescribes a practice of <soCalled>attention,</soCalled>
                devoting one’s life to a <soCalled>return</soCalled> to pure spirit.</item>
                     <item>Allegory: Plotinus treated Homer’s <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> as an
                allegory, to dramatize the circular journey of descent and return. Ulysses
                demonstrates the middle stage of striving, between Procession (the going down) and
                Epistrophe (return) (M. H. Abrams). The fourth mode of descent is
                  <soCalled>artificial,</soCalled> undertaken for purposes of wisdom, experiment,
                education. Ulysses leaves Circe, and follows her instructions to enter Hades (via
                ritual sacrifice), to learn from the shade (manes) of Tiresias how to return home. </item>
                     <item>Trajectory (movement, path, <hi rend="italic">Weg</hi>): The shape shared by the
                theory and the allegory, extracted as measure.</item>
                  </list> A lesson of this vocabulary is that <term>descent</term> entails three other
            stages of <term>avatar</term>. Up to modernity Western culture was devoted almost
            entirely to <term>return</term> or <term>ascent</term>, to escape the <q>prison of embodiment.</q> Such is the chief lesson of the Passion of
            the Christ. The stage that survives into modernity, however, with its commitment to
            immanence against all transcendence, is that of striving or dwelling. There are Sanskrit
            words for these other stages as well, although not applied to this context. Usage
            dictates that we retain <term>avatar</term> as metonym for the whole cycle.</p>
               <p>Ezra Pound begins his <title rend="italic">Cantos</title> with a version of Ulysses’s
            descent into Hades to consult Tiresias (one of the classic accounts of avatar). His
            method of access involved much sacrifice. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#pound1996">Dark blood flowed in
                the fosse,/ Souls out of Erebus, cadaverous dead, of brides/ Of youths and of the
                old who had borne much;/ Souls stained with recent tears, girls tender,/ Men many,
                mauled with bronze lance heads,/ Battle spoil, bearing yet dreory arms, / These many
                crowded about me; with shouting,/ Pallor upon me, cried to my men for more beasts;/
                Slaughtered the herds, sheep slain of bronze;/ Poured ointment, cried to the gods,/
                To Pluto the strong, and praised Proserpine;/ Unsheathed the narrow sword,/ I sat to
                keep off the impetuous impotent dead,/ Till I should hear Tiresias.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#pound1996"/>
                  </cit> The heuretic analogies continue: avatar descends into
            media spectacle as Ulysses into Hades, a fourth mode of descent, to question and to
            learn. The structural pattern repeats across civilizations and media. In Plato’s
            version, the Real is a realm of Ideas (Christianity placed Plato’s Ideas in the mind of
            God). Spirit enters a body when it is born, and this material kosmos is an image of the
            Real. Journeys to Hades are examples of the fourth descent, the probe (Dante’s tour of
            Inferno). Science Fiction has run ahead to predict the coming relationship of user and
            avatar, but the point of view is reactionary (witness <title rend="italic">The
              Matrix</title>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Synderesis</head>
               <p>Giorgio Agamben suggests a point of departure guiding our analogies. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#agamben2007">
                        <term>Synderesis</term> is a technical term used in the Neoplatonic
                mysticism of the Middle Ages and the Renaissance to designate the highest and most
                delicate area of the soul; it is in direct communication with the supersensory, and
                has never been corrupted by original sin. Perhaps these pages give us a glimpse of
                the future experience of the <term>ego cogito</term>, and furnish one more proof of
                the close proximity between two poles of our culture. We see that the
                  <term>cogito</term>, like mystical synderesis, is what remains of the soul when,
                at the end of a <soCalled>dark night,</soCalled> it is stripped of all its
                attributes and content. The heart of this transcendental experience of the I has
                been signally described by an Arab mystic, Al-Hallaj: <quote rend="inline" source="#agamben2007">I am
                    <emph>I</emph> and the attributes are no more; I am <emph>I</emph> and the
                  qualifications are no more… I am the pure subject of the verb.</quote>
                     </quote>
                     <ptr target="#agamben2007" loc="34"/>
                  </cit> This <soCalled>obsolete</soCalled> notion
            of synderesis may be retrieved for thinking about the connection of telepresence between
            player and avatar. The new attitude introduced within electracy (beginning with
            aesthetics) is the embracing of <soCalled>pleasure,</soCalled> characterized in the
            tradition as the <soCalled>vicious</soCalled> descent. In apparatus theory, dreams
            (visions, fantasies) motivate invention as much as does practical necessity.</p>
               <p>We may elaborate our allegory of prudence (good judgment based on wise counsel)
            following Agamben: to articulate a new experience of time, in order to invent a thought
            adequate to image spectacle. Even as our idea of history has changed, our model of time
            has remained within literate metaphysics. Time in this metaphysics has been thought
            through two shapes (two ideas, eidos = shape). The Greek shape is a circle. The
            Christian shape is a line: circularity and linearity. Modern time is a secularized line.
            We no longer have time for round trips or progress, when before and after, here and
            there, have collapsed into now. But what is this now? Agamben has one answer, alluding
            to Walter Benjamin’s Jetztzeit (now-time). The shape of this moment derives from a
            tradition of emergency (as Benjamin put it): an experience of the normal condition as a
            state of emergency. Agamben locates his third model in the Gnostic time of interruption,
            figured as a broken line. In this experience everything has already happened (the worst,
            the best, revolution, the resurrection). Time stands still, and nothing may be expected
            from the future. All that history has deprecated must be revisited.</p>
               <p>Agamben recommends retrieval as the method for expressing the new experience of time (a
            grammatology of the archive). He proposes two topics for further inquiry. First is the
            tradition of Kairos (even a <term>kairology</term>), with its roots in metis. In
            practice metic time breaks with the vulgar time of streaming instants, to recognize a
            moment of opportunity (an opening in time). The conventional emblem of a weaver throwing
            the shuttle does disservice to kairos, since the moment may not be awaited with such
            certainty or rhythm. The other topic Agamben proposes as the basis for a new time shape
            is pleasure. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#agamben2007">Yet for everyone there is an immediate and
                available experience on which a new concept of time could be founded. This is an
                experience so essential to human beings that an ancient Western myth makes it
                humankind’s original home: it is pleasure</quote>
                     <ptr target="#agamben2007" loc="114"/>
                  </cit>. The time of pleasure is neither that of
            precise continuous time nor of eternity. It is rather the time of history, Agamben,
            says, but a kairological history. Here is the primary issue for electrate experience:
            avatar as prosthesis of a time of <soCalled>pleasure</soCalled> (the nature of which
            remains to be defined).</p>
               <p>The invention of flash reason may approach a new operation of time through shape. There
            is no shape given in the intuition of time as inner experience (Kant). Since no shape is
            given (thus opening a history of time), we resort to a graphic analogy (the gramme).
            Here is the problematic of trace, according to Derrida. It is not a question of any one
            shape, a fourth graphic, for example, but the <emph>differance</emph> of time space.
            Thus we become aware of this other dimension, the undecidable trace working within any
            particular configuration of time space (chronotope). This is the trace in the term
              <term>electracy</term>. Once this problematic is thematized, the practices associated
            with a new temporality become accessible to invention. The preliminary problem addressed
            in our practice, however, is how or in what way this temporality may be experienced. How
            may we undergo differantial prudence (decision, judgment)? Most of the disappointments
            reported regarding social networking experience are made from the position of selfhood
            (of ego, of literate identity), concerned about attracting and holding attention upon a
            fixed identity. But <term>self</term> is not one in cyberspace. Avatar is no more ego
            than Krishna is Arjuna. The instructions are analogies. What is avatar, as practice and
            experience? <emph>It is like consulting with incarnate Vishnu in a moment of
              emergency.</emph>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Metis</head>
               <p>Avatar uses flash reason in order to deliberate on public policy issues in the
            dromosphere. Paul Virilio’s choice of the Greek term for race (dromos) to name the
            condition of dimension collapse in electracy is a clue guiding the heuretics of flash
            reason. The method poses a question: what is the reasoning that wins races; specifically
            (continuing with the tactic of retrieval), what was the logic of the <term>race
              course</term> in Classical Greece (grammatology, inventing electracy by analogy). The
            oral Greeks called this reason <term>metis</term>, (after Zeus’s first wife) and it
            survived in literacy as prudence, <term>phronesis</term>, practical reason. Plato
            configured it as his contrast while inventing the pure or contemplative reason and its
            logic of identity organizing the philosophy of Being. Metis, rather, is the logic of
            Becoming, useful in conditions of contingency such as those concerning ethics and
            politics, when the outcome depends on human judgment. A phronimos or prudent person is
            one capable of immediately assessing the givens of a particular situation, and drawing
            upon maxims formulated from past experience, making a decision to act in a way that
            foresees the best outcome in the future. In short, prudence is time-logic.</p>
               <p>The details of prudence (metis) in their oral version are exemplified by Odysseus, who
            relies on cunning and deceit to overcome more powerful adversaries and forces. The same
            vocabulary was used in early literacy in manuals teaching hunting and fishing. The
            emblematic figure of metis, in fact, is the fishing net, especially the cast net with
            its encircling meshes. The <term>net</term> of <term>network</term> in electracy
            resonates with this skill of creating or escaping snares, traps, lures, or any sort of
            aporia — mastery of circles and binds. Marcel Detienne and Jean-Pierre Vernant use the
            race course (dromos) to map the operating features of metis that may be projected onto
            any situation (Arjuna and Krishna in the battle chariot). Prudence means not caution but
              <emph>foresight</emph> that prepares one for success in open circumstances requiring
            improvisation and instant thought. The race course holds three sites and moments of
            danger and opportunity: the starting line, the turn (bend), and the finish line. The
            charioteer stands in for any pilot (Arjuna in his chariot with Krishna), with the
            vocabulary of navigation, cybernauts, cybernetics, helping translate practical reason
            into flash reason. The ultimate test of wayfinding is that of a stormy sea at night,
            when all guidemarks disappear (the scene of aporia), whether this night sea is literal
            or figurative (projected into the arts of medicine, politics, rhetoric). Avatar as guide
            through Tartarus (the trackless realm beneath the underworld).</p>
               <p>Virilio’s general emergency is a call for invention, not a prophecy of doom. The danger
            that he sketches begins with the formation of the <soCalled>mental map</soCalled> that
            each person develops. This map is what must be augmented in the new apparatus. What is
            the mental map of cyberspace? The threat to freedom, he says, begins with the reduction
            and impoverishment of this mental picture. As an urbanist he locates the source of the
            crisis as the displacement of the real city by the tele-city, the loss of a lived public
            space in favor of a virtual gathering on the internet <ptr target="#virilio1999" loc="45"/>. The challenge is that the lived city as a space and place is no longer
            visible, its borders or shape lost to perception, a loss that affects border itself and
            hence identity as such. Intelligibility depends on borders, edges, limits: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#virilio1999">the city is the law, and the law is the border</quote>
                     <ptr target="#virilio1999" loc="76"/>
                  </cit>. The new technologies of electromagnetism
            and the video screen no longer concern sun rays, light, and geometric perspective, but
            wave optics. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#virilio1999">Geometrical optics made the city centers and the
                suburbs. Centralized cities such as Palmanova are the result of perspective vision.
                The ideal city of Piero della Francesca is the vision of a city that implements
                perspective vision. Now, the invention of a perspective of real time and
                electromagnetic wave optics demands an understanding of what the city of that vision
                of the world will be — virtual city</quote>
                     <ptr target="#virilio1999" loc="85"/>
                  </cit>. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#virilio1997">Alongside air pollution, water pollution and the
                like, there exists an unnoticed phenomenon of a pollution of the world's dimensions
                that I propose to call <term>dromospheric</term> — from <term>
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">dromos</foreign>
                        </term>: a race, running. Contamination has in
                fact spread further than the elements, natural substances, air, water, fauna and
                flora it attacks — as far as the space-time of our planet. Gradually reduced to
                nothing by the various tools of transport and instantaneous communication, the
                geophysical environment is undergoing an alarming diminishing of its <soCalled>depth
                  of field</soCalled> and this is degrading man's relationship with his environment.
                The optical density of the landscape is rapidly evaporating, producing confusion
                between the apparent horizon, which is the backdrop of all action, and the deep
                horizon of our collective imagination; and so one last horizon of visibility comes
                into view, the transapparent horizon, a product of the optical (optocelectronic and
                acoustic) magnification of man's natural domain.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="22" target="#virilio1997"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>What makes the dromosphere so troubling is that it requires the invention of a new mode
            of governance. The rhetorical skills of deliberative reason within a public sphere that
            made democracy possible were inventions of literacy, and are not sustainable within
            electracy. The time of decision, the civic process of critical analysis and persuasion
            through argumentation, is a luxury we do not have in the conditions of Right Now. We
            need a rhetoric that is forensic, epideictic, and deliberative at once. What happened,
            who is responsible, what do we do now? Here is the point of departure for flash reason,
            the image logic of avatar. Avatar reason is as compressed as the compression ratios of
            the equipment supporting it. An apparatus is not only equipment, but also practices of
            thinking developed within emerging institutions, and behaviors of identity (individual
            and collective). </p>
               <p>Flash reason must do for the image prosthesis what argumentation did for the word in
            literacy. The resources needed for designing a logic of an Internet civic sphere are
            already available in the same cultural history that produced the technology. Marshal
            McLuhan’s laws of media indicate that apparatus invention proceeds by the <q>obsoleting</q> of some current practice, and the <q>retrieval</q> of some obsolete practice, newly recognized as
            relevant to a contemporary context. The larger purpose of Avatar Emergency is to
            establish a collection of cultural inventions associated historically with fast or
            sudden thinking, and compose from them an experimental procedure for collective and
            individual decision-making Now. Flash reason, adopted as a practice of general
            electracy, is a civic basis for democracy in the circumstances of the dromosphere.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Orpheus</head>
               <p>Our reconfiguration of avatar as a practice of electracy takes McLuhan’s advice about
            the laws of media: that with any artifact one must ask, what does it render obsolete,
            and what does it retrieve from the past? <ptr target="#mcluhan1992"/>. As our guiding
            scene suggests, avatar’s history includes various incarnations and theorizations, as
            god, soul, self. It is not that literate selfhood is rendered obsolete in our context,
            seeking a practice of flash reason adequate to the demands of the dromosphere, but that
            this experience of being an autonomous individual is brought into relationship with a
            new dimension of reality produced within the epoch of electracy. Avatar is the name of
            this relationship, and it may be figured in an emblem.</p>
               <p>Avatar in our Internet public sphere is a relationship, and depends upon a certain kind
            of experience. Another relay (rather than model) for this approach to avatar is provided
            by Maurice Blanchot’s appropriation of the Orpheus myth as an emblem of his theory of
            writing <ptr target="#blanchot1981" loc="171"/>. The Greek myth recounts the life and
            death of Orpheus, credited as the inventor of writing. Blanchot focuses on Orpheus’s
            descent (avatar) into Hades, which he was able to enter through the power of his art.
            His purpose was to retrieve his beloved Eurydice, who died in an accident. Blanchot
            focused his retelling, more or less faithful to the original, on the moment when Orpheus
            broke the agreement with the demi-gods and turned to look at Eurydice before they exited
            Hades. <quote rend="inline" source="#ovid1999">Thracian Orpheus took her and with her the command that he
              not turn back his gaze until he had left the groves of Avernus, or the gift would be
              revoked,</quote> as Ovid wrote. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ovid1999">Through the mute silence, they
              wrest their steep way, arduous, dark, and thick with black vapors. They were not far
              form the border of the world above; here frightened that she might not be well and
              yearning to see her with his own eyes, through love he turned and looked, and with his
              gaze she slipped away and down</quote> 
                     <ptr target="#ovid1999" loc="274"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The Greek terms for descent (<term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">catabasis</foreign>
                  </term>)
            and ascent (<term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">anabasis</foreign>
                  </term>) remind us that the
            West has its own tradition of avatar and <term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="sa">aarohat</foreign>
                  </term> (Sanskrit <term>ascent</term>). <term>Catabasis</term>
            (Greek <term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">kata</foreign>
                  </term>, <term>down</term>, and
              <term>base</term> or <term>foot</term>) is the essential epic convention of the
            hero’s trip into the underworld. A hero necessarily braves a catabasis, such as the
            descent of Orpheus into the lower world in order to charm Hades and Persephone to bring
            his wife, Eurydice back to the living world. Most catabases take place in the
            Underworld, such as the descent of Heraklês, or in Hell, such as that of Dante. However
            a catabasis can also be other dystopic areas such as what Odysseus encounters on his
            twenty year journey from Troy to Ithaca. Christ’s Harrowing of Hell appropriates this
            pagan narrative. Catabasis connects avatar with the very structure of narrative,
            codified in the templates of screenplay authoring: the protagonist becomes hero by
            leaving home, entering the special world of the narrative (that is, descends into the
            realm of death). This model is only the point of departure for our project (becoming
            image), since brand as the identity experience of electracy no longer possesses the
            coherence of narrative form.</p>
               <p>Blanchot’s appropriation of the myth typifies a device of existentialist authors of his
            period (Camus and Sisyphus, for example), of updating legends, fables, myths, as
            allegories for contemporary experience. The lesson passed along for us is the analogy
            between the writer’s relation with the work and the relation of self with avatar.
            Blanchot developed his poetics in explicit opposition to Sartre’s endorsement of prose
            and an activist engagement with political polemics. Blanchot takes <quote rend="inline" source="#blanchot1981">the other slope of language,</quote> that of poetry, with important implications for
            EmerAgency consulting. Poetry is <soCalled>useless</soCalled> in instrumental
            terms. Our purpose, rather, is to bring into ontology the disposition, attitude, virtue
            (desire) of the subject, in order to open a new front in the struggle for survival.
            Blanchot’s lesson is that the <quote rend="inline" source="#blanchot1981">entry into language</quote> by a
            speaking being is a kind of avatar descent.</p>
               <p>Blanchot was one of the first, and remains one of the most perceptive, French readers
            of Heidegger. He took up Heidegger’s project to introduce a new ontology, doing for the
            poetic slope of language what the Classical Greeks did for the propositional slope.
            Heidegger’s etymological reading of the Greek word for truth (<term>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">aletheia</foreign>
                  </term>), made explicit the limits of the Greek
            achievement. <term>Truth</term> is an uncovering, in a figure-ground relationship. The
            Greeks focused on the figure, which they ontologized, and forgot about the ground, the
            act of disclosure itself. A related point, important for distinguishing this ontology
            from the direction taken by modern science, is that the Greeks were concerned with what
            showed itself of its own accord, what attracted attention through the beauty of its
            form. Heidegger shifted attention to the ground that withdraws in order to disclose, and
            demonstrated that art with its circumspective devices of indirect intimation offered the
            means for ontologizing this more reticent dimension of Real.</p>
               <p>Blanchot takes up this angle, which was continued by Derrida. The moral that Blanchot
            extracts from the story of Orpheus concerns the author’s experience of writing this
            withdrawal. The writer is descending into the void that language opens in Real, the site
            of potential that Aristotle called <term>dunamis</term> and Deleuze the virtual.
            Eurydice is the object of desire, indicating that Eros and Thanatos are involved, life,
            human sexuality, the unconscious. Foucault’s reading of what Blanchot attempted has
            become definitive, when he named this void the <quote rend="inline" source="#blanchot1981">outside.</quote>
            Many other modern writers explored the Orpheus theme, in order to evoke the experience
            of creativity in which one’s personal identity is subordinated or extinguished, replaced
            by what is more than and beyond the limits of conscious thought, identity,
            understanding. Blanchot referred to this stance in language as <quote rend="inline" source="#blanchot1981">the
              neutral,</quote> beyond individual identity, in which the subject receives from world,
            from the outside (such is the experience of avatar). Roland Barthes was teaching a
            seminar on the Neutral at the time of the accident that killed him, the notes from which
            are now published. These <soCalled>accidents</soCalled> index the General Accident
            against which flash reason operates. It is worth noting in the context that Kafka (one
            of Blanchot’s favorite exemplars of writing) was a lawyer for the Worker’s Accident
            Insurance Company.</p>
               <p>An instruction of this analogy is that avatar as the enunciation of flash reason
            performs an entry into image, and must be designed according to this conative or
            receptive stance. Avatar is not mimetic of one’s ego, but a probe beyond one’s ownness,
            as a relationship with community. Deleuze and Guattari’s <term>rhizome</term> is much
            invoked in association with the Internet. Our use of the figure follows their example of
            rhizome as a symbiotic relationship between two separate domains brought into mutually
            beneficial alliance. It is significant that one of their primary examples of rhizome
            (the wasp and orchid, or bee and flower) was also the chief guiding image for students
            in manuscript culture, who were advised to compose texts the way bees made honey: by
            frequenting the best flowers of rhetoric, to retrieve and store their essence, with
            which to create honey in the hive. Here is another analogy for the avatar relationship:
            player to avatar is as artist to work. Analogy depends upon the familiarity of its
            ratio. To understand your relationship with avatar, you are offered a comparison with
            authoring, or with art making in general. Blanchot’s allegory specifies the relevant
            part of the analogy: player with avatar in an Internet dromosphere is like Orpheus with
            Eurydice in Hades. Such is the counsel provided by our traditions and our artists, said
            to be <emph>the antennae of the race</emph>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Abrams 1971" xml:id="abrams1971" key="abrams1971">Abrams, M. H. <title rend="italic">Natural
            Supernaturalism: Tradition and Revolution in Romantic Literature</title>, New York:
          Norton, 1971.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="agamben2007" label="Agamben 2007" key="agamben2007">Agamben, Giorgio. <title rend="italic">Infancy and History: On the Destruction of Experience</title>, New York: Verso,
          2007.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Arendt 1978" xml:id="arendt1978" key="arendt1978">Arendt, Hannah. <title rend="italic">The Life
            of the Mind. One: Thinking; Two: Willing</title>, New York: Harvest, 1978.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="blanchot1981" label="Blanchot 1981" key="blanchot1981">Blanchot, Maurice. <title rend="italic">The Space of Literature</title>, Trans. Ann Smock, Lincoln: University of Nebraska,
          1981.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Britt 2008" xml:id="britt2008" key="britt2008">Britt, Aaron. <title rend="quotes">Avatar,</title> in <title rend="italic">New York Times Magazine</title>, Aug. 8, 2008,
          online at <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/10/magazine/10wwln-guest-t.html?_r=1">http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/10/magazine/10wwln-guest-t.html?_r=1</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="detienne1978" label="Detienne &amp; Vernant 1978" key="detienne1978">Detienne, Marcel, and
          Jean-Pierre Vernant. <title rend="italic">Cunning Intelligence in Greek Culture and
            Society</title>, Trans. Janet Lloyd, Chicago: University of Chicago, 1978.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Huizinga 1950" xml:id="huizinga1950" key="huizinga1950">Huizinga, Johan, <title rend="italic">Homo
            Ludens: A Study of the Play Element in Culture</title>, Boston: Beacon Press, 1950.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1992" label="McLuhan &amp; McLuhan 1992" key="mcluhan1992">McLuhan, Marshall, and
          Eric McLuhan. <title rend="italic">Laws of Media: The New Science</title>, Toronto:
          University of Toronto, 1992.</bibl>
        
            <bibl xml:id="ovid1999" label="Ovid 1999" key="ovid1999">Ovid, cited in <title rend="italic">Classical Mythology</title>, Sixth Edition, Eds. Mark P. O. Morford and Robert J. Lenardon, New York: Oxford University Press 1999.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Pound 1996" xml:id="pound1996" key="pound1996">Pound, Ezra. <title rend="italic">The Cantos of
            Ezra Pound</title>, New York: New Directions, 1996.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="virilio1997" label="Virilio 1997" key="virilio1997">Virilio, Paul. <title rend="italic">Open
        Sky</title>, Trans. Julie Rose, New York: Verso, 1997.</bibl>
        
            <bibl label="Virilio 1999" xml:id="virilio1999" key="virilio1999">Virilio, Paul. <title rend="italic">Politics of the Very Worst</title>, Trans. Michael Cavaliere, New York: Semiotext(e), 1999.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Virilio 2003" xml:id="virilio2003" key="virilio2003">Virilio, Paul. <title rend="italic">Unknown
            Quantity</title>, New York: Thames &amp; Hudson, 2003.</bibl>

         </listBibl>

      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>