<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Playing with Chance: On Random Generation in Playable Media
                    and Electronic Literature</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Robert <dhq:family>Schoenbeck</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of California, Irvine</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>rschoenb@uci.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Rob Schoenbeck received a PhD in March 2012 from the English Department
                            at the University of California, Irvine, and as of 2013 works as a
                            Senior Learning Skills Counselor, amateur data analyst, web designer,
                            and freelance writer/editor. His dissertation project investigated how
                            algorithmic and human modes of understanding can’t be easily
                            disentangled, and that what we refer to as “computational procedure” in
                            digital media studies — and the arts more generally — reflects less the
                            significance of the thing itself than a particular set of human
                            anxieties and motivations surrounding that thing.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000165</idno>
                <idno type="volume">007</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2013-12-19">19 December 2013</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2013-10-12" who="MCC">Encoded article,</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Randomly generated content poses problems for theories of digital art: such
                    content is resistant to structural theories, which can only provide templates,
                    and one cannot assume a shared text for close analysis. Instead of reaching
                    fixed endings, such works also tend to be of indefinite length or at least
                    suggest indefinite possible combinations. I argue that the impact of such works
                    can instead be found in how one attempts to work through their underlying
                    grammar, based on limits in the algorithms that generate the content — not those
                    limits themselves, but how their outlines come to be known. Repetitively
                    iterating through these works simultaneously upholds the chance nature of the
                    epiphenomenal occurrences while also illustrating the sameness of the underlying
                    algorithm over time, creating a future-oriented interpretive arc. I examine two
                    works that play off of this technique in different ways: Nick Montfort’s Taroko
                    Gorge, a poetry generator which uses random generation to distill the essence of
                    its object’s possibility, and the action role-playing game Torchlight, which
                    attempts to elevate chance beyond a mere gameplay mechanic and toward an
                    ethic.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Engaging random variation in digital art</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Playing with Chance: On Random Generation in Playable Media and Electronic
                    Literature</head>
                <div>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="./resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <head>I. </head>
                    <p>The standard line on the conceptual status of the aleatory in the world of
                        electronic literature is strikingly demonstrated by Daniel C. Howe and Bebe
                        Molina’s <title rend="italic">Roulette</title> (shown above), which makes
                        the construction of poetic language into a game of chance marked by an acute
                        formal self-awareness. The work consists of three identical white wireframe
                        cubes slowly spinning in space, with a randomly created prose poem down
                        below. Inside each of the large wireframe cubes is a swarm of small,
                        colorful, and solid cubes, spinning and ricocheting about like so many
                        lottery balls, each with a single word printed on all their faces. The
                        player of this game may click on one of these tiny cubes in order to expand
                        its size to fill the wireframe, at which point the word written on it
                        finally becomes legible, and a set phrase containing this word (which is
                        highlighted in red) appears in the poem below. The position of the phrase is
                        tied to the order of the wireframe cubes in which the selected words appear,
                        and they often run across each other grammatically, creating a series of
                        moving parts that may recast earlier iterations in a new light depending on
                        how they fit together. For example, the words <q>a,</q>
                        <q>coat,</q> and <q>clouds</q> may produce the following poem: <quote
                            rend="block" source="#undocumented">Beneath a thought, disfigured, a shadow takes a
                            seat, removes the coat from its back; one sleeve inverted and left in a
                            drawer, clouds shift into new phrases; how they move into an ear, little
                            white coffins.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Whereas changing the first two words to <q>light</q> and <q>meter</q> creates
                        the following:<quote rend="block" source="#undocumented">Light, as a word, refracts
                            into misunderstanding, following shadows on the concrete, a thought
                            wavers without meter &amp; clouds shift into new phrases; how they move
                            into an ear, little white coffins.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The self-referential themes here are typical of the work, as well as the
                        genre of generative poetry to which it belongs — the focus on language, the
                        talk of new phrases and combinations, movement in and out of storage,
                        refraction and change. What is unique about <title rend="italic">Roulette
                        </title>is the way in which it aesthetically foregrounds the functions of
                        randomization and selection, which similar works tend to hide in the name of
                        some inscrutable combinatorial demiurge that underlies the symbolic
                        universe, linguistic and otherwise. The ‘Powerball’ motif of the wireframe
                        cubes and the bold red hue of the chosen words in the output text make the
                        roles of both uncontrollable chance and ludic choice readily apparent. At
                        the same time, the output text of <title rend="italic">Roulette </title>is
                        highly fluid, whereas other combinatorial and generative texts tend to be
                        segmented in ways that tend to sketch the outline of the underlying
                        algorithms that create them. In this way, <title rend="italic"
                            >Roulette</title> carnivalizes the ludic mechanics of chance, dressing
                        it up in the thrill and cheap commercialism of the lottery, while still
                        maintaining a strong investment in traditional poetic expressiveness. </p>
                    <p>In their own way, such works create a permanent now, a store of possible
                        variations that re-present themselves over and over through the workings of
                        their core procedures, indifferent to traditional narrative progression but
                        prone to altering and re-telling a story. In short, they present themselves
                        as configurations. To borrow from Stephane Mallarmé in <title rend="italic"
                            >One Toss of the Dice never will abolish Chance</title>, <q>Nothing….will have taken place…but the
                            place…except perhaps….a constellation.</q> If there is something
                        like a narrative element at all in works like <title rend="italic"
                            >Roulette</title>, it occurs outside the boundaries of the object proper
                        and becomes intertwined with the process of coming to understand how it
                        functions and what the meaning of those functions are, a process that occurs
                        somewhere between the user of a digital text and that text itself. This
                        requires an interpretive position oriented toward the future, one which
                        projects and then tests patterns — a struggle with faint outlines of meaning
                        that is like coming to know an alien grammar. The place of chance in this
                        investigation is key, as it supplies both the unpredictability and the
                        underlying algorithmic coherence that structure this experience.</p>
                    <p>Though complexity theory has a robust account of variation and randomness
                        that has occasionally made inroads into literary studies<note>See, for
                            example, N. Katherine Hayles' <title rend="italic">Chaos
                            Bound</title>.</note>, randomness is rarely broached in digital media
                        studies as a phenomenon in itself. Where it is considered, it is usually in
                        the context of branching possibilities for interaction created by a digital
                        artwork’s underlying rule set, programmed in its code, where the rule set
                        (and the computational procedures it entails) provides an explanation of the
                        experience of the object [c.f. <ptr target="#raley2006"/>, ,<ptr
                            target="#marino2006"/>, <ptr target="#bogost2007"/>, <ptr
                            target="#hayles2008"/>, <ptr target="#wardrip2009"/>]. This is consonant
                        with earlier approaches that subsumed expressions of variation and play in
                        digital literature under general categories [e.g., <ptr
                            target="#aarseth1997"/>], so that they could be treated as if they were
                        stable (as opposed to contingent) for the purposes of criticism. In essence,
                        this move attempts to stay the disorder of variation by setting limits,
                        identifying rules that govern what would otherwise appear to be
                        undifferentiated output or response in playable media including video games,
                        hypertext fiction, and other forms of interactive digital art. This approach
                        largely does not view the act of discovering or imagining such underlying
                        rules — part of the reader’s inferential process as he or she tries to cope
                        with a text that behaves in a seemingly unpredictable fashion — as an end in
                        itself; instead, it focuses on the rhetorical and structural implications of
                        a work’s rules, taking them as a starting point. To an extent, this is at
                        odds with earlier methods that sought first to capture the experience of
                        playable media, to identify key moments and themes through focusing on the
                        reader’s cognitive or affective experience of the work <ptr
                            target="#douglas2004"/>, and then address the work’s rules or underlying
                        structures of play as subsidiary to this, if at all. </p>
                    <p>If one were to compare two approaches at play here — at the risk of
                        oversimplifying, let’s call the first one the procedural method and the
                        second one the experiential method — one can see two different sets of
                        questions at work: the procedural method asks, <q>Why is the game played
                            with these particular rules, and what do those rules mean for play?</q>
                        whereas the experiential method asks, <q>How does a game typically go, and
                            what is the meaning of this particular result (or set of results)?</q>
                        The first aspires to view the object at a remove from experience, and thus
                        formalizes that experience in a way, while the second is more richly
                        detailed and yet more limited in its explanatory power, though it may
                        nevertheless attempt to universalize from its findings. As general
                        methodologies, however, these two aren’t equally useful for all kinds of
                        digital objects; I would emphasize that while it is true that processes and
                        experience both play an important role in playable media, they may prove to
                        be inadequate lenses by themselves where we encounter works that emphasize
                        chance operations above all else. In these cases, focusing on procedure
                        simply takes us back to the fact of variance, presenting us with a range of
                        possibilities without being able to adequately account for why it would be
                        interesting to experience them as variations of a pre-coded set of rules. On
                        the other hand, focusing on the experience of random variation gives us a
                        disconnected series of results or a narrative portrait of the typical user
                        experience that seems too personalized to account for the work’s plentitude. </p>
                    <p>To engage random variation in digital art requires a combined approach, one
                        that acknowledges the importance of procedure in giving shape to the
                        randomness while also treating the experience of the work as a prospective
                        act of discovery in which that underlying procedural shape gradually comes
                        into view through repetition and feedback. In this respect, we might
                        consider the procedural part of randomization like the grammar of a strange
                        language and the actual program output as expressions of that language.
                        Coming to understand the language, then, is a function of inferring that
                        grammar through the interpretation of its individual expressions — a kind of
                        procedural hermeneutics. By contrast, criticism that emphasizes the
                        importance of rules in governing the meaning of digital art tends to leave
                        out the fact that discovering the rules, either through inference or the
                        assistance of tools, is actually often part of a work itself, and to start
                        from the rules is in some cases to proceed backward,<note> There are, of
                            course, notable exceptions to this. In the Whitney Artport’s online
                                <q>CODeDOC</q> exhibit (CODeDOC), the code of the digital art
                            projects is presented before viewers actually see the exhibit in action.
                            In such cases, however, the foregrounding of the code is usually a
                            rhetorical device rather than an explicit roadmap: that is, it is a way
                            of foregrounding the technique involved in the creation of the project
                            rather than an attempt to explain its output. As the curator of the
                            CODeDOC exhibit, Christiane Paul, puts it, the code can be considered as
                            an artistic <q>signature,</q> in which one may find expression of
                            authorial identity or craft.</note> taking an already complete knowledge
                        of them for granted and analyzing them as formal restraints on play. There
                        is explanatory power in this approach, but there is also a remainder that it
                        necessarily can’t approach because of its temporal orientation.</p>
                    <p>This is because digital art has a tendency to live in the present,
                        particularly in the performative mode. Though the presentism of digital art
                        may not be as strong as that of, say, live television <ptr
                            target="#chun2008" loc="153"/>, there is an essential difference in
                        character between the two formats: the latter is loaded with the social
                        significance of an event, a mediation of a singularity, whereas the former
                        promises to be repeatable, equivalent. Nevertheless, despite their
                        iterability, generative algorithms in digital art can produce singularity on
                        par with the event: an ephemeral object that is subject to viewing, passing
                        into memory briefly before disappearing. Unlike the live TV example,
                        iterability in digital art promises that something of the original
                        experience will be recoverable, if not in the exact same expressive form; on
                        the other hand, we can’t, as individuals, demand on a whim that there be
                        another presidential debate. (An investigation into the ways in which modern
                        presidential debates function algorithmically would be interesting
                        nonetheless — input a question from a category, get a predictable easily
                        formalized response.) </p>
                    <p>But there are also live performances of digital art, of course, and the ways
                        in which they can be recorded and preserved highlight the perils of
                        delimiting human and machine participation where generative algorithms are
                        involved. One might be tempted to make the assumption that an archived
                        recording of a live digital art performance is equivalent to <q>previously
                            recorded</q> live TV reruns, but complications in the mechanics of
                        performance and redistribution create emergent problematics unknown to the
                        world of cable. Generative algorithms are central to this distinction: by
                        removing the viewer from interaction with or observation of generative
                        processes, the line between human and machine action becomes blurred in
                        reproduction. This effect is prominent in Bjørn Magnhildøen’s <title
                            rend="italic">Plaintext Performance, </title>which is <q>a live writing performance over the net
                            combining 1) keyboard writing, 2) machinated, algorithmic writing, and
                            3) feeds from the processes surrounding the writing (like system
                            monitoring, net connection monitoring, ftp log, etc.).</q> However,
                        what is presented under this name in the <title rend="italic">Electronic
                            Literature Collection Volume 2 </title>is a <q>static version</q> of the
                        performance: namely, a dumped record of the performance’s plain-text output,
                        combined into a single, unadorned block of text that is automatically
                        scrolled along an HTML web page using simple JavaScript code. This code
                        prevents the work from being <q>static</q> in the technical sense, and it is
                        the author’s concession to the live-ness of the original. The JavaScript
                        even randomizes the page scrolling rate and entry point, so that it imitates
                        the stops, stutters, and lurches endemic to any natural live performance —
                        but ultimately these gyrations are too regular and too arbitrary to
                        convincingly stand in for that performance.</p>
                    <p>This iteration of <title rend="italic">Plaintext Performance </title>(see
                        screenshot below) is in this way a document rather than a
                            <q>performance,</q> equal to a first-person narrative told by a
                        projection screen at the event. While it is rather easy to tell where <q>feeds from the processes surrounding the
                            writing</q> emerge in Magnhildøen’s work — this seems to refer to,
                        for example, a simple and cleanly formatted table of running processes and
                        their current actions, recurring at intervals — it is rather difficult to
                        separate out the other two key elements, <q>keyboard writing</q> and
                            <q>machinated, algorithmic writing,</q> in retrospect. There are
                        scattered quotes and symbols that seem too undisciplined to have come from a
                        machine, but one can never be sure; there are quotes, names, or fragmented
                        sentences that could have been generated on the spot, or not; and there are
                        bits of ASCII art that seem far too complex to have been generated on the
                        fly, but small errors and the broad range of human performative capability
                        lead one to uncertainty. It would be much easier to separate the
                        machine-generated and the human-generated content during the performance
                        itself, as the speed at which the generated versus the typed characters
                        appeared would be a major giveaway; however, since the record is stored in a
                        static, plain-text file, one is not given this observational luxury.</p>
                    <p>Therein lies the significance of digital art’s unique temporality: by
                        removing real-time computation from the equation and turning to the static
                        form of the document, one creates legibility, allowing the past to be
                        reproduced (or at least re-written), but in doing so one diminishes the
                        performative and theatrical aspects of the art. Inasmuch as generative
                        algorithms in digital art that isn’t <q>live</q> are nonetheless
                        performative in some way — they are, after all, designed to be run as much
                        as read — this can’t help but create a remainder that slips out of the range
                        of a totalizing critical gaze. A literary studies approach that considers
                        the text a self-contained object will necessarily experience much anxiety
                        before the task of analyzing such a work.</p>
                    <p> To confront performative, generative digital art is to confront an art that
                        appears to revel in the erasure or distortion of its own record. This seems
                        to go against foundational principles of humanistic study; as Alan Liu has
                        it, a significant societal danger of the digital present is the permanent
                            <q>now</q> that is enforced upon us by the endless creative destruction
                        of our current cultural moment, with its attendant erasure of history and
                        stifling of careful analysis, and resistance is to be achieved by
                        confronting that temporality through an ethical unearthing of its historical
                        failures <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="7–8"/>. In the past, attempts to
                        understand the formal qualities of a work of digital art through experience,
                        without reference to coded processes, have typically relied on narrative or
                        sensory metaphors<note> There are several readings of interactive fiction or
                            hypertext fiction — in particular, Michael Joyce’s <title rend="italic"
                                >Afternoon: A Story</title> — that compare such works to wandering
                            through a castle, maze, or other spatial construct (Douglas; Montfort,
                                <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages</title>); more recently,
                            N. Katherine Hayles compared the experience of Joyce’s <title
                                rend="italic">Twelve Blue</title> to the rhythm of the tides,
                            lovemaking, and a sheet of music (63-4).</note> to perform explanatory
                        work, and this is consonant with Marie-Laure Ryan’s suggestion that play
                        actions (e.g., actions undertaken in a video game) form a story when taken
                        together <ptr target="#ryan2006"/>. However, this method too has a hard time
                        accounting for chance operations and lyrical engagement: the story of chance
                        operations is the story of a dice roll told over and over again, and lyrical
                        transport has a similarly flat narrative arc. Branching possibilities are
                        resolved into the reader’s affective and cognitive states of exploration,
                        which, while providing a phenomenological richness, cannot address that
                        which of necessity can’t be narrated — namely, mutually exclusive
                        possibilities bound into the rule system of a digital artwork. The more a
                        digital artwork focuses on randomly generated content, the more it focuses
                        on constructing an intricate system that will indefinitely produce content
                        of a format that can be dictated algorithmically, and as such, the algorithm
                        is something that is both subject to experience and outside of it. Each
                        expression will have different contours of meaning while nonetheless
                        stemming from the same source, the outlines of which will be visible in
                        those expressions. Engaging with such a work is much like an engagement with
                        an unknown form, working in reverse toward a concept of it that isn’t some
                        kind of Platonic universal, but a particular and highly crafted artistic
                        expression.</p>
                    <p>The difficulty that generative art poses lies in the limitations of personal
                        narrative experience for analysis and also the sketchy, overly formalized
                        and abstracted outlines of procedural grammar that don't seem to do justice
                        to any particular moment of such art. One is put in the position of trying
                        to recover seemingly singular moments of the artwork into some broader
                        scheme, because they might otherwise not appear again in the same
                        configuration; this requires constantly memorializing the present with an
                        eye to the future, making sure that the creative 'destruction' of the
                        present maintains both a past and an afterlife free from structural
                        abstraction. This tension is evident not just in criticism's understanding
                        of art but also in the practice of digital artists who must juggle the
                        formal with the concrete. In this way, Nick Montfort's poetry generator
                            <title rend="italic">Taroko Gorge, </title>which includes clear
                        structural elements resulting from procedure as well as an emergent
                        aesthetic features irreducible to that structure, shows the limits of both
                        experiential and procedural approaches in understanding such works. Montfort
                        is known as a consummate craftsman of poetry generation — Mark Marino
                        identifies his <title rend="italic">ppg256</title> series of generators as
                        representing the <q>poetry of techneculture,</q> a culture focused as much
                        on coding technique and command lines as creating functional programs <ptr
                            target="#marino2010"/>. The way Montfort's work has been both presented
                        and received has traditionally borne this out: the <title rend="italic"
                            >ppg256</title> series, which I shall address in turn later, has been
                        discussed more for its remarkably compact code than for the poetry it
                        produces. His later work with Stephanie Strickland, <title rend="italic">Sea
                            and Spar Between, </title>makes the claim that its <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#montfort2010">resulting code tells the story [of the poetry
                            generator] in detail,</quote> identifying the structure of its generated
                        poetry by the code functions used to create it: <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#montfort2010">A first line uses either shortLine(),
                            oneNounLine(), or compoundCourseLine(). A second line uses either
                            riseAndGoLine(), butLine(), exclaimLine(), or nailedLine()</quote>
                        <ptr target="#montfort2010"/></cit>. Even the source code of <title rend="italic"
                            >Taroko Gorge</title> itself segments its output by phrases indicating
                        height or depth, transitive or intransitive verbs, imperatives, and
                        adjectives into lines of somewhat predictable length, and the elegance of
                        the program resulted in several authors turning out a variety of
                            <q>remixes</q> using the original code and line structure. All this
                        would seem to indicate that for Montfort's oeuvre, code and procedure are
                        king.</p>
                    <p>However, when Montfort provided a reading of <title rend="italic">Taroko
                            Gorge </title>at the 2009 Digital Arts and Culture conference, rather
                        than a presentation of its code, it was clear that its distinctive poetic
                        rhythm is as constitutive of the audience’s experience as the program's
                        built-in grammar and lineation. A series of short syllables punctuated by
                        longer, adjective-laced lines, as well as regular variations in both,
                        constitutes a second layer of poetic structuration above that called for in
                        the program code: <quote rend="block" source="#montfort2009b">
                            <p>Stone paces the shape.</p>
                            <p>Veins hum.</p>
                            <p>Brows rest.</p>
                            <p>Forest roams the vein.</p>
                            <p> run the fine cool dim — </p>
                            <p>Mist frames the flows.</p>
                            <p>Flows linger.</p>
                            <p>Shape roams the rippling.</p>
                            <p> run the fine sinuous clear — </p>
                            <ptr target="#montfort2009b"/>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The lengthening and truncating lines as they are read, followed by the lines
                        with their dashes trailing off at the end, align with a structure in the
                        source code that takes the form of a hiking sequence through the titular
                        gorge: the output’s lines are organized into three segmented functions
                        labeled <q>path,</q>
                        <q>site,</q> and <q>cave,</q> a winding ascent and descent of a journey that
                        tracks the rise and fall of the poetic cadence. In this way, the code makes
                        clear the setting of the poem — the structuring concepts, grammar, and
                        possible vocabulary used — while the reading of it makes clear the pacing
                        and character of the journey through that setting.</p>
                    <p>The methodological challenge of working toward such an outline is essentially
                        that it requires a sort of divination, connecting the output of a work with
                        an imagined version of its source code (or, if available, the actual code —
                        though in either case, the code is only a set of instructions for the
                        program that requires a non-trivial effort to connect to the actual
                        experience of its operation). Whether or not one has the rules of such a
                        work beforehand, it requires a prospective hermeneutic orientation to
                        actually be able to connect program output with the expressive potential of
                        those rules — that is to say, the difference between the rules as written
                        and the in-practice experience of them as expressions conforming to a
                        pattern. In that respect, then, it makes sense to treat the procedural
                        elements of these works as always in development, not absolute. To explain
                        this distinction, it will be useful to turn to Ernst Bloch’s philosophical
                        discontent with the limitations of ontology. Bloch thought that Western
                        philosophy relied too much on a static view of existence that was emblemized
                        by a focus on Being with a capital B — that is, on objects having a
                        definite, contained, and stable existence, not subject to growth or
                        reinterpretation — and he instead stressed the importance of
                            <q>becoming,</q> or the development of things in the world in a fashion
                        that isn’t necessarily teleological but nevertheless oriented toward the
                        outlines of a future state. He associated such a future-oriented style of
                        thinking with hope, namely <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bloch1986"
                            >hope…not taken <title rend="italic">only as emotion</title>, as the
                            opposite of fear (because fear too can of course anticipate), but <title
                                rend="italic">more essentially as a directing act of a cognitive
                                kind</title>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr target="#bloch1986" loc="12"/></cit>. This forward-reasoning style of thought
                        is also necessary to the act of inferring the formal rules of digital art
                        objects mentioned above: both employ a hermeneutic that categorizes
                        phenomena as signs of larger controlling forces that we don’t yet
                        understand, whether those forces be unknown computational processes or the
                        horizon of the future.</p>
                    <p>While that may seem intuitive on one level, the approach is more involved
                        when applied to works containing a vast array of combinatorial
                        possibilities. In those instances, interpretation regarding the procedures
                        that make up the work is essential to say anything at all, since many of
                        them privilege the semantic excess and resistance to meaning that are
                        hallmarks of randomization in art. The history of such procedures long
                        predates digital art, and critics most often ascribe their origin to the
                        language generation techniques of twentieth century writers using the
                            <q>cut-up</q> method pioneered by the Dadaists <ptr
                            target="#rettberg2008"/>, <ptr target="#wardrip2009" loc="8–9"/>, <ptr
                            target="#montfort2009a"/>, which involved cutting material from
                        newspapers and magazines and selecting from them at random to create a form
                        of word collage art. Another well-known reference point is the Oulipo group,
                        a gathering of artists and mathematicians that designed constraints and
                        formulae for creating literature (e.g., replacing each noun in a text with a
                        noun seven entries ahead in a dictionary, writing that excludes certain
                        letters, etc.). Beginning with Espen Aarseth’s oft-cited comparison between
                        Oulipian constraints and digital fiction in <title rend="italic"
                            >Cybertext</title>, such formal operations on language have been likened
                        to computational processes, since they structure an output stream based on
                        formulae <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="25"/>, <ptr target="#seaman2001"
                            loc="426"/>, <ptr target="#montfort2009a"/>; see also <ptr
                            target="#wardrip2009" loc="160"/>, and <ptr target="#bogost2006"
                            loc="51"/>. While cut-ups and Oulipian constraints are sometimes lumped
                        together under labels of combinatorial or formal processing, their
                        implications diverge. On the one hand, cut-ups use random selection as a
                        means to incorporate chance into art; on the other, the Oulipo’s constraints
                        and formulae have been presented as <q>anti-chance</q> from the beginning.
                        Though Oulipian constraints such as those mentioned above are <q>chance</q>
                        to the extent that they are arbitrary, what they produce has a syntactic
                        regularity that can be traced back to the originating formula <ptr
                            target="#james2009" loc="109, 121"/>]. In fact, the Oulipo had presented
                        themselves as maker of literary formulae rather than literature itself <ptr
                            target="#roubaud2005" loc="38–9"/>, cementing their focus on process
                        rather than the randomness of inspiration. </p>
                    <p>The gulf between <q>chance</q> and <q>anti-chance</q> may not be as wide as
                        it may seem when it comes to procedure, however. The cut-up method is, after
                        all, a predictable method with defined materials, and to be clear,
                            <q>anti-chance</q> does not mean a total absence of variation, a rule
                        that always generates the same result, but rather means the appearance of
                        formal consistency. This is summed up well by a distinction Marjorie Perloff
                        makes between rules and constraints in writing poetry: rules create definite
                        expectations for an audience that an author will follow, as in poetic
                        measure, whereas constraints are "primarily <title rend="italic"
                            >generative</title>, the constraint determining, not what is already
                        fixed as a property of the text, but<emph> how</emph> the writer will
                        proceed with his composition <ptr target="#perloff1991" loc="139"/>.
                            <q>Anti-chance</q> in this sense may then be redefined according to the
                        legibility of such a constraint within a composition.</p>
                    <p>The more a work is dominated by unseen chance operations, then the more a
                        simply procedural or experiential understanding of digital media objects
                        will be inadequate to understanding the significance of those objects. In
                        such situations, we are perhaps better served by emphasizing the act of
                        working through, that is, how one comes to know the rules (and the possible
                        results) in the first place. It is here that Bloch’s philosophy proves most
                        useful: according to Bloch, we understand the future by understanding the
                        present, by looking for signs of what is to come in many different places at
                        once. The act of coming to know the formal processes of a work of digital
                        art involves a similar method of interpretation: by experiencing multiple
                        chance iterations in a row, we begin to forecast what will come in the next
                        iteration using what we’ve already seen. The one important distinction is
                        that whereas Bloch’s world is in a constant state of becoming, the code that
                        governs most digital art objects remains the same. However, this doesn’t
                        mean that the subjective process of inferring the rules created by the code
                        is always the same, as the code is at the source of a work that is then
                        subject to a process of understanding, interpretation, and interaction that
                        is equally a part of digital art. To elaborate, I will turn now to a kind of
                        digital art that relies heavily on this balance between constraint and
                        chance: text generators, or computer programs that are able to combine text
                        to produce stories, poems, and so forth.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>II.</head>
                    <p>Text generating programs in the digital sphere frequently fall into one of
                        three categories: the genre parody, the mash-up, or the purely generative.
                        Parodies, the first category in question, are among the most common, as in
                        Andrew C. Bulhak’s <title rend="italic">Postmodernism Generator</title>
                        <ptr target="#bulhak2000"/>, a satire of postmodernist theoretical styles,
                        or Nanette Wylde’s <title rend="italic">Storyland</title>
                        <ptr target="#wylde2004"/>, a work that generates terse and absurd fairy
                        tales. Such works typically ape the language and tropes of a target object
                        and create a nonsensical or ridiculous output using recognizable genre
                        conventions. Secondly, a significant body of non-parodic text generating
                        programs borrows from the remix or mash-up, creating a pre-defined body of
                        text — either the author’s original work or borrowed from other sources —
                        and then de-combining and re-combining the text through various algorithms
                        and user interactions. These text mash-ups typically locate themselves
                        somewhere between the cut-up technique <ptr target="#geniwate2008"/>, <ptr
                            target="#andrews2004"/>, <ptr target="#rettberg2008"/> and the
                        procedural poetics of the Oulipo <ptr target="#geniwate2008"/>, <ptr
                            target="#seaman2001"/>, in that they involve procedural randomness in
                        selecting random text but nonetheless have highly structured patterns
                        regulating them in the source code. Such an approach may also be associated
                        more broadly with what Lev Manovich calls the <q>remix culture</q> of new
                        media: the tendency to <quote rend="inline" source="#manovich2004">place
                            together old and new in various combinations</quote> as a reflection of
                        growing hybridization in networked society <ptr target="#manovich2004"/>. A
                        third kind of text generation is more oblique, not relying on direct user
                        manipulation or recognizable styles or source text, and instead seeming to
                        generate text <title rend="italic">ex nihilo </title>based on original
                        algorithms. Works of this type engender a sense of boundlessness, as they
                        present seemingly inexhaustible source of text which shifts with each new
                        iteration and which isn’t as functionally targeted as, say, the parodic
                        styles mentioned above. As with other text generating programs, they are
                        meant to be run again and again: multiple runs reinforce (as well as verify)
                        their raison d’être, which is the creation of unique combinations with each
                        stroke. At the same time, their reiteration reinforces the fact that they
                        are not actually inexhaustible, as patterns will emerge from the grammar
                        employed by the source code.</p>
                    <p>As with much text generation, however, the unlimited, variable output is
                        nonetheless beholden to a curious form of stasis. Montfort recognizes that
                        programmed randomness isn’t absolute, and is instead more accurately a
                            <q>pseudorandom</q> process that <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#montfort2009a">chooses an element from a distribution</quote>
                        <ptr target="#montfort2009a"/></cit>. That is to say, randomly generated texts are
                        never generated entirely at <q>random,</q> but conform to a pre-coded limit
                        that is fleshed out by the computerized selection of elements from a data
                        set; <q>randomness</q> is therefore the approximation of chaos that the text
                        wants to own but can never properly have, and which it can only approach,
                        ironically enough, through the repetition of the same generative procedure
                        over and over. Each iteration is a ritual step in the establishment and
                        verification of the random elements as random, while at the same time making
                        the limitations on that randomness all the more apparent as patterns begin
                        to emerge. The meaning is in the repetition; this is part of a broader
                        phenomenon in digital art noted by David Ciccoricco, one that valorizes
                        looping structures at every level, from recursion in underlying computer
                        code to repeating navigation patterns in hypertext fiction <ptr
                            target="#ciccoricco2007" loc="22–3"/>. Tellingly, Ciccoricco frames this
                        phenomenon as <quote rend="inline" source="#ciccoricco2007">fundamental to
                            (hyper)textual comprehension,</quote> suggesting that it interrogates
                        our very ability to understand art as such and makes rereading an essential
                        (and not merely optional) element <ptr target="#ciccoricco2007" loc="23"/>.
                        However, in the case of text generation, <q>comprehension</q> comes about
                        only by conflating the program structure with its output, much like
                        confusing a language with its grammar. It is not sufficient to use terms
                        like <q>rereading</q> to describe what happens in different iterations of
                        such works, since to <q>reread</q> is to suggest that the repeated elements
                        are visible instead of a phantasmic structural trace of the source code and
                        to suggest that the product on screen is only what matters, not the concept
                        of the generator itself. As is the case with Montfort’s work, it is only the
                        combination of the two that makes each individually possible.</p>
                    <p>This model of tracing an underlying grammar through repetition, which thereby
                        produces something emergent that is irreducible to either procedure or
                        experience alone, can even be extended to how we play certain genres of
                        video games. While poetry and text generators along the lines described
                        above typically have no significant element of user choice or interaction,
                        since all they require is to be run, and their use is typically interpretive
                        rather than goal- or task-oriented<title rend="italic">, </title>there are
                        significant similarities in the way we work through both games and random
                        text generators. First, when considering video games as an interactive
                        medium, it is useful to bear in mind Espen Aarseth's caution regarding the
                        ideological <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">rhetoric of
                            novelty, differentiation, and freedom</quote> that surrounds such media
                        and obscures their connection to older expressive forms <ptr
                            target="#aarseth1997" loc="14"/> — the possibility of <q>interaction</q>
                        with a digital object does not necessarily entail that that interaction has
                        critical significance. Second, action in video games is <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#wardrip2009">situated and improvisational,</quote> as Noah
                        Wardrip-Fruin puts it — while players may make plans for action in a game
                        world, they nonetheless face constraints based in the game design, game
                        engine, etc. that requires a form of readjustment based on a limited number
                        of available affordances <ptr target="#wardrip2009" loc="344–5"/>. In other
                        words, the genre distinction between the poetry generator and the video game
                        isn't so much the insertion of player <q>choice</q> as two different modes
                        of creating an interpretive schema about the underlying processes involved
                        in the respective object. In the case of poetry and text generators, this
                        understanding may be offered for critical commentary or (in the case of
                            <title rend="italic">Taroko Gorge</title>, for example) passed on into
                        further work or remixes, while in the case of video games, the understanding
                        can be used to gain rewards in the game or in any number of social spaces
                        attached to the game (e.g., multiplayer modes, clans or other social
                        groupings of players, etc.).<note>Some may argue that this understanding is
                            already given with poetry generators that release their source code but
                            not the case with video games, which rarely release their source code.
                            While the code for poetry generators is published far more often than
                            the code of video games, typically game enthusiasts will nevertheless
                            investigate, compile, and then publish all relevant algorithms and game
                            mechanics that would thereby be discovered anyway.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Most video games have content that is generated with some random variation
                        according to an algorithm, as in a poetry generator, though those generated
                        objects typically take the form of rewards or obstacles rather than
                        language. Nevertheless, in order to play the game successfully, a player
                        must develop a means of dealing with this variation and must develop an
                        understanding of the mechanisms behind it, and this is particularly so in
                        the case of some games that rely heavily on randomly generated rewards and
                        repetitive action. The chief example of this kind of game is the
                        sub-subgenre of action role-playing games known as <q>
                            <title rend="italic">Diablo</title> clones</q> — so named for the game
                        that serves as its blueprint — which is predicated on the idea that the
                        process of discovering randomly generated rewards can create a world of
                        permanent surprise and interest, yet be contained within fairly simple,
                        unvarying, and even minimalist gameplay.</p>
                    <p> I will examine here for a moment one recent entry in the <q>
                            <title rend="italic">Diablo </title>clone</q> genre that distills
                        several stock elements into perhaps the sharpest focus on generated content
                        that the genre has yet seen. <title rend="italic">Torchlight</title>
                        <ptr target="#runic2009"/>, much like its predecessors in the mold of <title
                            rend="italic">Rogue </title>and <title rend="italic">Diablo</title>, has
                        the player descend through the randomly-generated levels of a dungeon while
                        picking up randomly-generated loot, killing the occasional randomly-enhanced
                        foe along with the standard ones, hacking and slashing in a typically
                        frenetic but repetitive fashion. The game isn’t really about reaching an
                        endpoint; though there is a final boss to defeat, there are an indefinite
                        number of generated levels in the dungeon to descend through thereafter,
                        with ever-stronger foes and loot to match. Though the aftermath of the game
                        is essentially a superficial, mathematically extended version of what comes
                        before, the choice to do away with the expected limits brought on by
                        narrative closure is telling in that it reveals the true object of play —
                        that is, an unstinting devotion to the character’s development, which occurs
                        through slaying more enemies, upgrading skills, and getting more powerful
                        equipment. Such an incentive structure may immediately call to mind
                        massively multiplayer online role-playing games; as Tof Eklund has noted,
                        the genre draws heavily upon the Protestant work ethic, where through
                        vigorously working on developing one’s character, one will eventually
                        receive the satisfaction of being promoted (to a higher character level, to
                        a higher status within one’s guild, etc.) <ptr target="#eklund2010"/>.
                        However, it’s important to note that <title rend="italic">Torchlight
                        </title>features no online component, which makes the application of social
                        models more complicated here. This, coupled with the unending string of
                        random levels and treasure, makes it unique among its peers while making the
                        attention to endless character enhancement all the more curious due to its
                        comparative isolation, limiting the sense of competition or transferability.
                        There is an almost monastic impulse in the self-denial of grinding through
                        levels of <title rend="italic">Torchlight </title>in order to receive
                        rewards that can only be understood in an isolation that is not exactly
                        spiritual, but nonetheless personal and unlinked to any primary social
                        economy. The loot collected provides the tools with which to collect more,
                        which then can be used to help promote the growth of the player’s avatar,
                        but there is no method to trade or otherwise compete, cooperate, or even
                        interact with other players. With no other unpredictable, human forces
                        present to reshape the player’s way of doing things in a social dimension,
                        the sense of repetitiveness is concentrated. This effect is further
                        compounded by <title rend="italic">Torchlight’s</title> basic gameplay,
                        which (as with other action RPGs) is tedious in design: the main action
                        consists of clicking the same two mouse buttons at hordes of similar-looking
                        monsters, punctuated by the occasional press of an additional shortcut key
                        to use one of the limited selections of items or powers. The sole exception
                        to this is the involved system of compromises one enters into with the
                        character upgrade and inventory menus, which are loaded with stats and
                        information, presenting a stark contrast to the otherwise fairly mindless
                        action and enshrining such development as the true focus of the game. Almost
                        like a penitent sinner, the player engages in borderline self-abuse chiefly
                        for the thought that there will be redemption — or some kind of reward,
                        which may not be comprehendible outside the player’s own self-abusive logic
                        — just around the corner.</p>
                    <p>Ernst Bloch would read this sort of activity as a basic form of longing
                        obsessed with itself, an addiction, and yet it seems all too close to the
                        ways in which we read through the ludic elements of electronic literature: a
                        repetition that creates pleasurable forms resembling an invisible but
                        nonetheless palpable generative process. In the narrative mode of thinking,
                        we forestall the need to repeat a ludic sequence by putting a narrative
                        frame around it: killing this or that monster, or getting this or that piece
                        of treasure becomes the analog of passing a certain guard field in hypertext
                        fiction or experiencing a certain combination of text, a chance event that
                        can’t seem to be represented without supplying a less variable background
                        that will give it critical coherence. In this way, the player experiences
                        saving the randomly generated elements from their ontological indeterminacy
                        as mere possibilities, establishing an intelligible order that will
                        nonetheless be challenged (as in any other critical enterprise) anytime
                        anyone decides to pick up the same object one more time. The establishment
                        of such an order differs slightly from what happens in the reading of print
                        literature because of the need to explain actions and occurrences — the
                        exercise of <q>non-trivial effort,</q> in Aarseth’s well-known terms — in
                        addition to emphases and interpretations. This creates the need to imagine a
                        structure, metaphorical or otherwise, under which an action’s potential
                        outcomes can become legible <emph>as events</emph>, granting them an almost
                        physical existence while at the same time subsuming their other possible
                        random variations all under an invented equivalency. Thus all potential
                        events from one action in a ludic text cannot but be the expression of a
                        single impulse, be it process or form or something else, which can truly be
                        elevated to the status of a <title rend="italic">happening</title> instead
                        of a radically indeterminate potential.</p>
                    <p>If this tension between process and possibility is something we value as an
                        essential component in playable media, and if this is a useful contrast with
                        the linearity we associate with non-interactive media, then perhaps it is
                        this desire to retain the openness of our objects that explains our frequent
                        looks in digital studies toward the future, rather than a shallow desire for
                        something new as the common accusation has it. Random generation requires a
                        context in order to be coherent and the underlying grammar of code to give
                        it shape, even if the outlines appear only gradually. In such cases, we must
                        consider that coming to know how processes work doesn’t always explain only
                        a work’s dynamics; rather, it also tells the story of the work itself.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Aarseth 1997" xml:id="aarseth1997" key="aarseth1997">Aarseth, Espen.
                        <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>.
                    Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Andrews 2007" xml:id="andrews2004" key="andrews2004">Andrews, Jim.
                        <title rend="quotes">Stir Frys and Cut Ups</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Stir Fry Texts</title> at <ref
                        target="http://vispo.com/StirFryTexts/text.html"
                        >http://vispo.com/StirFryTexts/text.html</ref>, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bloch 1986" xml:id="bloch1986" key="bloch1986">Bloch, Ernst. <title
                        rend="italic">The Principle of Hope Vol. I.</title> Trans. Neville Plaice,
                    Stephen Plaice and Paul Knight. Oxford: Basil Blackwell Ltd, 1986.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bogost 2006" xml:id="bogost2006" key="bogost2006">Bogost, Ian. <title
                        rend="italic">Unit Operations</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bogost 2007" xml:id="bogost2007" key="bogost2007">Bogost, Ian. <title
                        rend="italic">Persuasive Games</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press,
                    2007.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bulhak 2000" xml:id="bulhak2000" key="bulhak2000">Bulhak, Andrew C.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Postmodernism Generator</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Communications from Elsewhere </title>at <ref
                        target="http://www.elsewhere.org/pomo/"
                    >http://www.elsewhere.org/pomo/</ref>, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Chun 2008" xml:id="chun2008" key="chun2008">Chun, Wendy. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Enduring Ephemeral, or the Future is a Memory.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 35 (2008): 148-71.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ciccoricco 2007" xml:id="ciccoricco2007" key="ciccoricco2007"
                    >Ciccoricco, David. <title rend="italic">Reading Network Fiction</title>.
                    Tuscaloosa, AL: University of Alabama Press, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl label="CodeDOC 2002" xml:id="codedoc2002" key="codedoc2002">
                    <title rend="quotes">CodeDOC</title> in Whitney Artport at <ref
                        target="http://artport.whitney.org/commissions/codedoc/"
                        >http://artport.whitney.org/commissions/codedoc/</ref>, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Douglas 1989" xml:id="douglas1989" key="douglas1989">Douglas, J.
                    Yellowlees. <title rend="quotes">Wandering Through the Labyrinth: Encountering
                        Interactive Fiction</title> in <title rend="italic">Computers and Coposition
                    </title>3 (1989): 93-103.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Douglas and Haradon 2004" xml:id="douglas2004" key="douglas2004"
                    >Douglas, J. Yellowlees, and Haradon, Andrew. <title rend="italic">First Person:
                        New Media as Story, Performance, and Game. </title>Ed. Pat Harrigan and Noah
                    Wardrip-Fruin. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2004. 192-206.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Eklund 2010" xml:id="eklund2010" key="eklund2010">Eklund, Tof. <title
                        rend="quotes">New <q>Computer Board Games</q>: Counter-Immersive Forms and
                        Theories of Play.</title> Futures of Digital Studies 2010 Conference.
                    University of Florida, Gainesville, FLA, 25-27 February 2010.
                    Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl label="geniwate 2008" xml:id="geniwate2008" key="geniwate2008">geniwate.
                        <title rend="italic">Generative Poetry </title>in <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Literature Collection, Volume 1</title> at <ref
                        target="http://www.eliterature.org/collection/1/works/geniwate__generf"
                        >http://www.eliterature.org/collection/1/works/geniwate__generf</ref>,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hayles 2008" xml:id="hayles2008" key="hayles2008a">Hayles, N.
                    Katherine. <title rend="italic">Electronic Literature</title>. Notre Dame,
                    Indiana: Notre Dame University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Howe and Molina 2011" xml:id="howe2011" key="howe2011b">Howe, Daniel
                    C., and Bebe Molina. <title rend="italic">Roulette</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Literature Collection Volume 2 </title>at <ref
                        target="http://collection.eliterature.org/2/works/00_howe.html"
                        >http://collection.eliterature.org/2/works/00_howe.html</ref>. Ed. Borràs,
                    Memmott et al. Electronic Literature Organization, February 2011. </bibl>
                <bibl label="James 2009" xml:id="james2009" key="james2009">James, Alison. <title
                        rend="italic">Constraining Chance: Georges Perec and the Oulipo</title>.
                    Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Liu 2004" xml:id="liu2004" key="liu2004a">Liu, Alan. <title
                        rend="italic">The Laws of Cool: Knowledge Work and the Culture of
                        Information</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Magnhildøen 2011" xml:id="magnhildoen2011" key="magnhildoen2011"
                    >Magnhildøen, Bjørn. <title rend="italic">Plaintext Performance</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Electronic Literature Collection Volume 2 </title>at <ref
                        target="http://collection.eliterature.org/2/works/magnhildoen_plaintextperformance.html"
                        >http://collection.eliterature.org/2/works/magnhildoen_plaintextperformance.html</ref>.
                    Ed. Borràs, Memmott et al. Electronic Literature Organization, February 2011. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Mallarmé 1897" xml:id="mallarme1987" key="mallarme1987">Mallarmé,
                    Stephane. <title rend="italic">One Toss of the Dice never will abolish
                        Chance</title>. Trans. Christopher Mulrooney. Ubuweb, n.d.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Manovich 2004" xml:id="manovich2004" key="manovich2004">Manovich, Lev.
                        <title rend="quotes">New Media as Remix Culture</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">NY Arts Magazine</title> at <ref
                        target="http://www.nyartsmagazine.com/">http://www.nyartsmagazine.com</ref>,
                    2004.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Marino 2006" xml:id="marino2006" key="marino2006">Marino, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">Critical Code Studies</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Book Review </title>at <ptr
                        target="http://www.electronicbookreview.com/thread/electropoetics/codology"
                    />, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Marino 2010" xml:id="marino2010" key="marino2010">Marino, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">The ppg256 Perl Primer: The Poetry of Techneculture</title> in
                        <title rend="italic">Emerging Language Practices </title>1 at <ptr
                        target="http://epc.buffalo.edu/ezines/elp/issue-1/ppg256.php"/>,
                    2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Montfort 2003" xml:id="montfort2003" key="montfort2003">Montfort, Nick.
                        <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive
                        Fiction. </title>Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Montfort 2009a" xml:id="montfort2009a" key="montfort2009c">Montfort,
                    Nick. <title rend="quotes">The ppg256 Series of Minimal Poetry
                        Generators</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2009 Digital
                        Arts and Culture Conference</title> on DVD-ROM, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Montfort 2009b" xml:id="montfort2009b" key="montfort2009d">Montfort,
                    Nick. <title rend="quotes">Taroko Gorge.</title>. <ref
                        target="http://nickm.com/poems/taroko_gorge.html"
                        >http://nickm.com/poems/taroko_gorge.html</ref>, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Montfort and Strickland 2010" xml:id="montfort2010" key="montfort2010"
                    >Montfort, Nick, and Strickland, Stephanie. <title rend="quotes">Sea and Spar
                        Between</title> in <title rend="italic">Dear Navigator </title>2 at <ptr
                        target="http://blogs.saic.edu/dearnavigator/winter2010/nick-montfort-stephanie-strickland-sea-and-spar-between/"
                    />, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Perloff 1991" xml:id="perloff1991" key="perloff1991">Perloff, Marjorie.
                        <title rend="italic">Radical Artifice</title>: <title rend="italic">Writing
                        Poetry in the Age of Media</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                    1991.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Raley 2006" xml:id="raley2006" key="raley2006">Raley, Rita. <title
                        rend="quotes">Code.surface || Code.depth</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Dichtung Digital </title>36 at <ptr
                        target="http://www.brown.edu/Research/dichtung-digital/2006/1-Raley.htm"/>,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rettberg 2008" xml:id="rettberg2008" key="rettberg2008">Rettberg,
                    Scott. <title rend="quotes">Dada Redux: Elements of Dadaist Practice in
                        Contemporary Electronic Literature</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Fibreculture </title>11 at <ref
                        target="http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue11/issue11_rettberg.html"
                        >http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue11/issue11_rettberg.html</ref>,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Roubaud 2005" xml:id="roubaud2005" key="roubaud2005">Roubaud, Jacques.
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: The Oulipo and Combinatorial Art</title>
                    in H. Matthews and A. Brotchie (eds.) <title rend="italic">Oulipo
                        Compendium</title>. North Hollywood, CA: Make Now Press, 2005. 37-44.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Runic Games 2009" xml:id="runic2009" key="runic2009">Runic Games.
                        <title rend="italic">Torchlight.</title> 2009. Video game.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ryan 2006" xml:id="ryan2006" key="ryan2006">Ryan, Marie-Laure. <title
                        rend="italic">Avatars of Story</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of
                    Minnesota Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Seaman 2001" xml:id="seaman2001" key="seaman2001">Seaman, Bill. <title
                        rend="quotes">OULIPO Vs Recombinant Poetics</title> in <title rend="italic"
                        >Leonardo </title>34.5, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wardrip-Fruin 2009" xml:id="wardrip2009" key="wardrip2009a"
                    >Wardrip-Fruin, Noah. <title rend="italic">Expressive Processing</title>.
                    Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2009. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Wylde 2004" xml:id="wylde2004" key="wylde2004">Wylde, Nanette. <title
                        rend="italic">Storyland.</title>
                    <ref target="http://slippage.net/storyland2/"
                        >http://slippage.net/storyland2/</ref>, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Xangela.net 2003" xml:id="xangela2003" key="xangela2003">
                    <title rend="italic">Random Bad Romance Novel Generator</title> at <ptr
                        target="http://xangela.net/generators/romance.html"/>, 2003.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
