<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Visualizing and Analyzing the Hollywood Screenplay with
                    ScripThreads</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Eric <dhq:family>Hoyt</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Wisconsin-Madison</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>ehoyt@wisc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Eric Hoyt is Assistant Professor of Media &amp; Cultural Studies in the
                            Department of Communication Arts at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
                            He is the author of <title rend="italic">Hollywood Vault: Film Libraries
                                before Home Video</title> (University of California Press, 2014) and
                            co-director of the Media History Digital Library (<ref
                                target="http://mediahistoryproject.org"
                                >http://mediahistoryproject.org</ref>). He designed, developed, and
                            produced the MHDL’s search and visualization platform, Lantern (<ref
                                target="http://lantern.mediahist.org"
                                >http://lantern.mediahist.org</ref>), which received the 2014 Anne
                            Friedberg Innovative Scholarship Award from the Society for Cinema &amp;
                            Media Studies. Hoyt is the US PI on <title rend="quotes">Project
                                Arclight: Analytics for the Study of 20<hi rend="superscript"
                                    >th</hi> Century Media</title> (<ref
                                target="http://projectarclight.org"
                            >http://projectarclight.org</ref>), which received a Digging into Data
                            grant sponsored by SSHRC, IMLS, and the NEH Office of Digital
                            Humanities.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Kevin <dhq:family>Ponto</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Wisconsin-Madison</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kbponto@wisc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Kevin Ponto is Assistant Professor in the Living Environments Lab and the
                            Design Studies Department in the School of Human Ecology. Ponto received
                            his Bachelors from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, his master’s
                            from the university of California, Irvine and his Ph.D from the
                            University of California, San Diego. Ponto's research is focused on
                            advancing the state of the art in the field of virtual reality, ranging
                            from creating novel and natural interfaces for immersive virtual
                            environments to developing methods, techniques and tools to better
                            understand, evaluate, and develop interactive virtual experiences.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Carrie <dhq:family>Roy</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Wisconsin-Madison</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>croy@wisc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Carrie Roy is Coordinator for the <ref
                                target="http://bridge.library.wisc.edu">Humanities Research
                                Bridge</ref> at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. Her research
                            interests span digital humanities tools and data visualizations,
                            folklore, Scandinavian studies, medieval literature, art, folk art, and
                            material culture. Collaborations on tools, programming and research
                            involve partners in the humanities, biological sciences, healthcare,
                            statistics, computer science, and the most recent, <ref
                                target="http://bridge.library.wisc.edu/Projects_VictorianEyes.html"
                                    ><hi rend="italic">Victorian Eyes</hi></ref>, an art
                            exhibition.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000190</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2014-12-20">20 December 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Of all narrative textual forms, the motion picture screenplay may be the most
                    perfectly pre-disposed for computational analysis. Screenplays contain
                    capitalized character names, indented dialogue, and other formatting conventions
                    that enable an algorithmic approach to analyzing and visualizing film
                    narratives. In this article, the authors introduce their new tool, ScripThreads,
                    which parses screenplays, outputs statistical values which can be analyzed, and
                    offers four different types of visualization, each with its own utility. The
                    visualizations represent character interactions across time as a single 3D or 2D
                    graph. The authors model the utility of the tool for the close analysis of a
                    single film (Lawrence Kasdan’s <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title>
                    [1991]). They also model how the tool can be used for <q>distant reading</q> by identifying patterns of character
                    presence across a dataset of 674 screenplays.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Of all narrative textual forms, the motion picture screenplay may be the most
                    perfectly pre-disposed for computational analysis.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>In November 2009, the website xkcd.com published a series of info-graphics that
                    visualized character interactions in movies such as the <title rend="italic"
                        >Lord of the Rings </title>trilogy (2001-2003), the <title rend="italic"
                        >Star Wars </title>trilogy (1977-1983), and <title rend="italic">Jurassic
                        Park </title>(1993). Exhibiting both attention to detail and a nice sense of
                    humor, the xkcd charts allowed time to play out across the x-axis and showed how
                    the characters exist in different spaces within the narrative world (the
                    difference between storylines occurring on the Death Star and Tatooine, in the
                        <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> example). These info-graphics became
                    the motivation for Tanahasi and Ma’s <title rend="quotes">Design Considerations
                        for Optimizing Storyline Visualizations,</title> a computer science paper
                    published in <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and
                        Computer Graphics </title>(2012). Tanahasi and Ma propose an algorithmic
                    approach to generating the design of these types of visualizations. While these
                    types of visualizations were of interest to scholars and researchers, they came
                    with several short-comings, most notably that all of the information that was to
                    be visualized needed to be gathered externally. This meant that a human would
                    need to watch a film and manually fill in information as to when and where
                    certain characters appeared and interacted. It greatly diminished the utility of
                    these visualizations as a tool of data exploration; the analysis more or less
                    needed to be completed before the tool could be used.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>xkcd’s 2009 charts of character interactions in movies proved to be
                        popular on the Internet and influential to visualization designers.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The challenge of conveying complex information (character appearances, relations
                    with other characters, and absences) as it changes over time — along with our
                    shared interests in the Digital Humanities and our more singular scholarly
                    focuses on cinema and television (Hoyt), visualization and storytelling (Roy),
                    and computational approaches (Ponto) — spurred us to develop a tool that
                    algorithmically analyzes and visualizes screenplays. In building a tool to aid
                    Humanists, we sought to heed Abello, Broadwell, and Tanghrelini’s call for
                    computational approaches that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#abello2012"
                        >combine distant reading and close reading</quote>
                    <ptr target="#abello2012"/></cit>. One appeal of a fully algorithmic approach is that
                    it scales nicely — enabling the <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2000"
                        >distant reading</quote> that Franco Moretti first proposed and, in our
                    case, allowing a researcher to study 1,000 screenplays rather than 10 or 20 <ptr
                        target="#moretti2000"/>. Keeping in mind the value of close reading, though,
                    we also sought to create a narrative analysis tool that offered direct access to
                    every line of a screenplay — similar to the <title rend="quotes">Reading
                        View</title> window in the Watching the Script software prototype developed
                    for the visualization of theatrical text <ptr target="#roberts-smith2013"/>. In
                    our case, we wanted to connect this <title rend="quotes">Reading View</title>
                    window that displays lines from the screenplay to a series of visualizations
                    that account for scenes, pacing, and character interactions. Rather than
                    reducing a screenplay simply to statistical aggregates, we wanted to map the way
                    a screenplay unfolds as it moves from page to page. From generating several
                    hundred of these narrative profiles, we can compare and contrast large numbers
                    of screenplays across decades, by author, by genre, by narrative structure and
                    more. </p>
                <p>In this article, we introduce our tool, ScripThreads, and discuss some of our
                    initial research findings from using ScripThreads to analyze and visualize
                    hundreds of screenplays from the American Film Scripts Online collection. We
                    model how the tool can be productively used in film analysis as a tool for close
                    reading by analyzing and comparing two screenplays co-written and directed by
                    Lawrence Kasdan, <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> (1983) and <title
                        rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> (1991). We also model how the tool can be
                    used for distant reading by searching across hundreds of screenplays for the
                    pattern of the <soCalled>hyper-present protagonist</soCalled> — movies that
                    place a main character in every scene or nearly every scene. </p>
                <p>In the process of building the tool’s prototype and writing this article, we have
                    come to appreciate the many ways that a computer reads a screenplay differently
                    from you or me. Humans gather insight from watching and experiencing the
                    emotion, tension, and dynamics of a movie or screenplay. Rather than attempting
                    to train a computer to understand a film in the exact same way we do, we would
                    prefer to ask a computer to do tasks that it is designed to do well and that we
                    humans struggle with. Humans have memory limitations when it comes to matters of
                    sequential timing and the entrances and exits of dozens of characters. In
                    contrast, computers are excellent at gathering and recording these sorts of
                    details from structured texts. Lev Manovich has suggested that one of the most
                    valuable things that comes from combining computational analysis and the
                    visualization of vast amounts of information in a single image is that it
                    defamiliarizes our understanding of the works that we study in the Humanities
                        <ptr target="#manovich2012"/>. As we hope to demonstrate, ScripThreads is a
                    powerful framework for defamiliarization, provoking new questions, and producing
                    new answers through the combined strengths of the human analyst and the
                    computer.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Researching the Screenplay: Opportunities and Challenges</head>
                <p>Of all narrative textual forms, the motion picture screenplay may be the most
                    perfectly pre-disposed for computational analysis. As Murtagh, Ganz, and
                    Reddington explain, <title rend="quotes">a filmscript is a semi-structured
                        textual document in that it is subdivided into scenes and sometimes other
                        structural units. Both character dialog and also descriptive and background
                        metadata is provided in a filmscript. The metadata is partially
                        formalized</title>
                    <ptr target="#murtagh2011"/>. As semi-structured documents with formatting
                    conventions analogous to a metadata schema, screenplays are ideally suited for
                    automated computer parsing. There is no need for laborious TEI encoding to
                    detect character dialogue exchanges and interactions. When a character speaks,
                    his or her name is capitalized and centered on the page. The character’s
                    dialogue generally appears one line below. As we discuss below, there are
                    variations within this general format that create parsing challenges.
                    Nevertheless, the extraction of character interactions in a screenplay is far
                    easier to automate than in a novel or epic poem.</p>
                <p>Our research and software development contributes to a lively and growing area of
                    research about screenwriting history, form, theory, and practice. As a
                    discipline, Film Studies has long lived in the shadow of the <soCalled>auteur theory,</soCalled> which views the
                    director as the author of a film. Film scholars and critics seem unable to let
                    go of an <soCalled>auteur desire,</soCalled> in
                    the words of Dana Polan <ptr target="#polan2001"/>. Even scholars who
                    acknowledge that film is a highly collaborative medium will refer to <title
                        rend="quotes">Scorsese’s <title rend="italic">Taxi Driver</title></title> —
                    elevating the director to the status of author rather than the studio (Columbia
                    Pictures), screenwriter (Paul Schrader), or cinematographer (Michael Chapman).
                    Over the last decade, however, screenwriting studies has emerged as its own
                    sub-field within the discipline of film and media studies. The Screenwriting
                    Research Network held its first conference in 2008; the <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Screenwriting</title> published its first issue in 2010. </p>
                <p>A small contingent of screenwriting researchers are, like us, pursuing the
                    computational analysis of screenplays <ptr target="#marinov2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#marinovstitts2013a"/>
                    <ptr target="#mckie2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#murtagh2011"/>. The 2013 launch of Samuel Marinov and Brock
                    Stitts’ Screenplay Owl analysis tool marked an especially exciting development.
                    With its emphasis on dialogic exchange frequencies, Screenplay Owl differs
                    significantly from ScripThreads. However, both ScripThreads and Screenplay Owl
                    show that the initial speculations about computational screenplay analysis are
                    becoming realities. As we worked on revising this article for <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ </title>in early-2014, we witnessed the launch of another
                    promising screenwriting analytics tool: ScriptFAQ, developed by Stewart McKie.
                    McKie’s tool is designed for practicing screenwriters who want to ask questions
                    about a screenplay they are working on (for example, how many scenes is one
                    character in compared to another?). For ScriptFAQ to answer these questions, the
                    screenplay must be imported in the XML-based Final Draft file format and the
                    user must enter a substantial number of additional metadata fields, which
                    require detailed knowledge of the screenplay. For a writer working on a
                    screenplay, these metadata fields are quite easy to complete and the results are
                    well worth the effort. For a researcher wanting to quickly compare hundreds of
                    screenplays across history, however, the need for many additional metadata,
                    prior knowledge about each screenplay, and the Final Draft file format (which
                    most older screenplays aren’t readily available in) make ScripThreads better
                    suited than ScriptFAQ for distant reading. Ultimately, for a researcher
                    interested in computer-enhanced close reading, we believe the combination of
                    analyzing a screenplay in ScripThreads, ScreenplayOwl, and ScriptFAQ may
                    generate the richest results of all. </p>
                <p>Regardless of the software platform, there are some inherent limitations to an
                    automated approach to screenplay analysis. First, a screenplay nearly always
                    differs to some degree from the completed film version, which may include
                    improvised dialogue from the film’s production or lack scenes or characters that
                    were cut in post-production. Screenplay analysis requires us to qualify
                    arguments we may want to make about the entire film. Another major challenge to
                    this line of research is access — specifically, digital access to the
                    authoritative versions of screenplays. There are several websites offering free,
                    downloadable screenplays of contemporary Hollywood movies. The provenance,
                    authoritativeness, and legal status of these screenplays, though, are not clear.
                    Moreover, these websites generally have very few screenplays for movies produced
                    prior to the 1980s. </p>
                <p> American Film Scripts Online (AFSO) is the digital resource that we believe
                    provides access to the largest number of authoritative, digitized screenplays.
                    The resource’s creator, Alexander Street Press, licensed 1,009 screenplays from
                    Warner Bros., Universal, and a number of other rights holders. Roughly half of
                    the screenplays are available as PDF facsimiles of the original documents, and
                    all of the screenplays are available as HTML documents, which have been
                    re-keyed, eliminating most of the problems that come from uncorrected OCR text.
                    The HTML mark-up is not consistently or semantically structured, but this
                    productively forced us to code ScripThreads’s parsing algorithm so that it could
                    handle a wider variety of screenplays and not depend on rigid mark-up standards.
                    As for AFSO’s selection of screenplays, the collection is stronger in some areas
                    than others. Over half of the 1,009 screenplays derive from 1930s and 1940s
                    Hollywood movies — primarily, productions from Warner Bros., RKO, and MGM (it’s
                    no coincidence that Time Warner holds the rights to all three of these studio
                    film libraries). AFSO is well suited, then, for research questions focusing on
                    Hollywood’s <title rend="quotes">Golden Age.</title> Other strength areas of
                    AFSO include 1990s American films (both studio and independent) and large script
                    collections from certain contemporary screenwriters, including Paul Schrader,
                    Lawrence Kasdan, and John Sayles. As a result, AFSO is also well suited for
                    researching questions involving screenplay authorship, a topic we explore later
                    in this essay.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. ScripThreads: Parsing Method and Forms of Visualization</head>
                <p>The ScripThreads software prototype is a cross-platform tool for the analysis and
                    visualization of screenplays. The tool is written in C++ and utilizes the QT
                    toolkit for its graphical user interface, making it easily ported to multiple
                    systems. <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref> shows a screenshot of the
                    graphical user interface, which offers separate windows for the Reading View,
                    Visualization View, and Character and Settings View. By September 2014, users
                    will be able to download the ScripThreads prototype at <ref
                        target="http://scripthreads.org">http://scripthreads.org</ref>. ScripThreads
                    takes in text and HTML file screenplays as an input, parses these files and
                    generates data for visualization and analysis. The features of the tool are
                    described below and showcased with visualizations from <title rend="italic">The
                        Big Chill</title> (1983) and other Hollywood screenplays. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>The ScripThreads graphical user interface separate windows for the Reading
                        View, Visualization View, and Character and Settings View.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.1. Parsing Method</head>
                <p>While screenplays contain a structure that is far more defined than other
                    mediums, we still found substantial variation between different works. For
                    instance while most works contained indentation and then the character name in
                    full capitalization before each paragraph of dialogue, the number of spaces this
                    indentation took varied greatly between different works. Furthermore, some
                    authors used indentation and capitalization to indicate other screenplay
                    attributes such as sound effects, locations, and times. </p>
                <p>For these reasons we used a two-step process to automatically find characters in
                    a screenplay. In the first pass, each line was analyzed to determine if it was
                    potentially the indication of a character. Lines which were considered
                    candidates were pushed to a list. After the first pass, the list was analyzed to
                    determine the most likely amount of indentation before a character name. For
                    instance, a given screenplay may have 12 spaces of indentation before a
                    character name with the spoken lines included in the paragraph below.</p>
                <p>A second pass was then undertaken to generate information of which characters
                    were in which scene. This pass consisted of parsing for three different items,
                    character names, scene breaks, and meta-information. Character names were
                    gathered from the first pass. Additional names could also be entered by the
                    user. Scenes were determined by looking for a user defined set of keywords, such
                    as <q>int.</q> or <q>ext.</q>. In practice, it was determined that a list of
                    10-12 keywords well captured scene changes. Finally, meta-information data, such
                    as page numbers, were found using simple matching techniques.</p>
                <p>This second pass generated data for each scene as to how long the scene lasted,
                    which characters were involved, and for how many pages in the original
                    screenplay the scene encompassed. From this data, four different types of
                    visualization are available to users, each with its own utility. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.2. Force Directed Graph</head>
                <p>After the characters are detected, ScripThreads applies the framework of network
                    theory by drawing a relationship (edge) between characters (nodes) who share the
                    same scene. Force directed graphs are a common method visualizing this type of
                    information. Digital Humanities scholars have used force directed graphs to
                    represent networks of characters, literary authors, and topics <ptr
                        target="#simeone2012"/>. In a force directed graph, edges are represented as
                    virtual springs and nodes are represented as virtual masses. During runtime, a
                    virtual physics simulation is run which attempts to find an equilibrium position
                    for all nodes. <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> is an example of a typical
                    force directed graph. In this case, we used Gephi to graph the network of
                    characters from the 1983 film, <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>A typical force directed graph of a character network. This graph shows
                        the network of characters from <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>
                        (1983).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Unfortunately, this approach is only designed for representing connectivity
                    information, and is not designed for a time-based approach. One approach to
                    encode temporal information along with connectivity information is to treat each
                    time-step as an individual force directed graph. These graphs can then be
                    converted into a 3D data structure which can be analyzed from arbitrary
                    positions. The limitation of this approach on its own is that each time-step is
                    handled on an individual basis; there is no guarantee that the nodes will appear
                    as temporally connected threads.</p>
                <p>To overcome this limitation, ScripThreads accounts for the temporal dimension
                    through use of a single 3D data structure. Each node is placed on a series of
                    time-step planes on the z-axis and are not only connected to the other relevant
                    nodes in their time-step, but are also connected to the previous and future
                    states. This enables each character to be viewed as a virtual thread that can
                    become entangled in other threads when relationships occur. An added value to
                    the vertical alignment of character threads, as opposed to the horizontal
                    arrangement of the xkcd examples, is that the entire script is visible and able
                    to be scrolled alongside the visualization — enabling the integrated close and
                    distant reading noted in the introduction. The rendering system also simulates
                    the idea of a virtual thread, by rendering each character as a continuous
                    character thread — thick when the character is active, thin when not active.
                    This enables unbiased color blending to occur on a model level, often referred
                    to as <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hagh-shenas2007">color weaving</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hagh-shenas2007"/></cit>. Lines of dialogue between the characters can
                    be seen as interconnects between the thread with the color representing the
                    speaker.</p>
                <p>The force directed visualizations reveal insights into a screenplay’s narrative
                    structure, especially for films featuring episodic segments or parallel
                    narratives, parallel protagonists, or parallel lines of action. In screenwriting
                    manuals, <q>narrative structure</q> is often synonymous with <q>three act
                        structure</q> and the goal-oriented protagonist whose pursuit of some goal
                    pushes the story from one act to the next. The goal-oriented protagonist is
                    fundamental to Hollywood storytelling, and we acknowledge that ScripThreads does
                    not capture this important dimension of screenplay structure.<note> For a brief
                        overview of the three act structure and Kristin Thompson’s richer four act
                        structure, see Eric Hoyt’s online Prezi, <title rend="quotes">Hollywood
                            Storytelling: 3 Act or 4 Act Structure,</title> 3 October 2013, <ref
                            target="../customXml/item1.xml"
                            >http://prezi.com/x7fhnbeofobw/hollywood-storytelling-3-act-or-4-act-structure/</ref>.
                        Readers are also strongly encouraged to read Kristin Thompson’s <title
                            rend="italic">Storytelling in the New Hollywood: Understanding Classical
                            Narrative Technique </title>(1999).</note> However, we would also argue
                    that there is more to narrative structure than simply the pursuit of goals
                    across three acts. Supporting characters will be introduced along the way, but
                    will they return and, if so, how and when? Are there parallel lines of action as
                    other characters pursue their own goals or serve as thematic foils for the
                    protagonist? The force directed graph of Paul Schrader’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Mishima: A Life in Four Chapters</title> (1985) clearly captures the
                    specific character threads contained in four sections of the script (see <ref
                        target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). Similar visual patterns in other force
                    directed graphs would suggest the screenplay may be episodic in its overall
                    structure and the way in which it uses supporting characters. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Force directed graph of <title rend="italic">Mishima: A Life in Four
                            Chapters</title> (1985) by Paul Schrader. Circle annotations mark the
                        episodic segment breaks.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Another reoccurring visual pattern we have detected is alternating convergences
                    of different color character threads. Such alternating clusters strongly suggest
                    the screenplay features parallel protagonists, parallel narratives, or parallel
                    lines of action that play out across different spaces. The force directed graph
                    of <title rend="italic">The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King</title>
                    (2003), for instance, reveals the parallel lines of action as the hobbits and
                    their allies pursue their goals across different spaces (<ref target="#figure05"
                        >Figure 5</ref>). The different lines of action and character threads
                    converge for the climax and lengthy epilogue. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>Parallel lines of action (their intersections circled for emphasis)
                        revealed in the force directed graph of <title rend="italic">Lord of the
                            Rings: The Return of the King</title> (2003).<note>
                            <title rend="italic">The Return of the King</title> screenplay, written
                            by Peter Jackson, Fran Walsh, and Phillippa Boyens, came from the
                            Internet Movie Script Database (IMSDb). <ref
                                target="http://www.imsdb.com/Movie%20Scripts/Lord%20of%20the%20Rings:%20Return%20of%20the%20King%20Script.html"
                                >http://www.imsdb.com/Movie%20Scripts/Lord%20of%20the%20Rings:%20Return%20of%20the%20King%20Script.html</ref>
                            (accessed 5 October 2013). It is the only screenplay we discuss in this
                            article that does not derive from the American Film Scripts Online
                            Collection.</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In contrast to the <title rend="italic">Mishima’s </title>identifiable episodes
                    and the alternating lines of action in <title rend="italic">The Return of the
                        King</title>, the force directed graph of <title rend="italic">The Big
                        Chill</title> (1983) is an example of a film that clusters its characters
                    together in the same spaces and scenes throughout the movie (<ref
                        target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>). The narrative of <title rend="italic"
                        >The Big Chill</title>, directed by Lawrence Kasdan and written by Kasdan
                    and Barbara Benedek, centers on a group of seven college friends who reunite
                    after a shared friend, Alex, dies. Most of the film’s action occurs after the
                    funeral at a spacious vacation house — a setting that facilitates many different
                    types of character interactions, ranging from two characters speaking privately
                    to scenes that bring the entire group together. The frequency of these
                    interactions between the same group of characters is visibly evident in the
                    tight clustering of the threads colored red (Sam), pink (Harold), orange
                    (Michael), light orange (Nick), green (Meg), and light green (Sarah) toward the
                    center of the force directed graph. The character whose thread veers in the
                    largest arc from the central group is Chloe, Alex’s girlfriend who did not
                    attend college with the rest of the group and speaks far less than the other
                    characters. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>ScripThreads force directed graph of <title rend="italic">The Big
                            Chill</title> (1983), written by Lawrence Kasdan and Barbara
                        Benedek.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.3. Absence Graph</head>
                <p> In ScripThreads’ <q>absence graph,</q> the x-axis measures presence and absence.
                    A thread’s distance from the center of x-axis conveys length of absence as a
                    character — measured forward and backward in time. The resulting visualization
                    can be read like a bus map: characters run parallel routes when they both appear
                    in a scene. When a character is not in a scene, his or her bus route splits off.
                        <title rend="italic">The Big Chill’s</title> absence graph (<ref
                        target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref>) calls our attention to the purple thread
                    of Richard, who is Karen’s husband and an outsider from the core group of
                    college friends. Karen’s sub-plot in the film centers on her decision about
                    whether to stay with Richard or leave him for her college boyfriend, Sam. As the
                    purple thread’s wide arcs reveal, Richard is absent for most of the film.
                    However, the graph also shows that he is more important to the narrative than a
                    character who only matters to a single scene.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>ScripThreads absence graph of <title rend="italic">The Big
                        Chill</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.4. Presence Graph</head>
                <p> The <q>presence graph</q> provides a quick glance as to when a character is
                    active in a scene. The size of the thread is wider when the character is active
                    and is smaller when the character is not active. Time is shown in the y-axis
                    from top to bottom. Horizontal lines indicate dialog between the characters.</p>
                <p>If we return to <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>, this screenplay’s
                    presence graph (<ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>) helps us see that the
                    storytellers do not treat the core group of friends with equal emphasis. The
                    male characters of Sam, Harold, Michael, and Nick speak in more scenes and
                    appear with greater frequency than any of the female characters (the character
                    statistics CSV supports this claim). The character of Sam (red thread) is
                    integral to advancing the plotlines of multiple characters and helps motivate
                    transitions between scenes. However, his love interest, Karen (blue), is largely
                    absent unless the entire group comes together for a scene or the focus turns to
                    her plotline with Sam. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head>ScripThreads presence graph of <title rend="italic">The Big
                        Chill</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.5. Increasing Graph</head>
                <p> The increasing graph is useful for communicating, in a single image, character
                    activity and storytelling techniques across the course of a narrative. Unlike
                    the force directed and convergence graphs, ScripThreads’ increasing graph is not
                    rooted in the network theory. Perhaps for this reason, though, we’ve found that
                    Humanities researchers unfamiliar with networks tend to find the increasing
                    graph the fastest to grasp and interpret. </p>
                <p> The increasing graph rotates the axes from the convergence graph: the x-axis
                    becomes time and the y-axis becomes character presence. If a character is
                    present in a scene, then his or her colored thread vertically increases. If a
                    character is not present in a scene, then her thread remains flat. </p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">The Big Chill’s</title> increasing graph (<ref
                        target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>) shows that the Sam and Harold characters
                    (red and pink) have roughly an equal level of presence throughout the
                    screenplay. Slightly less present are Michael and Nick (orange and light
                    orange), who also appear roughly equally, and they, in turn, are followed very
                    closely by Meg and Sarah (green and light green). The increasing graph
                    reinforces our earlier observation that the male characters play active roles in
                    more scenes than the female characters. <title rend="italic">The Big
                        Chill’s</title> gender imbalance is small, though, compared to the vast
                    majority of Hollywood screenplays. Additionally, the proximity of the seven
                    threads representing the seven college friends is, relatively speaking,
                    extremely tight. We have yet to find another <q>ensemble</q> or
                        <q>multi-character</q> screenplay with such a tight range of presence levels
                    for this many characters. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure09">
                    <head>Increasing graphs of three films directed and written or co-written by
                        Lawrence Kasdan: from left to right, <title rend="italic">Body Heat</title>
                        (1981), <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> (1983), and <title
                            rend="italic">Silverado</title> (1985).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p> The screenplays that Kasdan wrote and directed immediately before and after
                        <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> are more typical of American
                    screenwriting (<ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>). In most Hollywood
                    movies, the story centers on the goals of one or two protagonists. These
                    protagonists — antiheroes, in the case of the neo-noir <title rend="italic">Body
                        Heat</title> — are the red and pink threads. The orange threads in <title
                        rend="italic">Body Heat</title> and <title rend="italic">Silverado
                    </title>reveal another common storytelling technique that our graphs help to
                    see: introducing a character in the first ten pages who will re-emerge in the
                    second act to increase conflict and complicate the protagonist’s pursuit of his
                    goals. Interestingly, and fittingly for the western and crime noir genres,
                    Kasdan made this character an authority figure in both screenplays: the sheriff
                    in <title rend="italic">Silverado</title> and the district attorney
                    friend-turned-threat memorably played by Ted Danson in <title rend="italic">Body
                        Heat</title>. </p>
                <p> When we looked at hundreds of screenplay increasing graphs, we noticed a
                    sub-group in which the red thread shoots up diagonally in a straight line, far
                    exceeding any other thread line (<ref target="#figure13">Figure 13</ref>). These
                    graphs are indicative of screenplays that focus on a single protagonist and in
                    which the protagonist appears in every scene or nearly every scene. We analyze
                    this pattern in greater depth in Section 5 of this article.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.6. Scene Stats and Character Stats</head>
                <p>ScripThreads also gives users the option to export two different types of data:
                    scene statistics and character statistics. In the <title rend="quotes">Scene
                        Stats</title> CSV, each row represents one scene, arranged in the order they
                    occur within the script. The fields (columns) indicate the scene’s number of
                    lines, number of characters, starting page, ending page, and location (interior
                    or exterior). In the <title rend="quotes">Character Stats</title> CSV, the rows
                    represent the screenplay’s characters, arranged in descending order of scene
                    activity. The fields here indicate the character’s number of active scenes,
                    number of dialogue lines, and percentage of involvement across the film. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Close Reading Case Study: Lawrence Kasdan’s <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title></head>
                <p> Thus far, we have demonstrated that ScripThreads generates visualizations that
                    reveal storytelling techniques, character interactions, and character activity
                    within a screenplay. In sharing our work, though, we have been asked: how does
                    this tool yield knowledge that couldn’t be gained simply through reading the
                    screenplay, watching the film closely, or turning to the existing body of
                    scholarship on narratology, cognitivism, and Hollywood storytelling? While we
                    are enthusiastic about the potential of ScripThreads for distant reading, we
                    also recognize that the close analysis of individual films will always be an
                    important activity of film criticism and scholarship. In this section, we model
                    how ScripThreads can be used as an interpretative tool that enhances — rather
                    than replaces — the use of narrative theory and the method of close reading. To
                    model how a scholar’s engagement with ScripThreads can enrich an understanding
                    of a film’s narrative structure, we will continue our focus on Lawrence Kasdan’s
                    work and analyze the screenplay for <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title>
                    (1991). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <head>The marketing of <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> (1991), written
                        by Lawrence Kasdan and Meg Kasdan, emphasizes the film’s ensemble of actors
                        and invites us to think of the film in relationship to <title rend="italic"
                            >Big Chill</title> (1983).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <q>In the 80’s he brought us <title
                            rend="quotes">The Big Chill.</title> Welcome to the 90’s.</q> So
                    reads the tag line on the movie poster for <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title> (1991), directed by Lawrence Kasdan and written by Lawrence
                    Kasdan and Meg Kasdan (<ref target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>). <title
                        rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title>’s marketing suggests a close relationship
                    between it and <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>, a comparison
                    emphasized further by both films’ casting of Kevin Kline and emphases on an
                    ensemble of actors. The question, then, arises — how similar or different are
                    the two films?</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure11">
                    <head>ScripThreads force directed graph of Grand Canyon (1991), written by
                        Lawrence Kasdan and Meg Kasdan.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p> The ScripThreads visualizations for <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title>
                    (1991) show that its scene structure and character interactions are
                    significantly different from <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> (1983).
                    The wider thread arcs and non-intersecting threads of <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon’s</title> force directed graph (<ref target="#figure11">Figure
                        11</ref>) show that there are characters who appear numerous times in the
                    film but never share the same scene. Davis (green thread) and Deborah (purple
                    thread), for example, are never present in the same scene. Other characters,
                    such as Dee (light green) and Claire (pink), are only present once in the same
                    scene. Whereas <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> is about a network of
                    old friends who physically reunite in the same space, <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title> is an example of what some film scholars have referred to as
                    a <quote rend="inline" source="#bordwell2006">network narrative</quote> — a
                    multi-protagonist film that follows numerous characters whose lives intersect at
                    different moments <ptr target="#bordwell2006" loc="94–103"/>. Of course, one
                    does not need a computer visualization to recognize this difference between
                        <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> and <title rend="italic">The Big
                        Chill</title>. From viewing both films, the difference between the
                    characters gathered spatially in <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>’s
                    house and the characters dispersed across the city of Los Angeles in <title
                        rend="italic">Grand Canyon </title>is quite apparent. The racially diverse
                    cast of <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> and the film’s overriding
                    interests in relations across race and social class are also starkly different
                    from <title rend="italic">The Big Chill</title>, a film in which no non-white
                    character holds narrative significance. So, the question remains — what does
                    ScripThreads offer that simply viewing the films does not? </p>
                <p> If we put aside the comparative question and instead focus on the details of
                        <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon’s</title> multi-character structure, then
                    more interesting insights begin to emerge. In <title rend="italic">The Way
                        Hollywood Tells It</title>, film scholar David Bordwell writes: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#bordwell2006">In Lawrence Kasdan’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Grand Canyon</hi> (1991), the married couple Mack and
                            Claire and the brother-sister pair of Simon and [Deborah] are given
                            roughly equal emphasis… other plotlines show Mack’s son falling in love
                            with a girl he meets at camp, [Deborah]’s son being alienated, and
                            Mack’s friend Davis vowing to stop making ultraviolent movies. The
                            subsidiary characters don’t encounter all the customary obstacles and
                            setbacks, yet their wants are developed beyond the limits of a
                            traditional subplot, providing thematic echoes or counterpoints.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bordwell2006" loc="96"/>
                    </cit> When we look at the increasing graph for <hi rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</hi>, it is striking to note how uneven the distribution of character
                    presence is across the film (see <ref target="#figure12">Figure 12</ref>). The
                    Kevin Kline character of Mack (red thread) appears in 50% more scenes than any
                    other character. The next two most active threads are those of Mack’s wife,
                    Claire (pink), and Simon (orange), the tow truck driver who helps Mack after a
                    car breakdown in one of L.A.’s worst neighborhoods. Simon’s sister, Deborah
                    (purple), appears as one of many of the subsidiary characters clustered toward
                    the bottom. She is present in fewer scenes than either Davis (green) or Mack’s
                    son Roberto (light orange).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure12">
                    <head>Increasing graph of <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> (1991),
                        written by Lawrence Kasdan and Meg Kasdan.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Does this mean that David Bordwell’s analysis of the film is incorrect? No.
                    Bordwell never claims that Mack, Claire, Simon, and Deborah are given equal
                    screen time. Instead, he’s suggesting that the storytelling techniques invite
                    the audience to think of the characters as equally important. In fact,
                    Bordwell’s book offers insights that explain the discrepancy between Mack’s
                    on-screen involvement and the audience’s understanding of Mack as one of
                    multiple roughly equal characters. Bordwell describes <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title> in the context of contemporary <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#bordwell2006">ensemble films</quote> in which <quote rend="inline" source="#bordwell2006"
                        >several protagonists are given equal emphasis, based on screen time, star
                        wattage, control over events, or other spotlighting maneuvers.</quote> The
                    star wattage and spotlighting maneuvers are especially significant to our
                    interpretation of <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> as an ensemble
                    drama. As already discussed, the film’s marketing emphasized the ensemble of
                    actors. In terms of star power, Danny Glover and Steve Martin had both headlined
                    more commercially successful movies than Kevin Kline prior to the movie’s
                    release. </p>
                <p> The screenplay’s two major spotlighting maneuvers, which occur at the beginning
                    and end, further encourage us to perceive Mack (Kevin Kline) and Simon (Danny
                    Glover) as equal in narrative importance. The script’s most important
                    spotlighting maneuver occurs from pages 6 to 16: the white lawyer Mack’s car
                    breaks down at night in South Central Los Angeles; armed young black men
                    approach him and tell him to get out of the car; Simon, a black tow truck
                    driver, pulls up, tells the armed men that Mack is his responsibility, and takes
                    Mack back to his house in an affluent neighborhood. The screenplay interweaves
                    scenes of Mack waiting for the tow truck and scenes of his family back in
                    Brentwood. When Simon and Mack are leaving South Central, Simon’s line, <q>My sister and her kids live near here,</q>
                    motivates a transition to a scene that introduces Simon’s sister and her
                    troubled son. The Mack and Simon characters are contrasted by their race and
                    social class, yet treated as equals through the attention to each one’s family
                    and their shared sense that, in the words of Simon, <q>the world ain't supposed to work like this... Everything's
                        supposed to be different than it is.</q> This loss of faith in the
                    social and moral order — counterbalanced by the possibility for human kindness,
                    growth, and, even, miracles — provides the thematic glue for the entire film.
                    The final scene of Mack, Simon, and their loved ones gazing in wonder at the
                    Grand Canyon reestablishes our understanding of the narrative parity between the
                    lives of Mack and Simon. Simon’s question, <q>What
                        do you think?</q> and Mack’s response, <q>I think… it’s not all bad. Not at all,</q> provides an affirmative,
                    glass-half-full answer to the existential questions that have run throughout the
                    136-page screenplay. </p>
                <p> The many scenes that occur between the car breakdown and visit to the Grand
                    Canyon further encourage the audience to think of <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#bordwell2006">the married couple Mack and Claire and the
                        brother-sister pair of Simon and [Deborah]</quote> as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bordwell2006">roughly equal [in]
                            emphasis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bordwell2006"/>
                    </cit>. Bordwell points out that “their lines of action follow Thompson’s
                    four-part template,” referring to the four act structure that Kristin Thompson
                    identifies as running through most Hollywood movies, including films with
                    multiple protagonists <ptr target="#thompson1999"/>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Grand Canyon</title>, Mack and Simon both move through the four act cycle
                    of setup, complicating action, development, and climax and epilogue. As Thompson
                    argues, it is characters in pursuit of goals that defines classical Hollywood
                    storytelling more than any other feature. The goals often change, and characters
                    generally have both long-term and short-term goals. Mack and Simon are both
                    seeking to restore their faith in the universe and humanity. Yet there are a
                    series of more concrete short-term goals (Mack wanting to return a favor to
                    Simon), appointments (Simon’s date with Jane), and deadlines (Mack and Claire’s
                    need to make a decision about the baby) that move these characters through the
                    four act structure and make <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> a
                    Hollywood film rather than one of the existential dramas of Ingmar Bergman. </p>
                <p> As our analysis has shown, the ScripThreads graphs can help scholars, critics,
                    and practitioners better appreciate how storytelling techniques shape the
                    audience’s perception of a narrative. In the case of <title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title>, the force directed graph (<ref target="#figure11">Figure
                        11</ref>) offers an additional insight: the character of Mack functions
                    structurally as the film’s key bridge node. Mack (red thread) is active in
                    scenes with nearly all the major characters. He introduces Simon (orange thread)
                    to Jane (blue thread), with whom Simon becomes romantically linked. More
                    importantly, Mack motivates our introductions to his co-worker and one-time
                    lover Dee (light green thread) and movie producer friend Davis (green thread).
                    Searching for happiness and answers in their own lives, Dee and Davis advance
                    the central themes of the film. Yet unlike some modern films, these thematically
                    linked storylines do not occur in isolation to one another. Mack motivates our
                    introductions to these characters and appears in subsequent scenes with them.
                    When Mack visits the wounded Davis, the focus is squarely on Davis and his
                    storyline — encouraging us to think of it as Davis’s scene, despite Mack’s
                    presence, and furthering the overall notion of <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon
                    </title>as an ensemble film. The ScripThreads force directed graph is useful,
                    then, for reminding us that Mack, as a bridge node, is still vital to the
                    structuring of multiple storylines that are not his own.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Distant Reading Case Study: Locating the Hyper-Present Protagonist</head>
                <p> Some research in the Digital Humanities begins with a fixed research question
                    and a clear process for gathering evidence. But as Sinclair, Ruecker, and
                    Radzikowska suggest, another important task for the Humanities is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sinclair2013">to locate (or discover) new
                            material, with no prior knowledge of the kinds of details used for
                            retrieval</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sinclair2013"/>
                    </cit>. In our case, we tested out the distant reading possibilities of
                    ScripThreads by using the tool’s “Automate” function to export four types of
                    graphs (force directed, absence, presence and increasing) and the statistical
                    CSV files for the screenplays in the corpus that were produced between 1930 to
                    2006. We then looked at the graph images for patterns that stood out visually
                    across numerous screenplays. The first pattern that came to our attention was a
                    sub-group of increasing graphs in which the red thread moves diagonally at a
                    straight line, advancing higher and straighter than any other thread line (<ref
                        target="#figure13">Figure 13</ref>). These graphs pointed us toward the
                    storytelling pattern of what we call the <soCalled>hyper-present
                        protagonist</soCalled> — screenplays featuring a main character who appears
                    in every scene or nearly every scene. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure13">
                    <head>Single character increasing graphs for four films with a protagonist who
                        appears in every scene or almost every scene: from left to right, <title
                            rend="italic">I Am a Fugitive from a Chain Gang</title> (1932), <title
                            rend="italic">Across the Pacific</title> (1942), <title rend="italic">On
                            Dangerous Ground</title> (1952), and <title rend="italic">Pi</title>
                        (1998).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p> After identifying the pattern, we began searching for all instances of the
                    pattern both visually and mathematically. We used R to write and execute a
                    simple algorithm that targeted the exported Character Stats CSV files and
                    extracted information on the character from each screenplay with the highest
                    percentage of involvement. ScripThreads’ Character Stats function calculates the
                    percentage of character involvement by: A) identifying whether a character
                    appears in a scene — yes or no; B) calculating how much of the screenplay any
                    given scene takes up as a percentage; C) adding all of the percentage points for
                    the instances when a character is present. In conducting this analysis, roughly
                    one quarter of the 935 screenplays did not parse properly and we chose to
                    disregard their results. We could have opted to use ScripThreads’ Advanced
                    Settings and gone one-by-one through the screenplays that returned inaccurate
                    results, adjusting the settings to more clearly identify the way a particular
                    screenplay notes characters and scene breaks. And if we were using ScripThreads
                    for close reading, this is exactly what we would have done. However, because we
                    wanted to test how the ScripThreads prototype performed at scale, we moved
                    forward in analyzing the reduced corpus of 674 screenplays. As we continue to
                    improve the tool, we anticipate the rate of screenplays that accurately parse at
                    the computer’s first pass will increase. </p>
                <p> Out of the 674 screenplays, the median percentage of maximum character
                    involvement was 80% and the mean percentage was 78%. Only 70 of the screenplays
                    (roughly one-tenth) had a main character present in 94% or more of the
                    screenplay. This group of 70 screenplays formed the sub-set of screenplays
                    featuring a hyper-present protagonist that we analyzed in more detail.
                    Specifically, we were interested in three variables: historical era, genre, and
                    author. Which, if any, of these variables held the most significance for stories
                    featuring the lead character in every scene? </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5.1 Historical Era</head>
                <p> When we the examined the production dates of our sub-set of data, we found
                    examples of the hyper-present protagonist in screenplays ranging from 1932 to
                    the 2000s.</p>
                <p>However, the data indicates that this storytelling tradition did not become
                    prominent in American cinema until the 1940s. Out of the 189 screenplays from
                    the 1930s that we analyzed, we found only two that clearly featured a
                    hyper-present protagonist — <title rend="italic">I Am a Fugitive from a Chain
                        Gang</title> (1932) and <title rend="italic">20,000 Years in Sing
                        Sing</title> (1932).<note> We should acknowledge that more screenplays from
                        the 1930s failed to parse properly than screenplays from any other decade.
                        Nevertheless, we stand by our analysis and claim that the ever-present
                        protagonist became more common in American cinema beginning in the
                        1930s.</note> These two outliers are both social problem films produced by
                    Warner Bros. during the pre-Production Code era. Both screenplays are also set
                    in prison contexts and co-written by Brown Holmes, a point we will return to in
                    our discussion of authorship. Our historical analysis suggests that the
                    hyper-present protagonist grew far more common in Hollywood movies produced
                    during and after World War II. Our findings confirm David Bordwell’s argument
                    that Hollywood writers, directors, and producers innovated new storytelling
                    techniques during the 1940s that filmmakers have used ever since <ptr
                        target="#bordwell2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#bordwell2013"/>. Historically, this rise can be understood as part
                    of the effort of filmmakers and writers during the 1940s to produce films of
                    greater psychological realism, moral ambiguity, and experimentation in
                    storytelling. </p>
                <p> Ultimately, our historical analysis was a case in which distant reading
                    confirmed what the leading historians of film style and narrative have argued.
                    But as Matthew Jockers points out, we should not expect distant reading and
                    computational literary analysis to always overturn previous understandings.
                    There is value to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#jockers2014">bring[ing] a new type of evidence
                            and a new perspective to the matter and in so doing fortify…the existing
                            hypothesis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#jockers2014"/>
                    </cit>. Additionally, in this case, our analysis also suggests something
                    interesting about <title rend="italic">I Am a Fugitive from a Chain
                    Gang</title>, a remarkable film about a man whose life is ruined when he is
                    falsely convicted of crime and sentenced to hard labor on a chain gang in the
                    American South. Few would dispute that this film was unusual for its day, with
                    its strong social critique and bleak ending. Our analysis suggests yet another
                    unusual element that contributes to the film’s power — the protagonist (played
                    by Paul Muni) is in nearly every scene, increasing the film’s psychological
                    intensity and sense of claustrophobia.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5.2. Genre</head>
                <p> In our analysis of genre, we confirmed certain existing assumptions about film
                    storytelling and challenged others. Screenwriting guidebooks generally discuss
                    the detective movie as the genre most likely to be presented as a <soCalled>closed story,</soCalled> a storytelling
                    strategy that keeps the audience aligned with the protagonist’s point of view
                    and reveals information to the audience only at the moments when information is
                    revealed to the protagonist. In contrast, an <soCalled>open story</soCalled> is one in which the audience learns
                    information that the character does not know <ptr target="#field2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#hunter2004"/>. As we expected, several examples of the
                    hyper-present protagonist were detective films, such as <title rend="italic"
                        >Murder, My Sweet </title>(1942), <title rend="italic">On Dangerous
                        Ground</title> (1952), and <title rend="italic">8MM</title> (1999). Our
                    analysis turned up other examples of films that were essentially detective
                    stories, even though the protagonist was not officially a detective, such as
                        <title rend="italic">Across the Pacific</title> (1942). And, in the case of
                        <title rend="italic">The Siege</title> (1998), our analysis allowed us to
                    more clearly see the film’s lead investigator character and detective structure,
                    even though the film was marketed on the basis of its action sequences and
                    premise (What if the U.S. responded to a terrorist attack by placing New York
                    City under martial law?). </p>
                <p> Interestingly, though, most of the hyper-present protagonist films we found did
                    not belong to the detective genre. Numerous dramas used the <soCalled>closed story</soCalled> and hyper-present protagonist technique to
                    place the audience firmly in the perspective of a main character and amplify the
                    film’s psychological intensity (examples include <title rend="italic">Now
                        Voyager</title> [1942], <title rend="italic">Light Sleeper</title> [1992],
                        <title rend="italic">Pi</title> [1998], and the previously mentioned <title
                        rend="italic">I Am a Fugitive from a Chain Gang</title> [1932]). We also
                    found dramas that were <soCalled>open stories</soCalled> yet
                    still featured the protagonist in nearly every scene. To provide an example
                    familiar to many readers, the character of George Bailey in <title rend="italic"
                        >It’s a Wonderful Life</title> (1946) appears in nearly every scene of the
                    film. When he goes absent, though, the audience learns vital information that
                    creates a sense of dramatic irony (for example, only the audience and Mr. Potter
                    know that Uncle Billy accidentally put the bank deposit in Potter’s lap).
                    Moreover, the first half of the film contains a great deal of voice-over
                    narration that provides information that George doesn’t know — not the least of
                    which being that angels in heaven are discussing his plight and reviewing his
                    life. Yet the film also pivots to a <soCalled>closed</soCalled> storytelling
                    mode as we learn dramatic news at the same as George, such as the stroke
                    suffered by George’s father or the community’s run on the bank. Our distant
                    reading analysis of genre helped us distinguish between the presence of a
                    hyper-present protagonist and the question of how a story conveys information.
                    Additionally, the analysis reveals how films can move much more fluidly between
                        <soCalled>open</soCalled> and <soCalled>closed</soCalled> modes than most
                    screenwriting manuals would suggest. </p>
                <p> If the detective genre is especially fertile ground for the hyper-present
                    protagonist, then are there other genres in which such a character is rarely
                    found? We have yet to find any occurrences in the romantic comedy or musical (a
                    genre that frequently sets a romantic comedy story to song). The romantic
                    comedy, by its nature, depends on multiple characters and obstacles to delay
                    their happy union until their end. These conflicts and obstacles are often
                    rooted in misunderstandings, which require the audience to know information that
                    one of the characters does not know. Beyond the romantic comedy, we found that
                    comedy screenplays, in general, almost never feature a hyper-present
                    protagonist. One explanation might be that writers depend on the protagonist’s
                    absence to create situations that serve as set-ups for the jokes later delivered
                    verbally or physically by the protagonist. The very title of <title
                        rend="italic">A Night at the Opera</title> (1935), one of the comedy
                    screenplays in our dataset, is premised on the incongruity between the
                    high-class form of the opera and the low-class antics of its stars, the Marx
                    Brothers. Numerous sequences are structured to play up this incongruity — moving
                    between scenes in which the brothers are absent to set up our expectations,
                    followed by one or more of the brothers entering to disrupt the status quo and
                    deliver the joke. </p>
                <p> Only one comedy screenplay in our dataset featured a hyper-present protagonist.
                    This outlier was the Jim Carrey comedy <title rend="italic">Liar Liar</title>
                    (1997), an example of what is known in contemporary Hollywood as “high concept”
                    (a movie with a story that can be distilled and marketed to audiences in 25
                    words or less). In the case of <title rend="italic">Liar Liar</title>, the high
                    concept is, <q>What if a hotshot lawyer could not
                        tell a lie for 24 hours due to his son’s birthday wish?</q> The premise
                    enables screenwriters Paul Guay and Stephen Mazur to generate nearly all the
                    jokes with the protagonist present. This comedy depends on incongruity, but it’s
                    different than the incongruity derived from placing the Marx Brothers at fancy
                    restaurants and the opera. Instead, the incongruity comes from the difference
                    between Fletcher’s (Jim Carrey’s) compulsive lying before his son’s wish and how
                    he must adapt after he can no longer tell a lie. This example demonstrates that
                    a film’s concept (and perhaps the desire of producers to fully capitalize on
                    their highly paid star) can override the pattern of character presence typical
                    for a particular genre. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5.3 Authorship</head>
                <p> Finally, we explored the question of authorship as it relates to patterns of the
                    protagonist’s presence. Do some screenwriters have a tendency to write films
                    that focus on one protagonist and place that character in nearly every scene?
                    The answer, we found, was yes. As noted earlier, screenwriter Brown Holmes
                    co-wrote the two outliers we identified from the 1930s, <title rend="italic">I
                        Am a Fugitive from a Chain Gang</title> and <title rend="italic">20,000
                        Years in Sing Sing</title>. This finding suggests that Holmes may have had
                    an especially important role in dramatically structuring and writing the two
                    films, despite working as a contract writer for Warner Bros. and sharing the
                    writing credit with co-authors on both screenplays. As we continue our research,
                    we plan to integrate ScripThreads with other modes of computational analysis and
                    examine more co-authored Warner Bros. screenplays from the 1930s and 40s. We
                    believe the result might offer a better sense of the individual contributions of
                    creative artists on the highly collaborative medium of film. We may find that
                    some writers contributed especially strongly to a film’s dialogue, while others,
                    like Brown Holmes, left major contributions to a film’s dramatic structure.</p>
                <p> As we examined the AFSO corpus for hyper-present protagonists, one author leapt
                    out at us for his tendency to structure films with a main character present in
                    nearly every scene. The AFSO corpus contains the screenplays for fifteen films
                    that were either written or co-written by Paul Schrader, who is best known for
                    writing and directing dark, character-oriented dramas, such as <title
                        rend="italic">American Gigolo</title> (1980) and <title rend="italic"
                        >Affliction </title>(1997), and writing some of the best films directed by
                    Martin Scorsese, including <title rend="italic">Taxi Driver</title> (1976),
                        <title rend="italic">Raging Bull</title> (1980), and <title rend="italic"
                        >The Last Temptation of Christ </title>(1988). Out of this group of fifteen
                    films, eight films feature a main character present in 94% or more of the
                    screenplay, and only two films place the main character in less than 80% of the
                    screenplay (the two outliers are <title rend="italic">Obsession</title> [1976],
                    a Hitchcockian thriller directed by Brian DePalma, and <title rend="italic">Blue
                        Collar</title> [1978], which Schrader directed about three auto workers who
                    rob their corrupt union). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure14">
                    <head>Increasing graphs of fifteen produced screenplays either written or
                        co-written by Paul Schrader. The graphs were superimposed onto one another
                        using ImageMagik.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Schrader’s tendency to frame stories around single characters who are almost
                    always present can be seen in <ref target="#figure14">Figure 14</ref>, which
                    superimposes the fifteen increasing graphs of Schrader’s screenplays onto one
                    another. The consistency of Schrader’s approach is clear from the cluster of red
                    lines (each one representing the most present character from a different
                    Schrader film) thrusting diagonally in a nearly straight line. For a point of
                    comparison, we can turn back to Lawrence Kasdan. <ref target="#figure15">Figure
                        15</ref> superimposes the seven Kasdan screenplays that are available in the
                    AFSO corpus. The Kasdan image shows a screenwriter who works across numerous
                    genres and utilizes a wide variety of storytelling approaches — one film
                    featuring a hyper-present protagonist (<title rend="italic">Mumford
                    </title>[1999]), one multi-character drama with no singular protagonist (<title
                        rend="italic">The Big Chill</title> [1983]), and several films that fall
                    in-between. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure15">
                    <head>Increasing graphs of seven screenplays written or co-written by Lawrence
                        Kasdan. The graphs were superimposed onto one another using
                        ImageMagik.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> In some ways, <ref target="#figure14">Figure 14</ref> provides an illustration
                    for what film critics and scholars already assume about Schrader: he is a
                    filmmaker who writes character studies about men who are psychologically and/or
                    existentially anguished. <title rend="italic">American Gigolo</title> (1980),
                        <title rend="italic">Light Sleeper</title> (1992), and <title rend="italic"
                        >Affliction</title> (1997) are all films that Schrader wrote and directed
                    that fit this paradigm. Schrader calls his protagonists <soCalled>existential
                        heroes</soCalled> and, in a widely quoted interview with Garry Wills,
                    remarked, <quote rend="inline" source="#schrader2006">all my life has been
                        dedicated to the existential hero, and the existential hero seems to have
                        come to the end of his path, replaced by the ironic hero</quote>
                    <ptr target="#schrader2006"/>. However, there is no inherent reason why an
                    existential hero needs to appear in nearly every single scene of a movie. As
                    noted earlier, Lawrence Kasdan’s <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon </title>keeps
                    its existential protagonist, Mack, absent for numerous scenes, even though he
                    appears in far more scenes than any other character. Similarly, the existential
                    heroes in films directed by Ingmar Bergman and Woody Allen generally exist
                    within an ensemble of characters. In Bergman and Allen films, the protagonist
                    will go absent to facilitate scenes focusing on supporting characters, who may
                    serve as foils to the existential hero, address the story’s major themes, and/or
                    advance the plot. There is a long history of this practice in literature, as
                    well. Tolstoy’s <title rend="italic">Anna Karenina</title> would have far less
                    to say about love, society, politics, and life’s meaning without the narrative
                    of Levin and Kitty playing out in parallel to Anna’s story. The ScripThreads’
                    increasing graph visualizations of Scharder’s work reveal that a defining
                    characteristic of Schrader’s existential hero is his hyper-presence. The
                    audience stays with the existential hero throughout the entire film. Ingmar
                    Bergman makes films that address the existential themes of Sartre and Camus, but
                    Schrader is the filmmaker who structures his narratives more similarly to their
                    novels — following the <soCalled>closed
                        story</soCalled> model that keeps the audience aligned with the protagonist’s
                    point-of-view. </p>
                <p> Schrader’s best known screenplays follow the hyper-present, existential
                    protagonist model we have described. However, a more heterogeneous portrait of
                    Schrader as an author emerges when we examine his twelve unproduced screenplays
                    in the AFSO corpus. To be clear, these are screenplays written by Schrader that
                    were never made into films. <ref target="#figure16">Figure 16</ref> shows the
                    superimposed increasing graphs of these 12 screenplays. This group of
                    screenplays includes four hyper-present protagonist scripts: three
                    music-oriented biopics (<title rend="italic">Dream Lover: The Bobby Darin
                        Story</title>, <title rend="italic">Eight Scenes from the Life of Hank
                        Williams</title>, and <title rend="italic">Gershwin</title>); and one
                    detective film (<title rend="italic">The Investigator</title>), a genre that we
                    know is comparatively likely to have a hyper-present protagonist. What is more
                    surprising is that seven out of the twelve unproduced screenplays place the
                    protagonist in less than 80% of the script. And three screenplays make the
                    protagonist present in less than 70% (Schrader’s two produced outliers, <title
                        rend="italic">Obsession </title>and <title rend="italic">Blue
                    Collar</title>, are both higher at 72% and 75% respectively). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure16">
                    <head>Increasing graphs of twelve unproduced screenplays written or co-written
                        by Paul Schrader. The graphs were superimposed onto one another using
                        ImageMagik.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Schrader’s unproduced project in which the protagonist is least present (59%) is
                    his script for a retelling of <title rend="italic">Snow White </title>(<ref
                        target="#figure17">Figure 17</ref>). Here, we see an interesting dynamic
                    between an author’s general tendencies and the demands of a particular project.
                    The <title rend="italic">Snow White</title> tale depends on dramatic irony — the
                    audience knows the apple is poisonous, but the protagonist does not. Moreover,
                    the antagonist needs scenes without the protagonist present to interact with the
                    magic mirror, one of the most iconic elements of the myth. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure17">
                    <head>Increasing graph of Paul Schrader’s unproduced screenplay for <title
                            rend="italic">Snow White</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> The increasing graphs of Schrader’s unproduced work open up a series of
                    questions that we plan to investigate further. What is the relationship between
                    genre and authorship in how narratives are structured? How do certain genres or
                    stories override a screenwriter’s established narrative techniques? Finally, how
                    do industrial and cultural assumptions about a particular screenwriter shape the
                    types of projects the writer is offered and that make it into production? By
                    examining Schrader’s unproduced works at a distance, we can speculate that
                    industry assumptions about what constitutes a <soCalled>Paul Schrader
                        film</soCalled> — namely, a dark, existential character study — may have
                    made studios and financiers more reluctant to produce screenplays by Schrader
                    that fell outside of this paradigm.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Conclusion</head>
                <p> In this article, we have introduced the ScripThreads tool and demonstrated how
                    it can be used for closely analyzing one screenplay (<title rend="italic">Grand
                        Canyon</title>) and analyzing a much larger group of screenplays to look for
                    a pattern. ScripThreads parses screenplays and extracts data about character
                    presence and interactions, then offers users statistical CSV files and a series
                    of 3D and 2D visualizations that present the data in a time-based manner. The
                    tool is not without its limitations. ScripThreads does not visualize act breaks,
                    shifts in spatial location, or a protagonist’s journey toward a particular goal.
                    Yet the data the tool offers can be quite telling. It can reveal details of
                    character presence and character co-occurrences that humans are prone to forget
                    or never remember in the first place. </p>
                <p> In using ScripThreads to closely analyze a single film, the continuities and
                    differences between the viewer’s perception and the computer’s visualizations is
                    a powerful starting point for uncovering storytelling techniques and better
                    understanding cognitive reception. In using ScripThreads to analyze a large
                    group of screenplays, the visualizations and CSV output files allow researchers
                    to recognize patterns without having prior knowledge of the films. To draw
                    accurate and meaningful conclusions, though, some domain expertise in film
                    history is essential (just as a researcher would want some knowledge of 19<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>-century literature before making arguments about
                    the century based on topic modeling 100 Victorian novels). Whether applied
                    toward close ready or distant reading, ScripThreads is meant to help researchers
                    gain a richer understanding of the text or texts they are studying. This is a
                    tool to aid Humanities scholars in analysis and interpretation, not a substitute
                    for screenwriting and criticism. </p>
                <p> ScripThreads offers one additional affordance — the ability to quickly visualize
                    the narrative structure of an unproduced screenplay. Films and television
                    programs play out their stories visually in sequences of photographed and edited
                    action; a produced screenplay has already been visualized for the screen.
                    However, due to the difficulty and expense of making a film, the vast majority
                    of screenplays are never produced, never visualized in this fashion. The
                    increasing graphs of Schrader’s unproduced screenplays (<ref target="#figure16"
                        >Figure 16</ref>) provide what may be the first transformative
                    visualizations of these twelve works. The graphs allow us to quickly recognize
                    one way (the protagonist’s level of presence) that some of these stories differ
                    from Schrader’s better known screenplays. What if we could apply a similar
                    analysis to the screenplay libraries of Hollywood’s studios, producers, and
                    talent agencies? The results would yield not simply graphs of character
                    presences, co-occurrences, and absences, but transformative renderings of
                    thousands of stories that have remained absent from audiences. We would no
                    longer be visualizing American film history; we would be visualizing a history
                    that might have been.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="abello2012" label="Abello, Broadwell, and Tangherlini 2012">Abello,
                    J., Broadwell, P., &amp; Tangherlini, T. R. (2012). “Computational
                    Folkloristics.” <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>, 55(7),
                    60-70. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="afso" label="AFSO 2009">American Film Scripts Online (2009). Alexander
                    Street Press. <ref
                        target="http://alexanderstreet.com/products/american-film-scripts"
                        >http://alexanderstreet.com/products/american-film-scripts</ref> (accessed 1
                    November 2013). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bordwell2006" label="Bordwell 2006">Bordwell, D. (2006). <title
                        rend="italic">The Way Hollywood Tells It</title>. Berkeley: University of
                    California Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bordwell2013" label="Bordwell 2013">Bordwell, D. (2013). <title
                        rend="quotes">The 1940s, mon amour.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Observations on Film Art [Blog]</title>. <ref
                        target="http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/2013/03/28/the-1940s-mon-amour/"
                        >http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/2013/03/28/the-1940s-mon-amour/</ref>
                    (accessed 14 May 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="field2009" label="Field 2009">Field, S. (2009). <title rend="italic"
                        >Going to the Movies: A Personal Journey Through Four Decades of Modern
                        Film</title>. New York: Random House. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hagh-shenas2007" label="Hagh-Shenas et al. 2007">Hagh-Shenas, H.;
                    Sunghee Kim; Interrante, V.; Healey, C., (2007) <title rend="quotes">Weaving
                        Versus Blending: a quantitative assessment of the information carrying
                        capacities of two alternative methods for conveying multivariate data with
                        color.</title> <title rend="italic">Visualization and Computer Graphics,
                        IEEE Transactions on</title>, vol. 13, no. 6, pp. 1270, 1277, Nov.-Dec. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hunter2004" label="Hunter 2004">Hunter, L. (2004). <title
                        rend="italic">Lew Hunter's Screenwriting 434: The Industry's Premier Teacher
                        Reveals the Secrets of the Successful Screenplay</title>. New York:
                    Penguin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2014" label="Jockers 2014">Jockers, M. (2014). <title
                        rend="italic">Text Analysis with R for Students of Literature</title>. New
                    York: Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kasdan2001" label="Kasdan and Kasdan 2001">Kasdan, L. and Kasdan, M.
                    (2001). <title rend="italic">Grand Canyon</title> (screenplay). American Film
                    Scripts Online. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2012" label="Manovich 2012">Manovich, L. (2012). How to
                    Compare One Million Images? <title rend="italic">Understanding the Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Ed. David M. Berry. Basingstoke, Hampshire, England and
                    New York: Palgrave Macmillan. 249-278.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marinov2011" label="Marinov 2011">Marinov, S. (2011). <title
                        rend="quotes">Making Plays: Comparative Structural Analysis of Writing for
                        Stage and Screen.</title> 4th Screenwriting Research Network International
                    Conference in Brussels, Belguim. September 2011. (Unpublished paper).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marinovstitts2013a" label="Marinov and Stitts 2013a">Marinov, S. and
                    Stitts, B. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Development of Screenwriting Analysis
                        Software Based on Pfister’s Theory of Verbal Communication.</title>
                    Screenwriting Research Network International Conference in Madison, Wisconsin.
                    August 2011. (Unpublished paper.)</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marinovstitts2013b" label="Marinov and Stitts 2013b">Marinov, S. and
                    Stitts, B. (2013). <title rend="italic">Screenplay Owl: Screenplay Analysis
                        Software</title>. <ref target="http://dramaticanalysis.com/owl/"
                        >http://dramaticanalysis.com/owl/</ref> (accessed 1 November 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mckie2014" label="McKie 2014">McKie, S. (2014). <title rend="italic"
                        >ScriptFAQ: Screenplay Analytics</title>. <ref
                        target="http://phd.tripos.biz/">http://phd.tripos.biz/</ref> (accessed 14
                    May 2014). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2000" label="Moretti 2000">Moretti, F. (2000) <title
                        rend="quotes">Conjectures on World Literature.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Left Review</title>. Jan-Feb 2000. 54-66.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murtagh2011" label="Murtagh, Ganz, and Reddington 2011">Murtagh, F.,
                    Ganz, A., and Reddington, J. (2011). New methods of analysis and semantics in
                    support of interactivity. <title rend="italic">Entertainment Computing</title>,
                    2: 115-121.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="polan2001" label="Polan 2001">Polan, D. (2001). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Auteur Desire.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Screening the past</title>, 12, <ref
                        target="http://www.latrobe.edu.au/www/screeningthepast/firstrelease/fr0301/dpfr12a.htm"
                        >http://www.latrobe.edu.au/www/screeningthepast/firstrelease/fr0301/dpfr12a.htm</ref>
                    (accessed 18 October 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roberts-smith2013" label="Roberts-Smith et al. 2013">Roberts-Smith,
                    J., et al. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Visualizing Theatrical Text: From
                        Watching the Script to the Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 7 (3). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/3/000166/000166.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/3/000166/000166.html</ref>
                    (accessed 5 May 2014). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schrader2006" label="Schrader and Wills 2006">Schrader, P. and Wills,
                    G. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Paul Schrader: An Interview with Garry
                        Wills.</title> In <title rend="italic">Shouts and Whispers: Twenty-one
                        Writers Speak about Their Writing and Their Faith</title>. Edited by
                    Jennifer L. Holber. 113-119. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="simeone2012" label="Simeone 2012">Simeone, Michael. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualizing Topic Models with Force-Directed Graphs.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Stone and the Shell</title> [Blog]. 2 December 2014.
                        <ref
                        target="http://tedunderwood.com/2012/12/02/visualizing-topic-models-with-force-directed-graphs/"
                        >http://tedunderwood.com/2012/12/02/visualizing-topic-models-with-force-directed-graphs/</ref>
                    (accessed 15 May 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sinclair2013" label="Sinclair, Ruecker, and Radzikowska 2013"
                    >Sinclair, S., Ruecker, R., and Radzikowska, M. (2013). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Information Visualization for Humanities Scholars.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Literary Studies in the Digital Age: An Evolving
                        Anthology</title>. Ed. Kenneth M. Price and Ray Siemens. MLA Commons. <ref
                        target="http://dlsanthology.commons.mla.org/information-visualization-for-humanities-scholars/"
                        >http://dlsanthology.commons.mla.org/information-visualization-for-humanities-scholars/</ref>
                    (accessed 14 April 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanahasi2012" label="Tanahasi and Ma 2012">Tanahasi, Y., and Ma,
                    Kwan-Liu. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Design Considerations for Optimizing
                        Storyline Visualizations.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions On Visualization And Computer
                        Graphics</title>, Vol. 18, No. 12: 2679-2688.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thompson1999" label="Thompson 1999">Thompson, K. (1999). <title
                        rend="italic">Storytelling in the New Hollywood: Understanding Classical
                        Narrative Technique</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="xkcd2009" label="Xkcd 2009">Xkcd. (Nov 2009). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Movie Narrative Charts,</title>
                    <ref target="http://xkcd.com/657/">http://xkcd.com/657/</ref> (accessed 2013
                    October 22).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
