<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Managing an Established Digital Humanities Project: Principles and
               Practices from the Twentieth Year of the William Blake Archive</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Ashley <dhq:family>Reed</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of North Carolina</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>reeda@email.unc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ashley Reed served as Project Manager of the William Blake Archive from
                     2007-2013 and now serves as Consultant for Special Projects. She recently
                     defended her dissertation on Protestant theology and personal agency in
                     nineteenth-century American fiction and will receive her PhD in English and
                     Comparative Literature from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in
                     May 2014.</p>
               </dhq:bio>



            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000174</idno>
            <idno type="volume">008</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2014-04-17">17 April 2014</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change who="DD" when="2018-07-30">@source checkinge</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>

            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>Scholars and practitioners of the digital humanities generally recognize the
               importance of solid project management and oversight. But coursework and publications
               related to DH project management tend to focus heavily on the difficulties of
               planning and launching a new project rather than the challenges of maintaining an
               established one. Meanwhile, online advice for would-be managers is couched in the
               language of <soCalled>tips and tricks</soCalled> or <soCalled>steps for
                  beginners</soCalled>. Together these phenomena downplay the professional skills
               needed to successfully manage a project while suggesting that project management is
               necessary only in the beginning stages of an endeavor. They may even give the
               impression that scholarship in the digital humanities is inherently ephemeral.
               Through a case study of project management practices at the William Blake Archive,
               which began publishing electronic scholarly editions in 1996, this essay details the
               challenges and rewards of managing an established digital humanities project.
               Managers of mature projects may be called upon to oversee expansions in scope and
               mission, research and recommend new features and tools, grow or shrink the number of
               project staff, seek out alternate sources of support when early grants run out,
               maintain continuity as collaborators join and leave the project, and develop new
               workflows and procedures to reflect these and other changes.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->

            <p>As your project matures your management must evolve. Management strategies for
               established and ongoing DH endeavors, as practiced by the William Blake Archive.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>When project management principles are made explicit among digital humanists, they
               are often presented with little project-specific grounding and usually from a
               beginner’s perspective. At THATCamp sessions, summer institutes, and other meetings
               of scholars working in or intrigued by the digital humanities, audiences are offered
                  <q>basic principles,</q>
               <q>tips and tricks,</q> or <q>top-ten lists</q> that give the impression that project
               management is a) simple and b) primarily a problem at the early stages of a project.
               Most of the roundtables, seminars, forums, and blog posts devoted to digital
               humanities project management, such as Bethany Nowviskie’s <title rend="quotes">Ten
                  Rules for Humanities Scholars New to Project Management,</title> Brian Croxall’s
                  <title rend="quotes">12 Basic Principles of Project Management,</title> and Sharon
               M. Leon’s more extensive <title rend="quotes">Project Management for
                  Humanists,</title> are concerned with how to plan and launch a new project rather
               than how to guide an ongoing one. The various <q>PM boot camps</q> that appear on the
               programs of THATCamps and DH conferences (or traditional humanities conferences
               hoping to attract a DH crowd) also usually operate on the assumption that
               participants are launching new projects and that they bring to the table little or no
               prior project management experience.<note>There are a few exceptions, of course:
                  Bethany Nowviskie and Dot Porter’s <title rend="quotes">Graceful Degradation
                     Survey</title> gathered information from collaborators on digital humanities
                  projects in an attempt to determine how long-term projects can best be maintained
                  during periods of change and transition. Preliminary results of the survey were
                  presented at Digital Humanities 2010, but as of this writing no complete analysis
                  has yet been published. And Daniel Pitti’s essay on <title rend="quotes">Designing
                     Sustainable Projects and Publications</title> is a useful resource that takes a
                  long-term view of project design, planning, and management.</note> Even intensive
               seminars like those offered at various summer and winter institutes tend to focus
               heavily on project planning rather than project management.<note>Lynne Siemens’
                  excellent course on Issues in Large Project Planning and Management, for instance,
                  skews heavily toward the first part of its title: it is 80-90% project planning
                  and 10-20% project management. I was fortunate to take Dr. Siemens’s course as an
                  attendee of the June 2012 Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI) at the
                  University of Victoria. As Lynne has done more to emphasize the professional role
                  of project managers in digital humanities scholarship than perhaps anyone else —
                  conducting on-site studies and publishing numerous articles on the topic — I
                  assume that her course’s emphasis on project planning over project management is a
                  response to student demand rather than a reflection on project managers as
                  scholarly professionals.</note> Meanwhile, scholars and collaborators involved in
               ongoing DH endeavors find that many of the questions raised by these articles and
               seminars have long since been answered, while the challenges of managing a project
               that is well past the planning stages go largely undiscussed.</p>
            <p>While these <q>just for beginners</q> offerings perhaps reflect the recent surge in
               attention and popularity experienced by the digital humanities — many scholars are
               newly interested in launching digital humanities projects and will need at least
               rudimentary management skills in order to do so — they can also give the mistaken
               impression that digital humanities projects are inherently disposable: that long-term
               project management is unnecessary because creating a project is more important than
               developing or sustaining it. This impression, in turn, contributes to the phenomenon
               that Nowviskie has characterized as the <title rend="quotes">Eternal
                  September</title> of the digital humanities: the sense among those just coming to
               DH that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2012">all of this is new and… that the
                     current scene is all there is</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nowviskie2012"/>
               </cit>. But funding agencies that support digital humanities scholarship appear to be
               moving away from models based on project proliferation and ephemerality and toward an
               emphasis on preservation and permanence — at least of data, if not of entire
                  projects.<note>A 2011 Digital Humanities Questions &amp; Answers exchange, for
                  instance, centered on how to <q>future-proof</q> a project to assuage granting
                  agencies’ and administrators’ fears that funded projects would simply disappear
                  after a few years. See <ref
                     target="http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/what-does-it-mean-to-future-proof-a-dh-project"
                     >http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/what-does-it-mean-to-future-proof-a-dh-project</ref>.</note>
               The NEH Office of Digital Humanities’ decision to require a data management plan from
               all potential grantees, for instance, will likely encourage scholars building digital
               projects to consider more deeply the eventual fate of their work.<note>See the NEH’s
                  guidelines at <ref
                     target="http://www.neh.gov/files/grants/data_management_plans_2012.pdf"
                     >http://www.neh.gov/files/grants/data_management_plans_2012.pdf</ref>. I do not
                  mean to suggest that all digital humanities projects should be permanently
                  maintained at the behest of granting agencies. But if funding agencies are going
                  to favor long-term projects and value the preservation of data, digital humanists
                  who hope to appeal to these funding agencies would do well to cultivate project
                  management practices that facilitate these goals.</note> While not every project
               needs to last forever, some funding agencies may soon begin insisting on the
               long-term sustainability of projects as a condition of their funding, making the
               question of how to maintain and manage an ongoing project a more urgent one.<note>Not
                  all projects need to remain active any more than all monographs need to become
                  standard reading in their fields. (A librarian once said to me, <quote
                     rend="inline" source="#private">Of course we’re all glad the Blake Archive is
                     still around, but if you’d built it in, say, Second Life we’d want it to
                     disappear as soon as possible.</quote>) But terminated projects and their data
                  should remain accessible whenever possible, for the same reason that libraries
                  maintain copies of out-of print books: because they are evidence of scholarship
                  completed and may be of use to future researchers. But the long-term maintenance
                  of such projects requires different management practices than those required for
                  print preservation or for early-stage project development.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This article seeks to fill a gap in scholarly discussions of project management for
               the digital humanities by discussing the challenges, not of launching a new project,
               but of managing a mature one. It does so through a case study of project management
               activities at the William Blake Archive, one of the longest-running digital
               humanities projects in existence. The Blake Archive, launched in 1993 at the
               University of Virginia’s Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities,
               published its first digital scholarly editions in 1996 and now includes over 120
               electronic editions of works by William Blake.<note> Founded by Morris Eaves, Robert
                  Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, the Archive published its first online digital
                  editions in November 1996 and its most recent (as of this writing) in July 2013.
                  Its first publication included five complete copies of Blake’s illuminated books:
                  three copies of <title rend="italic">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>
                  and two copies of <title rend="italic">The Book of Thel</title>. The Archive now
                  contains eighty-two complete copies of the illuminated books, as well as all of
                  Blake’s watercolor illustrations of the works of John Milton, Thomas Gray, and
                  Dante Alighieri; sketches, paintings, and engravings illustrating the book of Job;
                  manuscript works including <title rend="italic">An Island in the Moon</title> and
                  the <title rend="italic">Pickering Manuscript</title>; commercial engravings for
                  Mary Wollstonecraft’s <title rend="italic">Original Stories from Real
                  Life</title>, John Gabriel Stedman’s <title rend="italic">Narrative of a Five
                     Years’ Expedition Against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</title>, and <title
                     rend="italic">The Pastorals of Virgil</title>; and scores of watercolors and
                  temperas illustrating passages from the Bible — over 120 digital editions in all.
                  The Archive’s other scholarly apparatus include biographies, bibliographies,
                  museum and library collection lists, a demonstration of Blake’s illuminated
                  printing process, and the Archive’s own technical and project documentation, among
                  other items.</note> As Project Manager of this ongoing and actively publishing
               digital archive,<note>I began working with the Blake Archive in August 2005, when I
                  was assigned to a position as Joseph Viscomi’s research assistant during my first
                  year of graduate study. I brought to the job several years of experience in
                  project management and media production, and in June 2007 I took over as Project
                  Manager of the Archive.</note> I will offer insights into the challenges of
               managing a digital humanities project that is approaching its twentieth year. These
               challenges differ significantly from those of launching a new project but should
               nevertheless be considered by scholars just beginning their DH endeavors. I begin
               with a discussion of the important but sometimes hidden role that project management
               skills play in successful DH projects, and then follow with a set of general
               observations about managing mature projects, illustrated with specific examples from
               recent activities at the Blake Archive.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Making the Implicit Explicit: Project Management for the Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>Project management is often described as a <q>soft skill</q> and placed in opposition
               to — or in competition for scarce resources with — the <q>hard skills</q> of
               programming and software development. In a 2012 <title rend="italic">DH
                  Answers</title> discussion on <title rend="quotes">Founding staff for a new DH
                  Center,</title> for instance, several discussants asserted that a project manager
               is a relatively low-priority hire for a new DH initiative; one respondent asserted
               that because <quote rend="inline" source="#dhcenter2013">most academics already have
                  experience managing projects,</quote> programmers and developers should be hired
               first and a manager only later <ptr target="#dhcenter2013"/>. Early Project Bamboo
               documentation refers to best practices for project management as <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#ucbconference2013">the softest kinds of standards,</quote> placing them
               behind <quote rend="inline" source="#ucbconference2013">domain-specific technical
                  standards</quote> in terms of importance <ptr target="#ucbconference2013"
                  />.<note>Project Bamboo is <quote rend="inline" source="#bamboo2013">a
                     multi-institutional collaborative initiative to guide the creation of shared,
                     interoperable tools, services, and content to meet the real needs of humanities
                     researchers</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bamboo2013"/>.</note> The distinction between <q>hard</q> and
                  <q>soft</q> skills or standards imports a number of unfortunate connotations; a
               better formulation might center on the difference between explicit and implicit
               skills. While a new hire or graduate student’s mastery of a programming language can
               be codified in certifications or a portfolio of existing projects, it is much more
               difficult to test for the capabilities — including organization, planning and
               follow-through, prioritization, grant administration, human resources management, and
               conflict resolution — that are essential in a project manager. If you want to assess
               someone’s technical skills, you can always invite them to a hack-a-thon. There is no
               such thing as a manage-a-thon.</p>
            <p>As a position defined, in most cases, largely in terms of implicit skills, project
               management can be usefully placed in a category with those forms of <q>material
                  labor</q> defined by Helen Burgess and Jeanne Hamming that encompass <quote
                  rend="block" source="#burgess2013">both physical movement and the kinds of
                     <q>material</q> actions necessary to provide an infrastructure for digital
                  media. On an immediate level, these actions can be thought of as a nodal network
                  of bodies and machines in which machines <emph>combine with</emph> humans to
                  perform tasks…. In addition, we have the even wider infrastructural support
                  necessary for producing such media objects: the institutional search for grants,
                  the subvention of copyright clearances, the securing of financial support for and
                  mentoring of graduate students, and [the coordination of] technical assistance
                  provided by, variously, presses, contract programmers, videographers, and
                  animators. <ptr target="#burgess2013" loc="par. 8"/>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Such skills and activities are generally understood, Burgess and Hamming note, as
               related to the form of a project rather than its content, and thus are often
               overlooked or even denigrated under scholarly models that elevate content (writing
                  <emph>about</emph> new media) over form (the production <emph>of</emph> new
               media). The importance of project management for digital humanities scholarship thus
               risks demotion on several fronts: because project management skills fall under the
               heading of neither subject matter expertise nor technical expertise — both much more
               explicit and quantifiable modes of knowledge than the implicit skills of project
               management — they often go unexamined, and because they primarily affect the form
               rather than the content of a project, they can be underappreciated according to
               traditional evaluative models for scholarly work. </p>
            <p>But it is precisely those practices and standards that are most hidden from immediate
               view — those considered to be implicit, assumed, or already mastered — that should be
               most assiduously excavated and explored by scholars wishing to further the
               collaborative work of the digital humanities. This is perhaps especially true when
               the tasks of project management are performed, not by a professional hired
               specifically for the purpose, but by a project’s principal investigator or by
               programmers or developers who are expected to manage themselves. Making explicit the
               tasks and aptitudes required for good project management can help to reduce the
               frustration felt by principal investigators or developers who find themselves
               unexpectedly occupied with organizational tasks and stakeholder relationships that
               seemingly have little to do with researching content or writing code. Once these
               implicit tasks and expectations are made explicit, it becomes easier to recognize how
               indispensable they are, whether a team has one member or 100.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Managing an Established DH Project: Observations from the William Blake
               Archive</head>
            <p>In the following subsections I offer some general principles, gleaned from my work at
               the William Blake Archive, that demonstrate how the management of a mature and
               ongoing project differs from that of a newly established one. While these principles
               may not apply to all established projects — there is considerable difference, for
               instance, between maintaining a static project that is still in existence but no
               longer being actively developed and one that, like the Archive, is still growing and
               changing — I believe they can provide guidance to project managers (as well as
               content providers, developers, and other collaborators) who have moved beyond the
               planning stage and are anticipating a long relationship with their ongoing
               project.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Questions of Ontology and Epistemology Never Go Away</head>
               <p>Good digital scholarship, like good analog scholarship, will never be finished.
                  This does not simply mean that digital projects will always need upgrading (though
                  that will certainly be the case).<note>We have done our share of upgrading at the
                     Archive: from WBA 1.0 to WBA 2.0, from SGML to XML, from DynaWeb to eXist, and
                     then to later iterations of eXist. <q>WBA 2.0</q> was the Archive’s first major
                     site redesign, occurring in 2001. It streamlined site organization and featured
                     the launch of the new Compare and Navigator tools. At this point the Archive’s
                     digital editions were still created in the Standard Generalized Markup Language
                     (SGML); the transition to Extensible Markup Language (XML) began in 2005 and
                     was completed in May of 2006. The XML conversion also necessitated a change
                     from the DynaWeb SGML server to eXist, an open-source native XML database. The
                     Archive currently uses eXist version 1.4.</note> It means that a project’s ways
                  of being and knowing will be subjected to constant scrutiny as time goes on and
                  new data are incorporated. At a 2012 roundtable on digital humanities and digital
                  pedagogy at the conference for C19: The Society of Nineteenth-Century
                  Americanists, Kenneth Price raised the question of how scholars <q>know</q> their
                  subjects. Speaking of the challenges facing the Walt Whitman Archive as its
                  editors encounter objects like Whitman’s grocery lists or, even more
                  problematically, letters and official correspondence transcribed by Whitman but
                  composed by others, Price wondered, who is the Whitman we <q>know</q> in the
                  context of the Whitman Archive? Is it Whitman’s handwriting? Whitman’s mind? </p>
               <p>I would argue that such questions, about how we know our subjects, are endemic to
                  ongoing digital humanities projects, whether those projects archive a particular
                  author’s works, transcribe and translate ancient documents, investigate and
                  represent geospatial data, or comb through massive textual corpora. <title
                     rend="quotes">Knowing</title> is not the outcome of scholarly endeavors; it is
                  a process that is furthered collaboratively by members of a project team (and by
                  its users), and that process will continue and change for as long as the project
                  survives.</p>
               <p>At the Blake Archive, the Blake that we know is Blake-as-craftsman. The Archive’s
                  earliest publications sought to make available to scholars digital editions that
                  would reflect the unique artistic processes that Blake used to create his
                  illuminated books, and so our most basic ontological units are the
                     <emph>work</emph>, the <emph>copy</emph>, and the <emph>object</emph>:
                  art-historical terms that, in the case of Blake’s work, exist on a kind of sliding
                  scale from the theoretical to the material.<note>
                     <emph>Work</emph>, <emph>copy</emph>, and <emph>object</emph> are terms
                     specific (though not exclusive) to Blake studies. They all refer to Blake’s own
                     productions; the <emph>copy</emph> in this case is not to be confused with the
                     digital surrogates presented in the electronic editions at
                     blakearchive.org.</note> The <emph>work</emph> is largely an editorial concept:
                     <title rend="italic">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>, for instance, is
                  a work by Blake that we, as editors and readers, recognize only by virtue of the
                  nine complete and individually printed <emph>copies</emph> in existence. Each of
                  these copies is made up of twenty-seven <emph>objects</emph> printed on paper from
                  a set of copper plates and arranged in an order that need not remain consistent
                  among copies. (There are also three additional copies of the <title rend="italic"
                     >Marriage</title> consisting of only three or four objects each.) The texts and
                  images that make up each of these objects can also vary greatly depending on
                  whether and how Blake inked each of the copper plates, what colors he used, and
                  whether he added or altered the objects with pen or wash after printing. In other
                  words, there is no definitive copy or edition of the work known as <title
                     rend="italic">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>. </p>
               <p>Confusing as this may seem, in an illuminated book the distinction between the
                  work, the copy, and the object is actually relatively clear, and is represented
                  hierarchically in the Archive’s three-level structure, in which users progress via
                  hyperlink from a list of Blake’s works, to a list of available copies of a
                  particular work (<title rend="italic">The Songs of Innocence and of
                     Experience</title>, for example), to a list of objects in a particular copy
                  (such as copy Z), and finally to an individual object (say, <title rend="quotes"
                     >Infant Joy</title>). But these ontological distinctions have become less
                  obvious as the Archive has begun acquiring and publishing Blake’s works in other
                  media, including engravings, watercolors, tempera paintings, manuscripts, and
                  letters. A watercolor drawing such as <title rend="quotes">The Great Red Dragon
                     and the Woman Clothed with the Sun,</title> for instance, is a one-of-a-kind
                  creation in which the work, the copy, and the object are one and the same; Blake’s
                  notebook, in which he sketched preliminary drawings and drafted verse and prose,
                  is a manuscript work that exists in only one copy made up of multiple objects. The
                  matter of ontology extends to every aspect of the Archive’s design, from
                  individual object view pages to our main index: since the Archive’s basic
                  organizing principle is the medium of the work in question, image filenames
                  include designators like <q>WC</q> for watercolor and <q>MS</q> for manuscript,
                  and the site’s table of contents is arranged by medium, with illuminated books
                  followed by commercial book illustrations, then separate prints, then drawings and
                  paintings, then manuscripts and typographic works. Under such conditions, issues
                  of classification and organization must be perpetually renegotiated: how, for
                  instance, should we classify a book of poetry composed by Blake, printed for him
                  by others, and then emended in Blake’s hand? Is this a typographic edition or a
                  manuscript?</p>
               <p>Questions of classification are, of course, intimately related to problems of
                  presentation and display: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2004">one needs to balance the goals of
                        correctness against the practical exigencies of the system and its
                        users</quote>
                     <ptr target="#ramsay2004"/>
                  </cit>. At the Archive the problem of classification drove the development of a
                  new <title rend="quotes">Related Works</title> feature that links objects in
                  different media across wings of the Archive. Every new digital edition published
                  in the Archive (a set of watercolor drawings, for instance, or Blake’s engraved
                  illustrations to a commercially published book) includes a list of works related
                  to the newly published work. In the early years of the Archive these lists,
                  generated by the editors, often included works illustrating texts by the same
                  author, so that, for instance, every one of Blake’s watercolors illustrating one
                  of Milton’s texts was considered <q>related</q> to every other watercolor
                  illustrating Milton. But when Archive staff began building a tool that would
                  actually link related works within the Archive (rather than just listing them for
                  users to seek out on their own), we began to question this bibliographic
                  definition of <q>relatedness</q> and its epistemological implications for our
                  project. Were Blake’s watercolor illustrations to Milton’s <title rend="italic"
                     >Comus</title>, commissioned by Joseph Thomas in 1801, <q>related</q> to the
                  designs for <title rend="italic">Paradise Regained</title>, completed no earlier
                  than 1816, by virtue of anything other than Milton’s authorship? And if <q>texts
                     by the same author</q> was a valid definition of <q>relatedness</q> for the
                  Archive’s purposes, then was every one of Blake’s illustrations of the Bible
                     <q>related</q> to every other one — with God understood as
                     <q>author</q>?<note>This question of relatedness occupied us for several years.
                     Each summer at Blake Camp (the Archive’s annual planning meeting, held in
                     recent years at the Institute for Arts and Humanities at UNC Chapel Hill) the
                     editors, the Technical Editor, our bibliographer Mark Crosby, and I would hash
                     it out again; between Blake Camps the discussion continued on blake-proj, our
                     staff listserv.</note>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Object 6 of Blake’s engraved illustrations to <title rend="italic">The
                        Pastorals of Virgil</title> (center) alongside a proof impression (upper
                     left) and two preliminary drawings (right). Though these various objects were
                     executed in different media, they are related in the Archive’s terminology (and
                     tagged as such in our XML documents) because they represent stages in Blake’s
                     production process for the finished work known as the <title rend="italic"
                        >Pastorals</title>.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of William Blake Archive showing views of different Blake
                     works juxtaposed in different windows.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Unsurprisingly, the conclusion we eventually came to brought us back to the
                  project’s original vision of Blake-as-craftsman: within the context of the
                  Archive, works are now considered <q>related</q> if they are part of the same
                  production sequence — a material definition of <q>relatedness</q> that reflects
                  Blake’s unique creative processes. By the Archive’s standards, then, objects are
                  related if they represent different stages in the creation of a
                     work.<note>Versions of the same basic design are sometimes also linked as
                     related even when they are not part of the same production process. Blake’s
                     vision of <q>Death’s Door,</q> for instance, is a motif that appears repeatedly
                     in his works in different media; these works are classified as related simply
                     because they are very nearly the same design.</note> Thus, the monochrome wash
                  drawings that Blake produced for his influential illustrations to <title
                     rend="italic">The Pastorals of Virgil</title> (1821) are related to the wood
                  engravings published in that book because they represent earlier stages in Blake’s
                  artistic process.<note>This protracted debate over the concept of
                        <q>relatedness</q> and how it should be represented in the Archive’s
                     interface naturally both reflects and was constrained by the affordances of the
                     Archive’s XML database. As Stephen Ramsay notes, the employment of databases by
                     humanists raises questions about <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2004"
                        >[t]he inclusion of certain data (and the attendant exclusion of others),
                        the mapping of relationships among entities, … and the eventual
                        visualization of information patterns,</quote> and the answers to these
                     questions necessarily <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2004">imply a
                        hermeneutics and a set of possible methodologies</quote> that have
                     far-reaching consequences both for individual projects and for the humanistic
                     field <ptr target="#ramsay2004"/>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Further disambiguation of the term <q>related</q> has recently led Archive staff
                  to create another, similar feature: <title rend="quotes">Supplemental
                     Views.</title> This category contains additional photography of an object,
                  showing, for instance, the entire leaf on which an impression was printed. <title
                     rend="quotes">Supplemental Views</title> are distinguished from <title
                     rend="quotes">Related Works</title> because they refer not so much to the
                  Blakean object itself but to the digital reproduction of the Blakean object — they
                  offer a second, somewhat different photographic representation of the same
                  physical object. Hence their classification as <title rend="quotes">Supplemental
                        <emph>Views</emph>
                  </title> rather than <title rend="quotes">Related <emph>Works</emph>
                  </title> — <emph>work</emph>, in Archive nomenclature, being a term reserved for
                  creative productions by Blake or his contemporaries. </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Archive’s recently launched Supplemental Views feature offers additional
                     photography for objects displayed in the Archive. In this case, a full leaf
                     view of object 2 of <title rend="italic">Visions of the Daughters of
                        Albion</title> copy H shows the poor registration of the plate to the leaf;
                     an explanatory note indicates that the printed object <q>appears low and tilted
                        to the right.</q>
                  </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure>
               <p>This kind of thematic linking goes against the grain of current web development
                  trends, which favor dynamically-generated links created in response to the
                  behavior of users rather than the exigencies of content. As Brent Nelson and Jon
                  Bath note, a static-linking system based on principles inherent to content and
                  subject matter <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#nelson2012">requires editorial direction and is
                        thus inherently biased and selective rather than (potentially) exhaustive:
                        it is fixed and non-generative. For this reason, it is also necessarily
                        labour-intensive</quote>
                     <ptr target="#nelson2012" loc="par. 21"/>
                  </cit>. In the case of the Blake Archive, links between Related Works represent
                  technologically the collective knowledge of Archive editors and staff, who decide
                  before each publication which works are related to the new publication and in what
                  way they are related. Related Works links are thus <quote rend="inline"
                     source="#nelson2012">declarative about the nature of their linkage. Each link
                     indicates the nature of its target</quote> by virtue of its inclusion in the
                  Related Works menu <ptr target="#nelson2012" loc="par. 14"/>.<note>Nelson and
                     Bath’s study of the Thompson Chain Reference Bible and its sophisticated
                     textual linking system reveals many parallels with the systems developed at the
                     Blake Archive for linking related works and objects. As with the Thompson
                     Bible, the desire to create thematic links rather than, or in addition to,
                     semantic ones has driven the Archive’s development of multiple methods for
                     connecting objects across the Archive. This desire derives in large part, I
                     would argue, from the fact that readers of Blake, like readers of the Bible,
                     represent a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nelson2012">highly motivated reading
                           communit[y]</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nelson2012" loc="par. 25"/>
                     </cit>.</note> This feature is entirely in keeping with the scholarly
                  principles of the Archive, where relatedness is defined as an attribute of
                  artistic objects and their place in historical production processes. But the
                  Related Works feature is meant to supplement rather than to replace the
                  user-generated connections enabled by other tools in the Archive. Users seeking
                  works related to one another by virtue of a particular textual or visual motif
                  rather than by their place in Blake’s production processes can employ the
                  Archive’s search engines and Virtual Lightbox (a basic image editor) to find and
                  collect, for instance, textual mentions of the pope or images that include the
                  mythical figure of Comus. Such searches are not bound by the Archive’s own
                  standards for relatedness, but are left to the user’s discretion. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>There is a Fine Line between Scope Creep and Scope Change</head>
               <p>New and early-stage projects are often plagued with the problem of <q>scope
                     creep,</q> a phenomenon in which a manageable and fairly well delineated
                  project is derailed because the primary stakeholders cannot or will not limit
                  their ideas of what the project will be: as team members with varying levels of
                  technical knowledge and content expertise envision all of the directions a project
                     <emph>could</emph> take, they can find themselves going everywhere and nowhere
                  at once. In the beginning stages of a project, one of the project manager’s major
                  duties — and the reason why they sometimes come across as spoilsports — is
                  preventing scope creep by holding the team to agreed upon project parameters. For
                  this reason, <q>project management for beginners</q> articles often emphasize the
                  importance of setting realistic goals and limiting a project’s early ambitions. </p>
               <p>But projects that are ten or twelve years along are less likely to suffer from
                  scope creep than those in the beginning stages. If a project’s founders did their
                  jobs well (and if a project is functioning productively after a decade, the
                  chances are good that they did), by this point team members and collaborators
                  probably have a realistic understanding of the task at hand. Once a team has
                  mastered the primary functions of a project and brought it beyond the planning
                  stages, widening the project’s scope becomes the next logical step in its
                  development. At this point, a project manager’s priorities shift from preventing
                  unwanted change to facilitating productive growth. </p>
               <p>At the William Blake Archive the project team has recently made a move to widen
                  the scope of our endeavor by adding to our database 40 years of back issues of
                     <title rend="italic">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>, the journal of
                  record in Blake studies.<note>This work has been spearheaded by Morris Eaves and
                     Sarah Jones of the University of Rochester, with the Carolina Digital Library
                     and Archives assisting with hard-copy scanning and textual markup, graduate
                     assistants at UNC preparing images for publication, and Technical Editor Will
                     Shaw building the necessary XSL transformations and XQuery code.</note> The
                  Blake Archive has been publishing digital editions of Blake’s work for sixteen
                  years; its publication processes have been relatively stable over that time,
                  though they have been adapted somewhat to reflect both changing technology and the
                  nature of Blake’s work. (The Archive is designed such that a publication process
                  that works flawlessly for an illuminated book will require tweaking for a
                  manuscript or watercolor.) The decision to incorporate searchable back issues of
                     <title rend="italic">BIQ</title> came about not only in response to changing
                  paradigms of scholarly publishing, with many major journals now available in
                  digital form, but as a way of maximizing the Archive’s existing assets. As back
                  issues of <title rend="italic">BIQ</title> are scanned, transcribed, and marked up
                  for inclusion in the Archive, images that appeared as halftones in the print
                  edition are being replaced, whenever possible, with the same high-resolution
                  color-corrected JPEGs that make up the Archive’s digital editions. Thus, scholars
                  reading Eugenie R. Freed’s article from the Winter 1998 issue of <title
                     rend="italic">BIQ</title> on the Christian symbolism in plate 78 of Blake’s
                  illuminated book <title rend="italic">Jerusalem</title> will see a full-color
                  inline illustration of plate 78 and can also access the Archive’s digital edition
                  of <title rend="italic">Jerusalem </title>copy E (consisting of 100 objects in
                  all) with one click.<note>We plan to begin releasing these electronic back issues
                     in spring 2014; like the Archive’s digital editions, they will be freely
                     available and require no subscription or access fees. Scanned PDFs of the
                     original issues will also be available for print on demand; these PDFs will, of
                     course, retain the halftone images that originally appeared in the print
                     journal. Since 2011 current issues of <title rend="italic">BIQ</title> have
                     been published online (with a print on demand option); these current issues are
                     available only to <title rend="italic">BIQ</title> subscribers, but will join
                     the Archive’s repository of back issues as they emerge from behind a five-year
                        <q>moving wall.</q>
                  </note> Once this new resource is made available the Blake Archive will contain
                  over forty years of <title rend="italic">BIQ</title>s history, making the Archive
                  the premier source, not only for high-quality digital editions of Blake’s work,
                  but for scholarly commentary on that work. The incorporation of <title
                     rend="italic">BIQ </title>represents scope change of the best kind: a
                  manageable improvement that was perhaps not foreseen by the Archive’s founders,
                  but which aligns with the primary goal of the Archive — to make Blake’s work, and
                  excellent scholarship about it, available free of charge to as wide an audience as
                  possible — and thus enhances the project’s scholarly value.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Work in progress toward online back issues of <title rend="italic">Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly</title>. Like the Archive itself, these issues will be
                     highly searchable and require no subscription fees. Digitization and XML
                     encoding were performed by an outside vendor, with DTD design and interface
                     development handled in-house by Technical Editor Will Shaw, Technical
                     Consultant Joseph Ryan, and assistants Michael Fox and Adam McCune.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screen shot of an entry from Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>But while <q>scope creep</q> is less a problem to be avoided than a fact of life
                  for older projects, <q>feature creep</q> — the wish to make existing tools perform
                  more and more functions, just because they can — can be a major source of
                  contention in ongoing projects. While the manager of a new project can often nip
                  feature creep in the bud by appealing to time, staff, or budget constraints — the
                     <soCalled>let’s just get this up and running and then we’ll see</soCalled>
                  strategy — a digital project that is humming along happily is rife with
                  opportunities for tinkering. Add to this what I call the <q>educator
                     imperative</q> — the wish, common among academics, to give users/readers as
                  much information as possible — and project managers may find themselves fighting
                  the notion that because an existing tool <emph>could</emph> do something — and
                  because making it do so is neither prohibitively difficult nor particularly
                  expensive — it definitely <emph>should</emph> do that thing.</p>
               <p>As with scope change, feature change is sometimes a logical outcome of a project’s
                  continued mission: tools that were designed to do only one thing in the early days
                  of a project may grow more complex as that project fulfills its early goals and
                  develops in new directions. The Blake Archive’s Compare feature, for instance, was
                  built to automatically display objects in the illuminated books that were printed
                  from the same copper plate, regardless of the order in which they appear in
                  individual copies; it does so automatically based on the bibliographic information
                  included in our XML BADs.<note>BADs, or Blake Archive Documents, are the building
                     blocks of the Archive. They contain all of the XML data related to individual
                     Blake works, and thus enable the standardized publication of digital
                     editions.</note> Clicking on <q>Compare</q> beneath any impression of <title
                     rend="quotes">The Ancient of Days</title> (object 1 in most copies of <title
                     rend="italic">Europe a Prophecy</title>), for instance, opens a window that
                  displays every impression of the plate that is currently available in the Archive.
                  Over the years, as the Archive moved from publishing only Blake’s illuminated
                  books to his works in other media as well, Archive staff realized that objects in
                  different media would not automatically display in the Compare window. In response
                  to this situation the Archive’s Technical Editor, Will Shaw, revised the Compare
                  code to allow for manual inclusion of objects in different media. In the image
                  below, for instance, objects from <title rend="italic">The Small Book of
                     Designs</title> (a series of separate plates) appear alongside corresponding
                  images from <title rend="italic">The Book of Urizen</title> and <title
                     rend="italic">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title> (both illuminated
                  books). Like the integration of <title rend="italic">BIQ</title> (though on a much
                  smaller scale), this change reflected the logical development of an existing tool
                  rather than feature creep run amok.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Compare feature windows showing images printed from the same copper plates
                     but appearing in different works. The top row shows an object, far left, from
                        <title rend="italic">A Small Book of Designs</title> alongside objects from
                        <title rend="italic">The Book of Urizen</title>. The bottom row shows an
                     object, far left, from <title rend="italic">A Large Book of Designs</title>
                     alongside objects from <title rend="italic">Visions of the Daughters of
                        Albion</title>.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screen shot of an object from <title rend="italic">A Large Book of
                        Designs</title> alongside objects from <title rend="italic">Visions of the
                        Daughters of Albion</title>
                  </figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>In many cases, however, feature creep reflects, not the logical expansion of an
                  existing tool, but a kind of techno-utopianism (often felt most strongly by those
                  team members least responsible for coding and programming) that, if allowed free
                  rein, can quickly lead to unnecessary redundancy. At the Archive, the danger of
                  feature creep is that every tool will be expected to do everything: the Compare
                  feature, the Virtual Lightbox, the Related Works feature, and any number of other
                  tools would all perform the same functions, leading to confusion for users and
                  frustration for technical staff. As Morris Eaves has argued elsewhere, tools in
                  the Blake Archive should not do the work of scholarship <emph>for</emph> the user,
                  but should instead enable users “to make useful things for themselves. With tools,
                  applied to the primary textual and pictorial materials, users construct the
                  contexts most relevant to their purposes” <ptr target="#eaves2006"/>.<note>Eaves’
                        <title rend="quotes">Multimedia Body Plans: A Self-Assessment</title> is a
                     detailed analysis of the editorial decisions that helped shape the creation and
                     early evolution of the Blake Archive; it provides a useful companion piece to
                     this essay. The article is available, in slightly different versions, online
                     and in hard copy. This quotation is from the online edition; information on
                     both versions can be found in my bibliography.</note> Will Shaw, now Digital
                  Humanities Technology Consultant at Duke University, notes that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#shaw2012">containing feature creep is simply good
                        software development practice; smaller tools load faster and may be more
                        responsive to user input [while] multipurpose tools are almost certainly
                        larger and possibly less efficient from a computational standpoint, not to
                        mention that they can be unwieldy for users</quote>
                     <ptr target="#shaw2012"/>
                  </cit>.<note>Shaw invokes the Unix operating system’s <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#shaw2012">principles of modularity and
                           interoperability–you can chain together a lot of single-purpose tools to
                           do complex things</quote>
                        <ptr target="#shaw2012"/>
                     </cit> as an analogy for the importance of keeping user-facing features
                     lightweight and focused on a minimum number of tasks.</note> As new software
                  development tools and web technologies emerge, project managers must work with
                  programmers and content providers to determine which new features and tools will
                  support the project’s mission and which will create unnecessary redundancies or
                  tie up resources that might be better employed elsewhere. And they must make these
                  decisions with an eye both to the project’s past progress and to its future
                  growth. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Revision Gets Harder Rather than Easier</head>
               <p>In the planning stages of a digital humanities project collaborators must
                  constantly be sibyls: they must consider every decision in light of what it means
                  now as well as what it will mean for the future of the project. In the advanced
                  stages of a digital humanities project team members must constantly be Januses,
                  looking both forward — <q>how will this affect everything we want to do from now
                     on?</q> — and backward: “how will this affect what we have already done?”
                  Decisions that team members make will have consequences, not only for the future
                  of the project, but for work already completed, and those consequences may
                  determine or even limit the ways the project can develop and change.</p>
               <p>At the Blake Archive this phenomenon causes issues ranging from the relatively
                  mundane to the borderline terrifying. At the low-consequence end of the spectrum
                  is our book of image search terms: as the Archive’s editors and project assistants
                  prepare new works for publication, they write descriptions of Blake’s images using
                  an art historical vocabulary specific to Blake’s iconography; these descriptions,
                  in turn, enable the Archive’s image search feature. As assistants add new terms to
                  our image description glossary, it often becomes necessary to comb through already
                  published works to see if these new terms apply; when we decided to add the term
                     <q>mane</q> to describe the numerous horse sketches appearing at the end of
                     <title rend="italic">An Island in the Moon</title>, for example, we had to
                  retroactively add the term to every description of a horse (or lion, for that
                  matter) found elsewhere in the Archive. </p>
               <p>In a move with more far-reaching consequences, the Archive’s Technical Editor Will
                  Shaw recently updated the Archive’s DTD<note>The Archive’s DTD, or document type
                     definition, restricts and records which tags can be used in the Archive’s XML
                     BADs.</note> to allow for XML attributes that would <q>hide</q> certain
                  documents from the XSL transformation that dynamically generates our tables of
                  contents. This will eventually make it possible for proofs and impressions of an
                  illuminated work to appear in the Archive’s Compare feature without also appearing
                  in the table of contents that lists all copies of that work. (The need to
                  distinguish between a proof of an illuminated work and a copy of that work
                  reflects the Archive’s ongoing concern with Blake’s production processes.) Once
                  this improvement was made to the DTD, however, a member of the Archive staff had
                  to add an XML attribute to the root element (&lt;bad&gt;) for every BAD in our
                  eXist database to prevent all of the Archive’s electronic editions from
                  simultaneously disappearing from their respective tables of contents. Since there
                  are scores of digital editions already published and hundreds left to publish, at
                  the Archive we find ourselves perpetually looking forward as well as backward,
                  pondering the possible consequences of our actions for future staffers.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Longer a Project Lasts, the More Diffuse Its Collective Knowledge
                  Becomes</head>
               <p>One of the most exciting and frightening aspects of digital humanities projects is
                  their reliance on distributed expertise. This need is present from the beginning
                  of nearly every project; rare (though not unheard of) is the digital humanist who
                  can single-handedly write code, mark up data, build a database, design web
                  interfaces, write grants, manage a staff, and provide expert content. (Rarer still
                  is the scholar who can do all of these things while teaching, publishing, and
                  serving on numerous committees.) The longer a project exists, the greater the
                  number of collaborators (or, to use the private-sector term, stakeholders) —
                  principal investigators, editors, project managers, grant administrators,
                  developers, deans, graduate students, undergraduate assistants — who will pass
                  through the project and contribute their particular strengths. Over time, the
                  distributed cognition necessary to continue the venture will change as the
                  project’s staff, size, funding, and location change, so the uncertainty that often
                  characterizes digital projects can have temporal, geographic, economic, or
                  personal dimensions. Wrangling a project’s collective knowledge, including the
                  lingering — could we call it <q>spectral</q>? — contributions of past
                  collaborators, is one of a project manager’s most challenging tasks.</p>
               <p>Within the last few years the Archive’s collective knowledge has become more
                  geographically diffuse as the project, which is published at the University of
                  North Carolina at Chapel Hill, has opened a satellite office at the University of
                  Rochester, where Morris Eaves and Project Coordinator Laura Whitebell (who has
                  just replaced longtime coordinator Rachel Lee) oversee the production of digital
                  editions of Blake’s manuscripts.<note>The Rochester staff christened themselves
                     BAND: Blake Archive Northern Division. Robert Essick, not to be outdone,
                     quickly claimed BAWD — Blake Archive Western Division — for his outpost in
                     Altadena, California. The UNC office, after some deliberation, settled on BATS:
                     Blake Archive Team South; a former UNC assistant who now works from her home in
                     Queens, New York, represents BARD: Blake Archive Roving Division.</note> The
                  Rochester assistants have quickly become the Archive’s foremost experts on
                  manuscript tagging and markup, with the result that a large segment of the
                  Archive’s institutional knowledge is housed on a different campus from its primary
                  administrative and technical site. But in addition to its geographic dispersal,
                  Archive expertise has become more temporally diffuse as well, as graduate and
                  undergraduate staff members join and then leave the project, contributing their
                  analytical and practical skills to publications that take years to move through
                  the transcription and markup process. </p>
               <p>The Archive’s decision, in recent years, to begin publishing electronic editions
                  of Blake’s unique works in manuscript — including his letters, his prose satire
                     <title rend="italic">An Island in the Moon</title>, the notebook in which he
                  drafted poems and sketched designs, and the visionary poem <title rend="italic"
                     >Vala, or The Four Zoas</title> — has necessitated a major redesign of the
                  Archive’s markup tagset and transcription display protocols. Early Archive
                  publications reproduced Blake’s illuminated books, each of which Blake printed in
                  multiple copies from a copper-plate matrix that remained relatively stable from
                  printing to printing.<note>Though the copper plates, once etched, rarely changed,
                     Blake could alter the resulting texts before printing — by masking certain
                     portions of the plate or inking some lines of text and leaving others uninked —
                     or after, by obscuring text with watercolor washes or salvaging or altering
                     printed lines with pen and ink. These textual variants are important and are
                     reproduced in the Archive’s diplomatic transcriptions, but can be encoded using
                     a relatively basic markup tagset.</note> The Archive’s original transcription
                  tagset was thus quite simple and straightforward. The publication of manuscript
                  works including <title rend="italic">An Island in the Moon</title> and Blake’s
                  late letters necessitated considerable changes to this tagset to reflect
                  strike-throughs, underlined text, carets, and other manuscript features not found
                  in the illuminated books. This more robust tagset has served the Archive well for
                  several years, but the Rochester team’s preliminary work on Blake’s <title
                     rend="italic">Four Zoas</title> manuscript has revealed that another round of
                  substantial changes will be necessary — changes that will be undertaken over a
                  period of years and with an ever-changing staff.<note>Early attempts to mark up
                     the <title rend="italic">Four Zoas</title> manuscript using the Archive’s
                     existing tagset produced ugly and unreadable transcriptions in which deleted or
                     overwritten text was represented by long black bars or grey highlighting. The
                     Archive’s fairly simple tagset, developed for works containing little
                     overwriting or deletion, was untenable in the context of <title rend="italic"
                        >The Four Zoas</title>, in which erasures and overwriting are the rule
                     rather than the exception. The addition of this new work to the Archive’s
                     stable of editions-in-progress has thus required us to rethink our assumptions
                     about how to best represent Blake’s manuscript works.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A complex manuscript composed in several stages over a period of more than ten
                  years, <title rend="italic">The Four Zoas</title> is a far cry from the relatively
                  straightforward, almost <q>fair copy</q> clarity of <title rend="italic"
                     >Island</title> and of Blake’s letters. The poem combines drawings and text in
                  an extended response to Edward Young’s devotional poem <title rend="italic">Night
                     Thoughts</title>; during its composition Blake frequently erased large swaths
                  of his own writing and covered the erasures with new verse. Composed in part on
                  leftover proof sheets from Blake’s engraved illustrations of Young’s work, the
                  manuscript was unbound and reordered by Blake’s posthumous editors. As Fiormonte,
                  Martiradonna, and Schmidt have recently reasserted (the insight is one long known
                  to textual critics), <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#fiormonte2010">if we either look at the different
                        historical representations of a given text or at its documented writing
                        stages, we realize that there is not one text, but many texts, as many as
                        there are mechanisms of writing, material production, intertextual paths and
                        methodologies of reconstruction</quote>
                     <ptr target="#fiormonte2010" loc="par. 3"/>
                  </cit>. The <q>many texts</q> of the <title rend="italic">Four Zoas</title> are a
                  Blakean’s delight and a textual editor’s despair.</p>
               <p>In order to present the <q>many texts</q> of the <title rend="italic">Four
                     Zoas</title> in a coherent, readable, and philologically rigorous digital
                  edition, the Archive will need to call on the expertise of both its current staff
                  and past collaborators. The composition sequence of <title rend="italic">The Four
                     Zoas</title> has been successfully limned by the Archive’s former project
                  manager, Justin Van Kleeck, who created a fully tagged version of the manuscript
                  as his dissertation project.<note>Dr. Van Kleeck’s essay on the process of tagging
                        <title rend="italic">The Four Zoas</title> can be found at <ref
                        target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/editing_blake/vankleeck/vankleeck.html"
                        >http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/editing_blake/vankleeck/vankleeck.html</ref>.</note>
                  Justin’s efforts to reconstruct the composition sequence of <title rend="italic"
                     >The Four Zoas</title> and to represent that sequence in XML are now guiding
                  the Archive’s Rochester team as they prepare the manuscript for publication in the
                  Archive. But the Archive’s publication processes, while not bound specifically by
                  the <q>printing bias</q> identified by Fiormonte, Martiradonna, and Schmidt <ptr
                     target="#fiormonte2010" loc="par. 3"/>, are nevertheless subject to the
                  standards and protocols developed by the Archive in the twenty years of its
                     existence.<note>In another example of a development project marked by both
                     spatial and temporal diffusion, the Archive’s recently launched Virtual
                     Lightbox tool began at the University of Kentucky in 2000, was developed by
                     Matt Kirschenbaum and Amit Kumar at the University of Maryland, and was
                     developed further and finally adapted for the Archive by Will Shaw. Complete
                     credits can be found at <ref target="http://mith.umd.edu/lightbox/credits.html"
                        >http://mith.umd.edu/lightbox/credits.html</ref>.</note> The Rochester
                  team’s challenge is to expand the Archive’s markup tagset and transcription
                  display in ways that enable the symbolic representation of Blake’s composition
                  processes while remaining true to the Archive’s existing standards for textual
                  markup and representation.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Object 5 of Blake’s manuscript work <title rend="italic">Vala, or The Four
                        Zoas</title>. The Archive’s former Project Manager, Justin Van Kleeck,
                     completed a tagged edition of <title rend="italic">The Four Zoas</title> as
                     part of his dissertation work. This tagged edition will help to enable the
                        <title rend="italic">Four Zoas</title>'s eventual publication in the Archive
                     — an event that will require a considerable expansion of the Archive’s current
                     markup tagset.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Object 5 of Blake’s manuscript work <title rend="italic">Vala, or The
                        Four Zoas</title>.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Such temporal and geographical dispersals suggest that everyone involved with a
                  project — especially one with many years of history and change behind it — has to
                  commit to a certain level of perpetual uncertainty. This uncertainty, while a
                  function of all collaborative projects, is particularly germane to digital
                  endeavors, in which technical and administrative infrastructure are often
                  determined by geographic and funding considerations not entirely under the control
                  of the primary investigators. Morris Eaves, writing in the first decade of the
                  Archive, noted that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#eaves2006">[w]e plow forward with no answer to
                        the haunting question of where and how a project like this one will live out
                        its useful life…. [T]he need to persist without reassurance is one of the
                        many unsettling conditions of life in new media</quote>
                     <ptr target="#eaves2006"/>
                  </cit>. As Jerome McGann has noted in writing of the philological impulse of
                  digital archives, all forms of networked knowledge — electronic or otherwise —
                  have <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann2013">memory lapses that they’ve forgotten.
                        You can never be sure what’s there or, if it’s there, where it is</quote>
                     <ptr target="#mcgann2013" loc="342"/>
                  </cit>. Uncertainty and potential loss are the enabling conditions of ongoing
                  scholarship, and they do not disappear or mitigate with time.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Documentation and Communication are Additive Processes; They Will Remain
                  Important Throughout the Project, Though Emphases and Priorities Will Shift</head>
               <p>It is easy to agree that documentation is a high-priority task for a collaborative
                  project: important technical and administrative information should not be
                  entrusted to chance or allowed to reside in a single (sometimes human)
                     repository.<note>Joseph Viscomi is fond of asking me, whenever I point to my
                     head as the source of some important piece of Archive-related knowledge,
                        <q>What if you get hit by a bus?</q> He has a gruesome anecdote about a New
                     York museum curator to reinforce this lesson.</note> It is less simple to
                  maintain up-to-date documentation, which will always feel like the last priority
                  on an ongoing project: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#siemens2010">one more task to add to an already
                        full schedule</quote>
                     <ptr target="#siemens2010"/>
                  </cit>. But it must remain a priority nonetheless. Workflows and procedures often
                  change incrementally. A process that was once the sole province of programmers or
                  the technical editor will get easier for other staff to implement (or vice versa —
                  a seemingly simple task will get harder); a collaborator who shows a talent for a
                  particular task will take it over entirely; login procedures and passwords will
                  change as the university’s IT group tightens computer security; the number of
                  project staff will get bigger and harder to train individually, or smaller and
                  required to take on more tasks per person; the list of possible changes is
                  endless. In the day-to-day progress of the project these small changes can seem
                  unimportant, but in the aggregate they can, over time, completely change the way
                  project work is completed. If documentation is not updated frequently and
                  thoroughly, those responsible for documenting project history and necessary
                  procedures can be overwhelmed to find that workflows have been completely
                  transformed since the last update. This can necessitate weeks or months of
                  rewriting when an occasional well-timed revision, recorded immediately as
                  processes changed, would have required only an hour or two.</p>
               <p>There is a corollary to this piece of advice: the longer a project lasts, the
                  harder it will be to alter workflows and organizational protocols, or to adopt
                  out-of-the-box tools like Basecamp, Jira, or GitHub.<note>Basecamp (<ref
                        target="http://basecamp.com/">http://basecamp.com/</ref>), Github (<ref
                        target="https://github.com">https://github.com/</ref>), and Jira (<ref
                        target="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/overview"
                        >http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/overview</ref>) are tools for
                     project management and issue tracking. Basecamp and Jira charge per-month
                     subscription fees; GitHub is free for open-source projects but charges a fee
                     for those who wish to keep their activities private. There are other tools
                     available; see this DH Questions and Answers exchange (<ref
                        target="ttp://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/best-dh-project-management-system"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/best-dh-project-management-system</ref>)
                     for a discussion of their advantages and disadvantages.</note> Entrenched work
                  habits are difficult to change, especially in large groups that have been working
                  together for some time. New project management and task tracking tools can seem
                  like catch-all solutions until it becomes clear that the time and effort involved
                  in training staff members to use a new tool negate the software’s time-saving
                  potential. If you are at the beginning stages of a digital humanities project, it
                  would behoove you to be as careful in your choice of project management tools as
                  you are in selecting the hardware and software that will help you process,
                  analyze, and present your data. They may be with you for a long time.</p>
               <p>Because it is difficult to efficiently train a staff of approximately twenty
                  geographically dispersed collaborators — many of whom are graduate and
                  undergraduate students with short- to medium-term project tenures<note>Compared to
                     many digital humanities projects the Archive has a fairly stable staff; the
                     three founding editors are still with the project, and most assistants are
                     Ph.D. students who remain with the Archive for an average of five to eight
                     years. Cultivating reliable collaborators who will remain more than a few
                     months is key to managing a successful long-term project.</note> — to adopt new
                  tools, the Blake Archive relies on what might be considered <q>low-tech</q>
                  solutions to the problem of communication and collaboration between campuses. It
                  employs a simple staff listserv (called blake-proj and enabled by UNC’s Lyris list
                  management software) and a password protected <title rend="quotes">Work in
                     Progress</title> (WIP) site. The WIP site, accessible only to staff, includes a
                  training manual for new assistants (instructions for scanning, cataloguing, and
                  color correcting images; an introduction to Blake Archive Documents (BADs);
                  illustration and transcription markup guidelines) as well as essential technical
                  information, including our DTD and XML tagset documentation. It also provides
                  links to XML tracking sheets for both our electronic editions and the forthcoming
                     <title rend="italic">Blake Quarterly</title> back issues project and acts as a
                  repository for project history, featuring grant reports and the minutes from our
                  annual Blake Camp meetings.<note>The Archive’s Rochester office maintains its own
                     internal Google site to track manuscript-specific tasks, including primary
                     source research and multiple rounds of proofreading.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In addition to these two basic means of communication, the Blake Archive employs a
                  variety of tools and techniques to facilitate collaboration among Archive staff
                  and to maintain the Archive’s bimonthly publication schedule; this variety is
                  necessary to coordinate project staff on five different campuses (UNC Chapel Hill,
                  the University of Rochester, Duke University, Kansas State University, and the
                  University of California-Riverside). The Archive conducts an annual in-person
                  project meeting, Blake Camp, usually held at the Institute for Arts and Humanities
                  at UNC (though the 2013 meeting took place in Altadena, California, in conjunction
                  with a Huntington Library symposium organized by the Archive’s bibliographer, Mark
                  Crosby), that serves the dual purposes identified by Lynne Siemens in her study of
                  digital humanities collaboration tools: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#siemens2010">[f]irst, the gatherings are an
                        opportunity to review the previous year’s work and outline the tasks for the
                        upcoming year. Second, they are also the time to resolve those <q>thorny</q>
                        issues that could not be easily resolved on conference calls or by email
                        during the year</quote>
                     <ptr target="#siemens2010"/>
                  </cit>. To coordinate activities between the Archive’s primary office at UNC and
                  the manuscript markup division at the University of Rochester, I conduct biweekly
                  video chats with Project Coordinator Rachel Lee and Assistant Project Manager Joe
                  Fletcher using Google Chat (which we find more reliable than Skype). Because, as
                  Siemens notes, “unlike electronic communication tools such as emails and
                  listserves, no automatic record is created from these meetings,” Rachel usually
                  maintains a written record of our conversations <ptr target="#siemens2010"/>.
                  Other team members are then notified of important decisions via blake-proj,
                  creating an electronic record of essential points.</p>
               <p>It is important to note that communication and collaboration strategies among team
                  members will change over time, and that communication at the beginning stages of a
                  project will take different forms than a mature project requires. The early years
                  of the Blake Archive, for instance, included an intensive period of on-site
                  collaboration and development at the Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                  Humanities at the University of Virginia, where Dr. Joseph Viscomi received a
                  one-year Residential Fellowship to oversee the design and launch of the Archive.
                  Such meetings, Siemens notes, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#siemens2010">are particularly important at the
                        beginning stages of a project. It is at this stage of research projects
                        where the ambiguity and potential for conflict is greatest, especially when
                        individuals from different academic backgrounds and training are involved,
                        and when team members must develop a common understanding of the research
                        project, methodologies, tasks, and deadlines </quote>
                     <ptr target="#siemens2010"/>
                  </cit>. In recent years, by contrast, as the Archive has shifted from development
                  mode to a schedule characterized by frequent publication, ongoing site
                  maintenance, and occasional tool development, in-person collaboration has become
                  less essential, and the Archive has shifted to forms of long-distance
                  communication and the occasional in-person meeting.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Blake Archive’s workflow tracking site, designed by former project
                     assistant Michelle Langston (now a front-end web developer at Automattic, the
                     company behind Wordpress.com) and accessible only to project staff.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screen shot of The Blake Archive’s workflow tracking site</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Good DH Projects Are Like Strong Marriages: The Excitement Will Fade, But the
                  Love Will Remain</head>
               <p>Like any large, ongoing project (including a traditional monograph), you are more
                  likely to stick with a digital humanities endeavor if you feel genuinely
                  passionate about it. But the nature of that passion will change over the years, as
                  the thrill (and occasional agony) of launching a new project gives way to the
                  satisfaction of maintaining an ongoing one. And there are moments when it simply
                  won’t be much fun, when nothing will go right: grants won’t come through,
                  deadlines will pass, programmers will be wooed away, collaborators will stop
                  answering email. While as a project manager one is trained to plan for achievable
                  goals and projected endpoints, at these moments it can help to think in terms of
                  relationships rather than deliverables. You wouldn’t give up on your partner or
                  your best friend after a few arguments; digital projects require similar patience.
                  This is the essence of collaboration itself. <note>
                     <p> Morris Eaves recently forwarded to me an email conversation that took place
                        off-list between the Archive’s editors. They were debating how best to
                        present Blake’s unfinished <title rend="italic">Tiriel</title> manuscript
                        and its accompanying monochrome wash drawings. Should the drawings be
                        separated from the text or presented all together, producing the illusion of
                        a completed work despite the fact that no one is really certain how Blake
                        intended to fit the manuscript and drawings together? (Dr. Eaves has made
                        the text of this <title rend="italic">Tiriel</title> debate available to
                        curious readers on the Archive’s (un)official blog, <title rend="italic">The
                           Cynic Sang</title>
                        <ptr target="#eaves2012"/>.)</p>
                     <p>The detail with which the editors and staff discuss such topics (these
                        debates are a frequent occurrence, both on and off blake-proj) is
                        fascinating both to witness and to participate in; it is this kind of
                        devotion to Blake studies that has powered the Archive for almost twenty
                        years. But in this particular exchange I noticed something else: the editors
                        sign each of their emails to each other, not with <q>Best</q> or
                           <q>Regards</q> or <q>Your friend,</q> but with <q>Love</q> — a tiny
                        reminder of how long and happily they have worked together on this
                        project.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>In practical terms, it is often useful to think in terms of incentives: once a
                  project has moved from development to maintenance, the incentive structure that
                  enables it to proceed will have to change. Students and potential collaborators
                  who volunteered their time to initiate a new project may find an ongoing one less
                  appealing, so it may be necessary to rethink how credit is distributed, how work
                  on the project fits into graduate and undergraduate training, and where and how
                  students and faculty present and publish the results of their work. Such shifts,
                  while they require time and effort to initiate, can actually operate in a
                  project’s favor. For instance, while granting agencies are more likely to support
                  new, exciting projects than reliable, established ones, deans and department
                  chairs often value results and products that they can tout in annual newsletters
                  and the university magazine. Once your digital project has been underway for
                  several years, has grants and awards to its name, and has produced or inspired
                  articles and monographs, it may carry more weight with administrators not versed
                  in cutting-edge digital humanities research. That weight may then translate into
                  research assistantships, office space, or a teaching reduction.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conclusion</head>
               <p>In a 2009 issue of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> Matthew Kirschenbaum recalled
                  one of the joys of his early days at the William Blake Archive: the satisfaction
                  of completing a task, of pronouncing something <q>done.</q>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2009">It was easy to measure progress as
                     I ticked off tasks in email messages to the archive’s editors,</quote>
                  Kirschenbaum wrote. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2009">In time, when enough of these
                        individual tasks were <q>done,</q> the project might be finished</quote>
                     <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2009" loc="par. 1"/>
                  </cit>. As one of Kirschenbaum’s successors at the Archive,<note>Matthew
                     Kirschenbaum served as Project Manager and then Technical Editor of the Archive
                     from May 1997 until June 2003. In many ways this article is a follow-up,
                     fifteen years later, to his 1998 Romantic Circles article on <title
                        rend="quotes">Project Managing the William Blake Archive.</title>
                  </note> I too feel the joy of checking off boxes as the Archive’s staff complete
                  the tasks necessary to publish new electronic editions of Blake’s work every other
                  month. But the idea that the Archive might ever be finished is foreign to me;
                  since I arrived at Joseph Viscomi’s door in August of 2005 I have been perpetually
                  reminded that the William Blake Archive is a scholarly resource in a constant
                  state of growth and change. If the Archive ever manages to publish scholarly
                  editions of every illuminated book, watercolor drawing, manuscript, letter,
                  receipt, engraving, etching, sketch, scrawl, and scribble that Blake produced
                  during his long and prolific lifetime, there will still be Blake’s circle and his
                  throngs of admirers, both contemporary and modern, to include. In other words,
                  infinity is our project limit.</p>
               <p>Fortunately, the project management practices that were established in the early
                  years of the Archive have paid off over the last decade, enabling the Archive to
                  surpass its goal of making high quality electronic editions of Blake’s work
                  available to scholars and to move toward its larger vision of becoming a catalogue
                  raisonné, critical edition, and comprehensive database of all or nearly all of
                  Blake’s work. Decisions made at the beginning of the project — about approaching
                  contributing institutions, curating images and data, and cultivating project staff
                  — were vital, and continue to influence the Archive’s day-to-day operations. But
                  the need for thoughtful management practices has, if anything, increased as the
                  project has achieved and moved beyond its early objectives. As the digital
                  humanities field grows, it will become increasingly important to consider whether
                  and how projects should be maintained beyond their early development stages.
                  Project management for the long term will become a pressing question for the here
                  and now.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Acknowledgements</head>
               <p>For their generous assistance with this essay I would like to thank Morris Eaves,
                  Robert Essick, Jennifer Guiliano, Shawn Moore, Will Shaw, Rachel Lee, and Joseph
                  Viscomi as well as Julia Flanders and the anonymous reviewers for <title
                     rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Bamboo 2013a" xml:id="bamboo2013" key="bamboo2013">
               <title rend="italic">About Project Bamboo - Project Bamboo - UCB Confluence</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">wikihub.berkeley.edu.</title> Web. 17 Aug. 2013. <ref
                  target="https://wikihub.berkeley.edu/display/pbamboo/About+Project+Bamboo"
                  >https://wikihub.berkeley.edu/display/pbamboo/About+Project+Bamboo</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="ACH 2011" xml:id="system2012" key="system2012">
               <title rend="quotes">Best DH Project Management System?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Questions &amp; Answers</title>. Association
               for Computers and the Humanities, 2011. Web. 22 Sept. 2012. <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/best-dh-project-management-system"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/best-dh-project-management-system</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Burgess and Hamming 2013" xml:id="burgess2013" key="burgess2013">Burgess,
               Helen J, and Jeanne Hamming. <title rend="quotes">New Media in the Academy: Labor and
                  the Production of Knowledge in Scholarly Multimedia.</title>
               <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5.3 (2011). <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org.">http://www.digitalhumanities.org.</ref>
               Web. 4 Jun. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000102/000102.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000102/000102.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Croxall 2011" xml:id="croxall2011" key="croxall2011">Croxall, Brian. <title
                  rend="quotes">12 Basic Principles of Project Management.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ProfHacker</title> (<title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher
                  Education)</title>. Online ed. 3 Mar. 2011. Web. 13 June 2012. <ref
                  target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/12-basic-principles-of-project-management/31421"
                  >http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/12-basic-principles-of-project-management/31421</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="NEH 2012" xml:id="plans2012" key="plans2012">
               <title rend="quotes">Data Management Plans for NEH Office of Digital Humanities
                  Proposals and Awards.</title>
               <ref target="http://www.NEH.gov">
                  <title rend="italic">NEH.gov</title>
               </ref>. National Endowment for the Humanities, n.d. Web. 8 Oct. 2012. <ref
                  target="http://www.neh.gov/files/grants/data_management_plans_2012.pdf"
                  >http://www.neh.gov/files/grants/data_management_plans_2012.pdf</ref> .</bibl>
            <bibl label="Eaves 2013" xml:id="eaves2013" key="eaves2013">Eaves, Morris. "<ref
                  target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0003.202"
                  > Behind the Scenes at the William Blake Archive: Collaboration Takes More Than
                  E-mail</ref>. <title rend="italic">The Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>
               3.2 (Dec. 1997). Web. 30 Aug. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0003.202"
                  >http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0003.202</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Eaves 2006" xml:id="eaves2006" key="eaves2006a">Eaves, Morris. <title
                  rend="quotes">Multimedia Body Plans: A Self-Assessment.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Electronic Textual Editing</title>. Ed. Lou Burnard, Katherine
               O’Brien O’Keeffe, and John Unsworth. New York: Modern Language Association of
               America, 2006. 210-223. Print. Preview ed. available online: <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/About/Archive_new/ETE/Preview/eaves.xml"
                  >http://www.tei-c.org/About/Archive_new/ETE/Preview/eaves.xml</ref>. Web. 20 Aug.
               2012.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Eaves et al. 2012" xml:id="eaves2012" key="eaves2012">Eaves, Morris, Robert
               N. Essick, Joseph Viscomi, et al. <title rend="quotes">Xediting Blake’s Tiriel: How
                  It Lives and What It Lives For.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Cynic Sang: The (Un)Official Blog of the William Blake
                  Archive</title>. William Blake Archive, 31 Aug. 2012. Web. 12 Oct. 2012. <ref
                  target="http://blakearchive.wordpress.com/2012/08/31/xediting-blakes-tiriel-how-it-lives-and-what-it-lives-for/"
                  >http://blakearchive.wordpress.com/2012/08/31/xediting-blakes-tiriel-how-it-lives-and-what-it-lives-for/</ref>
               .</bibl>
            <bibl label="Fiormonte et al. 2010" xml:id="fiormonte2010" key="fiormonte2010"
               >Fiormonte, Domenico, Valentina Martiradonna, and Desmond Schmidt. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Encoding As a Hermeneutic and Semiotic Act: The Case of
                  Valerio Magrelli.</title>
               <title rend="italic"> DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly </title>4.1 (2010).<title
                  rend="italic"> www.digitalhumanities.org.</title> Web. 4 Jun. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000082/000082.htm"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000082/000082.htm</ref>l.</bibl>
            <bibl label="ACH 2013" xml:id="dhcenter2013" key="dhcenter2013">
               <title rend="quotes">Founding Staff for a New DH Center?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Questions &amp; Answers</title>. Association
               for Computers and the Humanities, 2012. Web. 20 July 2013. <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/founding-staff-for-a-new-dh-center"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/founding-staff-for-a-new-dh-center</ref>
               .</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2009" xml:id="kirschenbaum2009" key="kirschenbaum2009"
               >Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Done: Finishing Projects in the Digital
                  Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly </title>3.2 (2009): n.pag. Web. 31
               May 2012. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000037/000037.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000037/000037.html</ref> .</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2008" xml:id="kirschenbaum2008" key="kirschenbaum2008b"
               >Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Managing the Blake Archive.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Romantic Circles Features &amp; Events: Editors’
                  Dispatches</title>. Romantic Circles, Mar. 1998. Web. 7 June 2008. <ref
                  target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/dispatches/column7/"
                  >http://www.rc.umd.edu/dispatches/column7/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Leon 2012" xml:id="leon2012" key="leon2012">Leon, Sharon M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Project Management for Humanists: Preparing Future Primary
                  Investigators.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Getting There</title>. Ed. Bethany Nowviskie. <title
                  rend="italic">#alt-academy: a media commons project</title>, 6 May 2011. Web. 13
               June 2012. <ref
                  target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/pieces/project-management-humanists"
                  >http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/pieces/project-management-humanists</ref>
               .</bibl>
            <bibl label="McGann 2013" xml:id="mcgann2013" key="mcgann2013">McGann, Jerome. <title
                  rend="quotes">Philology in a New Key.</title>
               <title rend="italic"> Critical Inquiry </title>39.2 (January, 2013): 327-346.<title
                  rend="italic"> CrossRef.</title> Web. 20 July 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nelson and Bath 2012" xml:id="nelson2012" key="nelson2012d">Nelson, Brent,
               and Jon Bath. <title rend="quotes">Old Ways for Linking Texts in the Digital Reading
                  Environment: The Case of the Thompson Chain Reference Bible.</title>
               <title rend="italic"> DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly </title>6.2 (2012).<title
                  rend="italic"> www.digitalhumanities.org.</title> Web. 4 Jun. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/2/000137/000137.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/2/000137/000137.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie 2012a" xml:id="nowviskie2012" key="nowviskie2012b">Nowviskie,
               Bethany. <title rend="quotes">Eternal September of the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Open access ed.
               Minneapolis: U of Minnesota P, 2012. <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu"
                  >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu</ref>. Web. 9 Aug. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/book">http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/book</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie 2012b" xml:id="scholars2012" key="scholars2012">Nowviskie,
               Bethany. <title rend="quotes">Ten Rules for Humanities Scholars New to Project
                  Management.</title>
               <title rend="italic">nowviskie.org</title>, 2012. Web. 13 June 2012. <ref
                  target="http://nowviskie.org/handouts/DH/10rules.pdf"
                  >http://nowviskie.org/handouts/DH/10rules.pdf</ref> .</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nowviskie and Porter 2010" xml:id="nowviskie2010" key="nowviskie2010b"
               >Nowviskie, Bethany, and Dot Porter. <title rend="quotes">The Graceful Degradation
                  Survey: Managing Digital Humanities Projects Through Times of Transition and
                  Decline.</title>
               <title rend="italic">2010 Conference of the Alliance of Digital Humanities
                  Organizations</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities (DH 2010).</title>
               Web. 9 Aug. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/html/ab-722.html"
                  >http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/html/ab-722.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Pitti 2013" xml:id="pitti2004" key="pitti2004">Pitti, Daniel V. <title
                  rend="quotes">Designing Sustainable Projects and Publications.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Oxford: Blackwell,
               2004. <title rend="italic">XTF.</title> Web. 20 Jul. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Price 2012" xml:id="price2012" key="price2012">Price, Kenneth. <title
                  rend="quotes">Whitman’s Democratic Vistas and the Poetry of Democracy.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digits, Data, and Dilemmas: A Roundtable on Digitization and
                  Knowledge Production. </title>
               <title rend="italic">C19: The Society of Nineteenth-Century Americanists Conference.
                  Berkeley, CA. 13 Apr. 2012. Conference presentation.</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2004" xml:id="ramsay2004" key="ramsay2004">Ramsay, Stephen. <title
                  rend="quotes">Databases.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Oxford: Blackwell,
               2004. <title rend="italic">XTF.</title> Web. 20 Jul. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Scheinfeldt 2012" xml:id="scheinfeldt2012" key="scheinfeldt2012"
               >Scheinfeldt, Tom. <title rend="quotes">Intro to Project Planning and Management:
                  Bootcamp Session in Advance of THATCamp CHNM 2011.</title> 3 June 2011. Web. 13
               June 2012. <ref
                  target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Ex-b6zWtiuQWZw6DkV7B4cEGNovUWznvFV0fPvHXpN0/edit?hl=en_US&amp;pli=1"
                  >https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Ex-b6zWtiuQWZw6DkV7B4cEGNovUWznvFV0fPvHXpN0/edit?hl=en_US&amp;pli=1</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Shaw 2012" xml:id="shaw2012" key="[unlisted]">Shaw, William. <title
                  rend="quotes">Re: WBA tools.</title> Message to the author. 10 Oct. 2012. E-mail. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Siemens 2010" xml:id="siemens2010" key="siemens2010">Siemens, Lynne. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Balance Between On-line and In-person Interactions: Methods for
                  the Development of Digital Humanities Collaboration.</title>
               <title rend="italic"> Digital Studies/Le Champ Numérique </title>2.1 (2010).<title
                  rend="italic">www.digitalstudies.org.</title> Web. 22 Jun. 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/184/236"
                  >http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/184/236</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bamboo 2013b" xml:id="ucbconference2013" key="ucbconference2013">
               <title rend="italic">Standards &amp; Specifications - Project Bamboo - UCB
                  Confluence</title>. <ref target="http://wikihub.berkeley.edu"
                  >http://wikihub.berkeley.edu</ref>. Web. 13 Jul. 2013. <ref
                  target="https://wikihub.berkeley.edu/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=68619301"
                  >https://wikihub.berkeley.edu/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=68619301</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Van Kleeck 2012" xml:id="vankleeck2012" key="vankleeck2012">Van Kleeck,
               Justin. <title rend="quotes">Editioning William Blake’s <title rend="italic">The Four
                     Zoas</title>.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Editing and Reading Blake: A Romantic Circles Praxis
                  Volume</title>. Ed. Wayne C. Ripley and Justin Van Kleeck. Sep. 2010. Romantic
               Circles. Web. 1 July 2012. <ref
                  target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/editing_blake/vankleeck/vankleeck.html"
                  >http://www.rc.umd.edu/praxis/editing_blake/vankleeck/vankleeck.html</ref>
               .</bibl>
            <bibl label="What Does it Mean to Future-Proof a DH Project? 2012" xml:id="project2012"
               key="project2012">
               <title rend="quotes">What Does it Mean to Future-Proof a DH Project?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Questions &amp; Answers</title>. Association
               for Computers and the Humanities, 2011. Web. 7 Aug. 2012.<ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/what-does-it-mean-to-future-proof-a-dh-project"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/topic/what-does-it-mean-to-future-proof-a-dh-project</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
