<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Covers and <emph>Corpus</emph> wanted! Some Digital Humanities
                    Fragments </title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Claire <dhq:family>Clivaz</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>claire.clivaz@sib.swiss</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Claire Clivaz is Head of Digital Enhanced Learning at the Swiss Institute
                            of Bioinformatics (Vital-IT, Lausannne); she belongs to the team of
                            scholars that have started DH in Switzlerand. She leads her research at
                            the crossroad of New Testament and the digital transformations of
                            knowledge. She leads several projects, notably the development of the
                            etalks, a multimedia publication tool (<ref
                                target="http://etalk.vital-it.ch">etalk.vital-it.ch</ref>), as well
                            as a Swiss National Fund on the Arabic manuscripts of Pauline letters
                                (<ref target="wp.unil.ch/nt-arabe/">wp.unil.ch/nt-arabe/</ref>) and
                            participates with six other European partners to a strategic partenariat
                            ERASMUS+ in Digital Humanities (<ref target="dariah.eu/teach"
                                >dariah.eu/teach</ref>). She is a member of several scientific
                            committees (ADHO steering committee, EADH steering committee, IGNTP,
                            Humanistica, etc.) and editorial boards (NTS journal, Digital Religion
                            by de Gruyter, etc.). She is co-leading a series with David Hamidovic by
                            Brill «Digital Biblical Studies», and research groups in DH (SBL,
                            EABS).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000257</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2016-08-03">3 August 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Paper</item>
                        <item>Cover</item>
                        <item>History of reading</item>
                        <item>Jacques Derrida</item>
                        <item>Closure</item>
                        <item>Book</item>
                        <item>Digital Humanities</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="EH" when="2016-05-11">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Covers and bindings are collapsing in the digital textual world. To begin with,
                    the following paper argues that this is not a genuinely new situation, since all
                    cultural Western history attests to written texts as never having been
                    autonomous from oral discourses and versioning steps. Thenceforth – after
                    analyzing the relationship between paper and body, relying notably on Derrida –
                    this article will claim that we have the right and indeed, an obligation, to
                        <q>capture</q> new covers and bindings. During the 17th century, in the
                    lawless parts of the ocean, buccaneers realized that the right to depart was the
                    condition for the capacity to be bound. Therefore, let us dare to depart from
                    ancient bindings and create new boundaries.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article argues that we have the right and indeed, an obligation, to
                        <q>capture</q> new covers and bindings.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head> 1. <q>I have appended separate annotations...</q></head>
                <p>By commenting on his annotated edition of the Greek New Testament project from
                    the <title rend="italic">Vulgate</title>, Erasmus claims in 1515 <ptr
                        target="#erasmus1910" loc="113"/>: <quote rend="block" source="#krans2006">
                        I have translated the whole New Testament after comparison with the Greek
                        copies, and have added the Greek on the facing pages, so that anyone may
                        easily compare it. I have appended separate annotations in which, partly by
                        argument and partly by the authority of the early Fathers, I show that my
                        emendations are not haphazard alterations, for fear that my changes might
                        not carry conviction and in the hope of preserving the corrected text from
                        further damage (<title rend="italic">Epist. 337</title>, ll. 862–868; <ptr
                            target="#krans2006" loc="14"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>As the exegete Jan Krans explains, the last sentence shows that Erasmus considers
                    a text as remaining vulnerable and corruptible if it is not accompanied by a
                    commentary <ptr target="#krans2006" loc="14"/>. Erasmus adopts the same attitude
                    in other passages: the text has to be accompanied by comments in order to be
                    read correctly or according to the intended sense. In other words, decades after
                    the invention of printing, Erasmus is still conditioned by the practices of
                    manuscript culture. His opinion reminds one of the famous Platonian passage in
                    the <title rend="italic">Phaedrus</title> regarding the written discourse that
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">drifts all over the place [...and
                        is] unable to defend or help itself</quote>; Plato posits that speech is
                    superior to written text, since the former is: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">written with intelligence in the mind of the
                        learner</quote> (Plato, <title rend="italic">Phaedrus</title> 275e and 276a,
                        <ptr target="#yunis2003" loc="208"/>). A long time before the
                        <q>factishes</q> of the sociologist Bruno Latour <ptr target="#latour2010"
                    />, written discourse acts here as an intermediate being that is unable to know
                    when it has to speak or to stay quiet and which is dominated by oral discourse.
                    This present article thus aims to consider written texts in the aforementioned
                    manner and by specifically analyzing the transformations of the
                        <emph>corpus</emph> and <q>cover</q> notions; then inquiring about what
                    happens to them in the digital turn. Are covers and the <emph>corpus</emph>
                    desegregating in the process of <q><emph>dépapérisation</emph></q>, the idea of
                        <q>de-paperization</q> according to the words of Jacques Derrida? The French
                    philosopher gave an illuminating interview in 1997 (French version): <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida2005">Paper or me, you know…</quote>
                        <ptr target="#derrida2005"/>
                    </cit>. Derrida compares “de-paperization” to the progressive shrinking of the
                        <title rend="italic">Wild Ass’s Skin</title> by Balzac</p>
                <p>This article aims to delve into this process of <q>de-paperization,</q> and
                    argues that the digital world does not represent only a loss of corporeality but
                    eminently introduces new tensions, encounters with the body, and ways of
                    collaboration. Part 2 serves firstly as a reminder that oral discourse and
                    visual cultures have been superseded by written discourse for only a relatively
                    short period of time within the Western framework. From Codex <title
                        rend="italic">Zacynthius</title> commentaries (6<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> century) to the five manuscripts of the Swiss novel by
                    Charles-Ferdinand Ramuz <hi rend="italic">If the Sun Were Never to Return</hi>
                    (1937 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> edition), and the diverse <hi
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> versions, I wish to recapture Western memory in
                    its never-ending practice of perpetual annotating, rewriting and versioning. The
                    inception of written material, its versioning as well as its relationship to
                    visual and oral materials, leads to the enlightenment of its interaction with
                    the topic of the body-<emph>corpus</emph>. Part 3 focuses on the relationship
                    between corporeality and the digital material of writing, pointing to a new
                    relationship between the body and the digital world. Finally, Part 4 will raise
                    the question of closures and limits; leading to the examination of notions of
                    anxiety as well as liberation.</p>
                <p>The subtitle of this article includes <title rend="quotes">Some Digital
                        Humanities fragments,</title> the last word being a translation from the
                    French <emph><q>éclats</q></emph>, which can refer to fragments of wrath, light,
                    brilliance or something broken. This subtitle points to the fact that Humanities
                    is now present as fragments within digital culture. This process of Humanities’
                    fragmentation should draw Humanist scholars’ attention urgently to what the
                    literary scholar Yves Citton designates as the Humanities’ core duty:
                    interpretation. Considering Humanities as a social fact according to Latourian
                    inspiration, Citton expresses his own task thus: <quote rend="block"
                        source="#citton2010">I would like to suggest that our <q>knowledge
                            societies</q> are worthy to be analyzed first of all as
                            <emph>interpretation cultures</emph> – and that to put at the forefront
                        questions of interpretation has to lead us to deeply reconsider our vision
                        of social interactions, as well as our knowledge mapping, the structuration
                        of our academic institutions and the expression of our politics claimings
                            <ptr target="#citton2010" loc="l. 142–146"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>A similar approach was also presented by the great DH scholar, Stefan Gradman at
                    the DH 2013 conference in Lincoln, Nebraska. Commenting on the EU project DM2E,
                    Gradman described the center of the Humanities field – including
                        <emph>corpora</emph>, metadata, social contexts, references and
                    dissemination/publication – as an <q>interpretative modelisation</q>
                    <note> Stefan Gradman and Susan Schreibman, <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                            Infrastructure: Further Modeling the Scholarly Domain</title>, oral
                        presentation at the DH2013 in Lincoln (19/07/13). The expression is not
                        present in the published abstract <ptr target="#schreibman2013"/>.</note>.
                    Since interpretation is at stake, one should return to the beginning as Plato
                    suggests in <title rend="italic">Timaeus</title> 48b: let us reconsider the
                    written discourse that <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">drifts all over the
                        place [...and is] unable to defend or help itself</quote> (Plato, <hi
                        rend="italic">Phaedrus</hi> 275e), and thus put the interpretative process
                    at stake whilst looking for the fragments of digitized Humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. <q>This discourse which is written with intelligence in the mind of the
                        learner</q>: Telling and Listening as Parts of our Writings.</head>
                <p>In 2012, Clivaz et al. underlined that the mass-scholarization of the 19<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> century led to the supremacy of printed literacy
                    over other forms <ptr target="#furet-ouzouf1977" loc="349–369"/>. This supremacy
                    was however, rather short: between 1850 and 1980. This period is accompanied by
                    the notable decline of the rhetorics in Germany and France, when rhetorical
                    teaching at high schools and universities stopped, specifically in 1897 in
                    France <ptr target="#belhoste1977"/>. In Germany, the work of Lucian of Samosata
                    – a famous representative of Greek rhetoric historical writing <ptr
                        target="#samosate2010"/> – was withdrawn from high school teaching in 1857
                        <ptr target="#baumbach2002"/>. Instead, Leopold von Ranke, the father of
                    German historicism in contrast to Lucian, provided the basis of <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#ranke2000">annoying and
                        <emph>farblos</emph></quote> historical writing <ptr target="#ranke2000"
                        loc="4"/>. He contrasted historical communication with rhetoric and the use
                    of pathos. In a 1964-1965 seminar titled <title rend="italic">L’Ancienne
                        rhétorique</title>, Roland Barthes emblematically presented rhetoric as
                    already limited to memory and to the archives <ptr target="#barthes1970"/>. From
                    that moment on, oral culture seems to have been almost totally forgotten in
                    European historical and literary studies. This was to the profit of written
                    texts that were considered potential containers for all that which is semiotic
                    and thereby able to differentiate reality from the fictional.</p>
                <p>Since the 1950s in the USA, oral cultures have recaptured scholars’ interest,
                    notably in certain historical and sociological research areas. During this
                    period, a preoccupation with oral history appeared alongside two other
                    developments: research focused on the elites and institutions (Columbia School);
                    and on marginal populations (Chicago School). These developments aided the
                    emergence of alternative and hidden histories as well as their transmission by
                    orality (Descamps, 2005). This return to orality is also present in the study of
                    the notion of literacy, notably in the work of Walter Ong <ptr target="#ong2002"
                    />. These approaches have contributed to the development of a growing attention
                    to plural literacies in the Human and Social Sciences. Yves Citton evokes these
                    plural literacies in a <title rend="italic">Le Monde</title> article in the
                    following manner: <quote rend="block" source="#citton2013">In a literature
                        classroom, the point is to share the audacious gesture of interpretation, in
                        the presence of the historical collective that makes us interpreters. It is
                        related to the theatric or choreographic performance, or to the sportive
                        performance, but also to the mystical initiation. [...] The interpretative
                        gesture can be ‘performed’ only in the present <ptr target="#citton2013"
                        />.</quote></p>
                <p>A look back in history shows that the <q>performed work</q> seems obvious in
                    Antiquity, a cultural framework where orality is dominant, as the following
                    musical example demonstrates. The rhetor Dio Chrysostomus (2<hi
                        rend="superscript">nd</hi> century CE) speaks about <q>Homeric music</q>
                        (<hi rend="italic">musike</hi>), whereas his modern editor translates this
                    as <q>Homeric poetry</q>
                    <ptr target="#crosby1946" loc="362–363"/>. Crosby, in the first part of the
                        20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, is unable to conceive that the
                    Homeric work was predominantly <q>music</q> to ancient ears. Ancient culture and
                    texts are full of musical indications that underline its importance, as shown in
                    an <emph>a contrario</emph> way by Socrates’s ironic remark on public singers
                    (the <q>rhaposdes</q>) and the actors who seem the be the authentic wise men
                    (Plato, <title rend="italic">Ion</title> 532d). In fact, the recurrent Platonic
                    attacks on poetry, and arts in general, underline their importance; Plato
                    himself uses assonance games, and <emph>rythmus</emph> with long
                        <emph>sillabi</emph> (Plato, <title rend="italic">Laws</title> 764de). Such
                    a phenomenon can be observed even in the in Rev 18,22a or Rev 14,2, where Paolo
                    Garuti considers the etymological word games as an attempt to reproduce
                    something of the cithara sounds. He concludes that such phenomena belong to the
                    cultural encyclopedia of that time: music was present in words and minds <ptr
                        target="#garuti2013" loc="64"/>.</p>
                <p>It is more surprising – at least for scholars working on Antiquity, who often
                    present an amnesia regarding the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 17<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries – to consider the impact of oral
                    performance on the manuscripts of the Shakespearian <title rend="italic"
                        >Hamlet</title>. Such amnesia has a powerful impact on the way in which one
                    considers authorship in our present digital culture. If the <q>old audience</q>
                    of Humanist scholars was trained to focus on relatively narrow historical
                    periods, the new audience of Humanist PhD students, whatever they choose as
                    topic, should be trained to obtain a deep knowledge of the history of authorship
                    and of the writing material, from the roll to the screen. If one needs to be
                    further convinced thereof, the Shakespearian case of <title rend="italic"
                        >Hamlet</title>’s composition history is surely a good argument. Paul Eggert
                    has recently presented a synthesis of the situation of the first three editions
                    of the printed play dating from 1603, 1604-1605 and 1623. The first version is
                    probably an adaptation of a play performed on the 26<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> July 1602, reconstructed from memory by the actors of the play and
                    written to be sold to an editor, Nicholas Ling <ptr target="#eggert2013"
                        loc="110"/>. The longer versions, however, notably the second, could be
                    literary versions destined to be read rather than to be performed <ptr
                        target="#eggert2013" loc="111"/>. In other words, Shakespeare had a genuine
                    concern for his literary reputation and took care of it, a fact that has been
                    claimed by many scholars since the 1980s. One is able to verify here the
                    influence of spoken discourse on printed literature. Whereas the theatric
                    performance influenced the most ancient version of the text, the aggregate
                    formed by public discourse regarding the author has affected the longer
                    versions. Shakespeare was apparently influenced by the diffuse presence of the
                    public discourse on him. Borrowing from the terminology of the literary critic
                    Jérôme Meizoz, one may say that this influence represented the trace of the
                        <q>literary postures</q> in the middle of the 17<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> century <ptr target="#meizoz2007"/>. Such a notion is confirmed in
                    the following statement by the Shakespearian scholar Lukas Erne: <cit><quote
                        rend="inline" source="#erne2013">the first people who had a vested
                        interest in the rise of dramatic authorship were not the playwrights
                        themselves but the London printers, publishers, and booksellers eager to
                        render respectable and commercially profitable what was initially an
                        enterprise with little or no prestige</quote>
                    <ptr target="#erne2013" loc="l. 1765–1767"/></cit>. </p>
                <p>The impact of others’ discourses – readers, commentators, newspapers and people
                    in the street – on a printed text can be consistently traced: they influenced
                    Erasmus and his annotations, as well as Shakespeare and his diverse rewritings.
                    Even before printing, manuscript culture offered numerous traces of this impact.
                    Let’s consider the Codex <title rend="italic">Zacynthius</title> (6<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> century, palimpsest), where the Gospel according
                    to Luke appears in the middle of pages whose margins are full of patristic
                    commentaries. Certain folios even present two different versions of the Gospel
                    text, one in the center of the page and the other inside the commentaries.
                    However, in 1861, the modern editor Tregelles was chosen to edit only the
                    central version of the text while ignoring the alternative versions present in
                    the commentaries <ptr target="#parker2009" loc="113–119"/>. Such an editorial
                    attitude, whose impact was valorized from Plato to Erasmus, leads to loose
                    information and to the neglect of the commentaries – these
                        <emph>annotations</emph>. Yet such was the printed literacy at its height
                    that it believed it had the right to prune the <q>architext,</q> to return to
                    Genette terminology: it believed it had the right to select, choose, and cut
                    beneath the cover and the front-page, the <q><emph>page de garde</emph></q>. The
                    French phrase <q><emph>page de garde</emph></q> designates the front-page of a
                    book that has the task of being a <q>guard</q>: if we are to discard the
                    protection offered by a book’s <q>cover</q> and the <q>guarding</q> duty of the
                    front-page, are we losing something in digital writing? One can answer that the
                    capacity to consider textuality beyond the boundaries of the cover and
                    front-page was already present in Genette when he was describing the poetic
                    object as <q>the architext,</q> as a network of excellence: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#genette1992">the architext is, then,
                            everywhere – above, beneath, around the text, which spins its web only
                            by hooking it here and there onto that network of architexture</quote>
                        <ptr target="#genette1992" loc="83"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>If one considers the manuscripts and printed texts of Charles-Ferdinand Ramuz
                    from the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, one may estimate that
                    annotation and rewriting practices never stopped completely. In the 27<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> and most recent volume of the complete works of
                    Ramuz, a computing tool allows the reader to compare the five versions of <title
                        rend="italic">If the Sun Were Never to Return</title>, dating from 1937 to
                    1942 <ptr target="#sernier2013"/>. The readers now have to explain whether they
                    have read a version of <title rend="italic">If the Sun Were Never to
                        Return</title> from 1937, 1939, 1940, 1941, or 1942. Such a perspective
                    unbinds the work from the book to make several versions or steps. The
                    fluctuating text plays with the <q>guard</q> of the front-page. The
                    cinematographic version by Claude Goretta (1987) occupies its own space as yet
                    another version in a universe of plural literacies: it is the 1987 version of
                        <title rend="italic">If the Sun Were Never to Return</title><note> See the
                        website that presents the Swiss moovie <title rend="italic">If the Sun Were
                            Never to Return</title>, <ref
                            target="http://www.swissfilms.ch/fr/film_search/filmdetails/-/id_film/2146533716"
                            >
                            http://www.swissfilms.ch/fr/film_search/filmdetails/-/id_film/2146533716</ref>
                        (last accessed on 10/13/2015).</note>. With respect to the form, one is able
                    to verify here what Wido van Peursen refers to as constitutive of the digital
                    culture: the <q>text</q> is perceived as a document <ptr
                        target="#vanpeursen2010"/>. In the middle of digitalized documents, unbound
                    from their statuses as unique works, emerges the question of content
                    communication; <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida2005">to communicate a
                        thought,</quote> as an interviewer asked Derrida in 1997 during a seminal
                    interview about the function of paper: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida2005">To what extent has [the paper]
                            been adequate for you to communicate your thinking?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#derrida2005" loc="41"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Losing the body-corpus? </head>
                <p>Before answering this question about the adequacy of paper to relate one’s
                    thoughts, Jacques Derrida propounds an impressive perspective on the
                        <q>paper-body</q>: <quote rend="block" source="#derrida2005">Ever since I
                        started writing, both the institution and the stability of paper have been
                        constantly exposed to seismic shake-ups. The beasts of relentless writing
                        that we are could not remain either deaf or insensitive to this. Every sign
                        on the paper had to be picked up as an advance sign: it foretold the
                            <q>loss</q> of a support: the end of the <q>subjectile</q> is nigh. That
                        is also, doubtless, where this body of paper has a bodily hold on us <ptr
                            target="#derrida2005" loc="42"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>Holding on to this <q>paper-body</q> perspective, this current section of the
                    article will underline how Derrida frames this notion of fragmented textuality
                    as a bodily disconnection within our digital age. Relying on the shrinking of
                        <title rend="italic">The Wild Ass’s Skin</title>, he discusses the
                    inexorable shrinking of this <q>hyletic</q> material, recalling that the Greek
                            <emph><q>ule</q></emph> also means <q>hood, forest</q> and
                        <q>material</q>
                    <ptr target="#derrida2005" loc="46"/>. How could the biblical scholars – to whom
                    I belong – not be sensitive to what happens here, knowing that the word
                        <q>Bible</q> itself supports notions of writing: papyrus is accorded the
                    name <q><emph>bublos</emph>,</q>, which refers to a plant named in the Lebanese
                    region of the ancient city of Bublos. If one considers <q><emph>liber</emph></q>
                    or <q>
                        <emph>caudex</emph>,</q> these Latin words also refer to the vegetal domain,
                    specifically to the <q>hood</q> as represented by both parts of a book’s cover
                    which maintain the folios inside. As Derrida summarizes it: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#derrida2005">Paper is utilized in an experience involving the body,
                        beginning with hands, eyes, voice, ears; so it mobilizes both time and space
                            <ptr target="#derrida2005" loc="36"/></quote>. The same <q>shrinking</q>
                    process could affect <q>a certain writing,</q> warns Derrida: <quote
                        rend="block" source="#derrida2005">Can we speak then of abandon, arrest, or
                        inhibition when designating the ongoing withdrawal or decline of a certain
                        kind of writing: particularly the decline of steely writing with the point
                        of a pen on the surface of paper, the decline of the hand, or at any rate of
                        a specific and unique way of using the hand? If we were to associate this
                        withdrawal with an effectual untying, namely the untying that effectively
                        undoes the symbolic link of writing to walking. Thereby moving along,
                        breaking a path, and untying the plotted connections between eyes, hands,
                        and feet, then perhaps we would be dealing with the symptoms of another
                        historical-, or as some would perhaps say, a posthistorical-phase. At any
                        rate, another epoch could be hanging in the balance: keeping us in suspense,
                        carrying off another scene, another scenario, keeping us distanced from, and
                        raised above paper; all this according to another model of the prohibited.
                        Therein lies a form of anxiety within the agenda <ptr target="#derrida2005"
                            loc="54"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>Seventeen years later, this anxiety is what is really at stake in public opinion.
                    The USA has stopped teaching cursive writing to children <ptr target="#doll2012"
                    />, whereas French newspapers misunderstood this news and transmitted it as
                        <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#luteaud2013">the end of handwriting at
                        school</quote><ptr target="#luteaud2013"/></cit><note> See also <title
                            rend="italic">Le Courrier international : La fin de l’écriture</title>
                        1194 (18 septembre 2013). See also my blog <title rend="quotes">La vengance
                            de la gommette 2 : ne pas trop vite crier au loup !</title>, <ref
                            target="http://claireclivaz.hypotheses.org/348"
                            >http://claireclivaz.hypotheses.org/348</ref> (last accessed on
                        10/13/2015).</note>. Taking Derrida into consideration as he imagined the
                    shrinking of only <q>a certain writing,</q> but not without also conceiving this
                    moment as <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#derrida2005">the earthquake that is
                        happening sometimes leads to <q>losing one’s head</q> or loss of
                            <q>sense</q></quote>
                    <ptr target="#derrida2005" loc="58"/></cit>. Perhaps it is worth recalling that
                    western cultural memory does not stop to say it in a myriad of ways: body and
                    books were jointly liable. With this in mind, one should examine the figure of
                    Melany the Young, Christian literate in the fourth century CE. The life of Saint
                    Melany, beyond the hagiographical tone, represents an interesting testimony on
                    various aspects: individual consciousness, the form of books, the reading
                    practices and the spiritual cross around the object of the <q>book</q>
                    <ptr target="#gorce1962"/>. Married at the age of fourteen (§1), Melany risked
                    death during the birth of her second child (§5), and at twenty years old,
                    reached an agreement with her husband so that she could live in chastity (§6).
                    The pretext was an imperative need to devote herself to God but evidently Melany
                    focused on an intellectual and ascetic life; reading everything she found and
                    copying the Old and New Testaments several times per year (§26). She also wrote
                    small booklets called <title rend="italic">somatioi</title>, <q>little
                        bodies</q> (§23 and 36). There is a clear symbolic exchange: whereas
                    Melany’s body stopped making children, she translated her fecundity to these
                        <q>little bodies</q> that she wrote. This relationship between body and
                    manuscript can be seen throughout the entire history of the codex, as animal
                    skin parchments exemplify.<note> One can here refer to the thorough reading by
                        Emmanuèle Baumgartner (1999).</note></p>
                <p>One needs to consider the size of the loss, of the shrinking of this
                        <q>paper-body.</q> After a moment of nostalgic reflection, one can then look
                    closely at the next wave growing on the horizon: the new bindings, dependencies,
                    hybrids and paradoxical relationships between the body and the digital material
                    of writing. To consider the Digital Humanities for what they are or could be,
                    one has to let them walk at their own rhythms. Humanities is <q>done</q> with
                    fingers, according the Latin word <emph>digitus</emph>. Thus, one may refer to
                    the hand-machine interface that one sees with the finger-print scanning on the
                    iPhone 5S <note> See the Youtube video <title rend="italic">Hands on with iPhone
                            5S Touch ID fingerprint scanner</title>. <ref
                            target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lfIDSx2OHgQ"
                            >http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lfIDSx2OHgQ</ref> (last accessed on
                        10/15/15).</note> or by discovering words <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#fabre2013">with the top of the fingers</quote> as a Swiss
                    newspaper titled the DH project EPFL-Venice <ptr target="#fabre2013" loc="36"/>.
                    With symbolic and semantic sensitivity, Robert Darnton related the German word
                        <emph>Fingerspitzengefühl</emph> – to be able to discover the world in
                    details with the top of the fingers – to the emergence of digital screens:
                        <quote rend="block" source="#darton2009">We find our way through the world
                        by means of a sensory disposition that the Germans call
                            <emph>Fingerspitzengefühl</emph>. If you were trained to guide a pen
                        with your finger index, look at the way young people use their thumbs on
                        mobile phones, and you will see how technology penetrates a new generation,
                        body and soul <ptr target="#darton2009" loc="XII"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>Even breath can lead us to a surprising body-machine dialogue as we noticed in a
                    new form of multi-media publication, the eTalk, that we are developing as an
                    interdisciplinary team in Lausanne: the software, Audacity, shares the discourse
                    of a scholar in small pieces by following the rhythmus of their breath.
                        <q>Sentences</q> in the eTalk are replaced by another measure: breaths that
                    share the discourse in small pieces of 2-3 sentences each <ptr
                        target="#clivaz2015a"/>. In other words, the digital world does not
                    represent only a loss of corporeality but, as previously stated, eminently
                    introduces new ways of collaboration, tensions, and encounters with the body,
                    with amazing new medical and IT findings such as the creation of an artificial
                        skin.<note> See for example this blog of synthesis by Justin Alford on an
                        artificial skin (<ref
                            target="http://www.iflscience.com/technology/smart-artificial-skin-could-give-prosthetic-limbs-feeling"
                            >http://www.iflscience.com/technology/smart-artificial-skin-could-give-prosthetic-limbs-feeling</ref>;
                        last accessed on 10/15/15).</note> If the body is at stake in a digital
                    culture <ptr target="#clivaz2015b"/>, the questions of closure and delimitation
                    – notions so important in order to avoid a complete dissemination leading to
                    madness – remain necessary and have to be reconfigured. It is thus an area of
                    focus that requires examination.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Towards closure and delimitation: the <q>capture</q> as challenge.</head>
                <p> How will we react to the anxiety provoked by the loss of the relationship
                    between body and paper or by the so-called end of <q>handwriting teaching</q>?
                    Temporally speaking, our first reaction when faced with an <q>out of the
                        book</q> textuality collapsing into an infinite <q>architexture</q> would
                    have been to develop a new form of scribal elitist culture with the most
                    sophisticated methods of electronic encoding. Is this compatible with real DH
                    dissemination? One would hope to see more efforts made in this direction of
                    dissemination. Let us compare Wikipedia in its English and French versions:
                    Wikipedia.fr allows anyone to write and upload an article without requiring
                    basic HTML5 encoding thanks to a <q>visual editor,</q> whereas Wikipedia.org
                    requires HTML5 knowledge to modify a page or to create an article.<note> See for
                        Wikipedia.org guidelines : <ref
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:HTML_in_wikitext"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:HTML_in_wikitext</ref> (last
                        accessed on 10/15/15); see for Wikipedia.fr guidelines, with the choic of
                        the visual editor, or the HTML5 editor: <ref
                            target="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aide:Comment_modifier_une_page_en_wikicode"
                            >https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aide:Comment_modifier_une_page_en_wikicode</ref>
                        (last accessed on 10/15/15).</note> With the introduction of a visual
                    editor, it has been almost effortless to write an article on French Wikipedia.
                    This is not a mere detail: it provides a way for allowing wider DH
                    dissemination, resulting in the means to enroll a wide audience in the
                        <q>wiki</q> process. The University of Geneva (CH) has started to organize
                    open workshops to encourage and train women to contribute to the French
                    Wikipedia’s articles: the possibility to circumvent HTML5 encoding allows
                    contributors to reach diverse audiences and to raise the level of DH
                        dissemination.<note> Swiss news, 10/11/15 : the University of Geneva (CH)
                        organizes Wikipedia training workshops for women : <ref
                            target="http://www.rts.ch/play/tv/19h30/video/wikipedia-compte-tres-peu-de-collaboratrices?id=7159067"
                            >http://www.rts.ch/play/tv/19h30/video/wikipedia-compte-tres-peu-de-collaboratrices?id=7159067</ref>(last
                        accessed on 10/15/15).</note> Time will tell how the situation evolves; as
                    yet Wikipedia.org is still untransformed.</p>
                <p> The emergence of a new scribal culture will not be a guarantee to us
                    rediscovering the possibility of closures and delimitations. To recapture the
                    notion of a limit, one should imagine the process in three steps. First, we have
                    to keep in mind that manuscripts and printed cultures were also able to foster
                    fear – fear of being overwhelmed by books and paper. The end of the Gospel
                    according to John 21.25 claims that the world would not be able to contain
                    everything that could be written about Jesus’ stories, reflecting an anxiety
                    regarding a written knowledge able to absorb the world. Ann Blair, in <title
                        rend="italic">Too Much to Know</title>, refreshes one’s mind by helping one
                    to escape the academic <q>amnesia</q> related to the 16<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>-17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries: she pleads for us to
                    use the term <q>information age</q> anachronistically in a non technical way,
                    underlining the idea that <q>information management</q> has accompanied the
                    birth of the printed book <ptr target="#blair2010" loc="l. 136"/>. She reminds
                    us that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#blair2010">historians have pointed
                        especially to three main sources of information explosion in the
                        Renaissance: the discovery of new worlds, the recovery of ancient texts, and
                        the proliferation of printed books</quote>
                    <ptr target="#blair2010" loc="l. 324–325"/></cit>; in her book she expands this point
                    of view with examples from cultures with limited or no contact with Western
                    Europe. Such an approach, opening the historical gates to a thoroughgoing
                    perspective, beyond Western cultures, is absolutely necessary to facing the
                    anxiety one can face today. The building of a bridge between <q>old
                        audiences</q> and <q>new audiences</q> is required. Such a platform offers a
                    stable ground that one may move with Derrida from anxiety to the feeling of
                        <q>out-of-paper liberation</q> that he expresses so strongly in the
                    conclusion of his interview: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#derrida2005"
                        >Because on the other hand, I also suffer, to the point of suffocation, from
                            <emph>too much paper</emph>, and this is another spleen. Another
                        ecological sigh. How can we save the world <emph>from</emph> paper? And its
                        own body? So I <emph>also</emph> dream of living paperless – and sometimes
                        that sounds to my ears like a definition or <q>real life</q>, of the living
                        part of life. [...] Let’s not count the books. So paper expels me – outside
                        my home. It chases me off. This time, it’s an <emph>aut aut</emph>: paper
                            <emph>or</emph> me.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#derrida2005" loc="64"/></cit>. </p>
                <p>Firstly, we can also find a sense of liberation when one goes <q>out of the
                        paper.</q> Secondly, one has to bravely assume that the objectivation of
                    knowledge allowed by paper is ending. From the Modern duality of subject-object
                    succeeds an era of intersubjectivity, of networking and graphs. The
                    responsibility of subjects to transport knowledge and culture is increasingly at
                    stake in such a digital framework. If <title rend="italic">Fahrenheit
                        451</title> by Ray Bradbury was a science-fiction novel in 1953, it sounds
                    really less like that today. In particular it illustrates how much our own
                    bodies are the covers of what we know and we transmit today. By surfing on the
                    waters of the <q>web,</q> it is eminently our responsibility to define, enclose
                    and limit the pieces of knowledge we still want to keep, preserve and transmit.
                    In printed culture, we had the secure boundaries of <q>chapter, word, phrase,
                        line,</q> elements that allowed us to consider texts as <cit><quote rend="inline"
                        source="#witmore2010">massively addressable [objects] at different levels
                        of scale</quote>
                    <ptr target="#witmore2010"/></cit>. Yet, as in the manuscript culture of the first
                    centuries C.E., even these boundaries are not mandatory guarantees in the
                    digital architexture ocean. </p>
                <p>In consequence, a third step needs to be taken. It is surely not enough to
                    innovate by shrinking <ptr target="#goulet-vinck2009"/>, we need a <q>creative
                        fury</q> according to Citton’s statement: <cit><quote rend="inline"
                        source="#citton2010">to improve intelligence and make the world
                        evolve</quote>
                    <ptr target="#citton2010" loc="l. 142–146"/></cit>. In a quest for this <q>creative
                        fury,</q> we can once more solicit the reserves of Western historical memory
                    and return to the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century. To conclude, one may
                    borrow the excellent remarks made by Olivier Abel, Ethics professor at the
                    Protestant Institute of Theology (Montpellier/Paris), concerning the buccaneers
                    of this century and the <q>capture anthropology</q> that emerges from this
                    particular style of life. Olivier Abel underlines that: <quote rend="block"
                        source="#abel2009a">The time of the buccaneers was particularly flourishing
                        in the Caribbean between 1630 and 1670. In the new worlds, everything is
                        offered with profusion by the divine Providence. [...] We are not in a gift
                        and exchange economy any more, but in an economy of the <q>capture</q>, that
                        stands even in the title of the Dutch philosopher Grotius <title
                            rend="italic">On the Right of Capture</title>. The history tempest has
                        broken all links, and the pirate ship stands for the multi-religious and
                        multi-racial utopia of a free adhesion, after the tempest, even if one
                        adopts rules harder, as in an anti-reality. <ptr target="#abel2009a"
                            loc="107"/></quote></p>
                <p>The 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, with this focus on Grotius’ notion
                    of the <q>right of capture</q> forms a link to this article’s Part 2; it thus
                    proves fruitful to consider our digital transformation. Indeed, in 2011, Johanna
                    Drucker made the now-famous proposition to switch from the notion of <q>data</q>
                    to <q>capta</q>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#drucker2011">Differences in the etymological
                            roots of the terms data and capta make the distinction between
                            constructivist and realist approaches clear. <emph>Capta</emph> is
                                <q>taken</q> actively while <emph>data</emph> is assumed to be a
                                <q>given</q> able to be recorded and observed. From this
                            distinction, a world of differences arises. Humanistic inquiry
                            acknowledges the situated, partial, and constitutive character of
                            knowledge production, the recognition that knowledge is constructed,
                                <emph>taken</emph>, not simply given as a natural representation of
                            pre-existing fact.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2011" loc="§3"/>
                    </cit> The notion of <q>capta</q> can be related to the seldom-used French word
                        <q>capitation,</q> which means to capture a part of heritage or some
                        money.<note> See the definition of the French dictionary <title
                            rend="italic">Larousse</title>, <ref
                            target="http://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/captation/13011"
                            >http://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/captation/13011</ref>(last
                        accessed on 10/15/15).</note> Whatever it is on the digital ocean, or on the
                        17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century’s oceans, the act of capture seems
                    to be the one required by new open spaces and thence to grasp some parts of our
                    cultural heritage.</p>
                <p>After describing such an atmosphere, Abel pursues his analysis in another
                    article, arguing that out in the ocean there is neither king nor pope any more,
                    one stands alone with God, one has left everything behind. Forced to live
                    everyday without knowing what will come in the next, one quickly learns that it
                    is impossible to possess the sea, to keep it in one’s fingers. Nevertheless,
                    seafaring individuals are so unbound that they can contract new alliances, free
                    alliances: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#abel2009b">the right to depart is the
                            condition of the capacity to be bound. The political question will thus
                            gradually become: <q>How can we stay together?</q> when we can always
                            become unbound?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#abel2009b" loc="115"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Everything is said in the notion of: <quote rend="inline" source="#abel2009a"
                        >the right to depart is the condition of the capacity to be bound.</quote>
                    To exit the cover – to depart for lawless regions of the ocean – provides the
                    right to leave, to depart. Since textuality has now – literally speaking – the
                    right to depart from the book, it can also contract free alliances, with images,
                    sounds, and all the other forms of texts. During the 17<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> century, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#abel2009a">since on the
                        ocean everything is going unbound, ceaselessly, one has to reconsider what
                        are moorings, ropes, ties, knots and pacts</quote>
                    <ptr target="#abel2009a" loc="108"/></cit>. Today this is the role of new technologies
                    – to give us the right to break free from the bindings and the front-pages of
                    printed culture. This is an obligation, one could say, because it is impossible
                    to possess the Internet ocean, to keep it inside of our fingers, inside our
                    humanity. The right to capture, harvest, and select becomes the condition to
                    bind, delimit and draw a virtual cover. Humanities out of the book, unbound, may
                    force us to <q>go on board</q>! All our ways to <emph>net-work</emph> and to
                    bind will be then have to be reconsidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>With the kind permission of the editors, this English article is based on the
                    translation of a forthcoming French article by Clivaz, C., <title rend="quotes"
                        >En quête des couvertures et corpus. Quelques éclats d’humanités
                        digitales</title>. In Carayol Valerie, Morandi Franc (eds.), <title
                        rend="italic">Le Tournant Numérique des Sciences Humaines et
                        Sociales</title>, Pessac, MSHA, 2015, p. 97-109. The author reformulated
                    some sentences and expanded some passages in this English version. Many thanks
                    are due to Harley Edwards for the English proof reading of this article. I am
                    also very grateful to the two anonymous reviewers who brought important
                    suggestions for improvements as well as rich bibliographical references to this
                    article.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Abel 2009a" xml:id="abel2009a"> Olivier Abel. <title rend="quotes"
                        >L’océan, le puritain, le pirate,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Esprit</title> 356 (2009), 104–10.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Abel 2009b" xml:id="abel2009b"> Olivier Abel. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Essai sur la prise. Anthropologie de la flibuste et théologie radicale
                        protestante,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Esprit</title> 356 (2009b), 114–15; <ref
                        target=" http://olivierabel.fr/nuit-ethique-les-cultures-et-le-differend/pirates-puritains.php"
                        >http://olivierabel.fr/nuit-ethique-les-cultures-et-le-differend/pirates-puritains.php</ref>
                    (last accessed on 10/15/15). With Olivier Abel’s permission, the online version
                    is quoted, rather than the printed one, since I prefer it.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Barthes 1970" xml:id="barthes1970"> Roland Barthes. <title
                        rend="quotes">L’ancienne rhétorique. Aide-mémoire.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Communications</title> 16 (1970), 172–223.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Baumbach 2002" xml:id="baumbach2002"> Manuel Baumbach. <title
                        rend="italic">Lukian in Deutschland. Eine Forschungs-und
                        Rezeptionsgeschichtliche Analyse vom Humanismus bis zur Gegenwart</title>
                        (<title rend="italic">Beihefte zu Poetica</title> 25). Munich: Verlag
                    Wilhelm Fink, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Baumgartner 1999" xml:id="baumgartner1999"> Emmanuèle Baumgarnter,
                        <title rend="quotes">Du manuscrit retrouvé au corps retrouvé.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Le Topos du manuscrit trouvé. Actes du colloque
                        international Louvain-Gand</title>, 22-23-24 mai 1997 [hommage à Christian
                    Angelet]. Edited by Jan Hermann, Fernand Hallyn and Kris Peeters. Leuven:
                    Peeters, 1999, 1-14.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Blair 2010" xml:id="blair2010"> Ann Blair. <title rend="italic">Too
                        Much to Know</title>. Yale: Yale University Press, 2010. Kindle
                    edition.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Belhoste 1977" xml:id="belhoste1977"> Bruno Belhoste, <title
                        rend="quotes">L’enseignement secondaire français et les sciences au début du
                            XX<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle. La réforme de 1902 des plans
                        d’études et des programmes.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Revue d’histoire des sciences</title> 43 (1977):
                    371–400.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Citton 2010" xml:id="citton2010"> Yves Citton. <title rend="italic"
                        >L’Avenir des Humanités. Économie de la connaissance ou culture de
                        l’interprétation ?</title>. Paris: La Découverte, 2010. Kindle
                    edition.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Citton 2013" xml:id="citton2013"> Yves Citton, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Transmettre les textes ne se limite pas à transférer des
                        connaissances.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Le Monde</title>, 21 mars 2013. <ref
                        target="http://www.lemonde.fr/idees/article/2013/03/21/transmettre-les-textes-ne-se-limite-pas-a-transferer-des-connaissances_1852037_3232.html"
                        >http://www.lemonde.fr/idees/article/2013/03/21/transmettre-les-textes-ne-se-limite-pas-a-transferer-des-connaissances_1852037_3232.html</ref>
                    (last accessed on 03/15/2015).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Clivaz et al., 2012" xml:id="clivaz2012"> Claire Clivaz, Jérôme Meizoz,
                    François Vallotton and Joseph Verheyden, with Benjamin Bertho. <title
                        rend="italic">Reading Tomorrow. From Ancient Manuscripts to the Digital
                        Era / Lire Demain. Des manuscrits antiques à l’ère digitale</title>.
                    Lausanne: PPUR, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Clivaz et al., 2015a" xml:id="clivaz2015a"> Claire Clivaz, Marion
                    Rivoal and Martial Sankar. <title rend="quotes">A New Platform for Editing
                        Digital Multimedia: The eTalks.</title> In <ref
                        target="http://ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/40894"><title rend="italic"
                            >New Avenues for Electronic Publishing in the Age of Infinite
                            Collections and Citizen Science: Scale</title></ref>. Edited by Birgit
                    Schmidt and Milena Dobreva. Openness and Trust, Amsterdam (The authors and IOS
                    Press), 2015, 156–159 ; DOI : 10.3233/978-1-61499-562-3-156 ; <ref
                        target="http://ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/40894"
                        >http://ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/40894</ref>(last accessed on
                    10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Clivaz 2015b" xml:id="clivaz2015b"> Claire Clivaz. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Mais où est le corps? L’homme augmenté comme lieu des Humanités
                        Digitales.</title> In <title rend="italic">L’homme augmenté
                    (eTalks)</title>. Edited by Philippe Bornet, Claire Clivaz, Nicole Durisch
                    Gauthier and Etienne Honoré. VITAL-DH, Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, 2015.
                        <ref target="http://etalk2.vital-it.ch/?dir=Clivaz#0"
                        >http://etalk2.vital-it.ch/?dir=Clivaz#0</ref>(last accessed 10/15/15). </bibl>
                <bibl label="Crosby 1946" xml:id="crosby1946"> Dion Chrysostomus. <title
                        rend="quotes">On Homer. Discourse 53,7.</title> In <title rend="italic">Dio
                        Chrysostom</title>. Edited by Lamar Crosby, Volume 4. Cambridge/Londres:
                    Harvard University Press, 1946, 362–63.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Darton 2009" xml:id="darton2009"> Robert Darnton. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Case for Books: Past, Present, Future</title>. New York: PublicAffairs,
                    2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Derrida 2005" xml:id="derrida2005"> Jacques Derrida, <title
                        rend="quotes">Paper of me, You Know… (New Speculations on a Luxury of the
                        Poor.)</title> In <title rend="italic">Paper Machine</title>, 2<hi
                        rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed. Edited by Jacques Derrida. Translated by the
                    Board of Trustees (Stanford). Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2005, 41–65;
                        <ref target="http://users.clas.ufl.edu/burt/Derridapaperorme.pdf"
                        >http://users.clas.ufl.edu/burt/Derridapaperorme.pdf</ref> (last accessed on
                    10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Descamps 2005" xml:id="descamps2005"> Florence Descamps. <title
                        rend="italic">L’Historien, l’archiviste et le magnétophone</title> (<title
                        rend="italic">Histoire économique XIX</title><hi rend="superscript"
                        >e</hi><hi rend="italic">-XX</hi><hi rend="superscript">e</hi><hi
                        rend="italic"> siècle</hi>). Paris: Comité pour l’histoire économique et
                    financière de la France/IGPDE, 2005. <ref
                        target="http://books.openedition.org/igpde/438"
                        >http://books.openedition.org/igpde/438</ref> (last accessed on
                    10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Doll, 2012" xml:id="doll2012"> Jen Doll, <title rend="quotes">Cursive
                        May Die, But We’ll Talk About It Endlessly First.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Atlantic Wire</title>, 9 juillet 2012; <ref
                        target="http://www.theatlanticwire.com/entertainment/2012/07/cursive-may-die-well-talk-about-it-endlessly-first/54337/"
                        >http://www.theatlanticwire.com/entertainment/2012/07/cursive-may-die-well-talk-about-it-endlessly-first/54337/</ref>
                    (last accessed on 10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Drucker 2011" xml:id="drucker2011"> Johanna Drucker, <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> 5.1 (2011): <ref
                        target=" http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Eggert 2013" xml:id="eggert2013"> Paul Eggert. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Apparatus, text, interface: how to read a printed critical edition.</title>
                    In <title rend="italic">Cambridge Companion to Textual Scholarship</title>.
                    Edited by Neil Fraistat and Julia Flanders. Cambridge (MA): Cambridge Unviersity
                    Press, 2013, 97–118.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Erasmus 1910" xml:id="erasmus1910"> Desiderius Erasmus, <title
                        rend="italic">Opus epistolarum Des. Erasmi Roterodami / denuo recognitum et
                        auctum per P. Allen, H.M. Allen, H. W. Garrod</title>, vol. II, Oxonii : in
                    Typ. Clarendoniano, 1910.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Erne 2013" xml:id="erne2013"> Lukas Erne, <title rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare as Literary Dramatist</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University
                    Press, 2013. Second kindle edition.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fabre 2013" xml:id="fabre2013"> Joëlle Fabre, <title rend="quotes">Le
                        monde au bout des doigts. Humanités Digitales. Ressusciter le passé est
                        l’une des promesses du savoir numérisé.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">24Heures</title>, 12 September 2013, 36.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Furet-Ouzouf 1977" xml:id="furet-ouzouf1977"> François Furet and
                    Jacques Ozouf. <title rend="italic">Lire et écrire. La scolarisation des
                        Français de Calvin à Jules Ferry</title>. Paris: Minuit, 1977.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Garuti 2013" xml:id="garuti2013"> Paolo Garuti. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cultes et (natu-)culture dans l’Apocalypse de Jean: les emprunts à
                        l’imagerie d’origine hellénistique, romaine ou indo-iranienne comme
                        phénomène de perception de la <q>nature</q>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Angelicum</title> 90 (2013), 57–86.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Genette 1992" xml:id="genette1992"> Gérard Genette. <title
                        rend="italic">The Architext. An Introduction</title>. Translated by Jane E.
                    Lewin. Berkeley, Los Angeles and Oxford: University of California Press,
                    1992.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gorce 1962" xml:id="gorce1962"> Denys Gorce. <title rend="italic">Vie
                        de Sainte Mélanie</title> (<title rend="italic">SC</title> 90), Paris,
                    Éditions du Cerf, 1962.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Goulet-Vinck 2009" xml:id="goulet-vinck2009"> Frédéric Goulet and
                    Dominique Vinck. <title rend="quotes">L’innovation par retrait. Contribution à
                        une sociologie du détachement.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Revue française de sociologie</title> 53/3
                    (2009), 195–224.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Krans 2006" xml:id="krans2006"> Jan Krans, <title rend="italic">Beyond
                        What Is Written: Erasmus and Beza as Conjectural Critics of the New
                        Testament</title> (<title rend="italic">NTTS</title> 35). Leiden /
                    Boston: Brill, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Latour 2010" xml:id="latour2010"> Bruno Latour, <title rend="italic">On
                        the Modern Cult of the Factish Gods</title> (<title rend="italic">Science
                        and Cultural Theory</title>). Duke: Duke University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Luteaud 2013" xml:id="luteaud2013"> Bénédicte Luteaud. <title
                        rend="quotes">Apprendre à écrire ne sera plus obligatoire dans les écoles de
                        45 États américains.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Quoi.info</title>, 21 février 2013; <ref
                        target="http://quoi.info/actualite-education/2013/02/21/apprendre-a-ecrire-a-lecole-bientot-demode-1161153/"
                        >http://quoi.info/actualite-education/2013/02/21/apprendre-a-ecrire-a-lecole-bientot-demode-1161153/</ref>
                    (last accessed on 10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Meizoz 2007 and 2011" xml:id="meizoz2007"> Jérôme Meizoz. <title
                        rend="italic">Postures littéraires I et II</title>. Genève, Slatkine, 2007
                    and 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ong 2002" xml:id="ong2002"> Walter Ong. <title rend="italic">Orality
                        and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word</title>. New York: Routledge,
                    2002.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Parker 2009" xml:id="parker2009"> David Parker. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Date of Codex Zacynthius (Ξ): A New Proposal.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Manuscripts, Texts, Theology. Collected Papers
                        1977-2007</title> (<title rend="italic">ANTT</title> 40). Edited by David
                    Parker. Berlin/New York: Walter de Gruyter, 2009, 113–19.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Van Peursen 2010" xml:id="vanpeursen2010"> Wido van Peursen. <title
                        rend="quotes">Text Comparison and Digital Creativity: An
                        Introduction.</title> In <title rend="italic">Text Comparison and Digital
                        Creativity. The Production of Presence and Meaning in Digital Text
                        Scholarship</title> (<title rend="italic">Scholarly Communication</title>
                    1). Edited by Wido van Peursen, Ernst D. Thoutenhoofd and Adrian Van der Weel.
                    Brill, Leiden, 2010, 1–27.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ranke 2000" xml:id="ranke2000"> Leopold von Ranke, <title rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte der Germanischen Völker. Fürsten und Völker die Geschichte der
                        romanischen und germanischen Völker von 1494 bis 1514</title>. Genève:
                    Wiesbaden, Emil Vollmer Verlag, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Samosata 2010" xml:id="samosate2010"> Lucian of Samosata. <title
                        rend="italic">Comment il faut écrire l’histoire </title>(<title
                        rend="italic">La roue à livres</title> 55). Edited by André Husrt. Paris:
                    Les Belles Lettres, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sernier 2013" xml:id="sernier2013"> Emilien Sernier, <title
                        rend="quotes">C.F. Ramuz, Œuvres complètes vol. 27: Romans
                        (1932-1937).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Fabula</title> 28 août 2013. <ref
                        target="http://www.fabula.org/actualites/cf-ramuz-oeuvres-completes-vol-27-romans-1932-1937_58276.php"
                        >http://www.fabula.org/actualites/cf-ramuz-oeuvres-completes-vol-27-romans-1932-1937_58276.php</ref>
                    (last accessed on 10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Schreibman 2013" xml:id="schreibman2013"> Susan Schreibman, Stefan
                    Gradmann, Steffen Hennicke, Tobias Blanke, Sally Chambers, et. al. (2013). <ref
                        target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/files/downloads/DH2013_conference_abstracts_print.pdf"
                        >http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/files/downloads/DH2013_conference_abstracts_print.pdf</ref>
                    <title rend="quotes">Beyond Infrastructure – Modelling Scholarly Research and
                        Collaboration.</title> In <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2013:
                        Conference Abstracts</title>, University of Nebraska–Lincoln, USA, 16-19
                    July 2013, 386-389.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Witmore 2010" xml:id="witmore2010"> Michael Witmore, <title
                        rend="quotes">Text: A Massively Addressable Object.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Wine Dark Sea</title> blog. 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>
                    Decembre 2011, <ref target="http://winedarksea.org/?p=926"
                        >http://winedarksea.org/?p=926</ref>(last accessed on 10/15/15).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Yunis 2003" xml:id="yunis2003"> Harvey Yunis, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Writing for Reading. Thucydides, Plato, and the Emergence of the Critical
                        Reader.</title> In <title rend="italic">Written Texts and the Rise of
                        Literate Culture in Ancient Greece</title>. Edited by Harvey Yunis.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003, 189-212.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
