<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The Printing Press as Metaphor</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Elyse <dhq:family>Graham</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>SUNY Stony Brook</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jean.graham@stonybrook.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Elyse Graham is assistant professor of digital humanities at SUNY Stony
                            Brook and a research affiliate at the Massachusetts Institute of
                            Technology.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000264</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2016-08-10">10 August 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital humanities</item>
                        <item>book history</item>
                        <item>rhetoric</item>
                        <item>history of the discipline</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2016-07-11">Created File</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>These days, we are constantly looking for an image of ourselves in the historical
                    past. “The first ever information revolution,” begins a typical book jacket
                    blurb, “began with the advent of the printed book, enabling Renaissance scholars
                    to formulate new ways of organizing and disseminating knowledge” <ptr
                        target="#sawday2000"/>. A communications scholar offers a view of our place
                    in history that has echoes in countless other publications and presentations:
                    “At present we are witnessing an information revolution whose significance
                    parallels and perhaps even surpasses that of the information revolution caused
                    by the printing press in the fifteenth century” <ptr target="#jucker2003"
                        loc="129"/>. Publishers, both academic and trade, have created a new genre
                    of book titles that confidently find the digital sizzle in the analog past:
                        <title rend="italic">The Renaissance Computer</title> (on printed books),
                        <title rend="italic">The Victorian Internet</title> (on the telegraph),
                        <title rend="italic">Social Media: The First 2,000 Years</title> (on
                    letters, pamphlets, and graffiti). Scholars give talks with titles like <title
                        rend="quotes">Books as Social Media</title> (Leah Price), <title
                        rend="quotes">Blogging Now and Then (250 Years Ago)</title> (Robert
                    Darnton), and <title rend="quotes">What’s in a Visitor’s Book? Social Media and
                        Volcanic Tourism in the Nineteenth Century</title> (John Brewer).</p>
                <p>Surrounded as we are by these analogies — by these claims in favor of specific
                    ways of construing the relationship between the past and the present, and by the
                    significance claims that go with them — it seems fair to ask what purposes they
                    serve. There is no doubt that we feel ourselves to be in the midst of a period
                    of dramatic change in our media and information environments. My interest in
                    this essay lies not in these environments themselves, but rather in our popular
                    uses of historical metaphor to explain them. Why, in particular, do we turn to
                    the rise of the printing press, out of all the options available, as our
                    standard analogy for the rise of the internet? What value does this metaphor
                    hold for us, what does it enable and what does it constrain, and what value does
                    metaphoric thinking in general hold for analysis in media studies? It is as
                    common for us today to use the printing press as a unit of measure in
                    estimations of information history as it is for us to discuss our current
                    circumstances in terms of an <term>information revolution.</term> But how
                    historically accurate are these kinds of description? What do they mean for the
                    ways in which we as futurists make use of history — and what do they mean for
                    the ways in which we as historians take the long view? </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Elyse Graham analyzes how the printing press is used as a metaphor for all sorts
                    of technological advancements, but should it be?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>These days, we are constantly looking for an image of ourselves in the historical
                    past. “The first ever information revolution,” begins a typical book jacket
                    blurb, “began with the advent of the printed book, enabling Renaissance scholars
                    to formulate new ways of organizing and disseminating knowledge” <ptr
                        target="#sawday2000"/>. A communications scholar offers a view of our place
                    in history that has echoes in countless other publications and presentations:
                    “At present we are witnessing an information revolution whose significance
                    parallels and perhaps even surpasses that of the information revolution caused
                    by the printing press in the fifteenth century” <ptr target="#jucker2003"/>.
                    Publishers, both academic and trade, have created a new genre of book titles
                    that confidently find the digital sizzle in the analog past: <title
                        rend="italic">The Renaissance Computer</title> (on printed books), <title
                        rend="italic">The Victorian Internet</title> (on the telegraph), <title
                        rend="italic">Social Media: The First 2,000 Years</title> (on letters,
                    pamphlets, and graffiti). Scholars give talks with titles like <title
                        rend="quotes">Books as Social Media</title> (Leah Price), <title
                        rend="quotes">Blogging Now and Then (250 Years Ago)</title> (Robert
                    Darnton), and <title rend="quotes">What’s in a Visitor’s Book? Social Media and
                        Volcanic Tourism in the Nineteenth Century</title> (John Brewer).</p>
                <p>There is no doubt that we feel ourselves to be in the midst of a period of
                    dramatic change in our media and information environments. My interest in this
                    essay, however, lies not in these environments themselves, but rather in our
                    popular uses of historical metaphor to explain them. Specifically, my interest
                    lies in the practical and theoretical functions that historical metaphor serves
                    in the intellectual marketplace. It is as common today for us to use the
                    printing press as the central unit of measure in estimations of information
                    history as it is for us to discuss our current circumstances in terms of an
                        <term>information revolution.</term> Surrounded as we are by these analogies
                    — by these claims in favor of specific ways of construing the relationship
                    between the past and the present, and by the significance claims that go with
                    them — it seems fair to ask what purposes they serve. Situating an examination
                    of this rhetoric within a larger discussion of the market forces that affect
                    rhetorical practice, I seek to delimit a context for the emergence of a
                    distinctive set of contemporary tropes. What do these kinds of historical
                    analogy mean for the ways in which we make use of history, and what do they mean
                    for the ways in which we as historians take the long view? Why, in particular,
                    do we turn to the rise of the printing press as our standard analogy for the
                    rise of the internet? What meanings does this metaphor constrain, what values
                    does it offer to overwhelm those constraints, and what value does metaphoric
                    thinking in general hold for analysis in media studies? </p>
                <p>As I will show, this rhetoric offers a powerful reminder of the extent to which
                    technological discourse — inside as well as outside the academy — is obliged to
                    respond to market imperatives. The tropes that join Zuckerberg with Gutenberg
                    sell; thus they feature in the titles, cover blurbs, journalistic ledes, and
                    other peripheral elements of texts that do not advance the arguments they imply.
                    Objections to the revolutionary myths of technological history — for example,
                    that digital practice has failed to supplant the paper world or that computers
                    possess no single or unified history — risk retreating from figure to ground
                    when these elements are in play. Indeed, this set of tropes participates in a
                    longer history of technological rhetoric that utilizes slippery language to
                    shape the story of technological change in a form with popular appeal, a
                    rhetoric that, as Leo Marx has noted, includes our uses of the word
                        <term>technology</term> itself.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Everything New Is Old Again</head>
                <p>The analogy that joins “our time” with that of Johann Gutenberg precedes the
                    internet age, reaching back at least to the works of Marshall McLuhan in the
                    1960s and 1970s (especially his 1962 blockbuster, <title rend="italic">The
                        Gutenberg Galaxy</title>) and Walter Ong in the 1980s. McLuhan and Ong
                    heralded an electronic age that seemed poised to return society, albeit somewhat
                    differently configured, to the forms of orality that predated the era of print.
                    For them, a medium was not only a vehicle of expression, but an almost
                    inevitable logic that could shape entire social constellations and forms of
                    being. For example, while the logics that govern print culture include fixity,
                    systematization, and multiplicity, oral culture — both in its <q>primary</q>
                    (pre-print) and <q>secondary</q> (post-print) configurations — operates by
                    logics of fluidity, instability, and collective composition <ptr
                        target="#kernan1987" loc="54"/>.</p>
                <p>In 2007, the Danish scholar Lars Ole Sauerberg gave new life to this view of
                    media history by introducing the concept of a <term>Gutenberg
                        Parenthesis,</term> a historical model that Thomas Pettitt has done much to
                    popularize <ptr target="#pettitt2007"/> This model frames the <term>culture of
                        print</term> that came in the wake of the printing press as a temporary
                    interlude rather than a permanent structural change: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cordongarcia2013">a mere parenthesis between
                            the oral world of almost all of history prior to the invention of the
                            printing press and the secondary orality that we are experiencing as
                            from the invention of the Internet</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cordongarcia2013"/>
                    </cit>. The Gutenberg Parenthesis model seeks to unseat print culture from the
                    throne of modernity and progress, suggesting instead that print culture, despite
                    its apparent triumph over history, is in fact a temporary anomaly, with the
                    prevailing order of human communication remaining on the side of speech and
                    immediacy <ptr target="#ong2005" loc="207"/>. </p>
                <p>For scholars working within a modern liberal framework, the appeal of this model
                    is multidimensional. For one, the figure of the Gutenberg Parenthesis represents
                    an effort to make media history less triumphalist. From the perspective of
                    cultural pluralism, a valuable function of this historical model is that it
                    presents the historical development of technology as an uneven pattern of
                    recursion, restoration, and repetition, and thus allows the subject of literacy
                    and orality to be pursued in the era of the internet without reducing it to an
                    argument about the civilized and the non-civilized. The printing press stands as
                    the pivotal point that represents the beginning of the Gutenberg Parenthesis,
                    just as the computer stands as the pivotal point that represents its end. </p>
                <p>A second function of the model is to naturalize and effectively modernize the art
                    of pre-modern eras, whether to make new authority claims as readers of old
                    literature or to claim for ourselves, living in a time of tweets, viral videos,
                    and other seemingly cheap and forgettable media forms, the power, grandeur, and
                    rootedness of Shakespeare. Pettitt portrays the Gutenberg Parenthesis as a
                    framework with which we can connect <quote rend="inline" source="#pettitt2007"
                        >postmodern ideologies regarding artistic originality and
                        appropriation</quote> with the ideologies that governed Elizabethan
                    aesthetic culture. By these lights, only the <emph>recent</emph> past is a
                    foreign country; Shakespeare is revealed to have been a sophisticated
                    practitioner of remix culture and a connoisseur of the database.<note> See, for
                        example, Peter Stallybrass, <title rend="quotes">Against Thinking,</title> in <hi rend="italic"
                            >PMLA</hi> 122 (2007), 1580-87.</note> Thus a better understanding of
                    our own culture prepares us to understand the attitudes and mores of the more
                    distant past <ptr target="#pettitt2007" loc="2"/>. Louise George Clubb, a
                    proponent of this view, writes: </p>
                <p><cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#clubb2010">In the context of this occasion and
                            the cultural climate it breathes, the playmaking system of the
                            Renaissance assumes a modernity — more precisely, a postmodernity —
                            through the similarity of the modes of creative production before and
                            after the parenthesis. Recognizing a <term>Gutenberg Parenthesis</term>
                            makes it easier to recognize a theater technology that overlapped with
                            the print culture of the era Marshall McLuhan called the <term>Gutenberg
                                Galaxy,</term> which fifty years ago was not yet established in the
                            critical vocabulary as a perception of a major paradigm shift, much less
                            of a passing phase. Shakespeare straddled the threshold, entering the
                            parenthesis simultaneously with the actors of the commedia, whose
                            literary progenitors were already in it, at least insofar as their plays
                            were written in the hope of printing… unstable cobbled pre-parenthetical
                            theater that were excised when the texts were editorially stabilized for
                            the press.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#clubb2010" loc="17"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>Finally, the figure of the Gutenberg Parenthesis provides a model that allows
                    scholars to theorize about media history in terms of stasis and disruption. For
                    example, Jill Walker Rettberg, in an article that refers back to Pettitt, claims
                    that a look backward from the rise of print and print literacy can show us the
                    same primordial soup that produced digital social media. We should celebrate,
                    she says, that we have left the stiff and formal interim <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#rettberg2007">dominated by print and its
                            attendant norms such as the idea that you can have an autonomous, fixed
                            text, or the idea that a text or cultural object is originally composed
                            once, and thereafter passively reproduced by readers, musicians or
                            performers</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rettberg2007" loc="8"/>
                    </cit>. Recently, Pettitt has even proposed the historical existence of a
                        <term>Privacy Parenthesis</term>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pettitt2013">a great pause between the
                            semipublic life of the villager and the semipublic life of the netizen,
                            during which culturally contingent values such as privacy and
                            exclusivity came to seem like natural social rights</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pettitt2013"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>However, it is revealing that nearly all of these efforts to find the future in
                    the past focus far less on understanding the past than on understanding the
                    future. The use of popular terms like <term>social media</term> when discussing
                    18th- and 19th-century visitors’ albums and commonplace books promises that we
                    can identify the seeds of the future in the present by discovering our
                    doppelgängers on the other side of a brief swerve in history. In both academic
                    literature and the trade press, it has been a popular argument in recent years
                    that the apparent endings we are witnessing in our own time — the end of
                    privacy, the end of mass media, the end of the book — represent simply a return
                    to the past, to a historical norm of greater stability and longer duration. The
                    end of the printed book means the close of a Gutenberg parenthesis between
                    manuscript networks and e-mail networks; the end of privacy is the close of a
                    privacy parenthesis between the intrusiveness of the village well and the casual
                    intrusiveness of Facebook stalking; the end of mass media is simply the end of a
                    brief interlude in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, supported by the
                    economics of advanced industrial society, in which gathering and disseminating
                    high-quality news was an easier and cheaper task for huge enterprises than for
                    lay citizens <ptr target="#pettitt2013"/>. Yet past and present have never
                    joined up quite so easily. This approach to modeling history, although there is
                    something admirable in its presentation of an alternative to the literature of
                    elegy and nostalgia that has accompanied the <q>rise</q> of the digital age,
                    itself succumbs to a false nostalgia, and a false parallelism, in the suggestion
                    that a return to the past can heal a division that would otherwise be a wound.
                    Any return to ways of being that can be identified as <q>past</q> must be a
                    return with a substantial difference. Surely a lack of privacy in the village or
                    the clan, when intimacy was intimacy with several hundred people, was a
                    significantly different experience from a lack of privacy in a networked world
                    of 7.4 billion people.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Technology and Teleology</head>
                <p>Sauerberg, Pettitt et al. do not hide the fact that their claims rely on
                    associating specific periods of media technology with an intrinsic logic and
                    trajectory. Part of my argument is that this association often implicitly
                    attends more casual uses of the printing press metaphor, even when it is not
                    explicitly stated. For this reason, I would like to pause briefly to discuss the
                    recent history of this idea in media studies. Historians now tend to shy from
                    the idea that technology is an entity capable of acting under an autonomous and
                    self-derived logic.<note> Of course, it remains a prevailing historical model
                        for writers of popular nonfiction on technology and media.</note> Raymond
                    Williams, Adrian Johns, Michael Warner, and others have presented alternatives
                    to views of media change in terms of internal logic or seismic rupture. These
                    scholars argue that media change is gradual, iterative, and occurs in reciprocal
                    exchange with change in other aspects of society. </p>
                <p>Williams most famously articulates this view in his 1975 book, <title
                        rend="italic">Television: Technology as a Cultural Form</title>, which
                    argues that in the early years of any new medium — television included — that
                    medium can move in any number of directions; in time, it settles down in a
                    single direction, which then comes to seem natural and inevitable. Early
                    witnesses of the rise of television failed to perceive many of the directions it
                    might have taken, including a superior visual picture, in part because its
                    definition as a <emph>mass communication</emph> medium obscured them. In the
                    meanwhile, users of domestic television sets settled for an inferior standard of
                    visual quality because of the social system that surrounded television
                    broadcasting. Williams writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#williams1977">[T]here were, in the abstract,
                            several different ways in which television as a technical means might
                            have been developed... After a generation of universal domestic
                            television it is not easy to realize this. But it remains true that,
                            after a great deal of intensive research and development, the domestic
                            television set is in a number of ways an inefficient medium of visual
                            broadcasting</quote>
                        <ptr target="#williams1977" loc="28"/>
                    </cit>. Or, to borrow a phrase from evolutionary biology: not all traits are
                    adaptations. </p>
                <p>Johns turns a perspective informed, in part, by Williams to an analysis of the
                    medium of print during its initial spread through European culture. Against the
                    more deterministic claims of McLuhan, Eisenstein, and Kernan, among others —
                    that the print medium enforced on the world of letters new logics of fixity,
                    systematization, and the organization of information, in the process setting in
                    motion the social and intellectual revolutions of the early modern period — he
                    shows that it was necessary for human agents in the world of letters to enforce
                    those qualities on printed texts <ptr target="#johns2009"/>. The emergence of
                        <emph>stable,</emph>
                    <emph>reliable</emph> editions of printed texts represented not fulfillments of
                    an inherent print <emph>logic,</emph> but rather the struggle of various
                    literary and scientific communities to tame the messy and unstable world of
                    print. Warner, meanwhile, works from the position that terms such as
                        <emph>new</emph> media and <emph>obsolete</emph> technology act rather in
                    the way the misleading term <term>mass communication</term> did (if Williams is
                    right) in the early years of television, obscuring a more plural and pregnant
                    reality. For Warner, this includes the reality that differing media systems
                    always coexist, few ever becoming in a real sense obsolete, and all of them
                    constantly renewing themselves in response to one another <ptr
                        target="#warner1990"/>.</p>
                <p>But the <emph>uses</emph> of tropes are a different matter from their accuracy.
                    In practice, the uses of these analogies draw upon their ability to tacitly
                    present technology as an autonomous force that operates according to its own
                    logic and in dramatic leaps. That media change occurs in seismic shifts, or that
                    it occurs due to the autonomous <q>logic</q> of new technologies, are not widely
                    held ideas in media studies, but nonetheless they form the core of some of the
                    most widely used <emph>narratives</emph> in media studies. In this view, the
                    printing press is a ubiquitous analogy for the computer in part because it
                    readily summons narratives of seismic innovation. Even the language of
                        <q>obsolete</q> technology and <q>new</q> media reaffirms these buried
                    metaphors on a smaller scale. As I will discuss, the popularity of these
                    metaphors may best be attributed to marketplace pressures in Silicon Valley and
                    the academic marketplace of ideas. While we normally imagine debate in terms of
                    challengers vying for dominance in the marketplace, there are times when the
                    presence of a marketplace itself acts as a dominating force, and this is true,
                    albeit in different ways, in industry and the university alike.</p>
                <p>This pattern places the printing press metaphor in a lineage of technological
                    rhetoric that includes the terms information and even <emph>technology</emph>
                    itself. The philosopher Leo Marx has argued that over the course of the
                    twentieth century, the term “technology” became a misleading and philosophically
                        <q>hazardous</q> concept, used largely as a placeholder to fill a void
                    between the artifacts we create and the kinds of social change we want to
                    discuss. As I discuss below, the role — one of the roles — that the printing
                    press metaphor serves in the discourse of technological change resembles the
                    role that Marx has identified for the concept of <term>technology</term>. The
                    effort to find the key term or analogy to label our own time belongs to a
                    predictive impulse: an assumption, often buried but still forceful, that
                    technological culture develops according to an autonomous force and essence, and
                    that by identifying this essence we can gain a privileged vantage point onto the
                    future. </p>
                <p>In our general uses of it, the printing press as a symbol of technological change
                    likewise tends to imply that historical change is revolutionary and progressive.
                    Marx connects projections of this kind with the uses we make of the term
                        <term>technology.</term> The term is particularly dangerous, Marx says, when
                    we use it in ways that attribute to <term>technology</term> autonomy and agency,
                    as in <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#marx1997">Technology is changing the way we
                            live</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marx1997" loc="968–97"/>
                    </cit>. The word in its current sense is in fact a recent coinage. Up through
                    the late nineteenth century, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#marx1997">the word <term>technology</term>
                            primarily referred to a kind of book; except for a few lexical pioneers,
                            it was not until the turn of this century that sophisticated writers
                            like Thorstein Veblen began to use the word to mean the mechanic arts
                            collectively. But that sense of the word did not gain wide currency
                            until after World War I</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marx1997" loc="24–25"/>
                    </cit>. <note> The OED records early uses of the term <term>technology</term> to
                        refer to <q>a discourse or treatise on an art or arts.</q> In 1615, for
                        example, Sir George Buck’s <title rend="italic">Third University of
                            England</title>, a <q>report of the sciences, arts, and faculties</q> in
                        the city of London, speaks of <q>an apt close of this general
                            Technologie.</q> In 1706, <title rend="italic">Phillip’s New World of
                            Words</title> defines <term>technology</term> as <q>a Description of
                            Arts, especially the Mechanical.</q> As late as 1860, the magazine
                            <title rend="italic">Vanity Fair</title>, waggishly proposing a new
                            <q>Dictionary for Congressmen,</q> was able to include
                            <term>technologies</term> in the flood of dictionaries that
                        characterized the age: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#oed">We have Classical Dictionaries,
                                Dictionaries of Science, Dictionaries of Art, Rhyming Dictionaries,
                                — by which those who are not born Poets may achieve Poetry, or,
                                rather, have Poetry thrust upon them, — Cyclopædias and Technologies
                                without Number.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#oed"/>
                        </cit></note>
                </p>
                <p>Rather in the way that, according to Williams, the pressures of technological
                    innovation respond to prevailing ideologies and new social needs, the word
                        <term>technology</term> rose to dominance in our discourse by adapting to
                    the needs of the moment. It better served an emerging system of belief about
                    history and progress than prior terms for the same general concept, such as
                        <term>the mechanic arts, the practical arts</term>, and <term>the industrial
                        arts</term>. This system of belief included, first, the joining of an
                    earlier Enlightenment belief in historical progress (i.e. a view of history as a
                    force moving toward more advanced and enlightened stages of civilization) with a
                    newer belief that scientific and mechanical innovation were responsible for,
                    indeed constituted, this movement. The Enlightenment conception of history, as
                    Kant articulated it, assumed, first, that history has a forward impulse and a
                    destination, and second, that this destination consists of political progress,
                    which improvements in the mechanical arts might help (but only help) to bring
                    about. In the early nineteenth century, people began to speak as though
                    improvements in the mechanic arts were themselves the goal toward which history
                    moves, and thus constitute what people continued to call
                        <soCalled>progress</soCalled>. This conceptual shift entailed a new
                    treatment of history as the story of man’s intellectual conquest of nature.
                    Together, Marx argues, these ideological changes <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#marx2000">created a semantic void, that is, a
                            set of social circumstances for which no adequate concept was yet
                            available — a void that the new concept, <term>technology</term>,
                            eventually would fill</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marx2000" loc="25–8"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>A factor that sharpened the urgency of this <q>conceptual void</q> was the
                    specific form that the most visible improvements in the mechanic arts took
                    during the Industrial Revolution. The railway, the electric telegraph, and other
                    defining features of industrial life entailed massive and rhizomic social,
                    bureaucratic, and mechanical systems, difficult to separate and each a complex
                    entity in its own right. The railway alone required, besides the engine itself: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#marx2000"> (1) various kinds of ancillary
                            equipment (rolling stock, stations, yards, bridges, tunnels, viaducts,
                            signal systems, and a huge network of tracks); (2) a corporate business
                            organization with a large capital investment; (3) specialized forms of
                            technical knowledge (railroad engineering, telegraphy); (4) a specially
                            trained work force with unique railroading skills, including civil and
                            locomotive engineers, firemen, telegraphers, brakemen, conductors — a
                            work force large and resourceful enough to keep the system going day and
                            night, in all kinds of weather, 365 days a year; and (5) various
                            facilitating institutional charges, such as laws establishing
                            standardized track gauges and a national system of standardized time
                            zones.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marx2000" loc="30–31"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>The shrinking (in systems like the railway) of the <term>pivotal artifactual
                        component</term> in relation to the whole sharpened the need for a term that
                    could refer to a complex system while seeming to refer to a specific instrument.
                    Further, in keeping with the conceptual shift toward a sense that industrial
                    change is a goal in its own right, this semantic need entailed a meaning that
                    would encompass not only an instrument in the service of progress, but also the
                    fact of progress itself <ptr target="#marx2000" loc="36"/>. The term
                        <term>technology</term> emerged to fill that need. Thus we can say today
                    that automotive technology (for example) permeates the world in the form of
                    cars, trucks, roads and highway infrastructure, the shipping and delivery
                    industries, industries for materials such as steel and glass, through to the
                    abstract benefits of living in an automotive society. Computer technology is
                    likewise omnipresent, from tablets, phones, and PCs through to children’s toys,
                    washing machines, sewage systems, power plants, and, of course, automotive
                    technology <ptr target="#marx2000" loc="38"/>. The value of the term
                        <term>technology</term> lies in its very ambiguity. As Marx writes elsewhere
                    in reference to the concept of <term>the machine</term>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#marx2000">The whole issue becomes irrelevant
                            once we recognize that we are dealing with a metaphor, and that its
                            immense appeal rests, not on its capacity to describe the actual
                            character of industrialization, but rather on its vivid suggestiveness.
                            It evokes the uniqueness of a new way of life, as experienced, and, most
                            important, it is a vivid expression of the affinity between technology
                            and the great political revolution of modern times.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marx2000" loc="187n"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Like the railway engine — or the computer chip — the printing press is a small
                    material artifact that readily elides into a much larger social, organizational,
                    and mechanical system, the scope of which is vast and indeterminate. The view of
                    the effects of the printing press that Walter Ong promoted (that the transition
                    from <term>oral culture</term> to <term>literate culture,</term> along with the
                    changes this implies in terms of education, cultural production, trade, and so
                    forth, was immediate and thoroughgoing) and the opposing position that
                    eventually succeeded him (that these changes were slow and gradual) both
                    participate in the post-industrial rhetoric that elides a single artifact with
                    an unknowably large system. In short, the metaphor of the printing press serves
                    in our discourse much the same role that Marx has identified for the concept of
                        <term>technology.</term> The trope is useful precisely because our
                    understanding of its boundaries is so nebulous that we can apply the trope
                    without having to commit to any specific point of reference. </p>
                <p>Indeed, building on Marx’s lead, Paul Duguid has recently argued that
                        <term>information</term> is a term that takes on a problematic anachronism
                    when we use it in reference to periods before the quite recent past. In a
                    lecture at Harvard in 2014, he stressed the changes in meaning that the term has
                    undergone throughout the history of its usage. Until the mid-nineteenth century,
                    the word <term>information</term> was a transferred use of the verb <emph>to
                        inform</emph>, rather in the way that <emph>delineation</emph> is a
                    transferred use of the verb <emph>to delineate</emph>. For much of the twentieth
                    century, the term vacillated between vague meanings in popular usage and quite
                    different specific meanings in specialist terminology. <note> Claude Shannon,
                        the father of information theory, separated <term>information</term> from
                            <term>meaning</term>, a distinction that runs counter to common
                        usage.</note> Duguid argues that we have come more recently to use the word
                        <term>information</term> as a placeholder, a catchall term for phenomena we
                    do not know how to identify or describe <ptr target="#duguid2014"/>. </p>
                <p>In short, when we use the printing press as a metaphor for changes in our
                    information culture, we succumb to anachronism twice. First, this metaphorical
                    use relies on a now-belated concept, dating to the aftermath of the Industrial
                    Revolution, of a single artifact that can represent a wider matrix of political,
                    social, cultural, and institutional effects while diffusing specific claims
                    about what those effects might be. Our understanding of the effects of the
                    printing press is so multifarious that we can, and generally do, apply the
                    figure as a placeholder for the unknown. By comparing changes in our information
                    culture to changes that the printing press <q>created</q> in an earlier
                    information culture, we open our claim to include a wide range of possible
                    meanings, but in the process we drain the comparison of specific value. Second,
                    and more importantly, by unreflectively using the printing press as a metaphor
                    for changes in an information culture, we elide long-term shifts in ideology and
                    material practice that may represent the most important forms of difference
                    among various media systems. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Public Stories and Private Strategies</head>
                <p>Another context that illuminates the marketplace value of the printing press
                    metaphor is that of Silicon Valley. The distinctive incentive structures of
                    Silicon Valley — start-up culture, venture capital financing, payment in stock
                    options, IPOs — are geared toward the rhetoric of revolutionary change. For a
                    company seeking investors to claim that the near future will be radically
                    changed from the present, and that this change will be predicated on the
                    autonomous force of changing technologies, implies that the future is manageable
                    and claims ownership of that terrain. It recommends investors to the company and
                    consumers to its products. To claim that technological change is gradual,
                    iterative, unpredictable, and never fully complete, and that the future of
                    technology will depend at least as much on social and cultural factors as on
                    machinery viewed in isolation, would obviously be a weaker sell <ptr
                        target="#hyde2003"/>. <note> On start-up culture, see also <ptr
                            target="#saxenian1994"/>, <ptr target="#lee2000"/>, <ptr
                            target="#smith1988"/>, and <ptr target="#hiltzik1999"/>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Yet industry practice can differ dramatically from the public narratives that
                    technology companies present. The books on business strategy and innovation that
                    have enjoyed the most success and influence within the technology sector often
                    present, by contrast with public narratives of revolution and upheaval, a
                    granular and iterative narrative of technological change. For example, Clayton
                    Christensen’s theory of disruptive innovation, most famously articulated in a
                    best-selling 1997 book, <title rend="italic">The Innovator’s Dilemma</title>,
                    proposes that technological change in the marketplace often occurs as
                    lower-cost, lower-quality technologies gradually eat up the market share of
                    higher-quality technologies <ptr target="#christensen1997"/>. Not only is
                    Christensen’s book (and his follow-up books on the same subject) an enduring
                    best-seller in industry, but also corporations such as Apple implement business
                    strategies that put into practice the view of technological change he advocates;
                    for example, creating smaller, semi-independent companies that are meant to
                    gradually <q>disrupt</q> Apple’s current products, at which point they will be
                    absorbed back into the Apple mothership <ptr target="#mcfarquhar2012"/>. </p>
                <p>In a 2003 article in the <title rend="italic">Harvard Business Review</title>,
                    Nicholas Carr directed attention toward the relationship between the incentive
                    structures of the digital economy and the ways in which commentators embedded in
                    those structures frame and direct historical comparison. These comparisons, he
                    argues, tend to emphasize moments of revolutionary change, a structure that
                    coheres with the hype-driven framework of venture capital financing: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2003">Many commentators have drawn
                            parallels between the expansion of IT, particularly the Internet, and
                            the rollouts of earlier technologies. Most of the comparisons, though,
                            have focused on either the investment pattern associated with the
                            technologies — the boom-to-bust cycle — or the technologies’ roles in
                            reshaping the operations of entire industries or even economies. Little
                            has been said about the way the technologies influence, or fail to
                            influence, competition at the firm level</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carr2003"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>At stake in this form of historical comparison is an understanding of the actual
                    role of computers in the contemporary business world, a role that Carr describes
                    as distinctly non-revolutionary. Carr argues that once a new technology moves
                    past the relatively short phase of being a <term>proprietary</term> technology —
                    the phase during which only one or a few companies can benefit from the use of
                    that technology — it becomes an <term>infrastructural</term>technology, which
                    everyone uses and which therefore confers no comparative advantage. Technology
                    firms that rely on venture-capital funding and the sale of stock options
                    therefore have a substantial incentive to behave as though they are perpetually
                    in the proprietary cycle. Their rhetoric reflects this fact. But such rhetoric
                    is highly misleading, he argues; most computing technologies become
                    infrastructural technologies in a relatively short time <ptr target="#carr2003"
                    />.</p>
                <p>Another context is commercial publishing, the world’s most ferocious attention
                    economy. Incentive structures in publishing, too, promote the production of
                    rhetoric that frames computing technology in terms of revolutionary change. In
                    the trade press, which is, after all, self-consciously a consumer market, this
                    relationship is less troubled; books on technology abound whose titles include
                    the word <term>revolution</term> or suggest its tenor. Examples include <title
                        rend="italic">The Soft Edge: A Natural History and Future of the Information
                        Revolution</title>, <title rend="italic">Groundswell: Winning in a World
                        Transformed by Social Technologies</title>, and <title rend="italic">Smarter
                        than Us: The Rise of Machine Intelligence</title>
                    <ptr target="#levinson1997"/>, <ptr target="#li2011"/>, <ptr
                        target="#armstrong2014"/>. Academic publishing, too, seems to manifest a
                    perception that the market rewards depictions of media change as revolutionary
                    and technology-driven, although this perception is in tension with prevailing
                    academic theories of media change. Consider, for example, the stream of recent
                    books on computing whose titles turn on the famous name of Gutenberg, such as:
                        <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to the Global Information
                        Infrastructure</title> (2000), <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to
                        Google</title> (2006), and <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to
                        Zuckerberg</title> (2011) <ptr target="#borgman2000"/>, <ptr
                        target="#shillinsburg2006"/>, <ptr target="#naughton2011"/>. Some of these
                    books argue that Gutenberg effectively restarted the calendar, initiating an
                    epoch governed by a distinctive logic. Others do not, but for the sake of the
                    market they still take advantage of the famous name. </p>
                <p>That this phenomenon is most pronounced in the aspects of published works that
                    are directly associated with the marketplace, such as titles, blurbs, and other
                    framing devices, shows that these pressures affect the tactics even of authors
                    who reject a seismic view of technological change. For example, in a widely
                    praised media studies book of recent years, Asa Briggs and Peter Burke, <title
                        rend="italic">Social History of the Media: From Gutenberg to the Internet
                    </title>(2010), the authors take care to emphasize that the social history of
                    media does not actually begin with Gutenberg, and that media change is a diffuse
                    and nonlinear process: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#briggs2010">This book concentrates on the
                            modern west, from the late fifteenth century onwards. The narrative
                            begins with printing (c. AD 1450) rather than with the alphabet (c. 2000
                            BC), with writing (c. 5000 BC), or with speech, but despite the
                            importance often attributed to Johann Gutenberg (c. 1400-68), whom
                            readers of one British newspaper voted “man of the millennium” (Sunday
                            Times, 28 November 1999), there is no clean break or zero point at which
                            the story begins, and it will sometimes be necessary to refer briefly
                            back to the ancient and medieval worlds.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#briggs2010" loc="5"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Yet the most visible parts of the book telescope our attention to those zero
                    points of the press and the internet: not only the title, but also the image on
                    the cover, which places together, in a pas-de-deux, the letter <q>i</q> (a
                    common symbol of internet culture) and a printing press. This sort of motif is
                    common. The cover illustration of <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to
                        Zuckerberg</title> is a printing press that is visibly emitting a wi-fi
                    signal. </p>
                <p>Trade books, which sell solutions as much as they do analysis, may have a special
                    incentive to claim that changes in media technologies create changes in human
                    consciousness. Nicholas Carr’s bestseller <title rend="italic">The
                        Shallows</title> (2010) opens with the claim that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#carr2010">For the last five centuries, ever
                            since Gutenberg’s printing press made book reading a popular pursuit,
                            the linear, literary mind has been at the center of art, science, and
                            society</quote>
                        <ptr target="#carr2010"/>
                    </cit>. But although critics such as Briggs and Burke have moved away from
                    models like Carr’s, which echoes McLuhan and Ong in its longing look back at a
                    vanishing or vanished mentality, the framing elements in their works often
                    tacitly endorse these models. In this sense, the marketplace exerts a strong
                    enough force that scholars can find themselves making implicit claims in favor
                    of views of media culture and media change that they question or even explicitly
                    oppose. These claims serve functions that are valuable enough in the attention
                    economy of ideas that we may find ourselves deploying them, however unwillingly,
                    against our own arguments. </p>
                <p>Indeed, framing the computer narrowly as a communications instrument makes it
                    more available to academic discourse considered as a marketplace. It is
                    reasonable to acknowledge that communication has played a large role in the
                    history of computing; digital computers rely on symbol processing, for example,
                    and the most high-profile operations of modern computers involve
                        communication.<note> Bill Pascoe, email to the Humanist Mailing List, 27 May
                        2016. Bill Pascoe uses the phrase “symbol processing” in the email I cite
                        for this sentence, in which he says: “When it boils down to it, a computer
                        is a language tool. It's invention and core functionality is symbol
                        processing, and its higher order functioning is also largely about
                        communicating, representation, etc.”</note> Yet it is also reasonable to
                    acknowledge that the history of computers includes many genealogies besides the
                    one that runs through the history of communication.<note> See, for example,
                        Michael Sean Mahoney, <title rend="italic">Histories of Computing</title>
                        (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2011).</note> From the perspective of
                    humanities discourse, the most obvious benefit of framing the computer as a
                    communications instrument <emph>to the exclusion of all else</emph> is that it
                    translates all that computers produce into communication. If everything is
                    discourse, then everything can be analyzed discursively. In critical discourse,
                    the printing press metaphor enables us to evoke a sense of forward movement and
                    developmental logic that enhances the significance and narrative coherence of
                    the histories we tell. We can also see elements of such an agenda in the buried
                    metaphors that pervade narratives of media and literary history, such as the
                        <emph>rise</emph> of print and the <emph>rise</emph> of the book. In short,
                    although neither the academy nor Silicon Valley think of the computer as only a
                    communications instrument, both recognize benefits in linking computers to a
                    communications-based genealogy. Even when they acknowledge the diversity of the
                    forms and functions of computing technology, media theorists often find
                    themselves obliged to narrow those functions for the sake of a narrative they
                    can claim as their own. </p>
                <p>A famous and effective theorist of this form of self-contradiction is Pierre
                    Bourdieu. I invoke him in this essay simply to indicate that the problem is not
                    new, even if it is distinctively of our own time. He describes its operations in
                    several places, but especially in the essay <title rend="italic">“Flaubert and
                        the French Literary Field,</title> where he classifies cultural producers
                    and intellectuals under the description <emph>dominated dominants</emph>
                    <ptr target="#bourdieu1993b" loc="145–211"/>. As producers of ideology, these
                    figures hold positions of dominance within a culture’s general field of power;
                    but they are themselves dominated by the need for their ideas to succeed within
                    a marketplace, and in that sense they resemble, if perhaps are not one with, the
                    dominated <ptr target="#bourdieu1993a" loc="172"/>. Bourdieu writes of the
                    conditions that produce these figures: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#bourdieu1993a">[T]he literary and artistic
                            field is contained within the field of power, while possessing a
                            relative autonomy with respect to it, especially as regards its economic
                            and political principles of hierarchization. It occupies a
                                <emph>dominated position</emph> (at the negative pole) in this
                            field, which is itself situated at the dominant pole of the field of
                            class relations. It is thus the site of a double hierarchy: the
                                <emph>heteronomous</emph> principle of hierarchization, which would
                            reign unchallenged if, losing all autonomy, the literary and artistic
                            field were to disappear as such (so that writers and artists became
                            subject to the ordinary laws prevailing in the field of power, and more
                            generally in the economic field), is <emph>success</emph>, as measured
                            by indices such as book sales, number of theatrical performances, etc.,
                            or honors, appointments, etc.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bourdieu1993a" loc="37–38"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>In Bourdieu’s analysis, in a capitalist society, those who hold economic capital
                    enjoy positions of dominance in the field of power, while those who hold
                    cultural capital find themselves in an ambiguous position of gilded
                    subordination: they help to articulate the values and ideas of their time, and
                    they often find themselves under pressure to legitimate existing power
                    structures, but they can also criticize those structures and disseminate
                    subversive views. The scholars and critics who discuss technology in the
                    marketplace of ideas, as well as the tech companies that seek to stand out in
                    the crowded attention economy of Silicon Valley, represent distinctively
                    twenty-first century versions of this concept. While in theory and indeed in
                    practice they subscribe to the idea that technological change is gradual and
                    iterative, they regularly invoke the spirit of revolutionary technology because
                    it attracts attention and creates valuable claims for the authority and
                    significance of their work. Although they hold a dominant position in the
                    culture, they are dominated by the marketplace, which is the true form of
                    power.</p>
                <p>By way of a coda, I would like to draw attention to some of the implications of
                    this line of discussion for our understanding of the literary ecosystem
                    surrounding the young discipline of the digital humanities. Proponents of this
                    discipline, such as Lev Manovich, have occasionally drawn criticism for making
                    excessively revolutionary claims about the applications of computing technology
                    in humanistic studies. Such criticism ignores the fact that this kind of
                    rhetoric is consciously designed to operate within an attention economy that
                    rewards revolutionary claims about technology; that it represents, in part, the
                    most practical of objectives: to obtain support and set provisional boundaries
                    for the discipline. As a consequence, critics cannot properly engage with the
                    claims that it marshals unless they take these objectives into account. We
                    should be able to acknowledge that this kind of rhetoric is, to a certain
                    degree, strategizing, given that we are implicated in this kind of strategizing
                    ourselves. Otherwise we all risk talking past one another. In other words, what
                    is at stake in the effort to properly classify the role of revolutionary
                    rhetoric in digital humanities literature is the ability for the discipline’s
                    proponents and critics to meet on a common ground of understanding — which in
                    this case requires us to acknowledge openly the normally implicit and
                    unacknowledged fact that academic discourse is shaped by its presence in a
                    marketplace.</p>
                <p>Have digital technologies changed much of the surface character of our practice?
                    Reasonable people can disagree. Robert Gordon makes the similarity of our online
                    activities to our offline activities a key component of his proposed solution to
                    the Solow computer paradox, which observes that the omnipresence of computers
                    does not appear to have driven up productivity <ptr target="#gordon2004"/>. Yet
                    even if digital practice to a large extent recapitulates what we were doing
                    before, this is not a persuasive reason for us to ignore the fact that our
                    practice is digital. In recent years, articles in publications ranging from
                        <title rend="italic">The Los Angeles Review of Books</title> to <title
                        rend="italic">The New York Times</title> have taken issue with the digital
                    humanities as a discipline on the grounds that computers are less <title
                        rend="italic">revolutionary</title> than we pretend they are. Writing for
                    the <title rend="italic">New Republic</title>, Adam Kirsch asks why we cannot
                    simply proceed as before with the new tools: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kirsch2014">Was it necessary for a humanist in
                            the past five hundred years to know how to set type and publish a book?
                            Moreover, is it practical for a humanities curriculum that can already
                            stretch for ten years or more, from freshman year to Ph.D., to be
                            expanded to include programming skills?</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kirsch2014"/>
                    </cit>. Of course, one objection to this kind of comment is simply that
                    scholarship focused on digital practice represents a natural extension of
                    previous critical approaches in the humanities. Since the 1980s, for example,
                    Anglo-American textual scholarship has placed great emphasis on the fact that
                    authors once worked within a literary system that entailed setting type and
                    publishing books; naturally these scholars, and the scholars they train, would
                    take interest in programming and markup. But Kirsch’s question can be addressed.
                    While we may be doing much of the same humanistic work online — curating
                    exhibitions, creating films, staging performances, writing and publishing books,
                    teaching courses — that does not mean that the work of humanism will go on
                    unaffected by digital technologies.</p>
                <p>Some percentage of undergraduates who choose to major in the humanities — I would
                    guess a large percentage — do so in the hope of working in a humanities field
                    later on, and further a humanities field outside the academy. Many think,
                        <soCalled>This is my kind of field. I think I’ll go into publishing,
                        editing, something in the book business, and become a person of
                        letters.</soCalled> But the book business is not what it was even ten years
                    ago. For example, these days, it is common to see internship and job openings at
                    news organs, some of them old and staid, some of them as new as tomorrow’s viral
                    video — the <title rend="italic">Harvard Business Review</title>, the <title
                        rend="italic">Boston Globe</title>, New York University’s <title
                        rend="italic">GovLab</title>, Buzzfeed — that ask for students who know how
                    to clean, scrape, and otherwise work with data. They sometimes make explicit
                    that they will take someone who can work with data and teach them to write
                    stories in preference to taking someone who knows how to write stories and
                    teaching them to work with data. In a recent job announcement, Buzzfeed asked
                    that candidates, <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">Have a track record of using
                        data to find, tell, and reinforce powerful stories. Qualifying work isn’t
                        limited to journalism; it could include investigations within academia, law
                        enforcement, business, government, and other non-newsroom
                        environments.</quote> In short, it seems increasingly clear that the future
                    of letters, including the future of the roles that various agents play out in
                    the world of letters, requires skill sets that belong to the digital world. If
                    the promises that we make in humanities courses include, implicitly, that the
                    students will eventually be able to work in humanities fields, then these
                    promises should be fulfilled by a humanities education. </p>
                <p>This is just one reason to study the traditional humanities alongside new
                    technologies that has nothing to do with whether computers are revolutionary.
                    Making our praise for the discipline hinge on claims of revolutionary change has
                    its uses, as I have tried to show, but this practical utility may have lost its
                    force, since it has begun to make us vulnerable to critics like Kirsch. We do
                    not need to find the analogy that will enable us to perfectly identify the
                    computer age; in the end, we are simply living in it. The printing press and its
                    direct descendants might fade from use, but the humanities will not disappear
                    until we have done with metaphor.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="armstrong2014" label="Armstrong 2014">Armstrong, Stuart. <title
                        rend="italic">Smarter Than Us: The Rise of Machine Intelligence.</title>
                    Machine Intelligence Research Institute, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="briggs2010" label="Briggs and Burke 2010">Briggs, Asa and Peter Burke.
                        <title rend="italic">Social History of the Media: From Gutenberg to the
                        Internet.</title> Polity, 2010, 5.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman2000" label="Borgman 2000">Borgman, Christine, <title
                        rend="italic">From Gutenberg to the Global Information
                        Infrastructure.</title> Cambridge: MIT Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bourdieu1993a" label="Bourdieu 1993a">Bourdieu, Pierre. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Field of Cultural Production and the Field of
                        Power,</title> in <title rend="italic">The Field of Cultural Production:
                        Essays on Art and Literature</title>, trans. Randal Johnson, New York:
                    Columbia University Press, 1993, 172. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bourdieu1993b" label="Bourdieu 1993b">Bourdieu, Pierre. <title
                        rend="quotes">Flaubert and the French Literary Field,</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">The Field of Cultural Production: Essays on Art and
                        Literature</title>, trans. Randal Johnson, New York: Columbia University
                    Press, 1993, 145-211. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carr2003" label="Carr 2003">Carr, Nicholas. <title rend="quotes">IT
                        Doesn’t Matter,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Harvard Business Review</title> (May 2003), pp. 3-10: <ref
                        target="http://hbr.org/2003/05/it-doesnt-matter/ar/1"
                        >http://hbr.org/2003/05/it-doesnt-matter/ar/1</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carr2010" label="Carr 2010">Carr, Nicholas. <title rend="italic">The
                        Shallows: What the Internet Is Doing to Our Brains</title> New York: W.W.
                    Norton &amp; Company, 2010, 10.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clubb2010" label="Clubb 2010">Clubb, Louise George. <title
                        rend="quotes">Looking Back on Shakespeare and Italian Theater,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Renaissance Drama</title> 36, 37: Italy in the Drama of
                    Europe, ed. Albert Russell Ascoli and William I. West (2010): 17.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="christensen1997" label="Christensen 1997">Christensen, Clayton. <title
                        rend="italic"> The Innovator’s Dilemma: When New Technologies Cause Great
                        Firms to Fail.</title> Cambridge: Harvard Business Review Press, 1997. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cordongarcia2013" label="Cordon-Garcia et al., 2013"><title
                        rend="quotes">Towards a New Conception of Books and Reading: The Gutenberg
                        Parenthesis,</title> in Jose-Antonio Cordon-Garcia, Julio Alonso-Arevalo,
                    Raquel Gomez-Diaz, and Daniel Linder, <title rend="italic">Social Reading:
                        Platforms, Applications, Clouds, and Tags.</title> Chandos Publishing, 2013,
                    25-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crary1992" label="Crary 1992">Crary, Jonathan. <title rend="italic"
                        >Techniques of the Observer: On Vision and Modernity in the Nineteenth
                        Century.</title> Cambridge: MIT Press, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cressy1980" label="Cressy 1980">Cressy, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >Literacy and the Social Order: Reading and Writing in Tudor and Stuart
                        England</title> Cambridge, 1980.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daston2007" label="Daston and Galison 2007">Daston, Lorraine and Peter
                    Galison. <title rend="italic">Objectivity.</title> New York: Zone Books,
                    2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duguid2014" label="Duguid 2014">Duguid, Paul. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Getting Information from Books: A View of the 18th Century.</title> Lecture
                    at Harvard University, 4 February 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gordon2004" label="Gordon 2004">Gordon, Robert. <title rend="italic"
                        >Productivity Growth, Inflation, and Unemployment: The Collected Essays of
                        Robert J. Gordon.</title> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press,
                    2004.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hartley2005" label="Hartley 2005">Hartley, John. <title rend="quotes"
                        >After Ongism: The Evolution of Networked Intelligence,</title> in Walter J.
                    Ong, <title rend="italic">Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the
                        Word.</title> [Methuen &amp; Co., 1982] New York: Routledge, 2005, pp.
                    205-221; p. 207.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hiltzik1999" label="Hiltzik 1999">Hiltzik, Michael. <title
                        rend="italic">Dealers of Lightning: Xerox PARC and the Dawn of the Computer
                        Age.</title> New York: Harper Business, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hyde2003" label="Hyde 2003">Hyde, Alan. <title rend="italic">Working
                        in Silicon Valley: Economic and Legal Analysis of a High-Velocity Labor
                        Market.</title> New York: M.E. Sharpe, 2003: 7-10.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jay1993" label="Jay 1993">Jay, Martin. <title rend="italic">Downcast
                        Eyes: The Denigration of Vision in Twentieth-Century France.</title>
                    Berkeley: University of California Press, 1993.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="johns2009" label="Johns 2009">Johns, Adrian. <title rend="italic">The
                        Nature of the Book: Print and Knowledge in the Making.</title> Chicago:
                    University of Chicago Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jucker2003" label="Jucker 2003">Jucker, Andreas S. <title
                        rend="quotes">Mass Media Communication at the Beginning of the Twenty-First
                        Century: Dimensions of Change,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Historical Pragmatics,</title> 4:1 (2003),
                    129-148, 129.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kernan1987" label="Kernan 1987">Kernan, Alvin. <title rend="italic"
                        >Samuel Johnson and the Impact of Print.</title> Princeton: Princeton
                    University Press, 1987</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirsch2014" label="Kirsch 2014">Kirsch, Adam. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Technology Is Taking Over English Departments,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New Republic</title> (2 May 2014). Accessed online:
                        <ref
                        target="https://newrepublic.com/article/117428/limits-digital-humanities-adam-kirsch"
                        >https://newrepublic.com/article/117428/limits-digital-humanities-adam-kirsch</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lee2000" label="Lee et al. 2000"><title rend="italic">The Silicon
                        Valley Edge: A Habitat for Innovation and Entrepreneurship</title>, ed.
                    Chong Moon Lee, William F. Miller, Marguerite Gong Hancock, and Henry S. Rowen.
                    Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="levinson1997" label="Levinson 1997">Levinson, Paul. <title
                        rend="italic">The Soft Edge: A Natural History and Future of the Information
                        Revolution.</title> New York: Routledge, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="li2011" label="Li and Bernhoff 2011">Li, Charlene and Josh Bernhoff.
                        <title rend="italic">Groundswell: Winning in a World Transformed by Social
                        Technologies.</title> Cambridge: Harvard Business Review Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="naughton2011" label="Naughton 2011">Naughton, John. <title
                        rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Zuckerberg: Disruptive Innovation in the Age
                        of the Internet.</title> New York: Quercus, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcfarquhar2012" label="McFarquhar 2012">McFarquhar, Larissa. <title
                        rend="quotes">When Giants Fail: What Business Has Learned from Clayton
                        Christensen,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title> (14 May 2012), pp. 84-90. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1962" label="McLuhan 1962">McLuhan, Marshall. <title
                        rend="italic">The Gutenberg Galaxy: The Making of Typographic Man.</title>
                    Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1962.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marx2000" label="Marx 2000">Marx, Leo. <title rend="italic">The
                        Machine in the Garden: Technology and the Pastoral Ideal in America.</title>
                    Oxford: Oxford University Press, [1964] 2000: 187ffn.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marx1997" label="Marx 1997">Marx, Leo. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Technology: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept,</title><title
                        rend="italic"> Social Research</title>, 64, 3 (Fall 1997), pp. 968, 974-75,
                    977. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oed" label="Oxford English Dictionary">Oxford English Dictionary,
                        <title rend="quotes">Technology.</title> Accessed online 7 December 2015:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/198469?redirectedFrom=technology#eid"
                        >http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/198469?redirectedFrom=technology#eid</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ong2005" label="Ong 2005">Ong, Walter J. <title rend="italic">Orality
                        and Literacy.</title> [London: Methuen &amp; Co., Ltd., 1982] New York:
                    Routledge, 2005. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pettitt2007" label="Pettit 2007">Pettitt, Thomas. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Before the <emph>Gutenberg Parenthesis</emph>:
                        Elizabethan-American Compatibilities,</title> lecture, April 2007. Accessed
                    online: <ref
                        target="http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/mit5/papers/pettitt_plenary_gutenberg.pdf"
                        >http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/mit5/papers/pettitt_plenary_gutenberg.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pettitt2013" label="Pettit">Pettitt, Thomas. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Privacy Parenthesis: Gutenberg, <emph>Homo Clausus</emph>, and the Networked
                        Self,</title> lecture, April 2013. Accessed online: <ref
                        target="http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/mit8/papers/TomPettitt%20Paper.pdf"
                        >http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/mit8/papers/TomPettitt%20Paper.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rettberg2007" label="Rettberg 2007">Rettberg, Jill Walker. <title
                        rend="quotes">Blogs, Literacies, and the Collapse of Private and
                        Public,</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Leonardo Electronic Archive, </title>16, 2-3 (2007):
                    8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="robins1999" label="Robins and Webster 1999">Robins, Kevin and Frank
                    Webster, <title rend="italic">Times of the Technoculture: From the Information
                        Society to the Virtual Life.</title> London: Routledge, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rose1992" label="Rose 1992">Rose, Jonathan. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Rereading the English Common Reader: A Preface to a History of
                        Audiences,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas</title>, 53, 1 (Jan-Mar
                    1992), 47-70.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sawday2000" label="Sawday and Rhodes 2000"><title rend="italic">The
                        Renaissance Computer: Knowledge Technology in the First Age of
                    Print</title>, ed. Jonathan Sawday and Neil Rhodes. London: Routledge,
                    2000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="saxenian1994" label="Saxenian 1994">Saxenian, AnnaLee. <title
                        rend="italic">Regional Advantage: Culture and Competition in Silicon Valley
                        and Route 128.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1994.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shillinsburg2006" label="Shillingsburg 2006">Shillingsburg, Peter.
                        <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google: Electronic Representations of
                        Literary Texts.</title> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith1988" label="Smith and Alexander 1988">Smith, Douglas K.and
                    Robert C. Alexander, <title rend="italic">Fumbling the Future: How Xerox
                        Invented, then Ignored, the First Personal Computer.</title> New York:
                    Morrow, 1988. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="standage1998">Standage, Tom. <title rend="italic">The Victorian
                        Internet: The Remarkable Story of the Telegraph and the Nineteenth Century’s
                        Online Pioneers.</title> London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1998. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="standage2013" label="Standage 2013">Standage, Tom. <title
                        rend="italic">Writing on the Wall: Social Media - The First 2,000
                        Years.</title> New York / London: Bloomsbury, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thomas1986" label="Thomas 1986">Thomas, Keith. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Meaning of Literacy in Early Modern England,</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">The Written Word: Literacy in Transition</title>, ed. Gerd
                    Baumann. Oxford, 1986. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="warner1990" label="Warner 1990">Warner, Michael. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Letters of the Republic: Publication and the Public Sphere in
                        Eighteenth-Century America.</title> Cambridge: Harvard University Press,
                    1990. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="williams1977" label="Williams 1977">Williams, Raymond. <title
                        rend="italic">Television and Cultural Form.</title> New York: Schocken
                    Books, 1975; repr. 1977.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
