<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Close Rereading: A review of Jessica Pressman, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making It New in New Media</title> (Oxford:
                    Oxford UP, 2014)</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Shawna <dhq:family>Ross</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Arizona State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>smross3@asu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Shawna Ross is a lecturer at the Arizona State University who specializes
                            in modernist British literature, cultural studies, and digital
                            humanities. Her dissertation, defended in June 2011, was on the leisure
                            spaces of modernity, and currently, she is working on her book
                            manuscript, <title rend="italic">Spaces of Play: Inventing the Modern
                                Leisure Space in British Fiction and Culture, 1860-1960</title>,
                            about the relationship between literature and the emergence of modern
                            leisure spaces. She has published and presented on Henry James,
                            Katherine Mansfield, Elizabeth Bowen, Evelyn Waugh, Charlotte Brontë,
                            and others, and she is currently at work on a series of papers and
                            projects on the digital Henry James.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000207</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2015-05-26">26 May 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This review of Jessica Pressman’s <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making
                        It New in New Media</title> (2014) emphasizes the field-building
                    significance of Pressman’s innovative approach to analyzing electronic
                    literature, an approach that reinvigorates the dated methods of New Criticism
                    for use in the digital humanities. Pressman identifies a genre of contemporary
                    electronic literature, <q>digital
                        modernism,</q> and uncovers continuities linking it with early
                    twentieth-century modernism. In spite of an uneven style that oscillates between
                    belabored scholasticism and brilliant description, <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Modernism</title> rigorously wrangles a wide array of data points —
                    historical, literary, and technological — to create an account of contemporary
                    electronic literature relevant for digital humanists, literary scholars, and New
                    Media scholars. This review contextualizes the work within new currents in
                    modernist scholarship, reflects on the modernism and digital modernist
                        <soCalled>canon</soCalled> Pressman assembles, and then provides chapter
                    summaries, with an emphasis on <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s
                    reinvention of close reading for the twenty-first century.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>A review of Jessica Pressman's <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making It
                        New in New Media</title> (2014).</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Jessica Pressman’s <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making It New in New
                    Media</title> is an innovative, indispensable, and far-ranging work that
                contextualizes a compact canon of contemporary digital literature within the broader
                twentieth-century modernist tradition of artistic engagement with new media. Bogged
                down by a plodding scholarly proceduralism, the book’s conscientious tone nearly
                muffles a series of lively readings of digital literature. <title rend="italic"
                    >Digital Modernism</title>’s impressive interdisciplinarity, which combines
                principles from a variety of <soCalled>new</soCalled> fields — New Media Studies,
                New Modernist Studies, and New Criticism — is brought to bear on works by William
                Poundstone, Young-Hae Change Heavy Industries (YHCHI), Erik Loyer, Talan Memmott,
                Judd Morrissey, and Mark Z. Danielewski. Pressman argues that these works not only
                contain <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">immanent critiques of their
                    technocultural context</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="156"/></cit>, but also enable us <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">to see more clearly the world of print</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="54"/></cit>. Refashioning Marshall McLuhan, father of New
                Media Studies, as a midcentury axis or conceptual medium capable of reaching
                backward to modernism and forward to digital culture, Pressman achieves nothing less
                than a new vision of the intellectual and artistic history of new media and
                technology. <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">What is at stake,</quote>
                she boldly claims, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">is nothing short of
                    a better understanding of the significance of literary art, critical reading
                    practices, and humanistic culture in a our networked age</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="27"/></cit>. Due to Pressman’s fierce advocacy of close
                reading, <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s conceptual eclecticism
                does not impede the clarity of her vision, but it comes at the cost of a narrowness
                in the scope of literary works she investigates — in ways she sometimes compensates
                for and, at other times, does not. </p>
            <p><title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s opening salvo, Mark Wollaeger and
                Kevin J. Dettmar’s remarkably sassy Series Editors’ Foreword, is structured as a
                FAQ. Anticipating knee-jerk rejections of Pressman’s choice of modernism rather than
                postmodernism as the appropriate period concept for digital literature, the foreword
                reminds us that only a now-defunct distinction between <soCalled>highbrow</soCalled>
                and <soCalled>lowbrow</soCalled> art buoyed up theories separating modernism from
                postmodernism. <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">This isn’t the 1980s
                    anymore</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="x"/></cit>, they only half-jokingly growl, in a way that
                is likely puzzling to those without disciplinary training in modernism. Behind this
                impatience is New Modernist Studies, an interdisciplinary, cultural
                studies-inflected approach to modernist literature dating from 1994 with the
                founding of the journal <title rend="italic">Modernism/modernity</title> and the
                inaugural Modernist Studies Association (MSA) Conference in 1999. The journal’s
                inaugural issue announces an interdisciplinary editorial approach grounded in
                modernists’ insistence that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#rainey1994">changes in
                    the arts be viewed in conjunction with changes in philosophy, historiography,
                    and social theory, to say nothing of the scientific shifts that they claimed as
                    part of their moment's cultural revolution</quote>
                <ptr target="#rainey1994" loc="1"/></cit>. The MSA Conference crystallized this approach
                by expanding the canon, addressing issues of class, gender, sexuality, race, and
                empire, and emphasizing technology and new media. Pressman’s book seems to fit in
                because it reshapes modernism in light of digital culture and dovetails with the
                latest New Modernist criticism, which has expanded the traditional historical and
                geographical boundaries of what is considered to be <q>modernist.</q><note> I refer
                    here to the recent trend of approaching modernism through a transnational
                    approach. For more about this temporal and geographic expansion, see <title
                        rend="quotes">The New Modernist Studies</title>
                    <ptr target="#mao2008"/>.</note> Ultimately, the Foreword’s feisty pugilism,
                like Clint Eastwood in <title rend="italic">Dirty Harry</title>, dares you to make
                their day by claiming that Pressman does not subscribe to the policies of canonical,
                temporal, and spatial expansionism under two decades of New Modernist Studies.</p>
            <p><title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s central insight — that a new genre,
                    <q>digital modernism,</q> remixes older works of literary modernism to flout
                expectations of contemporary electronic literature — supports these diversifying
                efforts. But Pressman’s modernist canon privileges the usual suspects of Ezra Pound,
                James Joyce, and T. S. Eliot, hearkening back to the <soCalled>bad
                    modernism</soCalled> of pre-1994 scholarship.<note> To learn more about <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#mao2006">bad modernism,</quote> see the edited
                    collection of the same name, <title rend="italic">Bad Modernism</title>
                    <ptr target="#mao2006"/>.</note> The same can be said about Pressman’s digital
                canon, which features authors who have already attracted scholarly attention (the
                fêted YHCHI appears in two chapters) and whose conscious literariness makes them
                legible to traditional scholarship. With this caveat, we can answer their parting
                question, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">Should I not only read this
                    book but also assign it in classes and give it to all my friends and
                    family?</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="x"/></cit>, in the affirmative answer (though it
                certainly depends on one’s family).</p>
            <p>The foreword’s cheekiness does not offset the stiffness that calcifies much of the
                book inside its stringently cultivated framework of signposts, justifications, and
                qualifications. This is particularly true of the dauntingly learned Introduction,
                which, with its fifteen-page section <title rend="quotes">Defining My Terms</title>
                (itself divided into five subsections) prefacing sections on <title rend="quotes"
                    >The Stakes of My Argument,</title>
                <title rend="quotes">Critical Influences,</title> and <title rend="quotes">Chapter
                    Summaries,</title> reads like a book prospectus and distances readers from the
                clear, dynamic, and ingenious close readings yet to come. That the Introduction
                skips from <title rend="quotes">Part II</title> straight to <title rend="quotes"
                    >Part IV</title> suggests that even an Oxford University Press copyeditor cannot
                keep this structural rabbit warren straight. Of course, the micromanaging
                Introduction has a serious purpose: to convince serious readers that electronic
                literature is serious stuff. Pressman explains, <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#pressman2014">There is a countermovement underway,
                        this book argues, a serious effort to encourage digital literature to be
                        taken seriously.... [T]he majority of this book focuses on Internet-based
                        literature in order to show how and why one of the most maligned of literary
                        spaces, the web — one accused of fostering reading habits that destroy deep
                        attention and devalue hermeneutic analysis — is actually the place where
                        serious literature stages its rebellion and renaissance.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="8–9"/>
                </cit></p>
            <p>This is indeed an important task, and Pressman is equal to it. Her close readings of
                digital literature do <soCalled>reward</soCalled>
                (one of her key terms) her attention, and they do <soCalled>renovate</soCalled> (another key term) modernism by
                revealing its imbrication in contemporary digital culture. <soCalled>Remediate</soCalled> completes the core lexicon of <title
                    rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>, which adds to Bolter and Grusin’s
                concept <ptr target="#bolter2000"/> a new affordance: close reading. Pressman’s
                comparison of early twentieth-century modernism and contemporary digital modernism
                reveals that remediation is both a product of and an invitation to close reading,
                which <soCalled>rewards</soCalled> critical attention
                by <soCalled>renovating</soCalled> texts and
                technologies. In doing so, <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism
                </title>effectively remediates not just modernist new media, but indeed close
                reading itself — hence this review’s title.</p>
            <p>The Introduction responsibly, if ponderously, hits its required disciplinary beats by
                defining modernism, electronic literature, digital modernism, close reading, and New
                Criticism. Readers from a variety of fields are swiftly caught up to speed, ensuring
                the book’s accessibility to a broad audience. In defining close reading as a <quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">careful application of focused attention
                    to the formal operations in a literary text</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="11"/>, Pressman strikes a strong blow in the battle
                quantitative formalism now wages against close reading.<note> For a discussion of
                    the debate over the future of close reading in literary studies, see <title
                        rend="quotes">In Praise of Overstating the Case: A Review of Franco
                        Moretti’s <title rend="italic">Close Reading</title></title>
                    <ptr target="#ross2014"/>.</note> A close reading-positive critic, she claims
                that her texts inherently contain complexity: they <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">suggest,</quote>
                <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">invite,</quote>
                <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">encourage,</quote>
                <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">push,</quote> even <quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">propel</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="76"/> all sorts of readings. Assuredly,
                    <emph>readers</emph> are rewarded by attending to Pressman’s close readings, but
                the degree to which we owe this brilliance to the text or to the critic’s ingenuity
                remains an open question.</p>
            <p>Pressman’s most controversial definitions cover electronic literature and New
                Criticism. She defines electronic literature through aesthetic and material criteria
                — <soCalled>born-digital</soCalled> works that are <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">computational and processural, dependent upon the
                    operations of the machine for its aesthetic effects</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="1"/></cit> — an austere characterization that makes no
                reference to the Internet, networks, or multimedia. Pressman restricts her gaze
                further by focusing on digital modernism, a subgenre that rejects mainstream
                electronic literature’s investment in hyperlinks, interactivity, and multimedia. As
                a result, when she deprecates the <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014"
                    >small but certain canon</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="6"/></cit> of first-generation electronic literature, we
                could retort that she simply replaces it with a<emph> different</emph> small but
                certain canon. Still, <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s canon hangs
                together by other means than the rubber stamping of an expert’s approval: digital
                modernism <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">renovates</quote> and <quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">remixes literary modernism</quote> by
                being <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">text based, aesthetically
                    difficult, and ambivalent in [its] relationship to mass media and popular
                    culture</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="2"/></cit>. Like the earlier modernism it remediates,
                digital modernism <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">challenges
                    traditional expectations about what art is and does. It illuminates and
                    interrogates the cultural infrastructures, technological networks, and critical
                    practices that support and enable these judgments</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="10"/></cit>.</p>
            <p>This account savors somewhat of Theodor Adorno’s immanent critique and Frankfurt
                School social criticism,<note> The Frankfurt School refers, of course, to the group
                    of Marxist thinkers originally based out of the Frankfurt School for Social
                    Research. Adorno, Max Horkheimer, Walter Benjamin, Herbert Marcuse, and Jürgen
                    Habermas are generally considered among its practitioners. Immanent critique
                    refers to Adorno’s revision of Hegelian dialectics. For more on <q>immanent
                        critique,</q> see his <title rend="italic">Negative Dialectics</title>
                    <ptr target="#adorno1966"/>; for a general introduction to Frankfurt School
                    theory and method, see <title rend="italic">The Dialectical Imagination</title>
                    <ptr target="#jay1996"/>.</note> but Pressman submerges the Adornian themes in
                favor of the New Criticism she so passionately champions. Paradoxically, it is
                precisely this championing of <soCalled>old</soCalled> methods that makes <title
                    rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title> so refreshing in debates over the fate
                of close reading in the face of new methods from the digital humanities (DH). She
                positions Marshall McLuhan as a central figure in the scholarly uptake of the New
                Critical principles first espoused by I. A. Richards and F. R. Leavis. As <title
                    rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title> uncovers layers of technological and
                aesthetic histories contributing to electronic literature, its reuptake of close
                reading can be seen as anticipating Matthew Kirschenbaum’s recent essay <title
                    rend="quotes">What Is <q>Digital Humanities,</q> and Why Are They Saying Such
                    Terrible Things About It?</title>
                <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2014"/>. This essay calls for DH to turn its analysis on
                itself, praising Alan Liu’s <title rend="quotes">The Meaning of the Digital
                    Humanities</title>
                <ptr target="#liu2013"/> for its Science Studies-style analysis of a single DH
                project. Kirschenbaum exhorts us to <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#kirschenbaum2014">detail the material conditions of knowledge
                    production,</quote> including <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2014"
                    >usage patterns</quote> and <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2014"
                    >citation networks</quote>
                <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2014" loc="60"/></cit> — to do, in other words, what Pressman
                does for New Criticism. </p>
            <p>Recuperating the New Critical heritage in foundational texts of New Media Studies —
                chiefly <title rend="italic">The Mechanical Bride</title>
                <ptr target="#mcluhan1951"/>, <title rend="italic">The Gutenberg Galaxy</title>
                <ptr target="#mcluhan1962"/>, and <title rend="italic"> Understanding Media</title>
                <ptr target="#mcluhan1964"/> — takes up Chapter One. Pressman moves far beyond hoary
                chestnuts about the global village and the medium being the message, revealing that
                his method <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">was always approaching the
                    broader category of the literary <emph>within</emph> complex media
                    ecologies</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="29"/></cit>. Advocating a <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">slow, focused attention and rigorous
                    consideration</quote> of texts <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="13"/>, Pressman
                echoes recent reevaluations of New Criticism that cut through the stale, straw-men
                stereotypes that often compromise critiques of close reading. <note> For other
                    scholarly accounts that advocate New Criticism, see <title rend="italic"
                        >Praising It New: The Best of the New Criticism</title>
                    <ptr target="#davis2008"/> and Miranda Hickman and John McIntyre’s <title
                        rend="italic">Rereading the New Criticism</title>
                    <ptr target="#hickman2012"/>.</note> Though she supports the efforts of Critical
                Code Studies to analyze code regardless of its output, it <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">should not replace rigorous analysis of the aesthetic
                    ambitions and results of technopoetic pursuits</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="20"/></cit>. Close reading, as an avant-garde critical
                response that respects aesthetic complexity, provides this rigor — and pleasure: <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#pressman2014">For anyone who has read a good close
                        reading, one that takes you through a journey in a text that you’ve read
                        before and teaches you to see it anew, you know how transformative the
                        experience can be. A good close reading can change your mind. It can make
                        you reread and reconsider. Close reading can be not only about art but can
                        become art, and for the New Critics, this was part of the point.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="14"/>
                </cit></p>
            <p>By claiming that close readings are themselves cultural artifacts, Pressman elegantly
                sidesteps arguments that close reading demands a single <soCalled>correct</soCalled>
                interpretation. Although some of the stronger claims about McLuhan’s digital hipness
                force the issue through diction — he apparently knows <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">how different data sources and circuits of flow
                    constitute a literary experience</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="35"/></cit> — her genealogy joining modernism and digital
                modernism through McLuhan is otherwise solid.</p>
            <p>Chapter Two, <title rend="quotes">Reading Machines: MACHINE POETRY AND EXCAVATORY
                    READING in William Poundstone’s electronic literature and Bob Brown’s
                    Readies,</title> surveys early reading technologies, both real (the
                tachistoscope, subliminal advertising) and imagined (the hypothetical
                    <soCalled>Readies</soCalled> machine dreamed up by American modernist Bob
                Brown). This survey demonstrates <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">that
                    technologies of reading, not just writing, are an integral part of American
                    literary history</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="57"/></cit> and that <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">our reading practices [are] always shaped by historical
                    contexts and media formats</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="60"/></cit>. Although the stories of these technologies
                have been told elsewhere — the chapter relies heavily on <title rend="italic">Swift
                    Viewing</title>
                <ptr target="#acland2013"/> and <title rend="italic">Suspensions of
                    Perception</title>
                <ptr target="#crary1999"/> — what Pressman adds to these media-archaeological
                accounts is, as one should expect, excellent close readings, particularly of William
                Poundstone’s <title rend="italic">Project for the Tachistoscope {Bottomless
                    Pit}</title>. For me, this reading of <title rend="italic">Project</title> is
                incomplete: in calling the text a <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014"
                    >parable about reading in the midst of medial shift,</quote> Pressman empties
                Poundstone’s Flash narrative of its critical charge. Is the bottomless pit, whose
                sudden and troubling appearance constitutes <title rend="italic">Project</title>’s
                plot, really only <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">a symbolic entity: a
                    thing to read</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="62"/></cit>, or is it also something very literal —
                perhaps a timely representation of fracking, which has caused all-too-real
                collapsing sinkhole pits to appear all across the United States, from New Mexico to
                Pennsylvania? </p>
            <p>This lack of attention to current events is, again, likely a space issue but worth
                mentioning because critiques of New Criticism single out its ahistoricism. Chapter
                Three, <title rend="quotes">Speed Reading: Super-position and Simultaneity in
                    YHCHI’s <title rend="italic">Dakota</title> and Ezra Pound’s <title
                        rend="italic">Cantos</title>,</title> shares this blindness. Pressman
                develops another <soCalled>excavatory</soCalled> reading in her analysis of <title
                    rend="italic">Dakota</title>, but it, too, could be literally about excavation,
                as its South Dakota-to-South Korea setting documents the transformation of a state
                during a twenty-first century gold rush for the minerals on which <title
                    rend="italic">Dakota</title>’s Flash iterations depend. Space constraints thus
                leave chinks in <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>’s erudite armor. The
                last half of Chapter Two, for example, relies on Pressman’s access to a rare text:
                the 1931 collection of poems Bob Brown commissioned from major modernists, including
                Gertrude Stein, Filippo Marinetti, and William Carlos Williams, for Brown’s Readies
                machine. Pressman argues that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">these
                    poems are textual acts of programming; they are code</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="72"/></cit>. This parallel is more than a metaphor, and
                it is one of the most powerful, successful theses in <title rend="italic">Digital
                    Reading</title>. Unfortunately, its corresponding close reading is allotted a
                single paragraph. </p>
            <p>To be fair, though, when the reader pushes past the forest of scholarly apparatuses,
                the masterful close readings lying in wait are well worth the price of admission.
                The sixteen-page close reading of <title rend="italic">Dakota</title> is sheer joy:
                beautifully written, snappily paced, and filled-to-bursting with ideas. As it layers
                evidence showing that <title rend="italic">Dakota</title> is a close reading of
                Pound’s <title rend="italic">Cantos</title>, it argues that <title rend="italic"
                    >Dakota</title> elicits both close reading and speed reading. <title
                    rend="italic">Dakota</title>’s <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014"
                    >retroaesthetic</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="90"/></cit> therefore challenges assumptions about
                digital reading practices, revealing that <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">identity is distributed across and informed by network
                    technologies</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="92"/></cit>. But no more about <title rend="italic"
                    >Dakota</title>. Readers of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                    Quarterly</title> are simply exhorted to read this unforgettable section of
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title>.</p>
            <p>Chapter Four, <title rend="quotes">Reading the Database: Narrative, Database, and
                    Stream of Consciousness,</title> reviews contemporary electronic adaptations of
                James Joyce’s <title rend="italic">Ulysses</title> (1922) to show that <cit><quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">our definitions of <q>novel</q>...change
                    and adjust under the influence of digital databases</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="123"/></cit>. Without falling into technological
                determinism, Pressman analyzes Twitter, Flash, and print adaptations to show that
                they share a <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">database
                    aesthetic</quote> intended to provide access to human cognition. <title
                    rend="italic">Digital Modernism</title> shows that these iterations are invested
                in representing cognition by unpacking traces of <title rend="italic"
                    >Ulysses</title> in them: a Twitter performance by Ian Bogost and Ian McCarthy,
                Judd Morrissey and Lori Talley’s <title rend="italic">The Jew’s Daughter</title>,
                and Talan Memmott's <title rend="italic">My Molly (Departed)</title>. Pressman’s
                engaging descriptions reveal that the most famous modernist invention — the
                    <q>stream of consciousness</q> developed from William James’s psychology —
                models cognition as a database-based operation of search and retrieval. This chapter
                concludes that consciousness is <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">always
                    mediated and distributed across technologies</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="103"/></cit>. Though the argumentation is generally
                persuasive, I regret Pressman’s Joyce-centrism. <title rend="italic">Digital
                    Modernisms</title> refers to an outdated canon of modernism that privileges the
                    <soCalled>men of 1914</soCalled> (T. S. Eliot, Ezra Pound, James Joyce, Wyndham
                Lewis). Can Pressman find no electronic renovations of, say, Virginia Woolf, May
                Sinclair, or Dorothy Richardson to balance the book’s elaborations of Joyce, Pound,
                and Eliot? And if not, what does that say about digital modernism?</p>
            <p>Though digital modernism does not conform to the expanded modernist canon, it does
                share modernism’s difficulty. Digital modernism <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">rejects popular expectations of what it means to play
                    new media objects</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="122"/></cit> and reveals that <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">what we think to be real and analog about humanness is
                    actually the result of digital production</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="124"/></cit>. It also makes interpretation a <cit><quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">nightmarish task</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="108"/></cit>. About <title rend="italic">The Jew’s
                    Daughter</title>, Pressman shares <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014"
                    >a personal confession</quote>: <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#pressman2014">[T]he difficulty of deciphering this
                        work compelled me to undertake dramatic non-media-specific efforts. In order
                        to follow the narrative, I resorted to printing out all of the screens and,
                        on each page, highlighting in one color what text had changed and in a
                        different color what text would change. I also kept a detailed list of notes
                        identifying the main characters. But, even with this skeleton key, I
                        hesitate to attribute proper names to the ‘anonymous limbs and parts’ I
                        collected, assembled, and discuss in this chapter. Morrissey’s text is
                        incredibly difficult, and it depends on a disciplined reading
                        practice.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="109"/>
                </cit></p>
            <p>This <soCalled>confession</soCalled> is hardly shameful. In this passage Pressman
                describes not just close reading, but indeed close <emph>re</emph>reading, thus
                    <soCalled>making new</soCalled> traditional techniques of scholarship
                (note-taking, list-making). Some brave critic may develop different tools for
                wrangling these resistant electronic texts, perhaps tools <emph>accepting</emph> the
                fast-paced, hard-to-read, sensory-overloading style, appreciating difficulty as an
                aesthetic experience rather than <emph>overcoming</emph> it. Until then, Pressman’s
                strategy of combining close reading and media archaeology is rigorous and
                effective.</p>
            <p>The fifth chapter, <title rend="quotes">Reading Code: The Hallucination of Universal
                    Language from Modernism to Cyberspace,</title> is by far the longest, perhaps
                because it performs the kind of political critique that I found lacking in the
                second and third chapters. Pressman takes over a hundred pages to explore the
                insights that emerge <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">when computing
                    and literature are approached as sharing a historical and ideological
                    core</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="137"/></cit>. Interpreting Eric Loyer’s digital novel
                    <title rend="italic">Chroma</title> within the broader Western tradition seeking
                universal language, Pressman demythologizes the <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">belief that universal language is possible with the
                    right textual code. This belief undergirds ideologies that code is universal and
                    that cyberspace (or even digital culture more broadly) is natural or
                    inevitable</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="129"/></cit>. After <title rend="italic">Chroma</title>,
                Pressman analyzes YHCHI’s <title rend="italic">Nippon</title> as <cit><quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">as a critique of the homogenizing
                    influence of the English-based and Western-focused web</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="154"/></cit> and of <cit><quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">poets and philosophers [who] have fantasized about
                    Chinese as universal code</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="143"/></cit>. <title rend="italic">Nippon</title>’s
                difficulty dramatizes how computers work by translation and approximation, thereby
                    <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">disabl[ing] contemporary
                    hallucinations about universal language</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="151"/></cit>. In persuading us to resist <cit><quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">imaginative narratives, theories, and
                    mythologies about the natural and universal power of digital code</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="137"/></cit>, Pressman demonstrates why cultural and
                political critique is still relevant.</p>
            <p>Half the length of Chapter Five, the brisk concluding chapter, <title rend="quotes"
                    >CODA — Rereading: Digital Modernism in Print, Mark Z. Danielewski’s <title
                        rend="italic">Only Revolutions</title>,</title> incorporates this print
                novel to show <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">all literature...is
                    impacted by digitality</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="158"/></cit>. In this case, even non-electronic
                literature <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">demands that the reader
                    reread in order to close read</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="161"/></cit>. This 2006 epic of a pair of doomed but
                free-spirited road-trippers, from which Danielewski consciously jettisoned
                references to media, might seem an unlikely specimen. But if <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">the strategy of digital modernism</quote> involves
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">making it new</quote> by <cit><quote
                    rend="inline" source="#pressman2014">a recursive act of engaging with a
                    literary past through media</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="158"/></cit>, then <title rend="italic">Only
                    Revolutions</title> belongs. As a conclusion, the Coda cleverly uses <title
                    rend="italic">Only Revolutions</title> to review the broader argument that
                digital modernism illuminates both modernism and the history of New Media. Here
                Pressman finally relaxes — the Coda fancifully describes <title rend="italic">Only
                    Revolutions</title>’s included bookmarks as <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">meeting in the middle</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#pressman2014">kissing</quote>
                <ptr target="#pressman2014" loc="173"/> and disarmingly identifies which of
                Danielewski’s crowd-sourced data points was her personal submission <ptr
                    target="#pressman2014" loc="170"/> — and makes rewarding read out of what could
                have been a banal retread. This tonal anomaly, when considered as a performative
                extension of her argument, has a purpose: <title rend="italic">Digital
                    Modernism</title> remediates scholarship itself as it reveals close reading to
                be immanent to digital culture, so Pressman is rereading herself. Only one
                difficulty remains. If the dream of universal language is, as Pressman argues, a
                dangerous hallucination, and if close reading can be applied to any text, is close
                reading the scholar’s final hallucination?</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="acland2013" label="Acland 2013">Acland, Charles. <title rend="italic"
                        >Swift Viewing: The Popular Life of Subliminal Influence. </title>Durham,
                    NC: Duke University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adorno1966" label="Adorno 1966">Adorno, Theodor. <title rend="italic"
                        >Negative Dialectics</title>. Trans. E. B. Ashton. New York: Routledge,
                    1966.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bolter2000" label="Bolter and Grusin 2000">Bolter, Jay David and
                    Richard Grusin. <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New
                        Media</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crary1999" label="Crary 1999">Crary, Jonathan. <title rend="italic"
                        >Suspensions of Perception: Attention, Spectacle, and Modern
                    Culture</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis2008" label="Davis 2008">Davis, Garrick, ed. <title rend="italic"
                        >Praising It New: The Best of the New Criticism</title>. Columbus, OH: Ohio
                    University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="derrida1984" label="Derrida 1984">Derrida, Jacques. <title
                        rend="quotes">Two Words for Joyce.</title> In Derek Attridge and Daniel
                    Ferrer (eds.), <title rend="italic">Post-Structural Joyce: Essays from the
                        French</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1984, pp.
                    145-185.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hickman2012" label="Hickman and McIntyre 2012">Hickman, Miranda and
                    John McIntyre, eds. <title rend="italic">Rereading the New Criticism</title>.
                    Columbus, OH: Ohio University Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="james2014" label="James and Seshagiri 2014">James, David and Urmila
                    Seshagiri. <title rend="quotes">Metamodernism: Narratives of Continuity and
                        Revolution.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 129.1 (2014): 87-100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jay1996" label="Jay 1996">Jay, Martin. <title rend="italic">The
                        Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute
                        of Social Research, 1923-1950.</title> Berkeley, CA: University of
                    California Press, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2014" label="Kirschenbaum 2014">Kirschenbaum, Matthew.
                        <title rend="quotes">What is <q>Digital Humanities,</q> and Why Are They
                        Saying Such Terrible Things about It?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">differences </title>25.1 (2014): 46-63.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2013" label="Liu 2013">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes">The Meaning
                        of the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA </title>128 (2013): 409-23. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mao2006" label="Mao and Walkowitz 2006">Mao, Douglas and Rebecca
                    Walkowitz, eds. <title rend="italic">Bad Modernisms</title>. Durham, N.C.: Duke
                    University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mao2008" label="Mao and Walkowitz 2008">Mao, Douglas and Rebecca
                    Walkowitz. <title rend="quotes">The New Modernist Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA </title>123.3 (2008): 737-48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1962" label="McLuhan 1962">McLuhan, Marshall. <title
                        rend="italic">The Gutenberg Galaxy: The Making of Typographic Man</title>.
                    Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1962.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1951" label="McLuhan 1951">McLuhan, Marshall. <title
                        rend="italic">The Mechanical Bride: Folklore of Industrial Man</title>.
                    1951. Berkeley, CA: Gingko Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1964" label="McLuhan 1964">McLuhan, Marshall.<title
                        rend="italic">Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</title>. 1964.
                    Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pressman2014" label="Pressman 2014">Pressman, Jessica. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Modernism: Making it New in New Media</title>. Oxford:
                    Oxford University Press, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rainey1994" label="Rainey and von Hallberg 1994">Rainey, Lawrence, and
                    Robert von Hallberg. <title rend="quotes">Editorial/Introduction.</title><title
                        rend="italic"> Modernism/modernity</title> 1.1 (1994): 1-3. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2014" label="Ross 2014">Ross, Shawna. <title rend="quotes">In
                        Praise of Overstating the Case: A Review of Franco Moretti’s <title
                            rend="italic">Distant Reading</title>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 8.1 (2014). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000171/000171.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000171/000171.html</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
