<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">The Arrival Fallacy: Collaborative Research Relationships in the
               Digital Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Alix<dhq:family> Keener</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Michigan</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alixkee@umich.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Alix Keener is the Digital Scholarship Librarian at the University of Michigan
                     Library. She holds a Master of Science in Information (2014) from the
                     University of Michigan School of Information, with a specialization in Library
                     and Information Science.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000213</idno>
            <idno type="volume">009</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2015-08-07">7 August 2015</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>libraries</item>
                  <item>collaboration</item>
                  <item>digital scholarship</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change who="JDF" when="2015-06-24">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>As discussion and debates on the digital humanities continue among scholars, so too
               does discussion about how academic libraries can and should support this scholarship.
               Through interviews with digital humanities scholars and academic librarians within
               the Center for Institutional Cooperation, this study aims to explore some points of
               common perspective and underlying tensions in research relationships. Qualitative
               interviews revealed that, while both groups are enthusiastic about the future of
               faculty-librarian collaboration on digital scholarship, there remain certain tensions
               about the role of the library and the librarian. Scholars appreciate the specialized
               expertise of librarians, especially in metadata and special collections, but they can
               take a more active stance in utilizing current library resources or vocalizing their
               needs for other resources. This expertise and these services can be leveraged to make
               the library an active and equal partner in research. Additionally, libraries should
               address internal issues, such as training and re-skilling librarians as necessary;
               better-coordinated outreach to academic departments is also needed. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>A discussion about how academic libraries can and should support digital humanities
               scholarship.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In February 2014, the Online Computer Library Center (OCLC) published a report titled
                  <title rend="italic">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital Humanities
                  Center?</title>
               <ptr target="#schaffner2014"/>, meant to guide library deans and directors in
               deciding whether or not to <q>sink resources</q> into a digital humanities center.
               The report immediately generated intense discussion and even backlash and controversy
               among bloggers and users of Twitter (consisting mostly of academic librarians or
               academic staff). Criticisms of the report included that it strips agency from
               librarians, assumes incorrectly that digital humanities scholars always know for what
               they are looking, and misses the insight that sometimes librarians are actually the
               digital humanists.<note>See <ref
                     target="http://twitter.com/nowviskie/status/432357552501047296"
                     >http://twitter.com/nowviskie/status/432357552501047296</ref>.</note> Other
               than a broad example of the current landscape of digital humanities debates, the OCLC
               report serves as an example of the tensions underlying collaborative research
               relationships between faculty and librarians (or other academic staff, including
               postdoctoral researchers or support staff).</p>
            <p>Digital humanities (DH), as a field, has an increasing presence in institutions of
               higher education <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2010"/>. However, while its presence has
               grown, so have questions about the kind of infrastructure that is needed to support
               research in the digital humanities. In the last several years that presence has
               increasingly been in academic libraries. Whether it is a center, such as the
               University of Nebraska-Lincoln’s Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, or
               smaller, more ambiguous spaces staffed with DH-knowledgeable librarians, academic
               libraries are becoming inextricably linked with digital humanities research on their
               respective campuses. That means that new collaborative relationships are emerging
               between individuals on those campuses. However, the nature of these relationships may
               produce tension, as the nature of being an equal collaborator may not fit into the
               role of <q>traditional</q> librarianship <ptr target="#vandegrift2013"/>.</p>
            <p>New digital technologies are changing the way humanist scholars do research and the
               way they communicate their findings through the publication of their work <ptr
                  target="#burgess2011"/>. Academic libraries are also adapting to these new modes
               of research: no longer are librarians simply supporting research endeavors through
               reference and instruction services; they are partners in research collaborations <ptr
                  target="#vandegrift2013"/>. The findings of a survey included in the Association
               of Research Libraries (ARL) Spec Kit 326 demonstrate that libraries need to be
               familiar with the types of research being pursued at their institution. What kind of
               expertise is needed: that of an equal partner in collaboration, or an on-call service
               provider? The research reported in this article builds on the ARL investigation to
               analyze research relationships among scholars and librarians at CIC universities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Context</head>
            <div>
               <head>Definitions</head>
               <p>For the purposes of developing the interview protocols, this study adopts Kathleen
                  Fitzpatrick’s <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2010"/> definition of digital humanities as
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#fitzpatrick2010">a nexus of fields within which
                     scholars use computing technologies to investigate the kinds of questions that
                     are traditional to the humanities, or...who ask traditional kinds of
                     humanities-oriented questions about computing technologies</quote> and Abby
                  Smith Rumsey's  definition of digital scholarship as
                     <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#rumsey2011">the use of digital evidence and
                     method, digital authoring, digital publishing, digital curation and
                     preservation, and digital use and reuse of scholarship</quote><ptr target="#rumsey2011"/></cit>.</p>
               <p>To date, there has been little research done specifically on digital humanities
                  research relationships between faculty and academic librarians. Lynne Siemens and
                  her colleagues <ptr target="#siemens2011"/> have done similar research on
                  relationships in research; however, they interviewed and surveyed members of
                  established research teams working on established projects, where the study
                  presented here investigates more nebulous, emerging relationships between scholars
                  and librarians. An Association of Research Libraries SPEC Kit 326: Digital
                  Humanities (2011) surveys ARL member libraries on their successes and failures
                  offering digital scholarship support services. The results show that, as demand
                  for these services grows, librarians are reconsidering an ad hoc approach to
                  digital humanities services and beginning to adopt more scalable, sustainable, and
                  permanent programmatic approaches. However, the direction of these developments in
                  libraries is still unclear. Many responses in the ARL study reported on the early
                  stages of digital humanities services; libraries are still developing services,
                  and library staff are struggling to decide on the level of service and the need
                  for dedicated staff. The picture that emerges from the ARL study is of an evolving
                  field; questions still remain about how already-established digital humanities
                  services address the needs of DH initiatives on their campus, and the sorts of
                  activities those librarians perform. The ARL survey also provides a broad overview
                  of what the responding ARL libraries are doing, rather than an in-depth
                  perspective on the day-to-day of faculty research lives of doing digital
                  scholarship.</p>
               <p>The digital humanities, as a field, holds interest for scholars because it is
                  still in the process of defining itself as a technologically oriented discipline
                  (and is even currently in the process of being questioned about whether it is a
                  field, or a methodology, or a passing fad). Marija Dalbello outlines the
                  chronological development of the field of digital humanities, taking as evidence
                  the facts that it has its own journals (<title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                     Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly)</title>,
                  conference (called simply Digital Humanities), and body of literature <ptr
                     target="#dalbello2011"/>. Dalbello emphasizes the relevance of digital library
                  development to DH scholarship, by focusing on text analysis and digitization as
                  digital humanities practice as opposed to non-text-based activities like
                  geospatial analysis.</p>
               <p>Librarians have been interested in digital humanities research since its emergence
                  from humanities computing in the early part of the century, particularly within
                  the context of the universities that are part of the Center for Institutional
                  Cooperation (CIC) collaborative. CIC is home to three major DH centers: MATRIX at
                  Michigan State University, CDRH at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, and the
                  Institute for Computing in the Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences (I-CHASS) at
                  the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, as well as more grassroots DH
                  initiatives at other CIC schools (which could include lab spaces within humanities
                  departments and libraries, seminar series, etc.). Blossoming activity in CIC
                  universities has foreshadowed more explicit collaboration that now seems to be
                  emerging.</p>
               <p>CIC held its first Digital Humanities Summit at University of Nebraska-Lincoln in
                  spring 2012, when sixty faculty, librarians, and administrators as participants
                  gathered to compare the status of digital humanities activities in member
                  universities. One major recommendation of the 2012 summit was to recruit the
                  highest quality faculty and graduate students to CIC institutions for digital
                  research. In order to do this, the committee recommends that non-traditional,
                  digital scholarship should be weighted as equal when making tenure decisions, as
                  they found that many faculty did not engage in digital humanities work until after
                  they achieved tenure. The important roles that libraries play in supporting DH
                  scholarship are mentioned in the report numerous times. Besides becoming
                  increasingly responsible for disseminating open access scholarship, the CIC notes
                  that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#cic2012">we also need to acknowledge the
                        importance of interdisciplinary and collaborative work — a norm in digital
                        scholarship. Some of the best digital work is conducted in team of scholars,
                        librarians, technologists, and students (both graduate and
                        undergraduate)</quote>
                     <ptr target="#cic2012" loc="7"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The CIC report also states that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#cic2012">scholars, librarians, archivists, and
                        technologists should be partners in digital initiatives current
                        accessibility and future sustainability</quote>
                     <ptr target="#cic2012" loc="1"/>
                  </cit>. In digital scholarship literature, libraries are often mentioned in the
                  context of preserving or facilitating access to digital scholarship, but not
                  taking part in the scholarship itself. Andrew W. Mellon Foundation program officer
                  Donald Waters identifies universities, their libraries, and academic presses as
                  should-be supporters of digital humanities work: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#waters2013">Going forward — as centers of
                        humanistic research and teaching-universities, their libraries, and academic
                        presses must support the digital humanities, but where should they place
                        their emphasis? I would suggest, first, that it is critically important that
                        they be alert to the particular strands of research being pursued</quote>
                     <ptr target="#waters2013" loc="8"/>
                  </cit>. This issue of being <q>alert</q> to the types of research being pursued on
                  campuses indeed came up in the findings of this study.</p>
               <p>Libraries have indeed taken up the pursuit of being hubs for digital humanities
                  research and collaboration. Jennifer Vinopal and Monica McCormick have addressed
                  the main challenges in developing infrastructure for digital scholarship support,
                  including defining priorities, staffing, ongoing organizational change, and beyond
                     <ptr target="#vinopal2013"/>. They propose a four-tiered model, ranging from
                  academic and administrative tool support, the most widely used, to grant-funded
                  research, with institutional repositories, copyright consultation, and bulk data
                  loads sitting in between. Based on these different levels of support, they note
                  that librarians must engage with the entire research process more than ever
                  before.</p>
               <p>Miriam Posner has written extensively (on Twitter, her blog, and in scholarly
                  journals) on the challenges of supporting digital humanities in the library <ptr
                     target="#posner2013"/>. As with Vinopal and McCormick, Posner points out that
                  often the support for digital scholarship must be built out of and around the
                  library’s core mission, be part of a strategic vision, and have support from
                  library leadership. If supporting that type of work is a <q>distraction</q> from a
                  particular library’s core values, then perhaps it is not in the best interest of
                  the library. Posner also notes tensions about service vs. servitude and the
                  tension around whether librarians have equal status with faculty in fostering
                  digital humanities scholarship. Building on Vinopal and McCormick’s thoughts on
                  infrastructure, and Waters’ urging that institutional bodies be aware of
                  particular research strands, Posner contends that librarians must be knowledgeable
                  as humanists: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#posner2013">Many of the problems we have faced
                        ‘supporting’ digital humanities work may stem from the fact that digital
                        humanities projects in general do not need supporters — they need
                        collaborators. Libraries need to provide infrastructure (access to
                        digitization tools and servers, for example) to support digital humanities
                        work, but they need thoughtful, skilled, knowledgeable humanists to actually
                        work on it</quote>
                     <ptr target="#posner2013" loc="45"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>Previous research has been done on faculty-librarian coordination. After surveying
                  the literature on faculty and instructional librarians, Kate Manuel, Susan E.
                  Beck, and Molly Molloy found that faculty consider librarians to be more service
                  providers than teachers <ptr target="#manuel2005"/>. Reasons ranged from faculty
                  not considering librarians to be their academic equals to disbelief that
                  librarians had enough subject expertise in their area, particularly the sciences.
                  In a stark contrast to the literature the authors cited, the professors they
                  interviewed were enthusiastic about and had deep respect for their institution’s
                  librarians. In fact, one of the reasons they asked librarians to do instruction in
                  their classroom was because of the idea of librarian as <q>expert witness.</q>
                  Librarians served as outside influence for students, emphasizing and giving more
                  credibility to the professors; they also show another part of the research
                  universe of which the students are a part. Work has also been done on
                  collaboration of research teams doing digital research. Siemens found that,
                  through individual interviews with members of research teams and surveys to
                  digital humanities listservs, humanities research is growing more complex and
                  technologically sophisticated, so it often requires a team approach — sometimes
                  between scholars and librarians <ptr target="#siemens2011"/>. Librarians have
                  information management skills that are useful to DH researchers; however,
                  librarians do not want their values of public service to be confused with
                  servitude. </p>
               <p>More recently, there have been more voices speaking against the idea of librarians
                  as service providers from the library side. Trevor Muñoz has written specifically
                  on the problem of calling digital humanities a <q>service</q> in academic
                  libraries, along with the problems of identifying academic labor and power
                  balances in the academy <ptr target="#muñoz2012"/>. Micah Vandegrift and Stewart
                  Varner have made bolder claims, including that librarians <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#vandegrift2013">need to proudly identify
                        themselves as DHers, and fully expect to be regarded as such by peers,
                        colleagues, faculty and administrators, and let the broad work they do
                        engage with that community</quote>
                     <ptr target="#vandegrift2013" loc="76"/>
                  </cit>. The aim of this research project is to test the real-world implications of
                  that claim.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Methodology </head>

            <p>This research project aims to build on, and further refine, the work done in the
               Association of Research Libraries (ARL) SPEC Kit 326: Digital Humanities (2011). The
               participants are from the Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) libraries, for
               several reasons: first, to build on and to sample a different population from the ARL
               SPEC Kit 326 survey population, and second, because there are major digital
               humanities centers within the CIC (e.g. MATRIX at Michigan State University, Center
               for Digital Research in the Humanities at University of Nebraska Lincoln, University
               of Maryland’s Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities), as well as the
               fact that the CIC itself has declared their desire to be known for DH <ptr
                  target="#cic2012"/>. The population for this project is academic librarians
               (and/or academic support staff, postdoctoral researchers, etc. who work in an
               academic library setting) and faculty members who identify as doing some type of
               digital scholarship, digital humanities, or humanities computing type of research in
               the United States. Because of this rather specific population, and the exploratory
               nature of this project, the researcher used purposive sampling to individually
               identify suitable participants <note>The researcher acknowledges, as a potentially
                  limiting factor, that interviewees may have felt the need to give responses that
                  the interviewer wanted to hear as a graduate student researcher, especially
                  because they were, to some degree, familiar with the researcher's positive
                  interest in the digital humanities and her background in libraries.</note>. </p>
            <p>It must also be noted that the relationship between faculty and librarians at CIC
               schools may not be representative of the relationship between faculty and librarians
               at all academic institutions. The CIC is made up of large, public research
               institutions that have different resources from, for example, a small private liberal
               arts college. The course loads and teaching expectations may be different for both
               faculty and librarians at these different types of institutions and may influence the
               relationship between these groups.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Research Questions </head>
            <p>This project was designed to identify points of convergence and tease out any
               tensions that exist in faculty-librarian relationships in digital humanities research
               projects. The following questions guided the research, to that end:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>What are the unique needs of digital humanities scholars in terms of research
                  support?</item>
               <item>What do faculty and academic librarians expect of each other in the realm of
                  digital scholarship?<list type="ordered">
                     <item>in terms of physical space, technology, and collections, and the ways in
                        which each are used?</item>
                  </list></item>
               <item>For librarians whose work is related to digital scholarship, is collaborating
                  on research with scholars, faculty, or students more important, or is providing
                     <q>service(s)</q> — the more traditional support role of librarians?<list
                     type="ordered">
                     <item>Are there common underlying tensions in librarian-scholar relationships,
                        such as that of service vs. servitude?</item>
                  </list></item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Data Gathering Methods</head>
            <p>In order to get the nuanced, individual perspectives of both faculty and librarians,
               this research study utilized semi-structured telephone, Google Hangout, or Skype
               interviews to explore the collaborative relationship between faculty and academic
               librarians when doing digital humanities research, including attitudes toward
               collaborating with or supporting others. Similar but distinctive interview protocols
               were developed for a librarian/academic staff group and a faculty group. </p>
            <p>Given the emergent nature of the discipline, there are limited numbers of librarians
               in the United States who are explicitly charged with digital humanities liaison
               responsibility, not to mention a limited number of higher education institutions
               engaging in digital humanities activities. To identify interview subjects, the
               researcher performed targeted research via directories on institutional websites,
               scholarly blogs, Twitter, DH listservs, and so on to identify individuals with
               digital humanities or digital scholarships titles, as well as welcome references from
               participants. After identifying participants, the researcher sent individual email
               requests for interviews. The interviews were recorded for audio for later
               transcription. </p>
            <p>The researcher developed, tested, and used two different interview protocols: one for
               the faculty participants and one for the librarian/staff participants. Separate
               interview protocols were necessary in order to obtain the best data from the two
               different groups — while some questions were similar, such as the questions about
               preferred terms for digital humanities, others were different in order to get a
               representation of each person's individual outlook, experiences, and opinions.
               Questions included preferred terms and definitions, faculty expectations of their
               institution and their library, how librarians expected DH scholars to use the
               library, library outreach and planning for DH activities, and the needed expertise on
               the parts of both faculty and librarians/staff. The interviews were conducted in
               March 2014.</p>
            <p>The goal in recruiting participants for this project was to have one
               faculty-librarian pair from as many of the CIC institutions as possible. Gathering
               data from faculty-librarian pairs from several different schools would give even more
               nuanced insight into these collaborative relationships, and the perspectives each
               group holds, because they are on the same campus and are participating in the same
               activities. The interviews were conducted individually, allowing for open-ended
               questions, the opportunity for spontaneous follow-up questions tailored to each
               participant, and for different topics to come up that the researcher may not have
               been aware of as being important. Qualitative interviews are useful for revealing
               emotional information — such as questions about working relationships between faculty
               scholars and librarians, tensions, and the desire to be a collaborator or a service
               provider.</p>
            <p>The interviews were recorded, transcribed, and analyzed for overarching patterns and
               themes, which were categorized and named. The researcher analyzed the interview
               responses for similar patterns in faculty’s and librarians’ responses: are they aware
               of each others’ expectations, or is there a disconnect in perceptions? Do librarians
               identify as scholars, or <q>customer service professionals</q>? What do faculty
               consider the most important when it comes to librarian expertise, and what do
               librarians identify as critical in being able to engage with DH work on campus?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Findings</head>
            <div>
               <head>Demographics</head>
               <p>The study included 11 people: 5 faculty, 4 librarians, and 2 postdoctoral
                  researchers, positioned in the library and thus included in the <q>library</q>
                  group. The faculty members held appointments in the following academic
                  departments: English, History, Rhetoric, Philosophy, and Classics. One faculty
                  member also served as a curator faculty member also served as a curator in the
                  university’s museum. Of the 11 participants, there were four pairs, leaving one
                  faculty member and the two library-affiliated postdocs as <q>single</q>
                  participants.</p>
               <p>The findings are detailed in five sections: I), the best model for engaging DH
                  scholars, II), what domain expertise is needed, III), the areas in which faculty
                  and librarians agree, IV), the areas in which they disagree (tensions), and
                  finally, V), where the two groups have a perceptual disconnect. From the data
                  analysis, two overarching themes emerged: tensions and agreement between the two
                  groups. Within and related to those two themes, there are several sub themes: best
                  practices for digital humanities librarians, domain expertise, and disconnects.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>I. Best Model for Engagement of Digital Humanities Scholars</head>
               <p>One of the questions posed to the library-affiliated group was <q>How are you or your team engaging with DH scholarship
                     on your campus?</q> in order to explore the expectations faculty and
                  librarians hold for themselves and each other. The most successful model for DH
                  engagement for libraries seems to be actively going out on to campus. This is not
                  to say that having a <q>center</q> or a lab where scholars can come in and ask
                  questions is ineffective, but most of the schools in this research project do not
                  have a definitive digital humanities center. </p>
               <p>Of the six librarian participants, most detailed a case-by-case or consultative
                  approach, noting that some collaborations happened organically: one librarian said
                  that it was about <said>making yourself available to people. Go to colloquia, go
                     to brownbags, go to events; invite people to events at the library, think about
                     creating events where you can have people from different departments be on a
                     panel...All of those things have been successful for us in outreach.</said> The
                  lack of a robust workflow also played into the consultation model. Another
                  librarian described their process as <said>a scholar comes to me or someone in the
                     [office] or to someone they know who has the expertise and then we pull
                     together the team who would be needed for that project. We’re hoping to get a
                     better workflow together. They come to the library with help for metadata and
                     collections, but then they go [somewhere else on campus] when they need the
                     computing power.</said></p>
               <p>There were mixed statements among the librarians about either working to bring
                  scholars back into the library or going to their departments. One participant
                  talked about the library’s delivery service to offices and labs, which keeps
                  scholars from having to come in; that library is looking into redeveloping or
                  expanding library space to bring faculty back and to develop working relationships
                  with them. Other librarian participants stated that they had the most success in
                  going to different departmental events, <said>seeing what kinds of questions
                     people had,</said> or hosting library events outside of the library, with one
                  emphasizing that <said>my concern is that we’re involved in the research.</said>
                  The concern about librarians being familiar with the scholarship will be addressed
                  in the following sections.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>II. Domain Expertise</head>
               <p>Other questions on both the faculty and the librarian protocols involved needed
                  expertise for digital humanities research and expertise for supporting DH
                  research. Several people, both faculty and librarians, mentioned programming and
                  coding knowledge. There was not a general consensus on whether or not one
                  absolutely needs to be able to program: one faculty member felt strongly that
                  everyone should know how to code, while other faculty members pushed against that.
                  From the anecdotal evidence that the librarians provided it seems that there are
                  varying degrees of technical expertise in the library, but that it is quite
                  substantial. More broadly, this is connected with other domain knowledge: several
                  faculty brought up the importance of librarians being familiar with their field,
                  though not necessarily having secondary degrees in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>IIa. Programming Expertise</head>
               <p> One faculty participant firmly believed that <q>everyone</q> should learn
                  programming, that it is an essential skill, that it is flexible and can be applied
                  to many different things. However, the other four faculty interviewees spoke less
                  strongly about the need for coding expertise — they noted that they did not have
                  time to learn, or would rather spend that time on more humanistic research, or
                  even that they were <soCalled>builders,</soCalled>
                  in the Ramsay sense <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>, by doing community building
                  rather than technical building. Another faculty participant said that <said>I
                     don’t know that it’s necessary for librarians to have high-level technical
                     coding abilities... I think some great librarians are ones that can connect
                     people to those that have that [programming] ability,</said> recognizing that
                  one of librarians’ skills is the ability to identify and refer users to a more
                  relevant person. Other technical skills that both the scholars and librarians
                  possessed that were not programming skills were XML, XSLT, TEI, and other markup
                  languages. Others also stated that being open to learning new digital techniques
                  was important, as was the ability to understand code without having to learn
                  various programming languages.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>IIb. Academic Expertise</head>
               <p>One faculty interviewee spoke particularly highly of his institution’s librarian
                  pair, most notably because the librarian also held an advanced degree in the
                  faculty member’s subject area; this, combined with his library science degree,
                  made collaborating on projects more productive, easier, and more enjoyable.
                  However, several scholar participants stressed that it is not a requirement for
                  librarians to have additional advanced degrees in humanities disciplines. One
                  faculty respondent noted that <said>you need to know the kinds of questions to ask
                     your faculty to know what would help facilitate work in their
                  research.</said></p>
               <p> Speaking on both academic and programming expertise, another scholar interviewee
                  stated that <said>I don’t think librarians have to become programmers. I think, in
                     a way, they need to become better humanities scholars. Just in the sense of
                     asking questions… the thing I worry about is the model of the customer-service
                     provider will dominate and replace the idea of the librarian being someone to
                     engage in intellectual inquiry with.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>III. Faculty-Librarian Consensus</head>
               <p>Two topics came up repeatedly about which all participants seemed to agree:
                  scholars’ needs for metadata and special collections. There were several questions
                  for both groups that asked how scholars make use of the library, with probes for
                  uses of physical space, technology, and collections. One librarian mentioned that
                  scholars are using rare materials more frequently, especially when the material is
                  something not found in Google Books; she also predicted that rare materials will
                  be used <said>more actively</said> in the future. A faculty interviewee responded
                  that <said>we don’t use collections, but we do use expertise [of librarians]. We
                     have a good special collections librarian that we’ve worked with over the
                     years...for digitizing.</said> Every participant brought up special collections
                  as a way they make use of the library, or, on the librarians’ side, the way they
                  expect faculty to use the library. Special collections serve as a main entry point
                  for both faculty and students, because they are comprised of physical items for
                  which scholars must consult librarians, or students must in order to gain access.
                  In terms of collaboration in digital scholarship, this is both a boon and a bane:
                  rare physical objects that the library holds brings researchers into the physical
                  library, to interact with library staff, but it also means that scholars whose
                  work does not involve rare materials may never go into the physical library or
                  work with a librarian or library collections. One librarian participant spoke
                  about how his library is working to support scholars’ use of rare materials beyond
                  just having them available (i.e. digitizing rare materials), though he noted that
                     <said>this isn’t the most common use of the library</said>: <quote rend="block"
                     source="#private"> Special collections are different [from other library collections]
                     because there are people interested in either literature of previous centuries,
                     or history, or history of book, material culture around the book; those are
                     people who find their way to special collections. There are a few people in
                     English and History who have strong interest in having more collections in some
                     digital form to use, manipulate, what have you… what can we do to support that?
                     Do we have software, technology?... faculty want digitized material [including
                     digitized letters for a historical project]. </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, digitization was brought up by multiple participants. Within one
                  faculty-librarian pair, each brought up working with the other on the faculty’s
                  digital history course. In fact, both mentioned that that particular course was
                  what sparked an ongoing relationship between the department and the library.
                  Special collections librarians, archivists, and digital librarians worked with
                  students to digitize and use rare materials. </p>
               <p>Digital humanities scholars’ use of metadata was another area that both interview
                  groups agreed was a valuable asset for the library to support and provide
                  services. One faculty participant said that <said>the humanities tend to use
                     metadata...quite extensively, but they really don’t understand it, they don’t
                     understand data modeling and best practices... One of the things that is needed
                     to be successful in DH is to start with really solid infrastructure and really
                     good data plans; it doesn’t matter if you’re working with media, text, what
                     have you. Libraries have been indispensable partners.</said> The study
                  participants at the other institutions tended to agree with that statement, at
                  least to the extent that having good data is important, being able to understand
                  your data is important, and that librarians have the expertise in that area.
                  Several librarian interviewees brought up individuals going to the library for
                  help with metadata; the metadata librarians assisted with that. Librarians also
                  facilitated access to and provided training in analyzing metadata; one faculty
                  participant stated that the librarians were, in fact, training him in how to use
                  MARC records, which were central to his research.</p>
               <p>In fact, several participants in the library group are responding to that need for
                  metadata and metadata training by planning workshops and training sessions for the
                  coming academic year, as well as working to promote the library’s own metadata and
                     <said>making it available for humanists to do computational analysis on large
                     parts of the collection,</said> as one librarian said. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>IV. Tensions</head>
               <p>As Geoffrey Rockwell has noted: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#rockwell2013">one of the sites of [stress] in the
                        digital humanities has been the inclusion of those alternative academics
                        without faculty jobs</quote>
                     <ptr target="#rockwell2013"/>
                  </cit>. He traces the inclusion of non-faculty researchers — such as librarians —
                  to the beginnings of digital humanities and the inclusive nature of the community.
                  While digital humanities as a community still prides itself on that inclusiveness,
                  there remains tension around librarians participating as scholars alongside
                  faculty. It is important to note that none of the five faculty participants
                  espoused first-hand opinions about librarians or staff not <q>belonging</q> in the
                  digital humanities community, or on digital scholarship research teams. However,
                  one faculty interviewee talked at length about the phenomenon of heavy library
                  representation at DH seminars, which causes faculty and graduate students to not
                  show up — because they do not think it is <said>meant</said> for scholars such as
                  themselves: <quote rend="block" source="#private">We’ve held a reading seminar and it’s
                     been held at the humanities institute on campus. Most of the research reading
                     seminars tend to attract almost exclusively professors and graduate students.
                     However, the DH reading seminar has attracted many, many librarians and
                     technologists, sometimes more so than professors and grad students. That’s been
                     great, but I think it’s raised some unwritten hierarchies at the university. My
                     impression is the more librarians and technologists come, the fewer faculty and
                     graduate students come. They arrive… and see there aren’t people from their
                     immediate circle of colleagues. The librarians… ask some different questions.
                     There’s been a real challenge in working across the boundaries of training and
                     perspective in one group.</quote>
               </p>
               <p>Other faculty respondents noted the need for librarians to be more aware of the
                  types of humanities questions that are going on in their fields, as stated above
                  in section IIb on academic expertise. This seems to reinforce the earlier-quoted
                  participant on working <said>across the boundaries of training and
                     perspective.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>V. Faculty-Librarian Disconnect</head>
               <p>Throughout the interviews with faculty members it became clear that they were
                  operating under the possible fallacy that digital humanities has <q>arrived</q> at
                  the library, but not yet in the humanities departments. All were extremely
                  enthusiastic about and spoke very highly of the librarians they have worked with
                  on DH projects. One said that <said>I really prefer to think of my colleagues in
                     the library as partners than as resources… The people I work with in the
                     library are really smart, they usually know more about what’s current in DH
                     than I do, because I’m set in my own research.</said> This reveals the
                  potential for digital scholarship librarians to be specialists in DH support and a
                  resource for a broad, current overview of the DH field. A librarian participant
                  enthused that <said>we are much more collaborators and researchers than just the
                     point person for <q>get me this book or resource.</q> So, it’s an exciting
                     transition, we’re being welcomed, really, onto these research teams, and we
                     have a lot to contribute. I think all librarians should at least dip a toe into
                     exploring [digital humanities].</said></p>
               <p>This statement reflects a clearly positive attitude: faculty consider librarians
                  research partners and colleagues, they see sustainability in librarians providing
                  training to scholars and graduate students, and even view iSchools (schools that
                  have evolved from programs previously centered around library and information
                  science, informatics, and others) as hubs for DH activity and training. On the
                  library side, however, the librarians expressed that DH is not (yet) a unified
                  effort of the library. One librarian noted that collaboration is really just
                  getting started at his institution; another spoke on subject librarians wanting or
                  even needing to engage with DH work with their faculty but lacking the time for
                  training in it. Part of the reason for this, he went on, is that there is no
                     <q>top-down</q> initiative that would provide subject liaisons or other
                  librarians the time and space in their job for digital scholarship training. Also,
                  there was some disconnect in one particular pair about the <q>willingness</q> with
                  which the library is embracing DH and its maturity: the faculty member saw the
                  library as unified and enthusiastic about digital scholarship. He felt that
                     <said>there doesn’t seem to be the backlash against DH as such, it seems that
                     there’s a culture, they [the library] recognize that it’s a culture, they
                     recognize that it’s its own set of disciplinary expectations. It’s a much more
                     mature discipline to librarians that it is often to the faculty,</said> and
                  that his institution’s library was already well-organized and had a
                  well-established definition for digital scholarship work: <said>There seems to be
                     reticence to fully embrace DH on the part of humanities faculty. On the library
                     side, there’s a huge interest in and willingness to embrace DH as the moniker
                     under which we do our work.</said> However, his librarian pair was much more
                  cautious in declaring any unified efforts in digital humanities, as such, at his
                  library.</p>
               <p>Another faculty participant did realize and mention that <said>librarians aren’t
                     appreciated for their expertise as real scholars,</said> but sees DH as a space
                  where rank doesn’t matter — making it natural for librarians to work in that
                  space. Notably, another librarian participant was most aligned with the faculty
                  enthusiasm for the maturity of digital humanities support in libraries, but he
                  specifically brought up not seeing that support as a service vs. collaboration
                  dichotomy: his institution models it as a spectrum of
                  collection-instruction-consultation-collaboration, rather than reducing DH support
                  infrastructure to service provider or partner. This participant also eschewed that
                  support vs. collaborator distinction as unproductive: <said>You have someone come
                     in [to the library], they have a research question already, they might ask if
                     you want to collaborate… it [happens organically]... We’ve found that
                     consultation often turns into collaboration. Similarly, instruction turns into
                     consultation for the faculty you taught the class for, which can lead to
                     collaboration.</said></p>
               <p>However, it is important to recognize the issues around collaboration in
                  humanities disciplines. One faculty participant brought up the stigma against
                  multiple authors in humanities scholarship, saying that <said>[I wouldn’t want to
                     say] that the most important thing for a librarian is to be a collaborator,
                     then throw them into the situation where it’s hard for them to find someone to
                     collaborate with. We need to work on the institutional side to credential
                     effectively collaborative work… they do it in social sciences, why can’t we do
                     it in the humanities? ...the humanities don’t do much to incentivize
                     collaboration.</said></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>As one faculty participant noted, there seems to be a natural affinity between the
               digital humanities and librarians: <said>There’s often a sense where librarians
                  aren’t appreciated for their expertise as real scholars, and I think that’s often
                  true of the digital humanities. There tends not to be as much focus on rank and
                  where you’re at [in digital humanities], it’s more the expertise you bring to the
                  table.</said> The results of this study, especially the finding that faculty see
               DH support infrastructure in libraries as more established and mature than it
               realistically is, will aid academic librarians and library staff in strategic
               planning around the digital humanities. This could include more strategic outreach,
               making the strengths of digital scholarship/digital humanities/digital initiatives
               librarians more explicitly known, hosting more events outside of the library, and so
               on. Conversely, it could also take the form that one librarian participant detailed:
               not necessarily a <q>DH center</q>, but creating offices or residencies for faculty
               to bring them back into the library, beyond providing special collections services.
               It may also prove enlightening to digital humanities faculty in approaching their
               respective librarians both for support for projects (i.e. using library collections,
               learning to use metadata, specialized workshops) and as potential collaborators.
               Scholars have the space to have a more active voice in shaping their library's
               digital humanities support; in fact, librarians often welcome their faculty taking an
               active stance in using and/or requesting library resources in the DH space.</p>
            <p>A compelling point that arose from one interview was one librarian’s 4-tier model for
               supporting digital scholarship, while simultaneously moving away from the arguably
               unproductive dichotomy of librarians as collaborators versus supporters. As described
               earlier, the four tiers include collection, instruction, consultation, and
               collaboration. Professors might approach librarians to use collections, to use
               collections for teaching, or they might ask for consultation on using collections or
               tools for their own research. Any of these paths might lead organically to
               collaboration between faculty and non-faculty scholars, based on individual research
               interests and expertise. This is a useful model to think about digital scholarship
               support without the equally unproductive polarization of whether or not a library
               needs a DH center. There are also implications for librarian training and
               re-skilling. Multiple librarians brought up the time it takes to learn enough about
               digital scholarship to be able to answer scholars’ questions, especially in regard to
               subject librarians. One participant mentioned the development of <said>demystifying
                  DH</said> sessions for librarians.  However, that is beyond the scope of this
               project; gathering the thoughts, anxieties, and successes of subject liaisons in
               supporting their departments’ needs in digital scholarship would be helpful to
               librarians’ understanding of how to position themselves to support DH work. </p>
            <p>Several faculty participants commented on the tensions around interdisciplinary
               collaboration. As one participant said, <said>there’s a lot of distrust between
                  different disciplines and schools...the payoff is not that much to do
                  interdisciplinary work if you’re embedded in different departments. The way it’s
                  set up is to not encourage collaboration across boundaries.</said> This In regards
               to the comments of one faculty participant on the problems of working across
               departments and different schools within his institution, and that collaboration is
               not encouraged: this problem could be tempered by his librarian pair’s success in
               engaging DH scholars by going out on to campus, his opinion that events should
               behosting more library events happening outside of the library, and librarians going
               directly to the scholars, etc. In cases where there are problems of disciplinary
                  <q>silos,</q> there could be potential for the library and librarians to foster
               some cross-departmental work in the same way that this participant has. In fact, that
               particular faculty interviewee expressed excitement over the library as a place for
               engagement with the digital, and not a <said>customer service model.</said> He said
               that librarians have a different perspective in creating an environment for scholarly
               work, and that his library has <said>been a good neutral space for sidestepping some
                  of the turf battles and get down to the research they’re interested in.</said></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>As Schaffner and Erway have suggested, there is currently much to be figured out in
               how research libraries should position themselves to support digital scholarship and
               digital humanities <ptr target="#schaffner2014"/>. Several approaches are utilized at
               the moment: the ad hoc, consultative approach — which the majority of participants in
               this study advocated — or a one-size-fits-all suite of services. One of the original
               driving questions behind this project was whether faculty need and want individuals
               who are research partners and co-investigators on projects, or whether they prefer ad
               hoc services. The answer is not on either side of that line, but rather on both
               sides: librarians and library staff can provide ad hoc DH services while also being
               research partners; in fact, several participants reported that their partnerships
               were the result of an initial consultation with a librarian that grew into lengthier
               collaborations.</p>
            <p>For future research, it may be worthwhile to do paired faculty/librarian interviews
               both at universities that have an <q>official</q> digital humanities center and at
               universities that do not, and measure whether there is correlation between an
               institution having a DH center and the ways the faculty think of librarians and the
               library’s potential for support. If a school has no digital humanities center, then
               often the humanities departments are unaware of the digitally-related services that
               their library offers. The nature of the school — public or private, large or small,
               research- or teaching-oriented — would be another interesting factor to include. As
               noted in the Methodology section, these findings may not be applicable to all
               faculty-librarian relationships outside of the CIC. Several CIC schools have
               well-established DH centers, and accordingly those schools have had more time to
               negotiate partnerships and collaboration styles. Another theme that emerged from this
               project was the need to study curriculum around digital humanities. Surprisingly,
               though there were no interview questions specifically about teaching, many
               participants talked about changing or <said>overhauling</said> the curriculum, or
               about using the library in their digital humanities courses. However, it was unclear
               whether course content was tied to faculty’s research. There is more work to be done
               in this area.</p>
            <p>Much of these anxieties about the role of librarians in digital research could very
               well be tied to conversations about the future of libraries themselves. Indeed, a
               scholar participant brought this up independently, shining a light on why libraries
               are prime locations not just for digital humanities research, but for new media
               studies and digital scholarship — a broad umbrella: <said>The library seems like this
                  amazing place, this building with people in it, a central location on campus, it
                  has lots of books in it… what an amazing place to situate the exploration of
                  what’s good about the digital, what does the digital not do?</said></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>I would like to acknowledge the generous participation from the librarians, faculty,
               and postdoctoral researchers who graciously took the time to be interviewed for this
               study. I would also like to thank Associate Professor Paul Conway at the University
               of Michigan School of Information for his thoughtful comments, guidance, assistance,
               and advice in shaping this study.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix: Interview Protocols</head>
            <div>
               <head>FACULTY</head>
               <p>1. What is your title? What department are you a part of?</p>
               <p>2. Do you have any other appointments in other departments?</p>
               <p>3. From the reading I’ve done in DH, I’ve come across many different terms and
                  definitions. At the U-M School of Information we use “digital humanities.” How do
                  you define DH and what terms do you use at your institution?</p>
               <p>4. What do you expect of your institution in terms of support for DH research?</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>What do you expect of the library?</item>
                  <item>What about library space, technology, and collections?</item>
                  <item>Do you have a DH center?</item>
                  <item>Based on your answer, do you see this as an extension of things already
                     happening, or something new?</item>
               </list>
               <p>5. Have you been involved in DH planning at your institution, in the last year or
                  so?</p>
               <p>6. From my understanding, it takes a lot of expertise to do DH research. What
                  expertise is needed for your work?</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>What do you see as the library’s role?</item>
               </list>
               <p>7. My reading suggests that libraries could support DH in a number of ways…</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>What expertise do librarians need? Is it more DIY or just dividing up the
                     labor?</item>
                  <item>Which role is most important for librarians when it comes to digital
                     humanities in the library: collaborator or service provider?</item>
               </list>
               <p>8. Anything else you’d like to add?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>LIBRARIAN</head>
               <p>1. What is your job title?</p>
               <p>2. What do the reporting lines look like for your position? Do you hold any other
                  appointments?</p>
               <p>3. From the reading I’ve done in DH, I’ve come across many different terms and
                  definitions. At the U-M School of Information we use “digital humanities.” How do
                  you define DH and what terms do you use at your institution?</p>
               <p>4. How do you expect faculty to make use of your physical space, technology, and
                  collections?</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Do you have a DH center?</item>
                  <item>Based on your answer, do you see this as an extension of things already
                     happening, or something new?</item>
               </list>
               <p>5. Is digital humanities part of your library’s strategic plan?</p>
               <p>6. What, if any, activities are planned in the next fiscal year for DH at your
                  library?</p>
               <p>7. How is your library thinking about digital humanities? What activities,
                  training, new hires, or outreach are you planning, if any?</p>
               <p>8. How are you or your team engaging with DH scholarship on your campus?</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Have you hosted a meeting for DH scholars at the library?</item>
                  <item>Have there been any staff workshops or any DH conferences attended?</item>
               </list>
               <p>9. Anything else you’d like to add?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Bryson, Posner, St. Pierre, and Varner 2011" xml:id="bryson2011"
               >Association of Research Libraries. <title rend="none">SPEC Kit 326: Digital
                  Humanities.</title> Tim Bryson, Miriam Posner, Alain St. Pierre, and Stewart
               Varner (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Burgess and Hamming 2011" xml:id="burgess2011">Burgess, H. J. and Hamming,
               J. <title rend="quotes">New Media in the Academy: Labor and the Production of
                  Knowledge in Scholarly Multimedia.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 5.3 (2011). <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000102/000102.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000102/000102.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="CIC 2012" xml:id="cic2012">CIC DIGITAL HUMANITIES SUMMIT REPORT: Executive
               Summary (2012). <ref
                  target="https://u.osu.edu/ulman.1/files/2012/10/CIC-DH-Report-Sept-2012-Final.pdf"
                  >https://u.osu.edu/ulman.1/files/2012/10/CIC-DH-Report-Sept-2012-Final.pdf</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Dalbello 2011" xml:id="dalbello2011"> Dalbello, M. <title rend="quotes">A
                  genealogy of digital humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 67.3 (2011): 480. doi
               10.1108/00220411111124550</bibl>
            <bibl label="Fitzpatrick 2010" xml:id="fitzpatrick2010">Fitzpatrick, K. <title
                  rend="quotes">Reporting from the Digital Humanities 2010 Conference.</title>
               ProfHacker (2010). <ref
                  target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/reporting-from-the-digital-humanities-2010-conference/25473"
                  >http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/reporting-from-the-digital-humanities-2010-conference/25473</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2010" xml:id="kirschenbaum2010">Kirschenbaum, M. G. <title
                  rend="quotes">What is Digital Humanities and What’s it Doing in English
                  Departments?</title> ADE Bulletin 150 (2010): 55-61.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Manuel, Beck, and Molloy 2005" xml:id="manuel2005">Manuel, K., Beck, S.E.,
               and Molloy, M. <title rend="quotes">An ethnographic study of attitudes influencing
                  faculty collaboration in library instruction.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Reference Librarian</title> 43.89-90 (2005): 139.
               doi:10.1300/J120v43n89_10</bibl>
            <bibl label="Muñoz 2012" xml:id="muñoz2012">Muñoz, T. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                  humanities in the library isn't a service</title> (2012). <ref
                  target="http://trevormunoz.com/notebook/2012/08/19/doing-dh-in-the-library.html"
                  >http://trevormunoz.com/notebook/2012/08/19/doing-dh-in-the-library.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Posner 2013" xml:id="posner2013">Posner, M. <title rend="quotes">No half
                  measures: Overcoming common challenges to doing digital humanities in the
                  library.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title> 53.1 (2013):
               43-52.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ramsay 2011" xml:id="ramsay2011">Ramsay, S. <title rend="quotes">On
                  Building</title> (2011). <ref
                  target="http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/11/on-building/"
                  >http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/11/on-building/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Rockwell 2013" xml:id="rockwell2013">Rockwell, G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Inclusion in the Digital Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">Defining
                  Digital Humanities: A Reader</title>, ed. Melissa M. Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and
               Edward Vanhoutte. 249-253. Ashgate Publishing , Farnham, Surrey, England; Burlington,
               VT (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Rumsey 2011" xml:id="rumsey2011">Rumsey, A. S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >New-Model Scholarly Communication: Road Map for Change.</title> Scholarly
               Communication Institute 9 (2011). <ref
                  target="http://www.uvasci.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/SCI9-report.pdf"
                  >http://www.uvasci.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/SCI9-report.pdf</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Schaffner and Erway 2014" xml:id="schaffner2014">Schaffner, J., and Erway,
               R. <title rend="none">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital Humanities
                  Center?</title> Dublin, Ohio: OCLC Research (2014). <ref
                  target="http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf"
                  >http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf</ref>
               (Accessed April 11th, 2014).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Siemens, Cunningham, Duff, and Warwick" xml:id="siemens2011">Siemens, L.,
               Cunningham, R., Duff, W. and Warwick, C. <title rend="quotes">A tale of two cities:
                  Implications of the similarities and differences in collaborative approaches
                  within the digital libraries and digital humanities communities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 26.3 (2011): 335.
               doi:10.1093/llc/fqr028</bibl>
            <bibl label="Vandegrift and Varner 2013" xml:id="vandegrift2013">Vandegrift, M., and
               Varner, S. <title rend="quotes">Evolving in common: Creating mutually supportive
                  relationships between libraries and the digital humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title> 53.1 (2013):
               67.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Vinopal and McCormick 2013" xml:id="vinopal2013">Vinopal, J., and
               McCormick, M. <title rend="quotes">Supporting digital scholarship in research
                  libraries: Scalability and sustainability.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title> 53.1 (2013):
               27.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Waters 2013" xml:id="waters2013">Waters, D. J. <title rend="quotes">An
                  Overview of the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Research Library Issues</title> no. 284 (2013).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
