<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Some principles for making collaborative scholarly editions in
                    digital form</title>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Peter <dhq:family>Robinson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Saskatchewan</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>peter.robinson@usask.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Peter Robinson is interested in three areas of research: the works of
                            Geoffrey Chaucer; the study of large textual traditions; and the impact
                            of the digital medium on how we communicate with each other. All three
                            intersect in his work on Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales, where he tries to
                            use digital and other quantitative methods to make sense of the more
                            than 80 manuscript and print versions surviving from before 1500. His
                            research interests have led him in many directions. He has developed
                            methods for encoding scholarly editions in digital form, particularly as
                            a contributor, work-group leader and board member of the Text Encoding
                            Initiative. He has created tools for preparation of edition materials
                            (the widely-used collation tool Collate) and for the digital publication
                            of editions (the the Anastasia and SDPublisher systems). With others, he
                            has pioneered the application of phylogenetic methods from evolutionary
                            biology to the exploration of manuscript relations. He has also worked
                            on many other editorial projects, notably on the cluster of New
                            Testament editions based in Birmingham, UK and Münster, Germany; on
                            Dante’s Monarchia and Commedia; the Spanish Cancioneros: on the Leiden
                            Armenian Lexical Textbase; the Laures Virtual Library of pre-1650
                            Japanese Books; and the Parliament Rolls of Medieval England. He is
                            currently focussed on the making of ‘textual communities. This is a
                            web-based environment which will allow scholars and readers everywhere
                            to collaborate in the making of a scholarly edition in electronic form.
                            It is now been used by several major editorial projects, notably the
                            Canterbury Tales Project.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000293</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2017-05-22">22 May 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2017-03-07" who="JDF">Proofread file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p><title rend="quotes">Textual Communities</title> is a new system for managing and performing all aspects of
                    an online collaborative scholarly editing project. It permits mounting of
                    document images and offers page-by-page transcription and display, with the
                    facility for project leaders to recruit and manage transcribers and other
                    contributors, allocating and reviewing transcription work as it is done. Most
                    distinctively, Textual Communities is built on a comprehensive model of
                    scholarly editing, enabling both <q>document</q> (page-by-page) and <q>work</q>
                    (intellectual structure, or <q>entity</q>) views of the texts edited. Accordingly,
                    multiple texts of a single work, or part of a work (an entity) may be extracted
                    and compared, using an embedded installation of CollateX. While completely
                    conformant with Text Encoding Initiative guidelines, Textual Communities goes
                    beyond TEI and XML in its ability to handle multiple overlapping hierarchies
                    within texts. This paper will outline the thinking behind the development of
                    Textual Communities, and show examples of its use by several major projects.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Rationale and examples of Textual Communities, a system for managing and performing online collaborative scholary editing projects.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>

         <div>
                <head>Introduction: scholarly editions in the digital age</head>
                <p>While one may dispute how <q>revolutionary</q> scholarly editions in digital form may
                    be as compared to their print counterparts <ptr target="#robinsonforthcoming"/>, we can agree that the onset of digital methods has considerably broadened
                    the ways in which editions may be made and distributed. We<note>Although I am the sole author of this paper, at several points I speak of <q>we</q>.
                        Many people have contributed to the thinking behind this paper, and to the Textual
                        Communities system which seeks to implement that thinking. To name a few: the
                        discussion of text, document and work is deeply indebted to many discussions over
                        many years with Peter Shillingsburg, Paul Eggert, Hans Walter Gabler, David Parker
                        and Barbara Bordalejo, among others (see, for example, <ptr target="#shillingsburg2007"/>; <ptr target="#eggert2009"/>; <ptr target="#gabler2007"/>; <ptr target="#parker1997"/>; and particularly the
                        collection of essays in <ptr target="#bordalejo2013"/>.This does not mean that any
                        of these scholars agree with the definitions I offer: the best I can hope for, is
                        that I have learned enough from them that they might disagree with me less vehemently
                        now than they would have a few years ago. Here, <q>I</q> means <q>I</q>: those scholars are
                        not responsible for my opinions. However, the creation of Textual Communities has
                        been fully collaborative. The main implementation at Saskatchewan since 2010 has
                        been the responsibility of Xiaohan Zhang, with some parts written by myself and Erin
                        Szigaly. Throughout, we have consulted with Zeth Green (Birmingham) and Troy
                        Griffitts (Münster), who have contributed key insights and questions. The major
                        projects using Textual Communities, named in footnote 17, have been an invaluable
                        testing ground for Textual Communities. I am embarrassed for their long suffering
                        over the last years, and grateful for their patience, support and encouragement.
                        Finally, this article has benefitted significantly from the comments of many readers
                        on a draft version posted on GoogleDocs in May 2015. I have indicated each place
                        where I introduced a change suggested by one of these readers, and acknowledged the
                        person. I also thank Torsten Schassan for instigating the discussion, and for his
                        many corrections.</note>can now contemplate
                    editions made by wide collaborations of editors, transcribers, indexers,
                    commentators and annotators, all working across the internet. We are now
                    accustomed to seeing editions providing multiple interfaces, with distribution
                    ranging from strictly-controlled paid-for access to access open to anyone with
                    an internet connection.</p>
                <p>These possibilities require us to ask new questions. In terms of the edition as
                    product, as something made: how can we most usefully characterize the
                    fundamental intellectual components of a scholarly edition in the digital
                    landscape? In this article, I consider this question in terms familiar to
                    scholarly editors: the concepts of document, text and work. In terms of the
                    edition as a process, as something we make and use: who are <q>we</q>? how may we
                    relate to each other, both as creators and as readers? Indeed, digital methods
                    open up a yet more radical possibility: that readers may become creators, as the
                    edition becomes an ever-open field of interaction, with readers contributing to
                    its continuing remaking. In what follows, I express these two perspectives as
                    <q>axes</q>.</p>
                <p>This is not simply a matter of describing editions and how they may be made. We
                    have choices, more than ever, in the digital age, as to where we locate our
                    edition against these axes. An edition can be severely limited, or richly
                    substantive, both in terms of what it contains and who may use it and how they
                    may use it. In the latter part of the article, I describe an editorial
                    environment, <q>Textual Communities</q>, designed with these axes in mind. It goes
                    without saying that Textual Communities, like the editions it might make, is
                    subject to never-ending transmutation. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The axes of scholarly editions</head>
                <p>Every scholarly edition may be placed on two axes, representing (as it were) the
                    longitude and latitude of editing. The first axis is along the familiar
                    continuum of document/text/work: is the edition devoted to a particular document
                    (as for a modern genetic edition of an authorial manuscript)? Or is it oriented
                    towards presentation of a work found in many documents (as for an edition of the
                    Greek New Testament, or a medieval work found in many manuscripts)? The second
                    axis is along the range of relationships between the editor and the editions’
                    audience. Is the edition made by a specialist scholar and intended for a narrow
                    and specialist audience, not to be read but to be used as a resource for further
                    scholarly work? Or is it made by a non-specialist and intended for the broadest
                    possible audience, to be read rather than studied? Does its design and
                    implementation permit its endless re-use, so that readers may in turn become
                    editors, or other editors may take it and reforge it for their own purposes and
                    audiences? Note too that as in geographical coordinates, the place of an edition
                    on one axis is independent of its place on the other axis. An edition intended
                    for the general reader may be based on all the documents, or on just one; an
                    edition intended for a specialist reader may also be based on all the documents,
                    or on just one. An edition based on a single document, or on many, might be
                    designed to permit other editors to take and repurpose what is made in ways
                    unforeseen by its original makers.</p>

                <!--Figure 1: the document/work/text axis-->
                <figure>
                    <head>The document/work/text axis</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                
                <!--Figure 2: the editor/audience axis-->
                
                <figure>
                    <head>The editor/audience axis</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                

                <p>There is no novelty about these two axes. Editions made long before the advent of
                    digital methods may be referenced along these axes. However, digital methods
                    have widened the range of choices along each axis, and also altered the balance
                    between these choices, as they favour one choice over another. For example:
                    digital imaging has made it possible to make full-colour facsimiles for a very
                    low cost (as little as a few cents a page) and to distribute them over the
                    internet to any one with an internet connection and a computer, at no cost to
                    the reader. The emergence of successful methods for encoding a document
                    page-by-page combined with the availability of high-quality digital images has
                    favoured the making of a particular kind of edition, oriented towards the
                    document rather than the work. Along the other axis: the editorial decision
                    about the audience of the edition has been complicated by the emergence of
                    funding agencies as the primary sponsors of editions, and by the emergence of
                    centres substantially funded by these same agencies as the primary place of
                    making editions. In these circumstances, the primary motivation of an edition is
                    not to reach an audience, whether narrow or broad, but to satisfy the funder.
                    This has also led to the emergence of specialists in computer methods as leaders
                    in the making of editions, rather than specialists in (for example) the texts
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>One of the most influential commentators on scholarly editing in the digital age,
                    Jerome McGann, has frequently cited William Morris’s observation that (in
                    McGann’s wording) <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1983">you can’t have art without resistance in the material.</quote><note>So quoted by McGann <ptr target="#mcGann1983" loc="144"/>. For the
                        source of the Morris citation, and the relationship of McGann’s formulation
                        to Morris’s words, see <ptr target="#noviskie2013"/>. Noviskie traces the
                        quotation to Sparling 1924.</note> There is danger in failing to resist: in
                    editing, as in art, to do what is easiest may not be to do what is best.
                    Following the scenario sketched in the last paragraph, we have seen the making
                    of numerous <q>digital documentary editions</q> <ptr target="#pierazzo2011"/>,
                    typically created with considerable funding and support from a digital
                    humanities centre <ptr target="#sutherland2010"/> <ptr target="#maryland2014"/>. The coincidence of
                    cheap digital images, powerful encoding, and significant funding has resulted in
                    several remarkable editions. However, there is a danger of imbalance, if many
                    editions are made in a narrow band along the document/text/work axis, and for an
                    ill-defined audience. Resistance in the materials entails not doing what is
                    easiest. In scholarly editing terms: resistance means deciding where on the
                    document/text/work continuum your edition should be located, not simply placing
                    it where the technology makes it easiest, and identifying what audience you wish
                    to serve, not simply satisfying your funder and your own inclinations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Documents, texts and communicative acts</head>
                <p>Accordingly, the first task of any editor is to know what is meant by the terms
                    document, text and work, and how the edition may be located with reference to
                    these terms. Over the last decades, several scholars (notably Peter
                    Shillingsburg, Paul Eggert and Hans Gabler; see footnote 1) have debated the
                    valency of these terms, and I have summarized their arguments and presented my
                    own definitions in two articles <ptr target="#robinson2013a"/>, <ptr target="#robinson2013b"/>. In summary: a <term>document</term> is the material object
                    upon which marks are inscribed: a manuscript, a book, a clay shard. A <term>text</term> is
                    the communicative linguistic act which the reader deduces as present in the
                    document, represented by these marks. A <term>work</term> is a set of texts which are
                    hypothesized as related, in terms of the communicative acts which they
                        present.<note>Compare the well-known FRBR (Functional Requirements for
                        Bibliographic Records) Group 1 entities: <q>work, expression, manifestation,
                        item</q> <ptr target="#IFLA1998"/>; <ptr target="#tillett2004"/>. <q>Work</q> as I
                        define it maps broadly to FRBR <q>work</q> (but might in different circumstances
                        map to expression or manifestation); a document maps to an item. There is no
                        equivalent in FRBR to <q>text</q> as I explain it. The system here presented
                        extends, rather than replaces, FRBR. Particularly, this system enables works
                        (and hence texts) to be seen as structured objects, readily susceptible to
                        fine-grained manipulation, in ways that FRBR does not.</note> Thus: the
                    Hengwrt manuscript is a document preserved in the National Library of Wales,
                    comprising some 248 folios bound into 32 quires. This manuscript contains a text
                    which we recognize as an instance of Geoffrey Chaucer’s <title rend="italic">Canterbury
                        Tales</title>. Further, we know another eighty three manuscripts and four
                    print editions dating from before 1500 containing texts of the
                        <title rend="italic">Tales</title>, and (of course) many editions, adaptations and
                    translations dating from after 1500. We speak of the <q>work</q> as all these
                    together. In our common thought, we conceive the work as something beyond all
                    these physical documents: as the creative act conceived and executed by Geoffrey
                    Chaucer in the last decades of the fourteenth century.</p>
                <p>These definitions have many implications. First: there is a clear division
                    between document and text. The text is not simply the marks in the document. It
                    is the communicative act that I, the reader, identify as represented by those
                    marks. The difference may seem slight. It is critical. When we record the text
                    of the document, we are not simply saying: that mark is an <q>i</q>, this next mark
                    is a <q>t</q>; we have <q>it</q>. We see first a set of potentially meaningful marks in
                    the document. We hypothesize: these marks may represent a communicative act.
                        <note>This discussion of the stages of recognition of the text as a
                        communicative act is indebted to the description by Barbara Bordalejo of the
                        encoding system in the Prue Shaw edition of the Commedia, thus: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bordalejo2010">in this
                        article, I use the phrase the <q>text of the document</q> to refer to the
                        sequence of marks present in the document, independently of whether these
                        represent a complete, meaningful text. That is: the reader sees a sequence
                        of letters, occurring in various places in relation to each other (perhaps
                        between the lines or within the margins) and carrying various markings
                        (perhaps underdottings or strikethroughs). These make up what I here refer
                        to as the text of the document</quote><ptr target="#bordalejo2010"/></cit>.</note>
                    They are not (say) marks left by grubs crawling under the bark of a tree <ptr target="#eggert2010"/>. Someone made these marks to communicate something.
                    We then identify the language and writing system to which these marks belong. We
                    identify these marks as letters, composing the word <q>it</q>. As we examine the
                    marks, the communicative act takes shape in our minds: the words resolve into
                    sentences, into verse lines, paragraphs, as part of something we know as the
                    General Prologue of the <title rend="italic">Canterbury Tales</title>. This communicative act
                    has a double aspect. One aspect is the disposition of the marks in the document:
                    exactly where on the page they appear; the combination of strokes which compose
                    each letter. The other aspect is that of the components of the communicative
                    act: for prose, as constituted by a sequence of sentences within paragraphs; for
                    verse, as lines within stanzas. It is not simply a sequence of words: it is
                    structured, capable of division and labeling.</p>
                <p>Normally, these processes of recognition happen so quickly, so instinctively,
                    that they do not appear like thought at all. We see a text on a page and we read
                    it. We think the marks on the page are the text, and hence that recording the
                    text is a mechanical act of transposing those marks from one medium (the page)
                    to another (now, usually, an electronic file in a computer). Accordingly one
                    sees statements implying (or indeed asserting) that a transcription can somehow
                    not be <q>interpretive</q>, and hence aspire to some kind of <q>objective</q> status. As
                    an example: in a discussion on the Text Encoding Initiative list in February
                    2014, several participants routinely described transcription of the
                    communicative act, in terms of paragraphs, sentences, identification of names
                    and places within the text, as <q>interpretive</q> (or <q>interpretative</q>), while
                    recording exactly where the text appears on the document page was described as
                    <q>non-interpretive</q>. The Text Encoding Initiative even has distinct elements for
                    the two types of transcription: <q>interpretive</q> transcripts are held in
                    <code>&lt;text&gt;</code> elements; <q>non-interpretive</q> transcripts are held in
                    <code>&lt;sourceDoc&gt;</code> elements.<note>For example: an email by James Cummings to the
                        TEI-L discussion on 5 February 2014 which speaks of encoding <quote rend="inline" source="#private">both the
                        interpretative <code>&lt;text&gt;</code> view and non-interpretative <code>&lt;sourceDoc&gt;</code>
                            view</quote> (<ref target="http://permalink.gmane.org/gmane.text.tei.general/16892">http://permalink.gmane.org/gmane.text.tei.general/16892</ref>). Compare the
                        prioritization of <q>document-based editing</q> over other kinds of editing
                        argued by Hans Gabler <ptr target="#gabler2007"/>, while noting that
                        Gabler has always argued consistently that editors must also present the
                        work (e.g., <ptr target="#gabler1984"/>, <ptr target="#gabler1990"/>.</note> This distinction led Barbara Bordalejo to ask tartly in the
                    course of that discussion: <q>are you suggesting there are transcriptions that are
                    not interpretive? How do you distinguish them?</q></p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Encoding text as document and as communicative act</head>
                <p>In the definition of text here offered, all is interpretation: there is no such
                    thing as a <q>non-interpretive</q> transcript. Further, this definition stipulates
                    that text has two aspects: it is both marks upon paper (corresponding to TEI
                    <code>&lt;sourceDoc&gt;</code>) and it is the components of a communicative act
                    (corresponding to TEI <code>&lt;text&gt;</code>). Both aspects may be expressed as
                    hierarchies. The document hierarchy consists of the book, divided into quires,
                    divided into pages, divided into writing spaces: columns, lines, margins. The
                    components of the communicative act may also be expressed as chapters divided
                    into paragraphs divided into sentences, or poems divided into stanzas divided
                    into lines. The two hierarchies are completely independent of each other. The
                    General Prologue may be written across several quires, or contained in only one;
                    it may spread across as few as six folios, or as many as sixteen. Of course, the
                    hierarchies overlap. Paragraphs continue across page breaks, lines of verse
                    across line breaks. In the world of documents, this is no problem. The text of
                    the communicative act runs across quires, pages, line breaks in an orderly and
                    straight-forward manner. We are so used to this that we do not notice it. We
                    skip from page to page, across footnotes, past catchwords, page numbers, running
                    heads. Sometimes, the two hierarchies coincide. The book opens a new story, a
                    new chapter opens on a new page, a new section a new volume, before once more
                    the hierarchies diverge, and each runs their separate course, to the end of the
                    book and the end of the story. The codex, whether in scroll, manuscript or print
                    form, is superbly fitted to carry the text of communicative acts. A New
                    Testament gospel might fit neatly in a single small codex; the whole New
                    Testament in a larger one, or split across several codices. This overlapping,
                    this sliding of one hierarchy across another, this disposition of this printing
                    across many volumes in one instance, or in just one in another instance, is so
                    common that an editor might note it briefly, and move on.</p>
                <p>But while it is straightforward to represent a communicative act in a document,
                    it is not at all straightforward to represent both the components of a
                    communicative act and of a document in a single electronic representation – and
                    particularly not in a single electronic representation which conforms to the
                    norms of the Text Encoding Initiative, the gold standard of encoding for
                    humanities texts. The XML (<title rend="quotes">eXtensible Markup Language</title>) specification requires
                    that content objects within an XML document conform to a single hierarchy.
                    Accordingly, it is a simple matter to represent either the document hierarchy
                    (books, quires, pages, lines) or the communicative act components hierarchy
                    (poem, stanzas, lines; story, chapters, paragraphs). But it is not at all simple
                    to represent both hierarchies in a single XML document. <note>Among many
                        contributions to the discussion of overlapping hierarchies in mark-up
                        languages: see the original statement of <q>the OHCO thesis</q> in De Rose et al.
                            <ptr target="#derose1990"/> and its restatement and complication in
                        Renear et al. <ptr target="#renear1993"/>. See too footnote 15.</note> Over
                    the twenty years of encoding of texts of primary sources using the TEI
                    guidelines, scholars have used various devices to circumvent this problem. In
                    the <q>P3</q> version of the guidelines, the chapter on encoding of primary sources
                    suggests that one should represent the communicative act component hierarchy
                    exactly and fully, by identifying each part of the communicative act (each
                    paragraph, each verse line) with a discrete segment of the TEI document (thus, a
                    <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;l&gt;</code> element), and then nesting the segments within other
                    segments, so that <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> elements are contained within <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements,
                    just as paragraphs are contained within chapters.<note>The author, while not
                        formally a member of the workgroup (<q>TR9</q>) on <q>Manuscripts and codicology</q>
                        which was charged with drafting the chapter on representation of primary
                        sources in the <q>P3</q> guidelines (first published in 1994), wrote most of the
                        draft of what became Chapter 18 <title rend="quotes">Transcription of Primary Sources</title> in those
                        guidelines (see <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/GL/P3/index.htm">http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/GL/P3/index.htm</ref>). This chapter
                        persisted in revised form into the <q>P4</q> version, first published in 2002,
                        before finally being replaced by Chapter 11 of the first <q>P5</q> version in
                        2007.</note> XML (like its predecessor, SGML) is optimized for representing
                    a single <q>ordered hierarchy of content objects</q>: but it does also have a means
                    of recording other information about the encoded text, in the form of <q>empty
                    elements</q>, otherwise known as <q>milestones</q>. Accordingly, in a TEI document one
                    might record the communicative act hierarchy as the primary hierarchy, and then
                    represent the document hierarchy as a sequence of milestone elements:
                    <code>&lt;pb/&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> elements for pages and lines. In this ordering, the
                    <code>&lt;pb/&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> elements, unlike the <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;p&gt;</code>
                    elements, hold no content: they state where page breaks and line ends are
                    relative to the text of the communicative act within the document. The result is
                    that the components of the communicative act are represented completely, and one
                    may readily use all the tools available in the XML community, optimized for
                    dealing with hierarchies of content objects, to manipulate the document.
                    However, the material document which holds the text is represented far less
                    adequately. One might record the larger features of the document – the number of
                    pages within it, the number of lines within each page – and record too exactly
                    the page and line breaks that occur within the text. But it will be difficult to
                    represent more complex phenomena, such as a single page which contains multiple
                    writing spaces, each containing text in a complex relation with texts in other
                    writing spaces. Further processing of the document according to this second
                    hierarchy is complex, and often impractical.</p>
                <p>The P3 fundamental logic – that one identifies the components of the
                    communicative act (sometimes referred to as <q>intellectual</q> or <q>logical</q>
                    structure) as the primary hierarchy of its XML representation, and record
                    document features as milestone elements – is used in countless TEI-based
                    encodings of primary textual materials, including several scholarly editions in
                    digital form (such as those made by myself or in which I was involved, e.g. <ptr target="#robinson2004"/> and <ptr target="#shaw2010"/>. This logic
                    prioritizes representation of the components of the communicative act over the
                    physical document, and so is well-suited to situations where the disposition of
                    the text in the document is either straight-forward, as in many medieval
                    manuscripts or printed books, so that it may be adequately captured through
                    sequences of page and line-breaks alone, or is perceived as relatively
                    unimportant. However, there is an important class of documents where the
                    disposition of the text on the page is both complex and significant. This
                    applies particularly to authorial manuscripts, where authorial revision is
                    expressed through multiple acts of writing within a page, from which editors
                    must construct a text or texts by decryption of the sequence of revisions
                    embedded in these multiple writings. In these cases, the P3 system is
                    inadequate. Further, continuing from the last decades of the last century,
                    scholarly editors have become increasingly interested in the <q>material text</q>,
                    following the ground-breaking writings of Donald McKenzie <ptr target="#mcKenzie1999"/> and Jerome McGann <ptr target="#mcGann1983"/>,
                    and continuing through many others.<note>To name a few: <ptr target="#okeefe2006"/>; <ptr target="#bornstein2001"/>; and a whole
                        European Society for Textual Scholarship conference on <title rend="quotes">Textual Scholarship
                        and the Material Book: Comparative Approaches</title> in London in 2006. The
                        emergence of the document as the locus of scholarly attention now has a
                        name: <q>material philology</q>. See too <ptr target="#nichols1990"/>, and
                        Matthew K. Driscoll <title rend="quotes">The Words on the Page</title>, distilling talks given by him
                        around 2005-2007 and available at
                        <ref target="http://www.driscoll.dk/docs/words.html">http://www.driscoll.dk/docs/words.html</ref>.</note> Thus, it became increasingly
                    important to many scholars to represent as exactly as possible the document page
                    and the text upon it, with a fullness and precision which the P3 system could
                    not achieve. In response to this need, the TEI convened a working group to
                    prepare encodings for the making of documents where representation of the
                    document was paramount. This resulted in a new Section 11.2.2, first issued in
                    <q>version 2.0.0</q> of the P5 Guidelines in December 2011. This section introduced a
                    new high-level <code>&lt;sourceDoc&gt;</code> element, specifically to carry the <q>embedded
                    transcription</q> described in this section. This <q>embedded transcription</q> is
                    described as <q>one in which words and other written traces are encoded as
                    subcomponents of elements representing the physical surfaces carrying them
                    rather than independently of them</q>. The examples and the accompanying
                    documentation make very clear exactly what is meant by this: that the marks upon
                    the page are interpreted as words completely independent of any sense of their
                    being part of a communicative act. Thus, the letters and words of the page are
                    placed within the page hierarchy, in a series of elements which may be nested
                    within one another: the page as <code>&lt;surface&gt;</code>, which might contain a
                    <code>&lt;zonee&gt;</code> (a column, a writing area), itself containing <code>&lt;line&gt;</code> and
                    <code>&lt;sege&gt;</code> elements, which might contain the words themselves. There is no
                    place here at all for recording information about the text as a structured
                    communicative act. Instead, the Guidelines suggest that information about the
                    text as communicative act should be recorded in a separate <code>&lt;texte&gt;</code>
                    element, parallel to the <code>&lt;sourceDoc&gt;</code> elements. In theory, this is a better
                    solution than the rather makeshift procedure adopted by P3. In practice, it is
                    extremely difficult to maintain two distinct transcriptions, and to maintain the
                    complex sets of links between the two.<note>I know of only one substantial
                        project that attempts this parallel encoding: the Goethe Faust project, <ptr target="#brüningetal2013"/>.</note></p>
                <p>The Shelley-Godwin archive shows the power of document-based encoding <ptr target="#maryland2014"/>. A feature of this new encoding is that it
                    provides for explicit statement of the revisions within each document page and
                    their sequence. One can see (for example) exactly what Mary Shelley wrote, and
                    what Percy Shelley wrote. One can read the transcription in parallel to each
                    page facsimile, with each element of the transcription mirrored in transcript
                    and page: a considerable technical feat. However, what is excellent for these
                    materials – a classic instance of <q>genetic texts</q>, through which one may see the
                    authors (in this case) forging the text a phrase at a time – may not be
                    appropriate for other editions. While the TEI guidelines recommend that a
                    parallel encoding of the text-as-structured-communicative-act be made alongside
                    the encoding of the text-as-document, in practice editions may not follow this
                    advice, and indeed the Shelley-Godwin archive does not do this.<note>The
                        Shelley-Godwin archive creators were fully aware of the arguments for
                        encoding both <q>document</q> and <q>text</q>, and canvas these in <ptr target="#muñozetal2013"/>, while confessing themselves unable to
                        implement satisfactory encoding of both aspects.</note> The result is that
                    while one can see precisely the changes within each page, the failure to encode
                    the components of the communicative act within each document makes it extremely
                    difficult to see the changes between one document and another. Indeed, the rigid
                    segmentation of the document into pages makes it impossible to record a change
                    which spans across a page boundary. For example: one finds on fol 5v of Fair
                    Copy Notebook C1. c. 58 and on fol 73r of Draft Notebook B. c. 57 versions of
                    the end of chapter 22. But to locate these passages one is reduced to using the
                    search engine to discover parallel texts: not a very efficient procedure. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Representation of both work and document: the DET system</head>
                <p>This defect brings us to the third element of the document/text/work triumvirate:
                    the work. The definition of work given above – that a work is a set of texts
                    which are hypothesized as organically related, in terms of the communicative
                    acts which they present – depends on identification of an instance of the
                    communicative act and its components in any one document (e.g. this is the
                    General Prologue in the Hengwrt manuscript) and then identification of other
                    instances of related communicative acts in other documents (this is the General
                    Prologue in the Ellesmere manuscript, in the Caxton printings, in the Riverside
                    Chaucer). Because we identify the components of the communicative act in any one
                    document, we can compare its instantiation in that document with its
                    instantiation in any other. If we reduce our notion of text to simply words in
                    documents, we have no means of asserting relations between documents apart from
                    the happenstance of some words recurring in different documents (as I was able
                    to use the Shelley/Godwin archive search engine to discover that folios in
                    different notebooks had similar words to the end of Chapter 22 in various print
                    editions). This is unsatisfactory, to put it mildly. It provides no means of
                    linking translations, or radical rewritings. We can assert (to give an extreme
                    example) that the many hundred manuscripts of the medieval <emph>Visio
                        Pauli</emph> are related, through many recensions in many languages, many of
                    which have not a single word in common, because they share structure, subject,
                    theme, motifs and details, and because we can trace the historical growth of the
                    tradition across time and space and from document to document.<note>For the
                        complexities of the <emph>Visio Pauli</emph> tradition see <ptr target="#robinson1996"/>.</note> I can assert that both the Sion and the
                    Merthyr manuscripts contain versions of the <title>Canterbury Tales</title>,
                    even though there is not one line of the Tales in common to both (Sion holds the
                    sequence Clerk’s Tale-Summoner’s Tale, Merthyr has part of the Nun’s Priest’s
                    Tale and link), as surely as Darwin can assert that two multi-segmented
                    organisms are both barnacles, even though they have not a single segment in
                    common. Darwin can assert this by showing that both organisms descend from an
                    ancestor which had both sets of segments. I can show that both manuscripts
                    descend from other manuscripts which had both sets of tales.</p>
                <p>According to these definitions, then, a fundamental requirement of scholarly
                    editing is that both aspects of a text are recognized: both the text as marks
                    upon a document, and the text as structured communicative act. To put it at its
                    simplest: we need to be able to say that the words <q>Whan that Auerill with his
                    shoures sote</q> are found in a particular space on the first folio of the Hengwrt
                    manuscript, Peniarth 392D in the National Library of Wales, and that these words
                    are also the first line of the General Prologue of the works we know as Geoffrey
                    Chaucer’s <title>Canterbury Tales</title>. Over the last years, with the help of
                    many people, I have been developing a formal system for describing documents,
                    texts and works to enable just this. In essence: we need a scheme for labeling
                    all three elements, that will allow us to identify every part of each element,
                    in every document, text and work, and assert too how they relate to each other.
                        <note>I was aware, at an early stage, of the work of the Canonical Text
                        Services (CTS) group, and studied their system closely while devising the
                        system here devised <ptr target="#blackwell2014"/>. Briefly, this system
                        is highly compatible with CTS, in that every CTS reference may also be
                        expressed with no loss of information. However, the reverse is not true.
                        This system includes completely hierarchical information for both document
                        and communicative act, permitting full specification of both document space
                        (a line within a page within a volume) and communicative act component (a
                        word within a sentence within a paragraph within a chapter) to a degree that
                        CTS does not enable. Further, CTS does not use the key/value pair
                        architecture, nor does it specify the naming authority. It is in essence a
                        labelling scheme, with some hierarchical elements, and relies on external
                        index files to correlate (for example) text segments with the manuscripts in
                        which they appear. For example:
                        https://github.com/homermultitext/hmt-archive/blob/master/cite/collections/scholiainventory.csv
                        includes the line
                        "urn:cite:hmt:scholia.379","urn:cts:greekLit:tlg5026.msA.hmt:1.6","6th main
                        scholia of Iliad
                        1","urn:cite:hmt:chsimg.VA012RN-0013@0.57311951,0.24827982,0.22451317,0.04644495","urn:cite:hmt:msA.12r".
                        It appears that this links the <q>6th main scholia of Iliad 1</q> with the urn
                        <q>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg5026.msA.hmt:1.6</q>, and further with the manuscript
                        urn:cite:hmt:msA.12r, presumably page 12r of <q>MsA</q>. In contrast, the system
                        here described would yolk these statements together into a single URL, such
                        as <q>…/document=MsA/folio=12r/entity=Scholia/Book=1/n=6</q>, from which the full
                        page and communicative act hierarchies could be deduced.</note></p>

                <p>We call this scheme <q>documents, entities and texts</q> (DET), using the term
                    <q>entity</q> to refer to the unique labels we give each component of a communicative
                    act. <note>The term <q>entity</q> is used here in preference to <q>work</q> for several
                        reasons. Firstly, as the examples show, the term entity may be applied to a
                        structured object of a communicative act at any level: a single line of
                            <title>Hamlet</title> may be an entity; so too a single scene, an act,
                        and the whole play itself are also entities. Secondly, the term <q>work</q>,
                        hotly contested in textual scholarship <ptr target="#robinson2013b"/>,
                        comes with many connotations which might not be helpful in understanding the
                        system here proposed: <q>entity</q> has the advantage of neutrality. <q>Entity</q> is
                        also familiar from FRBR, which is built on the categorization of
                        relationships among <q>entities</q>: distinct intellectual objects, analogous to
                        the distinct components into which an act of communication may be
                        structured.</note> The labeling system we employ is based on the
                    Kahn/Wilensky architecture <ptr target="#kahn2006"/>. Like Kahn/Wilensky, we
                    use the familiar uniform resource name (<q>urn</q>) notation to hold each label.
                    Following Kahn/Wilensky, we separate the label into two parts: a naming
                    authority, and the name given by that naming authority to the object. Thus, in
                    Kahn/Wilensky the handle <q>berkeley.cs/csd-93-712</q> gives the naming authority as
                    <q>berkeley.cs</q>, and <q>csd-93-712</q> is the name given by that authority to a
                    particular object. In full urn form, this is expressed as
                    <eg>
                        &lt;URN:ASCII:ELIB-v.2.0:berkeley.cs/csd-93-712e&gt;
                    </eg>
                    In our system, we adopt
                    the use of <q>/</q> to separate the naming authority from the name, and we further
                    specify that the name must be composed of at least one of the key words ‘entity’
                    and ‘document’ and of one or more key value pairs, separated by the <q>:</q>
                    delimiter.</p>

                <p>Applying this to a document:</p>
                <p><code>TC:USask:CTP2/document=Hengwrt</code> - indicates that the naming authority TC:USask:CTP2 has given this document the name <q>Hengwrt</q></p>
                                <p><code>…/document=Hengwrt:Folio=1r</code> – indicates Folio 1r of the Hengwrt manuscript</p>
                <p><code>…/document=Hengwrt:Folio=1r:line=2</code> – indicates line 2 of Folio 1r of the Hengwrt manuscript </p>

                <p>Applying this to an entity, that is to a named component of a communicative act:</p>
                        <p><code>TC:USask:CTP2/entity=Canterbury Tales</code> – indicates that the
                    naming authority TC:USask:CTP2 has given this entity the name <q>Canterbury Tales</q></p>
                <p>
                        <code>…/entity=Canterbury Tales:Section=General Prologue</code> – the
                    General Prologue of the Canterbury Tales </p>
                <p><code>…/entity=Canterbury Tales:Section=General Prologue:line=1</code> – line 1 of the General
                    Prologue of the Canterbury Tales </p>

                <p>In full urn notation, the document would be</p>
                    <p><code>&lt;urn:DET:TC:USask:CTP2/document=Hengwrt&gt;</code>; the entity would be
                    <code>
                        &lt;urn:DET:TC:USask:CTP2/entity=Canterbury Tales&gt;
                    </code></p>

                <p>We have defined a <q>text</q> as a communicative act, which comprises both document
                    (the material upon which it is inscribed) and entity (the components into which
                    it might be divided). Accordingly, a text of any one communicative act in any
                    one document is the collocation of the entities and of the document for that
                    text. Thus, for the text of the Canterbury Tales in the Hengwrt manuscript:
                        <eg>
                            TC:USask:CTP2/document=Hengwrt:entity=Canterbury Tales
                        </eg>
                </p>

                <p>For the text of the first line of the General Prologue on the second line of
                    folio 1r of the Hengwrt Manuscript:
                        <eg>
                            …/document=Hengwrt:Folio=1r:line=2:entity=Canterbury Tales: Section=General Prologue:line=1
                        </eg>
                </p>

                <p>The power of this system should be immediately apparent. We can, from this naming
                    alone, identify all manuscripts which contain the <title>Canterbury
                        Tales</title>; all manuscripts which contain the General Prologue; all
                    manuscripts which contain the first line of the General Prologue. Or, in
                    reverse: we can say, for any one manuscript, exactly what parts of the
                        <title>Canterbury Tales</title> it contains; we can say, for any page in any
                    manuscript, what lines of what part of the Tales it contains; we can say, for
                    any line or space in any page in any manuscript exactly what words of what part
                    of the Tales it contains. Note that the document and entity naming is completely
                    hierarchical: each successive object within the sequence of name/value pairs
                    must be contained within the preceding object. Line one is part of the General
                    Prologue, which is part of the <title>Canterbury Tales</title>; the second line
                    is on Folio 1r which is part of the Hengwrt manuscript. Note too that the system
                    can cope with prose and other texts where communicative acts span across lines
                    and pages. Paragraph 162 of the Parson’s Tale in the Corpus Christi 198
                    manuscript of the <title>Tales</title> begins on line 36 of folio 272r, and
                    continues on the first two lines of folio 272v. This can be represented as
                    follows: <eg>
                        …/document=Corpus:Folio=272r:line=36:entity=Canterbury Tales: Section=Parson’s Tale:Segment=162
                    </eg>
                    <eg>
                        …/document=Corpus:Folio=272v:line=1:entity=Canterbury Tales: Section=Parson’s Tale:Segment=162
                    </eg>
                    <eg>
                        …/document=Corpus:Folio=272v:line=2:entity=Canterbury Tales: Section=Parson’s Tale:Segment=162
                    </eg>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Implementing DET: Textual Communities</head>
                <p>Theory is one thing; implementation is another. The basic outline of this scheme
                    was prepared by myself, with advice and help from Federico Meschini and Zeth
                    Green, in 2008-2009, and presented first by myself and Green at a symposium on
                    Collaborative Scholarly Editing in Birmingham in 2009, and then by Meschini and
                    myself in a paper presented to the ADHO conference in London in 2010. Following
                    suggestions at a meeting of the InterEdition project in Pisa in 2009, we first
                    experimented with expressing this scheme in the form of an ontology. This was
                    successful, as proof of concept: we could indeed connect documents, entities and
                    texts via RDF classes and properties. <note>A description of the RDF ontology
                        prepared in 2010, and an implementation of it, are available at
                        <ref target="http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/textual-community/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Historical+Documents">http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/textual-community/wiki/-/wiki/Main/Historical+Documents</ref></note>
                    This helped persuade us that the concept was fundamentally sound. However,
                    implementation of even a basic working prototype would take considerable effort
                    and resources. In late 2010 I moved from the University of Birmingham, UK, to
                    the University of Saskatchewan, Canada, and a considerable motive was the
                    prospect of adequate funding to create a real editing system, based on these
                    concepts. Such a system was needed also to support my own editorial work,
                    particularly on Geoffrey Chaucer’s <title>Canterbury Tales</title>.</p>
                <p>With funding initially from the University of Saskatchewan (2010-2011), then from
                    the Canada Foundation for Innovation (2011-2014) and now from the Canadian
                    Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (2014-), we have made a
                    collaborative editing environment, <title rend="quotes">Textual Communities</title>, built on the
                    documents, entities and texts definitions here explained. A full technical
                    description of the components of the Textual Communities environment is beyond
                    the scope of this article. In brief:</p>

                <list>
                    <item>Although the DET system is designed to support full hierarchies for both
                        document and communicative act, and has no difficulties with overlapping
                        hierarchies, we based the system on TEI encodings which cannot support
                        overlapping hierarchies. Partly, this was because we had many thousands of
                        pages of transcription already in TEI encoding. Also, we knew from years of
                        experience that use of the P3 primary text model, encoding the communicative
                        act hierarchy as the main hierarchy and recording the document hierarchy
                        through milestones, could yield useful results.</item>

                    <item>Our first intent was to work through RDF, and so create an RDF repository
                        of materials accessible via SPARQL and other RDF tools. Very quickly, we
                        realized that the RDF tools then available could not support our aim of a
                        large real-time editing environment. (This may change as new RDF tools are
                        developed.) The tools were immature and did not scale well, and we had
                        significant performance issues even with small amounts of text. Hence, we
                        moved to use of a relational database for back-end storage of all data.
                        Decades of development have made relational databases robust, responsive and
                        fast, with a multitude of tools for management and for web server
                        interfaces. We are currently moving from a relational database to a MongoDB
                        system. JSON (Javascript Object Notation) has become our central internal
                        representation of data, and the optimization of MongoDB for JSON objects
                        maps well to our data.<note>As part of the move to MongoDB and JSON storage,
                            Zeth Green, Xiaohan Zhang and myself reviewed how the document and
                            entity hierarchies relate to the text formed from the collocation of the
                            two hierarchies. We realized that it was possible, using a JSON-based
                            architecture, to support not just two hierarchies for any text, but any
                            number of hierarchies, thereby avoiding any difficulties with
                            overlapping hierarchies. As of November 2016, we are still developing
                            this new architecture. Recent articles by computer scientists
                            demonstrate increasing awareness of the need to move beyond a <q>document
                            paradigm</q>, with its reliance on hierarchical content models, to systems
                            which will natively support the multiply overlapping information schemes
                            we find in actual texts and their physical instances: thus <ptr target="#schmidt2009"/> and, especially, <ptr target="#schloen2014"/>. At present and for the near future, however, XML in the TEI
                            implementation remains crucial to our work, both because it keeps us
                            close to a wide community of scholars working with digital editions and
                            because of its sophisticated validation facilities.</note>
                    </item>

                    <item>The core of our implementation of the DET scheme with a database backend
                        is the use of the TEI <code>&lt;refsDcl&gt;</code> element to map any TEI document to a
                        DET scheme. Here is a fragment from a refsDcl declaration for the Canterbury
                        Tales project: 
                        <eg>
                            &lt;cRefPattern matchPattern="urn:det:TC:USask:CTP2/entity=(.+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(//body/div[@n='$1'])"&gt;&lt;/cRefPattern&gt;
                        </eg>  

                    </item>

                    <item>Here, the <q>replacementPattern</q> attribute declares that every top level
                        <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> element within the document is to be mapped to an entity. The
                        entity will be given the name of the ‘n’ attribute, thus 
                        <code>&lt;div n="General Prologue"&gt;</code> 
                        is associated with the entity name <q>General Prologue</q>. The
                        matchPattern attribute declares exactly what entity this ‘n’ attribute will
                        be associated with: here, the entity itself. Taken together, the system now
                        understands that when it sees <code>&lt;div n="General Prologue"&gt;</code> as a top
                        level <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>, it associates that <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> and its contents with the
                        entity <q>urn:det:TC:USask:CTP2/entity=Canterbury Tales</q>. In essence: these
                        refsDcl expressions are used to slice the whole document into entity and
                        document chunks, to associate each chunk with a document and entity name,
                        and hence each chunk of text in the document is linked to its document and
                        entity and this information stored in the database.<note>This paragraph
                            describes the procedure used for designating document and entity parts
                            in the first version of the Textual Community system. In the second
                            version, we drastically simplified this: now, any TE/XML element with an
                            <q>n</q> attribute becomes an element in either the document or entity
                            hierarchy.</note></item>

                </list>

                <p>Through this system, we have now been able to store some 40,000 pages of
                    manuscript transcription and images in the Textual Communities implementation at
                    the University of Saskatchewan: see www.textualcommunities.usask.ca
                    (particularly, for the Canterbury Tales project, see
                    <ref target="http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/canterbury-tales/viewer">http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/canterbury-tales/viewer</ref>). This is now
                    being used routinely by editors and transcribers in six substantial
                        projects.<note>The six projects are: at the University of Saskatchewan, the
                        Canterbury Tales Project (with KUL, Belgium), led by myself and Barbara
                        Bordalejo of KUL, 30,000 pages and 30 active transcribers; the John Donne
                        Digital Prose Project, led by Brent Nelson, 1800 pages and 25 active
                        transcribers; the Recipes Project, led by Lisa Smith, 1500 pages and 30
                        active transcribers; the Incantation Magic Project, led by Frank Klaassen,
                        400 pages and 10 active transcribers; at the University of Birmingham, UK,
                        the Estoria de Espanna project, 3500 pages and 20 active transcribers; at
                        City University New York, the Teseida Project, led by Bill Coleman and
                        Edvige Agostinelli, 600 pages and four transcribers. Numerous other projects
                        are also using the Textual Communities system, although it has not been
                        publically launched.</note> We are currently testing and refining the system
                    before full public launch.</p>

                <p>In its current form, Textual Communities does not (and cannot) go as far as we
                    want towards a full representation of both aspects of the text, as document and
                    as communicative act. This limitation arises from our use of the TEI as the base
                    form for text representation. While the structure of each communicative act can
                    be fully represented in XML, and hence in Textual Communities, the ability of a
                    single XML document to represent only one primary hierarchy means that because
                    our documents in Textual Communities choose to make the structure of the
                    communicative act the primary hierarchy, then we are limited in our
                    representation of the document hierarchy. We use (as do most TEI projects
                    representing documents) sequences of the omnipresent <code>&lt;pb/&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;cb/&gt;</code>
                    and <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> elements to represent the document hierarchy, and for the great
                    majority of our documents and our purposes, this gives satisfactory
                        results.<note>This use of <code>&lt;pb/&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;cb/&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> cannot
                        cope with instances where the flow of lines on a page is disrupted by, for
                        example, multi-line marginalia or annotations. We could use
                        <code>&lt;milestone/&gt;</code> elements to mark out such instances.</note> Note that the
                    limitation is not in the DET scheme, and indeed the current move of Textual
                    Communities to a JSON-based architecture will also remove this limitation within
                    the system <q>backend</q>.The problem then will lie only in the XML structures we are
                    currently using in the editorial and display interfaces. However, despite this,
                    Textual Communities goes further than any other online collaborative editing
                    environment known to me in its support for both the document and structured
                    communicative act aspects of the text. Everyone of the more than thirty editing
                    systems listed by Ben Brumfield at <ref target="http://tinyurl.com/TranscriptionToolGDoc">http://tinyurl.com/TranscriptionToolGDoc</ref> is
                    either very limited in its support for recording communicative act components,
                    or supports page-based transcription only.<note>Brumfield does not mention two
                        powerful systems for the creation of fully TEI-compliant XML documents in
                        collaborative environments: TextGrid (www.textgrid.de/en/) and eLaborate
                        (www.elaborate.huygens.knaw.nl/login). Both will support the making of the
                        same complex TEI-XML documents as Textual Communities, but neither offers
                        the same native support for both page-based and <q>text-based</q> transcription
                        as does Textual Communities. Support for transcription by page, the best way
                        to apportion transcription of full manuscripts among transcribers, is
                        particularly crucial, and fully supported by Textual Communities.</note></p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The second axis of scholarly editions: editors and readers</head>
                <p>The definitions of document, text and work here offered, as the foundation of the
                    DET system, are valid for any text of any period, and might have been offered by
                    any scholar at any period. Documents vary in form, from inscription on stone to
                    computer file, but these definitions and these relations hold, no matter what
                    the medium. The digital age and the stringent mandates of computing systems
                    require that they be defined more precisely than before: but if the concepts are
                    valid, they were valid long before the invention of the computer. As earlier
                    remarked, the advent of digital methods has favoured the making of some kinds of
                    edition over others, but the fundamentals have not changed. However, this is not
                    the case for the second axis of scholarly editions: the range of relationships
                    between the makers of editions and their audiences. This has not just altered
                    the balance between one kind of edition and another. It has created many more
                    kinds of relationship between editor, edition and audience, enabling radically
                    new kinds of edition.</p>

                <p>It is now fundamental to the web that every reader may be a writer. The rise of
                    social media means that communication across the web happens in every direction:
                    now, routinely, every newspaper article on the web comes with a comments
                    section, often more interesting than the article itself (though, mostly, not).
                    The rise of <q>crowd-sourcing</q> leverages individual activity into collective
                    movements: crowd-sourcing has produced remarkable results in areas as diverse as
                    investigating the expense claims of politicians to transcription of museum
                    labels. There have been several ventures into the use of crowd-sourcing for
                    editorial purposes, notably the Transcribe Bentham and Easter 1916 projects
                        <ptr target="#causer2012"/>; <ptr target="#TrinityCollegeDublin2014"/> .
                    Crowdsourcing raises the possibility of editions which are not made by a single
                    editor, or even a group of editors, but by many people who may have no formal
                    relationship with each other, and indeed nothing in common except a shared
                    interest in a particular text. Further along the editor/audience axis, the ways
                    in which an edition may be distributed to its readers and used by them are also
                    vastly changed. While many readers may want just to read a text, others may wish
                    to take the text of a document, add information to it, alter it, enrich it,
                    correct it, combine it with other texts, and then republish it. Others in turn
                    might take up this republished text and alter it still further, in a
                    never-ending chain.</p>

                <p>It has to be said that the scholarly editing community, up to now, has been very
                    slow in responding to these new potentials. With respect to crowdsourcing: the
                    Bentham and Easter 1916 enterprises are not <q>crowdsourced</q> editions. Rather, the
                    framework of each edition, the flow of work, and all significant decisions
                    concerning transcription systems and the distribution of the product of the
                    editions are made by a small group of academic editors, as has always been the
                    case for scholarly editions. Any reader is invited to contribute transcriptions,
                    and the Easter 1916 system allows readers to go further, and contribute their
                    own documents. But the reader’s role is strictly limited, and the Bentham
                    project even prevents the reader changing a transcript he or she has made after
                    it has been <q>locked</q> by an editorial supervisor. T-Pen and other systems do
                    offer much more freedom to the editor, but at the cost of a very limited
                    encoding of the structure of communicative acts. Further, almost all scholarly
                    editing digital projects severely restrict how their output might be used. The
                    Jane Austen Fiction Manuscripts project <ptr target="#sutherland2010"/> has a
                    whole page bristling with restrictions: the site and everything on it is
                    protected by copyright, no derivative works are allowed, the editor asserts her
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#sutherland2010">moral right to be recognized as author and editor of aspects of this work</quote> (it
                    is not explained what <q>aspects</q> mean), <q>individual, non-commercial</q> use is
                    permitted, but <quote rend="inline" source="#sutherland2010">All other use is prohibited without the express written consent
                    of the editor. Any requests to use the work in a way not covered by this
                    permission should be directed to the editor.</quote> Indeed, most projects, while not
                    going so far as the Jane Austen project, do invoke the <q>non-commercial</q> clause
                    of the Creative Commons license. The effect of the <q>non-commercial</q> restriction,
                    as many have observed <ptr target="#möller2005"/>, is not just to restrict the
                    republication of online materials by commercial publishers: it is actually to
                    make it nearly impossible for anyone, commercial or non-commercial, individual
                    or corporate, to republish those materials on the web. The problem is the
                    ambiguity of what is <q>commercial</q>, what is <q>non-commercial</q>, in the web. If you
                    publish your edition in a university website, which also sells university
                    services, then it might be deemed commercial. If you publish it in your own
                    website and this happens to provide links to other sites which sell anything, or
                    even just belong to a commercial entity, then it might be deemed commercial –
                    even if you and your edition did not create those links. For these reasons, many
                    people will not touch any materials covered by the <q>non-commercial</q> license, in
                    any circumstances. Indeed, among the many online digital materials which have
                    been created by humanities scholars very few are both free of the non-commercial
                    restriction, and actually made readily available for free re-use and
                    re-publication. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Editions by everyone, for everyone</head>
                <p>Full realization of the possibilities of readerly involvement in the making and
                    use of editions depends on the materials being available for re-use and
                    re-publication without restriction. This applies at both ends of the edition
                    spectrum. One cannot reasonably expect that people who contribute transcriptions
                    and other materials to an edition will be willing to do so if they cannot make
                    use of their own transcriptions — or indeed, if they see that the editors are
                    limiting the ways the transcriber’s work may be used, for the benefit of the
                    editors. And of course, if you cannot be sure that you can freely distribute
                    your own work on materials derived from an edition, then you will likely look
                    elsewhere. For this reason, Textual Communities mandates that any materials
                    created on the site must be made available under the Creative Commons
                    Share-Alike Attribution licence (CC SA-BY); all software created by the project
                    is also available as open source at
                        https://github.com/DigitalResearchCentre.<note>This sentence provoked a
                        lively discussion in the Google Docs forum on the draft. Three commentators,
                        Andrew Dunning, Hugh Cayless and Laurent Romary, questioned the need for the
                        ‘SA’ condition. The nub of the problem is the expression of the ‘SA’
                        condition in Creative Commons and other ‘copyleft’ licenses, which insists
                        that all further share-alike be under the same terms as the granting terms.
                        This leads to a problem when a site wishes to mix together materials
                        licencsed under different share-alike flavours: this cannot be done. Thus,
                        although SA is conceived as a guarantee of continued open access, in
                        practice it has become a very real restriction, inhibiting the free re-use
                        we seek <ptr target="#wiley2007"/>. Accordingly, many recent open-access
                        sites have dropped the SA requirement, and Textual Communities is likely to
                        follow this lead.</note> The <q>attribution</q> requirement mandates that anyone
                    who worked on the creation of the materials must be acknowledged, at every point
                    along the publication chain. The <q>share-alike</q> requirement mandates that the
                    materials, no matter how altered, must be made available under the same terms as
                    they came to the user. This does not prevent a commercial publisher taking the
                    materials, altering them, and then making them available as part of a paid-for
                    publication: just that somehow, the publisher must make those altered materials
                    available, for free (for example, by deposit on a public webserver). Further,
                    Textual Communities provides an open API (Application Programmer’s Interface)
                    that makes it possibly for anyone with reasonable computer skills to extract any
                    texts from editions within the Textual Communities system in just a few lines of
                    code (see
                    <ref target="http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/textual-community/wiki/-/wiki/Main/The+API+Basics">http://www.textualcommunities.usask.ca/web/textual-community/wiki/-/wiki/Main/The+API+Basics</ref>).</p>

                <p>However, requiring that materials be made freely available is pointless if those
                    materials cannot be made in the first place. Some two decades into the digital
                    revolution, and people routinely send emails, create Word documents,
                    spreadsheets and Facebook pages. But paradoxically, it is no easier (and indeed,
                    arguably much harder) to create a scholarly edition than it was two decades ago.
                    It is certainly harder if one takes the TEI advice, to create two transcriptions
                    corresponding to the two aspects of text as document and text as structured
                    communicative act and link them together. Even in cases where one is not going
                    to make two parallel transcripts: the renowned complexity of the TEI guidelines,
                    and the webs of software and hardware needed to turn a TEI document into an
                    online publication continue to require that anyone who wants to make a scholarly
                    edition in digital form must both master a range of special skills and have
                    access to considerable technical resources. The effect has been to limit
                    drastically the number of people who can make scholarly editions in digital
                    form: in effect, to relatively few people typically at a few digital humanities
                    centres. Hence, a key aim of Textual Communities is to make it possible for
                    scholars to make digital editions without having to master more of the TEI than
                    is necessary for their particular task, and with no need for specialized
                    technical support. Further (perhaps over-ambitiously) we would like it to be
                    possible for an edition made with this system to be placed anywhere along the
                    range of relationships between the makers of editions and their readers. This
                    means that as well as make it as easy as we can to use, we need to support all
                    this range. Thus, in Textual Communities one can create a community where
                    everyone is an editor, everyone can freely change what everyone else does, and
                    everyone can take whatever is done and use it in any way they wish. Or, an
                    editor can allow only the people he or she invites to collaborate in making the
                    edition, and can insist that every page published on the edition must be
                    approved by an editor before publication.</p>

                <p>In order to support this range of roles, and to encourage community building and
                    partnerships, Textual Communities is based on social media software,
                    specifically on the LifeRay implementation of the Open Social software suite,
                    itself used by Google as a foundation of its <title rend="quotes">Google Plus</title> social
                        network.<note>The second version of Textual Communities has abandoned the
                        LifeRay environment here described: in practice, LifeRay has considerable
                        difficulties, not least its vulnerability to <q>spam bots</q>, which routinely
                        dump spam within LifeRay documents.</note> This allows every community
                    within Textual Communities to have its own Wiki, Blog, Bulletin Board and Chat
                    facility. The screenshot below shows how Textual Communities appears to a user
                    within the Canterbury Tales community:</p>
                <!--Figure 3: The Canterbury Tales community within Textual Communities: access contents by page.-->
                
                <figure>
                    <head>The Canterbury Tales community within Textual Communities: access contents by page</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>At the top of the screen, the <q>Wiki</q>, <q>Blog</q> and <q>Bulletin Board</q> links take the
                    reader to the wiki, etc., for this community. To the right, we see an image
                    above of the manuscript page; below that, the transcription of this page, in the
                    last version saved by the transcriber. Notice that the <q>Compare with</q> tool
                    allows the transcriber to compare different revisions of the transcription. This
                    system does not attempt to hide the XML: we think it helpful for the editor and
                    transcribers to see exactly what encoding is being applied to the document. Nor
                    have we had any difficulty with transcribers at any level, including
                    undergraduates, understanding and using the XML we use in these page transcripts
                    (observe that, as a fully-compliant TEI implementation, any valid XML may occur
                    within the transcripts). Note too the use of explicit <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> elements at
                    the beginning of every manuscript line to structure the document. The buttons at
                    the base permit the transcriber to preview the document, showing it without the
                    XML and formatted for ease of reading, to save the transcript, and carry out
                    various other editorial activities (including, <q>Link Pages</q>, which allows the
                    editor to connect text which flows across the page boundaries).</p>

                <p>At the left of the screen, you can see the table of contents, showing the
                    document page by page. This table of contents is generated directly by Textual
                    Communities from the XML, following the schema for document elements set out in
                    the <code>&lt;refsDcl&gt;</code> element. If you click on the <q>By Item</q> tab, the table of
                    contents changes:</p>
                <!--Figure 4: The Canterbury Tales community within Textual Communities: access contents by entity.-->
                
                <figure>
                    <head>The Canterbury Tales community within Textual Communities: access contents by entity</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>Now, for the document Hg, we can access its contents by entity: that is, by the
                    components of the communicative act. Thus, it first contains the General
                    Prologue, which itself contains a sequence of line entities: first the initial
                    rubric (<q>IRE</q>) and then the first and following lines. Again, the information
                    about the entities is generated directly by Textual Communities from the XML,
                    following the schema set out for the textual entities in the <code>&lt;refsDcl&gt;</code>
                    element. Finally, the <q>Collations</q> interface allows the reader to see the
                    collation of the text in all the documents.</p>

                <!--Figure 5: The collation of the eighth line of the General Prologue-->
                
                <figure>
                    <head>The collation of the eighth line of the General Prologue</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>The collation here is built on the CollateX system, here extended by the addition
                    of regularization and other facilities for adjusting the collation.</p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Textual Communities, like any computing system, is in constant development. We
                    have not yet announced it publically, and will not do so until we are fully
                    satisfied as to its robustness and usability. We are also aware that the demands
                    of comparatively few users (six major communities, some one hundred and fifty
                    active transcribers and editors) already place considerable strain on the
                    current installation, on a virtual server at the University of Saskatchewan. We
                    are both translating the system to the MongoDB backend and moving it to the
                    Compute Canada cloud (one of the first Digital Humanities projects to be hosted
                    on this service, hitherto devoted to <q>hard science</q> data). However, it is not at
                    all our aim that the whole world, or at even a significant part of the whole
                    scholarly editing community, should use Textual Communities. We are more
                    concerned that the concepts behind Textual Communities should be promulgated.
                    Firstly, we argue that scholars understand the reasoning behind the
                    text/documents/entities division, with its insistence on the double aspect of
                    the communicative act present in any textual document. Secondly, we argue that
                    it should be possible for any textual scholar to make an edition, with a minimum
                    of specialist computing and encoding knowledge and technical support. This
                    requires that computing systems need to respond to the needs of scholars, rather
                    than scholars restrict their editions to what computer systems can support.
                    Thirdly, scholarly editing, perhaps more than any other area of the humanities,
                    is uniquely positioned to profit from the social web. Scholars and readers may
                    engage together in understanding documents, the texts they contain, and the
                    complex histories of works which they compose. If we are able to move our
                    discipline a small way in those directions, we will have done well.</p>
            </div>


        </body>

        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Blackwell 2014" xml:id="blackwell2014">Blackwell, Christopher, Smith,
                    Neel. <title rend="quotes">The Homer Multitext: Technically speaking</title>, <title rend="italic">The Homer
                        Multitext</title>.
                    <ref target="http://homermultitext.blogspot.nl/2014/02/technically-speaking.html">http://homermultitext.blogspot.nl/2014/02/technically-speaking.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Bordalejo 2010" xml:id="bordalejo2010">Bordalejo, Barbara. <title rend="quotes">Appendix C:
                    The Encoding System</title>, In Prue Shaw (ed.) <title rend="italic">Dante Alighieri. Commedia. A
                        Digital Edition</title>. Scholarly Digital Editions, Birmingham and Sismel,
                    Florence (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bordalejo 2013" xml:id="bordalejo2013">Bordalejo, Barbara (ed.)
                        <title rend="italic">Work, Text and Document in the Digital Age</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Ecdotica</title>, 10 (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bornstein 2001" xml:id="bornstein2001">Bornstein, George.
                        <title rend="italic">Material Modernism: The Politics of the Page</title>. Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Brüning 2013" xml:id="brüningetal2013">Brüning, G, Henzel K., and
                    Pravida, D. <title rend="quotes">Multiple Encoding in Genetic Editions: The Case of ‘Faust’</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> [Online]. URL:
                    <ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/697">http://jtei.revues.org/697</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Causer 2012" xml:id="causer2012">Causer, T., Tonra, J. and Wallace, V.
                    <title rend="quotes">Transcription maximized; expense minimized? Crowdsourcing and editing The
                    Collected Works of Jeremy Bentham</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                        Computing</title> 27, pp. 119-137 (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl label="DeRose 1990" xml:id="derose1990">De Rose, Steven, Durand, David,
                    Mylonas, Elli, Renear, Allen. <title rend="quotes">What is Text, Really?</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Computing in Higher Education</title> 1(2), pp. 3-26 (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Eggert 2009" xml:id="eggert2009">Eggert, Paul. <title rend="italic">Securing the Past:
                        Conservation in Art, Architecture and Literature</title>. Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Eggert 2010" xml:id="eggert2010">Eggert, Paul. <title rend="quotes">Text as Algorithm and
                    as Process</title>. In W. McCarty (ed.) <title rend="italic">Text and Genre in Reconstruction: Effects
                        of Digitalization on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and Institutions</title>.
                    Open Book Publishers, Cambridge, pp. 183-202 (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gabler 1984" xml:id="gabler1984">Gabler, Hans Walter. <title rend="quotes">The Synchrony
                    and Diachrony of Texts: Practice and Theory of the Critical Edition of James
                    Joyce’s Ulysses</title>. <title rend="italic">Text</title>, 1, pp. 305–26 (1984).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gabler 1990" xml:id="gabler1990">Gabler, Hans Walter. <title rend="quotes">Textual Studies
                    and Criticism</title>, <title rend="italic">The Library Chronicle</title>, The University of Texas at
                    Austin, pp. 151–65 (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gabler 2007" xml:id="gabler2007">Gabler, Hans Walter. <title rend="quotes">The Primacy of
                    the Document in Editing</title>, <title rend="italic">Ecdotica</title>, 4, pp. 197–207 (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl label="IFLA 1998" xml:id="IFLA1998"><title rend="italic">Functional Requirements for
                        Bibliographic Records</title>. IFLA Series on Bibliographic Control. Munich,
                    K. G. Saur (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Kahn 2006" xml:id="kahn2006">Kahn, Robert and Wilensky, Robert. <title rend="quotes">A
                    Framework for Distributed Digital Object Services</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal
                        on Digital Libraries</title> 6(2), pp. 115–123 (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Maryland 2014" xml:id="maryland2014">Maryland Institute for Technology
                    in the Humanities, et al. <title rend="italic">Shelley-Godwin archive</title>.
                    <ref target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="McGann 1983" xml:id="mcgann1983">McGann, Jerome J. <title rend="italic">A Critique of
                        Modern Textual Criticism</title>. Chicago, Chicago University Press
                    (1983).</bibl>
                <bibl label="McKenzie 1999" xml:id="mcKenzie1999">McKenzie, Donald F.
                        <title rend="italic">Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts (The Panizzi Lectures,
                        1985)</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Möller 2005" xml:id="möller2005">Möller, Erik. <title rend="quotes">Creative Commons -NC
                    Licenses Considered Harmful</title>.
                    <ref target="http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2005/9/11/16331/0655">http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2005/9/11/16331/0655</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Muñoz 2013" xml:id="muñozetal2013">Muñoz, Trevor, Viglianti, Raffaele,
                    Fraistat, Neil. <title rend="quotes">Texts and Documents: new challenges for TEI interchange and the
                    possibilities for participatory archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Abstracts for TEI Members
                        conference</title> (2013).
                    <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2013/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/book-abstracts.pdf#page=99">http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2013/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/book-abstracts.pdf#page=99</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Nichols 1990" xml:id="nichols1990">Nichols, Stephen (ed.) <title rend="italic"><title rend="quotes">The
                        new philology</title>, Special issue of Speculum: A Journal of Medieval
                        Studies</title>, LXV (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Noviskie 2013" xml:id="noviskie2013">Noviskie, Bethany.
                        <title rend="italic">Resistance in the materials</title>.
                    <ref target="http://nowviskie.org/2013/resistance-in-the-materials/">http://nowviskie.org/2013/resistance-in-the-materials/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="O’Keefe 2006" xml:id="okeefe2006">O’Keefe, Katherine O’Brien.
                        <title rend="italic">Visible Song: Transitional Literacy in Old English Verse</title>.
                    Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Parker 1997" xml:id="parker1997">Parker, David C. <title rend="italic">The Living Text
                        of the Gospels</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pierazzo 2011" xml:id="pierazzo2011">Pierazzo, Elena. <title rend="quotes">A Rationale of
                    Digital Documentary editions</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>,
                    26 pp. 463-477 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Renear 1993" xml:id="renear1993">Renear, Allen, Mylonas, Elli, Durand,
                    David. <title rend="italic">Refining Our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of
                        Overlapping Hierarchies</title>, Brown
                    University. <ref target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html">http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Robinson 1996" xml:id="robinson1996">Robinson, Peter M. W. <title rend="quotes">Is there a
                    text in these variants?</title>, In R. Finneran (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Literary Text in the
                        Digital Age</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, pp. 99-115
                    (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Robinson 2004" xml:id="robinson2004">Robinson, Peter M. W. (ed.)
                        <title rend="italic">Geoffrey Chaucer. The Miller’s Tale on CD-ROM</title>. Scholarly
                    Digital Editions, Leicester (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Robinson 2013a" xml:id="robinson2013a">Robinson, Peter M. W. <title rend="quotes">Towards A
                    Theory of Digital Editions</title>, <title rend="italic">Variants</title>, 10, pp. 105-132
                    (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Robinson 2013b" xml:id="robinson2013b">Robinson, Peter M. W. <title rend="quotes">The
                    Concept of the Work in the Digital Age</title>, In Barbara, Bordalejo (ed.) <title rend="italic">Work,
                        Text and Document in the Digital Age</title>, <title rend="italic">Ecdotica</title>, 10, pp.
                    13-41 (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Robinson forthcoming" xml:id="robinsonforthcoming">Robinson, Peter M.
                    W. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Revolution in Scholarly Editing</title>, <title rend="italic">Ars Edendi Lecture
                        Series</title>, IV, Stockholm University, Stockholm.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Schloen 2014" xml:id="schloen2014">Schloen, David, Schloen, Sandra.
                    <title rend="quotes">Beyond Gutenberg: Transcending the Document Paradigm in Digital Humanities</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 8(4) (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Schmidt 2009" xml:id="schmidt2009">Schmidt, D. and Colomb, R. <title rend="quotes">A Data
                    Structure for Representing Multi-version Texts Online</title>, <title rend="italic">International
                        Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title>, 67, pp. 497-514 (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Shaw 2010" xml:id="shaw2010"><title rend="italic">Shaw, Prue. Dante Alighieri. Commedia. A Digital Edition</title>. Scholarly Digital Editions,
                    Birmingham and Sismel, Florence (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Shillingsburg 2007" xml:id="shillingsburg2007">Shillingsburg, Peter.
                        <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sparling 1924" xml:id="sparling1924">Sparling, Henry H. <title rend="italic">The
                        Kelmscott Press and William Morris, Master Craftsman</title>. London (1924).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sutherland 2010" xml:id="sutherland2010">Sutherland, Kathryn (ed.)
                         <title rend="italic">Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts: A Digital Edition</title>.
                    <ref target="http://www.janeausten.ac.uk">http://www.janeausten.ac.uk</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Tillett 2004" xml:id="tillett2004">Tillett, Barbara. <title rend="italic">FRBR: A
                        Conceptual Model for the Bibliographic Universe</title>. Library of Congress
                    Cataloging Distribution Service (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Trinity College Dublin 2014" xml:id="TrinityCollegeDublin2014"><title rend="italic">Letters of 1916: Creating History</title>.
                    <ref target="http://dh.tcd.ie/letters1916/">http://dh.tcd.ie/letters1916/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Wiley 2007" xml:id="wiley2007">Wiley, David. <title rend="quotes">Noncommercial Isn’t the
                    Problem, ShareAlike Is</title>, <title rend="italic">Open Content</title>, 17 July 2007.
                    <ref target="http://opencontent.org/blog/archives/347">http://opencontent.org/blog/archives/347</ref> (Accessed 25 June 2015).</bibl>

            </listBibl>
        </back>



    </text>
</TEI>