<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Sound and Digital Humanities: reflecting on a DHSI
                    course</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>John F. <dhq:family>Barber</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>The Creative Media &amp; Digital Culture Program, Washington
                        State University Vancouver</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jfbarber@eaze.net</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>convenes with the faculty of Creative Media &amp; Digital Culture at
                            Washington State University Vancouver. As part of his interest in sound,
                            Barber developed and maintains Radio Nouspace (<ref
                                target="http://www.radionouspace.net/"
                                >http://www.radionouspace.net</ref>), a web-based radio station,
                            interactive installation / performance work, practice-based research
                            site, and virtual museum, all focused on sound as a primary component of
                            digital narrative, drama, and storytelling. His radio+sound art work has
                            been broadcast internationally, and featured in juried exhibitions in
                            America, Canada, Germany, Portugal, and Macedonia. A recent multimedia
                            performance installation with voice is <title rend="quotes">Remembering
                                the Dead,</title> an elegiac piece that speaks the names of victims
                            of intentional gun violence in America in 2015 (<ref
                                target="http://dtc.wsuv.org/remember-the-dead"
                                >http://dtc-wsuv.org/remembering-the-dead</ref>).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000239</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2016-02-12">12 February 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital pedagogy</item>
                        <item>sound</item>
                        <item>sound editing</item>
                        <item>sound studies</item>
                        <item>sound art</item>
                        <item>digital humanities</item>
                        <item>information representation</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>The creation and utilization of sound as a methodology for information
                    representation is intriguing for Digital Humanities research, teaching, and
                    practice. However, scholars, researchers, and artists may lack appreciation
                    and/or ability for using sound(s) to enhance or ground their research /
                    presentations. In response, the author created and taught a week-long course,
                        <title rend="quotes">Sound of / in Digital Humanities,</title> offered
                    during the 2014 Digital Humanities Summer Institute. This essay reflects on the
                    course, its planning, implementation, and outcomes and offers insight into the
                    role sound might play in the research, communication, and consumption of Digital
                    Humanities. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>A reflection on a DHSI course on the role of sound in DH research, communication,
                    and consumption.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head><title rend="italic">Sound and Digital Humanities: reflecting on a DHSI
                    course</title>
            </head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This essay discusses the <title rend="quotes">Sound and Digital
                        Humanities</title> course offered during the week-long 2014 Digital
                    Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI) at the University of Victoria, Victoria,
                    British Columbia, Canada, 2-6 June. The focus of this course was promoting sound
                    and aural representation of information in Digital Humanities (DH) research,
                    teaching, and practice.</p>
                <p>This course evolved from previous experience at DHSI. During the summers of 2012
                    and 2013, I collaborated with colleagues from the Creative Media &amp; Digital
                    Culture faculty at Washington State University Vancouver to provide a course
                    focusing on <title rend="quotes">Creating Digital Humanities Projects for the
                        Mobile Environment.</title> Participants were, I observed, quick to
                    visualize information in their apps using video, graphics, or animation. Sound,
                    however, was often overlooked, primarily because participants lacked insight as
                    to how it might be used.<note> A growing area of interest in the digital
                        humanities is the mobile environment, especially projects that take
                        advantage of the affordances of smart phones and tablets. This course,
                        derived from the Mobile Tech Research Initiative of The Creative Media &amp;
                        Digital Culture Program at Washington State University Vancouver, was aimed
                        at assisting participants to: 1) conceptualize the space and special
                        features of mobile devices; 2) develop the architecture, design, and
                        multimedia content production for a mobile project; and 3) understand the
                        coding and programming requirements for mobile devices. By the end of the
                        course, participants had information they needed for creating projects for
                        the mobile environment and had completed steps toward the development of
                        their own projects. Archival website: <ref
                            target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/wp/dhsi/2011/06/08/mobile-tech-research-initiative-mtri/"
                            >http://dtc-wsuv.org/wp/dhsi/2011/06/08/mobile-tech-research-initiative-mtri/</ref></note></p>
                <p>Based on that observation, and a belief that sound plays an important role in
                    arts and humanities research and scholarship, I proposed a course titled <title
                        rend="quotes">Sound and Digital Humanities</title> to be offered during DHSI
                        2014.<note> Learn more about this course. <ref
                            target="http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/sounds-and-digital-humanities/"
                            >http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/sounds-and-digital-humanities/</ref></note></p>
                <p>This essay reflects on the course, its planning, implementation, and outcomes. I
                    first situate sound as a worthy context for DH work, one that, unfortunately,
                    has been under explored. Next, I outline, from a practice orientation, basic
                    assumptions, and from them, daily goals, objectives, activities, and outcomes
                    for this week-long course. The following section takes a more theoretical tone
                    as I provide an overview of ideological approaches to sound and sound studies.
                    This combination of theory and practice, subjective and objective, I hope, will
                    be illustrative of my approach to this course, and provide a case study for
                    others seeking a similar approach for their own DH research/work. My conclusion
                    suggests that sound provides interesting opportunities for DH research,
                    scholarship, and practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Context</head>
                <p>DH is an area of interdisciplinary, collaborative research and practice at the
                    intersection of digital computing technologies and the disciplines of the
                    humanities. The hybrid approach of DH involves combining digitized or
                    born-digital materials, and methodologies from disciplines such as art, art
                    history, archaeology, cultural studies, literary criticism, philology, and
                    others, with computing tools like data mining and/or visualization, digital
                    mapping and/or publishing, information retrieval, and statistics. Practices
                    include analysis, coding, curation, criticism, databases, digitization, document
                    analysis, geographical information systems, information digitization /
                    visualization, multimedia publications, pedagogy, project management, text
                    encoding, processing, and visualization. The results influence creation,
                    dissemination, preservation, research, and teaching activities. The desired
                    outcome is to answer or challenge existing research paradigms, as well as
                    suggest new research questions and approaches. This essay brings sound into the
                    mix.</p>
                <p><q>Sound</q> is the name we give our physical, subjective experience of acoustic
                    energy — a sequence of pressure variations — that travel through a medium (air,
                    gas, water) to our ears. Sound may have a variety of sources but is usually one
                    object moving over or striking another, thus creating vibrations. For example,
                    air passing over human vocal cords and then modulated by tongue, teeth, mouth,
                    and lips produces the sounds we know as speech. Sound travels in all directions
                    from its source in waves and is heard (experienced as sound) when it interacts
                    with appropriate listening devices, like human ears. The higher the energy
                    involved with its production, the louder the sound is perceived. But, unless
                    preserved in some manner, all sound is ephemeral, disappearing soon after its
                    creation.</p>
                <p>Regarding sound, scholar Bruce R. Smith, discussing his research of sounds
                    associated with London, circa 1600, notes many sounds, unless they have been
                    recorded, are no longer available for study, or are difficult to study. For
                    example, the only source for studying historical speech accents might be
                    impressions / depictions written by authors, travelers, or journalists <ptr
                        target="#smith2003"/>.</p>
                <p>DH scholars have long been able to discuss developments in film and television
                    because of the ability to situate commentary alongside or directly within visual
                    media as it unfolds over time. But, the ability to do the same with sound has
                    not been widely possible until the introduction of SoundCloud in 2007. According
                    to Jonathan Sterne, as they become more widely available, evolving affordances
                    like looping an audio file; setting begin and end points; setting the volume;
                    tagging, commenting, annotating; close listening (via skipping around, speeding
                    up, slowing down, scrubbing, freezing); and comparing different channel formats
                    will increase opportunities for sound-focused scholarship <ptr
                        target="#sterne2011"/>.</p>
                <p>More specifically, Annie Murray and Jared Wiercinski describe how listening and
                    annotation are essential endeavors for DH scholars undertaking literary
                    criticism on poetry sound recordings. They present a methodology for designing a
                    web-based sound archive for literary criticism and propose features and
                    functionalities that facilitate this criticism <ptr target="#murray2014"/>.</p>
                <p>Despite such pioneering efforts, Allison Whitney says DH scholarship, with its
                    embrace of images, animation, video, or text as image for research and
                    information presentation, is biased toward visuals. Sound is largely overlooked
                        <ptr target="#whitney2008"/>. Part of the reason for this may be technical,
                    as noted by Sterne, previously. Another factor may hinge on what Tara McPherson
                    notes as DH's historical focus on the use of digital media / technology to
                    critique / analyze print. Less attention, she says, has been given to scholars'
                    ability to shift from commenting about new media and technologies to
                    constructing arguments with and through them <ptr target="#mcpherson2009"/>.
                    This will change, however, with the development and availability of tools that
                    facilitate the comparison and mining of complex information source relationships
                    and their multimodal publication. eBooks provide interesting opportunities, as
                    do web content development tools like WordPress and Scalar.<note> Jentery Sayers
                        introduces Scalar as designed for authoring and publishing multimodal books
                        through its ability to assemble multiple media files and juxtapose them with
                        one’s writing. A Scalar book assumes digital communications frequently
                        entails blending approaches to composition (images, sound, video, text, and
                        databases, for example). With regard to sound, such affordances enable
                        authors to <cit>
                            <quote rend="block" source="#sayers2012">represent audio [recorded
                                sound(s)] across the material specificities of multiple media
                                (rather than reducing audio to simply sound or text). It also allows
                                historical evidence to be modeled and exhibited independently of the
                                author’s writing (e.g., audiences can navigate all audio files
                                collected for the history without reading the author’s
                                interpretations). However, any given audio file in a Scalar book can
                                be annotated through discrete, time-stamped commentary by the
                                author, and this commentary is displayed within the medium’s own
                                temporality. While such features are now typical in visual culture
                                (e.g., annotating lexia in Commentpress or tagging an image in
                                Flickr), few such mechanisms exist for the scholarly treatment of
                                sound.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#sayers2012"/>
                        </cit></note></p>
                <p>Sound(s) should facilitate such intersections and comparisons as well. Imagine
                    Smith being able to compare voice dialects using embedded sound files. Or,
                    another DH researcher using sound(s) of speech to mark or define boundaries
                    between research areas — between class, gender, or race relations, for example.
                    Aural artifacts might include soundscapes, sound maps, sound collages, and
                    remixes; digital storytelling (perhaps in transmedia projects); aural and oral
                    histories / biographies / documentaries; curated exhibitions / installations /
                    performances / broadcasts; or as stand alone artifacts (embedded sound,
                    podcasts, web-based radio, archives, curated collections). However, DH scholars
                    may lack appreciation and/or ability for using sound(s) to enhance or ground
                    their research / presentations. In response, I proposed the <title rend="quotes"
                        >Sound and Digital Humanities</title> course to introduce, explore, and
                    investigate how sounds might be utilized in DH research and information
                    presentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Assumptions</head>
                <p>DHSI convenes colleagues from the arts, humanities, library, archives, and other
                    communities to share ideas and develop skills using digital, computational, and
                    network technologies for teaching, researching, sharing, creating, and
                    preserving in their disciplines. The atmosphere is informal, friendly, and
                    community-based. As noted, during summers 2012 and 2013, I helped facilitate
                    courses in building DH applications for mobile environments. From this previous
                    experience, I felt I could establish some descriptors for potential course
                    participants. For example, participants would <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Be post-graduate faculty, librarians, and graduate students.</item>
                        <item>Align their own research interests with sound. However, their desired
                            course outcomes might not be finalized.</item>
                        <item>Differ regarding theory vs. practice. Some would want only or
                            primarily to theorize sound. Others would want a theoretical framework
                            but also an opportunity to engage in creative practices of recording,
                            editing, and manipulating sound for research and presentation. Others
                            would want only to learn what could be done with sound in order to
                            inspire future projects.</item>
                        <item>Begin with only rudimentary sound design / editing skills. Or none.
                            They might wish to learn sufficient skills for use in their classes, or
                            to inform their own work(s).</item>
                        <item>Appreciate some course structure, but more so, flexibility to explore
                            topics as they arose.</item>
                        <item>Desire to complete the course feeling they gained new knowledge and
                            opportunity for research, presentation, or creative activity in the arts
                            and humanities.</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Course Goals and Objectives</head>
                <p>Based on these assumptions, my course, as planned, would assume no previous
                    knowledge of recording and/or editing sound files. It would survey different
                    sound genres and their use in DH projects. The course would be flexible, able to
                    adapt to the participants' projects, and allow time for workshops and hands-on,
                    learning-by-doing, collaborative learning experiences. As course facilitator, I
                    outlined goals, objectives, activities, discussion, and workshops for each day
                    of the course.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 1</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Goals</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Understand the broad and important applications of sound to
                                various DH endeavors.</item>
                            <item>Understand basic equipment needs / configurations for sound work
                                in DH.</item>
                            <item>Understand basics of sound recording and editing, and how to build
                                on those basics.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Objectives</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Introduce participants to sound production / editing.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Projects</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Learn and apply basic sound editing and manipulation skills to
                                reduce an hour-long radio drama into ten minutes or less, while
                                maintaining narrative continuity.</item>
                            <item>Plan the overarching structure of a collaborative sound
                                composition illustrating the breadth and richness of sounds for the
                                DHSI-wide show-and-tell session scheduled for the final day.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 2</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Goals</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Understand that sound provides a place for embodied social and
                                cultural traces through discussion of a theoretical framework for
                                using sound.</item>
                            <item>Understand that various forms of auditory culture can provide
                                foundations for defined areas of DH practices.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Objectives</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Appreciate principles of fair use (fair dealing in Canada) for DH
                                projects.</item>
                            <item>Appreciate other best practices associated with the use of
                                sound(s) for scholarship and creative endeavors.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Projects</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Examine resources and discuss applications. Continue work on both
                                individual and collaborative sound projects.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 4</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Goals</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Understand different ways in which sonic DH projects can be
                                packaged and distributed.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Objectives</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Understand basic concepts of streaming, on demand, downloading,
                                and podcasting as ways to share sound-based/-augmented DH
                                projects.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 5</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Goals</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Reflect on and evaluate the role of sound(s) in DH
                                projects.</item>
                            <item>Reflect on and evaluate course learning opportunities.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Objectives</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Discuss future use of course knowledge in individual sound-based
                                DH projects.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Project</head>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Engage in the DHSI-wide show and tell session.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Example Course Outcomes</head>
                <p>Outcomes from this course went far beyond my expectations. Where many course
                    participants arrived with an individual project, each left with a shared and
                    collaboratively constructed body of knowledge regarding the theory and
                    application of sound-augmented DH projects. Specifically, participants could
                        <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Effectively theorize the use of sound as a medium for experiencing and
                            communicating information in DH projects.</item>
                        <item>Manipulate and edit sound files for presentation in DH
                            projects.</item>
                        <item>Appreciate different categorization, archival, and curatorial systems
                            / practices regarding sound(s) in DH projects.</item>
                        <item>Effectively use different forms of sound distribution for DH
                            projects.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>A brief discussion of each day's outcome(s) follows.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 1</head>
                    <p>As the basis for the sound editing project, participants downloaded a digital
                        sound file of the 30 October 1938 radio drama broadcast, <title
                            rend="italic">The War of the Worlds</title>. Directed by and starring
                        Orson Welles and The Mercury Theatre on the Air, this is, arguably, the most
                        influential radio broadcast of all time.<note> As part of my Radio Nouspace
                            project (<ref target="http://www.radionouspace.net"
                                >http://www.radionouspace.net</ref>), I maintain archival and
                            curatorial information focusing on <title rend="italic">The War of the
                                Worlds</title> radio broadcast (<ref
                                target="http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/the-war-of-the-worlds"
                                >http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/the-war-of-the-worlds</ref>).
                            I provide links to sound files of the original radio broadcast, the
                            program script, responses, and remediations, as well as to curation by
                            re-creation projects undertaken with students in my digital storytelling
                            class.</note> The challenge was to edit this hour-long performance into
                        a coherent narrative ten minutes in length, or less. Course participants
                        discussed the overall structure of their edited sound compositions, and how
                        their particular perspectives on sound (many participants were working with
                        collections of recorded poetry readings / poet interviews) contributed to
                        the resulting artifact.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 2</head>
                    <p>As a starting point for discussing auditory culture, participants considered
                        Steven Feld's attention to <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#feld2003">the primacy of sound as a
                                modality of knowing and being in the world</quote>
                            <ptr target="#feld2003" loc="226"/>
                        </cit>. This opened our discussion to different types of listening: <q>deep</q> or <q>agile</q> listening proposed by Michael Bull and Les
                        Beck, acousmatic listening proposed by Pierre Schaeffer, and ambient
                        listening proposed by Brian Eno. More information in the <title
                            rend="quotes">Theoretical Framework</title> section, below.</p>
                    <p>Sound, we agreed, provides a place in which embodied social and cultural
                        traces can be carried, often without the awareness of their bearers <ptr
                            target="#schafer1977"/>. By carefully considering sound, however, we
                        open new ways of thinking about and appreciating the social experience,
                        memory, time, and place — the auditory culture — of sound <ptr
                            target="#bull2003" loc="12"/>.</p>
                    <p>As specific examples of auditory culture, we discussed aural / oral history,
                        biography / documentary, and sound archives. Aural history is a method of
                        gathering and preserving historical information through recorded sounds
                        which provide context, background, and deep, rich information about the
                        subject. Aural histories may include voice recordings regarding some
                        historic event or way of life, but they are primarily composed of
                        environmental / mechanical sounds.</p>
                    <p>With oral history, the primary audio emphasis is the human voice as a speaker
                        tells her eye witness account, experience(s), or opinion(s) of past events /
                        ways of life. The use of video recording includes gesture as part of the
                        communication, thus expanding oral history beyond verbal form.</p>
                    <p>Audio biographies and documentaries may provide additional access to cultural
                        and historical information contained in or provided by sound(s). The
                        remainder of the day's discussion and exploration centered on the efforts of
                        sound archives to archive and curate sound(s), either broadly defined or
                        specifically focused. Participants explored sound archives online and
                        discussed their relative affordances in light of their own sound-based DH
                        projects.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 3</head>
                    <p>The focus of this day's class was rights associated with audio files, and how
                        these might affect their utilization in DH projects. Copyright, fair use,
                        and creative commons were at the forefront of our discussions. The Statute
                        of Anne (1710) established principles of an author's ownership of copyright
                        and provided a fixed term of protection for copyrighted works (fourteen
                        years). Since then, U.S. law has been revised to broaden the scope of
                        copyright, change the term of copyright protection, and address new
                        technologies. Section 107, Limitations on Exclusive Rights: Fair Use of The
                        Copyright Act of 1976 provides exemptions, in certain contexts, to the
                        exclusive rights built into the copyright law. Participants from Canada and
                        the United Kingdom added their understanding of copyright considerations in
                        their home countries, thus broadening the discussion. Creative Commons (CC)
                        provides a model for how creative works might be shared. Essentially,
                        Creative Commons licenses allow photographers, artists, educators, and
                        others to license their work in advance as content for creative endeavors by
                        others. We discussed these implications for course participants' individual
                        projects.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 4</head>
                    <p>Making sound files available for listening and further DH research /
                        presentation is important. <emph>Streaming</emph> provides content on a
                        continuous basis. Listeners can tune in or out at will, as with traditional
                        radio broadcasting. But, they can also pause, stop, and start the program
                        stream at will. The stream is ongoing and particular portions cannot be
                        heard again unless they are recorded in some manner.
                            <emph>Downloading</emph> involves transferring a sound file from a
                        remote computer to a local computer where it can be saved and listened to
                        whenever desired. <emph>Podcasting</emph> refers generally to an audio
                        episode, self-contained, sometimes augmented by text or visuals, that can be
                        either streamed or downloaded. <emph>On demand</emph> speaks to sharing an
                        audio file only when it is needed or desired by the listener. The listener
                        evokes the playback process by interacting with an audio player. The audio
                        file plays through to conclusion and then, since it is embedded in the
                        interface, can be evoked repeatedly.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Day 5</head>
                    <p>Course participants contributed samples from their individual or course
                        projects, audio biographies, found sounds, field recordings, oral histories,
                        poetry, and creative sound arts, to a collaborative project that was shared
                        with others during a DHSI-wide final-day show-and-tell session. The sound
                        file they created as a course artifact was a narrative of human endeavor
                        that, like DH, is deep and rich, broad and diverse.<note> This sound file,
                            along with the one produced by 2015 course participants, can be heard on
                            the <title rend="quotes">Sounds and Digital Humanities</title> page of
                            my Radio Nouspace website. Learn more at <ref
                                target="http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/sounds-and-digital-humanities"
                                >http://www.radionouspace.net/index.php/sounds-and-digital-humanities</ref></note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Theoretical Framework</head>
                <p>Perhaps an overarching course outcome would be the realization that even in the
                    visual context of contemporary life, sound remains a powerful sensory input, and
                    a fundamental factor in many arenas of inquiry for DH: speech, writing,
                    literature, reading, narrative, storytelling, and listening.<note> I outline a
                        theoretical framework for sound as the basis for storytelling and use it to
                        underpin Radio Nouspace and its associated projects, like Re-Imagined Radio
                        and my DHSI Sounds and Digital Humanities course. Discussion, resources, and
                        additional links are available at <ref
                            target="http://radionouspace.net/index.php/theoretical-framework/"
                            >http://radionouspace.net/index.php/theoretical-framework/</ref></note></p>
                <p>Regarding the power of sound as a sensory input, film editor and sound designer
                    Walter Murch says sound is the earliest sensory stimulus available to humans,
                    switching on <quote rend="inline" source="#murch2005">four-and-a-half months
                        after we are conceived.</quote> Newborns rely predominately on hearing
                    before their visual acuity has stabilized <ptr target="#murch2005"/>.</p>
                <p>Communications theorist Marshall McLuhan echoes this point when he argues sound
                    provided the first frame of reference through which humankind attempted to
                    create and communicate a world view. McLuhan, with his son and collaborator,
                    Eric, describes two spaces, acoustic and visual, in which humankind has
                    contextualized itself with different results: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1988">Acoustic space . . . is
                            spherical, discontinuous, non-homogeneous, resonant, and dynamic. Visual
                            space is structured as static, abstract figure minus a ground; acoustic
                            space is a flux in which figure and ground rub against and transform
                            each other</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcluhan1988" loc="33"/>
                    </cit>.<note>
                        <p>Marshall McLuhan, with his son and collaborator, Eric, expanded the terms
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1988">figure</quote> and
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1988">ground,</quote> both
                            coined by psychologist and phenomenologist Edgar Rubin in 1915, to
                            explore visual perception. By figure, the McLuhans mean any object
                            rising from or receding into ground. Ground is surface, configurational
                            and comprised of all available figures <ptr target="#mcluhan1988"
                                loc="5"/>. As Thomas MacFarlane explains, ground is subliminal,
                            always beyond perception except through analysis of emerging and
                            receding figures <ptr target="#macfarlane2013" loc="62"/>. We may
                            connect ground and figure with McLuhan’s idea of acoustic space.
                            Acoustic space is ground, the surface from which emerge figures (sounds)
                            and into which they recede.</p> MacFarlane provides an interesting
                        example in his book, <title rend="italic">The Beatles and McLuhan:
                            Understanding the Electric Age</title>. MacFarlane discusses how The
                        Beatles, four young men from England then and still reigning as the world’s
                        most famous and influential rock music group, used multi-track recording
                        technologies from 1964-1970 to explore McLuhan’s predicted shift from visual
                        modes of perception to a way of knowing based increasingly on sound, a shift
                        to a world where immersion in a global community trumps the fixed individual
                        viewpoint. They stopped touring, concentrating their time and effort instead
                        in the studio where they produced increasingly complex narrative recordings.
                        The Beatles, the group, as a form of ground <ptr target="#macfarlane2013"
                            loc="109"/>, engaged with recorded sound to create a <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#macfarlane2013">technological fable
                                (myth)</quote>
                            <ptr target="#macfarlane2013" loc="104"/>
                        </cit> that required active participation from all band members (figures) as
                        well as audience to achieve its creation and consumption. </note></p>
                <p>Acoustic space is a world awash in sounds. With aural information emerging from
                    all directions, and with no opportunity to shut off or organize the constant
                    stream of sound, pre-writing humankind, the only to experience acoustic space,
                    according to McLuhan, perceived its world as both surrounding and inclusive, a
                    permeable extension of itself, and they of it <ptr target="#levinson1999"
                        loc="5–6"/>.</p>
                <p>For McLuhan, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1964">The <soCalled>content</soCalled>
                            of any medium is always another medium. The content of writing is
                            speech, just as the written word is the content of print, and print is
                            the content of the telegraph. If it is asked, <q>What is the content of
                                speech?,</q> it is necessary to say, <q>It is an actual process of
                                thought, which is in itself nonverbal</q></quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcluhan1964" loc="23–24"/>
                    </cit>. Speech, as the expression of thoughts and feelings by articulate sounds,
                    incorporates abstract thought and extends its ability to explain and/or
                    characterize human agency and situation.</p>
                <p>Speech tamed the acoustic wilderness by translating abstract thought into
                    communicable ideas. Storytellers produced explanations for the sounds in
                    acoustic space and wove them into larger narratives that helped explain the
                    presence and purpose of humankind. Orality provided a means to preserve and
                    share cultural histories and memories, a human tendency documented by Joseph
                    Campbell who investigated the reenactment of myths as ritualistic participatory
                    drama, often involving narrative, music, and/or other sound sources, by cultures
                    around the world <ptr target="#campbell1949"/>.</p>
                <p>Alphabets and writing (and printing and reading), in turn, by visualizing its
                    sounds, incorporate and preserve speech while extending its reach beyond the
                    transmission range of the human voice. With the advent of writing, during the
                    height of ancient Greece, speech was visualized, replacing the speaker’s voice
                    with text. Printing and distribution of texts, encouraged humankind to see and
                    read (literally and figuratively) the world as a series of discrete pieces,
                    letters and words strung like beads on a linear continuum running from the past,
                    through the present, toward the future. As this emphasis on visualization
                    continued with film, television, and the World Wide Web, the visual was elevated
                    as the primary sensory input. Sound was relegated to a secondary, augmenting
                    role to the visual.<note> Marshall McLuhan argued that alphabets and writing
                        preserved and extended the aural nature of speech. But, Plato argues in
                            <title rend="italic">The Phaedrus</title>, the first critique of
                        writing, written circa 360 B.C.E., that the absence of the rhetor/writer
                        means the text cannot be questioned and is therefore suspect. Plato's work
                        might be considered a landmark in the debate over orality vs. writing. Prior
                        to the age of Plato, speech was the repository of memory. The ear dominated
                        the mind's eye. Writing removed the sound source, placed the source of
                        credibility with seeing. For a long time ancient Greece was bicultural with
                        orality and writing in uneasy coexistence. Orality slowly wound down, until
                        it was replaced by typography and book publication.</note></p>
                <p>However, even as new visual media replaced / extended the older orality, they
                    incorporated its content: spoken narrative, storytelling, drama, and literature,
                    and various literary practices associated with their creation and consumption.
                    Thus, speech (as sound), with its origins in abstract thought and presentation,
                    is the oldest medium and the most prevalent form of human communication. It
                    claims a presence in most all media that follow <ptr target="#levinson1999"
                        loc="1981"/>. As James O’Donnell notes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#odonnell1988">the manuscript was first
                            conceived to be no more than a prompt-script for the spoken word, a
                            place to look to find out what to say . . . to produce the audible
                            word</quote>
                        <ptr target="#odonnell1988" loc="54"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Sound, despite its secondary relation to visual, still conveys deep, rich
                    information capable of prompting cognitive and emotional responses. McLuhan
                    likens sound to a <quote rend="inline" source="#mcluhan1964">subliminal echo
                        chamber</quote> capable of evoking memories/associations long forgotten or
                    ignored <ptr target="#mcluhan1964" loc="264"/>.</p>
                <p>According to Smith, sound is pervasive. Most humans, he says, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2003">live immersed in a world of sound .
                            . . sound is at once the most forceful stimulus that human beings
                            experience, and the most evanescent</quote>
                        <ptr target="#smith2003" loc="127, 128"/>
                    </cit>. Most academic disciplines are vision-based, he continues, not only in
                    the materials they study, but in the theoretical models they deploy to interpret
                    those materials. Sound, says Smith, as an object of study, has been neglected.
                    This is unfortunate, he concludes, as knowing the world through sound is
                    fundamentally different from knowing the world through vision <ptr
                        target="#smith2003" loc="129"/>. Stephen Feld concurs, noting <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#feld2003">the primacy of sound as a modality
                            of knowing and being in the world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#feld2003" loc="226"/>
                    </cit>. In short, sound provides a place in which embodied social and cultural
                    traces can be carried, often without the awareness of their bearers <ptr
                        target="#schafer1977"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Listening</head>
                <p>Experiencing sound, and the information it carries, involves listening, the
                    conscious processing of auditory stimuli. Gary Ferrington likens listening to
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ferrington1994">theater of the mind,</quote>
                    where every individual listener is her own dramaturge <ptr
                        target="#ferrington1994"/>. Alan Hall notes listening opens a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hall2010">portal through which a deeper, often
                            inarticulate, consciousness can be glimpsed</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hall2010" loc="99"/>
                    </cit>. Such glimpses may promote imagination, interaction, even immersion. Tim
                    Crook says sound very effectively prompts life from little details <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#crook1999">seen</quote> in the mind's eye <ptr
                        target="#crook1999" loc="8"/>.</p>
                <p>Michael Bull and Les Beck suggest by considering sound we open new ways of
                    thinking about and appreciating the social experience, memory, time, and place —
                    the auditory culture — of sound <ptr target="#bull2003" loc="12"/>. They
                    advocate <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2003">deep listening</quote> or
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2003">agile listening,</quote> both of
                    which involve <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2003">attuning our ears to
                        listen again to the multiple layers of meaning potentially embedded in the
                        same sound.</quote> Deep listening, they say, also involves <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bull2003">practices of dialogue and procedures
                            for investigation, transposition and interpretation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bull2003" loc="3–4"/>
                    </cit>. They argue several outcomes from deep listening. <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Sound makes us rethink our social experience, its meaning, nature, and
                            significance.</item>
                        <item>Sound makes us rethink our relation to community.</item>
                        <item>Sound makes us rethink our relation to others, ourselves, and the
                            spaces and places we inhabit.</item>
                        <item>Sound makes us rethink our relationship to power [Bull and Beck 2003,
                            3-4].</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>In addition to deep or profound listening, we might also consider acousmatic,
                    ambient, or profound listening. Sound artist Francisco López uses the term
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lópez2004">profound listening</quote> to
                    denote listening without constraints in order to explore and affirm all the
                    information inside any sound <ptr target="#lópez2004" loc="82–83"/>.</p>
                <p>Ambient listening, as defined by Brian Eno, principal innovator of ambient music,
                    is an accompaniment to life activities, often a background or secondary
                    activity. Eno defines ambient music as <quote rend="inline" source="#eno2004"
                        >new music</quote> whereby <quote rend="inline" source="#eno2004"
                        >compositional attention</quote> to technological production is key <ptr
                        target="#eno2004" loc="95"/>. The goal of ambient music is to produce music
                    that offers <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#eno2004">an atmosphere, or a surrounding
                            influence: a tint</quote>
                        <ptr target="#eno2004" loc="96"/>
                    </cit>. Since the music is designed to be predictable, attentive listening is
                    not required for best experience. The desired outcome is to have the music
                    become part of the background against which people live their lives.</p>
                <p>On the other hand is acousmatic, defined by Pierre Schaeffer, electroacoustic
                    musician-theoretician and pioneer of musique concrète, as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#schaeffer2004">a noise that one hears without
                            seeing what causes it</quote>
                        <ptr target="#schaeffer2004" loc="77"/>
                    </cit>. With acousmatic listening we no longer are concerned with the Cartesian
                    split between objective and subjective reality. Instead, it is the listening
                    itself, as a process, that becomes the phenomenon to be studied. The question
                        <q>What am I hearing?</q> asks one to describe the perception itself, not
                    simply the external references. The acousmatic situation generally precludes any
                    relation with what is visible, touchable, measurable <ptr
                        target="#schaeffer2004" loc="78"/>.</p>
                <p>The study of acousmatics is important for several reasons, according to
                    Schaeffer. Acousmatics, he says, emphasizes the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#schaeffer2004">subjectivities</quote> involved in listening,
                    focuses attention on the <quote rend="inline" source="#schaeffer2004">sonorous
                        object,</quote> what we are hearing, rather than the sound source, and
                    strips sound back to a state beyond interpretation <ptr target="#schaeffer2004"
                        loc="78, 79, 81"/>. When listening to sounds which are hidden from view we
                    take interest in them for themselves. We can gain knowledge of these sounds, we
                    can analyze and describe them, and, we hope, we can transmit this knowledge.</p>
                <p>Sound is, thus, relative to our listening experience. This point is considered by
                    Brian Kane, in his scholarly study of Schaeffer's theory of acousmatics, as he
                    argues for acousmatic listening to take a central role in sound and music
                    aesthetics, sound studies, literature, and philosophy from a number of
                    methodological perspectives — historical, cultural, philosophical, and musical
                        <ptr target="#kane2014"/>.<note>
                        <p>Other worthwhile resources on listening include <title rend="italic"
                                >Acoustic Territories: Sound Culture and Everyday Life</title>
                            (Brandon LaBelle. Continuum: New York 2010) — explores auditory
                            experience as located inside cultural histories and related
                            ideologies.</p>
                        <p><title rend="italic">Hearing Cultures: Essays of Sound, Listening and
                                Modernity</title> (Veit Erlmann, ed. Continuum: New York 2004) —
                            considers how sound offers a new lens through which to examine culture
                            and complex social issues.</p>
                        <title rend="italic">Listening</title> (Jean-Luc Nancy. Fordham University
                        Press: New York 2007) — examines sound in relation to the human body. How is
                        listening different from hearing? What does listening entail? How does what
                        is heard differ from what is seen?</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>How to proceed?</head>
                <p>Existing DH scholarship, as noted previously, is largely biased toward visuals
                        <ptr target="#whitney2008"/>. A shift in focus to sound will increase
                    opportunities for scholarship in the arts and humanities focused on sound <ptr
                        target="#sterne2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#murray2014"/>. Action research, advocated by Stefano Vannotti,
                    combines design / creative practice with critical academic research and may
                    provide an appropriate methodology for DH work with sound. Action research
                    involves a <quote rend="inline" source="#vannotti2008">systematic enquiry
                        conducted though the medium of practical action, calculated to devise or
                        test new, or newly imported, information, ideas, forms, or procedures and to
                        generate communicable knowledge</quote> and essentially <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#vannotti2008">undertake[s] research through
                            practice</quote>
                        <ptr target="#vannotti2008" loc="55"/>
                    </cit>. In other words, to critique and comment on sound, DH researchers should
                    work directly with sound — collecting, recording, archiving, curating, and
                    listening to sounds — the premise of this course.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>In this essay, I have discussed a course entitled <title rend="italic">Sound and
                        Digital Humanities,"</title> taught during the 2014 Digital Humanities
                    Summer Institute at the University of Victoria. I have discussed the context for
                    this course, its goals and objectives, and outlined a theoretical framework for
                    utilizing sound(s) in digital humanities (DH) research, teaching, and
                    practice.</p>
                <p>My argument is that sound provides scholarly and creative opportunities for those
                    involved with DH. Researchers and scholars may be uncertain how to proceed,
                    however. This course was meant to fill the information gap. To summarize, there
                    are several reasons for a focus on sound . . . <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Sound is ephemeral, disappearing, its meaning quickly lost.</item>
                        <item>Sound is temporal, but capable of returning, here but not here, a
                            feeling, a sense, an experience.</item>
                        <item>Sound was the original and remains a fundamental sensory input and
                            communication channel for human culture.</item>
                        <item>Sound conveys deep, rich information; is capable of providing
                            immersive, interactive contexts for listeners. Through the act of
                            careful listening, listeners can derive a great deal of information
                            about the world they inhabit.</item>
                        <item>Sound transforms space to place.</item>
                        <item>Sound is the phoneme for speech (verbalization of abstract
                            thought).</item>
                        <item>Sound is the central component of narrative (the recounting of a
                            sequence of events and their meaning) and storytelling (the addition of
                            setting, plot, characters, logical unfolding of events, a
                            climax).</item>
                        <item>Sound is the basis for literature (written works considered to possess
                            lasting artistic merit) and the various practices and cultures
                            associated with its production and consumption (reading, writing, and
                            listening).</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>In short, sound creates not only new phenomena to observe, research, interpret,
                    and report, but more importantly, new applications for such endeavors in DH.
                    This diversity of approaches to sound was heard by all DHSI 2014 participants
                    during a show-and-tell session at week's end. Participants from each course
                    shared some artifact in the DHSI central auditorium. With room lights
                    extinguished, participants walked onto the stage where, illuminated only by
                    glowing laptop and/or tablet screens, they added their respective aural
                    components to a live performance of <title rend="quotes">Sounds and Digital
                        Humanities.</title><note> A recording of this composition and a similar
                        sound composition created by participants of the 2015 class can be heard at
                            <ref
                            target="http://radionouspace.net/index.php/dhsi-more-information/#history"
                            >http://radionouspace.net/index.php/dhsi-more-information/#history</ref></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bull2003" label="Bull and Beck 2003">Bull, M. and L. Beck. <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction.</title> In M. Bull and L. Beck (ed.), <title
                        rend="italic">The Auditory Culture Reader</title>, Oxford, UK, Berg (2003),
                    pp. 3-4, 12, 16.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="campbell1949" label="Campbell 1949">Campbell, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Hero with a Thousand Faces</title>. Bollingen Foundation (1949).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crook1999" label="Crook 1999">Crook, T. <title rend="italic">Radio
                        Drama. Theory and Practice,</title> London, Routledge (1999), p. 8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eno2004" label="Eno 2004">Eno, B. <title rend="quotes">Ambient
                        Music.</title> In C. Cox and D. Warner (ed.), <title rend="italic">Audio
                        Culture,</title> Continuum Press, New York (2004), pp. 94-97.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="feld2003" label="Feld 2003">Feld, S. <title rend="quotes">A Rainforest
                        Acoustemology.</title> In M. Bull and L. Beck, (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                        >The Auditory Culture Reader,</title> Oxford, UK: Berg (2003), pp.
                    223-239.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ferrington1994" label="Ferrington 1994">Ferrington, G. <title
                        rend="quotes">Audio Design: Creating Multi-Sensory Images For The
                        Mind,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Visual Literary</title> 14.1 (1994):
                    61-67.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hall2010" label="Hall 2010">Hall, A. <title rend="quotes">Cigarettes
                        and Dance Steps.</title> In J. Biewen and A. Dilworth, (ed.), <title
                        rend="italic">Reality Radio: Telling True Stories in Sound</title> (eds),
                    University of North Carolina Press, Chapel Hill (2010), p. 99.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kane2014" label="Kane 2014">Kane, B. <title rend="italic">Sound
                        Unseen: Acousmatic Sound in Theory and Practice</title>, Oxford University
                    Press, New York (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="levinson1999" label="Levinson 1999">Levinson, P. <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital McLuhan: A Guide to the Information Millennium</title>. Routledge,
                    New York (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="levinson1981" label="Levinson 1981">Levinson, P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Media Evolution and the Primacy of Speech.</title> ERIC #ED 235510
                    (1981).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lópez2004" label="López 2004">López, F. <title rend="quotes">Profound
                        Listening and Environmental Sound Matter.</title> In C. Cox and D. Warner,
                    (ed.), <title rend="italic">Audio Culture: Readings in Modern Music</title>.
                    Continuum, New York (2004) pp. 82-83.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macfarlane2013" label="MacFarlane 2013">MacFarlane, T. <title
                        rend="italic">The Beatles and McLuhan: Understanding the Electric
                        Age</title>. The Scarecrow Press: Lanham, NJ (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1977" label="McLuhan 1977">McLuhan, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Laws of Media.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">et cetera</title> 1977 34(2): 173-179.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1964" label="McLuhan 1964">McLuhan, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</title> New York, McGraw Hill
                    (1964).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1988" label="McLuhan and McLuhan 1988">McLuhan, M. and McLuhan,
                    E. <title rend="italic">Laws of Media: The New Science</title>. University of
                    Toronto Press: Toronto (1988).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2009" label="McPherson 2009">McPherson, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Media Studies and the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> 48.2 (2009): 119-123.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murch2005" label="Murch 2005">Murch, W. <title rend="quotes">Womb
                        Tone,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Transom Review</title> 5.1 (2005). <ref
                        target="http:/transom.org/2005/walter-murch-part-1/"
                        >http:/transom.org/2005/walter-murch-part-1/</ref> (accessed 15 September
                    2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murray2014" label="Murray and Wiercinski 2014">Murray, A. and
                    Wiercinski, J. <title rend="quotes">A Design Methodology for Sound-based Web
                        Archives.</title>
                    <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 8.2 (2014). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000173/000173.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000173/000173.html</ref>
                    (accessed 15 September 2014)</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odonnell1988" label="O'Donnell 1988">O'Donnell, J. <title
                        rend="italic">Avatars of the Word: From Papyrus to Cyberspace</title>.
                    Harvard University Press, Cambridge (1988).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2012" label="Sayers 2012">Sayers, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Writing with Sound: Composing Multimodal, Long-Form Scholarship.</title>
                    Digital Humanities 2012 Conference (2012). <ref
                        target="http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/conference/programme/abstracts/writing-with-sound-composing-multimodal-long-form-scholarship/"
                        >http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/conference/programme/abstracts/writing-with-sound-composing-multimodal-long-form-scholarship/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schafer1977" label="Schafer 1977">Schafer, R. M. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Tuning of the World: A Pioneering Exploration Into the Past History and
                        Present State of the Most Neglected Aspect Of Our Environment: The
                        Soundscape</title>. McClelland and Stewart, Toronto (1977).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schafer" label="Schafer">[See also Schafer, R. M. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Soundscape: Our Sonic Environment and The Tuning of the World</title>.
                    Destiny Books, Rochester, Vermont (1993) adapted from <title rend="italic">The
                        New Soundscape</title> (1966) and <title rend="italic">The Tuning of the
                        World</title> (1977)]</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schaeffer2004" label="Schaeffer 2004">Schaeffer, P. <title
                        rend="quotes">Acousmatics.</title> In C. Cox and D. Warner, (ed.), <title
                        rend="italic">Audio Culture: Readings in Modern Music</title>. Continuum
                    Press, New York (2004), pp. 76-81.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2003" label="Smith 2003">Smith, B. <title rend="quotes">Tuning
                        into London c. 1600.</title> In M. Bull and L. Beck (ed.), <title
                        rend="italic">The Auditory Culture Reader.</title> Oxford, UK, Berg (2003),
                    pp. 127-135.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sterne2011" label="Sterne 2011">Sterne, J.<title rend="quotes">Audio
                        in Digital Humanities Authorship: A Roadmap (version 0.5)</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Super Bon!</title> (July 24, 2011) <ref
                        target="http://superbon.net/?p=1915">http://superbon.net/?p=1915</ref>
                    (accessed 15 September 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vannotti2008" label="Vannotti 2008">Vannotti, Stefano M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Let Us Do What We Can Do Best: But How Can We Produce
                        Knowledge by Designing Interfaces?</title> In C. Sommerer, L. Mignonneau,
                    and D. King (ed.), <title rend="italic">Interface Cultures: Artistic Aspects of
                        Interaction</title>. New Brunswick, NJ, Transaction Publishers (2008), pp.
                    51-60.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whitney2008" label="Whitney 2008">Whitney, A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cultivating Sonic Literacy in the Humanities Classroom,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Music, Sound, and the Moving Image</title> 2.2 (2008):
                    145-148.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
