<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Past Visions and Reconciling Views: Visualizing Time, Texture
                    and Themes in Cultural Collections</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Katrin <dhq:family>Glinka</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>glinka@fh-potsdam.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Katrin Glinka is a research associate and lecturer at the Potsdam
                            University of Applied Sciences. She combines approaches from art
                            history, sociology and museum studies with an interest in digital
                            cultural heritage and visualization research. She studied cultural
                            sciences with a focus on art theory, visual culture, sociology and
                            philosophy and holds an M. A. degree from Leuphana University Lüneburg.
                            Since 2014 she has been working on her doctoral thesis on digitization
                            and visualization in the cultural feld and their means and potentials
                            for curation, critical and interventionist approaches and visitor
                            orientation in museums. Correspondence e-mail: glinka@fh-potsdam.de</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Christopher <dhq:family>Pietsch</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>cpietsch@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Christopher Pietsch is a versatile information visualization researcher
                            for the Urban Complexity Lab at the University of Applied Sciences
                            Potsdam. He blends art, design, and technology to create interactive
                            experiences and spaces to explore novel types of visualization
                            metaphors. He studied Computer Science at the HTW Berlin and Interaction
                            Design at the University of Applied Sciences Potsdam. His bachelor’s
                            thesis is an experimental attempt on Brain-Computer-Interfaces that
                            discusses the multidisciplinary mysteries of human visual perception.
                            His current research circles around aesthetic interfaces in order to
                            enable profound new forms of data exploration.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Marian <dhq:family>Dörk</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>doerk@fh-potsdam.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Marian Dörk is a Research Professor for Information Visualization at the
                            Urban Futures Institute for Applied Research of the University of
                            Applied Sciences Potsdam. In his research he is particularly interested
                            in the potential of visual interfaces to support new forms of data
                            exploration. Since Fall 2014 he leads a 3-year research project on
                            visualizing cultural collections and since January 2015 he has been
                            co-directing the Urban Complexity Lab, a transdisciplinary research
                            space at the intersection between information visualization and urban
                            transformation.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000290</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2017-02-27">27 Feburary 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Visualization in the Humanities</item>
                        <item>Digital Art History</item>
                        <item>Zooming and Navigation Techniques</item>
                        <item>Digital Collections</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-02-15">Second encoding pass</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>We present a case study on visualizing a collection of historic drawings along
                    its metadata structure while also allowing for close examination of the
                    artifacts’ texture. With regards to the specific character of cultural heritage
                    at the intersection of research, education, and public interest, the presented
                    visualization environment aims at meeting the requirements of both researchers
                    as well as a broader public. We present the results from a collaborative
                    interdisciplinary research project that involved a cultural heritage foundation,
                    art historians, designers, and computer scientists. The case study examines the
                    potential of visualization when applied to, and developed for, cultural heritage
                    collections. It specifically explores how techniques aimed at visualizing the
                    quantitative structure of a collection can be coupled with a more qualitative
                    mode that allows for detailed examination of the artifacts and their contexts by
                    displaying high-resolution views of digitized cultural objects with detailed art
                    historical research findings. Making use of latest web technologies, the
                    resulting visualization environment allows for dynamic filtering and zooming of
                    a collection of visual resources that are arranged along a contextualized
                    timeline. We share insights from our collaborative design process and the
                    feedback and usage data gathered during the deployment of the resulting
                    prototype as a web application. We end with a discussion of transferability of
                    carefully crafted and collaboratively negotiated visualizations of cultural
                    heritage and raise questions concerning the applicability of our approach to
                    related strands of humanities research.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Glinka, Pietsch, and Dörk present a case study on visualizing a collection of
                    historic drawings along its metadata structure while also allowing for close
                    examination of the artifacts’ texture.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <figure>
                <head>The interface developed for the <title rend="italic">Past Visions</title> case
                    study provides a distanced view on the topical and temporal dimensions of 1492
                    historic drawings. The view can be filtered and zoomed to see specific subsets
                    and details of individual drawings. <ref target="http://uclab.fh-potsdam.de/fw4/en/">http://uclab.fh-potsdam.de/fw4/en/</ref></head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>In recent years, numerous projects have been initiated and funded that aim to
                    digitize cultural artifacts. Archives, museums, libraries, and other heritage
                    institutions are now facing the challenge to make digitized inventories publicly
                    accessible and provide new modes of engagement with the cultural content. At the
                    same time, there is an increase in visualization research related to the digital
                    humanities that explores computational and data-driven approaches to literature,
                    art, and other cultural domains. The asset of computational analysis and
                    visualization is often reduced to their benefit in regards to quantitative
                    analysis, which implies a distancing from the singular object or phenomenon. At
                    the same time, the object-centered nature of museums, art history, archeology,
                    and archives is fueling a growing interest in harmonizing digital approaches
                    with qualitative and interpretative methods, i.e., <soCalled>close
                        viewing</soCalled> or <soCalled>close reading,</soCalled> an approach that
                    we aim to extend with this work.</p>
                <p>The case study<note> The visualization prototype presented in this paper has been
                        previously mentioned in a project description published under the title
                            <title rend="quotes">Linking structure, texture and context in a
                            visualization of historical drawings by Frederick William IV
                            (1795-1861)</title>, K. Glinka, C. Pietsch, C. Dilba, M. Dörk, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Digital Art History</title> 2
                        (2016).</note> that we present shows the potential of applying techniques
                    largely drawn from information visualization to an art historical source. With a
                    zoomable visualization environment we seek to explore how a
                        <soCalled>distant-viewing</soCalled> approach can be combined with a
                        <soCalled>close-viewing</soCalled> mode in a dynamic and contextualized
                    arrangement (see Fig. 1). We aim to examine how visualizing the quantitative
                    structure of a collection can be complemented by allowing for examination of the
                    qualitative texture of the individual object. We describe a design space for
                    visualizing cultural collections that also does justice to the aesthetic value
                    of the collection and objects. Our contributions further include an evaluation
                    of the prototype in regards to usability, user interaction, and audience
                    groups.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Related Work</head>
                <p>Our work builds on prior research on information visualization in the context of
                    digital humanities, the emerging field of digital art history, and
                    visualizations particularly developed for cultural collections.</p>
                <p>The analysis of textual data has been an important method for the largely
                    language-centric digital humanities <ptr target="#janicke2015"/> and a major
                    strand of research in information visualization <ptr target="#kucher2014"/>.
                    While early text visualizations were created for relatively abstract use
                    contexts, more recent work focuses on specific needs of particular user groups
                    such as humanities scholars <ptr target="#janicke2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#koch2014"/>. The scope of visualization tools for textual analysis
                    ranges between single-purpose tools <ptr target="#wattenberg2008"/> to
                    comprehensive analysis environments  <ptr target="#muralidharan2013"/>.
                    Moretti’s notion of <soCalled>distant reading</soCalled> <ptr target="#moretti2005"/> has become a provocative yet productive term to
                    negotiate quantitative and qualitative methods of literary history, and more
                    generally for interpreting cultural data. The distinction between close and
                    distant readings has informed a wide range of visualization projects aiming to
                    support analysis that ranges from individual words and sentences to documents
                    and entire corpora <ptr target="#janicke2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Apart from these predominantly text-based efforts in digital humanities, the
                    broader context of digital cultural heritage has attracted a variety of
                    experimental visualization research and innovative design of collection
                    interfaces. Visualizations of cultural heritage collections promise to offer
                        <soCalled>rich-prospect interfaces</soCalled> that represent an entire
                    collection at once, afford interactive control over its arrangement, and provide
                    detailed access to its elements <ptr target="#ruecker2011"/>. This approach is
                    based on the principle that the default interface should <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ruecker2011">show a meaningful representation […] of every single
                            item in the collection</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ruecker2011"/>
                    </cit> that is apparent to the user and helps them to understand, on a visual
                    basis, what is available in a collection. Image plots of thousands of Instagram
                    photos arranged by time and hue fulfil some of these aspirations in that they
                    blend the representation of the metadata with the visual qualities of the images
                        <ptr target="#hochman2013"/>. The resulting visualizations offer impressions
                    of large stocks of photos that were not visible in that way before. The
                    Viewshare tool was explicitly designed for rapid creation of visual interfaces
                    that can be used to explore and share patterns in collection data using
                    established techniques such as maps, timelines, and lists <ptr target="#algee2012"/>. In contrast, the <soCalled>Bohemian
                        Bookshelf</soCalled> interface contains deliberately idiosyncratic
                    visualizations each offering a unique point of entry to a visually rich and
                    multidimensional collection <ptr target="#thudt2012"/>. The principle of
                        <soCalled>generosity</soCalled> can be used to qualify to which degree an
                    interface reveals the material and semantic qualities of a collection and
                    encourages its exploration <ptr target="#whitelaw2015"/>. Our research aims to
                    contribute to this line of work on generous and rich-prospect interfaces for
                    cultural collections in particuarly by supporting the shift between abstract,
                    distanced explorations and highly detailed close-up views.</p>
                <p>Related to these developments in the wider cultural sector, digital art history
                    is gradually emerging as a research area in its own right <ptr target="#bentkowskakafel2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#drucker2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#promey1997"/> with a distinct set of use cases, tasks, and
                    requirements for digital tools and data structures. While early mentions of the
                    term focused on teaching <ptr target="#promey1997"/>, there has been a continued
                    interest in making sense of digital technologies and exploring their potential
                    for art history, especially with regard to purposes like preservation and
                        presentation <ptr target="#bentkowskakafel2005"/>. Museums and art history,
                    although preoccupied with visual resources, have been predominantly text-based
                    fields of research in that sense that the visual object of study had to be
                    translated into text (e.g. on index cards or in cataloguing systems and
                    databases) to be able to retrieve relevant information from rich collections,
                    either analog or digital. Efforts in computation and digital humanities research
                    thus also include the improvement of ontologies and text-based information
                    retrieval systems <ptr target="#isemann2014"/> or the use of folksonomy or
                    crowdsourcing for textual annotation of cultural heritage <ptr target="#ridge2014"/>. Consequently, some approaches in digital art history
                    research build upon the prior developments in text-based humanities, introducing
                    approaches that allow for <soCalled>distant viewing</soCalled> and quantitative
                    analysis of art historical data <ptr target="#bender2015"/>. Computational
                    non-textual analysis of art historical resources, on the other hand, include
                    methods for image analysis that are able to group or cluster artworks on the
                    basis of similarity of artistic style <ptr target="#shamir2012"/> or the
                    development of computer vision algorithms classifying fine-art paintings by
                    style, genre, and artist <ptr target="#saleh2015"/>. Although the application of
                    digital methods in art historical research still represents a small subset of
                    disciplinary practice, digital art history is on the rise <ptr target="#zweig2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Despite the dominance of <soCalled>distant</soCalled> approaches in digital
                    humanities and digital art history, there is a growing recognition that digital
                    methods in these fields should incorporate qualitative and interpretive modes of
                        analysis <ptr target="#schnapp2009"/>. Drucker argues for a fundamental
                    shift in visualization design from viewer-independent representation of data to
                    viewer-codependent interpretation of <soCalled>capta</soCalled>, i.e., data that
                    is purposefully collected and constructed <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>. Data in
                    the arts and humanities are not about absolute truths, they are constructed to
                    develop novel interpretations and advance arguments. Visualizations in this
                    sense should be seen as propositions for a certain reading (or viewing) of a
                        phenomenon <ptr target="#galey2010"/>. Current visualization research in the
                    context of literary studies reflects this need for interpretive, experimental,
                    and even playful approaches to data <ptr target="#mccurdy2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#hinrichs2016"/>. Similarly, our intention is to conceive
                    intriguing visualizations that make rich art historical collections available
                    for casual analysis and exploration while still supporting detailed
                    inspection.</p>
                <p>Much of digital art history, and more generally digital cultural heritage, is
                    reliant on textual information about artifacts. Additionally, computationally
                    processed, clustered, and interpreted image data, or sometimes a combination of
                    text and digital image processing, are used to organise and make sense of
                    digital cultural heritage. Metadata, understood as textual information on
                    (digitised) cultural heritage, connects the expert’s knowledge to the visual
                    resources and helps to address entities via title, author, date oder descriptive
                    elements like keywords or classification <ptr target="#schumacher2016"/>. As
                    part of the efforts to also develop visually rich representations of and new
                    modes of interaction with digital cultural heritage, there is a growing interest
                    in the question of how the underlying textual-digital fragmentation of an
                    artifact influences our perception of digital cultural heritage on a more
                    general note. These discourses engage, amongst others, with the question of how
                    to address, represent or preserve the materiality of objects in digital
                    representations. This is especially relevant in the context of museums that, for
                    a long time, have given primacy to the materiality of objects. Nonetheless,
                    within museum studies, and the study of material culture in general, the notion
                    of <soCalled>object biographies</soCalled> has come to acknowledge the ways in
                    which objects become invested with meaning through the social interactions they
                    are caught up in <ptr target="#gosden1999"/>. This shift away from a strict
                    focus on materiality and towards a notion that understands the accumulation and
                    transformation of an object’s meaning and values as a distinctly sociocultural
                    process can now also be accentuated in the context of digital cultural heritage.
                    Objects, in this sense, can be recognised as being in a state of motion, that
                    might occupy or migrate through different states and media <ptr target="#parry2007"/>. Nonetheless, debates on the meaning, value, and
                    presence of digital objects, quite often still rely on the object-centeredness
                    of museum culture and thus argue from the standpoint of the
                        <soCalled>superior</soCalled> physical counterpart of the digital object
                        <ptr target="#cameron2007"/>. In this context, we would like to acknowledge
                    that the materiality of a museum object could also be problematised even in
                    regards to how it is conveyed in a museum display. Although museums can be
                    regarded as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dudley2012">material institutions par excellence</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dudley2012"/>
                    </cit>, they often limit the extent to which people can engage with the things
                    on display and thus likewise limit the access to the objects’ materiality <ptr target="#dudley2012"/>. Naturally, this restricted access is a due measure
                    of precaution that ensures the preservation of valuable and unique objects.
                    Nonetheless, neither in a physical nor digital display can we touch, feel,
                    smell, taste, or weigh the objects with the help of all our senses. What we have
                    to rely on in both instances is our sense of vision and, if provided, the
                        <soCalled>knowledge</soCalled> assigned to the (digital) object by the
                    museum as metadata or other additional information <ptr target="#dudley2012"/>.
                    Concerning the influence of new media on our way of perceiving and engaging with
                    cultural heritage, Jeff Malpas has remarked that we need to retain a sense of
                    the materiality of objects <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#malpas2007">understood in terms of the way in which human life is
                            essentially formed and articulated, and so also understood, in relation
                            to spatio-temporal formation and articulation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#malpas2007" loc="19"/>
                    </cit>. He emphasises the need to differentiate between what is interpretation
                    and what is the object in its spatio/temporal materiality in order to not <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#malpas2007">lose a sense of the object</quote>
                        <ptr target="#malpas2007" loc="24"/>
                    </cit>. With our research we are attempting to address some of the challenges
                    arising from the material and interpretative complexity within cultural
                    collections.</p>
                <p>With the expanding use of digital methods in the humanities, tool creation is
                    certainly a valuable scholarly practice <ptr target="#davis2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#schnapp2009"/> that expands the ways a phenomenon can be seen and
                    examined. Prompted by limited adoption of more advanced tools in the digital
                    humanities, the results of a survey with historians highlight the critical
                    importance of interface design, instructions, and ease of use <ptr target="#gibbs2012"/>. Besides their immediate function, visualizations also
                    act as arguments and rhetorical expressions <ptr target="#galey2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#hullman2011"/> that can serve critical approaches towards cultural
                        collections <ptr target="#glinka2015"/>. Accordingly, to benefit the
                    research agendas in the humanities, it is the scholars themselves who should be
                    much more involved in setting the parameters for the design of tools and
                    formulating questions for their interpretation and critique <ptr target="#drucker2013"/>. Taking these findings into account, we are pursuing
                    an interdisciplinary research process that brings together humanities scholars,
                    designers, and engineers to collaboratively create and make sense of
                    visualizations of cultural collections.</p>
                <p>The temporal dimension is often of particular importance in cultural collections.
                    When reflecting this by visualizing cultural data along a timeline, it is
                    advisable to also consider its genealogy <ptr target="#davis2013"/>, going back
                    to the design decisions made in the 18th century when the first timelines were
                        conceived <ptr target="#davis2015"/>. Even though the timeline is almost
                    omnipresent, there can be good reasons to subvert its linearity, for example, to
                    counter absolute notions of time and advance more complex models of times <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>, expose the uncertainty in the dating of
                        artifacts <ptr target="#davis2015"/>, or to pique the interest of an
                    exhibition audience about the oeuvre of an artist <ptr target="#hinrichs2008"/>.
                    The temporal dimension can also serve as the basis to trace the evolution of
                    visual features of art such as color usage in paintings <ptr target="#haber2011"/>. Following the aim to provide users with a visual basis for understanding
                    what is available in a collection in rich-prospect interfaces, Ruecker et al.
                    have identified the temporal arrangement of collections as one that helps
                    identify meaningful connections between items <ptr target="#ruecker2011"/>. In
                    our research we continue this line of work of visualizing temporal patterns in
                    cultural collections and further seek to integrate the material and thematic
                    qualities of the artifacts.</p>
                <p>There is a traditional emphasis on the overview in information visualization <ptr target="#shneiderman1996"/>, which is typically understood to be distinct
                    from the preview of individual resources in a collection <ptr target="#greene2000"/>. However, the primacy of overviews is increasingly
                    being challenged, for example, by visually rich <soCalled>innerviews</soCalled>
                    as local perspectives that show both the visual material and its dense
                        metadata <ptr target="#whitelaw2015"/>. Akin to blending or alternating
                    between distant and close reading, there is growing interest in bringing
                    bird’s-eye and close-up views on collections together. For shifting from
                    high-level aggregations of an entire collection to the detailed views of
                    individual resources, zoomable interfaces prove particularly powerful <ptr target="#bederson1994"/>
                    <ptr target="#dork2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#hochman2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#sfmoma2008"/>. Typically, however, the arrangement of elements in
                    zoomable interfaces is relatively static and highly detailed views of the
                    artifacts are seldom provided. Our intention is to develop dynamic arrangements
                    of rich, visual artifacts that make full use of interactive and graphical
                    capabilities of modern web technologies. Thus, we build upon and refine
                    visualization techniques in the context of the challenges and potentials of
                    cultural heritage and digital art history.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Approaching a Collection of Historic Drawings</head>
                <p>Within the scope of this research project, we are collaborating with the Prussian
                    Palaces and Gardens Foundation Berlin-Brandenburg or SPSG, a cultural heritage
                    foundation that administers several historical buildings, palaces, gardens,
                    collections of paintings, furniture, sculptures, porcelain, drawings, and other
                    historical objects, which have only partially been digitized, so far. Motivated
                    by the lack of research combining quantitative and qualitative analysis of art
                    historical collections, we proceed with the ambition to select a data set that
                    would allow us to examine a collection along its structure, i.e., based on the
                    artefacts’ metadata, as well as their texture, i.e., visual, physical, or
                    aesthetic qualities. Additionally, we seek to incorporate context, i.e., frame
                    the collection in such a way that would allow non-experts (or interested
                    laypersons) to explore the collection. In the following we detail our framework
                    of collaborative, interdisciplinary research and the design and development of
                    cultural heritage visualizations in cooperation with art historians, designers,
                    and engineers.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1. Research Questions</head>
                    <p>Our main aim is to investigate how visualization can reconcile the
                        perpetuated antagonism between qualitative and quantitative methods of
                        distant and close viewing of cultural collections. In accordance with this
                        ambition we pursue two main research questions with our case study:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>How can we visualize a cultural collection in a way that employs a
                            quantitative analysis of a collection’s structure while also offering
                            qualitative insights and exploration of the objects’ textures?</item>
                        <item>What are promising features of a visualization environment that cater
                            to the needs and interests of interested laypersons as well as art
                            historians and other domain experts?</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The overall research project as well as the case study operate on a notion of
                            <soCalled>cultural sensitivity.</soCalled> We employ this term in two
                        senses. For one, we embrace the differences in disciplinary backgrounds as
                        part of a "culture"<note> Although much has changed in educational systems
                            since C. P. Snow’s 1959 lecture on "The Two Cultures" <ptr target="#snow1959"/>, some of his analysis of the differences in
                            culture in <soCalled>the sciences</soCalled> and <soCalled>the
                                humanities</soCalled> still hold true today.</note> within e.g.
                        computer sciences, design, museums, the arts, and the humanities and start
                        from the premise that these cultures should be equally included, respected,
                        and brought to their full potential in any transdisciplinary project. This
                        could be affiliated with the notion that <soCalled>cultural
                            sensitivity</soCalled> (in the more common meaning of the term) involves
                        acknowledging <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#bhawuk1992">sensitivity to the importance of cultural
                                differences and to the points of view of people in other
                                cultures</quote>
                            <ptr target="#bhawuk1992" loc="346"/>
                        </cit>. For the other, we construe this term in a more literal sense as a
                        sensibility towards <soCalled>culture</soCalled> (or the cultural artefact)
                        in regards to the collection that we engage with. More precisely, by using
                        this term in its double meaning, we seek to emphasize that the cultural
                        content, meaning, and specific qualities of a collection and its items would
                        be the driving force while developing and designing the visualization in
                        close collaboration and on the basis of mutual respect with the heritage
                        institution and the different involved disciplines. Hence, our approach is
                        not primarily technology driven nor originally aimed at building a
                            <soCalled>one size fits all</soCalled> solution for exchangeable
                        datasets. Nonetheless, we deem the findings and results from our case study
                        to be central to our research concerning the transferability of our
                        visualization approach to other image-based collections.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.2 Sourcing Data</head>
                    <p>When seeking to visualize the quantitative structure of a collection, the
                        data set has to cover a minimum of properties such as year or period of
                        creation, name of artist or school, material, and size. More interpretative
                        metadata might include genre, style, or iconographic classification. While
                        we have seen some promising results from applying computer vision algorithms
                        to fine art <ptr target="#saleh2015"/>
                        <ptr target="#shamir2012"/> and thus, in theory, could compensate missing
                        metadata by algorithmically classifying artworks, most heritage institutions
                        (as our cooperating institution) still rely on manually annotating their
                        collections. Some subsets from the foundation’s collection databases do
                        involve descriptive or interpretative texts, research findings, and other
                        related resources, while other areas of the collections are almost untapped.
                        Regarding our aim to also allow for exploration of a collection’s texture,
                        we had to make sure that the subset included high-resolution digital images
                        of the collection items.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Collage making during co-creation workshop with collaborators.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Taking all of our requirements into account, we identified a subset of
                        drawings from a collection of prints and drawings, which includes 1492
                        sheets with drawings executed by King Frederick William IV of Prussia
                        (1795-1861). This subset is part of a larger collection of 7500 sheets with
                        drawings by the King that are in the process of being inventoried and
                        digitized. Many of these sheets reveal the planning eye of the King in the
                        form of architectural visions and dreamy drafts while they bear witness to
                        historical events such as wars and revolutions, literary influences or
                        personal obsessions. Many of the drawings depict actual palaces, churches,
                        gardens, and other sites that are part of the cultural heritage administered
                        by the SPSG.</p>
                    <p>Most of the following data was available for each sheet: inventory number,
                        description of sheet, art historical interpretation, labelling (e.g.,
                        hand-written by King or later researchers), watermarks, physical dimensions,
                        year, material, titles of corresponding thematic texts, list of
                        corresponding secondary literature, and hierarchical index-based list of
                        descriptors. The descriptors had been previously developed by a group of art
                        historians during the research process alongside a controlled vocabulary and
                        either belonged to a thematic or a topographical categorization. To make the
                        art historical sources explorable by a non-expert public, we also included
                        the content of an exhibition catalogue, which, in contrast to the object
                        description and interpretation, were written and published for a broader
                        audience and offered contextual information on the King’s life, prevailing
                        interests, and general historical background. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.3. Towards Cultural Sensitivity</head>
                    <p>In order to pursue our research questions, we decided to employ a
                        user-centered design approach that integrates experts from the involved
                        disciplines into a co-creation process. Thus, a key element for our close
                        collaboration with the heritage institution was a workshop framework that
                        practically and conceptually engages participants from various professions
                        in thinking about how different facets of a collection could be translated
                        into a visual representation <ptr target="#chen2014"/>. The first iteration
                        of the workshop, which to a certain degree resembles co-creation practices
                        in design research <ptr target="#sanders2008"/>, involved 11 participants
                        (seven employees of the heritage foundation including a scientific editor
                        responsible for print and online publications, a collections inventory
                        custodian, a castellan and art historian, a marketing and public relations
                        officer, the head of the center for documentation and information, a
                        classical scholar, and the head of the IT department; one participant was
                        from a company that develops database management systems for museums, three
                        were members of our research group). The first iteration of the workshop had
                        no designated thematic focus, but rather served as a platform to get to know
                        the scope of the partnering institution, the collections, the database
                        structure, and allowed us to identify promising areas for a first case
                        study.</p>
                    <p>The workshop format provides a setting, in which the participants
                        individually create collages from sample material with the aim to tease out
                        promising relationships among objects (see Fig. 2). The workshop was
                        documented (as audio recordings of the discussions, photographs of paper
                        collages and the making process). These records were later transcribed and
                        thematically clustered. By analyzing the material, we were able to identify
                        prevailing topics of interest and challenges that were relevant for the
                        subsequent steps of our project. First of all, most approaches to the
                        collections that were developed during the workshop were of qualitative
                        nature. Participants presented collages and discussed ideas that highlighted
                        content-based facets or interpretational elements. Thus, the collages
                        resembled an approach that is mostly associated with a curatorial practice
                        in museums. When discussing these approaches, a challenge was seen in the
                        fact that the existing metadata and level of digitization of the
                        foundation’s collections often did not include such content keywords and
                        in-depth descriptive elements and interpretational texts.</p>
                    <p>Following this first workshop that identified mutual interests, we analyzed
                        the overall metadata structures of the collections that had already been
                        digitized. As a result, the thematic focus on the drawings by Frederick
                        William IV was influenced by the quality of the digital copies, the thorough
                        and complete art historical metadata, as well as the fact that the metadata
                        included descriptive and interpretational texts. The second workshop was
                        then specifically aimed at identifying promising structures and parameters
                        within this sub-collection of drawings that could serve as a dimension for
                        an exploratory visualization environment. With this specific goal in mind,
                        we invited not only colleagues from our department with a background in
                        interface design and information visualization, but also a scientific editor
                        of the foundation and the art historian that led the research group which
                        produced the metadata. According to our overall goal to proceed on the
                        notion of <soCalled>cultural sensitivity,</soCalled> the identification and
                        involvement of the right domain experts was a central element of our
                            cooperation <ptr target="#sedlmair2012"/>. With this, we act on the
                        observation that digital research in areas like art and cultural heritage
                        often demonstrates inferior or uncertain cognitive value of the findings
                        when it is not informed by professional art historical knowledge and
                        scholarly methodology <ptr target="#bentkowskakafel2015"/>. The collages
                        that were produced during the second workshop were much more specific and
                        related to the actual data and scope of the collection. During an iterative
                        process, we then identified dimensions and parameters that were both
                        appealing from an art historical point of view and offered interesting
                        challenges for visualization research and design.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Visualizing Time, Themes and Texture</head>
                <p>Our collaborators repeatedly emphasized the temporal and thematic patterns to be
                    particularly important for making sense of the collection. In addition, there
                    was an interest in incorporating the actual reproductions of the drawings in the
                    visualization. This corresponds with the assertion that visualizations,
                    especially in the context of digital humanities, should take into account the
                    unique visual and material qualities of digitized collections to reflect their
                    physical counterparts <ptr target="#hinrichs2016"/>. Obviously, the digital
                    cannot surmount the restricted access to materiality posed upon a museum object.
                    Nonetheless, we can try to at least tap into the full potential of displaying a
                    digitized museum object and still be aware that much of what constitutes the
                    display and the ways of engaging with the object is based on the interpretation
                    and not on its spatio-temporal materiality. Reflecting on these conditions, we
                    have found it to be productive for our research to try and exhaust the given
                    technological potentials in making high-resolution reproductions of fragile (and
                    mostly non-public) objects available to the public. Thus, we hope to at least
                    maximise the visual information about the material qualities that can be
                    extracted from the digital collection at hand, maybe even surpassing the
                    accessibility of the original that would be shielded from the public with <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dudley2012">glass cases, picture frames, ropes</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dudley2012"/>
                    </cit>, or other visually distancing precautionary measures. At the same time,
                    we concede that it is not solely the physical materiality of the objects that
                    affect the conditions under which we can engage with the collection by
                    subjugating the arrangement of the visual resources to their interpretation (of
                    temporal, contextual, or thematic attributes). The aforementioned challenge of
                    conveying the materiality of digitial cultural heritage also influenced our
                    decision-making in regards to the treatment and processing of the digitized
                    drawings. We decided to preserve and highlight the traces of materiality that
                    are conveyed through the high-resolution digital reproductions, such as
                    ripped-out corners, faded-out strokes, and the proportions of the sheets and
                    differences in size. Following our aims and research questions, we have devised
                    a zoomable visualization environment that arranges a collection of drawings
                    based on their temporal attribution, allows for thematic filtering, provides
                    historical and art historical context, and enables the close inspection of the
                    high-resolution images and their visual texture.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The interface consists of a keyword visualization (top) and a zoomable
                        canvas arranging high-resolution images and historical and biographical
                        events along a timeline (bottom). Information panels can slide out from the
                        sides to provide instruction on how to interact with the interface (left)
                        and read detailed art historical information about a selected
                        object (right)</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The interface contains a keyword visualization, a zoomable canvas and timeline,
                    and information panels (see Fig. 3). The visual design of the interface with a
                    dark screen canvas and muted colors takes into account the collection’s texture.
                    Many prints, engravings, or drawings are monochromatic and low in contrast. This
                    also being the case for the collection of drawings by Frederick William, a light
                    screen canvas would have blended the drawings with their background. Since the
                    original sheets were furthermore digitized mounted to a dark carrier paper, the
                    contrast between the light sheets of paper and the dark carrier paper, that
                    extends to the screen canvas, makes it possible to discern the cut-outs and
                    texture of the paper more easily. Additionally, the physical context of the
                    original drawings can be associated with the interface, since the design reminds
                    of the dim and concentrated aesthetics of print rooms in museums. In the
                    following we describe the specific design decisions behind the visualization
                    along the three main facets of our visualization: time, themes, and texture.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>4.1. Time</head>
                    <p>The primary organization scheme for the collection of drawings is time, which
                        is not only highlighted by the collection experts to be important, but
                        reflects its fundamental significance for the visualization of historical
                            collections <ptr target="#davis2013"/>. According to the date of likely
                        creation, all drawings are arranged on a canvas in columns, each
                        representing one year, spanning the period of 1810-1856. As some sheets do
                        not have an exact year, but rather estimated time ranges, the median of the
                        range is used for the positioning. Within the columns, sheets are sorted
                        vertically based on the complexity of their metadata. Since Frederick
                        William often used one piece of paper for several independent sketches or
                        drawings, some sheets accumulate a number of motives, themes, and places
                        that are identified separately and included in the metadata associated with
                        each sheet.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The images on the canvas can be filtered using themes (a-c) and
                            situated in their historical context (d-f). Hovering over a keyword
                            highlights all respective drawings in the canvas (b), clicking it the
                            selection of drawings is further constrained (c). A timeline that
                            separates selected and grayed-out drawings can be zoomed to reveal more
                            details about historical events (d-f).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When the interface is launched, the visualization offers a bird’s-eye view on
                        the complete set of drawings with each of the 1492 images being displayed
                        (see Fig. 1). In this initial view the images are shown at a relatively
                        small size of about 20 mm on a 13" laptop display to make room for the
                        entire collection.</p>
                    <p>The temporal arrangement of images is accompanied by a timeline that is
                        positioned at the bottom of the interface, with entries slightly surpassing
                        the scope of the drawings as they provide additional biographical and
                        historical context such as birth and death of the King. The 40 events with
                        historical and biographical context to the drawings were in part derived
                        from the existing exhibition catalogue and collaboratively authored with our
                        partners at the foundation. In order to facilitate the establishment of a
                        connection between the personal and historical developments and the drawings
                        that the King produced at the time, the timeline is positioned right below
                        the columns of drawings. The timeline implements a semantic zoom
                            functionality <ptr target="#bederson1994"/>, i.e., it gradually reveals
                        more and more detail as the viewer zooms further in into the respective time
                        periods (see Fig. 4, d-f). While the temporal arrangement of the sheets
                        arguably follows a quantitative logic, the integration of the actual digital
                        copies of the drawings and the annotated timeline provide qualitative
                        content and context intended to support a deeper engagement with the
                        collection.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2. Themes</head>
                    <p>In the top area of the interface, a keyword visualization displays the most
                        prolific subjects and places as a horizontal list of tags that are derived
                        from the index-based list of descriptors. Depending on the size of the
                        screen, the list contains between 30 and 50 words and phrases. Akin to word
                        clouds, the font sizes represent the relative frequency of sheets per
                        subject. The keywords are sorted alphabetically in order to allow viewers to
                        quickly locate a subject they might be looking for. Interactions with the
                        keyword visualization result in changes in the image canvas. Hovering over a
                        keyword highlights all the sheets that are associated with this subject (see
                        Fig. 4, b).</p>
                    <p>Besides indicating the major subjects and places, the keyword visualization
                        serves as a filtering method for the image canvas. After selecting a
                        keyword, all drawings not associated with this subject move to the bottom of
                        the timeline and are displayed with a lower opacity (see Fig. 4, a-c). The
                        transition is animated in order help the viewer understand the new display
                        state. The images that match the current keyword selection remain above the
                        timeline but will move closer together. The resulting subset of images forms
                        a more specific temporal visualization indicating the ebb and flow of a
                        particular topic within the King’s strand of work. As more and more keywords
                        are activated, the selection of drawings gets more constrained, resulting in
                        smaller image columns. As indicated by the cross added to a selected
                        keyword, clicking on a keyword again cancels its selection. Changing the
                        selection of keywords also changes the display of the remaining keywords. As
                        some keywords may not be associated with the drawings in a given selection,
                        they will be hidden, making space for more specific keywords to be revealed,
                        thus increasing the level of specificity of the keywords.</p>
                    <p>In addition to the themes represented by the keywords, the detail panel
                        provides more in-depth information about each drawing. These details include
                        descriptions of the content shown on each sheet, art historical
                        interpretation, commentaries on their historical significance and relation
                        to other objects, and annotations made by the King or subsequent maintainers
                        of the collection. Besides metadata fields such as the physical dimensions
                        and material of the sheet, the detail panel also provides access to thematic
                        essays written by art historians about specific places or topics depicted in
                        the drawings.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.3. Texture</head>
                    <p>A key feature of the visualization is the provisioning of high-resolution
                        imagery in an arrangement that supports zooming, panning, and filtering.
                        Similar to image plots of photos or magazine covers <ptr target="#hochman2013"/>
                        <ptr target="#manovich2015"/>, high-level views on cultural collections can
                        reveal global patterns and trends, however, typically only general shades
                        and shapes can be differentiated. Our intention is to make these
                        arrangements dynamic through filtering and thus allow for rapid access to
                        custom subsets of the collection. The canvas is designed as a continuously
                        zoomable space, allowing for the gradual increase of detail for particular
                        segments of the arrangement of images. Zoom operations can be carried out
                        either through the mouse wheel or by performing scrolling or zoom gestures
                        on touchpads and touch-enabled displays. By zooming into particular groups
                        of images, the thumbnails continuously grow into larger images with a higher
                        resolution. By clicking and dragging, it is possible to pan the canvas in
                        all directions. The viewer can examine sheets in the same year by performing
                        vertical movements and shift in time between different year columns by
                        moving horizontally. By clicking or tapping on an image, it is possible to
                        immediately focus on this particular drawing and display it in high
                        resolution. Once an image is in focus, the neighboring images fade out and
                        the detail information becomes available on the right side panel. In the
                        same visual context of the canvas, it is now possible to further zoom into
                        the image of the drawing to closely inspect the texture of the paper and
                        even the grain of the pencil strokes (see Fig. 5, bottom left). These
                        high-resolution views of the drawings are highly detailed and surpass what
                        would be visible to the naked eye in a museum or archive.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The images’ scales in the visualization span several orders of
                            magnitude from a high-level perspective showing the entire collection as
                            small images (top left), zooming into the arrangement revealing more and
                            more detail for each visible image (right), until the very details of
                            one single drawing can be examined (bottom left).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Technology</head>
                <p>To make the visualization of 1492 images immediately responsive and interactive
                    we take several optimization measures<note> We are currently working on
                        generalizing our prototype. In this process, we will also publish the code
                        and a detailed documentation in an online repository for re-use and
                        replication of our framework.</note>:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><term>Multiple resolutions:</term> Images are provided at three different
                        resolutions depending on the current zoom level. The smallest versions (100
                        pixels per longer side) are rendered immediately when the visualization is
                        opened. This version provides sufficient resolution for an overview and some
                        level of zooming without loading additional images. The next level of detail
                        (1000 pixels per longer side) is rendered when the interface is zoomed to
                        such a detail that only a few images are visible in the current clip-out of
                        the canvas (see Fig. 5). Once one image is viewed individually, the highest
                        resolution is retrieved (5000 pixels), which allows the viewer to see
                        details of the drawing such as pencil strokes.</item>
                    <item><term>Image multiplexing:</term> The images of each zoom layer are bundled
                        and transferred as combined HTTP packages, in which the binary image data is
                        base64 encoded JPEG. This reduces the number of server requests and enables
                        faster transfer <ptr target="#grigorik2013"/>. ImageMagick’s lanczos2
                        algorithm provides the best compression while keeping borders and contours
                        of the drawings sharp. The HTTP payload is subsequently reduced through gzip
                        compression, in order to compensate for the bloating due to the base64
                        encoding. To allow for dynamic interaction right from the start, we employ a
                        progressive loading approach (see Fig. 6).</item>
                    <item><term>Web graphics:</term> The browser-based graphic rendering is
                        implemented using the graphics library pixi.js<note>
                            <ref target="http://www.pixijs.com/">http://www.pixijs.com/</ref></note>, which utilizes a WebGL context in a
                        canvas element. In addition, we used the visualization library d3.js<note>
                            <ref target="http://www.d3js.org/">http://www.d3js.org/</ref></note> for
                        scales, transitions and the zooming behavior. All images are rendered in
                        their full resolution onto a layer, which is then downscaled to the
                        corresponding zoom level. Once a scaled layer reaches its native resolution,
                        the subsequent new layer containing the images with higher resolution will
                        be displayed. This layer itself will start with a downscaled version and
                        will be scaled up when zooming.</item>
                    <item><term>Performance tweaks:</term> To prevent stuttering during panning and
                        zooming operations <ptr target="#liu2014"/>, we made sure that
                        computation-heavy tasks trigger after, not during interactions. For example,
                        during zooming, more detailed images are put in a queue, which is pushed
                        into the WebGL canvas after the zoom interaction is finished. The canvas
                        only renders images that are within 50% reach beyond the current viewport.
                        When the viewport is panned, high-resolution images beyond this area will be
                        removed from the render cache (not the browser cache) to reduce the
                        rendering load. To achieve fast and seamless animations for the text-based
                        elements, the rendering of the keywords and timeline is done using CSS3
                        animations of translate and scale operations, which are carried out on the
                        GPU.</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <head>Progressive loading: The user is able to view and interact with the
                        visualization after the first layer of detail is loaded. The second layer of
                        detail is being transferred in the background, which is split into multiple
                        CSV files, holding up to 150 high-resolution images per file.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Evaluation</head>
                <p>According to our research questions, we studied the visualization in different
                    settings and with a range of audiences. Besides regularly discussing the
                    prototype with our collaborators, we also presented it to other domain experts
                    at network meetings, public talks, or research colloquiums and collected their
                    responses and questions. At an earlier stage of development, the visualization
                    was shown during an exhibition in Berlin under the title <title rend="quotes">Past Visions of the Future City–Exploration of drawings penned by Frederick
                        William IV of Prussia,</title> putting an emphasis on the subset of drawings
                    that depict architectural and urban planning visions for Berlin and Potsdam.
                    Visitors mainly identified as being from the visualization and design community,
                    but also as groups of museum professionals. Still, there was a good balance with
                    spontaneous visitors from the neighborhood and surrounding areas with no
                    expertise in neither one of the fields. Most exhibition visitors had no, or only
                    little, knowledge of Prussian history or the King’s life. Accordingly, one
                    particular insight from conversations with visitors was their desire to also
                    learn more about Frederick William’s personal life or the political developments
                    of his time that had an influence on the drawings and sketches.Thus, we decided
                    to supplement the timeline with general historical facts, biographical events,
                    and other relatable information that would help to comprehend the collection
                    with little prior knowledge about the subject matter. By presenting these
                    earlier stages of the prototype in controlled environments and with the
                    potential to engage in conversations with domain experts or the general public,
                    we were able to continuously react to feedback by our peers during the
                    development process and learn more about how different types of users react to
                    the visualization and interface. Finally, we deployed the visualization as a web
                    application, logged user interactions, and linked a questionnaire in the
                    interface. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>6.1. Into the web</head>
                    <p>The visualization was then deployed online, framed by an introductory
                        microsite that laid out some general information about the scope and
                        background of the project. We integrated a questionnaire and anonymously
                        logged the user interaction on the basis of a list of pre-defined
                        parameters, including session time, time spent with the different
                        visualization components, and zoom level along these activities. The
                        deployment was monitored and logged over a 6-week period (10 February until
                        22 March 2016), during which a total of 994 unique users interacted with the
                        visualization. In addition to the data gathered from tracking the
                        interactions, we collected responses from 49 users that filled out the
                        questionnaire. Thereof, 31 identified as being residents of Potsdam or
                        Berlin, eight identified as living in other cities in Germany, Austria, and
                        Switzerland, three were UK residents, two each were from Australia and the
                        USA, one from the Netherlands. 14 users had a professional education in both
                        the humanities (art, history, cultural sciences, or architecture, which we
                        refer to as <soCalled>arts or culture experts</soCalled>) as well as in
                        design, computer sciences, or data visualization (referred to as
                            <soCalled>design or vis experts</soCalled>). 20 users had a background
                        only in arts or culture, 10 had a background only in design or vis. All but
                        three users had at least a university degree, 16 had a doctorate degree. The
                        log was linked to the questionnaire and allowed us to analyze the
                        interaction in correlation to the evaluation of the respective user. We
                        clustered the participants into experts in both fields (group 1), arts or
                        culture experts (group 2), design or vis experts (group 3), and laypersons
                        (group 4).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The interaction sequence visualization shows the first 6 minutes of
                            usage for participants who also filled out the questionnaire. Each
                            sequence is divided into blocks, which are colored by the interaction
                            classification corresponding with the different interface elements, and
                            scaled vertically to represent zoom level and the specificity of the
                            current keyword filter.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We analyzed the log files using an interaction sequence visualization (see
                        Fig. 7) with which we can see the order of functions used and level of
                        engagement with the visualization. Each relevant interaction parameter is
                        translated into a visual variable indicating the components of the interface
                        using color, temporal length as width, and the level of
                            <soCalled>closeness</soCalled> reached during the interaction as height.
                        Closeness is defined by the zoom level in the canvas and timeline as well as
                        by the number of keywords that were clicked and combined as a filter (thus
                        resulting in more refined results and only a few images displayed above the
                        timeline). The overall impression of the sequence visualization indicates
                        that people using the visualization in fact shifted between distanced
                        (small) and very detailed (tall) perspectives. A closer look on the sequence
                        visualization shows two distinct ways of bridging the different levels of
                        detail, one more gradual (triggered via zooming) and the other very abrupt
                        (triggered by clicks on individual images). Furthermore, the iterations
                        between canvas and timeline interactions are clearly visible by the
                        alternating red and orange blocks.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.2. Findings</head>
                    <p>With the questionnaire, participants were asked to evaluate a number of
                        statements on a Likert-scale (see Fig. 8). Regarding the usability of the
                        visualization, the assertion <q>While using the
                            visualization, I was able to easily find my way around the
                            interface</q> (question 7) reached a median agreement of 5 on a
                        scale from 0 (strongly disagree) to 6 (strongly agree). Accordingly, the
                        statement, <q>the interface is difficult to
                            operate</q> only scored a median agreement of 2. While more detailed
                        user experience testing has to be conducted to identify more specific
                        problems and obstacles, these first usability results already show us a
                        tendency towards decent operability. The participants reported that they
                        were able to get an overview of the contents and objects of the
                        visualization (median agreement of 5), while it also invited them to explore
                        the scope of the themes and engage with unfamiliar topics (question 3 and
                        5). Thus, the questionnaire confirmed our analysis of the interaction
                        sequences, which had already shown a good balance between
                            <soCalled>close</soCalled> and <soCalled>distant</soCalled> viewing. The
                        questionnaire also showed that the visualization is not perceived as being
                        solely a research tool but suitable for people looking for a cultural
                        recreational activity (questions 10 and 11). Due to the fact that only five
                        of the respondents were not experts in arts, culture, design or
                        visualization, it would nonetheless need further evaluation in order to be
                        able to better assess if the visualization also works well for interested
                        laypersons.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Box-and-whisker plot of questionnaire results along a Likert-scale
                            from 0 (strongly disagree) to 6 (strongly agree).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We also included two open questions and invited the participants to share
                        some general insights and suggestions for improvements. The answers given in
                        this qualitative section of the questionnaire can be grouped into four
                        categories of recurring feedback: interaction, content, design, and general
                        observations. All of which covered a range from positive to negative
                        observations. </p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item><term>Interaction.</term> The ability to zoom in into the canvas,
                            filter images by selecting tags, and have the images displayed in high
                            resolution was pointed out as positive features of the visualization and
                            were remarked as being noteworthy by seven participants. Nonetheless,
                            although the basic interactions are illustrated in the information
                            sidebar of the interface, five participants reported experiencing
                            trouble while using the visualization. As an example, one person
                            misinterpreted the text labels as a selector for the images instead of a
                            filter and thus was irritated when no image <quote rend="inline" source="#private">opened
                                in full size</quote> [P3, 40-45 years, group 1] after clicking on a
                            tag. This was also the case for two other participants, stating that the
                            images were too small - although the visualization is indeed zoomable up
                            to a high-resolution image. The visual indicators on the info sidebar
                            and the a text panel in the single-image view (clickable arrows pointing
                            to the side that hide the panels for a full-screen view of the canvas
                            and images) seemed to be too subtle for some participants, since three
                            people stated that they e.g. <quote rend="inline" source="#private">had wished to be able
                                to see a full-screen version of the images</quote> [P28, 40-45
                            years, doctorate degree, group 2] without having the info sidebar or the
                            text panel block the view. In one instance, the panning was perceived as
                            cumbersome. One person remarked that the zoom interaction depends on a
                            scroll wheel or touchpad and thus might exclude users that use other
                            hardware. This concurs to the call for being able to interact with the
                            interface using a keyboard and to improve accessibility as expressed by
                            one person.</item>
                        <item><term>Content.</term> The scope and richness of the drawings, the
                            artistic talent of the King, as well as his interest in architecture,
                            were pointed out as being memorable and impressive by seven people. The
                            King’s repeated journeys to Italy were among the discoveries pointed out
                            by several participants.<quote rend="block" source="#private">Well, up to now I have not
                                engaged much with Frederick William IV. In this respect I definitely
                                learned something new. This is a nice method for learning in a
                                discovery-mode. [P40, 45-50 years, group 3].</quote>The timeline was
                            perceived as novel and descriptive (4x) and deemed to be well suited for
                            the thematic scope (1x). One person pointed out that the descriptions
                            and art historical comments were very valuable for research purposes but
                            might be deterring for laypersons. Another person found the
                            visualization in itself interesting but not the content of it. One
                            person alludes to a key question of visualization in the humanities, how
                            to reveal what is missing or uncertain: <quote rend="block" source="#private">The metadata
                                is great, but the visualization seems to focus on what is in there
                                and easily accessible, not what is needed to really be interesting
                                [P35, 35-40 years, group 3].</quote></item>
                        <item><term>Design</term>. The combination of a timeline with entities of
                            different themes was pointed out and highlighted by one person as a
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#private">pleasant stimulation</quote> [P2, 40-45, group
                            1]. Being able to focus on a time of creation in relation to the themes
                            within the drawings, thus rapidly gaining an overview on what the king
                            was preoccupied with the most during what time, was also a feature that
                            was singled out (2x). One person found the visualization particularly
                            immersive: <quote rend="block" source="#private">I soaked up so much information in a
                                relative short amount of time and can now describe the setting of
                                this time period. I love the zooming and stumbling across this great
                                collection [P34, 30-35 years, doctorate degree, group 2].</quote>
                            The intersection of quantity and content with the drawings piled up as
                            bar chats was singled out as an interesting design feature (3x).</item>
                        <item><term>General.</term> Along more general observations, one person
                            stated that the visualization created the urge to revisit it with more
                            time on hand to be able to delve into the images. The quality of the
                            images was positively remarked (2x), while another person pointed out
                            that the loading time of the high-resolution images was disruptive. A
                            remark on possible improvements made by two people was to include
                            full-text search. Other desired features were additional content linked
                            to the timeline and the images (2x), such as historical photos or a
                            geovisualization of the places and buildings depicted in the
                            drawings.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.3. Expert observations</head>
                    <p>We were interested to evaluate if the visualization could also be used as a
                        tool for art historical research. Thus, we asked one of the art historians
                        from the heritage foundation to assess if he or his colleagues are able to
                        derive insights by using the visualization. His feedback summarized the
                        advantages of the temporal arrangement and thematic filter functionality,
                        which creates curve progressions that are highly interesting for art
                        historical research. One significant example for this observation is
                        provided by the sheets covering Charlottenhof Palace. The shape created by
                        the bars along the timeline clearly shows the intensity with which the crown
                        prince worked on his later executed designs after receiving the estate by
                        his father in 1825. Other biographical or political events, such as his
                        marriage or the dawn of revolutions, equally left their traces in his
                        drawings. Thus, his intensive planning on the restructuring of his study and
                        his apartment can be related to his marriage and settling with his wife in
                        the Berlin city palace. Apart from being able to identify dominating themes,
                        the visualization could be instrumental in the effort of obtaining more
                        precise dating. One of the examples is the depiction of the German piked
                        helmet on some of the King’s drawings. The helmet was not used by the
                        Prussian Army earlier than 1843, allowing for a specification of time
                        assigned to some sheets that accumulate several drawings that were
                        interpreted and dated independently. From an expert point of view, the
                        visualization may provide an effective and powerful tool to refine and
                        verify previous art historical findings, datings, and examinations. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>7. Discussion</head>
                <p>The importance of close collaboration with domain experts in fields like digital
                    art history <ptr target="#promey1997"/> was self-evident throughout the process
                    of our research and the development of the visualization. Only by including
                    expert knowledge from the humanities as well as from interface design, computer
                    science, and data visualization we were able to reach a level of mutual
                    understanding for the relevant topics and challenges that were crucial to our
                    work. Pursuing the notion of <soCalled>cultural sensitivity,</soCalled> the
                    content of the collection was the driving force during the design process.
                    Although the resulting visualization was not intended as a one-fits all solution
                    in the sense of a visualization tool that could be used unmodified for a broad
                    range of data sets, we recognized some promising aspects in the zoomable and
                    filterable canvas that can be transferred to other use cases beyond this
                    specific collection. In the following, we discuss some of our insights and
                    critically evaluate our use case with regard to the areas that would call for
                    additional research and refinement.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The temporal arrangement of paintings by Van Gogh reflects a general
                        tendency from dark to lighter colors.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The collection subset used for the case study consists of about 1500 data records
                    of a collection of drawings that will eventually include more than 7000 sheets.
                    Knowing that the collection will be gradually digitized, we had to take into
                    account the scalability of our approach. Although we have already run some
                    preliminary tests with 7000 images, we would have to assess the performance of
                    the visualization when scaled to such a size more thoroughly. These questions of
                    scalability pave the way for transferring our approach to other image datasets
                    of varying sizes and metadata structures. While the use case was specifically
                    designed and developed for the drawings of Frederick William IV, the relatively
                    monochrome drawings with low contrast are weaker in a ‘distant’ viewing mode,
                    compared to images with higher contrast and a broader palette of colors. Thus,
                    in order to assess the general viability of transferring our framework, we ran
                    two trials with other data sets. For one, we explored about a thousand
                    paintings, drawings, and other artworks by Vincent Van Gogh<note><ref target="http://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/">http://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/</ref></note> (see Fig. 9). For the other, we
                    loaded 3915 items from the New York Public Library collection of Detroit
                    Publishing Company postcards<note>
                        <ref target="http://digitalcollections.nypl.org/collections/detroit-publishing-company-postcards/">http://digitalcollections.nypl.org/collections/detroit-publishing-company-postcards/</ref></note>.
                    Initial results indicate that images with a higher contrast and broader palette
                    of colors lend themselves well to exploration in a zoomable and filterable image
                    plot. For example, in the case of Van Gogh, not only quantitative insights about
                    the thematic distribution of works are visualized, but also their visual texture
                    can be examined, e.g., the dominance of darker colors in his early paintings
                    compared to brighter or more colorful shades in the later years becomes clearly
                    visible (see Fig. 9). Similarly, the potential of alternative layouts came up
                    during the iterative development. On the one hand, these layouts could be
                    particularly relevant to the specifics of a collection, for example, the
                    geographical distribution was suggested by participants of our study. On the
                    other hand, we are interested to see how the collection would behave in
                    similarity-based layouts (such as t-SNE) or grid layouts <ptr target="#klingemann2015"/> based on the metadata. Since the metadata is
                    based on in-depth art historical research along a controlled vocabulary,
                    similarity-based layouts may support the exploration of drawings by affinity. In
                    that sense, such layouts could translate the qualitative insights from the art
                    historical classification into a spatial arrangement.</p>
                <p>Cultural heritage data is often characterized by incompleteness and uncertainty.
                    While we were able to employ a subset from a collection that had a relatively
                    high level of completeness in regards to required metadata fields, depth of
                    assessment, and a standardized taxonomy, it lies in the nature of qualitatively
                    sourced data to implicate uncertainty, especially with regard to time <ptr target="#davis2015"/>. This also being the case for the subset of drawings
                    by Frederick William IV, discussing the issue with our project partners again
                    highlighted that this is not a problem that is possible to be solved, but that
                    needs to be addressed in the design of what might be called <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2011">humanistic interfaces</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>
                    </cit>. During the next iteration of the prototype, we hope to be able to futher
                    discuss and explore how timeline visualizations could visually reflect temporal
                    uncertainty. Even though we already decided to integrate additional contextual
                    information in the timeline — thus including data that had to be specifically
                    sourced and authored manually — some responses by participants in the
                    questionnaire showed that there is a desire for even more contextual data and
                    content from sources that go beyond the defined collection data set. Although
                    the problem was addressed as a general one in regards to cultural heritage
                    interfaces, considering the expansion of used sources and maybe even
                    implementing a layer for community co-creation and annotation (by using
                    folksonomy or crowdsourcing <ptr target="#ridge2014"/>) could be valuable during
                    the next phase of the project. Nonetheless, the question of missing data also
                    has to be seen with regard to the reality and actual state of digitization in
                    most collecting institutions. The sheer amount of collection items, the costs of
                    the digitization process, and the need of expertise when assessing an item and
                    its metadata often make it hard for collecting institutions to meet such
                    requirements just yet.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>8. Conclusion</head>
                <p>With this research we have explored the potential of zoomable visualizations of
                    cultural heritage collections. A collaborative design process with a heritage
                    institution resulted in a visualization technique, which is aimed at supporting
                    a <soCalled>distant-viewing</soCalled> approach coupled with a
                        <soCalled>close-viewing</soCalled> mode for the exploration of a historical
                    collection. We showed how visualizing the quantitative structure of a collection
                    can be complemented by allowing for examination of the qualitative texture of
                    the individual object. This work contributes insights to discourses on digital
                    heritage as well as on information visualization. In the early years, research
                    in the field of digital cultural heritage and the digital humanities was often
                    dominated by computational or technological solutions originally developed in
                    other fields and for other purposes. Following a shift towards digital heritage
                    research that puts the needs, challenges, and requirements of cultural heritage
                    in the focus and then seeks to find technological and computational solutions
                    for a mainly content-driven approach, we introduced our research in a sense of
                        <soCalled>cultural sensitivity.</soCalled> At the same time, humanities
                    research that employs computational methods is often perceived as dominated by a
                    solely quantitative, positivist, or distant approach. Quantitative research in
                    the humanities, in turn, is often questioned on the notion of the alleged
                    necessity of qualitative examination in order to be able to truly grasp the
                    sources’ significance. This <soCalled>quantitative-qualitative divide</soCalled>
                    in the humanities, though, is not inherently a digitally inducted discord.
                    Empirical or quantitative methodologies existed in the humanities long before
                    the establishment of computers and web technologies in these fields <ptr target="#drucker2015"/>. Even in pre-digital humanities research, the
                    tendency to either value quantitative research over qualitative research or vice
                    versa already existed <ptr target="#macnealy1999"/>. Rather than carrying on an
                    antagonistic discourse of <soCalled>close vs. distant,</soCalled>
                    <soCalled>qualitative vs. quantitative</soCalled> under the slogan of
                        <soCalled>digital vs. analog,</soCalled> there is an increasing recognition
                    of the potential in experimenting and engaging with digital technologies that
                    can help to actually unify these seemingly opposed strands, predominantly in
                    language-centric research <ptr target="#janicke2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#koch2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#muralidharan2013"/>. With our research we expand on this notion
                    and apply it to a collection of visual resources. Our contributions thus are
                    relevant for the ever growing research activities in digital art history, as
                    well as a foundation for further work on visualization in the context of digital
                    cultural heritage.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>We wish to thank the reviewers of the Digital Humanities Quarterly for their
                    thoughtful feedback and suggestions. We would like to acknowledge the German
                    Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF) for their generous funding of
                    our research project VIKUS - Visualizing Cultural Collections (Visualisierung
                    kultureller Sammlungen). We thank our project partners SPSG and Programmfabrik
                    GmbH for the productive cooperation. We wish to thank Matthias Graf for his work
                    on a previous version of the visualization, Jörg Meiner for his scientific
                    consulting and for valuable ideas, Carsten Dilba for his continuous feedback,
                    and – last but not least – we are thankful for the support from our colleagues
                    Sebastian Meier, Till Nagel, Stephanie Neumann und Jan-Erik Stange.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="algee2012" label="Algee et al. 2012">Lauren Algee, Jefferson Bailey,
                    and Trevor Owens. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Viewshare and the Kress Collection:
                        Creating, sharing, and rapidly prototypingvisual interfaces to cultural
                        heritage collection data.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title>, 18(11):3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bederson1994" label="Bederson and Hollan 1994"> YB.B. Bederson and
                    J.D. Hollan. 1994. <title rend="quotes">Pad++: a zooming graphical interface for
                        exploring alternate interface physics.</title> In <title rend="italic">UIST 1994: Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology</title>.
                    ACM, 17–26.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bender2015" label="Bender 2015">K Bender. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Distant Viewing in Art History. A Case Study of Artistic
                        Productivity.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Int. Journal for Digital Art History</title> 1
                    (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bentkowskakafel2015" label="Bentkowska-Kafel 2015">Anna
                    Bentkowska-Kafel. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Debating Digital Art
                        History.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Int. Journal for Digital Art History</title> 1
                    (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bentkowskakafel2005" label="Bentkowska-Kafel 2005">Anna
                    Bentkowska-Kafel, Trish Cashen, and Hazel Gardiner (Eds.). 2005. <title rend="italic">Digital art history: a subject in transition</title>.
                    Computers and the history of art series 1, Vol. 1. Intellect.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bhawuk1992" label="Bhawuk and Brislin 1992">Dharm Bhawuk and Richard
                    Brislin. 1992. <title rend="quotes">The Measurement of intercultural sensitivity
                        using the concepts of individualism and collectivism.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Intercultural Relations</title>.
                    16(4), 413-436. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cameron2007" label="Cameron 2007">Fiona Cameron. 2007. <title rend="quotes">Beyond the Cult of the Replicant–Museums and Historical
                        Digital Objects: Traditional Concerns, New Discourses.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Theorizing Digital Cultural Heritage A Critical
                        Discourse</title>. The MIT Press, 49–75.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chen2014" label="Chen et al. 2014">Ko-Le Chen, Marian Dörk, and Martyn
                    Dade-Robertson. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Promises and Potentials
                        of Visual Archive Interfaces.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">iConference 2014 Proceedings: Breaking Down Walls. Culture
                        - Context - Computing</title> (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis2013" label="Davis et al. 2013">Stephen Boyd Davis, Emma Bevan,
                    and Aleksei Kudikov. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Just in time: defining
                        historical chronographics.</title> In <title rend="italic">Electronic
                        Visualisation in Arts and Culture</title>. Springer, 243–257.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis2015" label="Davis and Kräutli 2015">Stephen Boyd Davis and
                    Florian Kräutli. 2015. <title rend="quotes">The Idea and Image of Historical
                        Time: Interactions between Design and Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visible Language</title> 49, 3 (2015), 101.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dork2012" label="Dörk et al. 2012">Marian Dörk, Sheelagh Carpendale,
                    and Carey Williamson. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Fluid Views: a zoomable search
                        environment.</title> In <title rend="italic">AVI 2012: Advanced Visual
                        Interfaces</title>. ACM, 233–240.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Johanna Drucker. 2011. <title rend="quotes">Humanities approaches to graphical display.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5, 1 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013">Johanna Drucker. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Is There a “Digital” Art History?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visual Resources</title> 29, 1-2 (2013), 5–13.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2015" label="Drucker et al. 2015">Johanna Drucker, Anne
                    Helmreich, Matthew Lincoln, and Francesca Rose. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Digital art history: the American scene.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Perspective [Online]</title> 2 (2015). <ref target="http://perspective.revues.org/6021">http://perspective.revues.org/6021</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dudley2012" label="Dudley 2012">Sandra Dudley. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Materiality Matters: Experiencing the Displayed
                        Object.</title> In <title rend="italic">Working Papers in Museum Studies
                    </title>8. University of Michigan (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galey2010" label="Galey and Ruecker 2010">Alan Galey and Stan Ruecker.
                    2010. <title rend="quotes">How a prototype argues.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 25, 4 (2010),
                    405–424.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibbs2012" label="Gibbs and Owens 2012">Fred Gibbs and Trevor Owens.
                    2012. <title rend="quotes">Building better digital humanities tools: Toward
                        broader audiences and user-centered designs.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 6, 2 (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="glinka2015" label="Glinka et al. 2015">Katrin Glinka, Sebastian Meier,
                    and Marian Dörk. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Visualising the Un-seen: Towards
                        Critical Approaches and Strategies of Inclusion in Digital Cultural Heritage
                        Interfaces.</title> In <title rend="italic">Kultur und Informatik</title>.
                    vwh, 105–118.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gosden1999" label="Gosden and Marshall 1999">Chris Gosden and Yvonne
                    Marshall. 1999. <title rend="quotes">The Cultural Biography of Objects.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">World Archaeology</title>, Vol. 31, No. 2 (1999),
                    169-178.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greene2000" label="Greene et al. 2000">Stephan Greene, Gary
                    Marchionini, Catherine Plaisant, and Ben Shneiderman. 2000. <title rend="quotes">Previews and overviews in digital libraries: designing surrogates to
                        support visual information seeking.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information
                        Science</title> 51, 4 (2000), 380–393.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grigorik2013" label="Grigorik 2013">Ilya Grigorik. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Making the Web Faster with HTTP 2.0.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Queue</title> 11, 10 (2013), 40:40–40:53. 1542-7730</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="haber2011" label="Haber et al. 2011">Jonathan Haber, Sean Lynch, and
                    Sheelagh Carpendale. 2011. <title rend="quotes">ColourVis: exploring colour
                        usage in paintings over time.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the International Symposium on Computational Aesthetics in Graphics,
                        Visualization, and Imaging</title>. ACM, 105–112.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hinrichs2016" label="Hinrichs et al. 2016">Uta Hinrichs, Stefania
                    Forlini, and Bridget Moynihan. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Speculative Practices:
                        Utilizing InfoVis to Explore Untapped Literary Collections.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions
                        on</title> 22, 1 (2016), 429–438.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hinrichs2008" label="Hinrichs et al. 2008">Uta Hinrichs, Holly
                    Schmidt, and Sheelagh Carpendale. 2008. <title rend="quotes">EMDialog: Bringing
                        Information Visualization into the Museum.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 14, 6 (Nov/Dec 2008), 1181–1188.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hochman2013" label="Hochman and Manovich 2013">Nadav Hochman and Lev
                    Manovich. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Zooming into an Instagram City: Reading the
                        local through social media.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">First Monday</title> 18, 7 (July 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hullman2011" label="Hullman and Diakopoulos 2011">Jessica Hullman and
                    Nick Diakopoulos. 2011. <title rend="quotes">Visualization Rhetoric: Framing
                        Effects in Narrative Visualization.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 17, 12 (Dec 2011), 2231–2240.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="isemann2014" label="Isemann and Ahmad 2014">Daniel Isemann and
                    Khurshid Ahmad. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Ontological Access to Images of Fine
                        Art.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title> 7, 1,
                    Article 3 (April 2014), 25 pages. 1556-4673 <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2538030">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2538030</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="janicke2015" label="Jänicke et al. 2015">Jänicke, Stefan; Franzini,
                    Greta; Cheema, Muhammad Faisal; Scheuermann, Gerik 2015. <title rend="quotes">On
                        Close and Distant Reading in Digital Humanities: A Survey and Future
                        Challenges.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Eurographics Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) -
                        STARs</title> (2015), 83–103.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klingemann2015" label="Klingemann 2015">Mario Klingemann. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Raster Fairy transform any kind of 2D point cloud into a
                        regular raster.</title> https://github.com/Quasimondo/RasterFairy –
                    Retrieved 2016-03-25. (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koch2014" label="Koch et al. 2014">S. Koch, M. John, M. Worner, A.
                    Muller, and T. Ertl. 2014. <title rend="quotes">VarifocalReader – In-Depth
                        Visual Analysis of Large Text Documents.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 20, 12 (Dec 2014), 1723–1732.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="krautli2016" label="Kräutli 2016">Florian Kräutli. 2016. <title rend="italic">Visualising Cultural Data: Exploring Digital Collections
                        Through Timeline Visualisations.</title> PhD thesis, Royal College of
                    Art.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kucher2014" label="Kucher and Kerran 2014">Kostiantyn Kucher and
                    Andreas Kerren. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Text visualization browser: A visual
                        survey of text visualization techniques.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Poster Abstracts of IEEE VIS</title> 2014 (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2014" label="Liu and Heer 2014">Z. Liu and J. Heer. 2014. <title rend="quotes">The Effects of Interactive Latency on Exploratory Visual
                        Analysis.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 20, 12 (Dec 2014), 2122–2131.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macnealy1999" label="MacNealy 1999">Mary Sue MacNealy. 1999. <title rend="italic">Empirical Research in the Humanities</title>. Vol. Strategies
                    for Empirical Research in Writing. Allyn and Bacon, Chapter 1.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malpas2007" label="Malpas 2007">Jeff Malpas (2007) <title rend="quotes">Cultural Heritage in the Age of New Media.</title> In: Yehuda
                    Kalay, Thomas Kvan, Janice Affleck (eds.) <title rend="italic">New Heritage: New
                        Media and Cultural Heritage.</title> Routledge, 2007. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2015" label="Manovich 2015">Lev Manovich. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Data Science and Digital Art History.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Int. Journal for Digital Art History</title> 1 (2015),
                    13–35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccurdy2016" label="McCurdy et al. 2016">N. McCurdy, J. Lein, K.
                    Coles, and M. Meyer. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Poemage: Visualizing the Sonic
                        Topology of a Poem.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 22, 1 (Jan 2016), 439–448.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2005" label="Moretti 2005">Franco Moretti. 2005. <title rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract models for a literary
                        history</title>. Verso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muralidharan2013" label="Muralidharan and Hearst 2013">Aditi
                    Muralidharan and Marti A. Hearst. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Supporting
                        exploratory text analysis in literature study.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 28, 2 (2013),
                    283–295.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parry2007" label="Parry 2007">Ross Parry. 2007. <title rend="italic">Recoding the Museum. Digital Heritage and the Technologies of
                        Change.</title> Routledge. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="promey1997" label="Promey and Stewart 1997">Sally M Promey and Miriam
                    Stewart. 1997. <title rend="quotes">Digital art history: A new field for
                        collaboration.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">American Art</title> 11, 2 (1997), 36–41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ridge2014" label="Ridge 2014">Mia Ridge. 2014. <title rend="italic">Crowdsourcing our Cultural Heritage</title>. Ashgate Publishing Company. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruecker2011" label="Ruecker et al. 2011"> Stanislaus Ruecker, Milena
                    Radzikowska, and Stéfan Sinclair. 2011. <title rend="italic">Visual interface
                        design for digital cultural heritage: A guide to rich-prospect
                        browsing.</title> Ashgate Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="saleh2015" label="Saleh and Elgammal 2015">Babak Saleh and Ahmed
                    Elgammal. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Large-scale Classification of Fine-Art
                        Paintings: Learning The Right Metric on The Right Feature.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">arXiv preprint arXiv:1505.00855</title> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanders2008" label="Sanders and Stappers 2008">Elizabeth Sanders and
                    Pieter J. Stappers. 2008. <title rend="quotes">Co-creation and the new
                        landscapes of design.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Co-design</title> 4, 1 (2008), 5–18.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schich2010" label="Schich 2010">Maximilian Schich. 2010. <title rend="quotes">Revealing Matrices.</title> In <title rend="italic">Beautiful
                        Visualization: Looking at Data through the Eyes of Experts</title>.
                    O’Reilly, Chapter 14, 227–254.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schnapp2009" label="Schnapp et al. 2009">Jeffrey Schnapp, Todd
                    Presner, Peter Lunenfeld, and others. 2009. <title rend="italic">The digital
                        humanities manifesto 2.0.</title>
                    <ref target="http://http://manifesto.humanities.ucla.edu/2009/05/29/the-digital-humanities-manifesto-20/">http://http://manifesto.humanities.ucla.edu/2009/05/29/the-digital-humanities-manifesto-20/</ref>
                    – Retrieved 2016-08-25. (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sedlmair2012" label="Sedlmair et al. 2012">Michael Sedlmair, Miriah
                    Meyer, and Tamara Munzner. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Design Study Methodology:
                        Reflections from the Trenches and the Stacks.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 18, 12 (2012), 2431–2440.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sfmoma2008" label="SFMOMA 2008">SFMOMA. 2008. <title rend="italic">Explore Modern Art — ArtScope.</title>
                    <ref target="https://www.sfmoma.org/experience/artscope/">https://www.sfmoma.org/experience/artscope/</ref> – Retrieved 2016-08-26.
                    (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shamir2012" label="Shamir and Tarakhovsky 2012">Lior Shamir and
                    Jane A. Tarakhovsky. 2012. Computer <title rend="quotes">Analysis of
                        Art.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title> 5, 2,
                    Article 7 (Aug. 2012), 11 pages. 1556-4673 <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2307723.2307726">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2307723.2307726</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shneiderman1996" label="Shneiderman 1996">Ben Shneiderman. 1996.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for
                        Information Visualizations.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages</title>. 336–343.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schumacher2016" label="Schumacher 2016">Susanne Schumacher (2016)
                        <title rend="quotes">Using words to network images: indexing and interaction
                        strategies in a digital archive,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visual Studies</title>, 31:2, 121-130.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="snow1959" label="Snow 1959">C. P. Snow. 1959. <title rend="italic">The
                        Two Cultures and the Scientific Revolution. The Rede Lecture.</title>
                    Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thudt2012" label="Thudt et al. 2012">Alice Thudt, Uta Hinrichs, and
                    Sheelagh Carpendale. 2012. <title rend="quotes">The Bohemian Bookshelf:
                        Supporting serendipitous book discoveries through information
                        visualization.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the SIGCHI
                        Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>, pages
                    1461–1470.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="watkins2015" label="Watkins et al. 2015">Rebecca D. Watkins, Abigail
                    Sellen, Siân E. Lindley. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Digital collections and
                        digital collecting practices.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems,</title> pages
                    3423–3432.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wattenberg2008" label="Wattenberg and Viégas 2008">Martin Wattenberg
                    and Fernanda B. Viégas. 2008. <title rend="quotes">The Word Tree, an Interactive
                        Visual Concordance.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TVCG: Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title> 14, 6 (2008), 1221–1228.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whitelaw2015" label="Whitelaw 2015">Mitchell Whitelaw. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Generous Interfaces for Digital Cultural Collections.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 9, 1 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zweig2015" label="Zweig 2015">Benjamin Zweig. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Forgotten Genealogies: Brief Reflections on the History of
                        Digital Art History.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Int. Journal for Digital Art History</title> 1 (2015),
                    101–110.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>