<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">A Culture of non-citation: Assessing the digital impact of
                    British History Online and the Early English Books Online Text Creation
                    Partnership</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jonathan <dhq:family>Blaney</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute of Historical Research, University of
                        London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jonathan.blaney@sas.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jonathan joined the IHR in 2007 as Project Editor for British History
                            Online's project to complete the digitisation of the Calendars of State
                            Papers. He now continues to work for part of the time on BHO, as well as
                            spending time on Connected Histories and IHR web projects. ORCID ID:
                                <ref target="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5044-5038">0000-0002-5044-5038</ref>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Judith <dhq:family>Siefring</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>judith.siefring@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Judith Siefring is the Head of Digital Research at the Bodleian
                            Libraries' Center for Digital Research at Oxford University. ORCID ID:
                                <ref target="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4385-6576">0000-0002-4385-6576</ref>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000282</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2016-12-01">1 December 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>citation</item>
                        <item>digital citation</item>
                        <item>URL structures</item>
                        <item>digital resources</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p> This article discusses the culture of digital citation within the humanities,
                    with specific reference to research done on the citation of two well-used
                    digital resources: British History Online and the Early English Books Online
                    Text Creation Partnership. Because these two resources are available in both
                    print and digital form, they provide a good test case of whether academics
                    prefer to cite print sources when they have used digital resources in their
                    research.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Blaney and Siefring explore the culture of digital citation within the
                    humanities.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#compagnon1979">The initial effect of printing was not that of an increased
                        distribution of identical copies being put into numerous hands...it was,
                        first and foremost, the very transformation of the ethics of reading and
                        writing</quote>
                    <ptr target="#compagnon1979" loc="245"/>
                </cit>
                <note><foreign xml:lang="fr">"L'effet initial de l'imprimerie n'est pas celui d'une
                        diffusion accrue d'exemplaires identiques d'un même texte mis ainsi dans
                        beaucoup de mains...il est d'abord et surtout la transformation même de
                        l'éthique de la lecture et de l'écriture"</foreign>.</note>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <head>The glamour of print</head>
                <p>There is no doubt that print sources, as opposed to digital ones, still carry
                    immense cultural cachet. As this article will explore in detail, many scholars
                    prefer to cite the print version of a work, even when they have only seen a
                    digital surrogate, in part because of this perceived prestige. We shall see that
                    such practice is problematic in a number of ways, and causes difficulties even
                    when using resources which are widely used and respected. For example, reference
                    works such as the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title> (OED)
                    and <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia Britannica</title> (particularly the 11th
                    edition of 1910-11) are viewed as paragons of scholarship. Those who have worked
                    in reference publishing (such as the authors of this paper) may have a slightly
                    more nuanced view: mistakes and misjudgements inevitably occur and a large pool
                    of contributors creates problems of consistency. The larger the project (the OED
                    runs to 20 volumes plus supplements as of last printing<note> The Oxford English
                        Dictionary (Second Edition), edited by John Simpson and Edmund Weiner, was
                        published by the Clarendon Press in 1989. The first edition was printed in
                        parts between 1884 and 1928, and the dictionary has been revised, updated
                        and supplemented over the years. In 2000, the OED moved from print to online
                        publication, www.oed.com, and since then the dictionary has been undergoing
                        its first major revision. A concise account of the history of the OED may be
                        found at <ref target="http://public.oed.com/history-of-the-oed/">http://public.oed.com/history-of-the-oed/</ref> [Accessed November
                        2015]</note>) the more difficult amendments, at least in the print copies,
                    become.</p>
                <p>An example of this unevenness is the OED entry for <term>hubris</term>, which
                    falls far below its usual standards. The definition is <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#oed1933">Presumption, orig. towards the gods; pride, excessive
                        self-confidence</quote>
                    <ptr target="#oed1933"/></cit>. This is flatly contradicted by the first quotations,
                    which have nothing to do with gods. The etymology is short by OED standards,
                        <soCalled>&lt;Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὓβρις</foreign></soCalled> and
                    inadequate: which parts of the definition equate to Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὓβρις</foreign>? All of them? Arguably none of them do, in
                    fact. Liddell and Scott’s Greek Lexicon, still the standard dictionary of
                    classical Greek for English speakers, gives a number of meanings of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὓβρις</foreign>: <quote rend="inline" source="#oed1933">wanton violence;
                        insolence; lust, lewdness; (of animals) violence; an outrage; violation,
                        rape; serious injury to the person; a loss by sea; an overbearing
                        man</quote>. The sense development from Greek to English has been ignored by
                    the OED, except insofar as it has confused the definer.</p>
                <p>A much better treatment of <term>hubris</term> is to be found in Wikipedia <ptr target="#wikipedia2016"/>. Here the complexities of the term are addressed
                    much more fully<note> One of our peer reviewers pointed out that this definition
                        is derived from Merriam-Webster Online, which had escaped our notice. We are
                        grateful for the information and, more generally, to the comments of the
                        anonymous reviews which have enabled us to improve this article.</note>. The
                    OED entry was written in 1933 and, it seems, has not been revised since, other
                    than to add some newer citations. There is no doubt that when the OED team comes
                    around to revising <title>hubris</title> they will produce a superior
                        entry<note> Compare, for example, the etymology in the OED’s (revised) entry
                        for <term>omphalos</term>: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#oed2004">&lt; ancient Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀμϕαλός</foreign> navel, centre, hub, round stone in the temple
                                of Apollo at Delphi supposed to mark the centre of the earth, knob
                                or boss (ultimately cognate with navel n.). In quot. 1847 at sense
                                2a via German Omphalos (1830 in the source translated)</quote>
                            <ptr target="#oed2004"/>
                        </cit>.</note>. However, it is likely that there will never be another print
                    edition of the OED <ptr target="#dailytelegraph2014"/>, so any improved
                        <term>hubris</term> will never be citable in a print format. Advocates of
                    print citation over digital citation would be condemned by their stated
                    principles to forever cite a piece of work that is flawed.</p>
                <p>It is clear that we are at a critical juncture in the culture of citation.
                    Reference sources and journals are increasingly becoming online only, or exist
                    online in expanded versions of print. Yet, for reasons this paper will explore,
                    there is still a widespread aversion to the citing (as opposed to the using) of
                    digital resources. It remains a brave researcher who will cite Wikipedia in
                    preference to the OED.</p>
                <p>In this article we will explore the resistance to citing digital sources that is
                    still widespread in the humanities. We have found that this resistance is
                    particularly prevalent where a print version of the source also exists; for this
                    reason we have focused on two digital projects which can be consulted online but
                    whose citations can be silently <soCalled>converted</soCalled> to a print-only
                    reference. As well as presenting the results of several surveys of users, we
                    will suggest some solutions to the culture of non-citation which we
                    uncovered.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A neglected topic</head>
                <p>Despite our discovery of this pervasive culture of non-citation, we have been
                    able to find little mention of it as a research topic. It is noticeable, in
                    reviewing the literature on digital citation, that cross-disciplinary studies of
                    the subject tend to <emph>exclude</emph> humanities subjects<note> For example,
                            <ptr target="#hajjem2005"/>, which does not include a humanities subject
                        in its 10 candidate disciplines.</note>, preferring to measure disciplines
                    from the sciences and social sciences. One such study says, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lozano">Humanities papers were excluded from the analysis
                            because of their long citation windows and high uncitedness
                            rates</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lozano"/>
                    </cit>. Effectively, digital citations in the humanities are so low as not to
                    register in comparison with science and social sciences: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#larviere2009">The very low percentage of articles cited at least once
                            may be a reflection of the tendency of humanities researchers to cite
                            books instead of articles</quote>
                        <ptr target="#larviere2009"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Note that here we are talking about citation of articles. The focus of this
                    article, the citation of digital resources, appears to be the unloved son of the
                    unloved son. This impression is borne out by the present authors’ experience
                    when surveying journal editors about their digital citation practices. Many
                    editors assumed, in an understandable but illuminating example of
                        <emph>déformation professionelle</emph>, that by digital citation we meant
                    simply citation of online articles. This is not primarily what we mean here, but
                    it is important to note that citation of articles is more familiar to humanities
                    scholars than citation of digital resources such as digital libraries. This is
                    in part because tools such as Crossref automatically offer digital citations for
                    articles alongside print citations and in part because citation of online
                    articles has a certain congruity and familiarity with their print siblings.</p>
                <p>Dalbello et al. have studied the digital citations in five journals in Classical
                    Studies and English and come to the same broad conclusions as the present
                    article: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dalbello2006">supporting argument by means of electronic document
                                [<emph>sic</emph>]…is not considered to be evidentiary… and… [t]hese
                            citation practices point to the still invisible nature of the electronic
                            document that is now ubiquitous in supporting the actual research
                            practice</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dalbello2006" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>A small-scale study (with 16 participants) examined the use of e-texts, defined
                    as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sukovic2009">any textual material in electronic form, used as a
                            primary source</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sukovic2009" loc="1002"/>
                    </cit>, and found that e-texts used in research were largely excluded from
                    citation in the written output: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sukovic2009">references clearly did not represent the extent of
                            e-text used in the research</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sukovic2009" loc="1007"/>
                    </cit>. Sukovic’s study, although not statistically significant, also found more
                    likelihood of citing e-texts where no corresponding print version exists <ptr target="#sukovic2009" loc="1009"/>. What is unique about the present study
                    is that we have concentrated on digital resources where a print copy does exist
                    and where a digital citation is very easily converted to a print citation. This
                    situation provides the sternest test of a scholar’s attitude and citation
                    ethics, which in itself reflects the prevailing attitude to the scholarliness of
                    each type of citation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>British History Online and EEBO-TCP as case studies</head>
                <p>This paper studies the citation of two digital resources: <title rend="italic">British History Online</title> (BHO) and <title rend="italic">The Early
                        English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</title> (EEBO-TCP). These are
                    highly instructive case studies for two reasons: they both offer digital
                    versions of print originals (which means that users can choose to cite print,
                    even when they have used digital) and both resources proved amenable to being
                    analysed using the Oxford Internet Institute’s <title rend="italic">Toolkit for
                        the Impact of Digitised Scholarly Resources</title> (TIDSR), which uses
                    quantitative (analytics, bibliometrics, log file analysis, surveys, webometrics)
                    and qualitative (focus groups, workshops, interviews, user feedback) methods to
                    evaluate the impact of scholarly digital resources <ptr target="#tidsr"/>.</p>
                <p>British History Online <ptr target="#bho2015"/> and the Early English Books
                    Online Text Creation Partnership <ptr target="#eebotcp2015"/> have both become
                    key resources in their fields. BHO, begun in 2003, is a digital library of core
                    sources for the history of the British Isles; it is run by the Institute of
                    Historical Research (IHR) and the History of Parliament Trust (HoP). It contains
                    about 1250 transcribed texts to date. EEBO-TCP is a collaboration between the
                    Universities of Oxford and Michigan and the commercial publisher ProQuest, which
                    creates searchable XML-encoded editions of early English books based on
                    ProQuest’s image resource. EEBO-TCP began in 1999 and will ultimately create
                    around 70,000 full texts which are accessed chiefly via ProQuest’s interface,
                    although there are also other, local implementations. EEBO-TCP is currently
                    available only through academic subscription at institutional level. However,
                    all EEBO-TCP texts will ultimately be freely available in the public domain, and
                    restrictions were lifted on the first batch of materials on 1 January 2015<note>
                        This first public release amounted to 25,363 texts. Eventually, around
                        70,000 texts will be made freely available.</note>. By contrast, in BHO,
                    while some of the texts are behind a subscription paywall, the majority of the
                    site is freely available. </p>
                <p>EEBO-TCP aims to create an XML-encoded edition of every monographic text printed
                    in English or in England in the period 1473-1700. If there is more than one
                    edition of a particular work, then the first edition is selected unless there is
                    a compelling reason to choose a later one (if the first edition is badly damaged
                    or incomplete, for example). The texts for BHO are chosen by an academic
                    advisory group from the IHR and HoP, with a view to meeting the needs of its
                    core users; BHO is aimed at research-level historians (one university, after a
                    trial of BHO's subscription content, declined on the basis that it was too
                    advanced for its undergraduates). Similarly, EEBO-TCP’s core users are generally
                    scholars at postgraduate level and beyond, although many undergraduates do use
                    the resource too<note> It is notable that only 1% of respondents to an EEBO-TCP
                        user survey (discussed in more detail below) identified themselves as
                        undergraduates, compared to, for example postgraduate students (38%),
                        professors (19%) and academic researchers (20%).</note>.</p>
                <p>BHO receives about 10 million page views per year. Having carried out the TIDSR
                    analysis in 2010-11, it became clear that, despite this high usage, it is very
                    little cited in academic literature <ptr target="#webster2011"/>. The
                    bibliometrics (citation analysis) that allowed this conclusion are corroborated
                    by qualitative data: feedback sent to BHO from scholars who are irritated by the
                    site’s practice of not displaying inline page numbers. These scholars complain
                    that it makes the process of converting what they are reading on BHO to a print
                    citation more difficult.</p>
                <p>As set out in Webster and Blaney (2011), a search for citations of British
                    History Online in journals (carried out in 2010) found 14 results using the
                    Scopus service and 17 results using Google Scholar. By contrast, blog posts for
                    just the period June to November 2010 showed that British History Online was
                    referred to 84 times.</p>
                <p>Qualitative data suggested the reason for under-citation: analysis of site
                    feedback over the period 2003-2010 found a number of complaints about the
                    non-display of the print page numbers from the digitized books. For example,
                    this feedback message from 2007 is representative: <quote rend="block" source="#private">With
                        great pleasure, I have been going through your most excellent online version
                        of the ‘Thurloe State Papers’ for a scholarly paper which I am writing.
                        After consulting a particular transcribed document, I would then click on to
                        its approximate ‘Page’ number in the heading above, so as to search and find
                        the exact citation for my Endnotes. However, I now see that your current
                        online version does not display any original page images, thus preventing me
                        from determining a precise citation. How can I access the images, so as to
                        find the correct page-number for any given document?</quote></p>
                <p>EEBO-TCP’s application of the TIDSR analysis was carried out in 2012-13, as part
                    of the Jisc-funded project <title rend="italic">SECT: Sustaining the EEBO-TCP
                        Corpus in Transition</title>
                    <ptr target="#sect2013"/>, a study of the impact and sustainability of the
                    EEBO-TCP corpus. The TIDSR analysis was used to inform a set of recommendations
                    and practical implementations for the future curation and development of the
                        corpus<note> A full discussion of the TIDSR analysis of EEBO-TCP can be
                        found in <ptr target="#siefring2013"/>.</note>.</p>
                <p>Bibliometric analysis suggested that EEBO-TCP is having a steadily increasing
                    impact on scholarship in relevant fields. The analysis surveyed EEBO and
                    EEBO-TCP-related publications in databases such as JSTOR and Scopus,
                    demonstrating a steady growth in such publications over the decade 2002 to 2012.
                    The Scopus data allows us to see the country of the authors of the publications,
                    indicating that authors from USA and the UK are most likely to mention their use
                    of EEBO, followed by two other English-speaking countries, Canada and Australia.
                    If we look at the journals that these articles were published in, we find a
                    range of journals chiefly in the fields of English Literature, Language and
                    History of the medieval and early modern periods. The bibliographic data,
                    therefore, supports the assertion that EEBO has had an increasing positive
                    impact on scholarship, particularly in English-speaking countries <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="29–31"/>. </p>
                <p>However, user feedback (particularly via a user survey discussed in detail
                    below), as with BHO, indicated that many scholars, particularly in the
                    humanities, fail to cite or otherwise acknowledge their use of digital
                    resources. The quantitative data accumulated during bibliometric analysis can
                    therefore only be partial; if users are not citing their use of EEBO and
                    EEBO-TCP then any numbers-based demonstration of their impact could be
                    significantly lower than the true impact on scholarship. This disparity raises
                    the issue of citation practice – what are users citing if they are not pointing
                    to their use of digital collections? The image sets in EEBO and the full texts
                    based on them in EEBO-TCP are based on actual printed books from libraries
                    around the world: do users cite these original print copies even though they
                    have never actually seen them? </p>
                <p>This raises questions for all creators of digital resources: Why do users avoid
                    citing the digital copies? What implications does this have for creators of
                    digital resources, particularly when they need to demonstrate impact? And what
                    measures can content creators introduce to combat the problem?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Survey of citation practice</head>
                <p>As part of the TIDSR analysis, the SECT project conducted an online survey of
                    EEBO-TCP users. The survey was run for around four months from the summer into
                    the autumn of 2012. The survey was advertised on the project website and via
                    Twitter, and was highlighted at the EEBO-TCP Oxford conference in 2012. Details
                    were also sent to faculty administrators at units specialising in the early
                    modern period at institutions across the UK, for circulation to their students
                    and staff. 220 people in total started the EEBO-TCP survey, 208 completed at
                    least part of the survey, and 185 completed it in full. The survey asked
                    participants for lots of information about their use of EEBO and EEBO-TCP, and
                    some of the questions asked pertained to citation practice <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="7–26"/>. </p>
                <p>The survey sought to establish the impact of EEBO-TCP in both teaching and
                    research, and revealed interesting attitudes to citation in both areas. First we
                    asked users who identified themselves as spending at least one-fifth of their
                    time teaching <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="7"/>:</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>How often do you use online resources in your teaching? N=97</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Most respondents use online resources in their teaching either daily (20%) or
                    several times a week (40%). Teaching academics not only use online resources for
                    teaching themselves but actively encourage their students to use them for their
                    own work. As we would expect from a survey that set out to reach EEBO-TCP users,
                    a high number of respondents encourage their students to use EEBO in particular
                        <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="8"/>:</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Do you encourage your students to use online materials? N=97</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Almost all of these teachers encourage students to access online materials (97%),
                    and none of the remaining 3% of respondents actively discourage their use. The
                    survey also revealed that use of online resources in research is similarly
                    ubiquitous <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="8"/>:</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>How often do you use online resources in your research? N=186</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>It is clear that online resources are now heavily used by most teaching academics
                    and researchers. EEBO-TCP in particular is very widely used in early modern
                    studies. But is this enormous weight of use reflected in citation practice? In
                    order to explore this question further, researchers were asked how they
                    themselves cite materials from EEBO-TCP. Those who teach were asked how they
                    would instruct their students to acknowledge resources that they have consulted
                    online <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="17"/>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>How do (or would) you cite materials from EEBO-TCP? Researchers, n=172;
                        Teaching students, n=97</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The use of EEBO is now commonplace in research and teaching and yet 34% of
                    respondents fail to acknowledge that they have used an EEBO text and instead
                    cite the print version only. A quarter of respondents actively teach their
                    students to cite only print. These students are being taught to ignore or
                    disguise their use of digital resources. The responses to this question suggest
                    an additional problem: many (and in the case of the EEBO-TCP-aware audience for
                    the survey, most) researchers want to acknowledge their use of online material
                    but, as there is no single established way of doing so, there is considerable
                    variation in practice. Some cite both print and online sources, some online
                    only, some simply place <soCalled>[Online]</soCalled> after their citation.
                    Further illustrative examples can be found in the free-text responses of those
                    who answered <soCalled>other</soCalled> to the question above. </p>
                <p>Examples of “other” answers to the question of how to teach students to cite:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><said>Cite original print version, using originating library's citation
                            system (e.g., Huntington Library) and then indicate that they read the
                            copy on EEBO.</said></item>
                    <item><said>Like in the EEBO guidelines - cite the print version as seen in
                            EEBO, including ref to EEBO as well as the library the digital version
                            is scanned from.</said></item>
                    <item><said>Cite the original and the source they've used (e.g. EEBO,
                            Online)</said></item>
                    <item><said>Cite the original where there is one or the online one where there
                            is not</said></item>
                    <item><said>It really depends on the specific situation</said></item>
                    <item><said>Good question!</said></item>
                </list>
                <p>Examples of <soCalled>other</soCalled> answers to the question of how researchers
                    do or would cite EEBO-TCP:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><said>(In the case of my recent book, I had in fact seen physical copies
                            of all the EEBO resources I used.)</said></item>
                    <item><said>Cite the resource, cite the online source name but not
                        URL</said></item>
                    <item><said>Cross-check against image and then cite print version
                        only</said></item>
                    <item><said>Cite fully both electronic and print versions</said></item>
                    <item><said>Due to recent discussions with colleagues, I am in transition as to
                            how I would cite documents obtained from EEBO.</said></item>
                    <item><said>Don't know</said></item>
                </list>
                <p>These responses suggest the uncertainty that many feel when confronted with the
                    issue of how to cite their online sources. But the deeper problem remains that
                    many apparently don’t want to reveal that they used online sources at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The culture of non-citation</head>
                <p>The EEBO-TCP user survey suggested that around a third of researchers fail to
                    indicate their use of digital resources at all. Is this indicative of wider
                    practice? What are the reasons for users failing to cite digital material? Why
                    are (some) authors reluctant to cite digital if they can change to a print
                    citation?</p>
                <p>In order to try to find out more about the culture of citation, in April and May
                    2013 the authors sent via email a short survey to 60 UK-based print journals
                    covering the fields of literature and history. Representatives from each journal
                    were asked to send their responses also via email. An attempt was made to
                    balance the selection by surveying journals covering different time periods,
                    geographical focus, and thematic approach. In order to maximise the likelihood
                    of reply, the survey asked three simple questions:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>If you receive mss with digital citations do you change them to print if
                        possible or leave them as digital?</item>
                    <item>If you receive mss with print citations do you change them to digital if
                        possible or leave them as print?</item>
                    <item>Do you have a policy on digital versus print citation in your authors'
                        guidelines?</item>
                </list>
                <p>37 replies (a response rate of 62%) were received. 97% said they would not change
                    a print citation to digital, and 78% would not change a digital citation to
                    print. Nine asked for clarification on what was meant by <soCalled>digital
                        citation.</soCalled> Some responses treated the question as only pertaining
                    to the DOI of a journal article, not appearing to have in mind citations to
                    online text resources.</p>
                <p>More interesting than the bald figures are the comments included by some editors
                    with their replies. For a number of journals digital citation by authors was
                    mentioned as a rare or non-existent occurrence, for example, <said>[our journal]
                        doesn't receive submissions with digital citations, so these questions are
                        not relevant to us.</said></p>
                <p>This raises the question of cause and effect. Do authors eschew digital citation
                    because they think it would be frowned upon? If a journal never prints digital
                    citations then potential authors reading it may think this is a deliberate
                    policy (although the editor mentioned above did not say that they would not
                    include digital citations, only that they do not receive them).</p>
                <p>So, it may be that journal editors receive few digital citations and researchers
                    rarely see such citations in articles they are using for their research. What
                    assumptions are fuelling this cycle? Why do many shy away from citing digital,
                    whether they be authors or editors?<note> The views on digital citation
                        expressed in this and subsequent paragraphs reflect the thoughts and
                        opinions of scholars, editors, publishers and digital humanities specialists
                        expressed at a number of forums, chiefly in relation to Blaney’s paper on
                        citing digital at the Sheffield Digital Humanities Congress in September
                        2012 <ptr target="#blaney2012"/>, a digital citation focus group held by
                        Siefring in Oxford in November 2012, and Blaney &amp; Siefring’s joint
                        presentation on assessing the impact of digital resources at the Digital
                        Humanities@ Oxford Summer School in July 2013 <ptr target="#blaney2013"/>.</note></p>
                <p>Practically, including URLs is seen to be a problem. Many fear that a particular
                    URL will no longer be active in five or ten years’ time (see, for example, <ptr target="#europeanscience2011"/>). While it is true that some URLs might not
                    remain the same, this problem is increasingly being addressed by libraries and
                    archives. </p>
                <p>Legislation change in 2013 mandated the UK’s copyright libraries to capture the
                    UK’s public web domain as part of their remit <ptr target="#ukwebarchive2016"/>.
                    Additionally The National Archives have addressed this problem in their UK
                    Government Web Archive <ptr target="#ukgwa2016"/> (prompted by complaints that
                    Hansard references were suffering from link rot) by providing a bridging page
                    that takes users from the defunct URL to the archived web page. </p>
                <p>The Internet Archive has released a Firefox extension, <soCalled>No More
                        404s</soCalled>. If the extension is enabled the browser hitting a broken
                    link will offer to take the user to an archived version of that page in the
                    Wayback Machine <ptr target="#firefox2016"/>. This cannot be comprehensive
                    (because the Internet Archive is not comprehensive) but it offers a broad
                    solution to link rot that only this particular archive is equipped to
                    provide.</p>
                <p>Harvard Law School Library leads a group of libraries and others in maintaining
                    Perma.cc, a free service which allows anyone with an account to create a link to
                    an archival version of a web page <ptr target="#permacc2016"/>. In principle
                    this makes it possible for scholars to create digital citations which will never
                    break.</p>
                <p>A more pertinent barrier to digital citation might be URLs that are too long and
                    cumbersome. Journal editors and print publishers dislike them because they look
                    ugly and are hard to typeset or format. Academics and students too dislike their
                    appearance, and the fact that, together with a full citation, they can affect
                    the word or page count of a piece of work. They are unattractive for readers
                    more generally. They have often been generated for technical reasons by the
                    content creators with little thought for the needs of eventual users. </p>
                <p>Philosophically, some researchers may feel that there is little difference
                    between the database where one accesses a text and the library where one reads a
                    book. Such researchers wouldn’t cite the library, so why cite a database? Many
                    scholars, especially early modernists, do of course cite the source library.
                    Those who give this as a reason for failure to cite have perhaps never
                    considered the question of whether it is honest to hide their use of digital
                    material, or thought about how such material is funded. We would further argue
                    that there is a clear difference in the reading experience between manuscript,
                    print and digital, and to elide this in citation does an injustice to each <ptr target="#grafton2009" loc="310f"/>
                    <ptr target="#edwards2013"/>.</p>
                <p>This <soCalled>hiding</soCalled> of the use of digital resources gets to the
                    heart of the problem of non-citation: many believe digital resources are, or are
                    perceived to be, less reliable or not as good as <soCalled>real</soCalled> (i.e.
                    conventional print) resources. Some seem to believe that they need to hide their
                    use of digital surrogates in order to appear to be a better scholar (see <ptr target="#sukovic2009"/> for some instructive examples from interviews with
                    researchers).</p>
                <p>It may be that leading scholars, secure in their jobs and reputations, would be
                    less nervous about citing digital resources, if they think it appropriate. There
                    is some anecdotal evidence that this is the case. Historians Paul Kennedy
                    (internationally famous for <title rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of the Great
                        Powers</title>) and Norman Davies (internationally famous for <title rend="italic">The Isles</title>) have both approvingly cited Wikipedia,
                    sometimes in explicit preference to print sources, in more recent books <ptr target="#kennedy2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#davies2012" loc="143–149"/>. Michael Screech’s <title rend="italic">Laughter at the Foot of the Cross</title>, written as an
                    emeritus professor, mentions his being unable to find a reference despite
                    reading the complete works of St Jerome, but that a <soCalled>young
                        friend</soCalled> found the passage easily by using a database <ptr target="#screech1997" loc="70"/>. But these are senior academics with
                    nothing left to prove.</p>
                <p>In a trenchant article, the historian Tim Hitchcock points to a deeper scholarly
                    problem that lack of transparency over digital sources is obscuring. Researchers
                    are trained in traditional source materials: libraries, archives, conventional
                    reference works. They are, usually, inexpert in using digital resources: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hitchcock2013">We have not established the necessary new systems of
                            reference and validation that would make our use of these resources
                            transparent and repeatable.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hitchcock2013" loc="18"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>Hitchcock is making a broader point than this article seeks to address: digital
                    resources are problematic, often deeply so, and in claiming to use print where
                    they have used digital, researchers are seriously misrepresenting their
                    methodology. In order that scholarly work receive due scrutiny, it is essential
                    that scholars be clear, open and honest about their use of digital
                    resources.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Solutions? Changing perceptions and practice</head>
                <p>What, then, can be done to improve the reputation of digital resources and to
                    encourage users to acknowledge their use? Such change must start with the actual
                    content creators themselves.</p>
                <p>Fundamentally, content creators need to make it easy for their users to be open
                    and to properly acknowledge their use of a particular resource. If it is easy to
                    cite a digital resource, more users will do so. Digital resources should make
                    URLs as short as possible and, if possible, human-decodable, and should include
                    a clear link to an automatically-generated citation from the main page of a
                    text, image, or entry. In this way, content creators can make it as easy as
                    possible for their users to cite (or as difficult as possible for them not to),
                    with the result that citation rates should improve. A number of high profile
                    sites, such as the OED, Oxford DNB, Wikipedia, and indeed British History
                    Online, do allow users to automatically generate citations in multiple formats,
                    although even these excellent resources use URLs that are not obviously
                    decodable for readers.<note> The URL included in the Oxford DNB’s automatically
                        generated citation for the writer Thomas Churchyard (1523?-1694) is <ref target="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/5407">http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/5407</ref>, for example, while
                        Wikipedia’s entry for the same writer has the URL <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Thomas_Churchyard&amp;oldid=576213384">http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Thomas_Churchyard&amp;oldid=576213384</ref>
                        [both accessed November 2015].</note>
                </p>
                <p>Some scholars are concerned about how to cite something that may change or be
                    updated. Digital editors must, therefore, make it clear how to date content
                    accessed via their resource. Release information and/or editorial updates should
                    be made as obvious as possible. By dating digital items in this way, online
                    resource managers can help users feel comfortable about how to clearly refer to
                    the evidence that they are citing and when they are citing it. Sites should
                    encourage or guide users always to give a date of access whenever they cite a
                    digital resource, and should include such a date in automatically generated
                    citations.</p>
                <p>Indeed, while this article was being researched and written, British History
                    Online was relaunched with a new citation generator and using a completely new
                    format for its URLs, to make them more immediately meaningful to the user.
                    (British History Online had for a number of years offered citation help,
                    allowing the automatic generation of a citation for any page of content: this
                    has not had a discernible effect on citation habits). As a secondary benefit, if
                    British History Online completely disappeared the new URLs would enable a
                    researcher to trace the URL to a portion of a print book. In practice it might
                    be easier to locate the URL in the UK Web Archive maintained by the British
                    Library on behalf of all copyright libraries in the UK, although this is not
                    currently publicly available; the Internet Archive’s crawls of the site are, it
                    seems, not comprehensive.</p>
                <p>What was previously a database-generated number has now been converted to a
                    human-readable series and book. Further specificity is provided by the page
                    range of the book; where this is not possible, for born-digital content and
                    dictionary-like material, a meaningful subsection name has been chosen. For
                    example the old URL for the Survey of London, Volume 46, pages 280 to 293
                    was:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=119422">
                            http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=119422</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>This has now become:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol46/pp280-293">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol46/pp280-293</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>An additional advantage here is that the user who only wants the volume level, or
                    the series level, can strip off parts of the URL intuitively: </p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol46">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol46</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>This process was carried out semi-automatically for about 100,000 URLs, using the
                    original database and simply concatenating database fields. Although the results
                    are surely a great improvement, the process was not onerous. There was
                    consultation in the team about the best forms of abbreviations to use for the
                    best trade-off between shortness of URL and clarity. The decisions here were,
                    first, to use standard abbreviations where they exist. For example, for the
                    Victoria County History (known to historians as the VCH) standard county
                    abbreviations were used:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/oxon/vol6/pp7-14">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/oxon/vol6/pp7-14</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>The process could only be semi-automatic because some fields of the database
                    inevitably contained characters which are not allowed in URLs (such as quotation
                    marks in the titles of Acts of Parliament), which had to be located with a
                    regular expression and treated on a case-by-case basis (a side-benefit was that
                    this process exposed some metadata errors which could be fixed). Further, the
                    URLs had to be tested for uniqueness. Some of the new URLs were not unique
                    because they pointed to the single page of the same book. This was most
                    frequently the case with the folio volumes of the journals of the House of Lords
                    and House of Commons, where several days’ sittings might occur on the same page,
                    but had been separated for digitisation.</p>
                <p>For example, page 14 of the print version of the <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        the House of Lords</title>, volume 1, contains very short summaries of
                    sittings on various days in January 1550. Each sitting is a different file on
                    BHO, with a different URL. These have been given a suffixed letter to
                    disambiguate what would otherwise be the same URL:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/commons-jrnl/vol1/p14a">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/commons-jrnl/vol1/p14a</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/commons-jrnl/vol1/p14b">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/commons-jrnl/vol1/p14b</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>As this example shows, although page ranges are easily added automatically to
                    URLs, they are not necessarily best practice. Better still would be a meaningful
                    string chosen by an editor: in the Lords and Commons journals this would be the
                    date of sitting; in the VCH example above, the parish or other unit under
                    discussion. This could not be done retrospectively in this case, but can be done
                    conveniently as content is created. Future material digitised on the site will
                    use an editorial decision to create each URL. For example, since relaunch the
                    site has published Proceedings in Parliament 1624, each with a bespoke URL
                    encoding the date of sitting:</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item><ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/no-series/proceedings-1624-parl/mar-03">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/no-series/proceedings-1624-parl/mar-03</ref></item>
                </list>
                <p>The new version of the site went live in December 2014 and so it is still too
                    early to say if this change of URL convention will make a difference to the
                    under-citation of BHO discussed above. But one of the impediments given to
                    digital citation has, for this resource, been definitively removed. Indeed a
                    further refinement was added in October 2015, in response to the objection that
                    a page range was too imprecise for an academic reference. When the user mouses
                    over a paragraph of text, a pilcrow appears in the left-hand margin (very
                    faintly, so as not to be distracting); clicking on the pilcrow inserts the
                    relevant paragraph number into the URL bar, allowing a more precise reference
                    than a traditional print one.</p>
                <p>These practical measures could help users feel more comfortable with the
                    practicalities of digital citation. However, the more philosophical discomfort
                    of according digital materials the same weight as print must also be addressed.
                    Those working in the field of digital content creation are doubtless aware that
                    some digital resources seem to be held in particularly high esteem. Despite the
                    nuances of editorial practice discussed at the beginning of this article, the
                    OED or the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, for example, are understood
                    to be built on sound scholarship and their medium is considered unimportant.
                    With such examples in mind, other digital content creators could usefully
                    consider how best to promote the scholarly rigour and importance of their own
                    resource as a way of gradually eroding residual beliefs in the lack of
                    respectability of the digital. As a first step, web resources should provide
                    easily accessible editorial documentation at the point of accessing texts and
                    images (rather than solely on project-descriptive websites), enabling users to
                    fully understand the nature of the material they are accessing and the
                    assumptions that they can make about it. By making clear the nature of their
                    materials, content creators encourage researchers to use them in appropriate
                    ways and thereby enhance their own scholarly reputations.</p>
                <p>All of these mechanisms may help change individuals’ scholarly citation
                    practices. In turn, these scholars, should they become teaching academics, will
                    pass on their habits and expectations to their students. The EEBO-TCP user
                    survey asked participants how they prefer to learn about digital resources <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="12"/>:</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>How do you prefer to learn how to use digital resources? N=208</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Overwhelmingly participants prefer to explore digital resources themselves or
                    learn about them from peers. Uptake for library training sessions tends to be
                    low. Uptake for web tutorials seems rather low too – but this may be due to lack
                    of publicity or planning for dissemination. However, participants indicated in
                    the free text responses <soCalled>other</soCalled> ways of learning about
                    digital resources. Of the 17 free text responses to this question, 11 of them
                    describe recommendations by a tutor, professor or lecturer, at both
                    undergraduate and graduate level. This reveals a particularly important means of
                    learning about online collections: from those who teach <ptr target="#siefring2013" loc="12"/>.</p>
                <p>Teaching academics play a vital role in disseminating scholarly practices. Online
                    resources could usefully prepare citation guidelines and editorial documentation
                    that could be circulated to academic departments and subject administrators for
                    inclusion in local documentation given to students as they begin their studies.
                    Although beyond the scope of this article, a survey of what guidelines are
                    currently used would provide useful data on the current generation of students
                    and how they are expected to cite. Making such teaching and training materials
                    easily available on project websites would also be helpful. One-off project-led
                    training sessions could be worthwhile, providing that they are properly promoted
                    to encourage good attendance. By integrating awareness of the nature of digital
                    resources and the importance of citing them directly into teaching, digital
                    content creators can work together with academics to help shape the practices of
                    the next generation of scholars.</p>
                <p>An increasing problem for contributors and editors who prefer print citation for
                    journal articles will be that journal publishers themselves are steadily moving
                    towards online-only publication for their journals (for obvious economic
                    reasons). Alice Meadows, of Wiley Publishing, argues in a blog post that one
                    sticking point — the provision of print journals to members as a key benefit of
                    the membership of a learned society — is beginning to become less important as
                    an issue <ptr target="#meadows2012"/>. Another driver will be the moves towards
                    open access in journal publishing: open access presupposes a digital format.
                    Likewise the changes to the UK Research Excellence Framework (in operation after
                    1 April 2016) will require scholars to deposit all scholarly outputs in an
                    institutional repository (by their nature, primarily digital) <ptr target="#hefce2015"/>.</p>
                <p>As mentioned above, most survey respondents conceived our questions about digital
                    citation generally as being about DOIs specifically. As also mentioned earlier,
                    this may be a form of <term>deformation professionelle</term>: they were
                    thinking as journal editors, so they thought only of journal citation. But it
                    seems plausible too that the ubiquity of DOIs has acted as a forcing function:
                    editors have had to engage with them and make policy decisions about them. There
                    has been no such forcing function for other digital sources, as is evidenced by
                    survey responses such as: <said>I would change them [digital citations] to
                        print, but have actually not had the need to, since authors seem to choose
                        print anyway.</said></p>
                <p>Online-only journals can, obviously, only be cited digitally. It will become more
                    and more confusing if – as scholars increasingly use three-fold citation types:
                    items which exist only in print, digital versions or surrogates of originally
                    print items, and items which are born-digital – researchers cite some online
                    items and not others. As citing online-only material becomes commonplace, it
                    should become equally commonplace to cite all material accessed online,
                    regardless of whether a print version exists or not.</p>
                <p>While active solutions can be undertaken by individual projects and content
                    creators, a gradual shift in culture and practice may already be being led by
                    respected institutions. But as Patrick Dunleavy argues in a thought-provoking
                    blog post, change cannot be effected unilaterally but will be <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dunleavy2014">a long process of driving out legacy citation
                            systems</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dunleavy2014"/>
                    </cit>. Contra Dunleavy, however, we would argue that the principle should be:
                        <emph>cite what you used.</emph> This does not preclude giving an additional
                    digital or print citation to aid discovery.</p>
                <p>Recently the Royal Society announced their move to continual publication, whereby
                    they will give a DOI but no page numbers <ptr target="#royalsociety"/>. Such
                    moves will change the focus within digital scholarship. It might help, too, to
                    bear in mind historical precedents. For example, we might consider when it
                    became standard practice to include colophon data or title page printing
                    information during the move from manuscript to print culture. We should also
                    bear in mind that there is an element of serendipity in which citation methods
                    take off and which don’t. For example, in classical studies, Stephanus
                    pagination has become a standard way of referencing the work of Plato. The
                    system is based on a 1578 edition of Plato’s works by Henri Estienne <ptr target="#wikipedia2016"/>. Estienne is also responsible for the division of
                    Bible chapters into verses that have become so conventional today that many do
                    not realise that verses, and indeed chapters, of the Bible are bibliographic
                    conventions that have nothing to do with the earliest known manuscripts. It was
                    pure chance that these arbitrary systems, eschewing page numbers and even
                    editions, became the standard. It is easy to imagine other, equally arbitrary
                    but effective, citation norms arising for the citation of digital texts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Change of practice at individual scholarly level reflects and promotes change at
                    a wider cultural level. As more and more established academics are open about
                    their use of online resources, the belief that digital content is less scholarly
                    should lessen, and citation should improve. Open access and changes to the REF
                    in the UK will, as mentioned above, sharpen the imperative to cite digital
                    versions of content. Like the OED, many journals are abandoning print. Young
                    researchers, not just luminaries like Kennedy and Davies, should find it
                    increasingly easy to cite what they used in research without apology; their
                    critics will find their position increasingly untenable.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, it falls primarily to digital content creators to heighten
                    awareness of the issues involved. Simply raising the issue is often enough – in
                    conversation with them, the authors of this article have found that many
                    scholars have never thought carefully about their digital behaviour and simply
                    require some prompting to reconsider their citation habits. We must continue to
                    talk about it, formally and informally. Conference papers, blog posts, articles
                    and presentations which focus on the problem of digital citation will keep the
                    issue current and will encourage users to consider their own practices<note> An
                        excellent example is Victoria Van Hyning’s blog post written in response to
                        this article’s authors’ joint presentation at the Digital Humanities@Oxford
                        Summer School in July 2013 <ptr target="#vanhyning2013"/>
                        <ptr target="#blaney2013"/>.</note>. We must take the opportunity to look
                    beyond our own specialisms to interdisciplinary knowledge exchange. Text and
                    image-based resources, for example, should look for input from other areas of
                    study where there is philosophical overlap – such as citation for audiovisual
                    material <ptr target="#bufvc2013"/> or for music. Raising awareness of digital
                    citation should become part of the public engagement strategy for all digital
                    resources.</p>
                <p>Digital citation is important because it is a reflection of how digital resources
                    are valued. It is important because it helps build cases for further funding and
                    enhancement based on evidence of use and impact. It is important because it
                    allows readers of published research to trace and discover sources, both known
                    and new to them, as accurately as possible. It is also honest. </p>
                <p>We hope and expect that, in time, the currently too widespread practice of citing
                    a print work which has neither been seen nor used will come to seem an
                    unfortunate historical interlude, one in which the practice of scholarly
                    transparency was briefly and lamentably abandoned. Digital resources are here to
                    stay – it is time that they received the credit that is their due.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>We would like to thank Julianne Nyhan and Jane Winters for their feedback and
                    suggestions while we were writing this article.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bho2015" label="BHO 2015">British History Online 2015, University of
                    London and the History of Parliament Trust. Available from <ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/</ref> [14 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blaney2012" label="Blaney 2012">Blaney J. 2012 <title rend="quotes">The Problem of Citation in the Digital Humanities. </title> Available from
                        <ref target="http://www.hrionline.ac.uk/openbook/chapter/dhc2012-blaney">http://www.hrionline.ac.uk/openbook/chapter/dhc2012-blaney</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blaney2013" label="Blaney and Siefring 2013">Blaney J. and Siefring J.
                    2013 <title rend="quotes">EEBO-TCP Measuring Impact and Making Changes.</title>
                    Available from <ref target="http://podcasts.ox.ac.uk/04eebo-tcp-measuring-impact-and-making-changes">http://podcasts.ox.ac.uk/04eebo-tcp-measuring-impact-and-making-changes</ref>
                    [14 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bufvc2013" label="BUFVC 2013">British Universities Film &amp; Video
                    Council 2013 <title rend="quotes">Audiovisual Citation Guidelines.</title>
                    Available from <ref target="http://bufvc.ac.uk/projects-research/avcitation">http://bufvc.ac.uk/projects-research/avcitation</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="compagnon1979" label="Compagnon 1979">Compagnon, A. <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="fr">La seconde main - ou le travail de la
                            citation</foreign></title>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">Éditions du
                        Seuil</foreign>, Paris (1979).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dailytelegraph2014" label="Daily Telegraph 2014">Flanagan, P. <title rend="quotes">RIP for OED as world’s finest dictionary goes out of
                        print.</title> Available from <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/culturenews/10777079/RIP-for-OED-as-worlds-finest-dictionary-goes-out-of-print.html%20%5b13">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/culturenews/10777079/RIP-for-OED-as-worlds-finest-dictionary-goes-out-of-print.html</ref>
                    [13 September 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dalbello2006" label="Dalbello et al. 2006">Dalbello, M. Lopatovska I.,
                    Mahony P. &amp; Ron N. <title rend="quotes">Electronic texts and the citation
                        system of scholarly journals in the humanities: case studies of citation
                        practices in the fields of classical studies and English literature.</title>
                    Available from <ref target="http://arizona.openrepository.com/arizona/bitstream/10150/105648/1/Dalbello_posterrev.pdf">http://arizona.openrepository.com/arizona/bitstream/10150/105648/1/Dalbello_posterrev.pdf</ref>
                    [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davies2012" label="Davies 2012">Davies D. <title rend="italic">Vanished Kingdoms: The History of Half-Forgotten Europe</title>, Penguin,
                    London (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dunleavy2014" label="Dunleavy 2014">Dunleavy P. 2014 <title rend="quotes">Academic citation practices need to be modernized so that all
                        references are digital and lead to full texts.</title> Available from <ref target="http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2014/05/21/academic-citation-practices-need-to-be-modernized/">http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2014/05/21/academic-citation-practices-need-to-be-modernized/</ref>
                    [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eebotcp2015" label="EEBO-TCP 2015">Early English Books Online Text
                    Creation Partnership 2015, Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford. Available
                    from <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/eebotcp/">http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/eebotcp/</ref> [14 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edwards2013" label="Edwards 2013">Edwards A. S. G. 2013 <title rend="quotes">Back to the real?.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Times Literary Supplement</title>, 7 June 2013.
                    Available from <ref target="http://www.the-tls.co.uk/tls/public/article1269403.ece">http://www.the-tls.co.uk/tls/public/article1269403.ece</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="europeanscience2011" label="European Science Foundation 2011">European
                    Science Foundation 2011 <title rend="quotes">Science Policy Briefing 42:
                        Research Infrastructures in the Digital Humanities.</title> Available from
                        <ref target="http://www.esf.org/fileadmin/Public_documents/Publications/spb42_RI_DigitalHumanities.pdf">http://www.esf.org/fileadmin/Public_documents/Publications/spb42_RI_DigitalHumanities.pdf</ref>
                    [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="firefox2016" label="Firefox 2016"><title rend="quotes">No More
                        404s.</title> Available from <ref target="https://testpilot.firefox.com/experiments/no-more-404s/">https://testpilot.firefox.com/experiments/no-more-404s/</ref> [12 October
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grafton2009" label="Grafton 2009">Grafton A. 2009, <title rend="quotes">Codex in Crisis: the Book Dematerializes</title> in <title rend="italic">Worlds Made By Words: Scholarship and Community in the Modern
                        West</title>, Harvard University Press, Cambridge MA (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hajjem2005" label="Hajjem et al. 2005">Hajjem C., Harnad S. &amp;
                    Gingras Y. <title rend="quotes">Ten-Year Cross-Disciplinary Comparison of the
                        Growth of Open Access and How it Increases Research Citation Impact,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin</title> 28.4 (2005), 39-47.
                    Available from <ref target="http://arxiv.org/ftp/cs/papers/0606/0606079.pdf">http://arxiv.org/ftp/cs/papers/0606/0606079.pdf</ref> [11 March
                    2015].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hefce2015" label="HEFCE 2015">Higher Education Funding Council for
                    England 2014 <title rend="quotes">Policy for open access in the post-2014
                        Research Excellence Framework.</title> Available from <ref target="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/pubs/year/2014/201407/">http://www.hefce.ac.uk/pubs/year/2014/201407/</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hitchcock2013" label="Hitchcock 2013">Hitchcock T. <title rend="quotes">Confronting the Digital: or How Academic History Writing Lost
                        the Plot,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural and Social History</title>, 10.1 (2013),
                    9-23.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kennedy2013" label="Kennedy 2013">Kennedy P. <title rend="italic">Engineers of Victory: The Problem Solvers Who Turned the Tide in the Second
                        World War</title>, Allen Lane, London (2013). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="larviere2009" label="Larivière and Gingras 2009">Larivière, V. and
                    Gingras Y. <title rend="quotes">The decline in the concentration of citations,
                        1900–2007</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and
                        Technology</title>, 60.4 (2009), 858-862. Available from <ref target="http://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/0809/0809.5250.pdf">http://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/0809/0809.5250.pdf</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lozano" label="Lozano et al. n.d.">Lozano, G. A., Larivière, V. &amp;
                    Gingras Y. <title rend="quotes">The weakening relationship between the Impact
                        Factor and papers’ citations in the digital age.</title> Available from <ref target="http://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/1205/1205.4328.pdf">http://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/1205/1205.4328.pdf</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meadows2012" label="Meadows 2012">Meadows A. 2012 <title rend="quotes">Moving Scholarly Society Members Online-Only – Are We Reaching the Tipping
                        Point?.</title> Available from <ref target="http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2012/12/13/moving-scholarly-society-members-online-only-are-we-reaching-the-tipping-point/">http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2012/12/13/moving-scholarly-society-members-online-only-are-we-reaching-the-tipping-point/</ref>
                    [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oed1933" label="OED 1933">hubris, n. Available from <ref target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/89081">http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/89081</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oed2004" label="OED 2004">omphalos, n. Available from <ref target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/131290">http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/131290</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="permacc2016" label="Perma.cc 2016"><title rend="quotes">About
                        Perma.cc.</title> Available from <ref target="https://perma.cc/about%20%5b12">https://perma.cc/about</ref> [12
                    October 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="royalsociety" label="Royal Society n.d."><title rend="italic">Continuous publication</title>. Available from <ref target="https://royalsociety.org/journals/authors/continuous-publication/">https://royalsociety.org/journals/authors/continuous-publication/</ref> [11
                    March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="screech1997" label="Screech 1997">Screech M. <title rend="italic">Laughter at the Foot of the Cross</title>, Allen Lane, London
                    (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sect2013" label="SECT 2013">SECT: Sustaining the EEBO-TCP Corpus in
                    Transition, 2013. Available from <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/eebotcp/SECT/">http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/eebotcp/SECT/</ref> [14 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siefring2013" label="Siefring and Meyer 2013">Siefring J. and Meyer E.
                        <title rend="italic">Sustaining the EEBO-TCP Corpus in Transition: Report on
                        the TIDSR Benchmarking Study</title> (2013). JISC, London (2013). Available
                    from SSRN: <ref target="http://ssrn.com/abstract=2236202">http://ssrn.com/abstract=2236202</ref> or <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2236202">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2236202</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sukovic2009" label="Sukovic 2009">Sukovic, S. <title rend="quotes">References to e-texts in academic publications,</title>
                    <title rend="quotes">Journal of Documentation</title>, 65.6 (2009),
                    998-1015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tidsr" label="TIDSR n.d."><title rend="quotes">TIDSR: Toolkit for the
                        Impact of Digitised Scholarly Resources.</title> Available from <ref target="http://microsites.oii.ox.ac.uk/tidsr/">http://microsites.oii.ox.ac.uk/tidsr/</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ukgwa2016" label="UKGWA 2016">UK Government Web Archive. Available
                    from <ref target="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/webarchive/">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/webarchive/</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ukwebarchive2016" label="UK Web archive 2016">UK Web Archive 2016.
                    Available from <ref target="http://www.webarchive.org.uk/ukwa/">http://www.webarchive.org.uk/ukwa/</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanhyning2013" label="Van Hyning 2013">Van Hyning, V. 2013 <title rend="quotes">Citing and Contributing to Digital Resources.</title>
                    Available from <ref target="http://snakeweight.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/citing-and-contributing-to-digital-resources/">http://snakeweight.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/citing-and-contributing-to-digital-resources/</ref>
                    [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webster2011" label="Webster and Blaney 2011">Webster, P. and Blaney,
                    J. 2011, <title rend="quotes">The Impact and Embedding of an Established
                        Resource: British History Online as a Case Study.</title> Available from
                        <ref target="http://sas-space.sas.ac.uk/2819/">http://sas-space.sas.ac.uk/2819/</ref> [11 March 2015].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wikipedia2015" label="Wikipedia 2015"><title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>, <title rend="quotes">Stephanus Pagination.</title>
                    Available from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephanus_pagination">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephanus_pagination</ref> [11 March
                    2016].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wikipedia2016" label="Wikipedia 2016"><title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>, <title rend="quotes">Hubris.</title> Available from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubris">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubris</ref> [11 March 2016].</bibl>
                <bibl/>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>