<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The Data Sprint Approach: Exploring the field of Digital
                    Humanities through Amazon’s Application Programming Interface</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David M. <dhq:family>Berry</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Sussex</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>d.m.berry@sussex.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David M. Berry is Reader in the School of Media, Film and Music at the
                            University of Sussex and co-Director of the Sussex Humanities Lab. His
                            recent work includes Critical Theory and the Digital, the edited
                            collection Understanding Digital Humanities and the co-edited collection
                            Postdigital Aesthetics: Art, Computation and Design. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Erik <dhq:family>Borra</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Amsterdam</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>erik@erikborra.net</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Erik Borra (♂) is researcher at and technical director of the Digital
                            Methods Initiative. He is also a lecturer in the New Media and Digital
                            Culture M.A. program at the University of Amsterdam. His PhD research
                            focuses on the Web as a source of data for social and cultural research,
                            specifically focusing on search engine queries, Wikipedia edit histories
                            and social media data.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Anne <dhq:family>Helmond</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Amsterdam</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>a.helmond@uva.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Anne Helmond is assistant professor in New Media and Digital Culture at
                            the University of Amsterdam. Her research interests include software
                            studies, platform studies, infrastructure studies, digital methods, and
                            web history. In her dissertation she examined the platformization of the
                            web which entails the extension of social media platforms into the rest
                            of the web and their drive to make external web data <soCalled>platform
                                ready.</soCalled></p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jean-Christophe
                        <dhq:family>Plantin</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>London School of Economics and Political
                        Science</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>j.plantin1@lse.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jean-Christophe Plantin is Assistant Professor at the London School of
                            Economics and Political Science, department of Media and Communications.
                            His research investigates the implications of big data and visualization
                            technologies for civic participation and social science research. He is
                            the author of <title rend="italic">Participatory Mapping: New Data, New
                                Cartography</title> (Wiley, 2014).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jill <dhq:family>Walker Rettberg</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Bergen</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>Jill.Walker.Rettberg@lle.uib.no</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jill Walker Rettberg is the author of <title rend="italic">Seeing
                                Ourselves Through Technology: How We Use Selfies, Blogs and Wearable
                                Devices to See and Shape Ourselves</title> (Palgrave 2014) and
                                <title rend="italic">Blogging</title> (Polity 2008, 2014), and the
                            co-editor of a scholarly anthology on World of Warcraft (MIT Press
                            2008). She has been a research blogger at <ref
                                target="http://www.jilltxt.net">jilltxt.net</ref> since 2000.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000222</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2015-12-23">23 December 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Amazon</item>
                        <item>API</item>
                        <item>Data Sprint</item>
                        <item>Digital Humanities</item>
                        <item>Digital Culture</item>
                        <item>Electronic Literature</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2015-10-15">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This paper documents the results of an intensive <soCalled>data sprint</soCalled>
                    method for undertaking data and algorithmic work using application programming
                    interfaces (APIs), which took place during the Digital Method Initiative 2013
                    Winter School at the University of Amsterdam. During this data sprint, we
                    developed a method to map the fields of Digital Humanities and Electronic
                    Literature based on title recommendations from the largest online bookseller,
                    Amazon, by retrieving similar purchased items from the Amazon API. A first step
                    shows the overall Amazon recommendation network for Digital Humanities and
                    allows us to detect clusters, aligned fields and bridging books. In a second
                    step we looked into four country-specific Amazon stores (Amazon.com,
                    Amazon.co.uk, Amazon.fr and Amazon.de) to investigate the specificities of the
                    Digital Humanities in these four countries. The third step is a network of all
                    books suggested for the Electronic Literature field in the four Amazon stores we
                    searched, which offers a comparison to the field of Digital Humanities.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Mapping the fields of Digital Humanities and Electronic Literature by retrieving
                    similar items from the Amazon API.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                <p>In this article we seek to tentatively explore the field of digital humanities
                    (DH) through the production of particular outputs of knowledge rather than the
                    tools that are used. In this we are, perhaps, acting counter to the often
                    remarked processual aspect of DH, that is, that digital humanities focuses not
                    just on the outputs but also on the processes involved in producing those
                    outputs, by, for example, creating data sets, digital tools, archives, etc. <ptr
                        target="#berry2012"/>. However, as part of a rapid <soCalled>Data
                        Sprint</soCalled>, research outputs, in this case books and monographs,
                    offer a means of producing quick datasets amenable to analysis under the tight
                    restrictions on time that the Data Sprint form imposed upon us. We undertook
                    this analysis to examine the epistemic connections represented through a network
                    analysis of key texts in the field and we also aimed to explore the extent to
                    which the digital humanities differ in comparable countries. By including an
                    analysis of the field of electronic literature we sought to compare DH writ
                    large to a possibly more specific discourse field. Electronic literature
                    includes genres such as kinetic poetry, hypertext fiction, social media fiction
                    and generative narratives, where the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#rettbergs2014">the computer (or the network
                            context) is in some way <emph>essential</emph> to the performance or
                            carrying out of the literary activity in question</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rettbergs2014"/>
                    </cit>, and is a strong subfield or related field to the digital humanities,
                    depending on one's perspective.</p>
                <p>This article brings two contributions to the field of DH. Firstly, we show the
                    relevance of the <q>data sprint</q> method for DH inquiry, during which data are
                    collected and analyzed over a short period of time, offering a mezzo-level of
                    analysis between small and large datasets (or <soCalled>big data</soCalled>).
                    Secondly, we show how web-based digital platforms can be repurposed to offer
                    insightful data sources to investigate the field of digital humanities itself,
                    therefore contributing to reflexivity in the community. Concerning the first
                    point: the data sprint was part of a Winter School held at the University of
                    Amsterdam in 2013<note>This paper is the result of a data sprint at the Digital
                        Methods Winter School, <title rend="quotes">Data Sprint: The New Logistics
                            of Short-form Method</title>, 22-24 January 2013, Amsterdam, the
                        Netherlands. See <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/Dmi/WinterSchool2013"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/Dmi/WinterSchool2013</ref> for more
                        info. Thanks to Richard Rogers and other participants at the Winter School
                        for helpful comments and suggestions.</note> and was designed to facilitate
                    short-form data analysis work in a rapid prototyping format, rather similar to
                    hacklabs and hackathons. The term data sprint itself is drawn from the notion of
                    a Book Sprint which is a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#berry2012">genre of the ‘flash’ book, written
                            under a short timeframe, to emerge as a contributor to debates, ideas
                            and practices in contemporary culture... interventions that go well
                            beyond a well-written blog-post or tweet, and give some substantive
                            weight to a discussion or issue...within a range of 20-40,000
                            words</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2012"/>
                    </cit>. This rapid and collaborative means of writing is very creative and
                    intensified, and tends towards the creation of texts that are appropriately
                    geared to a specific subject or topic <ptr target="#hyde2013"/>. Indeed,
                    participants in a Book Sprint, who are not always necessarily professional
                    writers, are usually experts in a field but from a range of professions,
                    backgrounds and interests. Book Sprints themselves are usually formed from 4-8
                    people actively involved in the writing process, and are facilitated by another
                    non-writing member. However in the data sprint, which created this paper, the
                    team was made up of five members with varying degrees of competence in data
                    analysis and programming. Nonetheless, the basic tenets of the Book Sprint were
                    observed, in as much as the data sprint was carried out over a period of three
                    days aiming towards final presentation of the results at a workshop organised at
                    the University of Amsterdam. This compression of time naturally results in rapid
                    prototyping and scoping aggressively in order to produce the work within the
                    timeframe available, nonetheless it creates an extremely creative space for the
                    use and reuse of data and algorithms in digital humanities-type work. </p>
                <p>Due to the <q>data sprint</q> format of this project, several members were
                    involved in multiple projects at the same time, or were not working
                    co-locatedly. As a consequence, we heavily relied on online collaborative
                    applications in order to work remotely together. A specific Skype channel was
                    used for multiple purposes: after the tasks were divided between the various
                    members, it served as a means to let the others know which step was done. It was
                    also used to ask questions on a specific task. Furthermore, it served to quickly
                    transfer lists of ASIN numbers from the seed books, or to transfer .zip files
                    containing Gephi files resulting from requests to the Amazon API. Collaborative
                    spreadsheets on Google Drive were a means to collaboratively write descriptive
                    tables of seed books, but also to share first results from the graph (e.g. in a
                    spreadsheets showing Eigenvector Centrality, indegree or outdegree - see below).
                    Finally, a Dropbox was used to share .gexf (Gephi) files resulting from the
                    crawling, and to share the graphs after working on the visualisation. Data
                    sprints are based on reproducibility: the work done needs to be documented and
                    shared online in order to foster similar work and further developments. In
                    parallel to the collaborative online applications used to work together, we set
                    up a website<note>
                        <ref target="https://sites.google.com/site/whatisdigitalhumanities/results"
                            >https://sites.google.com/site/whatisdigitalhumanities/</ref></note>
                    from the beginning that served to document the methods, process, and results of
                    our work. Similarly, crawl results and graphs were instantly uploaded on a
                    specific Github page<note>
                        <ref
                            target="https://github.com/dmberry/Digital-Humanities-and-Electronic-Literature"
                            >https://github.com/dmberry/Digital-Humanities-and-Electronic-Literature</ref>
                    </note>, as was the code accompanying the project<note>
                        <ref target="https://github.com/digitalmethodsinitiative/arpg"
                            >https://github.com/digitalmethodsinitiative/arpg</ref>
                    </note>.</p>
                <p>Secondly, this article demonstrates how digital methods <ptr target="#rogers2013"
                    /> can be useful to reach a reflexive account of the field of DH. By doing so,
                    we rely on both traditional social network analysis and digital methods. One way
                    of mapping a field, and the approach we take here, is by locating the books that
                    are read by its scholars. Traditionally this has been done by citation analysis
                        <ptr target="#desollaprice1965"/> for example by using Web of Science or,
                    more recently, Google Scholar. There are also examples of network analysis of
                    citations, for instance as in Dan Wang’s analysis of key texts in sociology
                    where two texts being taught in the same week of a syllabus is interpreted as a
                    link between the texts <ptr target="#wang2012"/>. In this paper, we instead use
                    a similar approach to Krebs, who used Amazon recommendations to uncover <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#krebs1999">emergent communities of interest on
                            the WWW by examining purchasing patterns</quote>
                        <ptr target="#krebs1999"/>
                    </cit>. We used data from Amazon’s online bookstores in the US, UK, France and
                    Germany to analyse buying patterns for the digital humanities and electronic
                    literature, revealing a network of books connected by frequently being purchased
                    together. This research aims to apply a form of algorithmic <emph>distant
                        reading</emph>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2005"/> of the books, in as much as we rely on the readings
                    and purchasing patterns of others to inform the selections that are returned by
                    the API. We have undertaken this extraction of data by retrieving it from the
                    Amazon Product Advertising API.</p>
                <p>Kaplan’s typology of data sources in digital humanities scholarship <ptr
                        target="#kaplan2015"/> is useful to describe the data used in our work: it
                    falls in the category of <q>digital culture</q>, as opposed to works based on
                        <q>big cultural datasets</q> (such as the Google Ngram project mentioned
                    above) or offering <q>digital experiences</q> (such as 3D virtual worlds). To
                    this extent, we follow Borgman <ptr target="#borgman2015"/> who recently
                    highlighted that more data is not necessarily more insightful than smaller data,
                    as well as Schöch <ptr target="#schoch2013"/> who calls for a preference towards
                    smaller yet more structured <quote rend="inline" source="#schoch2013">smart
                        data</quote> instead of large and messy <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#schoch2013">big data.</quote> In order to fetch data, we use here a
                    digital methods approach by repurposing an online device, the Amazon
                    recommendation system, to see how we can make use of web-native objects such as
                    recommendations for social and cultural research <ptr target="#rogers2013"/><ptr
                        target="#marres2013"/>. In other words, we seek <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gerlitz2013">to deploy the logic of
                            recommendation cultures</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gerlitz2013"/>
                    </cit> as put forward by Amazon’s recommendations based on similar purchased
                    items as an alternative consumer-based approach based on buying patterns to map
                    a field. By moving beyond the traditional <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#gillespie2012">editorial logic</quote> which <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gillespie2012">depends on the subjective
                            choices of experts</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gillespie2012"/>
                    </cit> we explore the possibilities and boundaries presented by the rise of the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2006">algorithmic logic</quote> (idem)
                    to retrieve, organize and present relevant information. Our research explores
                    the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2006">algorithmic structure of today’s
                            informatic culture</quote>
                        <ptr target="#galloway2006" loc="17"/>
                    </cit> through the Amazon recommendation algorithm by combining both the
                    editorial logic and algorithmic logic to provide an alternative way to map a
                    field. </p>
                <p>In this paper we call the Amazon API for different countries to show the
                    relationships between different titles using the SimilarityLookup feature<note>
                        <ref
                            target="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/SimilarityLookup.html"
                            >http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/SimilarityLookup.html</ref>
                    </note>, an API operation that <q>returns up to ten products per page that are
                        similar to one or more items specified in the request</q> to map the fields
                    digital humanities and electronic literature. By focusing on country-specific
                    versions of Amazon we can visualise national networks of book purchases and
                    analyse differences and similarities for the fields per country or linguistic
                    area. The introduction of geo-location technology on the web <ptr
                        target="#goldsmith2006"/> has brought into being the notion of <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#goldsmith2006">national webs</quote> which are
                    demarcated by devices such as search engines that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#rogers2013">go local</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rogers2013"/>
                    </cit>, as for example Google’s country-specific websites like Google.ca,
                    Google.za, Google.jp or Google.com.mx. Amazon's recommendation engine also comes
                    with ten country-specific websites: United States (amazon.com), United Kingdom
                    (amazon.co.uk), Canada (amazon.ca), Austria (amazon.at),<note>Amazon Austria
                        (.at) redirects to Amazon Germany (.de)</note> Germany (amazon.de), Spain
                    (amazon.es), France (amazon.fr), Italy (.it), Japan (.jp) and China (amazon.cn)<note>
                        <ref target="http://www.amazon.com/gp/feature.html?ie=UTF8&amp;docId=487250"
                            >http://www.amazon.com/gp/feature.html?ie=UTF8&amp;docId=487250</ref>
                    </note> that we can use to compare the fields per country. This analysis across
                    national webs allows us to see whether recommendations for the field of digital
                    humanities would be different in different countries. </p>
                <p>This paper is presented as a partial and tentative means of mapping a field, but
                    also as a moment in the developing field of digital humanities <ptr
                        target="#jameson2006"/>. As such we are fully appreciative of its
                    limitations as a study: indeed this is a crucial part of the approach which
                    stresses the <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2010">hermeneutics of screwing
                        around,</quote> as Ramsay <ptr target="#ramsay2010"/> called it, as our
                    research is the result of a <soCalled>data sprint</soCalled>. Thus, we present
                    this work as suggestive of the formation of a discursive network crystallising
                    around the notion of <soCalled>digital humanities</soCalled> and the
                    possibilities of further research in this vein. To this extent, we follow the
                    critical tradition of DH towards <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2013">tools, data, and metadata</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu2013"/>
                    </cit> used and analyzed in this study. To put it in other words, our work <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2012">extend[s] reflection on core
                            instrumental technologies in cultural and historical directions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu2012" loc="501"/>
                    </cit>, by mixing new media studies resources with DH. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>METHOD</head>
                <p>In this paper we use a form of social-network analysis that visualises the
                    relationships between the different entities, in this case books, in our
                    networks. As Alan Liu explains,</p>
                <quote rend="block" source="#liu2013">the premise of social-network analysis is that
                    it is not individuals or groups but the pattern of relations between individuals
                    or groups that is socially significant. Such an approach commonly produces
                    analyses in the form of social-network graphs composed of nodes and connecting
                    edges (also called ties) accompanied by metrics of degree, distance, density,
                    betweenness, centrality, clustering, and so on. The goal is to describe a
                    topology of social relations that allows researchers to understand, for
                    instance, which nodes are pivotal to connections within communities <ptr
                        target="#liu2013"/>. </quote>
                <p>One of the interesting outcomes of the practices involved in undertaking this
                    form of digital method is the "hermeneutics of screwing around" <ptr
                        target="#ramsay2010"/>. Interpreting the data of a network visualisation is
                    an iterative process of adapting the viewing perspective, changing the data
                    filters, editing colours, layout, depth, degree, and relative <q>importance</q>
                    of particular nodes. In other words, adapting the way the data is presented to
                    view it from different perspectives is a method that lets us surface patterns
                    and interesting features of the graph.</p>
                <p>In our case study we used ten seed books<note>These ten seed books were selected
                        by two topic experts: David M. Berry selected ten key books in the field of
                        digital humanities and Jill Walker Rettberg selected ten key books in the
                        field of electronic literature. The concept of seed used here is drawn from
                        the computational use of pseudo-random numbers to begin a computational
                        process, it is a term also used in <title rend="quotes">Minecraft</title> to
                        indicate a starting number to generate a procedural world in the game. A
                        seed in the context of this paper is a set of values, in this case book
                        ASINs, which can be used to bootstrap the API call process. Using 10 seeds
                        rather than just one increased the space of results which could be produced
                        from the Amazon API and the rapidity of the data set collection, which, due
                        to the compressed time available in the data sprint, was extremely
                        useful.</note> for each of the fields of digital humanities and electronic
                    literature (see Table 1 and 2) as a starting point to request up to ten similar
                    books per book using the SimilarityLookup operation in the Amazon.co.uk Product
                    Advertising API. According to the API documentation, <quote rend="inline"
                        source="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/SimilarityLookup.html"
                        >Similarity is a measurement of similar items purchased, that is, customers
                        who bought X also bought Y and Z. It is not a measure, for example, of items
                        viewed, that is, customers who viewed X also viewed Y and Z.<note>
                            <ref
                                target="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/SimilarityLookup.html"
                                >http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/SimilarityLookup.html</ref>
                        </note></quote> Initially we repeated the request to reach a depth of three,
                    which includes the results, the subsequent results and subsequent result to
                    create a broad overview over the Digital Humanities (see Figure 1). However, for
                    subsequent analysis we decided to limit our request to the results and the
                    subsequent results (a depth of two) in order to limit the scope of our dataset
                    and complexity of analysis.</p>
                <p>In other words, we fetched a maximum of ten recommendations per book to a depth
                    of two degrees. This generated a maximum of one hundred book titles for each of
                    the subject areas of digital humanities and electronic literature<note>As some
                        books may have the same recommendations and some books have less than 10
                        recommendations, the actual number is much lower.</note>. This data set then
                    allowed us to do a first analysis with the Gephi software <ptr
                        target="#bastian2009"/>, which allows sophisticated data analysis and
                    visualisation, and based upon this we constructed the next data phase which we
                    could scope in relation to the first data set. </p>
                <p>The second data phase was organised around a comparative approach in relation to
                    data requests to the Amazon API for recommendations for the digital humanities
                    books in each of the following countries: <q>ca</q>, <q>cn</q>, <q>de</q>,
                        <q>es</q>, <q>fr</q>, <q>it</q>, <q>jp</q>, <q>co.uk</q>, <q>com</q>. We requested our data for all ten
                    countries via the Amazon API, but only retained the four (US, UK, FR, DE) that
                    returned results for our requests. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Seeds</head>
                    <p>These are the subject domain expert <soCalled>seeds</soCalled> that were used
                        to generate the initial data output. The word <soCalled>seed</soCalled> here
                        refers to a computational notion of a piece of data that is used to generate
                        other data, such as in the snowball technique described by Issuecrawler.net
                            <ptr target="#rogers2010"/>. A seed is an expert-determined
                            value<note>In determining the seeds we relied on the editorial logic of
                            subject experts David M. Berry for choosing the Digital Humanities seed
                            set and of Jill Walker Rettberg for the Electronic literature seed set
                            (see previous footnote).</note>, in this case the Amazon Standard
                        Identification Number (ASINs) for a specific book on digital humanities or
                        electronic literature, which is fed into the Amazon Related Product Graph,
                        created by Erik Borra, calling the Amazon API<note>The source code for this
                            tool is available at <ref
                                target="https://github.com/digitalmethodsinitiative/arpg"
                                >https://github.com/digitalmethodsinitiative/arpg</ref></note>. We
                        used ten seeds per subject area that returned up to ten <q>similar</q> books
                        per item, and then for each of these results the process was repeated. Using
                        Gephi, the ten data sets were then <q>appended</q> into one master data set
                        that was used for the generation of the subject area visualisations. </p>
                    <p>The selection of seeds was somewhat heuristic, and based on discussion
                        between subject domain experts on the most important books in each field.
                        For the field of electronic literature, the selection took into account
                        frequently referenced books as documented in the <title rend="quotes">ELMCIP
                            Knowledge Base of Electronic Literature</title>. </p>
                    <p>Below are the initial seeds for the subject areas.</p>
                    <table rend="unbordered">
                        <head>Digital Humanities Seeds</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell>ASIN</cell>
                            <cell>Title</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>262018470</cell>
                            <cell>Digital_Humanities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>230292658</cell>
                            <cell>Understanding Digital Humanities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1405168064</cell>
                            <cell>A Companion to Digital Humanities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>816677956</cell>
                            <cell>Debates in the Digital Humanities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1856047660</cell>
                            <cell>Digital Humanities in Practice</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>472051989</cell>
                            <cell>Hacking the Academy: New Approaches to Scholarship and
                                Teaching</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>226321428</cell>
                            <cell>How We Think: Digital Media and Contemporary Technogenesis</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>252078209</cell>
                            <cell>Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>26251740<note>The lookup of these books failed because the actual
                                    ASIN ends with an X (26251740X and 26212176X). This does not
                                    mean that the book is automatically excluded from the analysis
                                    because if it is recommended by one of the other seed books it
                                    will once again be included in the data set.</note></cell>
                            <cell>Mechanisms: New Media and the Forensic Imagination</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>26212176<note> Ibid.</note></cell>
                            <cell>The Digital Word: Text-based Computing in the Humanities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1409410684</cell>
                            <cell>Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities</cell>
                        </row>

                    </table>

                    <table rend="unbordered">
                        <head>Electronic literature Seeds</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell>ASIN</cell>
                            <cell>Title</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>801842816</cell>
                            <cell>Hypertext</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>801855853</cell>
                            <cell>Hypertext 2.0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>801882575</cell>
                            <cell>Hypertext 3.0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>801855799</cell>
                            <cell>Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>816667381</cell>
                            <cell>Digital Art and Meaning</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>268030855</cell>
                            <cell>Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the Literary</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>262517531</cell>
                            <cell>Expressive Processing: Digital Fictions, Computer Games, &amp;
                                Software Studies</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>262631873</cell>
                            <cell>Hamlet on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in
                                Cyberspace</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>262633183</cell>
                            <cell>Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive Fiction</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1441115919</cell>
                            <cell>New Directions in Digital Poetry</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1441107452</cell>
                            <cell>Cybertext Poetics: The Critical Landscape of New Media Literary
                                Theory</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Gephi Procedure</head>
                    <p>The following section describes the steps taken in creating network
                        visualisations using Gephi from the GEXF result files as output of
                        requesting the recommendations for the seed books with a depth of two. These
                        steps describe how a <q>master set</q> was created from ten individual files
                        (corresponding with the seeds) for each of the queried local Amazons.
                        Described here is the process for creating the Digital Humanities .co.uk
                            <q>master set</q>. Any deviations from these settings for creating the
                        other master sets are noted below.</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>For each seed book we have 10 .gexf files, each containing the
                            recommendations for one ASIN with a depth of two.</item>
                        <item>Combine those ten .gexf files to create one graph by appending them in
                                Gephi<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Open the first file as a New Graph. Graph Type:
                                    Directed</item>
                                <item>Open the next file and choose <q>Append Graph</q> to add it to
                                    the first.</item>
                                <item>Repeat until done</item>
                                <item>We now have one graph with 155 nodes and 257 edges.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Run spatialization algorithm Force Atlas 2 <ptr target="#jacomy2011"
                                />.<note>It is scaled for small to medium-size graphs, and is
                                adapted to qualitative interpretation of graphs <ptr
                                    target="#jacomy2011"/>.</note><list type="ordered">
                                <item>Settings: Scaling 100, Gravity 5<lb/>These settings are not
                                    fixed settings, rather, they are adjusted per graph to increase
                                    readability and are adjusted during the process in an iterative
                                    process to produce the best readability. Scaling represents
                                    repulsion and increasing gravity prevents islands from drifting
                                    away.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Rank nodes according to InDegree to relatively scale node size
                            according to the number of recommendations it receives from other
                                books.<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Settings linear scaling: Min size: 4, Max size: 40.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Color code clusters to algorithmically detect communities in the graph
                            using modularity statistics<note>
                                <ref target="#blondel2008" loc="1000">see: Blondel et
                                al.</ref>.</note>:<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Statistics: Run Modularity with the following settings:
                                    randomize 1, use weights 1, resolution 1.0</item>
                                <item>Partition nodes with Modularity Class partition
                                        parameter<note>"This structure, often called a community
                                        structure, describes how the the network is
                                        compartmentalized into sub-networks. These sub-networks (or
                                        communities) have been shown to have significant real-world
                                        meaning." <ref
                                            target="http://wiki.gephi.org/index.php/Modularity"
                                            >http://wiki.gephi.org/index.php/Modularity</ref></note>.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>In the Data Laboratory copy data from <q>title</q> to Label to only
                            show the book title as the node’s label.</item>
                        <item>Show labels (in our case book titles) of the nodes scaled to node
                            sizes in overview and run the <q>Label Adjust</q> layout algorithm to
                            prevent overlap for readability</item>
                        <item>Preview: Default Straight presets<list type="ordered">
                                <item>in order to improve readability, shorten labels if they are
                                    longer than thirty-four characters</item>
                                <item>custom label color (#333333) </item>
                                <item>custom edge color (#BDBDBD) to further increase readability of
                                    the graph.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Save graph as PDF</item>
                        <item>Calculate network statistics for tables 1 and 2. In the
                                <q>statistics</q> panel<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Click <q>Average Degree</q> and note the resulting
                                    number</item>
                                <item>Click <q>Graph Density</q>, check <q>Directed</q>, and note
                                    the resulting number</item>
                                <item>Click <q>Network Diameter</q>, check <q>Directed</q>, leave
                                    other options empty, and note the diameter, average path length,
                                    and number of shortest paths (rounded to three decimals)</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Design graph further in Adobe Illustrator:<list type="ordered">
                                <item>Adjusted community cluster colors using the tool <title
                                        rend="quotes">I want Hue</title>
                                    <note><ref
                                            target="http://tools.medialab.sciences-po.fr/iwanthue/"
                                            >http://tools.medialab.sciences-po.fr/iwanthue/</ref></note>
                                    a tool for data scientists which generates palettes of optimally
                                    distinct colours. These are the colours we generated and used in
                                    our graphs: <list>
                                        <item>#7CD5B0</item>
                                        <item>#CA52CC</item>
                                        <item>#C44639</item>
                                        <item>#CAC943</item>
                                        <item>#503A60</item>
                                        <item>#50733C</item>
                                        <item>#CB99A2</item>
                                        <item>#C0477D</item>
                                        <item>#70D151</item>
                                        <item>#8675CB</item>
                                        <item>#C1823A</item>
                                        <item>#533B2E</item>
                                        <item>#7BA7BD</item>
                                        <item>#C4C488</item>

                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Highlight seed URLs</item>
                        <item>Put graph in pre-cooked country template</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Digital humanities Amazon.de same but Force Atlas 2 Settings: Scaling 300,
                        Gravity 1</p>
                    <p>Digital humanities Amazon.fr same but Force Atlas 2 Settings: Scaling 300,
                        Gravity 5</p>
                    <p>Electronic literature Amazon combined same but Force Atlas 2 Settings:
                        Scaling 300, Gravity 5</p>
                    <p>Electronic literature Amazon.com same but Force Atlas 2 Settings: Scaling
                        300, Gravity 5</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>VISUALIZATIONS OF DIGITAL HUMANITIES</head>
                <p>This first graph was created by combining the ten master data sets from the ten
                    digital humanities seeds (see Table 1) for Amazon.com with a depth of three and
                    shows the overall Amazon recommendation network for Digital Humanities.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Part of the full Digital Humanities Amazon.com similar items purchased
                        graph with 853 book titles with color-coded communities: Game Studies,
                        Electronic Literature, Internet &amp; Technology, New Materialism, Digital
                        Humanities, Book Studies, Deleuze Studies and OOO/Speculative Realism. Node
                        size scaled according to InDegree. Seeds indicated in yellow. Full image:
                            <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_Full_ClusterColorCoded_A4.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_Full_ClusterColorCoded_A4.pdf</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>

                </figure>

                <p>Within the graph visualisation (Figure 1) each node represents a book. It is a
                    directed graph which means that the edges between the source (book A) and the
                    target (book B) are directed (A points to B). In our case the edges represent
                    recommendations so the source (book A) points to the target (recommended book B,
                    C, D etc.). We retrieved recommendations to a depth of three, meaning that our
                    data set includes the seed books (i.e. depth 0), books recommended in relation
                    to the seeds (i.e. depth 1), books recommended in relation to the books in depth
                    1 (i.e. depth 2), and books recommended in relation to the books in depth 2
                    (i.e. depth 3). </p>
                <p>What we see in Figure 1 is the clustering of particular books into more or less
                    distinct genres or disciplinary groups. For example, we see that there are many
                    connections between books on internet and technology, electronic literature and
                    game studies, but fewer between game studies and book studies, or between book
                    studies and speculative realism. A closer reading of this visualization by a
                    topic expert on the Digital Humanities, David M. Berry, revealed that the books
                    cluster around particular fields within the Humanities such as Digital
                    Humanities, Media Studies, Literary Studies and related areas. We identified the
                    following clusters from the visualisations produced: Game Studies, Electronic
                    Literature, Internet and Technology, New Materialism, Digital Humanities, Book
                    Studies, Deleuze Studies and OOO/Speculative Realism. Some books appeared to
                    form bridges between the fairly distinct clusters, such as Hayles’ <title
                        rend="italic">How We Think.</title></p>
                <p>We also see here how, while some books are densely interconnected leading to the
                    clustering in the graph, others simply lead away from the initial seeds. An
                    example is Bate’s <title rend="italic">The Public Value of the
                        Humanities</title> (2011), which is bought by many Amazon customers who
                    bought Gold’s <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
                    (2012). However, as you see from Figure 2, people who bought Bates’ book don’t
                    tend to buy many other digital humanities books. Instead they are more likely to
                    buy other books about universities and the current crisis in academia. This
                    suggests that digitial humanists are interested in the crisis in academia, but
                    those interested primarily in the crisis in academia are not, on average,
                    particularly interested in the digital humanities. </p>
                <p>We also see many connections between the seed books, which suggests that our
                    initial choice of seeds was reasonably representative of the field.</p>


                <figure>
                    <head>Zoom into the full Digital Humanities similar items purchased graph with
                        853 book titles with one visible color-coded community: Digital Humanities
                        and a related cluster around “The Humanities/The University in crisis” on
                        the right (circled in blue).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>

                <p>Figure 1 and 2 show the network as generated from Amazon.com with a depth of
                    three. If we look at the networks generated from individual country Amazon
                    stores, we find important differences between the countries. In order to be able
                    to compare the US, UK, French, and German Amazon we limited the crawl depth for
                    recommendations to two. This means that we only looked at similar items
                    suggested for our seed books as well what was recommended for those similar
                    items.</p>
                <p>Feeding the seed books for the digital humanities into the US Amazon (.com)
                    generated a densely interlinked graph showing ninety-five individual books
                    (Figure 3) with all seed books clustered in the middle. We also see that all the
                    books bought by people who bought the seed books are connected to more than one
                    seed book. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The Digital Humanities Amazon.com similar items purchased graph with 95
                        book titles. Node size scaled according to InDegree. Clusters are
                        color-coded using modularity. Seeds indicated in yellow. Full image: <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_COM_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_COM_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>

                </figure>

                <p>Here a group of central digital humanities books have clustered in the center of
                    the graph. Eight of the seed books are visible here<note>Two seeds are not
                        visible on the map because they are not connected to the graph: <title
                            rend="italic">The Digital Word</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities</title>. There were no
                        similar items suggested for these books.</note>, but we also prominently see
                    four new books not on the list: Bartscherer and Coover’s anthology <title
                        rend="italic">Switching Codes</title>, Fitzpatrick’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Planned Obsolescence</title>, Moretti’s <title rend="italic">Graphs, Maps,
                        Trees</title> and McGann’s <title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality</title>.
                    Their size, scaled according to InDegree, indicates that they are often bought
                    together with other books that are recommended with the seeds. These additions
                    can be found around the digital humanities cluster, suggesting more affinity (or
                    more precisely, more links or edges) between these books than some of the other
                    digital humanities books. We see adjacent fields beyond this central cluster. </p>
                <p>The first related field is electronic literature on the right of the graph in
                    Figure 3. McGann’s <title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality</title> connects to
                    Hayles’ <title rend="italic">Electronic Literature</title>, which connects on to
                    other books on electronic literature. In the bottom of the graph, circled in
                    blue and green in Figure 4, we see a cluster on materiality, software and code
                    studies, alongside books on speculative realism/object-oriented philosophy,
                    which again lead to posthuman studies. </p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Detail of the Digital Humanities Amazon.com similar items purchased
                        graph.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>


                <p>Ian Bogost’s <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title> is notable for
                    being a bridge to speculative realism, circled in green in Figure 4, and you can
                    see books linked through Hayles’ <title rend="italic">How We Became
                        Posthuman</title> are also part of this cluster, which on the Hayles' side
                    includes cybertheory and posthumanist theory. At the lower left of the graph, in
                    blue, we see Alex Galloway’s <title rend="italic">The Interface Effect</title>
                    is an important hub, with a fairly disparate group of books surrounding it.</p>
                <p>Hayles' <title rend="italic">How We Think</title> has the highest InDegree (that
                    is, it is referenced by the most other nodes: it is recommended as a book
                    frequently bought by purchasers of the highest number of other books in our
                    sample) but is positioned on the edge of the main digital humanities cluster and
                    not centrally within this digital humanities cluster. Instead, this book appears
                    to function as a bridge or broker between different fields such as speculative
                    realism/object oriented ontology and new materialism. Very interestingly, it has
                    the same function in the electronic literature networks, as we will discuss
                    later in this paper. </p>

                <figure>
                    <head>The Digital Humanities Amazon.co.uk similar items purchased graph with 155
                        book titles. Node size scaled according to InDegree. Clusters are
                        color-coded using modularity. Seeds indicated in yellow. Full image: <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_UK_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_UK_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>

                </figure>



                <p>The UK Amazon graph shows 155 book titles with seven seeds clustered in the
                        middle<note>Three seeds are not visible on the map because they are not
                        connected to the graph: <title rend="italic">The Digital Word</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital
                            Humanities</title>, and <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New Media and
                            the Forensic Imagination</title>. For the first two books there were no
                        similar items suggested. <title rend="italic">Mechanism</title> is included
                        in the graph because lookup of the incorrect ASIN failed. It did show up in
                        the previous graph because it was a similar item to one of the other
                        books.</note>. Similarly to the US Amazon, Hayles' <title rend="italic">How
                        We Think</title> functions as a bridge to the fields of object oriented
                    ontology and new materialism and Bogost’s <title rend="italic">Alien
                        Phenomenology</title> functions as a bridge to speculative realism on the
                    top. However, there are three new clusters visible that distinguish it from the
                    US Amazon graph. First, we see a cluster of (popular) new media theory books on
                    the left with Geert Lovink’s<title rend="italic"> Networks without a
                        Cause</title>, Nancy Baym’s <title rend="italic">Personal Connections in the
                        Digital Age</title> and Sherry Turkle’s <title rend="italic">Alone
                        Together</title> forming bridges. Second, a cluster on digital history in
                    the bottom middle and third, a cluster on book history and book publishing on
                    the bottom right.</p>
                <p>Figures 6 and 7 show the networks generated by feeding our English-language seed
                    books into the French and German Amazon stores. In both cases, the seed books
                    almost all disappear.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>The Digital Humanities Amazon.fr similar items purchased graph with 62
                        book titles. Node size scaled according to InDegree. Clusters are
                        color-coded using modularity. Seeds indicated in yellow. Full image: <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_FR_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_FR_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding_ColoredSeeds.pdf</ref>
                    </head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>

                </figure>


                <p>On the graph for Amazon.fr, only two books from the seeds remain: <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> and <title
                        rend="italic">Understanding Digital Humanities</title>. It immediately
                    becomes apparent that besides these two seeds there are only two other English
                    language books in the graph: <title rend="italic">Planned Obsolescence</title>
                    and <title rend="italic">Switching Codes</title>. The seed <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> acts as a bridge to four
                    clusters, which, unlike the other graphs, solely consist of French-language
                    books. These books are both original French books and translations. A possible
                    explanation for this lack of English books in the French-speaking DH network is
                    the current trend in translating DH into French terms, either <q><foreign
                            xml:lang="fr">Humanités numériques</foreign></q><note> cf. example here:
                            <ref target="http://books.openedition.org/oep/238"
                            >http://books.openedition.org/oep/238</ref></note> or <q><foreign
                            xml:lang="fr">Humanités digitales</foreign></q><note> cf. example here:
                            <ref target="http://cdh.epfl.ch/digital"
                            >http://cdh.epfl.ch/digital</ref></note>.</p>
                <p>The first cluster with the largest number of nodes (in pink/purple), is
                    constituted by French sociology and media studies books, mostly written by
                    academics but published by mainstream publishing houses which aims to foster
                    general public debates about technology in society. On the right side, the
                    cluster with blue nodes revolves around two books written by Milad Doueihi, a
                    French-speaking classical historian: <title rend="italic">Pour un humanisme
                        numérique</title> and <title rend="italic">La grande conversion
                        numérique</title>. These books on <soCalled>numerical humanism</soCalled>
                    deal with the <soCalled>numerical turn</soCalled> and the future of books and
                    education after digitalization, which echoes the general purpose of the previous
                    cluster. Books about philosophy of technique constitute the cluster on the top
                    left side and all these books are connected to a French edition (<title
                        rend="italic">La raison graphique</title>) of Jack Goody’s <title
                        rend="italic">The Domestication of the Savage Mind,</title> which acts as a
                    bridge to the digital humanities. Books about sociology, philosophy of risk
                    society, and citizen science constitute the last cluster, with green nodes on
                    the top right side, and they are all connected by the French edition of Ulrich
                    Beck’s <title rend="italic">Risk Society: Towards a New Modernity</title>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The Digital Humanities Amazon.de similar items purchased graph with 92
                        book titles. Node size scaled according to InDegree. Clusters are
                        color-coded using modularity. Seeds indicated in yellow. Full image: <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_DE_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/DH_DE_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding.pdf</ref>
                    </head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>

                </figure>

                <p>On the graph for Amazon.de, five books from the seeds remain. The various
                    clusters are less thematized than the other countries, and topical drifting
                    appears. The cluster in the center, in green, contains digital humanities
                    literature, and media studies books. The cluster in purple, in the bottom
                    center, goes from media studies to philosophy and French theory, which echoes
                    the close cluster on the right (in brown nodes) on posthuman theories. The two
                    clusters on the top are related to information science (red nodes on the top
                    left side) and to computer science books, mainly about Turing (green nodes, top
                    right). The last cluster, at the bottom left with blue nodes, contains literary
                    theory and novels.</p>
                <p>Unlike the French graph, there are many English language books in the German
                    graph, but interestingly enough the graph introduces German books on digital
                    humanities such as <title rend="italic">Digitale Arbeitstechniken: für die
                        Geistes- und Kulturwissenschaften</title>, <title rend="italic">Digitale
                        Geschichtswissenschaft</title>, and <title rend="italic">Digital Past:
                        Geschichtswissenschaft im digitalen Zeitalter</title> on the topics of
                    digital history and digital tools for the humanities and cultural studies. It
                    also includes <title rend="italic">Die technologische Bedingung: Beiträge zur
                        Beschreibung der technischen Welt</title>, a compilation of translated
                    essays including Galloway, Hansen, and Hayles translated into German. As an
                    introduction into the topic of <q>the technological condition</q> in German it
                    acts as a bridge to related books in English.</p>
                <p>Further comparing the various local Amazon domains under study we can see that
                    .com has the most densely interlinked recommendations (see density and average
                    degree in Table 3) while .fr is the sparsest. This of course also reflects how
                    quickly other books are recommended (average path length).</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Network statistics for the networks of each of the local Amazon domains
                        under study.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>data set</cell>
                        <cell>nodes</cell>
                        <cell>edges</cell>
                        <cell>density</cell>
                        <cell>avg degree</cell>
                        <cell>diameter</cell>
                        <cell>avg path length</cell>
                        <cell>number of shortest paths</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">.co.uk</cell>
                        <cell>155</cell>
                        <cell>257</cell>
                        <cell>0.011</cell>
                        <cell>1.658</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>3.139</cell>
                        <cell>3808</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">.fr</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>0.019</cell>
                        <cell>1.129</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1.884</cell>
                        <cell>207</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">.de</cell>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>118</cell>
                        <cell>0.014</cell>
                        <cell>1.283</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>2.910</cell>
                        <cell>1052</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">.com</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>206</cell>
                        <cell>0.023</cell>
                        <cell>2.168</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>2.716</cell>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                    </row>

                </table>


            </div>
            <div>
                <head>VISUALIZATIONS OF ELECTRONIC LITERATURE</head>
                <p>Our analysis suggests that electronic literature is a far less cohesive field
                    than digital humanities is in the USA, at least in so far as printed books can
                    be said to represent the field. Figure 8 shows the network of all books returned
                    for our electronic literature seed books in the four Amazon stores we searched,
                    and you can see that a large number of books were returned for the seed books.
                    The seed nodes, which are marked in yellow, are scattered around the graph
                    rather than clustered in the center as in the US digital humanities graph in
                    Figure 3, and they are not heavily recommended, as is indicated by the small
                    size of most of the seed nodes. The two seed books within electronic literature
                    that Amazon.com notes readers of other books buy are Hayles’ <title
                        rend="italic">Electronic Literature</title> and Aarseth’s <title
                        rend="italic">Cybertext</title>, but as Figure 8 shows, the Force Atlas 2
                    algorithm in Gephi does not pull them close together, although they are directly
                    linked to each other. This is because people who buy these two books also buy
                    books in distinctly different fields: <title rend="italic">Electronic
                        Literature</title> connects to DH, book culture, and disucssions of
                    materiality, and <title rend="italic">Cybertext</title> to game studies. There
                    are very few links directly between game studies and DH or game studies and book
                    culture. Between <title rend="italic">Electronic Literature</title> and <title
                        rend="italic">Cybertext</title> we see a range of key texts in new media
                    studies that are also important in electronic literature, such as Manovich’s
                        <title rend="italic">The Language of New Media</title>, Bolter and Grusin’s
                        <title rend="italic">Remediation</title>, and Jenkins’ <title rend="italic"
                        >Convergence Culture</title> as well as core media studies texts such as
                    McLuhan. </p>
                <p>Further comparing the DH and electronic literature graphs from a more numerical
                    point of view (see Table 4), we can see that although the electronic literature
                    graph has fewer nodes, it is actually more densely connected than the DH one
                    (see density and average degree). Looking at the average path length, one can
                    see that it is easier to reach other books given a book related to EL according
                    to Amazon.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Network statistics for the full Digital Humanities (DH full) and
                        Electronic Literature (EL full) networks.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>data set</cell>
                        <cell>nodes</cell>
                        <cell>edges</cell>
                        <cell>density</cell>
                        <cell>avg degree</cell>
                        <cell>diameter</cell>
                        <cell>avg path length</cell>
                        <cell>number of shortest paths</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">DH full</cell>
                        <cell>853</cell>
                        <cell>1402</cell>
                        <cell>0.002</cell>
                        <cell>1.644</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>5.807</cell>
                        <cell>58965</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">EL full</cell>
                        <cell>464</cell>
                        <cell>977</cell>
                        <cell>0.005</cell>
                        <cell>2.106</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>4.111</cell>
                        <cell>33944</cell>
                    </row>

                </table>


                <figure>
                    <head>The Electronic Literature Amazon (.com, .fr, .de, .co.uk combined) similar
                        items purchased graph with 464 book titles. Node size scaled according to
                        InDegree. Clusters are color-coded using modularity. Seeds indicated in
                        yellow. Full image: <ref
                            target="https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/EL_FULL_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding.pdf"
                            >https://wiki.digitalmethods.net/pub/Dmi/Winter13AmazonRecommendations/EL_FULL_FA2_ScaledIndegree_ModularityColorCoding.pdf</ref>
                    </head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>

                </figure>


                <p>The games studies cluster below <title rend="italic">Cybertext</title> is far
                    more cohesive and interlinked than the rest of the network, suggesting that this
                    is a more clearly defined field than electronic literature, at least in terms of
                    having an established set of printed books that are frequently bought
                    together.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Detail of the electronic literature graph in Figure 8, showing the game
                        studies cluster.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>

                </figure>


                <p>At the top of Figure 8, we see links leading away from electronic literature into
                    discussions of the role of the book in a networked society and further away into
                    book history and general discussions of bookmaking and the book business. This
                    shows how one field drifts towards another, but we also see that this section of
                    the graph is not interlinked and that there are few or no connections back into
                    the more centrally placed books that are more closely related to electronic
                    literature.</p>
                <p>The upper right of Figure 8 shows a digital humanities cluster very similar to
                    that generated by our digital humanities seeds, while the lower right hand side
                    shows an interesting loosely connected cluster of works on conceptual poetry and
                    writing and on digital poetics. We see Perloff’s <title rend="italic">Unoriginal
                        Genius: Poetry by Others</title> is a hub here, and while Perloff’s book is
                    not specifically about electronic literature, its focus on remixing and
                    cut-and-paste as literary techniques is clearly relevant to electronic
                    literature. Another hub, seen towards the bottom right of Figure 10, is Montfort
                    et.al.’s <title rend="italic">10 Print Chr (205.5+Rnd(1))</title>, a book about
                    a one line BASIC program that generates a simple graphic maze consisting of two
                    randomly repeated characters in the Commodore 64 computer’s character set. This
                    is again not exactly electronic literature, but it is closely related to
                    electronic literature, and in the book the short program is analysed as closely
                    as literature ever was by several important critics in the field of electronic
                    literature. Perhaps we must conclude that some of the most important books for
                    the study of electronic literature are not about electronic literature per se? </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Detail of the electronic literature graph in Figure 8 showing a cluster of
                        books on conceptual writing and digital poetics. </head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>

                </figure>

                <p>Far out to the right in Figure 8, we see a cluster of books about generative art
                    and code art (Figure 11).</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Detail of the electronic literature graph in Figure 8 showing a cluster of
                        books on code and art.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>

                </figure>

                <p>As you can see in Figure 8, this cluster is quite distant from the rest of the
                    network, and is connected to it by a few clear brokers: Bartscherer and Coover’s
                    recent anthology <title rend="italic">Switching Codes</title>, Simanowski’s
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Art and Meaning: Reading Kinetic Poetry, Text
                        Machines, Mapping Art, and Interactive Installations</title>, and Montfort
                    et.al.’s <title rend="italic">10 Print</title>. <title rend="italic">Switching
                        Codes</title> also shows up as a very central book in the US digital
                    humanities network as shown in Figure 3, and appears to function as a bridge
                    between different communities related to digital humanities, electronic
                    literature and digital art. </p>
                <p>Despite the fact that electronic literature research is scholarship about
                    creative works of electronic literature, only three works of electronic
                    literature show up in the graph, and these are works published on CD-ROM by
                    Eastgate systems in the early 1990s. Most electronic literature is published
                    online and is not part of Amazon’s database. We see in Figure 12 that Joyce’s
                    seminal hypertext fiction <title rend="italic">afternoon, a story</title>, shows
                    up and is connected to the seed books Hayles’ <title rend="italic">Electronic
                        Literature</title> and Landow’s <title rend="italic">Hypertext 3.0</title>
                    as well as Murray’s <title rend="italic">Hamlet on the Holodeck</title>, and
                    also to a relatively unrelated book, Shirky’s <title rend="italic">Here Comes
                        Everybody</title>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Detail of the electronic literature graph in Figure 8 showing hypertext
                        fictions <title rend="italic">afternoon</title>, <title rend="italic"
                            >Patchwork Girl</title> and <title rend="italic">Victory
                        Garden</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>

                </figure>

                <p>We see that people who bought <title rend="italic">afternoon</title> also bought
                    two other frequently cited hypertext fictions from the early 1990s: Jackson’s
                        <title rend="italic">Patchwork Girl</title> and Moulthrop’s <title
                        rend="italic">Victory Garden</title>. Research in the field of electronic
                    literature tends to reference a broad range of creative works in the field <ptr
                        target="#rettbergjw2014"/> and while using our methodology on a traditional
                    field of literary studies might capture literary works as well as scholarly
                    books, literary works of electronic literature are not sold on Amazon. This may
                    be one reason why the field of electronic literature appears less cohesive than
                    that of the digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>LIMITATIONS</head>
                <p>Studying a field only from the point of view of Amazon book recommendations is
                    clearly not going to tell the whole story about digital humanities or electronic
                    literature. This type of study of the field excludes other book sellers and
                    traditional scholarly resources such as journals and journal articles and also
                    excludes the outputs of digital humanities projects such as archives, TEI
                    projects, websites, tools and code archives, and also works of art and
                    literature which are central to the field of electronic literature. Also, it
                    bears the temporal limitations imposed by the time constraint of the three-day
                    data sprint format. Finally, there are also technical limitations using the
                    Amazon API in our survey of the fields of electronic literature and digital
                    humanities, such as a limit of ten recommendations per book and a maximum of
                    3600 requests to the API per hour. </p>
                <p>Nonetheless, it does provide a new way of looking at the field. The sheer size of
                    the Amazon database allows us to see interesting connections between the digital
                    humanities and adjacent fields. Also, even with these caveats it is notable that
                    the results, broadly speaking, do reflect clusters of what we might think of as
                    fields of study, and the connection between them. </p>
                <p>It is also important to realise that while the data does, according to Amazon,
                    give information about what other books are bought by customers who buy book X,
                    book sales don’t necessarily mean that the books are read, cited, used, or
                    influential. In addition, customers who buy digital humanities books also buy
                    other books on Amazon and if books are frequently bought together they will be
                    marked as <soCalled>similar</soCalled> by Amazon as recommendation engine. This
                    leads to the inclusion of <title rend="italic">The Portrait of Dorian
                        Gray</title> in the German digital humanities graph and, as a classic novel,
                    it is the most sold item in the graph. </p>
                <p>Our data from the French and German Amazon stores differed slightly from the
                    English-language Amazon stores with fewer results. One reason is that we use the
                    same, English-language books as seeds in all the national Amazon stores. While
                    we could have chosen French and German language books, we thought the results
                    yielded were still interesting, and many non-English titles rapidly appeared in
                    these graphs. The seeds introduced similar language-specific items on the topic
                    of digital humanities. This may point us to French and German-specific subfields
                    of the digital humanities in their native language.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>CONCLUSIONS AND FURTHER RESEARCH</head>
                <p>Based on these network graphs of different disciplines, we would conclude that
                    they appear to have different styles of communication, at least in terms of the
                    importance of printed books in the field. The field of digital humanities in the
                    USA as viewed through Amazon’s SimilarityLookup is cohesive, with a relatively
                    small number of books that are bought together. In France and Germany, on the
                    other hand, we see that the field is far less well defined, and based on the
                    books that are bought together, it is hard to say clearly what the digital
                    humanities are or are not in these countries. Britain offers an intermediate
                    position, where the digital humanities are understood in a less precise or
                    perhaps broader manner than in the US, and where we see relationships to many
                    more fields. </p>
                <p>Electronic literature, as viewed through print books and Amazon’s
                    SimilarityLookup, is a field that is far less cohesive than the digital
                    humanities in the USA, and we see instead that books on electronic literature
                    intermingle with books in related disciplines: new media studies, game studies
                    and the digital humanities chief among them. Game studies in fact comes to the
                    fore in the graph drawn from our electronic literature seeds, and appears to be
                    a field almost as cohesive as the digital humanities in the US. </p>
                <p>We mentioned earlier that there is some irony to analysing the digital humanities
                    by looking at the books published in the field rather than at the digital
                    projects and tools developed. But at least in the US, it appears that the field
                    of digital humanities is very clearly defined by its books. Our diagrams would
                    be an excellent starting point for a reading list for a newcomer to the digital
                    humanities. Electronic literature, on the other hand, is not as easily described
                    by this method. Perhaps more of the publications on electronic literature are
                    entirely digital, whether as creative works or as shorter articles in online
                    journals and other online publications, and thus they are not visible to Amazon.
                    Or perhaps electronic literature is more interdisciplinary by nature, and thus
                    people who read books about electronic literature read more broadly rather than
                    focusing on that topic alone. </p>
                <p>This research raises further questions that we think could be explored in
                    relation to the research questions.</p>
                <p>How can a more formal and defensible seeding strategy be developed? In the
                    project, in common with other digital methods projects, a domain subject expert
                    is used to generate initial data sources, seeds, and links. It would be
                    interesting and useful to reduce or eliminate the seeding process such that once
                    the general thematic area is identified, a standard seed generation methodology
                    can be followed. This may still use knowledge elicitation from the subject
                    domain expert, but would be formalised.</p>
                <p>How can validation of the API results be implemented so that the API does not
                    always return identical data for search queries? This is a result of how Amazon
                    handles data fields that contain a super-set in relation to the capacity of the
                    API return values. One method might be multiple requests and a smoothing
                    algorithm to average the results from the API.</p>
                <p>The ability to create the graphs from the API is extremely powerful and although
                    we undertook some limited secondary data generation, such as querying the Kindle
                    Highlights database<note><ref target="https://kindle.amazon.com/search"
                            >https://kindle.amazon.com/search</ref></note>, it would be useful to
                    formalise this method and generate sufficient data which when linked to the
                    primary graph data enables interactive exploration of the graph output.</p>
                <p>As an example of further research we ran some preliminary data requests to the
                    Kindle Highlights database, however, the number of highlights in our texts was
                    very low. Most digital humanists either do not read the digital (or at least,
                    the Kindle) versions of the texts, or they do not highlight their digital
                    versions. Nonetheless, with the growth in e-readers, iPads, tablets, and the
                    like, we can expect this database to be of increasing interest to researchers
                    undertaking similar projects to this in the future. For example, these are the
                    most popular highlights in Kirschenbaum’s <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New
                        Media and the Forensic Imagination,</title> which is important to both the
                    digital humanist and electronic literature subject areas. </p>
                <quote rend="block" source="kirschenbaum2011">forensic materiality rests upon the principle of
                    individualization (basic to modern forensic science and criminalistics), the
                    idea that no two things in the physical world are ever exactly alike.</quote>
                <quote rend="block" source="#kirschenbaum2011">The point is to address the fundamentally social,
                    rather than the solely technical mechanisms of electronic textual transmission,
                    and the role of social networks and network culture as active agents of
                    preservation.</quote>
                <quote rend="block" source="#kirschenbaum2011">a digital environment is an abstract projection
                    supported and sustained by its capacity to propagate the illusion (or call it a
                    working model) of immaterial behavior.</quote>
                <p>Each of these sections has limited information associated with it, although it is
                    noticeable that no page number is given – Kindles do not have page numbers as
                    part of the product.</p>
                <p>As an exploratory approach to mapping a field or disciplinary area of research,
                    this approach has much to recommend it. It provides a useful entry point for
                    drawing up an initial map of the field and for developing understanding of the
                    way in which books provide a structure for a field's development. Whilst we wish
                    to reiterate the limitations of this approach, particularly in view of the
                    digital nature of the two fields we chose for comparison, digital humanities and
                    electronic literature, and the resultant absences in the data and visualisations
                    that are created, we nonetheless think that used appropriately it is a method
                    that is very amenable to an exploratory method of field-mapping. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>

                <bibl label="Bastian et al. 2009" xml:id="bastian2009">Bastian, Mathieu, Sebastien
                    Heymann, and Mathieu Jacomy. <title rend="quotes">Gephi: an open source software
                        for exploring and manipulating networks.</title> <title rend="italic"
                        >ICWSM</title>: 361-362.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Berry 2012" xml:id="berry2012">Berry, D. M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Understanding Digital Humanities</title>, Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan,
                    2012. </bibl>

                <bibl label="Berry and Dieter 2012" xml:id="berrydieter2012">Berry, D. M. and
                    Dieter, M. <title rend="quotes">Book Sprinting</title>, accessed 14/08/2013,
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.booksprints.net/2012/09/everything-you-wanted-to-know/">
                        http://www.booksprints.net/2012/09/everything-you-wanted-to-know/</ref>,
                    2012</bibl>
                <bibl label="Borgman 2015" xml:id="borgman2015">Borgman, C. L. <title rend="italic"
                        >Big Data, Little Data, No Data: Scholarship in the Networked World</title>.
                    Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl label="De Solla Price 1965" xml:id="desollaprice1965">De Solla Price, Derek J.
                        <title rend="quotes">Networks of Scientific Papers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science</title>149, no. 3683: 510–15, 1965. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Galloway 2006" xml:id="galloway2006">Galloway, Alexander R. <title
                        rend="italic">Gaming: Essays on Algorithmic Culture</title>. Minneapolis,
                    MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gerlitz and Helmond 2013" xml:id="gerlitz2013">Gerlitz, Carolin and
                    Helmond, Anne. <title rend="quotes">The Like Economy: Social Buttons and the
                        Data-intensive Web</title>. <title rend="italic">New Media &amp; Society,
                    </title>2013</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gillespie 2012" xml:id="gillespie2012">Gillespie, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Relevance of Algorithms.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                        >Media Technologies</title>, edited by T Gillespie, Pablo Boczkowski, and
                    Kirsten A Foot, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gold 2012" xml:id="gold2012">Gold, M. K. <title rend="italic">Debates
                        in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Goldsmith and Wu 2006" xml:id="goldsmith2006">Goldsmith, J.L. &amp; Wu,
                    T. <title rend="italic">Who controls the Internet?: illusions of a borderless
                        world</title>, Oxford [u.a.: Oxford Univ. Press], 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hyde 2013" xml:id="hyde2013">Hyde, A. <title rend="quotes">Book
                        Sprints</title>, accessed 14/08/2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.booksprints.net">http://www.booksprints.net</ref>,
                    2013.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Jacomy et al. 2011" xml:id="jacomy2011">Jacomy, Mathieu, Tommaso
                    Venturini, Sebastien Heymann, and Mathieu Bastian. <title rend="quotes"
                        >ForceAtlas2, a Continuous Graph Layout Algorithm for Handy Network
                        Visualization Designed for the Gephi Software.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PLoS ONE</title>, 2011, 9 (6): e98679.
                    doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0098679.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Jameson 2006" xml:id="jameson2006">Jameson, F. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Postmodernism or the Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism</title>, in Kellner,
                    D. Durham, M. G. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Media and Cultural Studies
                        Keyworks</title>, London: Blackwell, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2011" xml:id="kirschenbaum2011">Kirschenbaum, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities As/Is a Tactical Term</title>, in Gold, M.
                    K. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>,
                    University of Minnesota, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Krebs 1999" xml:id="krebs1999">Krebs, V. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Social Life of Books. Visualizing Communities of Interest via Purchase
                        Patterns on the WWW.</title> Orgnet.com, 1999, accessed 14/08/2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.orgnet.com/booknet.html"
                        >http://www.orgnet.com/booknet.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Issuecrawler n.d." xml:id="issuecrawler">Issuecrawler (n.d.)
                    Issuecrawler.net, accessed 08/07/2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.govcom.org/Issuecrawler_instructions.htm"
                        >http://www.govcom.org/Issuecrawler_instructions.htm</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Kaplan 2015" xml:id="kaplan2015">Kaplan, F. <title rend="quotes">A Map
                        for Big Data Research in Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Frontiers in Digital Humanities</title>, 2015, 1. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Liu 2012" xml:id="liu2012">Liu, A. <title rend="quotes">Where Is
                        Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title> In M. K. Gold (ed.),
                        <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis:
                    U of Minnesota P, 2012, pp. 490-509.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Liu 2013" xml:id="liu2013">Liu, A. <title rend="quotes">From Reading to
                        Social Computing,</title> in Price, K. and Siemens, R. (eds.) <title
                        rend="italic">Literary Studies in the Digital Age: An Evolving
                        Anthology</title>, 2013, New York: MLA P / MLA Commons, accessed 11/02/2013,
                        <ref target="http://dlsanthology.commons.mla.org"
                        >http://DLSAnthology.commons.mla.org</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Marres and Weltevrede 2013" xml:id="marres2013">Marres, Noortje and
                    Weltevrede, Esther <title rend="quotes">Scraping the Social?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Economy</title>, 2013, 6, no. 3:
                    313–335. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Moretti 2005" xml:id="moretti2005">Moretti, Franco. <title
                        rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Tree: Abstract Models for Literary History.
                    </title>London: Verso, 2005. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Ramsay 2010" xml:id="ramsay2010">Ramsay, Stephen. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Hermeneutics of Screwing Around; or What You Do with a Million
                        Books.</title> Presented at Brown University, April 17 2010. <ref
                        target="http://www.playingwithhistory.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/hermeneutics.pdf"
                        >http://www.playingwithhistory.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/hermeneutics.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="S. Rettberg 2014" xml:id="rettbergs2014">Rettberg, S. <title
                        rend="quotes">Electronic Literature.</title> In Ryan, Marie-Laure, Lori
                    Emerson and Benjamin J. Robertson. <title rend="italic">The Johns Hopkins Guide
                        to Digital Media</title>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP, p 169-172, 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl label="J. W. Rettberg 2014" xml:id="rettbergjw2014">Rettberg, J. W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualising Networks of Electronic Literature: Dissertations
                        and the Creative Works They Cite.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Electronic Book Review</title>. 2014-07-06. <ref
                        target="http://www.electronicbookreview.com/thread/electropoetics/analyzing"
                        >http://www.electronicbookreview.com/thread/electropoetics/analyzing</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Rogers 2010" xml:id="rogers2010">Rogers, Richard. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Mapping public Web space with the Issuecrawler.</title> <title
                        rend="italic">Digital cognitive technologies: Epistemology and the knowledge
                        economy</title>: 89-99, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rogers 2013" xml:id="rogers2013">Rogers, Richard. <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Methods</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rogers et al. 2013" xml:id="rogersetal2013">Rogers, Richard, Esther
                    Weltevrede, Erik Borra, and Sabine Niederer. <title rend="quotes">National Web
                        Studies: The Case of Iran online.</title> In <title rend="italic">A
                        Companian to New Media Dynamics</title>, edited by J. Hartley, J. Burgess,
                    and A. Bruns, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Schöch 2013" xml:id="schoch2013">Schöch, C. <title rend="quotes">Big?
                        Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities, </title>November 22, 2013.
                        <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/"
                        >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wang 2012" xml:id="wang2012">Wang, Dan. <title rend="quotes">Is there a
                        Canon in Economic Sociology?</title> in <title rend="italic">ASA Economic
                        Sociology Newsletter </title>11(2), May 2012. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
