<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">How do we get to the Humanitarium from here?</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Stan <dhq:family>Ruecker</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>IIT Institute of Design</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sruecker@id.iit.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Stan Ruecker is an Associate Professor at IIT Institute of Design in
                            Chicago. He works in humanities visualization, the future of reading,
                            and information design, focusing on the design of experimental
                            prototypes to support the interpretive process.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000260</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2016-07-12">12 July 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>public relations</item>
                        <item>public funding</item>
                        <item>humanities research</item>
                        <item>digital humanities</item>
                        <item>humanities computing</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2016-05-24">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>For the past century, the sciences have made terrific strides in capturing the
                    public imagination. From dedicated television channels to online learning
                    materials to science-related entertainment and educational facilities for
                    families in practically every major city on the planet, the scale of public
                    relations has been impressive and continuous. However, the same cannot be said
                    for the Humanities. Although we certainly have cultural institutions for adults,
                    ranging from art galleries to opera houses, their primary emphasis has been on
                    providing opportunities for passively consuming cultural production, rather than
                    with the core interest of the Humanities, which is in enriching objects of study
                    by analyzing them through a variety of theoretical lenses. In this paper, I
                    argue, as others have been doing for some time, that the Humanities need to
                    learn in this respect from the sciences, in order to increase their public
                    stature. Further, the driving force behind this education is Digital Humanities.
                    Since public relations has been on the back burner for so long, this initiative
                    is both important and daunting; it is one of the ways in which the Digital
                    Humanities are strengthening the Humanities while at the same time encouraging
                    them in a task that seems difficult enough that everyone wishes it was not
                    necessary.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A call for the Humanities to increase its public stature, with Digital Humanities
                    at the lead.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>At some point around the turn of the millennium, I was shown a graph of federal
                    research funding in the USA. It was divided into the conventional three
                    categories used in North America, and presumably elsewhere: Medicine, Science,
                    and the Humanities. What was astonishing about the graph was that it only had
                    two bars. The bar for medical research reached to the top of the page, and the
                    bar for scientific research was about a third of the page. But the bar for
                    support for research in the Humanities was invisible at this scale — you would
                    have had to use log paper for it to appear. I used to point to this graph, where
                    the Humanities bar should have been, and say, <said>Here is where I get my
                        research funding.</said> The situation hasn’t changed. Figure 1 shows a
                    similar graph from a 2014 report of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences,
                    except medical research has been separated from biological research, and there
                    are three columns for the sciences and Engineering. By dint of these changes,
                    the Humanities are visible, but barely.<note>I note that here and throughout, I
                        use the term <q>Humanities</q> to mean Arts and Humanities, and in some
                        cases also Fine Arts and Social Sciences, recognizing that there is some
                        disagreement among institutions of higher education about which disciplines
                        fit where.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Comparison of research funding in the USA, 2006–2012 (American Academy of
                        Arts &amp; Sciences 2014, pg. 4)</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The discrepancy in research support is a surprise to no one. Traditional wisdom
                    has it that the Humanities don’t need money, because the kinds of research
                    equipment required are mostly books and other kinds of written material, with an
                    occasional bit of travel to find books or writings that aren’t available
                    locally. Even graduate students are treated as independent entities, for whom
                    individual funding programs are not usually associated with the research program
                    of the supervising faculty member. The reasoning is that in the sciences, grad
                    students typically join a lab, and most often pick up a research project that is
                    part of the larger program of research of the supervisor. Grad students in the
                    Humanities, however, typically consult with the supervisor, but in essence
                    choose an independent project — then sit somewhere and read their own books. </p>
                <p>The only problem with this model is that traditional wisdom is not entirely
                    accurate, and is downright inaccurate when it comes to research in the Digital
                    Humanities (DH). We digital humanists tend to be dealing with different issues —
                    in some cases, actually creating the objects of study in order to address
                    particular questions, and in others, building online collections, experimenting
                    with a variety of algorithms, trying out visualizations, and so on. Although it
                    is still unusual for a graduate student to join a DH lab, it does happen, and it
                    happens with increasing frequency. DH research also often calls for more
                    experimentation, less solitude, interdisciplinary teams of researchers, a
                    broader range of more powerful equipment, and so on. </p>
                <p>There has been some recognition of this change in the creation of specialized
                    funding programs for DH in several countries, including Canada and the US;
                    adding to their funding levels, however, still produces just a tiny movement in
                    the overall graph for Humanities research funding. The deprecation of learning
                    in the Western world as a public benefit and an essential component of democracy
                    has been almost unremitting for a generation, and even the disciplines outside
                    the humanities are beginning to see the effects. For example, a <title
                        rend="italic">Huffington Post</title> article from 2014 cites a recent study
                    showing that illiteracy in the US has held steady at a ridiculous rate for a
                    decade: <quote rend="block" source="#huffington2014">According to a study
                        conducted in late April by the U.S. Department of Education and the National
                        Institute of Literacy, 32 million adults in the U.S. can't read. That's 14
                        percent of the population. 21 percent of adults in the U.S. read below a 5th
                        grade level, and 19 percent of high school graduates can't read <ptr
                            target="#huffington2014"/>.</quote></p>
                <p>Literacy is a relatively low bar, and although in its basic form it is associated
                    with primary education, at its higher levels it is required for medical and
                    scientific research, and those higher levels have traditionally been in the
                    wheelhouse of the Humanities. That a fifth of the adult population in the U.S.
                    hasn’t achieved even the basic levels suggests that there are systemic problems;
                    once again, this state of affairs is not news to anyone. I hesitate somewhat to
                    use literacy statistics, because they are notoriously politicized, but
                    anecdotally, I meet people in the US who appear to have no literacy and little
                    or no numeracy. Some of them are holding jobs, but usually there appear to be
                    some workarounds in place to allow that to happen. For example, retail outlets
                    like McDonalds use cash registers where the keys are images of the products,
                    rather than numbers.</p>
                <p>What is also clear, at least anecdotally, is that the Humanities don’t get much
                    respect from the rest of the campus. It is rarely the case that upper
                    administration at major research institutions has a background in the
                    Humanities: a 2012 study by the American Council on Education found that
                    40 percent of college and university presidents in the US have backgrounds in
                    Education, and another 20 percent come from industry <ptr target="#cook2012"/>.
                    It is also often the case that the Humanities face funding cuts that are
                    disproportionate to the rest of the campus. At the major Canadian research
                    university where I used to work, the humanities had a three-year hiring freeze
                    at a time when the College of Engineering had a standing open call for 100 new
                    faculty members. We were nickel-and-dimed for everything from photocopies to
                    office space, culminating in a cost-cutting measure where every faculty member
                    in the Department of English and Film Studies had the telephones removed from
                    their offices. Although it was probably intended to make a statement of some
                    kind, the statement it actually made was that there was no need for faculty in
                    that department to be reached through that medium, whether by colleagues,
                    students, potential students, or the media. I spoke some years ago with one of
                    the professors in Engineering to find out what he thought about it. <said>I keep
                        watching,</said> he said, <said>for something exciting to be happening over
                        on your side of campus, and the only thing I’ve seen in a long time is what
                        is going on in Digital Humanities.</said> I was nonplussed; exciting
                    research is being done in the Humanities all the time. The difference was that
                    DH was visible in his world.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Public Relations</head>
                <p>In order to make their positive impact known, the Humanities need to rear up on
                    their hind legs and make some bold statements about what they are trying to
                    accomplish. Moreover, it is likely that they need to make those statements in
                    such a way that they will reach someone other than the choir — namely, the tens
                    of millions of illiterate adults. A hundred years ago, Medicine was not a
                    significant research discipline, and although doctors were valued, many were
                    valued in terms of domestic produce such as chickens and jars of jam, much like
                    members of the clergy. Lewis Thomas, for example, remembers how his father would
                    celebrate if he received his entire fee immediately; the idea that anyone would
                    enter Medicine as a means of obtaining capital wealth was laughable <ptr
                        target="#thomas1983" loc="3"/>. A hundred years before that, the term
                        <term>science</term> was being deprecated as an unreasonable barbarism, far
                    inferior to the more ambitious and exalted <term>natural philosophy</term> of an
                    earlier era.</p>
                <p>All of which is to say that conditions have not always been what they are today.
                    We are living in what used to be the future, and it is terrific in many ways.
                    For example, medical research has vastly reduced the instances of cholera, and
                    the same can be said for a wide range of afflictions, including calamities like
                    polio, where up until less than 60 years ago, all that could be done was to
                    stick people in a giant metal coffin that reduced the air pressure enough that
                    they could breathe. Governments, NGOs, and the public in general may debate the
                    high costs of health care, but no one suggests that the solution is to stop
                    doing medical research; there are enough success stories to more than justify
                    its existence, and the health it helps to support is recognized as important by
                    practically everyone. </p>
                <p>Scientific research has similarly been working miracles, from industrial systems
                    to the Internet; hardly a year goes by without someone announcing a new kind of
                    crop, a new device, a new material. For the sciences, however, the commitment of
                    third parties is less secure, since the connection to personal benefit is not so
                    visceral. I am, however, personally looking forward to having tiny little repair
                    robots in my blood, combining science research with medical research once again
                    to produce levels of health and vivacity that are hard to imagine here in
                    tomorrow’s past.</p>
                <p>We find similarly remarkable advances in the Humanities, where we tend not to
                    speak of <q>advances</q> at all. However, discourse aside, they do exist. For
                    example, we are now on the lookout for all kinds of new perspectives that lend
                    depth and richness to how we understand the world. What is going on, we now ask,
                    with how this writer or that is dealing with women, minorities, the postcolonial
                    world, the posthuman? We don’t primarily seek to crunch the numbers and get an
                    answer, but instead we try to enrich the object of study by iterative analysis
                    and reporting from different perspectives — more like building up a pearl than
                    climbing up a ladder. As I often put it, we are not trying to solve Shakespeare
                    and move on to Milton; instead, every generation we have new ideas about
                    both.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Wicked Problems, Wicked Opportunities</head>
                <p>That very humanistic approach, of dealing with what we are studying as though it
                    will reward continued study from all the angles we can conceive of and argue
                    for, is a method with the potential to radically transform the world. It is at
                    least as vital and amazing as anything going on elsewhere on campus. </p>
                <p>One of the distinguishing features of scholarly activities in the Humanities is a
                    focus on people: what they’ve done, what they think, what they’ve written. In
                    practical terms, any problem involving people is likely to be, to use the term
                    first proposed by Rittel and Webber, a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#rittel1973">wicked problem</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rittel1973" loc="160"/>
                    </cit>. They define this category of problem with the following wonderful list
                    of conditions:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>A definitive definition of the problem does not exist</item>
                    <item>It is impossible to know when it is solved</item>
                    <item>Solutions are just better or worse, not true or false</item>
                    <item>Solutions cannot by definitively tested</item>
                    <item>Every attempt at a solution changes the conditions</item>
                    <item>Possible solutions are innumerable</item>
                    <item>Each problem is essentially unique</item>
                    <item>Every problem is a symptom of another problem</item>
                    <item>Problems can be explained in different ways, and each explanation suggests
                        different solutions</item>
                    <item>People must take responsibility for the solutions they choose <ptr
                            target="#rittel1973" loc="161"/></item>
                </list>
                <p>If we replace the word <q>problem</q> with <q>object of study</q> and
                        <q>solution</q> with <q>interpretation,</q> the criteria read like a list of
                    statements about how the humanities have always understood the world: </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>A definitive definition of the object of study does not exist</item>
                    <item>It is impossible to know when an interpretation is complete</item>
                    <item>Interpretations are just better or worse, not true or false</item>
                    <item>Interpretations cannot by definitively tested</item>
                    <item>Every attempt at an interpretation changes the conditions</item>
                    <item>Possible interpretations are innumerable</item>
                    <item>Each object of study is essentially unique</item>
                    <item>Every interpretation is a symptom of another interpretation</item>
                    <item>Objects of study can be explained in different ways, and each explanation
                        suggests different interpretations</item>
                    <item>People must take responsibility for the interpretations they choose</item>
                </list>
                <p>It seems clear that wicked problems are the class of problems most effectively
                    addressed using the methods of the Humanities. Moreover, I would go further and
                    say that the same criteria apply not only to problems, but also to
                    opportunities. It is increasingly believed in government and industry that the
                    problems worth addressing are wicked problems, and the opportunities are in this
                    sense wicked too. For example, the language of the <q>Grand Challenge,</q>
                    meaning a global wicked problem/opportunity, is being used by organizations such
                    as USAID, Grand Challenges Canada, and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
                    Although the vast bulk of resources is currently being allocated to projects of
                    a technical nature, the Humanities are well positioned in both theoretical and
                    methodological terms to take the lead in understanding what is going on, which
                    is an indispensable component of planning for a better future.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4Humanities.com</head>
                <p>In 2010, a leading group of digital humanists, including Alan Liu, Geoffrey
                    Rockwell, Melissa Terras, Stéfan Sinclair, and Christine Henseler began an
                    online collection of success stories from the Humanities. Called <title
                        rend="italic">4Humanities</title> (Fig. 2), the collection is intended to
                    serve as a resource for anyone who is trying to make a case about the importance
                    of the Humanities. </p>
                <p><title rend="italic">4Humanities</title> began because the digital humanities
                    community — which specializes in making creative use of digital technology to
                    advance humanities research and teaching as well as to think about the basic
                    nature of the new media and technologies — woke up to its special potential and
                    responsibility to assist humanities advocacy. The digital humanities are
                    increasingly integrated in the humanities at large. They catch the eye of
                    administrators and funding agencies who otherwise dismiss the humanities as
                    yesterday’s news. They connect across disciplines with science and engineering
                    fields. They have the potential to use new technologies to help the humanities
                    communicate with, and adapt to, contemporary society <ptr
                        target="#fourhumanities"/>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The 4Humanities website <ptr target="#fourhumanities"/> was organized and
                        is run by a group of prominent digital humanists; it is a rich resource of
                        material highlighting the value of the Humanities.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>With a large collection of examples, advocacy projects, and tools,
                    4Humanities.com is currently and has been for some time a valuable site in the
                    ongoing struggle for public recognition and support. However, it is also only
                    one approach to the problems that need to be addressed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Humanitarium</head>
                <p>I have spent countless hours on family trips, school trips, and even trips with
                    friends and colleagues to places that specialize in promoting the sciences,
                    whether to a science museum, planetarium, discovery center, or other venue where
                    the goal is to make science fun and attractive to children. They are usually big
                    places (e.g., Fig. 3) and garner a lot of public support; they take at least
                    tens and usually hundreds of millions of dollars to build, and similar amounts
                    to operate (e.g., <ptr target="#morell2012"/> and <ptr target="#smg2013"/>).
                    Even for those places that charge an entry fee, it is not unusual for those fees
                    to account for less than 20 percent of the annual operating budget <ptr
                        target="#cscckms2013" loc="18"/>. </p>
                <p>However, they have earned it. I have watched bees moving in their hive, seen
                    someone making elephant toothpaste, started a captive tornado fifty feet high,
                    and zoomed not just through our galaxy, but also through a universe of galaxies.
                    It was amazing and fun, and it encouraged me, and the children I was with, to
                    think that science was a big deal — that it was worthwhile, whether or not we
                    would ever seek out a career as a professional part of it. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>A map of a typical science center <ptr target="#osc2004" loc="1"/></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>I ask myself, however, why there is no comparable interactive space — call it a
                        <q>Humanitarium</q> — in every single city for school trips and families and
                    members of the public who are interested in knowing more, not just about
                    individual objects of study (although those are important) but even more so
                    about the way the Humanities work. It might be argued that the techniques of
                    interpretation are too sophisticated, take too long, and are too situated within
                    the various disciplinary traditions to be of general interest. The same can be
                    said, however, for the techniques, timeframes, and disciplinary boundaries of
                    the sciences.</p>
                <p>The digital humanities have already been making experiments of this kind. In the
                    years 2007 and 2008, for example, the Humanities Computing (HuCo) MA program at
                    the University of Alberta ran a series of activities intended for middle school
                    students. These were not the usual students who were headed to the university
                    from the day they were born, but instead they were students from schools where a
                    transition to university was rare enough to be extraordinary. </p>
                <p>One set of experiences was planned and conducted by Maryanne Wynne, and involved
                    introducing the students to corpus linguistics, a field that in the University
                    of Alberta is located in the Faculty of Arts. Her approach was exemplary. She
                    began by talking about slang and how it changes over time: <said>What kinds of
                        things do your parents say that you would never say, for instance when they
                        really like something?</said> As the responses came in, she used the
                    interface to one of the online corpora to show the graphs of use of the word,
                    and how it varied between use in speaking, in writing, and so on. From there she
                    called up graphs of words the young people used: at the time one of them was
                        <q>awesome,</q> which showed a spike in recent usage (Fig. 4).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>The COCA corpus showing frequency of usage changing over time for the word
                            <q>awesome</q>
                        <ptr target="#ccae2015"/>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p><said>Now what kinds of things do people say are awesome?</said> and she
                    introduced the concept of collocation, showing various lengths of word-level
                    n-grams and how their usage had changed over time. In short order, the children
                    couldn’t wait to get their hands on the tools of corpus linguistics, which is
                    not one of the fields that would immediately leap to mind as having an
                    attraction for non-experts with questionable literacy. Her strategy combines
                    several key aspects. First, she wasn’t showing them a system designed for
                    children, but instead was using the actual online tools on real data. Second,
                    her emphasis was not on the field of study (reporting, for instance, some recent
                    findings), but instead on the techniques. Third, she applied those techniques to
                    material that was quite likely to get everyone’s imagination engaged. </p>
                <p>As an activity at the Humanitarium, I believe <q>how do people say something is
                        cool</q> would go a long way to increasing public awareness of and interest
                    in a relatively specialized and somewhat arcane part of the academy. </p>
                <p>However, corpus linguistics is only one example. If the sciences are about
                    understanding the physical world, and Medicine is about making life possible in
                    that world, the Arts and Humanities are about the quality of life. A typical
                    Humanitarium might have materials and experiences ranging from interactive
                    displays to fun, hands-on activities in a wide range of fields, including but
                    not limited to:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Anthropology</item>
                    <item>Art</item>
                    <item>Classics</item>
                    <item>Cultural Studies</item>
                    <item>Design</item>
                    <item>Drama</item>
                    <item>Economics</item>
                    <item>English</item>
                    <item>Environmental Studies</item>
                    <item>History</item>
                    <item>Linguistics</item>
                    <item>Music</item>
                    <item>Philosophy</item>
                    <item>Political Science</item>
                    <item>Psychology</item>
                    <item>Sociology</item>
                    <item>Gender Studies</item>
                </list>
                <p>Another strategy for organizing the experiences of the Humanitarium is to focus,
                    not necessarily on the existing fields of study, but instead on a variety of
                    theoretical lenses. Rivkin and Ryan, for example, list more than a dozen <ptr
                        target="#rivkin2010" loc="v"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Television Programming</head>
                <p>In a similar vein, we can imagine an audience for shows that demonstrate the core
                    competency of Humanities disciplines. In this respect, historians have done an
                    admirable job. However, there could equally well be a series of, for example,
                    literary theorists; in each episode, each theorist could interpret an object of
                    public interest from a different perspective.</p>
                <p>Although not necessarily an object of public interest, I often use Shakespeare’s
                    play <title rend="italic">The Tempest</title> as an example, especially when I
                    am speaking with audiences from the sciences. A straightforward, naïve reading
                    has a magician (Prospero) and his daughter (Miranda) stranded on an island.
                    Using his magic skills and the help of some esoteric creatures like Caliban and
                    Ariel, he arranges to reintroduce himself and his daughter into society. </p>
                <p>However, if we read <title rend="italic">The Tempest</title> from the perspective
                    of a postcolonial scholar, it is quite a different story. There are indigenous
                    slaves, including Caliban, whose mother Sycorax was murdered by Prospero before
                    the start of the play, and Ariel and her invisible friends, who were similarly
                    captured and forced to work for a stern foreign master.</p>
                <p>From a feminist perspective, one must wonder about the patriarchal Prospero, who
                    has raised his daughter Miranda in such an ill-informed way that she can observe
                    the ragged, dissolute crew of the arriving ship and respond with delight: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#shakespeare2000">O brave new world/That has
                            such people in't!</quote>
                        <ptr target="#shakespeare2000" loc="72"/>
                    </cit>. She is, of course, in for a surprise. The real interpretations are much
                    more sophisticated and nuanced than these brief examples could ever be, but they
                    serve to get the strategy across.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Public Service Announcements (PSAs)</head>
                <p>Although they are not as common on television as they once were, nor as common in
                    North America as in other parts of the world, the PSA has a venerable history as
                    a kind of commercial that is selling ideas rather than commodities. If the
                    humanities and their core activities are not well known or understood by the
                    general public, whoever that might be, PSAs could be another quick and
                    comparatively easy form of dissemination. Whatever contemporary form they take,
                    whether web videos, tweets, blog posts, or any other media, the principles are
                    the same: keep them short, simple, and friendly.</p>
                <p>As an example, I worked with Milena Radzikowska, Gerry Derksen, and others on a
                    series of one-minute video clips about design research projects. Design research
                    is another area that is not well understood by the public, and can benefit from
                    increased dissemination. We have therefore been briefly summarizing projects
                    like pill identification, visualization for decision support, and conversational
                    modeling. However, there are also short videos about a variety of DH-related
                    design research projects, such as the mandala browser, bubblelines, and the
                    dynamic table of contexts <ptr target="#iit2014"/>. Unfortunately, as in all
                    marketing efforts, it is nearly impossible to judge the impact of a single
                    project. All we really know is that some people have watched them, and with more
                    promotion, more people might, and with every viewer, we have extended awareness
                    of what design research is like.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Public relations have not been a central concern for the Humanities, for several
                    reasons. First is the cost of marketing and promotion, which is not easily
                    justified in an area where core programs have already faced decades of budget
                    cuts.</p>
                <p>Next is the nature of the activity being promoted. Since one of the primary
                    purposes of the Humanities is to multiply valid interpretations, the ground is
                    constantly shifting, not in an accidental or secondary way, but instead as a
                    central practice. Changes in perspective are core to the Humanities approach to
                    creating new knowledge (or improved understanding, as you prefer), and so any
                    promotional activity faces the challenge of not having a fixed object to
                    promote. From the perspective of the people whose work is being promoted, the
                    fundamental necessity of troubling any assumptions being made also creates a
                    challenge. The simplification process that is often necessary in creating a
                    public message is inimical to the kind of nuanced understanding that Humanities
                    researchers see as the point of the enterprise. From the marketing perspective,
                    this can appear as an incessant tendency to quibble. Possible workarounds might
                    include highlighting debates rather than outcomes, and including dissenting
                    viewpoints in sidebars or footnotes to the promotional materials.</p>
                <p>To complicate matters further, the accumulation of widely-accepted perspectives
                    takes place over long stretches of time, with validation processes carried out
                    in discussions that rely on publication cycles that take years for each
                    carefully-crafted statement to be made. Occasional media-genic moments, like
                    Lancashire and Hirst <ptr target="#lancashire2009" loc="1"/> using text analysis
                    to diagnose Altzheimer’s disease, are amazing and wonderful, but also
                    extraordinary; they cannot be construed as representing a general program of
                    action. This is less a criticism of the Humanities than it is of the capacity of
                    the media to cover work that does not easily produce press releases.</p>
                <p>Another factor is that the value of the Humanities has largely been assumed to be
                    understood. However, the allocation of resources over time argues otherwise. As
                    shown in Figure 1, above, research funding in the U.S.A. from 2005 to 2012
                    (adjusted for inflation) increased on the order of $5 billion each in fields
                    such as medicine, biology, and engineering, while remaining more or less fixed
                    in the Humanities <ptr target="#aaas2014" loc="4"/>. Admittedly, this is hard to
                    judge from the graph, since the Humanities allocation is nearly invisible to
                    begin with. </p>
                <p>We also live in a world that is increasingly undereducated, not only in the sense
                    of people not attending school, but also in the decrease of general education in
                    favour of early specialization. At my current university, it is possible, by
                    focused selection of electives, for undergraduate students in one of the
                    technical departments to take virtually no courses outside their major. So the
                    time may have arrived for the development of public relations campaigns, whether
                    in the form of new television or online programming and dedicated channels, the
                    establishment of Humanities discovery centers, or the expansion of the
                    application of humanities approaches to a larger range of cultural production,
                    including business and government. The Digital Humanities have already been
                    active in pursuing this agenda, and in that respect provide an opportunity and
                    challenge to the traditional Humanities and their concerns. However, a great
                    deal more remains to be accomplished.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl/>
                <bibl label="4Humanities 2010" xml:id="fourhumanities">4Humanities n.d., ‘Mission’,
                        <title rend="italic">4Humanities blog</title>, 4Humanities, Montréal, viewed
                    1 September 2015, <ref target="http://4humanities.org/mission/"
                        >http://4humanities.org/mission/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="American Academy of Arts &amp; Sciences 2014" xml:id="aaas2014"
                    >American Academy of Arts &amp; Sciences 2014, <title rend="italic">The State of
                        the Humanities: Funding</title>, American Academy of Arts &amp; Sciences,
                    Cambridge, MA</bibl>
                <bibl label="Cook 2012" xml:id="cook2012">Cook, B J 2012, <title rend="quotes">The
                        American college president study: key findings and takeaways</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">The Presidency</title> Spring Supplement, n.p., viewed 1
                    September 2015, <ref
                        target="http://www.acenet.edu/the-presidency/columns-and-features/Pages/The-American-College-President-Study.aspx"
                        >http://www.acenet.edu/the-presidency/columns-and-features/Pages/The-American-College-President-Study.aspx</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Calgary Science Centre &amp; Creative Kids Museum Society 2013"
                    xml:id="cscckms2013">Calgary Science Centre &amp; Creative Kids Museum Society
                    2013, <title rend="italic">Growing with our Community: 2013 Annual
                        Report</title>, Telus Spark Science Centre, Calgary, AB</bibl>
                <bibl label="Corpus of Contemporary American English 2015" xml:id="ccae2015"><title
                        rend="quotes">Corpus of Contemporary American English 2015</title>, viewed 6
                    October 2015, <ref target="http://corpus.byu.edu/coca/"
                        >http://corpus.byu.edu/coca/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Huffington Post 2014" xml:id="huffington2014">Huffington Post 2014,
                        <title rend="quotes">The US illiteracy rate hasn’t changed in 10
                        years</title>, <title rend="italic">Huffington Post blog</title>, web log
                    post, 12 December, viewed 1 September 2015, <ref
                        target="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/09/06/illiteracy-rate_n_3880355.html"
                        >http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/09/06/illiteracy-rate_n_3880355.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="IIT Institute of Design Vimeo Channel 2014" xml:id="iit2014">IIT
                    Institute of Design Vimeo Channel 2014. Professor Stan Ruecker Album. <ref
                        target="http://vimeo.com/album/2983883"
                    >http://vimeo.com/album/2983883</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Lancashire and Hirst 2009" xml:id="lancashire2009">Lancashire, I &amp;
                    Hirst, G 2009, <title rend="quotes">Vocabulary Changes in Agatha Christie’s
                        Mysteries as an Indication of Dementia: A Case Study</title>, Presented at
                    the 19th Annual Rotman Research Institute Conference, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cognitive Aging: Research and Practice</title>, 8–10 March 2009,
                    Toronto</bibl>
                <bibl label="Morell 2012" xml:id="morell2012">Morell, V 2012, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Budget cuts hit Chicago’s Field Museum</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) blog</title>,
                    web log post, 20 December, viewed 1 September 2015, <ref
                        target="http://news.sciencemag.org/2012/12/budget-cuts-hit-chicagos-field-museum"
                        >http://news.sciencemag.org/2012/12/budget-cuts-hit-chicagos-field-museum</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Ontario Science Centre 2004" xml:id="osc2004">Ontario Science Centre
                    2004, Ontario Science Centre English Guide Map, <ref
                        target="http://www.OntarioScienceCentre.ca"
                        >www.OntarioScienceCentre.ca</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Rittel and Webber 1973" xml:id="rittel1973">Rittel, H &amp; Webber, M
                    1973, <title rend="quotes">Dilemmas in a general theory of planning</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Policy Sciences</title> vol. 4, pp. 155–169</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rivkin and Ryan 2010" xml:id="rivkin2010">Rivkin, J &amp; Ryan, M 2010,
                        <title rend="italic">Literary Theory: An Anthology</title>, 2nd edn,
                    Blackwell Publishing, Malden, MA</bibl>
                <bibl label="Science Museum Group 2013" xml:id="smg2013">Science Museum Group 2013,
                        <title rend="italic">Annual Report and Accounts 2012–2013</title>, cat. no.
                    HC 519, TSO, Norwich, UK</bibl>
                <bibl label="Shakespeare 2000" xml:id="shakespeare2000">Shakespeare, W, Vaughan, V
                    M, &amp; Vaughan, A T 2000. <title rend="italic">The tempest</title>. London,
                    Arden Shakespeare.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Thomas 1983" xml:id="thomas1983">Thomas, L 1983, <title rend="italic"
                        >The youngest science: notes of a medicine-watcher</title>, Viking Press,
                    New York, NY</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
