<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Is this Article a Comic?</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jason Muir <dhq:family>Helms</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Texas Christian University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jason.helms@tcu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jason Helms is an Assistant Professor of English at TCU where he teaches
                            courses on video games, new media, critical theory, and the history of
                            rhetoric. His research focuses on the intersection of rhetoric and
                            technology, particularly in comics, video games, and digital media. His
                            digital monograph, <title rend="italic">Rhizcomics: Rhetoric,
                                Technology, and New Media Composition</title> (University of
                            Michigan Press), will be released in 2016.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000230</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2015-12-23">23 December 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>comics</item>
                        <item> comics as scholarship </item>
                        <item> deleuze</item>
                        <item>critical theory</item>
                        <item> digital humanities </item>
                        <item>defining comics</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2015-11-18" who="EH">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The article begins by asking why comics scholars should create comics as
                    scholarship and traces possible answers through a variety of related fields:
                    English, Rhetoric and Composition, Art, and Games. It then investigates the
                    question of whether this article is itself a comic, by reviewing the history of
                    the conversation about defining comics as an imitation of the Bayeux Tapestry.
                    This tapestry section outlines the major camps, positions, and moves that comics
                    scholars have made. The two major threads are the essentialist camp (with
                    Kunzle, Eisner, McCloud, Harvey, Carrier, and Hayman and Pratt) and the
                    constructivist camp (Meskin and Beaty). The section ends with Bart Beaty’s
                    recent (2012) conceptualization of a comics world that does not need to define
                    individual artifacts as being or not being comics. The article ends with a
                    discussion of the importance of distinguishing definition from
                    conceptualization. Building on Beaty’s conceptualization and Gilles Deleuze’s
                    theory of the concept and critique of representation, it offers applications to
                    the comics world. Finally, it returns to the question of whether or not this
                    article is a comic. The answer (yes, and becoming something else), calls for
                    further interventions throughout the comics world that don’t ask what comics are
                    but what comics might become. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Examines why comics scholars should create comics as scholarship</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Creator's Statement</head>

            <!-- start slipsum code -->

            <ptr style="width:1160px; height:1800px; margin:1em;" type="dhq-annex-embed"
                target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq-annex/000300/index.html"/>


            <p> Creating this article was one of the most challenging and exhilarating academic
                projects I’ve ever taken part in. I had to learn how to do new things every day
                (when I began, I’d never used Adobe Muse before). It also gave me the techniques and
                knowledge to create a book-length digital monograph, <title rend="italic"
                    >Rhizcomics</title> (forthcoming from the University of Michigan Press). In many
                ways, this article was a test-run to teach me how to write the book.</p>
            <p>I began with a script and a few sketches and ideas for interactive elements. I knew I
                wanted to push the boundaries of what could be considered a comic (similar to Chris
                Ware’s <title rend="italic">Building Stories</title> or Richard McGuire’s <title
                    rend="italic">Here</title>, neither of which had been published when I wrote the
                script). I also knew I wanted to engage various strands of DH thought. Typically,
                when I think of DH I think of data and numbers. If I think of visuals at all, it’s
                of graphs and other <q>dry</q> visualizations. However, I’ve also pushed students to
                create compelling visualizations of information and arguments in my classes, and I
                began to realize that drawing is another form of visualization. </p>
            <p>The script led to a storyboard and then a few proof-of-concept web pages designed in
                Adobe Edge Animate. My first experiment was with one of the panels of the Tapestry
                section. It was the first time I had drawn using a stylus, so I wanted to get a feel
                for the look of the finished product. Originally, I planned on including all sorts
                of marginalia throughout the Tapestry section. That plan got scrapped pretty quickly
                when I realized just how long it was going to take to draw with a stylus. </p>
            <p>After getting feedback on the storyboard, script, and single page, I created the
                article over a three-week period during the summer. It was fantastic to be able to
                give the project such sustained focus. Each morning I drew new images (almost all of
                them with pencil and ink on paper) and each afternoon I did the computer work:
                scanning, fine-tuning and coloring in Photoshop and Illustrator, adding
                interactivity in Edge Animate, and doing layout in Muse. Finally, I shared the
                article with a few colleagues to get initial feedback, and I judiciously made just
                about every change they recommended. </p>
            <p>I ended up doing a lot less coding than I had foreseen. Edge Animate allows users
                some space to compose and edit javascript, but Muse generally pushes its users away
                from code entirely. I found this a strange way to work, as I was more comfortable
                with Dreamweaver and with being able to edit the code I create. I have mixed
                feelings about Muse: it’s simple, but it takes a great deal of control away from
                designers. </p>
            <p>I was very excited to play with paraphrase and block quotations in particular. When
                reading scholarship, I often find block quotes to be jarring, pulling me away from
                the author’s thread. On the other hand, I’m often frustrated by paraphrase,
                wondering what the cited author <emph>really</emph> said. The digital comics
                platform gave me a way to have my cake and eat it too, providing paraphrases in the
                speech balloons and offering the full quotation to those who click on the balloons.
                It also helped me avoid the awkwardness of academic prose appearing in speech
                balloons. Speech balloons are meant to represent dialogue, and academic prose is
                rarely that conversational. </p>
            <p>I was surprised to discover the ways my arguments changed as the project coalesced.
                The Deleuzian Comics section in particular was difficult to visualize initially, but
                came together gradually and from many directions at once. The final product falls
                short of what comics might be, but that was also always the plan. I’m hoping it
                pushes someone to make something better (see the other articles in this issue for
                more answers to the question <q>What might comics become?</q>).</p>
            <p>I would like to thank the editors and reviewers at DHQ for their help in making this
                article work. The reviewers offered insightful feedback throughout the process. I am
                amazed that Anastasia Salter and Roger Whitson were able to propose this collection
                and see it through to publication. It was a monster and couldn’t have been completed
                without their careful guidance. Julia Flanders and John Walsh were incredibly
                helpful and forgiving of the technological complexities of this article. It
                certainly provided to be more work for them than most articles would be and I
                sincerely appreciate their efforts. Amanda Booher, Joshua Hilst, and Ben and Meaghan
                Helms read early versions of this article and their feedback proved invaluable.</p>

        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Ball 2008" xml:id="ball2008"> Ball, Cheryl, and Ryan Moeller. <title
                        rend="quotes">Converging the ASS[umptions] between U and ME; Or How New
                        Media can Bridge a scholarly/creative Split in English Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computers and Composition Online</title> (2008). Web.
                    January 29, 2014.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Beaty 2012" xml:id="beaty2012"> Beaty, Bart. <title rend="italic"
                        >Comics Versus Art.</title> Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2012.
                    Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Becker 1959" xml:id="becker1959"> Becker, Stephen D. <title
                        rend="italic">Comic Art in America: A Social History of the Funnies, the
                        Political Cartoons, Magazine Humor, Sporting Cartoons, and Animated
                        Cartoons.</title> New York: Simon and Schuster, 1959. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Carrier 2000" xml:id="carrier2000">Carrier, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Aesthetics of Comics.</title> University Park: Pennsylvania State
                    University Press, 2000. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Couperie 1972" xml:id="couperie1972">Couperie, Pierre. <title
                        rend="quotes">Antecedents and Definition of the Comic Strip.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Art of the Comic Strip.</title> Eds. Walter Herdeg and
                    David Pascal. Zurich: The Graphis Press, 1972. 8-13. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Deleuze 1994a" xml:id="deleuze1994a">Deleuze, Gilles, and Félix
                    Guattari. <title rend="italic">What is Philosophy?</title> New York: Columbia
                    University Press, 1994. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Deleuze 1994b">Deleuze, Gilles. <title rend="italic">Difference and
                        Repetition.</title> New York: Columbia University Press, 1994. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Dosse 2010" xml:id="dosse2010">Dosse, François. Gilles Deleuze &amp;
                    Félix Guattari: <title rend="italic">Intersecting Lives.</title> Tran. Deborah
                    Glassman. New York: Columbia University Press, 2010. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Eisner 2008" xml:id="eisner2008">Eisner, Will. <title rend="italic"
                        >Comics and Sequential Art: Principles and Practices from the Legendary
                        Cartoonist.</title> New York: W.W. Norton, 2008. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Groensteen 2007" xml:id="groensteen2007"> Groensteen, Thierry. <title
                        rend="italic">The System of Comics.</title> Trans. Bart Beaty and Nick
                    Nguyen. Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 2007. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Harey 1994" xml:id="harvey1994">Harvey, Robert C. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Art of the Funnies : An Aesthetic History.</title> Jackson, Miss.:
                    University Press of Mississippi, 1994. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Jay 2002a" xml:id="jay2002a">Jay, Martin. <title rend="quotes">Cultural
                        Relativism and the Visual Turn.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Visual Culture</title> 1.3 (2002): 267-78.
                    Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Jay 2002b" xml:id="jay2002b">Jay, Martin. <title rend="quotes">That
                        Visual Turn.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Visual Culture</title> 1.1 (2002): 87-92.
                    Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Kunzle 1973" xml:id="kunzle1973">Kunzle, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >History of the Comic Strip.</title> Berkeley: University of California
                    Press, 1973. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Macleod and Holdridge 2006" xml:id="macleod2006">Macleod, Katy, and Lin
                    Holdridge. <title rend="italic">Thinking through Art: Reflections on Art as
                        Research.</title> New York: Routledge, 2006. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="McCloud 1994" xml:id="mccloud1994">McCloud, Scott. <title rend="italic"
                        >Understanding Comics: The Invisible Art.</title> New York: HarperPerennial,
                    1994. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Meskin 2007" xml:id="meskin2007">Meskin, Aaron. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Defining Comics?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</title> 65.4
                    (2007): 369-79. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Meskin 2012" xml:id="meskin2012">
                    <title rend="quotes">The Ontology of Comics.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Art of Comics: A Philosophical Approach.</title> Eds.
                    Aaron Meskin and Roy T. Cook. Malden, MA: Wiley-Blackwell, 2012. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Mitchell 1994" xml:id="mitchell1994"> Mitchell, W. J. T. <title
                        rend="italic">Picture Theory: Essays on Verbal and Visual
                        Representation.</title> Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1994.
                    Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Moulthrop 2005" xml:id="moulthrop2005"> Moulthrop, Stuart. <title
                        rend="quotes">After the Last Generation: Rethinking Scholarship in the Days
                        of Serious Play.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Digital Arts and Culture Conference</title>
                    (2005): 208-15. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Ramsay 2011a" xml:id="ramsay2011a">Ramsay, Stephen. <title
                        rend="quotes">On Building.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Stephen Ramsay.</title> January 11, 2011. Web. January 24,
                    2014 .</bibl>

                <bibl label="Ramsay 2011b" xml:id="ramsay2011b"> Ramsay, Stephen. <title
                        rend="quotes">Who's In and Who's Out.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Stephen Ramsay.</title> January 8, 2011. Web. January 24,
                    2014 .</bibl>

                <bibl label="Sim 1991" xml:id="sim1991"> Sim, Dave. <title rend="italic"
                        >Cerebus</title>, Volume 1. Kitchener, ON: Aardvark-Vanaheim, 1991.
                    Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Spiro 2012" xml:id="spiro2012">Spiro, Lisa. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><q>This is Why we Fight</q>: Defining the Values of the Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities.</title> Ed. Matthew K.
                    Gold. Minneapolis: University of Minnessota Press, 2012. Web. January 30,
                    2014</bibl>

                <bibl label="Sullivan 2010" xml:id="sullivan2010"> Sullivan, Graeme. <title
                        rend="italic">Art Practice as Research: Inquiry in Visual Arts.</title>
                    Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications, 2010. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Svensson 2012" xml:id="svensson2012">Svensson, Patrik. <title
                        rend="italic">Beyond the Big Tent.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities.</title> Ed. Matthew K.
                    Gold. Minneapolis: University of Minnessota Press, 2012. Web. January 30, 2014. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Ulmer 1983" xml:id="ulmer1983">Ulmer, Gregory L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Object of Post-Criticism.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Anti-Aesthetic: Essays on Postmodern Culture.</title>
                    Ed. Hal Foster. Port Townsend, WA: Bay Press, 1983. 83-110. Print.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Wesch 2007" xml:id="wesch2007">Wesch, Michael. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Machine is Us/ing Us.</title> YouTube. 2007. Web. May 1, 2013 .</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
