<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
        <title type="article">The Kuzushiji Project: Developing a Mobile Learning Application for
          Reading Early Modern Japanese Texts</title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>Yuta <dhq:family>Hashimoto</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Kyoto University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>yhashimoto1984@gmail.com</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Yuta Hashimoto is a PhD student at Kyoto University studying history of science in
              the 19th century. He used to work as a programmer for three years and is engaging in
              several digital humanities projects in the field of history.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>Yoichi <dhq:family>Iikura</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Osaka University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>iikurayoichi@gmail.com</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Yoichi Iikura is a professor in the Graduate school of Letters at Osaka University,
              where he works on classical Japanese literature in the early modern period.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>Yukio <dhq:family>Hisada</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Osaka University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>fmptsr3431@gmail.com</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Yukio Hisada is a PhD student in the Graduate school of Letters at Osaka University.
              He studies the history of Japanese language in the early modern period.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>SungKook <dhq:family>Kang</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Osaka University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>izaya6013@yahoo.co.jp</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>SungKook Kang is a research fellow in the Graduate school of Letters at Osaka
              University, where he works on classical Japanese literature in the early modern
              period.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>Tomoyo <dhq:family>Arisawa</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Osaka University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>t.arisawa212@gmail.com</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Tomoyo Arisawa is a PhD student in the Graduate school of Letters at Osaka
              University. She is studying on classical Japanese literature in the early modern
              period.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
          <dhq:author_name>Daniel <dhq:family>Kobayashi-Better</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Osaka University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>wappuccino@gmail.com</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Daniel Kobayashi-Better is a PhD student in the Graduate school of Letters at Osaka
              University. He studies Japanese linguistics and the history of linguistics.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000281</idno>
        <idno type="volume">011</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2016-11-29">29 November 2016</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability>
          <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Japanese studies</item>
            <item>mobile development</item>
            <item>mobile learning</item>
            <item>kuzushiji</item>
            <item>hentaigana</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
      <change who="YH" when="2016-03-15">Encoded document</change>
      <change who="YH" when="2016-10-03">Revised following reviewers' feedbacks</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
        <p>Learning how to read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> is the most important
          skill for studying the history of pre-modern Japan and classical Japanese literature.
          However, the difficulty of acquiring this skill has prevented both scholars and amateurs
          from other fields and countries to work on classical Japanese writings. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> project is an attempt to provide accessible resources
          and training on mobile devices for learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>,
          and available for free. KuLA, the learning app we developed, has already been downloaded
          more than 36,000 times since its release in February 2016. In this paper, we describe our
          background, aims, and approach of our project, as well as the implementation of KuLA.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
        <p>Describes the <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> project, which aims to develop a
          mobile learning application for reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>The 20th century saw drastic changes in writing systems in many East-Asian countries;
          Mongolia, for instance, introduced the Cyrillic script in 1941 to replace its traditional
          script under the political pressure of the Soviet Union. Vietnam switched its public
          writing system to a Latin-based one from its traditional Chinese-based writing
          system, Chữ nôm. Malaysia also introduced a Latin-based script (<foreign>Rumi</foreign>)
          at the beginning of the 20th century. Since the skill of reading historical writings is
          directly linked to familiarity with past writing systems, these countries must equally
          suffer from difficulties in handing down past knowledge written in historical resources to
          their younger generations. <note> In Mongol, for instance, there was an attempt from 1991
            to 1994 to reintroduce the traditional alphabet but failed in the face of popular
            resistance <ptr target="#svantesson2005" loc="34"/>. </note> In the case of Japan,
            <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>, a general term for classical
          calligraphic renderings of Japanese characters which used to be common for both publishing
          and handwriting before the end of 19th century, has become an obstacle to accessing
          knowledge recorded in the past.</p>

        <p>The current Japanese writing system consists of two types of characters: 46 syllabic
            <foreign xml:lang="ja">kana</foreign> and thousands of logographic <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign>, which are adapted Chinese characters. The modern system
          has been developed since the Meiji Restoration of 1868, and in this process Japanese
          society obsoleted some types of characters and writing styles that used to be common
          before the Meiji period. First, pre-modern Japanese had the option to use different
          characters other than the current <foreign xml:lang="ja">kana</foreign> to denote a single
          syllable. For instance, a <foreign xml:lang="ja">kana</foreign> “す” (pronounced "su") had
          more than five alternative characters (see Figure 1). These variants of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kana</foreign> are called <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign>,
          which were officially obsoleted by the amended education law announced in 1900. Second, in
          most publications and writings before the Meiji era, <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign> had been written mostly in cursive forms that appear today only in
          calligraphy (See Figure 2). As letterpress printing had replaced wood-block printing after
          the Meiji period, this cursive style of writing gradually declined. <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kuzushiji</foreign> is a general term (including hentaigana and cursive <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign>) for characters that are not used today. <note> Some
            people use the word <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> referring to only cursive
              <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign> characters. For simplicity, we use <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> as an inclusive word for <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> and cursive <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign>.</note>
        </p>
        <figure>
          <head> Five hentaigana characters for a syllable "す". </head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head> A comparison of a <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> and a modern Japanese
            type character. Both represent the same character 前, "front" in English. </head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
        </figure>

        <p>Through the process of modernization in the 20th century, modern Japanese (except trained
          experts) have lost the ability to read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. A
          scholar of Japanese classical literature Mitsutoshi Nakano estimates in his book that even
          in a humanities faculty less than ten percent of the faculty members can read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>
          <ptr target="#nakano2011"/>. Robert Campbell, a scholar of Japanese classical literature
          originally from the US, summarizes this situation: <cit>
            <quote rend="inline" source="http://www.toppan.co.jp/news/2015/07/newsrelease150703_2.html"> We read characters in order to learn about Japan in the pre-modern
              era. But ironically, Japanese lost the skill to read these characters in exchange for
              the modernization they have achieved for the last 150 years. Those who rely on printed
              text can learn only small portions of the past Japan. Contrary to European and
              American countries, Japanese have lost the abilities to go back freely to their own
              historical landscapes.<note> Translation by the authors.</note>
            </quote>
            <ref target="http://www.toppan.co.jp/news/2015/07/newsrelease150703_2.html">http://www.toppan.co.jp/news/2015/07/newsrelease150703_2.html</ref>
          </cit> As Campbell implies here, the skill of reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> is deeply connected to the ability to access past knowledge;
            The <title rend="italic">Kokusho Sōmokuroku</title> (<title rend="italic">General
            Catalog of National Books</title>) <ptr target="#morisue1963"/>, a Japanese reference
          work for books written in Japanese in the pre-modern era, lists more than 450,000 entries,
          most of which are written in <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. It is said that
          the ratio of transcribed books among these entries is less than 1%. <note> This is a mere
            estimation since there is no reliable statistics for this topic, however.</note> So
          reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> is a must-have skill for studying
          historical writings written in Japanese. </p>

        <p>Since the curriculum of Japanese compulsory education doesn't include training for
          reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>, this skill has become the exclusive
          ability of scholars of Japanese literature and history, who have access to the original
          materials with few exceptions. Scholars from these two fields have made a lot of effort to
          teach the skill of reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> to the general
          public, by means of publishing textbooks and delivering face-to-face lectures; since 2010
          at least nineteen textbooks for teaching <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> have
          been published. However, we believe that these traditional modes of teaching have
          limitations in terms of availability. In fact, there are groups of people inside and
          outside academia with keen interests in learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> and reading Japanese classical writings whose needs are not
          satisfied by these traditional pedagogical tools, as we point out later in detail. In
          order to appeal to these groups, some new methods that make use of modern digital media
          must be developed.</p>

        <p>What role can digital humanities play in developing such methods? Digital Humanities has
          an apparent advantage that other fields of humanities do not have: direct access to both
          classical writings and digital technology. In other words, digital humanities has a
          potential ability to offer learning materials of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> to the general public efficiently with the help of digital media.
          Also, since the loss of the ability to read written historical resources in the modern era
          is not a phenomenon specific to Japan, building a model for teaching an obsolete or dead
          writing system with the help of digital media could possibly contribute to the humanities
          in a wider area of the world. This would make digital humanities even more important in
          the general field of humanities. </p>

        <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> project, which we will describe in this
          paper, is an interdisciplinary project started in 2015 through the cooperation of scholars
          of Japanese literature, linguistics and digital humanities. It
          aims to build a mobile learning application for providing accessible
          resources and training for reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. We call our
            app KuLA (<foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> learning application), which is
          already available for free both on the App Store and Google Play <ptr target="#hashimoto2016"/>. In this paper, we will describe the target and approach of
          our project, the features KuLA provides, and the results we achieved after launching KuLA.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Who are Interested in <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kuzushiji</foreign>?</head>
        <p> As we mentioned in the previous section, there are groups who have keen interest in
            <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> but not satisfied with the traditional
          approach of teaching. To be more precise, there is a growing need recently for the skill
          of reading kuzusjiji among the following three groups: </p>
        <p> (1) Scholars of Japanese studies outside Japan, who used to rely mostly on transcribed
          or translated works for their research. Thanks to the recent progress of the digitization
          of cultural heritage materials in Japan, they now have access to a large number of digital
          images of pre-modern Japanese texts without having to visit Japan. Because of this change,
          acquiring the ability to read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> has become quite
          important to eliminating the only barrier that prevents them from using these resources
          and efforts are being made to expand <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> literacy.
          For instance, Laura Moretti, who teaches pre-modern and early modern Japanese literature
          at Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge, has held a summer school on Japanese
          paleography for reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> every year since 2014
            <ptr target="#moretti2014"/>. We can see similar classes and workshops take places in
          universities from all over the world: Oxford, Paris, Berlin, Heidelberg, Rome, Chicago,
          Pennsylvania, Michigan etc. </p>
        <p> (2) Scholars from different fields, especially from natural sciences. It may seem odd
          that scientists read these classical writings, but there are some fields that need to
          investigate written historical resources to elucidate past phenomena that cannot be
          observed directly. A good example of such a field is seismology. Since the instrumental
          recordings of earthquakes in Japan began only after the end of the 19th century, studies
          of past earthquakes have to rely on written historical records to a considerable extent.
          For this reason some Japanese seismologists read classical writings written with <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> for their research with the help of humanities
          scholars. There is even an academic association dedicated to historical earthquake recordings.<note>
            <ref target="http://sakuya.ed.shizuoka.ac.jp/rzisin/">http://sakuya.ed.shizuoka.ac.jp/rzisin/</ref></note> Since the great earthquake and
          tsunami that struck the  Tōhoku area in 2011, Japanese seismologists have become more
          interested in reading these historical recordings. </p>
        <p>(3) The younger generation who are interested in Japanese classical writings. In
          particular, there has recently been a growing number of Japanese female history buffs who
          have become interested in history through playing video games or watching TV dramas based
          on historical materials. These young females are often called reki-jo (歴女), which can
          literally be translated to <soCalled>history girls</soCalled>.<note> See <ref target="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=125898462">http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=125898462</ref></note> The most
          popular game among them, Touken Ranbu, a web browser game developed by Nitroplus and DMM,
          has gained about 1.5 million users as of February 2016 (since its launch in January 2015).
            <note> The website of the Touken Ranbu: <ref target="http://www.dmm.com/netgame/feature/tohken.html">http://www.dmm.com/netgame/feature/tohken.html</ref></note> The purpose of this game
          is to defeat evil forces using legendary Japanese swords, which are depicted as attractive
          young men. It’s often reported that the players of Touken Ranbu have formed long lines to
          see actual Japanese swords displayed in history museums. <note> Japan Times reports this
            news: <ref target="http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2016/01/22/national/fukuoka-museums-famed-14th-century-sword-finds-renewed-fans-thanks-online-game/">http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2016/01/22/national/fukuoka-museums-famed-14th-century-sword-finds-renewed-fans-thanks-online-game/</ref></note>
          Some of them are also interested in learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> in
          order to read historical books on Japanese swords. In fact, when we announced the launch
          of our app on Twitter, we found that about 30% of the total 1750 users who retweeted our
          tweet were players of Touken Ranbu. <note> See hit tweet: <ref target="https://twitter.com/yuta1984/status/700003313454985218">https://twitter.com/yuta1984/status/700003313454985218</ref></note>
        </p>
        <p>These three groups have different backgrounds and needs, but still have a common
          interest: to read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. However, the traditional
          methods of teaching based on printed textbooks and face-to-face lectures cannot adequately
          help these groups achieve their goals because of geographical or institutional
          limitations. In this regard, mobile devices including smartphones and tablets, which are
          spread all over the world and can be used at any time according to the owner's needs, are
          the best alternative media. According to a survey conducted in 2014 by the Ministry of
          Internal Affairs and Communications, 62.3% of Japanese own smartphones.<ptr target="#mic2014"/></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Previous Works and Our Approach</head>
        <p>A number of textbooks for learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> have been
          written. However, there are not so many options available in digitally. Probably the first
          one among them to be released is Kanaclassic developed in 1999, which demonstrates the
          strokes of <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> in video and animations <ptr target="#yang1999"/>. The National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics
          (NINJAL) provides the images of three volumes from <title rend="italic">the Tale of
            Genji</title> as a teaching material on its website <ptr target="#ninjal2013"/>; The
          images are accompanied with their transcriptions so that users can practice how to read
            <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. The Hentaigana App <ptr target="#ucla2015"/>, which was developed through the collaboration work of UCLA and Waseda University, is
          the first iOS/Android app for learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign>. The
          Hentaigana app offers a flashcards-like feature that enables users to memorize the 323
          types of <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> it includes quickly, with beautifully
          designed background pictures. </p>
        <p>Our basic standpoint is that the learning process of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> goes through multiple stages, and each stage requires different
          learning materials and training. Thus our approach is a more complex than those focused on
          a specific ability. Based on experience of teaching <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> in university classes for years, we reached the conclusion that the
          skill of reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> is composed of the following
          three elements, which are acquired in different stages of learning:</p>
        <list>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Basic knowledge of character shapes.</hi> This is the basis for
            recognizing both <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> and cursive <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign>. Most of the learners of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> start their learning process by memorizing a table that lists
              <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign>. This ability is efficiently trained
            through flashcard-based exercises, as in the Hentaigana app, which takes this approach.
            In this regard, however, it is important to memorize characters in conjunction with
            other characters since the shapes of characters change in accordance with the strokes
            with which the handwriting is performed. Thus the teaching materials for this ability
            should contain word-level examples of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> as well
            as those of single characters.</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">A decent amount of exercises for reading actual texts.</hi>
            Memorizing character shapes is, of course, not enough to be able to read <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. Learners need to integrate knowledge of each
            character organically in order to get the meaning of a single sentence, just like they
            do when they read texts written in a foreign language. Also, learners will often have to
            make a guess as to the meaning from the context of a phrase and they may not have clear
            background knowledge on the text when some part of it that they are reading is damaged
            or when the handwriting in it is not clear. These abilities are developed mostly through
            reading actual texts.</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Social connections with mentors and fellows.</hi> This is the
            hardest thing to find when you learn <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> outside
            the faculties of Japanese literature or history. Even if you have mastered the abilities
            described above, you will be very likely to encounter some characters completely
            illegible to you. This is the sort of moment when you need someone to ask for help,
            which you could find easily if you belonged to a faculty of Japanese literature or
            history. The previous works for learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>
            don't seem to address this difficulty, but the lack of mentors and fellows to give you
            help and advice can significantly delay the learning process and undermine the
            motivation of a learner.</item>
        </list>
        <p>On the other hand, it is not realistic to make the app cover all the books published in
          the pre-modern era, since characters and writing styles vary across time. Thus we limited
          our target to writings from the Edo period (1603-1868). This limitation will not be a
          large hindrance to our purpose because it is said that 90% of the classical writings that
          still remain today are from this period <ptr target="#nakano2011"/>.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Features of the KuLA</head>
        <p>According to the approach described in the previous section, we made our app from the
          following three modules:</p>
        <p>(1) The characters module:</p>
        <p>This module implements flashcard-like features for acquiring the ability to recognize the
          character shapes of the basic <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> characters. It
          includes sample images and comments for 102 <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign>
          and 176 <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign> characters. <note> The number of characters
            included in KuLA may seem to be too small, since there are thousand of kinds of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kanji</foreign> characters used in Japanese texts. However, there is a
            deviation in the frequency of characters. For instance, <title rend="italic">Ugetsu
              Monogatari</title> (<title rend="italic">Tales of Moonlight and Rain</title>), one of
            the most important Japanese fiction of the 18th century published in 1776, contains 1996
            types of characters. But 82% of the whole text can be written with only 200 characters.
            In order to not perplex beginners by giving too much information, we decided to select
            only these frequently-appearing characters. </note> These characters are selected
          according to a frequency analysis of characters we conducted on the Taikei Hombun
          database, a text corpus made from Japanese classical works run by the National Institute
          of Japanese Literature (NIJL).<note> Unfortunately the Taikei Hombun database was
            suspended after 29 January 2016.</note> The module is divided into 14 lessons and each
          lesson is made up of 19-24 characters. Each character has several sample images both in
          single-character forms and in multiple-character forms (See Figure 3). The total 3,000
          sample images were taken from the NIJS's digital collection of classical Japanese works.<note>
            <ref target="http://www.nijl.ac.jp/pages/database/">http://www.nijl.ac.jp/pages/database/</ref></note> By browsing these examples the
          user is supposed to memorize how to read each <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign>
          or <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. This module is also accompanied with a test
          feature to check if the user can correctly recognize the characters, where a randomly
          selected character image is shown and the user is required to input how to read the
          character in the text field below the image (See Figure 4). Then Shimimaru, the mascot of
          our app, will tell whether the answer given by the user is correct or not.<note> The
            design of Shimimaru is taken from silverfish (shimi, in Japanese), an insect notorious
            for damaging old books by eating paper.</note> After finishing each test, Shimimaru
          gives a comment on how good the user did in the session.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>The character module. Left: single character examples for a <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> of "す". Right: its word-level examples.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head>The test feature in the character module. User is supposed to make a guess on how to
            read the character shown above (in this case the answer is"さ"). </head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>(2) The reading module:</p>
        <p>This module is intended for acquiring fluency of reading <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> through reading actual classical texts. The module implements a
          reader function and currently contains the following three works as learning materials:
          (1) <title rend="italic">Hōjōki</title>, a classical essay written in the 13th century by
          Kamo no Chōmei. The included version is taken from an 18th century publication of the
          text. (2) <title rend="italic">Nazo nazo Esugoroku</title>, a sugoroku (a kind of Japanese
          board game) with pictures published in 1886. (3) <title rend="italic">Arami Meizukushi
            Kōshu</title>, a catalogue of Japanese swords published in 1735. In order to show the
          text in the small displays of mobile devices, most images are divided and cropped (see
          Figure 5). All the learning materials are accompanied with transcriptions which are hidden
          by default, so that the user can check whether he or she can read the original text
          correctly by showing its transcriptions. </p>
        <figure>
          <head>The reading module. Left: <title rend="italic">Hōjōki</title>. Right: <title rend="italic">Nazo Nazo Esugoroku</title>.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>(3) The community module:</p>
        <p>The aim of this module is to let the users communicate with each other and exchange
          information on learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. When a user encounters
          an illegible section while reading a classical text outside the app, she or he can take up
          to four photos of the section by using the device's camera and posting a question with
          these photos attached (see Figure 6). Other users can browse the photos and add a short
          comment on the question. In order to prevent vandalism by anonymous users, accessing this
          module requires authentication with Facebook (authentications with Google and Twitter are
          also planned).</p>
        <figure>
          <head>The community module. You can take photos of illegible parts of texts and ask
            questions to other users.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
        </figure>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Technical Considerations</head>
        <p>Through the development phase we have made use of open source software and cloud-based
          services that offer free plans with limited usages. These products and services made it
          possible to build KuLA with a very small cost. </p>
        <p>One of the major challenges in building KuLA was the collection of example <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. Each use case included in KuLA contains the image
          data of a character and metadata such as the title of the source document, how to read the
          character, etc. How can one collect 3,000 images of characters with metadata efficiently
          from digitized historical writings? For this task we developed a simple cloud
          server-client system which consists of a web server and a Chrome extension (a type of
          plugin that runs on the Google Chrome web browser). The Chrome extension we developed
          enables users to crop an arbitrary region in an open tab and input metadata on the
          image (see Figure 7). The cropped image and metadata are automatically sent to the web
          server that we built with Ruby on Rails running on Heroku<note>
            <ref target="https://www.heroku.com/">https://www.heroku.com/</ref></note>, a cloud
          Platform-as-a-Service run by Salesforce.com. The web server stores the metadata into the
          relational database on Heroku and transfers the uploaded image to Cloudinary<note>
            <ref target="http://cloudinary.com/">http://cloudinary.com/</ref></note>, a cloud image
          storage service that provides the REST API to store and manipulate image data. The image
          and its metadata immediately become accessible on the Web, so that every team member can
          share the progress of the image collection.<note> You can browse the list of examples we
            have collected in the following link: <ref target="https://yourei-collector.herokuapp.com/characters/">https://yourei-collector.herokuapp.com/characters/</ref>.</note></p>
        <figure>
          <head>How a character image is selected with the Chrome extension we developed.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Another challenging task was to have our app run both on iOS and Android; these two
          operation systems require developers code in two different languages: Objective-C (Swift)
          and Java. Building a single app in two different languages was not acceptable in terms of
          cost and time. So as a workaround we built our app with Ionic<note>
            <ref target="http://ionicframework.com/">http://ionicframework.com/</ref></note>, an
          HTML5 mobile framework based on AngularJS<note>
            <ref target="https://angularjs.org/">https://angularjs.org/</ref></note> and Apache Cordova<note>
            <ref target="https://cordova.apache.org/ ">https://cordova.apache.org/ </ref></note>.
          Ionic offers the mobile-optimized UI components that make it possible to build and test a
          mobile app quickly, as well as the APIs to interact with the device’s native functions
          such as camera and file storage. You can build an Ionic app with only HTML, CSS, and
          JavaScript without coding in the native languages required by both operating systems. So
          we could generate distributions both for iOS and Android from a single source code.</p>
        <p>In order to implement the community features we needed a server for receiving and
          delivering user messages. However, the cost of building and maintaining a server
          application cannot be ignored for a small team like us. For this we adopted
              Firebase<note><ref target="https://www.firebase.com/">https://www.firebase.com/</ref></note>, a cloud-based backend service for mobile and
          web applications. The user messages are stored in a key-value store controlled by Firebase
          and are synchronized with clients in real time. Also, the image data uploaded by users are
          transferred to Cloudinary and delivered to other users.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Download Statistics and User Feedback</head>
        <p> Since our aim in this project is to provide learning opportunities of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> to a wide range of the public, we set a target of
          getting at least 10,000 downloads in total. KuLA was released on both the App Store and
          Google Play on February 18, 2016. One of the authors announced the launch of our app on
          his Twitter account. <note>
            <ref target="https://twitter.com/yuta1984/status/700003313454985218">https://twitter.com/yuta1984/status/700003313454985218</ref></note> The reactions to
          the announcement were immediate and massive; this tweet was retweeted more than 1,700
          times and favorited by 2,000 users in three days after the launch. On March 16, the total
          number of downloads reached 10,000. Thus our initial goal was achieved within the first
          month after the release. As of October 10, KuLA has been downloaded a total of 36,649
          times: 19,400 on the AppStore and 17,249 on Google Play. Although most downloads have been
          made from Japan, there has been a small but constant number of downloads from other
          countries: the United States (214 downloads), Korea (168 downloads), Germany (47
          downloads), and Italy (44 downloads). We received a message from an Italian scholar who
          teaches Japanese paleology at Sapienza University of Rome that some of his students use
          the KuLA for their self-studies. <note> The message was posted on a Facebook group
            “Digital Humanities in Japan” on February 29, 2016. See <ref target="https://www.facebook.com/groups/758758500904522/permalink/913511928762511/">
              https://www.facebook.com/groups/758758500904522/permalink/913511928762511/</ref>
          </note>
        </p>

        <p>The user reviews on our app are mostly positive so far. The average ratings of our app
          are 4.5/5.0 (total 43 reviews) on App Store, and 4.6/5.0 (total 93 reviews) on Google
          Play. Also, there are hundreds of tweets made by users about our app on Twitter. <note>You
            can find tweets about our app by searching on Twitter with keywords like "くずし字"
            (kuzushiji) and "アプリ" (application).</note>
        </p>

        <p> Another metric that indicates how users reacted to our app is the retention rate, the
          ratio of users who launched the app after installing it over time. Figure 9 shows the
          retention rate of KuLA during May 1-31, 2016. <note> The reason we chose May 1-31 is
            because the download count in this period is larger than in the others we
            recorded</note> In this period, about 2,900 users downloaded KuLA, 35.4% of them
          launched it one month after they downloaded it, and 9.55% are still using after three
          months. The retention rate after five months went down to 2.65%. Are these rates high or
          low? Localytics, a business analytics company that specializes in mobile markets, provided
          benchmarks for apps in the Business, Education and Technology category based on their
          analysis of more than 37,000 apps. <note> See <ref target="https://www.localytics.com/lp/cheat-sheet-business-education-technology-app-benchmarks-h1-2016/">https://www.localytics.com/lp/cheat-sheet-business-education-technology-app-benchmarks-h1-2016/</ref></note>
          According to their benchmarks, the average monthly retention rate of apps in this category
          for the first three months is 32%, 21%, and 15%. Thus the retention rate of KuLA in May
          1-31 is higher than the average in the first month, but lower in the next two months. This
          means that there is still work to be done to improve the support of users' long-term
          learning. </p>
        <figure>
          <head>Retention rate of the users who downloaded KuLA during May 1-31.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
        </figure>

        <p>Also, some criticisms and suggestions on our approach have been also posted on Twitter.
          Yoshiki Takao, a historian of early modern Japan who has written several textbooks for
          learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>, stated that the test feature of our
          app gives too much focus on the user's ability to decide how to read a single character,
          which is not appropriate because there are cases where you have to decide how to read a
          character based on its context. <note>
            <ref target="https://twitter.com/yoshiki_takao/status/708106622317363200">
              https://twitter.com/yoshiki_takao/status/708106622317363200</ref></note> Some users
          also suggested that our app should implement a feature to allow users to trace the strokes
          of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> characters by moving their fingers, so that
          they can memorize the shapes of the characters efficiently using their fingers and eyes.
          Both the criticism and suggestion we received have reasonable points. We are planning to
          include improvements to reflect these criticisms and suggestions in the next release.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>User Engagement in the Community Module</head>
        <p>As described earlier, the aim of the community module is to enable online communications
          and mutual support for learning among users. We shall examine how much user engagement has
          actually taken place for the last seven months after the release. From February to October
          2016, 68 posts and 233 comments on these posts have been created by total 60 users. Out of
          68 posts, 6 are just greetings but another 61 posts (91%) are questions with attached
          images of <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. And 57 (85%) have recieved at least
          one comment from other users. The average time that it takes for each post to recieve a
          first comment is 43.4 hours. Thus users can have a high expectation that they will get a
          response within a few days if you post a question. </p>
        <p>Here are some examples of actual user comments. A user named Takushi Misoi, who is trying
          to read a manuscript about a traditional festival that has been held in his hometown for
          ages, posted the pictures of some part of the manuscript that he was unable to read by
          himself (see Figure 9). Four other users responded to his question and gave suggestions on
          how to read these parts. Through the 21 messages exchanged among these users, his question
          has almost been resolved. Another user Hitomi Kinto posted a picture of a hanging roll on
          which some waka poem is written with <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>, saying
          she couldn’t read this poem at all. One user soon pointed out that the poem was one first
          composed in <foreign xml:lang="ja">Teijiin-Uta-Awase (亭子院歌合)</foreign>, a historical waka
          poetry contest held in 913. <figure>
            <head>Left: the question posted by Takushi Misoi. Right: comments by other users on the
              post.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>The kinds of communications as we have envisioned are certainly taking place in the
          community module. However, considering the download count of KuLA for the last seven
          months, we have to say that the amount of engagement by users is still small and there
          remains a lot to be improved in this feature. Our current hypothesis is that the lack of
          mechanisms to motivate users is preventing further participation from users. In the next
          update planned for the end of 2016, we will add some additional features to make up for
          this flaw: voting on comments, a leaderboard based on voting, push notifications, etc. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>In this paper, we described the background, approach, method and result of our project to
          build a mobile app for learning <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. The number of
          downloads our app has received in a month clearly shows that there is a great deal of
          interest in Japanese society about its obsolete writing system: <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>. A user named Megumi Kato says in her review of our app (which she
          posted on Google Play) that she was hoping to learn <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> but didn’t know what to do at all. While traditional humanities
          have failed to offer people like her opportunities to learn <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign>, our mobile app could provide her with a starting point for
          learning, available for free. Also, the high ratings given by users of our app indicate
          that our complex approach for teaching <foreign xml:lang="ja">kuzushiji</foreign> meets
          their requirements quite well, although there is still room for improvement in our
          approach and implementation (as shown in the criticisms and suggestions made by users of
          our app). One of the major advantages of developing a learning material as a mobile app is
          that the developer can continue to respond to the users’ needs by continuing to update the
          app. </p>
        <p>As mentioned earlier, there are many countries (especially in East Asia) whose
          traditional writing systems have been changed or completely replaced with other systems in
          the process of modernization. Although further investigation is needed, It is very likely
          that people in these countries share the same interests in learning their historical
          writing systems. Making a survey of the situations in these countries and developing
          applications for the support of learning their traditional writing systems may be an
          important task for digital humanities, which is becoming a global academic discipline.</p>
      </div>

    </body>
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>, and delete dummy record below. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->
        <bibl xml:id="hashimoto2016" label="Hashimoto et al 2016"> Hashimoto, Y. et al. <title rend="quotes">KuLA: The Kuzushiji Learning Application</title> (2016). Available at:
            <ref target="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=yuta.hashimoto.kula">
            https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=yuta.hashimoto.kula (Android) </ref>, <ref target="https://itunes.apple.com/app/kuzushi-zi-xue-xi-zhi-yuanapurikula/id1076911000">
            https://itunes.apple.com/app/kuzushi-zi-xue-xi-zhi-yuanapurikula/id1076911000 (iOS)
          </ref>. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mic2014" label="MIC 2014"> Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications,
          Japan. <title rend="quotes">A survey on the usage time and activities of information
            media</title> [Japanese] (2014). Available at <ref target="http://www.soumu.go.jp/iicp/chousakenkyu/data/research/survey/telecom/2014/h25mediariyou_3report.pdf">
            http://www.soumu.go.jp/iicp/chousakenkyu/data/research/survey/telecom/2014/h25mediariyou_3report.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="moretti2014" label="Moretti 2014"> Moretti, L. <title rend="quotes">Reading
              <foreign xml:lang="ja">hentaigana</foreign> and kuzushiji Manual</title> (2014).
          Available at <ref target="http://wakanedo.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Edo-no-kakikotoba-2014-hentaigana-kuzushiji-Manual-1.pdf">
            http://wakanedo.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Edo-no-kakikotoba-2014-hentaigana-kuzushiji-Manual-1.pdf
          </ref>. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="morisue1963" label="Morisue et al. 1963"> Morisue, Y. et al. <title rend="italic">Kokusho Sōmokuroku</title> (<title rend="italic">General Catalog of
            National Books</title>). Iwanami Shoten, Tokyo (1963). </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="nakano2011" label="Nakano 2011"> Nakano, M. <title rend="italic">Wahon No
            Susume</title>. Iwanami Shoten, Tokyo (2011). </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ninjal2013" label="NINJAL 2013"> The National Institute for Japanese Language
          and Linguistics <title rend="italic">『源氏物語』画像（桐壷・須磨・柏木）</title> (2014). Available at <ref target="http://dglb01.ninjal.ac.jp/lcgenji_image/">http://dglb01.ninjal.ac.jp/lcgenji_image/</ref>. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="svantesson2005" label="Svantesson et al 2005"> Svantesson, J. et al. <title rend="italic">The Phonology of Mongolian</title>. Oxford University Press, Oxford
          (2005). </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ucla2015" label="UCLA and Waseda 2014"> UCLA and Waseda University <title rend="italic">The Hentaigana App</title> (2015). <ref target="http://wakanedo.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Edo-no-kakikotoba-2014-hentaigana-kuzushiji-Manual-1.pdf">
            http://wakanedo.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Edo-no-kakikotoba-2014-hentaigana-kuzushiji-Manual-1.pdf
          </ref>. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yang1999" label="Yang 1999"> Yang, X. <title rend="italic">Kanaclassic: An
            Electronic Guide to Learning Classical Japanese Kana Writing</title>. Columbia
          University New York (1999). </bibl>
      </listBibl>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>