<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">TypeWright: An Experiment in Participatory Curation</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Alan <dhq:family>Bilansky</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>alanbilansky@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Alan Bilansky is completing an MS in Library and Information Science at
                            the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, after earning a PhD in
                            Rhetoric and Democracy form Penn State. At the U of I he has taught
                            undergraduates in social aspects of information technology, and also
                            consults with faculty. He is currently at work studying the
                            institutional, social and material history of databases like EEBO and
                            ECCO and how they affect scholarly practice.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000220</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2015-12-23">23 December 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>English literature</item>
                        <item>curation</item>
                        <item>OCR</item>
                        <item>digital texts</item>
                        <item>crowdsourcing</item>
                        <item>ECCO</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2015-08-22">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>TypeWright (housed on the website 18thConnect) is an experiment in participatory
                    curation; it asks volunteers to make texts more findable, useable, and
                    trustable. These contributions are not without rewards to the volunteer.
                    TypeWright is part of some important trends in digitization, addressing two
                    problems of digital texts: flawed optical character recognition (OCR) and the
                    complicated terrain of intellectual property.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A review of TypeWright, an experiment in participatory curation housed on the
                    website 18thConnect.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The eighteenth century was a golden age when print first came to the crowd, and
                TypeWright brings crowdsourcing to the texts of that century. An experiment in
                participatory curation, it asks volunteers to make texts more findable, useable, and
                trustable. These contributions are not without rewards to the volunteer. TypeWright
                is part of some important trends in digitization, and we might say it is part of a
                growing movement, addressing two problems of digital texts: flawed optical character
                recognition (OCR) and the complicated terrain of intellectual property. </p>
            <p>TypeWright is housed on 18thConnect, one of four sister sites, all coordinated
                through a group called the Advanced Research Consortium (ARC). Since 18thConnect
                launched in 2010 its director, Laura Mandell, and editorial boards are actively
                reviewing projects and collecting metadata to make online objects discoverable and
                collectable through their site. The other three sites are NINES (Networked
                Infrastructure for Nineteenth-Century Electronic Scholarship, both an organization
                and Website), the Renaissance English Knowledgebase (REKn), and the Medieval
                Electronic Scholarly Alliance (MESA). The first of these, launched in 2005, is
                NINES. NINES allows federated searching of 124 online scholarly projects, such as
                the Whitman Archive and the Rossetti Archive. Its editorial boards review these
                projects and then the site ingests the metadata. Scholars logging into NINES can
                search all these resources at once, and collect results into <q>exhibits</q> that
                can be used in teaching and scholarship. In doing so, scholars are volunteering
                their labor to a good cause. Collex, an open-source collections-and-exhibits
                builder, was originally designed to store the data from the searches and the
                exhibits created and to use it to improve search results. For an excellent review of
                the search and exhibit functions of Collex, turn to Amy Earhart’s reflections on
                using NINES in a college course <ptr target="#earhart2010"/>. </p>

            <figure>
                <head> The four sister Websites belonging to the Advanced Research Consortium. </head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            </figure>

            <p>ARC's other three sites run on the same software and have the same editorial and
                publishing model. <ref target="http://www.mesa-medieval.org/">MESA</ref> (the
                Medieval Electronic Scholarly Alliance) came online in 2013. REKn, the Renaissance
                English Knowledgebase, has yet to launch. After launching in 2010, 18thConnect, the
                focus of this review, is actively reviewing and collecting metadata to make online
                objects discoverable and collectable through their site. </p>
            <p>Anyone can create a login to 18thConnect, and will find tabbed links to the functions
                of Collex, including <q>Search</q>, <q>Exhibits</q>, and <q>Peer Review</q> (where
                editors can submit online resources for inclusion in searches here). There is also a
                link to <q>TypeWright</q>.</p>
            <p>Understanding TypeWright requires a brief detour through the history of Eighteenth
                Century Collections Online (ECCO). It was created by Gale Cengage, scanning
                microfilm images of texts published in Great Britain between 1701 and 1800. Although
                comprehensiveness is not possible, ECCO has a substantial collection of 155,000
                texts from that century printed in Great Britain and America. I know researchers who
                have begged, borrowed, and occasionally stolen access to it if they weren’t lucky
                enough to work for a school that subscribes to it. In the world of large collections
                of primary texts, ECCO is dwarfed by behemoths like Google Book Search, but it makes
                up for size with its relative accuracy in metadata such as author and date of
                publication. At the same time, two other publishers created similar collections:
                Chadwyck-Healey (later ProQuest) created Early English Books Online (EEBO),
                collecting images of British texts published before 1800; and Readex created Early
                American Imprints (Evans for short), a digital collection of American texts before
                1819. All of these collections consisted of high-quality scans of microform (not
                always of high quality to begin with).</p>
            <p>Transcriptions of these images were created by optical character recognition (OCR),
                mainly for the purpose of searching to locate images of the pages. OCR is prone to
                errors, particularly with structural information (title pages, chapter headings,
                etc.) and notoriously with features of eighteenth-century printing like the long S. </p>
            <p>The more accurate our transcriptions are, the more we can trust our searches to
                locate texts to read, and the more we can trust algorithmic approaches to a body of
                texts. </p>
            <p>The Text Creation Partnership is a consortium of more than 150 academic libraries
                that started at the University of Michigan and Oxford University, with the mission
                of producing human-keyed, accurate transcriptions of texts digitized in EEBO, Evans,
                and ECCO. Work continues on EEBO texts, but has ceased after transcribing 4,977
                texts from Early American Imprints and 2,331 ECCO texts. The page images from
                microform remain the property of the publisher, but the transcriptions belong to the
                institutional members of the TCP, and after five years they pass into the public
                domain. </p>
            <p>TypeWright aims to continue this effort by using scholarly volunteers to check and
                correct the OCR transcriptions. Scholars can work through the OCR transcripts of
                ECCO texts that the TCP could not get to, making the texts more useable and more
                available. A similar project, to correct OCR transcripts of the EEBO texts, is to be
                launched on REKn. </p>
            <p>An example will demonstrate how this works: Professor Y, a scholar of the eighteenth
                century, already has a text in mind. Perhaps she plans to teach <title rend="italic"
                    >Edgar Huntly</title> or <title rend="italic">The Female Quixote</title> next
                semester, so she needs to reread the book anyway. So she logs in to 18thConnect,
                goes to TypeWright, and searches for a text. </p>


            <figure>
                <head> Search Results on 18thConnect. </head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
            </figure>

            <p>In a list of results, if a new editor clicks on the title of a text, a confusing
                error message appears. That’s because TypeWright has access to the texts, and users
                can see them only through through the TypeWright interface (otherwise, we can only
                access ECCO though our institutions, if they subscribe to it). So, if you click on
                the <q>Edit</q> button, you can begin reviewing the transcript. </p>
            <p>My first impression of working in TypeWright was how different the interface is from
                    <ref target="http://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/">Transcribe
                    Bentham</ref>, a similar crowd-sourced project. This difference reflects that
                the two tools are conducting distinct curatorial tasks. In the case of Transcribe
                Bentham, there are no transcriptions yet and we humans are called upon to create
                them. TypeWright texts are beginning with transcriptions produced by a machine, in
                need of human attention to correct them. TypeWright editors generally won’t be
                starting with a blank page. </p>

            <figure>
                <head> Editing a page in TypeWright. </head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            </figure>


            <p>After a user clicks the button to <q>Start Editing,</q> their workspace appears: a
                blown-up image of one line of text, a space to edit the line as currently
                transcribed, and a thumbnail image of the page being edited, with a box locating the
                current line. The user can edit the text, approve the current transcription or
                delete it entirely. One can also move around the page or around the document. The
                pencil icon reveals the edit history of the current line. It’s worth noting here how
                easy it is to accidently delete a line from the transcript (an undo button silently
                appears, but it’s easy to miss). Generally, there is an assumption that users of
                this site will take this work seriously and discharge their editorial duties with
                great care. </p>
            <p>Once editing is complete, the user can click the <q>Mark Complete</q> button on the
                last page. 18thConnect has procedures in place to check the edited text and notify
                the user if the document has been declared complete, or what work remains to be
                done. The organization will also provide a letter and a certificate of completion.
                Documentation of a partly-edited work is also possible (e.g., <q>Professor X has
                    corrected 37% of this 500pp text</q>).</p>
            <p>This is the sort of documentation that can turn into credit in a seminar or a line on
                a CV. I say this expecting a <foreign xml:lang="latin">de minimis</foreign> benefit
                for those seeking jobs or promotions and tenure — not because digital work is
                undervalued, but because editorial work is generally undervalued.</p>
            <p>There’s more. When an editor completes a text, she owns it. 18thConnect will send the
                editor either of two versions of the text, one plain text, and one minimally marked
                up in TEI. The Text Encoding Initiative’s XML standard is the basis of most
                contemporary textual curation efforts. The TEI version of the text is intended to
                serve as the foundation for a scholarly edition. Someone interested enough to
                correct the transcription of a text might also be moved to publish an edition. (An
                example of a scholarly edition that started as a Typewrite text is Jess McCarthy’s
                edition of Daniel Defoe’s <title rend="quotes">Hymn to the Pillory</title>: <ref
                    target="http://ahymntothepillory.blogspot.com/"
                    >http://ahymntothepillory.blogspot.com/</ref>.) The plain text version would be
                ideal for carrying out text mining approaches to the text, as in this case TEI tags
                would just get in the way.</p>
            <p>As the screenshot demonstrates, the first lines of the <q>Featured text</q> (figure
                4), a single line can be edited multiple times. </p>

            <figure>
                <head> The edit history of a single line. </head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            </figure>

            <p>The back-and-forth we see in the version history of that line casts some doubt on the
                assumption that all editors will discharge their duties with the same care.
                18thConnect’s preference is for an editor to take ownership in a text and edit it
                from beginning to end, and there are good reasons good scholars would want to.</p>
            <p>A few technical improvements would enhance this tool's usability. (1) It could be
                useful to allow scholars to formally adopt texts (e.g., a message like <q>User
                    Professor X is actively working to correct this text</q> would display in the
                interface). (2) It would be very useful to bookmark a text where you left off. Or
                perhaps a user could automatically go to the first uncorrected page in a text,
                instead of always starting on the first page. (3) And as was mentioned, it seems too
                easy to delete a line from the transcript. (4) It would also be useful to include
                information on eighteenth-century printing. The typical graduate student might not
                be certain of how to handle features like the long S or graphemes. As a benchmark,
                Transcribe Bentham includes basic information on paleography. </p>
            <p>What I would most like to see is incorporation of the texts of Early American
                Imprints. ECCO contains some American texts but nowhere near a comprehensive
                collection, and 18thConnect includes Americanists of course. My other suggestions
                all require mere technical effort. Adding texts from Evans would require a whole new
                set of negotiations with a different publisher. Just the same, we are waiting for
                someone to come forward and take on the challenge of making the TCP-Evans texts
                easily available for text mining or the uncorrected OCR available for correction in
                the way that TypeWright does for the ECCO texts.</p>
            <p>In the near future, REKn will be providing access to the TCP texts from EEBO. In the
                very near future, users of 18thConnect will be able to run the corrected ECCO texts
                through Voyant directly. Voyant is an easy-to-use text-mining tool that makes it
                easy to find trends in a text or body of texts. </p>
            <p>In an environment where most funding comes from fixed-term grants and it is easier to
                fund a pilot than a sustained effort, a question we have to ask about any online
                resource is how long can we count on using it. The fact that 18thConnect is part of
                a larger organization and has seen past and planned advances serve as reasons to
                expect it to stick around.</p>
            <p>I am a zealot. I think every student in English studies or in information science
                should contribute to a particular curatorial project like TypeWright. Participation
                would serve a valuable function in a seminar in digital humanities, text modeling,
                digital curation, literature, history, or scholarly editing. Students of literature
                and history and related fields should volunteer to learn about eighteenth-century
                printing, digitization, and editing. Even more important, those who study this
                century should volunteer for the cause of making these texts more accessible. </p>

        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Earhart 2010" xml:id="earhart2010">Earhart, Amy. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Using NINES in the Classroom.</title> ProfHacker (2010). <ref
                        target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/using-nines-collex-in-the-classroom"
                        >http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/using-nines-collex-in-the-classroom</ref></bibl>


            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
