<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Shakespeare’s Tragic Social Network; or Why All the World’s a
                    Stage</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>James <dhq:family>Lee</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Cincinnati</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>james.jlee@uc.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>James Lee is Assistant Professor of English, and Co-Director of the
                            Digital Scholarship Center at the University of Cincinnati. His work has
                            been published in <title rend="italic">Studies in Philology</title>
                            (2016), <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> (2013), <title
                                rend="italic">Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery</title> (2001), and
                            by the Korea Foundation (2012). His research has been supported by the
                            Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, the University of Iowa’s Obermann Center
                            for Advanced Studies, and the Intel Corporation.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Jason <dhq:family>Lee</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jjsnlee@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jason Lee is a software engineer experienced with the tools of the
                            internet, analytics, and big data. He has worked in a spectrum of
                            industries and is currently in financial services.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000289</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2017-05-02">2 May 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Shakespeare</item>
                        <item>network analysis</item>
                        <item>social networks</item>
                        <item>text mining</item>
                        <item>visualization</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2017-07-09" who="DD">Validation Check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>We propose that network visualization is a digital humanities method that can
                        <soCalled>explore</soCalled> and <soCalled>negotiate</soCalled> the space
                    between text and performance in the study of Shakespeare. The networks developed
                    in this project use the language of Shakespearean plays to trace the
                    relationships between characters in space, in effect, translating the literary
                    text into a web of spatial relations, which are difficult to perceive solely in
                    the act of reading. Our analysis presents a particular method of network
                    visualization, and also demonstrates how this technique can be used as a
                    critical tool to revise our understanding of social disorder in Shakespearean
                    tragedy. We therefore propose a dual scope for this paper. At a methodological
                    level, we argue that network visualization is a way to infer staging and the
                        <soCalled>blocking</soCalled> of theatrical space from the language of the
                    playtext. In our case study, we show how this technique can be used as a form of
                    Shakespearean literary criticism deploying this method to reframe the larger
                    question of social disorder in his tragedies. The network visualizations used in
                    this analysis serve as a stable and reproducible way, beyond any single
                    performance, to delineate how the language of Shakespeare’s plays structures the
                    relationships of characters in space. This study represents the beginning of a
                    digital method that aims to bridge text and performance in the study of
                    Shakespeare by reading the dramatic text for the linguistic codes that organize
                    the space of the stage.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Argues that network visualization can bridge text and performance in the study of
                    Shakespeare.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#weimann1999">Hence the question may legitimately be
                        asked whether the space for discontinuity between text and performance was
                        not used quite significantly. Was it, perhaps, potentially a site in which
                        cultural difference between imaginary representations and physicality in
                        performance could be presented, explored, negotiated, released, or otherwise
                        delivered? </quote>
                    <ptr target="#weimann1999"/>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> Robert Weimann has suggested that bridging the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#weimann1999">discontinuous</quote> space between the literary
                    text and the theatrical performance would require us to reimagine the gap
                    between the two media as a productive site of cultural <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#weimann1999">negotiation,</quote> rather than an irreconcilable
                    methodological divide <ptr target="#weimann1999" loc="427"/>. In this essay, we
                    offer a response to Weimann’s theoretical proposal, by arguing that network
                    visualization gives us the specific tools to <soCalled>explore</soCalled> and to
                        <soCalled>negotiate</soCalled> the space between text and performance in the
                    study of Shakespearean drama. In this approach, digital humanities techniques
                    serve as a way to link traditionally different modes of aesthetic engagement,
                    such as, in the case of Shakespeare, reading his plays as literary texts or
                    performing them on stage. The networks developed in this project use the
                    language of Shakespearean playtexts to trace the relationships between
                    characters in space, in effect, translating the literary text into a web of
                    spatial relations, which are difficult to perceive solely in the act of reading.
                    Our analysis presents a particular method of network visualization, and also
                    demonstrates how this technique can be used as a critical tool to revise our
                    understanding of social disorder in Shakespearean tragedy. We therefore propose
                    a dual scope for this paper. At a methodological level, we argue that network
                    visualization is a way to infer staging and the <soCalled>blocking</soCalled> of
                    theatrical space from the language of the playtext. In our case study, we show
                    how this technique can be used as a form of Shakespearean literary criticism
                    deploying this method to reframe the larger question of social disorder in his
                    tragedies.</p>
                <p>Our network visualizations quantify from the beginning to the end of each scene
                    in Shakespeare’s thirty-seven plays the number of words and lines spoken by each
                    character, which characters interact by responding to one another (i.e. if
                    character A speaks, and character B replies, the program counts this as a
                    reciprocal exchange of language) and how frequently the two characters interact
                    by this response mechanism. Here we have adapted Emma Pierson’s counting method,
                    which measures network interaction by <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pierson2014">counting the number of lines of A
                            spoken immediately after B, and vice versa, and summing them</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pierson2014"/>
                    </cit>. This logic defines interaction in terms of dialogic response: if two
                    characters are adjacent in the playtext, our program measures this as a proxy
                    for a reciprocal linguistic exchange. To validate our method, we will compare
                    the network diagrams to actual performances by the Royal Shakespeare Company to
                    show that the density or sparseness of each play’s network, and the proximity
                    and distance of the characters composing that network, correspond to the
                    positioning and arrangement of the actors’ bodies on stage. This homology
                    between the network and the embodied performance is logical because each
                    character’s speech structures their relationship to others, and frames their
                    physical interaction in the space of the stage. There are, of course, exceptions
                    to this trend (dumbshows, asides, and eavesdropping scenes are some of the
                    obvious examples), and the network can by no means function as an exact template
                    for a performance. However, the network visualizations used in this analysis
                    serve as a stable and reproducible way, beyond any single performance, to
                    delineate how the language of Shakespeare’s plays structures the relationships
                    of characters in space.</p>
                <p> The networks lead us to a new vantage point on Shakespeare’s dramatic art,
                    allowing us to revise a longstanding view that his plays draw their power from
                    the subversive portrayal of social disorder, either in the form of the
                    carnivalesque or as the <q>conflict and
                        waste</q> of tragic violence. The network visualizations reveal a new,
                    more subtle logic of enantiosis, or <foreign xml:lang="la">discordia
                        concors</foreign>, which requires the building of dense social networks on
                    stage as a performance strategy representing a disordering of the social in the
                    plot. Shakespeare’s plays bind characters into a social network in space so as
                    to break apart the social order. This is important because it complicates
                    contemporary network theories that define the social network as an array of
                    positive relationships bound by affiliations or affinities – for instance, the
                    friends or family in a social media network. Our network analysis of the
                    tragedies adds a level of historical nuance to our understanding of social
                    network structure, by showing how Shakespeare builds the densest social networks
                    at precisely the moments where the social order is being destroyed. In
                    Shakespeare’s tragic social networks, then, <emph>making</emph> a network link
                    between two characters can actually signify the <emph>breaking</emph> of a
                    social relationship between them. The network visualization method permits us to
                    see how this counterintuitive performance strategy unfolds by translating the
                    language of the text into an array of character relationships in space. This
                    study represents the beginning of a digital method that aims to bridge text and
                    performance in the study of Shakespeare by reading the dramatic text for the
                    linguistic codes that organize the space of the stage. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><title rend="quotes">Reading toward Performance</title>: Character-space and
                    Stage Geography</head>
                <p> The attempt to use digital humanities tools to span the methodological distance
                    between textual criticism and theater studies responds directly to the recent
                    critical project exemplified by Lukas Erne, Patrick Cheney, David Scott Kastan,
                    and Peter Stallybrass, among many others, which has recuperated a vision of
                    Shakespeare as a literary artist, who did not simply write plays for theatrical
                    production, as the commonplace assumption has long held (<ptr target="#erne2013"
                    />; <ptr target="#cheney2008"/>; <ptr target="#kastan2001"/>; <ptr
                        target="#degrazia1993"/>). This laudable historical work emphasizing
                    Shakespeare’s literariness has persuasively demonstrated that the playwright was
                    indeed interested in the textual dissemination and afterlife of his works in the
                    marketplace of books and ideas. We intend to affirm and complicate this critical
                    trend by exploring the space between text and performance as a productive site
                    of critical reading in its own right. The word <q>reading</q> is used both
                    purposefully and provocatively here, since Shakespeareans have traditionally
                    recognized the limits of reading the plays as only one part of the range of
                    signification made possible by the text. As Gary Taylor, editor of the Oxford
                    editions of Shakespeare’s complete works, famously puts it, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2002">the written text depended upon an
                            unwritten para-text…an invisible life-support system of stage
                            directions, which Shakespeare could either expect his first readers (the
                            actors) to supply, or which those first readers would expect Shakespeare
                            to supply orally</quote>
                        <ptr target="#taylor2002" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. Or, to the mind of Antony Hammond, <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#hammond1992">ninety percent</quote> of the materiality of
                    performance and staging lies beyond the scope of literary critics. <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hammond1992">The plain fact of the matter,
                            which has been ignored by most editors and by many academic critics, is
                            that while better than ninety percent of the dialogue text can be
                            recovered, with a good degree of accuracy, for most surviving plays of
                            the Elizabethan period, ninety percent of what actually happened on
                            stage in their performance is not to be found in the stage-directions of
                            any manuscript or printed text, or in the occasional descriptions of
                            performances, and illustrations. The actors’ movements, quite apart from
                            their body language, their positioning and grouping (what directors call
                                <q>blocking</q>) and their business with props, is largely
                            unrecoverable terra incognita.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hammond1992" loc="81"/>
                    </cit><note> See also <ptr target="#DeMarinis1993"/> on the irreversibility of
                        theatrical transcoding. More recent digital work <ptr target="#smith2013"/>
                        has attempted to use <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2013"
                            >avatars</quote> to allow users to position characters on a virtual
                        stage. However, this tool does not base the organization of space on the
                        text of plays.</note> Taylor and Hammond influentially have cast the final
                    form of the play as non-textual, and thus mark performance as something in
                    excess of the literary critic’s capacity to analyze the linguistic contours of
                    the text.</p>
                <p> Recent work in the theory of dramatic narrative, however, offers an alternative
                    by not foreclosing performance from the gaze of the critic (<ptr
                        target="#jahn2001"/>; <ptr target="#fludernik2008"/>; <ptr
                        target="#nünning2008"/>; <ptr target="#richardson2007"/>). Ryan Claycomb, to
                    take the most recent example, has argued that dramatic narratives encode their
                    own rules of performance - <quote rend="inline" source="#claycomb2013">they
                        tell us much about their understanding of the relationship between author
                        and production…in short, they tell us how and to what degree we should be
                        reading toward performance</quote>
                    <ptr target="#claycomb2013" loc="161"/>. Claycomb suggests that theatrical
                    performance inheres in the dramatic narrative itself, and so readers can gain
                    some insight into the performance strategies immanent to the play. More
                    specifically in Shakespeare criticism, Robert Weimann has notably claimed, much
                    like Claycomb, that inscribed within the text itself lies <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#weimann2000">both play and production,</quote> or <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#weimann2000">representational acting and
                            presentational playing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#weimann2000" loc="420"/>
                    </cit>. Similarly, Michael Goldman considers the text to be a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#goldman1985">design for performance,</quote>
                        <ptr target="#goldman1985" loc="15"/>
                    </cit> while Inga-Stina Ewbank insists that Shakespeare’s text encodes a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ewbank1983"><soCalled>grammar</soCalled> of
                            the situation…where words repeat in small what Shakespeare and the
                            actors do at large</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ewbank1983" loc="55–75"/>
                    </cit>. The crucial difference between Claycomb’s general model of <q>reading toward performance</q>
                    and the corresponding trend in Shakespeare criticism is the latter’s emphasis on
                    space and not narrative (<ptr target="#ichikawa2013"/>; <ptr target="#stern2009"
                    /> and <ptr target="#stern2004"/>; <ptr target="#paul2008"/>; <ptr
                        target="#weingust2007"/>; <ptr target="#foakes2006"/>; <ptr
                        target="#gurr1992"/>; <ptr target="#weimann1987"/>). Erika Lin, exemplifying
                    this turn to theatrical space, argues that the playtext expresses within its
                    language a <quote rend="inline" source="#lin2012">stage geography</quote>
                    where <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lin2012">bodies act as signifiers in
                            theatre</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lin2012"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p> Franco Moretti and his Literary Lab have participated in this effort to
                    understand the playtext as a <soCalled>grammar</soCalled> for the organization
                    of characters’ bodies in space, toward the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#lin2012">stage geography</quote> proposed by Lin. However,
                    unlike Shakespearean performance space critics such as Lin, Tiffany Stern and
                    Mariko Ichikawa, who employ a materialist method, the Literary Lab fashioned
                    networks as a way to analyze the space structured by the text of <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title>. Networks translate narrative time into space,
                    by representing <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">a character-system arising out of
                            many character-spaces</quote>
                        <ptr target="#moretti2011" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>. His innovation lies in using networks, and not just close reading or
                    materialist historiography, to study how the text of <title rend="italic"
                        >Hamlet</title> shapes a specific <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#woloch2003">character-space,</quote> to borrow Alex Woloch’s
                    terminology <ptr target="#woloch2003"/>. For Moretti and the Literary Lab,
                    networks change our <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">perception of
                        the plot</quote> by turning the interaction between characters into an array
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">visible</quote> in space, and
                    not just as the readerly printed text. His use of networks to examine the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">character-space</quote> inscribed
                    within the play moves the study of space as the medium linking the literary text
                    and theatrical performance in a provocative new direction. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methods: From Network Theory to Network Visualization</head>
                <p> The present argument builds on the work of Moretti, but our visualization method
                    defines and constructs the Shakespearean networks differently than the Literary
                    Lab and other existing analyses of literary networks. A scan of previous network
                    methods would be useful here to sharpen the contrast with our own techniques. In
                    his pamphlet, Moretti defines a network as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">made of vertices and
                            edges...basically, two characters are linked if some words have passed
                            between them: an interaction is a speech act</quote>
                        <ptr target="#moretti2011" loc="3"/>
                    </cit>. By contrast, an earlier network study from 2003 conducted by a group of
                    evolutionary psychologists makes very different choices in crafting networks of
                    Shakespeare’s plays. The psychologists, Stiller, Nettle, and Dunbar, explain
                    their method as follows: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#stiller2003">The network structure calculations
                            were obtained by treating each speaking character as a node, and deeming
                            two characters to be linked if there was at least one time slice of the
                            play in which both were present (that is, if two characters spoke to
                            each other or were in each other’s presence, then they have a
                            link).</quote>
                        <ptr target="#stiller2003" loc="399"/>
                    </cit> As Moretti draws a contrast between their two approaches, his networks
                    exclusively use <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">explicit</quote>
                    data - <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">some words passed</quote>
                    between characters - as a measurement of social interaction, whereas Stiller, et
                    al. infer <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">implicit</quote>
                    relationships as well, by using both verbal exchange (<quote rend="inline"
                        source="#moretti2011">if two characters spoke to each other</quote>) or
                    silent proximity on stage (if they <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011"
                        >were in each other’s presence</quote>) <ptr target="#moretti2011" loc="3"
                    />. More recently, Emma Pierson of the statistical analysis website
                    fivethirtyeight.com attempted to quantify network relationships in Shakespeare’s
                    romances programmatically, and not manually as the previous two studies had
                    done, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pierson2014">by writing a computer program to
                            count how many lines each pair of characters in <title rend="italic"
                                >Romeo and Juliet</title> spoke to each other</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pierson2014"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p> There are strengths and weaknesses to each of these prior network methods.
                    Moretti’s use of <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">explicit</quote>
                    ties in language is a concrete and specific way to mark interaction, but he
                    admits that <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">some questionable
                        decisions</quote> were made in the study since he concedes that the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">edges</quote> between characters
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">are not weighted</quote>:
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">when Claudius tells Horatio in
                        the graveyard scene, <q>I pray thee, good
                            Horatio, wait upon him</q>, these eight words have in this Figure
                        exactly the same value as the four thousand words exchanged between Hamlet
                        and Horatio</quote>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2011" loc="3"/>. He acknowledges that this flattening of
                    all linguistic exchanges to <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">exactly
                        the same value</quote> paints a picture that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#moretti2011">can’t be right.</quote> Amounting to what he calls
                    the <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">childhood of network
                        theory...before the stern adulthood of statistics,</quote> Moretti recounts
                    a struggle <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">to find a non-clumsy way
                        to visualize weight</quote> of the speech between characters, and <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">as a consequence, the networks in
                        (his) study were all made by hand.</quote> He adopted this approach to
                    construct his networks since <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011"
                        >machine-gathering of the data, essential to large-scale quantification, was
                        not yet a realistic possibility</quote>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2011" loc="10"/></cit>. The resulting manually constructed
                    networks are based upon a hazy description of what constitutes a <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">speech act.</quote> The measurement of
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">some words</quote> exchanged
                    between characters defines an imprecise approximation of how language structures
                    the links in the network. </p>
                <p> In the case of the paper by Stiller, et al., the primary advantage of their
                    approach lies in the attempt to include <q>implicit</q> stage presence alongside <q>explicit</q> spoken language, but as in the case of the Literary Lab’s
                    network analysis, the problem of a lack of weighting arises. Their networks deem
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#stiller2003">two characters to be linked if there was
                            <emph>at least one</emph> time slice of the play in which both were
                        present.</quote> The <q>&gt;1 instance</q>
                    approach treats a single encounter as being identical to many recurring
                    encounters, having the effect of flattening the distinction between strong
                    patterns of interaction and more sporadic ones. Additionally, their study does
                    not weight <q>implicit</q> and <q>explicit</q> interactions differently:
                        <q>presence</q> is determined by <quote rend="inline" source="#stiller2003">two
                        characters (who) spoke to each other <emph>or</emph> were in each other’s
                        presence.</quote> The <q>or</q> criterion defines explicit linguistic
                    interaction as being equivalent to implicit shared stage presence. This ignores
                    much of the nuance of dramatic performance by eliding the distinctions between
                    different kinds of relationships into a single generic metric of non-specific
                    social bonds.</p>
                <p> In sum, both the Literary Lab and Stiller, et al. encounter problems with how to
                    accurately weight the volume and frequency of interactions (i.e. how do repeated
                    interactions have a greater weight than less frequent ones?) and in how to
                    weight the difference between explicit and implicit interactions (i.e. how do
                    direct linguistic exchanges have a different weight than characters who silently
                    share the stage?). The technical problem of weighting is not exclusive to
                    network analyses of Shakespeare. Hoyt Long and Richard So’s methodology in
                    examining modernist poetic networks <quote rend="inline" source="#long2013"
                        >treats every published poem as essentially equal, and thus commits to a
                        flagrant abstraction of the cultural content from which (their) network data
                        is derived.</quote> This is a tactical choice on their part, however,
                    because they aim <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#long2013">to identify broader
                        structural patterns</quote>
                    <ptr target="#long2013" loc="9"/></cit>. By contrast, Pierson’s quantitative network
                    analysis adds a level of methodological sophistication by attempting to weight
                    interactions by <quote rend="inline" source="#pierson2014">counting how many
                        lines each pair of characters in <title rend="italic">Romeo and
                            Juliet</title> spoke to each other,</quote> but her study places a
                    self-imposed limit by focusing exclusively on dyads in Shakespeare’s love
                    stories, and does not consider multivalent relationships between several
                    characters across all of his many plays and numerous genres.</p>
                <p> How can we resolve these problems of accurate weighting in measuring interaction
                    in Shakespeare’s plays? It is important to acknowledge that the strengths and
                    weaknesses of these existing network methods derive from the technical choices
                    these scholars have made in constructing their networks. As Borgatti explains, a
                    central assumption of network theory is that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#borgatti2011">it is the researcher - by choosing a set of nodes
                        and a type of tie - that defines the network.</quote> The choices involved
                    in building a given network <quote rend="inline" source="#borgatti2011">should
                        not generally be regarded as an empirical question. Rather it should be
                        dictated by the research question and one’s explanatory theory.</quote> This
                    necessary logic of selection stems from the fact that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#borgatti2011">in contrast to groups, networks do not have
                            <soCalled>natural</soCalled> boundaries,</quote> and are artificial
                    abstractions used to visualize complex systems <ptr target="#borgatti2011"
                        loc="2"/>.<note> So, for example, <ptr target="#borgatti2011"/> specify that
                        a researcher interested in communications networks may study email exchanges
                        and phone calls, whereas a researcher examining kinship networks would study
                        psychological and affective bonds.</note></p>
                <p> With this proviso in mind that the investigator’s methodological choices
                    governed by an explanatory theory inflect the structure of the network, our
                    network analysis uses actor-network-theory (ANT) as a theoretical framework
                    organizing our methodological decisions. ANT gives us a useful working
                    vocabulary to define our networks, and is the most robust network paradigm
                    dominant in the humanities, social sciences, and in business and organizational
                    studies today that specifically adopts linguistic exchanges as the medium of
                    social interaction composing the network’s structure. ANT is additionally useful
                    for literary criticism since it unabashedly places theatrical and literary
                    metaphors such as <q>actor,</q>
                    <q>performance,</q>
                    <q>stage,</q> and <q>narrative</q> at the center of their definition of how
                    networks constitute the social.<note> By contrast, sociological, organizational,
                        and quantitative network theories define networks in much more general
                        terms. Quantitative network theory defines a social network as <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#scott2000">a set of people or groups of
                                people with some pattern of contacts or interactions between
                                them</quote>
                            <ptr target="#scott2000"/>
                        </cit>
                        <ptr target="#wasserman1994"/>. Easley and Kleinberg define <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#easley2010">the idea of a network</quote> as <quote rend="inline" source="#easley2010">a
                            pattern of interconnections among a set of things</quote>
                        <ptr target="#easley2010" loc="15"/>. In organization studies, Borgatti and
                        Halgin posit that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#borgatti2011">a network consists of a set
                                of actors or nodes along with a set of ties of a speciﬁed type (such
                                as friendship) that link them</quote>
                            <ptr target="#borgatti2011" loc="2"/>
                        </cit>.</note> ANT defines a network as a social structure created by a
                    lattice of intersubjective communication. According to Bruno Latour and John
                    Law, the form of the network maps the circulation of social energy by tracing
                    the movement of language between <quote rend="inline" source="#latour1996"
                        >actors</quote> in space, in a process called <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#latour1996">translation.</quote> The network thus offers to us a
                    model of the social that does not rely on the ordered arrangements of
                    hierarchies, institutions, ranks, categories, or taxonomies. ANT describes the
                    social order in a seemingly chaotic, unordered way, where the linguistic
                    transactions between actors in the network empirically determine the nature of
                    the social structure in the first place, without any formal, <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">a priori</foreign> presupposition of what the social
                    organization should look like. Thus, if conceptualized in the form of the
                    network, our introduction to the fractured political world of Elsinore looks
                    something like this (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Hamlet, </title>Act 1, Scene 2.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p> The network organizes the competing factions in space, organized around the hubs
                    of Hamlet and Claudius, with Gertrude caught in between. This more closely
                    matches the experience of spectators who would first encounter power
                    relationships by inferring spatial and linguistic interactions between
                    characters, and would have to figure out for themselves the tensions and
                    allegiances driving the play’s plot. By contrast, modern text editions, such as
                    the Oxford Shakespeare shown in <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>, provide
                    the reader with a neat organization classified by rank, nationality, gender,
                    heredity, or among other rubrics, in the form of a cast of characters, which was
                    not provided to Renaissance audiences, or many theatergoers today <ptr
                        target="#wells2005"/>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>Cast of Characters from the Oxford Shakespeare.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p> Unlike the seemingly codified hierarchy of the cast of characters, the social
                    relationships visualized in the network are not static. The network captures the
                    ephemeral dynamism of unstable and constantly shifting social vectors. It is
                    defined by its actors and their movements structuring relationships in a web.
                    The actions composing the network involves a range of verbs describing the
                    tracing and writing performed by the actors: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#latour1996">there is an actor whose definition
                            of the world outlines, traces, delineate, limn, describe, shadow forth,
                            inscroll, file, list, record, mark, or tag a trajectory that is called a
                            network</quote>
                        <ptr target="#latour1996" loc="14"/>
                    </cit>. The discourse of texts resulting from these acts compose a network that
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2007">renders the movement of the
                        social visible to the reader</quote>
                    <ptr target="#latour2007" loc="128"/>. The network translates the
                        <soCalled>movement of the social</soCalled> into a
                        <soCalled>visible</soCalled> form, revealing a social structure determined
                    by intersubjective relationships mediated by language. Central to ANT’s
                    definition of the network is a literalization of the word <q>actor.</q> Latour
                    attempts to <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2007">reactivate</quote> the
                    actor’s theatrical signification as a way to redefine agency in the network <ptr
                        target="#latour2007" loc="46"/>. Theatrical action is <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#latour2007">borrowed, distributed, suggested, influenced,
                        dominated, betrayed, translated</quote> in a constant linguistic negotiation
                    of social energy with other actors and agents in the fictional space of the
                    stage. The collective agency performed on the theatrical stage serves as a
                    useful paradigm for ANT by providing a well-developed model describing how
                    linguistic exchanges between actors in space create a social world in miniature.
                    Our network analysis of Shakespeare’s plays thus enacts a productive cross-talk
                    between theater and the network. ANT has appropriated the technical vocabulary
                    of drama to define its <q>actors</q> in space, while we are reciprocally using
                    ANT as a framework to define the space of the stage latent in Shakespearean
                        language.<note> John Law’s definition of the network in terms of <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#law2009">playing parts</quote> and the <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#law2009">enactment of performance</quote>
                        echoes Jaques’ famous declaration in <title rend="italic">As You Like
                            It</title> that <quote rend="inline" source="#law2009">all the world’s
                            a stage / … and one man in his time plays many parts</quote>
                        (2.7.138-141), as well as Antonio’s melancholic assertion in the <title
                            rend="italic">Merchant of Venice</title> that the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#law2009">world</quote> is <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#law2009">a stage where every man must play a part</quote>
                        (1.1.79) <ptr target="#law2009" loc="151"/>. The theatrical worldview
                        adopted by network theory is already inscribed within Shakespearean drama,
                        which presents an insistent performative definition of the social that
                        defines the <q>world</q> as immanently theatrical, precisely as network
                        theory has begun to do four centuries later.</note> ANT’s articulation of an
                    organic, emergent model of the social in which the linguistic relationships
                    between actors constitute the social structure itself, gives us an alternative
                    technical vocabulary to examine the social organization of Shakespeare’s plays
                    from a different spatial angle. ANT’s stress on linguistic exchange as the basis
                    of defining <q>actors,</q>
                    <q>performance,</q> and the <q>stage</q> of the network gives us a specific
                    framework to work with the language of the plays as the medium of social
                    interaction.</p>
                <p> ANT’s definition of language as the tissue binding the performance network
                    together also suggests a way to resolve some of the problems of weighting found
                    in the prior network analyses of Shakespeare’s plays and literary works. To
                    address Moretti’s admitted issue of a lack of weighting the volume and frequency
                    of dialogue between characters, we have adapted Pierson’s method of using the
                    number of lines exchanged between speakers as a way to weight different
                    magnitudes of interaction. The result of Pierson’s quantitative weighting of
                    line numbers provides a way to avoid hand-drawn diagrams, and permits the
                    development of a machine-based technique of constructing the play’s networks
                    that Moretti has suggested was not yet possible. This technique defines each
                    line of the play as an <soCalled>event
                        tie,</soCalled> which is a concept in network theory where connections have a
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#borgatti2011">discrete and transitory nature
                        and can be counted over time...Cumulated over time, event-type ties can be
                        dimensionalized in terms of frequency of occurrence...It is these kinds of
                        ties that researchers have in mind when they define networks as a
                            <q>recurring pattern of ties</q>.</quote> (<ptr target="#borgatti2011"
                    />; <ptr target="#dubini1991"/>; <ptr target="#ebers1997"/>) </p>
                <p> Our own network visualization method aims to learn from the existing range of
                    network analyses outlined above. To trace the relationships between characters
                    in all of Shakespeare’s plays, we created the diagrams using the Python library
                    NetworkX, which has been used by scientists to examine complex systems and by
                    social scientists to visualize social media networks. The network visualizations
                    are divided by scene, and not the whole play, which was a shared problem of
                    scale in the networks of Moretti, Stiller, Nettle, and Dunbar, and Pierson. Each
                    network layers four dimensions of textual information into a single
                    visualization: interaction between characters measured by who a speaker directly
                    responds to (the edges between the nodes), frequency of interaction with other
                    characters (the length of the edges between nodes), volume of each character’s
                    speech (the radius of the node), and network density (the number of edges
                    surrounding each character). In developing this definition of <q>interaction</q>
                    or <q>ties</q> in the program producing the network visualization, we concur
                    with Moretti, and draw from actor-network-theory, by using explicit textual
                    criteria to determine whether <q>two characters are linked</q> if <q>words have passed between them</q> as a type
                    of <q>speech act</q>
                    constituting interaction in the network. Pierson’s counting method also gives us
                    a basic rubric for measuring these linguistically based interactions
                    programmatically (as opposed to manually), by <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pierson2014">counting the number of lines of A
                            spoken immediately after B, and vice versa, and summing them</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pierson2014"/>
                    </cit>. This measurement of adjacency and proximity in dialogue directly
                    accounts for <emph>response</emph> to a previous speaker as a proxy for
                    reciprocal or mutual ties composing a two-way communication exchange. Here we
                    have attempted to factor in the central distinction in network theory of
                        <q>strong</q> versus <q>weak</q> ties. Network theorists define
                        <q>strong</q> ties as recurrent, direct, mutual, reciprocal relationships
                    and <q>weak</q> ties as indirect, uni-directional, faint, or sporadically
                    occurring relationships (<ptr target="#granovetter1973"/>; <ptr
                        target="#easley2010"/>; <ptr target="#greteman2015"/>). Network theory uses
                    this distinction to evaluate how the two tiers of interaction have different
                    roles in composing a heterogeneous network structure. Thus, measuring the
                    frequency of lines spoken after a certain character attempts to identify
                        <q>strong</q> reciprocal bonds where speakers respond directly to the person
                    speaking before them in the dialogue to engage in a conversation.</p>
                <p> Based on this definition of reciprocal, strong interactions as a response in the
                    dialogue that can be counted as <q>event ties,</q> the <emph>edges</emph>
                    between the nodes in our network diagrams signify each character’s relationship
                    to others, or the characters to whom the character explicitly responds in the
                    text’s language. We measured the <emph>length</emph> of the edges between the
                    nodes by calculating the inverse of how frequently a given pair of characters
                    speak to one another - the more they respond to each other in the dialogue, the
                    closer they will be in the network and the edge between them will be
                    proportionally shorter. Using frequency of interaction in the playtext’s
                    language as a metric modulating the distance between speakers’ nodes represents
                    a way to gauge the strength or reciprocity of their relationship by tracking how
                    much they respond to one another. Characters that reply a single time to an
                    interlocutor will be distant, while characters that repeatedly respond to one
                    another will have a more recurrent tie, and the distance between their nodes
                    will be correspondingly shorter. Our method identifying response frequency by
                    measuring adjacent or immediately proximate speech aims to weight the strength
                    or weakness of interactions. This addresses some of the limitations of previous
                    network studies that vaguely considered <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">some
                        words</quote> passed between characters (in the case of Moretti) or <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#stiller2003">at least one</quote> interaction (in the case of
                    Stiller, et al.) to create connections that are not precisely scaled to the
                    actual amount of interaction that takes place in the play. Thus our network
                    method does not employ an absolute scale in which any interaction greater than a
                    single occurrence creates an unweighted edge between speakers. Rather, our
                    scalable model modulates the length of the edge between characters’ nodes as a
                    proportion of the number of direct responses between them.<note> To test the
                        resulting visualizations, we used two other forms of methodological
                        verification. Adapting Pierson’s method to our own dataset, we <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#pierson2014">counted the number of lines A
                            spoke in scenes in which B was present, and vice versa, and added these
                            two numbers together.</quote> We then <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#pierson2014">computed the above number but, for each
                            character in each scene, multiplied by a <q>normalization factor</q>
                            equivalent to the number of lines that character spoke in the scene
                            divided by the total number of lines in that scene.</quote> The three
                        methods agreed at a much larger scale than in Pierson’s analysis, which
                        aggregated the results for whole plays and only focusing on the romances,
                        while we applied this methodological verification to all of Shakespeare’s
                        plays at the more local context of the scene <ptr target="#pierson2014"
                        />.</note> To verify these machine-based results, we manually checked all of
                    the scenes included in the analysis to validate that the line response method of
                    measuring interaction accurately reflected the narrative spirit of the scene.
                    The manual verification found an average error rate of 2.56% of misattributed
                    interactions across the tragedies studied in this analysis. Some fairly clear
                    trends emerged among the false interactions that the algorithm struggled to
                    parse. First, when too many characters speak at once, such as when two or more
                    characters respond in sequence to one character’s speech. Take for example when
                    Lodovico and Gratiano both respond to Iago’s vow of silence:</p>
                <quote rend="block" source="#canonical">Iago: Demand me nothing: what you know, you know:
                    <lb/> From this time forth I never will speak word. <lb/> Lodovico: What, not to
                    pray? <lb/> Gratiano: Torments will ope your lips. (<title rend="italic"
                        >Othello</title>, 5.2.349-352)</quote>
                <p>Second, the reverse also held true: when one character speaks to several
                    characters at once, such as in Act 1, Scene 5 of <title rend="italic"
                        >Hamlet</title> when the Ghost responds to his son by commanding Horatio and
                    Marcellus to <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">swear</quote> from offstage. This
                    is not a conversation, but in responding to Hamlet, he also directs his
                    imperative to the other two characters. Third, eavesdropping and spying
                    interactions were difficult to account for, with a famous example being Claudius
                    eavesdropping on Hamlet in Act 3, Scene 1. Eavesdropping is a boundary case,
                    because Claudius doesn’t directly engage with Hamlet (i.e. he listens, but they
                    don’t exchange words), but for the sake of accuracy we included these moments.
                    Overall, the manual reading found that characters do indeed predominantly
                    respond to the speaker before them as a general rule shaping Shakespearean
                    dialogue.</p>
                <p> The methods described above, and the technical and theoretical choices informing
                    our measurement of interactions between characters in the network diagrams aim
                    to quantify strong ties, or as Moretti puts it, the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#moretti2011">explicit</quote> links created by direct verbal address
                    and response. But what about weak or implicit ties, such as being present on
                    stage without directly conversing? The effort to include implicit ties was a
                    strength of the study by Stiller, et al., but their lack of weighting made both
                    explicit linguistic interactions, and implicit spatial ones, equivalent. This
                    assumption of equivalence seems to go against the spirit of dramatic
                    performance, which consciously plays between the two. Our method accounts for
                    these weak ties implicitly by structuring the network visualizations at the
                    scale of the scene and not the whole play, as Moretti, Stiller, Nettle, and
                    Dunbar, and Pierson all chose to do. An aggregate whole-play network makes it
                    difficult to infer who shares the stage with whom at any given point. They are
                    also difficult to interpret since they tend to create, as Nathan Yau puts it,
                    graphs that <quote rend="inline" source="#yau2015">in total look
                        hairball-ish,</quote> and which are fairly nonspecific in flattening subtle
                    differences between plays, possessing <quote rend="inline" source="#yau2015"
                        >similar network densities, which suggests similar story structures</quote>
                    across texts <ptr target="#yau2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#grandjean2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Some of this information, however, is already encoded by the plays, within the
                    structure of each scene as a narrative unit that groups a set of characters,
                    selected by Shakespeare himself, to interact both explicitly and implicitly in
                    the frame of the stage. The more focused scale of our method inherently limits
                    the number of ties that are possible because only a certain set of characters,
                    determined by the text, can be present on stage during a scene, and all possible
                    connections in that scene can only occur between these characters. By chunking
                    our network visualizations to represent the local narrative context of the
                    scene, and not the macro-level agglomeration of all interactions in the entire
                    play, our networks capture the range of characters who share the narrative space
                    of each scene implicitly by respecting Shakespeare’s own organizational
                    rules.</p>
                <p> To enrich the layers of information represented in the networks, our
                    visualizations have two further dimensions. Within the network, we have scaled
                    the <emph>radius</emph> of each node according to the number of lines that the
                    character speaks - the larger the node, the more he or she dominates the scene
                    with speech. Calculating the node radius in this way allows us to compare a
                    given character’s volume of speech in general to the volume of speech that is
                    used to communicate with others in the network (represented by the edges). This
                    is a way to measure the total amount of language spoken by a character versus
                    the language defining his position in relation to others. Scaling node radii in
                    this manner expands upon previous network techniques, where nodes were simple
                    vertices or flat points between edges. </p>
                <p> The final dimension in our network method is <emph>density</emph>. Comparing the
                    number of edges linking a character’s node to others, and the distance between
                    characters and their interlocutors, allows us to perceive the network density
                    surrounding each speaker within each scene. Increasing the number of links
                    connecting a character to others, and drawing the edges closer to one another
                    with more frequent reciprocal interactions, create an effect of network density
                    that indicates a high frequency and intensity of network connectedness and
                    social interaction. Scenes with a great deal of interaction will display a dense
                    network of character nodes that are tightly clustered together. Scenes with
                    fewer interactions among characters result in a sparse network with few
                    connections between distant nodes. </p>
                <p> The network visualization method transforms the language of Shakespeare’s plays
                    into an array of spatial relationships structuring the network based on four
                    different measurements. The four metrics encapsulated in our network diagrams -
                    character interaction, frequency of interaction, the volume of each character’s
                    speech, and network density - give us multiple scalable methods of visualizing
                    how the language of Shakespeare’s playtexts structures a lattice of social
                    interactions. Our approach attempts to build on the aforementioned precedents in
                    network analysis. This technique with multiple dimensions in a single
                    visualization offers a richer, and more granular understanding of Shakespeare’s
                    social networks than previous network studies that elided the difference between
                    scenes by constructing aggregate networks for whole plays, flattened the key
                    distinction between strong and weak ties, and did not weight interactions
                    precisely. We propose that our networks learning from these precedents open up a
                    new method using visualization technologies to study a literary or dramatic text
                    from multiple angles simultaneously in a single network diagram. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Network Analysis between Text and Performance: Revising the Social Disorder
                    Hypothesis</head>
                <p> With the visualization method we have developed, what types of network analysis
                    are made possible? How might other critics use this network technique to find
                    new avenues of research in the study of Shakespearean drama and dramatic
                    literature more generally? In the case study that follows, we demonstrate how
                    the networks constructed by our methodology function as a <emph>critical
                        tool</emph> used to evaluate and to test a widely-accepted scholarly
                    consensus on the nature of social order in Shakespeare’s tragedies. Our
                    visualization technique transforms the <emph>idea</emph> of social order into
                    actual social networks of Shakespeare’s dramatic world. We use Shakespeare’s
                    social networks created by the interactions within the plays to read the results
                    of the visualizations against the grain of two other methods predominant in
                    Shakespeare studies - close reading and theatrical performance. Reproducing this
                    critical methodology entails independently conducting three levels of analysis
                    in parallel - network visualization, close reading, and the visual analysis of
                    staged performance - in order to test the results of any given approach against
                    the others. Comparing the network graphs with still images from theatrical
                    performances of the plays will demonstrate how the network analysis reveals to
                    the reader some aspect of embodied performance that they could not perceive
                    intuitively through a reading of the text alone. In this way, the network
                    visualization represents the beginnings of a method that will allow us to read
                    between the written playtext and the theatrical performance. Our argument uses
                    the network analysis as a novel way to study both text and performance in a
                    single visualization, which effectively translates Shakespeare’s language into
                    the web of relationships structuring the characters in the space of performance.
                    It focuses our critical gaze on the exchange between the words and bodies that
                    work together to define Shakespearean performance by transmuting the words of
                    the playtext into character relationships in space.<note> Will use film versions
                        for the sake of analyzing a repeatable and stable performance of the plays
                        in question. Performances produced by the Royal Shakespeare Company, or
                        performed by actors trained by the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art.</note> If
                    Hammond has asserted that <q>blocking</q> or the positioning and grouping of
                    characters in space is <q>unrecoverable</q> for the Shakespearean critic, we
                    propose that the network visualizations allow us to imagine such a spatial
                    arrangement. The network analysis does not create a single, inescapable way of
                    staging inherent in the text, but it does offer to us a way to envision how the
                    text structures the character-space that embodied performances ultimately occupy
                    through the decisions of directors and actors. Ultimately, we propose that
                    Shakespeare’s drama must be shown and not exclusively read, but through a
                    visualization method that is fundamentally textual and rooted in the structure
                    of Shakespeare’s language. By aligning Shakespeare’s text and images from staged
                    performances alongside our network diagrams, we suggest that the playtext itself
                    can be used as a template to begin to organize the space of the Shakespearean
                    stage.</p>
                <p>Using the network visualizations, we aim to address a live question in the
                    digital humanities today: can computational methods teach us something new about
                    literary texts, or do algorithms and visualizations simply confirm readings,
                    arguments, and theories we already know well? The promise of the network method
                    lies precisely in offering to critics a new vantage point that would otherwise
                    not be possible through a conventional reading of the text. The network allows
                    us to rethink one of the oldest stories in Shakespeare criticism and pedagogy,
                    what we will call the social disorder hypothesis. Since A.C. Bradley
                    influentially defined the essence of Shakespearean tragedy as <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#bradley1909">division of spirit involving conflict
                        and waste,</quote> and not the ultimate reconciliation or renewal suggested
                    by Hegel, generations of critics to the present have described the tragic nature
                    of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> in terms of <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >thanatos</foreign>: confusion, destruction, and violence that violates
                    natural law, ethics, and social order (<ptr target="#bradley1909"/>; <ptr
                        target="#McAlindon2013"/>; <ptr target="#heller2005"/>; <ptr
                        target="#prendergast2005"/>; <ptr target="#aebischer2004"/>; <ptr
                        target="#foakes2003"/>; <ptr target="#danner2003"/>; <ptr
                        target="#marshall2002"/>). T.S. Eliot famously describes the violence of the
                    play as an attempt to <quote rend="inline" source="#eliot1998">express the
                        inexpressibly horrible</quote> that is marred by <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#eliot1998">excess</quote>
                        <ptr target="#eliot1998" loc="58–59"/>
                    </cit>. George Santayana describes the play as fundamentally <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#santayana1968">incoherent</quote> and it represents
                    a confusion or <quote rend="inline" source="#santayana1968">disarray</quote>
                    of the social world <ptr target="#santayana1968" loc="145"/>. More recently,
                    Franco Moretti has inferred from his qualitative, manually drawn network
                    analysis of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> that the net effect of
                    Shakespearean tragedy is a <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011"
                        >scattering</quote> and a <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2011">total
                        disproportion</quote> of social connections. Moretti’s conclusion from the
                    networks simply reconfirms the standard story of tragedy as disorder <ptr
                        target="#moretti2011" loc="4"/>. Readers of the comedies have developed a
                    parallel hypothesis on social disorder in accounts of the carnivalesque. Drawing
                    inspiration from the work of Mikhail Bakhtin in <title rend="italic">Rabelais
                        and his World</title>, a long tradition of critics has focused on the
                    inversions and disorderings of political and sexual hierarchies opened up in the
                    chaos of Shakespeare's comedies (<ptr target="#bakhtin1984"/>; <ptr
                        target="#goldberg2013"/>; <ptr target="#pikli2010"/>; <ptr
                        target="#grady2001"/>; <ptr target="#knowles1998"/>; <ptr
                        target="#gorfain1991"/>; <ptr target="#bergeron1991"/>; <ptr
                        target="#wilson1987"/>; <ptr target="#newman1987"/>; <ptr
                        target="#kastan1985"/>; <ptr target="#danson1984"/>; <ptr
                        target="#bristol1983"/>; <ptr target="#logan1982"/>; <ptr
                        target="#berry1972"/>; <ptr target="#salingar1976"/>. As Brian Richardson
                    has put it, comedies such as <title rend="italic">A Midsummer Night’s
                        Dream</title> perform <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#richardson1987">the overthrowing of law - in
                            particular, the laws of nature</quote>
                        <ptr target="#richardson1987" loc="302"/>
                    </cit>. In this story told about Shakespeare, the tragedies and comedies draw
                    their power and enduring interest from the subversive representation of social
                    disorder. For the sake of space, the present argument focuses on Shakespeare’s
                    tragedies, and acknowledges that the comedies and histories require further
                    analysis.</p>
                <p> This canonical account of Shakespearean drama as a fictional space for the
                    eruption of disorder severing social bonds and overthrowing political
                    hierarchies certainly holds true at the level of plot, and Act 5, Scene 2 of
                        <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> is one of the most striking examples of
                    this. However, the critical vocabulary of entropy and chaos - incoherence,
                    conflict, waste, violence, destruction, scattering and disproportion - used to
                    describe tragic plot as the unraveling of society and the destruction of human
                    bonds, fails to capture the dramatic technique required in a performance to
                    represent this <soCalled>scattering</soCalled> of the social on stage. The
                    network in Figure 3 demonstrates that scenes of a tragic
                        <soCalled>scattering</soCalled> disorder and the most disruptive and violent
                    severing of social bonds are precisely the moments where the closest connections
                    between characters are made, and the densest concatenation of network links
                    exists.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, Act 5, Scene 2.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The network density at the end of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> revises the
                    commonly accepted notion, expressed most recently by Emma Smith, that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#smith2009">tragedies tend to move towards the
                            isolation of a single figure on the stage, getting rid of other people,
                            moving towards a kind of solitude, whereas comedies tend to end with a
                            big scene at the end where everybody’s on stage</quote>
                        <ptr target="#smith2009"/>
                    </cit>. The network structure suggests precisely the opposite. It is true that
                    in this explosion of murder and political upheaval concluding the tragedy, all
                    of the characters could not be more distant from one another in terms of kinship
                    and affective bonds. The network visualization of this culminating scene,
                    however, suggests that the play enacts a <soCalled>scattering</soCalled> and
                    destruction of Elsinore’s social fabric by crowding the characters into a more
                    densely packed and interrelated social network. To put this point in narrative
                    terms, at the level of discourse, the play links and intermeshes speakers and
                    bodies in a dense knot so as to represent the intersubjective disorder between
                    previously <soCalled>close</soCalled> or related characters at the level of
                    plot. The network visualization of 5.2 pushes the characters at the moment of
                    violence and the greatest political and filial disorder into uncomfortably close
                    relationships - the dense proximity of characters in relation to one another
                    signifies that they speak to each other with a high level of frequency. </p>
                <p> This counterintuitive network structure adds an important level of historical
                    nuance to contemporary network theory, which defines social networks most
                    frequently as affinity or affiliation groups bound by positive relationships
                    between people. The assumption of positive bonds defining network links is most
                    readily apparent in the persistent example of <soCalled>friends</soCalled>
                    composing social networks. As Mark Granovetter suggests, relationships with
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#granovetter1983">close friends</quote> and
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#granovetter1983">acquaintances</quote> make
                    up a social network <ptr target="#granovetter1983" loc="203"/> and Easley and
                    Kleinberg define the social network itself as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#easley2010">the collection of social ties
                            among friends</quote>
                        <ptr target="#easley2010" loc="1"/>
                    </cit>. By contrast, Shakespeare’s tragedies exhibit precisely the opposite
                    structure: they are not composed of affinity networks bringing together friends
                    or family, but rather these networks represent an array of negative
                    relationships, where social bonds are being broken. In Shakespeare’s historical
                    networks then, each edge in the network that initially signaled kinship or
                    affiliation can, within the scenes of greatest social discord, signify the
                    destruction of a social relationship between the two characters. Thus analyzing
                    the social structure of Shakespeare’s plays adds a useful level of historical
                    subtlety to our understanding of network behavior, which is often grounded in
                    the study of social media networks in the present.</p>
                <p> A more precise way to define network relationships lies in the concept of
                        <q>clustering</q> from quantitative network theory. Mark Newman explains
                    network clustering as a type of transitive relationship in space: <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#newman2003">If vertex A is connected to vertex B,
                        and vertex B to vertex C, then there is a heightened probability that vertex
                        A will also be connected to vertex C. In the language of social networks,
                        the friend of your friend is likely also to be your friend</quote>
                    <ptr target="#newman2003" loc="183"/>
                    <ptr target="#newman2010"/>. The network visualization of 5.2 exhibits such
                    clustering behavior, with the scene populated by triangles of transitive
                    relationships between all of the characters. The clustering displayed by 5.2
                    differs markedly from the <q>hub and spoke</q> model of 1.2, where Hamlet and
                    Claudius serve as the social hubs around which the spokes of the network gather
                        (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The culminating violence of 5.2
                    displays a far more dense network clustering pattern, with the characters in the
                    network interacting far more frequently with others, and not simply relaying
                    their communication through the central figures of Hamlet or Claudius. </p>
                <p> A second way to think about the density of the network in this instance is the
                    distance between nodes. The close positioning of Hamlet, Claudius, Gertrude,
                    Laertes, Osric, and Horatio at the center of the network signals a greater
                    frequency of interaction between the characters than we have seen in previous
                    scenes. In the dense clustering of the network, characters speak to more people,
                    more frequently: the density of lines between characters traces the increase in
                    interaction, and the decreased distance between nodes signifies a greater
                    intensity of communication, with more frequent speech exchanged. To describe the
                    density of the network in quantitative terms, 5.2 has 34 total network
                    connections between characters, or 23.6% of total network links in the play as a
                    whole, as opposed to the symmetrically organized scene of Act 1, Scene 2 above,
                    which displays 9 network connections or 13% of the play’s total network links.
                    Additionally, 5.2’s 34 connections creates a network that is approximately 450%
                    more dense than the play’s average of 7.57 connections per scene (<ref
                        target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Network Density in <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The clustering density of 5.2 describes a world unraveling with more frenetic
                    social energy and thickly intermeshed social connections than we have seen in
                    the previous scene, which had exhibited a relatively diffuse network
                    characterized by greater distance between characters and fewer total network
                    connections between them. In the scene representing the destruction of the
                    social order of Elsinore, the play constructs a social network to bind the
                    characters being destroyed together at the moment of the greatest
                        <q>scattering</q> and chaos. The positive act of theatrically connecting
                    bodies in a dense network tells the story of the negative act of breaking apart
                    the social bonds between characters that had held Elsinore together.</p>
                <p> The dense clustering of characters and bodies in scenes of social disordering is
                    not isolated to <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>. A scan of other tragedies
                    substantiates the same logic of dense imbrication in a social network created at
                    the moments of the greatest social unraveling. Figures 5-7 show several key
                    scenes from <title rend="italic">King Lear</title> that contain the key moments
                    where filial bonds are broken and inverted, and where blood relations degenerate
                    into bloodshed. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head><title rend="italic">King Lear</title>, Act 1, Scene 1.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head><title rend="italic">King Lear,</title> Act 2, Scene 4.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head><title rend="italic">King Lear,</title> Act 5, Scene 3.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Act 1, Scene 1 depicts Lear’s famous opening move dividing his kingdom into
                    thirds in return for verbal affirmations of the strength of his paternal bond
                    with his daughters, Act 2, Scene 4 represents the scene of conflict where
                    Goneril and Regan strip Lear of his retainers, and Act 5, Scene 3 is the moment
                    of tragic reversal where the web of filial and political betrayals leads to the
                    deaths of Lear, Cordelia, Goneril, Regan, Gloucester, and Edmund. All of these
                    scenes representing the rending of family bonds and the established political
                    order exhibit heavily concatenated networks marked by clustering behavior, with
                    a high number of connections between characters and a dense clustering of
                    speakers in close spatial relation to one another. </p>
                <p> As an internal point of reference or control, <ref target="#figure08">Figure
                        8</ref> shows Act 4, Scene 7, which depicts Lear’s reunion with Cordelia. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head><title rend="italic">King Lear,</title> Act 4, Scene 7.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This scene of re-establishing a family bond, a reunification and a linking
                    together of father and daughter, results in a sparse network, with greater
                    distance between affectively <soCalled>close</soCalled> characters, and fewer
                    overall network links. To be more precise about the comparison of network
                    density, the three scenes of greatest social discord disproportionately possess
                    73% of the play's total network links - the 3 scenes out of 26 total scenes
                    contain 124 out of 168 total social connections. The anguishing conclusion of
                    Act 5, Scene 3 alone has 56 network connections, or 33% of the play’s total, in
                    comparison to the thinness of the reunion in Act 4, Scene 7, which has 18
                    connections, and to the play’s overall average of 6.46 network connections per
                    scene (<ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure09">
                    <head>Network Density in <hi rend="italic">King Lear.</hi></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>That a single scene containing the greatest moment of social discord has the
                    densest network of the play by far, with 33% of the entire play’s social links
                    or over 300% of the network ties compared to the scene of reconciliation with
                    Cordelia, and over 850% of the average network connections per scene, shows that
                    the <q>dissolving</q> (5.3.202) and <q>decay</q> (5.3.296) of the play’s social
                    world densely packs the stage with speakers and with bodies as the performance
                    strategy necessary to depict the act of <q>dissolving</q> the bonds between
                    those speakers - a clustering in space so as to divide in the plot. The network
                    thus visualizes the manner in which the play’s structure - the internal
                    relationships between speakers formed by the text’s language - works according
                    to a logic that is the reverse of the content or plot of the scene. The network
                    functions according to a logic of clustering and increased social interaction
                    that is the reverse mechanism of the plot’s dissolution of social bonds.</p>
                <p> A census of Shakespeare’s tragedies, including <title rend="italic"
                        >Coriolanus</title>, <title rend="italic">Julius Caesar</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Antony and Cleopatra</title>, <title rend="italic">Titus
                        Andronicus</title>, and <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>, all
                    demonstrate the same logic of dense network clustering at the moment of social
                    unraveling (<ref target="#figure10">Figures 10-14</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Coriolanus</title>, Act 3, Scene 1.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure11">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Julius Caesar</title>, Act 3, Scene 1.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure12">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Antony and Cleopatra</title>, Act 5, Scene 2.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure13">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Titus Andronicus</hi>, Act 1, Scene 1.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure14">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</hi>, Act 5, Scene 3.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>These pointed scenes of disarray, ranging from Coriolanus’ brawl in the Senate,
                    Julius Caesar’s assassination, Cleopatra’s suicide and Octavius Caesar’s
                    conquest of Egypt, the violent introduction to Titus’ perverse Rome, and the
                    fatal conclusion to <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>, all spin a
                    dense web of social connections to represent social and political breaking
                    points. By quantifying the network densities across these scenes of heightened
                    disorder versus the average number of network connections in all scenes of the
                    play, we can see that the moments of greatest tragic <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                        >frisson</foreign> exhibit much denser social networks than the average for
                    each play (<ref target="#figure15">Figure 15</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure15">
                    <head>Network Density in a Census of Tragedies.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The networks from this cross section of Shakespeare’s tragedies suggest a
                    performance strategy of binding in a social network so as to break apart the
                    social. The plays also describe in their own language the structure of dense
                    binding and knitting that occurs in the final scenes of chaos. Cleopatra defines
                    her own suicide as being wound in a <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >knot intrinsicate</quote> in 5.2.295 visualized above (<ref
                        target="#figure12">Figure 12</ref>). <title rend="italic">Othello</title>
                    most persistently uses the language of nets and webs to describe the
                    intersubjective mesh that binds the characters. Othello, for example, defines
                    himself during the violence of 5.2 as <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >being wrought, / perplexed in the extreme</quote> (5.2.355). Being <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">perplexed</quote> gestures to his
                    confusion upon being <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">enmeshed</quote>
                    in Iago’s <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">net.</quote> However, the
                    etymology of <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">perplexed</quote> adds a
                    second level of meaning to Othello’s final self-definition. The verb <q>to
                        perplex</q> derives from the Latin <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >perplexitas</foreign>, which signifies a knotting, winding, or
                        binding.<note> The OED describes the etymology of <q>perplex</q> from
                        classical Latin as: <foreign xml:lang="la">perplexus</foreign> — involved,
                        confused, intricate &lt; <foreign xml:lang="la">plexus</foreign> -
                        interwoven, entangled, involved, intricate, past participle of <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">plectere</foreign> to plait, interweave. For another
                        prominent example, Spenser’s <title rend="italic">Faerie Queene</title>
                        describes Redcrosse Knight’s entanglement in Errour’s <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#spenser2006">wicked bands</quote> as a state of <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#spenser2006">great perplexitie</quote>
                            <ptr target="#spenser2006" loc="I.i.xix."/>
                        </cit></note> Othello therefore voices in the word <q>perplexed</q> a basic
                    state of being confused, but based on the Latin root, also defines himself in an
                        <q>extreme</q> knotted or tangled
                    state. Othello’s state of perplexity reflects the play’s sustained obsession
                    with how individuals become bound in intersubjective nets. The network traces in
                    spatial form the play’s own vocabulary of nets and webs entangling individuals
                    with others. In Act 2, Scene 2, Iago voices the broad strokes of his plot as a
                    web: <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">With as little a web as this will
                        I ensnare as great a fly as Cassio…I will gyve thee in thine own
                        courtship.</quote> (2.2.169-171) The <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">little web</quote> expands beyond Cassio in Act 2,
                    Scene 3, to <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">enmesh</quote> Cassio,
                    Desdemona, and Othello in a <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >net</quote>: <quote rend="block" source="#canonical">
                        <l> His soul is so enfettered to her love</l>
                        <l> That she may make, unmake, and do what she list,</l>
                        <l> […]</l>
                        <l> And out of her own goodness make the net</l>
                        <l> That shall enmesh them all. (2.3.319-336)</l>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>Iago’s consistent use of the language of <q>webs</q> and <q>nets</q> as the
                    method to <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">ensnare,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">gyve,</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">enmesh</quote> others into his scheme does not suggest that
                    Shakespeare was thinking in terms of networks, in the contemporary sense of the
                    word, when the play's characters speak of <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >webs,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">nets,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">mesh,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">snares,</quote> and being <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">perplexed.</quote> The play does, however, persistently mobilize
                    the language of webs and nets as a way to dramatize the discord between them.
                    The network captures how the playtext spins a <q>web</q> or <q>net</q> of
                    conflict between the characters in the language of the text and between the
                    bodies of the speakers on stage as a linguistic and physical way to structure
                    intersubjective tension.</p>
                <p> The network visualization of Act 5, Scene 2, alongside frames from two
                    performances of the play, show the extent to which Othello is <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#burge1965">perplexed in the extreme</quote> in a
                    web of other characters (<ptr target="#burge1965"/>; <ptr target="#parker1995"
                    />; <ptr target="#nunn1990"/>). The network of speakers <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">enmeshes</quote> Othello in this scene of murderous
                    unraveling in a <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">perplexed</quote>
                    relationship to others that matches the density and clustering found in other
                    tragedies (<ref target="#figure16">Figures 16-20</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure16">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Othello</title>, Act 5, Scene 2.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure17">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Othello</title> 5.2 (Oliver Parker
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure18">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Othello</title> 5.2 (Oliver Parker
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure18.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure19">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Othello</title> 5.2 (Stuart Burge
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure19.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure20">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Othello</title> 5.2 (Trevor Nunn
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure20.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The final scene of violence, then, demonstrates that Othello is not <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">all-in-all sufficient</quote> (4.1.262), but comes
                    to be defined by his binding in a network of other characters circumscribing him
                    at the moment of his self-destruction. For Othello, his binding in the network
                    precipitated by Iago's scheme signifies a basic confusion or <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">perplexity</quote> in defining the self.</p>
                <p>To extend the visual homology, the network of Act 5, Scene 2 in <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title> corresponds to the arrangement of bodies in
                    productions featuring actors as diverse as Tennant, Branagh, Richard Burton, and
                    Sir Laurence Olivier (<ptr target="#doran2008"/>; <ptr target="#branagh1996"/>;
                        <ptr target="#gielgud1964"/>; <ptr target="#olivier1948"/>). The network
                    visualization is structurally analogous to the clustering of bodies that results
                    in the various performances of Act 5, Scene 2 (<ref target="#figure21">Figures
                        21-26</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure21">
                    <head><title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, Act 5, Scene 2.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure21.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure22">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 5.2 (Gregory Doran
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure22.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure23">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 5.2 (Kenneth Branagh
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure23.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure24">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 5.2 (Kenneth Branagh
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure24.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure25">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 5.2 (John Gielgud
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure25.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure26">
                    <head>Performance of <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 5.2 (Laurence Olivier
                        production).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure26.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In the networks and the performance staging, Hamlet lies at the focal point of
                    the network of bodies defining the final scene. Claudius, Laertes, Gertrude,
                    Horatio, Osric, Fortinbras, the Ambassador from England, and the
                        <soCalled>audience</soCalled> all are clustered around Hamlet’s body as the
                    hub of this final tragic tableau as a network of mangled bodies. To a certain
                    extent, the film images demonstrate that the collision of bodies on stage as a
                    way to precipitate conflict and disorder is somewhat obvious - characters need
                    to be brought together to engage physically and to inflict violence upon one
                    another. However, readers of Shakespearean drama such as Nietzsche, Hegel,
                    Bradley, and other critics of tragedy in general in their wake have focused on
                    the thematic content of disorder, chaos, and the breaking of the social order,
                    without adequately acknowledging the organization of bodies in space - close
                    connections and physical proximity - as the basic condition needed to create a
                    theatrical frame for the tearing apart of human relations being expressed in the
                    plot.</p>
                <p> The network and each film’s <foreign xml:lang="fr">mise-en-scène</foreign>
                    cannot be identical since every performance requires interpretive decisions left
                    open by the text to each director and actor. The point of the network analysis
                    is not to say that every performance will be the same, which is obviously
                    impossible. What is significant in the comparison in the network to the two
                    performances is that despite the artistic latitude opened by Shakespeare’s
                    plays, the underlying structural logic defining the relationship between the
                    characters as a chaotic arrangement of bodies in space in this catastrophic
                    scene is remarkably consistent.<note> Ichikawa has emphasized the important, and
                        largely ignored, role of corpses in shaping the space of the Shakespearean
                        stage. For this, see: <ptr target="#ichikawa2013" loc="129f."/></note> The
                    spatial organization of the network describes a character-space that directors
                    and actors populate with movements, gestures, and speech. We could examine many
                    more scenes to compare the network to the performance as a mode of
                    methodological control. But beyond verification, the point of the present
                    analysis is to suggest that the network visualization method can teach us
                    something new about Shakespeare’s plays that revises a widely-held critical
                    consensus. The network analysis performed here opens up a space for reading
                    between text and performance, precisely as Weimann proposes, and should not be
                    understood as an authoritative account of tragedy. This represents the beginning
                    of a methodological conversation, rather than the final word on Shakespearean
                    tragedy in networks or in performance.</p>
                <p> These claims may seem terribly abstracted from the content of the play itself.
                    But Shakespeare’s text demonstrates a persistent metatheatrical preoccupation
                    with precisely this translation of words into embodied performance, or how
                    language can be represented in space. Hamlet defines himself in his final
                    moments not in terms of an ontology - moving away from the question of <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">to be or not to be</quote> - but rather in terms
                    of his literariness: <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">in this harsh world draw
                        thy breath in pain / To tell my story</quote> (5.2.290-291). By impelling
                    Horatio to <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">report</quote> him <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">aright</quote> and by giving Fortinbras his <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">dying voice,</quote> (5.2.298) Hamlet transforms
                    his afterlife, that <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">undiscovered
                        country</quote> into an act of correct narration, a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">story.</quote> Hamlet’s final transplantation of voice focuses
                    on the act of linguistic articulation and <q>report.</q> However, Horatio’s
                    final story is not vocative or oratorical in nature. Rather, Horatio and
                    Fortinbras perform a crucial modification in transforming Hamlet’s story into a
                    spatial arrangement of bodies on a <q>stage</q>: <quote rend="block" source="#canonical"
                            ><l>Horatio: Give order that these bodies</l>
                        <l> High on a stage be placed to the view;</l>
                        <l> And let me speak to th’yet unknowing world</l>
                        <l> How these things came about. So shall you hear</l>
                        <l> Of carnal, bloody, and unnatural acts,</l>
                        <l> Of accidental judgments, casual slaughters,</l>
                        <l> Of deaths put on by cunning and forced cause;</l>
                        <l> And, in this upshot, purposes mistook</l>
                        <l> Fall’n on th’inventors’ heads. All this can I</l>
                        <l> Truly deliver.</l>
                        <l>Fortinbras: Let us haste to hear it,</l>
                        <l> And call the noblest to the audience.</l>
                        <l>[…]</l>
                        <l>Horatio: Of that I shall have also cause to speak,</l>
                        <l> And from his mouth whose voice will draw on more.</l>
                        <l> But let this same be presently performed,</l>
                        <l> Even while men’s minds are wild, lest more mischance </l>
                        <l> Of plot and errors happen. (5.2.321-339)</l></quote> Horatio’s account
                    moves away from the idiom of <q>story,</q>
                    <q>report,</q> and <q>voice,</q> dictated by Hamlet. He instead orders that
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">these bodies / High on a stage be placed to
                        the view,</quote> translating Hamlet’s <q>story</q> and the act of
                        <q>reporting</q> from the articulation of the voice to a spatial arrangement
                    of bodies. The story is told not only in words, but also in the placement of
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">bodies high on stage</quote> as the
                    materials of <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">carnal, bloody, and unnatural
                        acts, / Of accidental judgments, casual slaughters, / Of deaths put on by
                        cunning and forced cause.</quote> These bodies function in the plane of
                    vision - they are <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">placed to the view</quote> -
                    transmuting Hamlet’s story into an act of spectatorship. Fortinbras compounds
                    this definition of the metatheatrical space by calling the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">audience</quote> and commanding that the soldiers bear Hamlet
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">to the stage.</quote> Horatio insists that
                    the <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">story</quote> will not take the form of an
                    ode or an oratory. He argues that the voice given to him by Hamlet is
                    insufficient to represent the events of the tragedy, since he will have to
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">draw on more</quote> than speaking alone.
                    The ultimate account of Hamlet’s life takes on the form of a theatrical
                    performance: it will be <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">presently
                        performed.</quote> The performance in question exerts a
                        <soCalled>wild</soCalled> effect, reflecting the chaotic social disorder and
                    violence of the final scene. For Horatio, the <q>plot</q> will paradoxically be
                    most accurate, with the fewest <q>errors</q> and <q>mischance,</q> in this state
                    of wildness. As in the preceding reading of the network, the bodies densely
                    clustered on stage for the performance of Hamlet’s story reflects the state of
                    wildness that concludes the play. The network analysis corresponds with
                    Horatio’s own metatheatrical appraisal of performance. Both lead to the
                    conclusion that the gathering and performance of bodies in the space of the
                    stage is the most accurate way to recount the <q>wild</q> disordering of
                    Elsinore’s social bonds.</p>
                <p>Reading the contours of the network as a way to translate the text into the
                    relationship of bodies in space is not an anachronistic imposition of digital
                    tools onto the Shakespearean text. The network visualization follows the rules
                    of Hamlet’s own metatheatrical commentary, and a commonplace understanding in
                    the Renaissance of the crosstalk between the body and the text. If anything,
                    this reading strategy converting language into spatial relationships takes
                    seriously the metatheatrical rules of performance that Hamlet himself
                    articulates in the play. In the <q>purpose of playing</q> speech in Act 3, Scene
                    2, Hamlet advises the players to <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >suit the action to the word, the word to the action,</quote> insisting that
                    proper performance technique requires a movement beyond the enunciated word to a
                    more dynamic conversion of the written word into the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">actions</quote> of the moving body. The
                    translation of word to action occurs in space, indicated in Hamlet’s statement
                    of the <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">purpose of
                        playing.</quote>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#canonical">…the purpose of playing, whose
                        end, both at the first and now, was and is to hold as ‘twere the mirror up
                        to nature, to show virtue her own feature, scorn her own image, and the very
                        age and body of the time his form and pressure. (3.2.19-22)</quote>
                    Transmuting the word into dramatic action functions as a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">mirror up to nature</quote> in space, <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">showing,</quote> representing <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#canonical">images,</quote> and revealing to the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">very age and body of the
                        time</quote> the physical contours of <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">his form and pressure.</quote> The mirror analogy,
                    and the gesture to Aristotle’s image of the wax seal as a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">form and pressure</quote> defines <q>playing</q>
                    as a play in space - a specular optics or an experience of spectatorship -
                    constituted by a visual array of images, bodies, and forms <ptr
                        target="#aristotle1936" loc="412a6–412b6"/>. Putting Hamlet’s body on a
                        <soCalled>stage</soCalled> at the end of the play is therefore a fitting
                    final confirmation of his preoccupation with <q>playing.</q> Beyond his specific
                    fate, however, Hamlet’s injunction to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">suit the action to the word, the word to the
                        action</quote> reflects a broad Renaissance <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >topos</foreign> understanding the body’s gestures as a crucial component of
                    linguistic communication <ptr target="#hammond1992" loc="82"/>. One example
                    within Shakespeare’s corpus is the response of the witnesses at the conclusion
                    of the <title rend="italic">Winter’s Tale</title>: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#canonical">There was speech in their dumbnesse, Language in
                        their very gesture</quote> (5.2.11-12). The convertibility of body and
                    language was not simply theatrical, however, with Thomas Wilson’s rhetorical
                    manual calling for <quote rend="inline" source="#wilson1909">the whole bodie
                        stirring together</quote> as an embodied component of rhetorical eloquence
                    and delivery <ptr target="#wilson1909" loc="220–221"/>. Hamlet’s model of
                    visualizing the word that <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >denotes</quote> the spatial <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical"
                        >play</quote> of actions and of bodies is precisely what the network
                    analysis attempts to accomplish by using the language of the text as the basis
                    of tracing the social links between different characters in space. This is not
                    to claim over-literally that Hamlet urges us to create networks. He is, however,
                    concerned with the translation of the linguistic <q>word</q> of the playtext
                    into the <q>play</q> of bodies in visual space, which is the basic logic of the
                    network analysis method. For Hamlet, theater is not meant to be read as the
                    word, but rather <soCalled>shown</soCalled> as a series of images. The network
                    graph is a good way of analyzing these spatial relationships in a repeatable,
                    robust way representing the ephemeral experience of theatrical performance.</p>
                <p>The methodological problem lies in the fact that broad themes of conflict,
                    violence, and social disorder at the level of content and plot can be readily
                    perceived through reading, but visualizing the web of social relationships in
                    the reading process proves to be more difficult. Reading the Shakespearean text
                    necessarily requires a linear syntax, the unidirectional physical movement
                    through the language arranged in the space of the line on the page <ref
                        target="#figure27">Figure 27</ref>. <figure xml:id="figure27">
                        <head><title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, Act 5, Scene 2 printed in the
                            First Folio.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure27.png"/>
                    </figure> To begin to think about how the page translates to the stage,
                    Shakespeareans have taken up Jerome McGann’s famous dictum that the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#McGann1991">reading eye is a scanning mechanism as
                        well as a linear decoder</quote> by attempting to understand how the spatial
                    structure of the printed play influences the reading experience and performance
                        <ptr target="#McGann1991" loc="113"/>. For example, Margaret Jane Kidnie’s
                    focus on how stage directions force a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#kidnie2004">two-axis</quote> reading beyond linear syntax,
                    suggests that the printed page contains <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#kidnie2004">impressions of activity</quote> encoding actions to
                    be performed on stage <ptr target="#kidnie2004" loc="169"/>. The visualization
                    method we are proposing adds another dimension to a multi-axis reading practice
                    by translating the relationships (or <quote rend="inline" source="#kidnie2004"
                        >impressions of activity</quote>) traced on the printed or inscribed page
                    into the space of a network. The network organizes the language of the play into
                    coordinates in graphical space that can more accurately delineate the complex
                    relationships between multiple characters across all of the scenes composing the
                    play. The network graphing method therefore functions as an intermediate step in
                    the conversion of the unidimensional syntax of the written playtext into the 3D
                    performance of bodies in the space of the stage. </p>
                <p> The network’s visualization of character interactions within the space of
                    performance more accurately matches early modern understandings of the stage
                    itself as a place framing the actors’ bodies. The 1595 Swan sketch, which is the
                    only surviving drawing of the interior of an Elizabethan theater, shows a
                    performance in progress on the proscenium, with the actor’s bodies serving as
                    the focal point of the theatrical space. The positioning, motion, and embodied
                    gestures of the three characters on stage in the Swan sketch begin to tell a
                    story of social interaction based on the proximity and distance, and the
                    intensity of physical connection in space in precisely the same way that the
                    network attempts to capture based on the text’s language (<ref
                        target="#figure28">Figure 28</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure28">
                        <head>Buchel / DeWitt Sketch of the Swan Theatre (1595).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure28.jpg"/>
                    </figure> By contrast, influential modern renderings of the Globe Theatre’s
                    interior by C. Walter Hodges <ptr target="#hodges1947"/> represent the
                    Elizabethan theatre as a disembodied architectural space, focused on the
                    building’s structure (<ref target="#figure29">Figures 29-30</ref>). <figure
                        xml:id="figure29">
                        <head>C. Walter Hodges’ rendition of the Globe Theatre.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure29.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>C. Walter Hodges’ rendition of the Globe Theatre.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure30.jpg"/>
                    </figure>The Swan sketch suggests an Elizabethan understanding of theater
                    organized around the actors’ bodies as the hub of the performance space, while
                    more recent diagrams attempting to imagine the Globe have studied the theater as
                    an architectural problem, or in terms of the class stratification of the
                    audience <ptr target="#cook1997"/>. The actors on stage in the Swan sketch are
                    in the midst of performance, and the image presents the interaction and movement
                    of characters. The left hand of the standing actor touches the shoulder of the
                    seated actor facing him, and his right hand gestures outward. The proximity and
                    physical connection between the characters on stage contrasts with the motion of
                    the third character, who stands at a distance from the other two and is captured
                    in a state of more dynamic movement across the stage closer to the groundlings,
                    while gesturing away from his plane of motion. Hugh Richmond has argued that the
                    dynamism of Shakespearean performance was a function of the performance space
                    itself. The presence of pillars on the Globe’s stage blocked the sight lines of
                    spectators, and thus its design required <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#richmond2004">an enormously active, dynamic blocking plan</quote>
                    that was <quote rend="inline" source="#richmond2004">almost violently active
                        and mobile, rather like a rugby league match</quote> in order to ensure that
                    the audience could see what was happening <ptr target="#richmond2004" loc="74"
                    />. The Swan sketch’s attention to the positioning, gesture, and dynamic
                    movement of characters on the stage (or blocking, which Hammond believes to be
                    irrecoverable) affirms Richmond’s take, and represents a model of theatrical
                    space that organizes the characters’ bodies in performance in a state of motion,
                    rather than defining that space as disembodied architecture, or through the
                    conjectural experience of the audience. The network analysis corresponds closely
                    to the understanding of the theatrical space in terms of blocking and the
                    positioning of characters and bodies, and attempts to recuperate the early
                    modern vision of performance as the conversion of <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#richmond2004">action to the word, word to the action.</quote></p>
                <p> We have much more evidence about the importance of character-space and stage
                    geography in contemporary productions of Shakespeare. The director Gregory Doran
                    describes the Royal Shakespeare Company’s 2008 production of <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title> (visualized in <ref target="#figure22">Figure
                        22</ref>) as precisely a process of theatrical <q>translation</q> that begins with a bibliographical
                    examination of the Company’s First Folio edition, exploring the text <q>word-by-word, line-by-line</q> in
                    order to structure the blocking and positioning of the <q>stage geography.</q> The meticulous process of
                    close reading reveals the characters’ <q>relationships with each other,</q> and Doran insists that the playtext
                    itself contains a sort of blueprint for the organization of, and movement
                    within, space, apart from the director’s intervention: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#doran2008">the scenes begin to move
                            themselves</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2008" loc="1–5"/>
                    </cit>. The network’s approach to understanding the play’s social world by
                    reasserting the importance of character-space as an organizing principle of the
                    playtext hews closely to the imagination of theatrical performance as the
                    clustering of bodies interacting within the spatial geography of the stage,
                    evinced by the Swan Sketch and as the mode of <q>translation</q> between
                        <q>words</q> and <q>stage geography</q> practiced by the Royal Shakespeare
                    Company today.</p>
                <p> Shakespeare’s plays and Renaissance theatrical discourse thus contain a latent
                    meditation on the movement from text to performance, from words to bodies
                    performing on stage, which the network method allows the critic to perceive.
                    Hamlet’s final metatheatrical preoccupation with how <q>story,</q>
                    <q>voice,</q> and linguistic <q>report</q> can be translated into <q>bodies high on a stage placed to the view</q>
                    to be <q>presently performed</q> before an
                        <q>audience</q> shows that the
                    Shakespearean text contains within itself a blueprint of sorts describing how to
                    perform the movement from text to stage. With network visualizations, the critic
                    is able to conduct a form of double reading, unpacking the signification of the
                    printed language composing the text simultaneously with a spatial analysis
                    showing how the text’s language structures a relationship between speakers on
                    stage.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A New Vantage Point on Shakespeare’s Dramatic Art and Network Theory</head>
                <p> We are beginning to move our understanding of Shakespearean tragedy away from
                    the <soCalled>conflict and waste</soCalled> hypothesis mobilized by countless
                    critics since Bradley. Rather, the paradoxical theatrical move of linking
                    together as a means of disordering the social gestures to the logic of
                    enantiosis, or <foreign xml:lang="la">discordia concors</foreign>, articulated
                    by the pre-Socratics and later appropriated as a model by both Hegel and
                    Nietzsche to define tragedy <ptr target="#McAlindon1991" loc="11 and 261–262"/>.
                    If Bradley’s understanding of tragedy as a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#bradley1909">division of spirit involving conflict and
                        waste</quote> attempted to reject the Hegelian and Nietzschean view of
                    tragedy as a dialectic of order and disorder, the network visualization shows
                    that Shakespeare’s playtext itself structures the space of tragic scenes in a
                    more nuanced, if paradoxical, way <ptr target="#hegel1975"/>
                    <ptr target="#nietzsche1956"/>. The performance of tragedy is not characterized
                    by a wasting away or violent incoherence, nor is it defined by a dialectical
                    movement of order and disorder. Rather, the network shows that scenes of tragic
                    violence perform a disordering of the social by organizing the characters as a
                    densely clustered network of bodies arranged in theatrical space. The scattering
                    of social bonds at the level of plot requires a movement away from order and
                    toward the alternative organizational indices of <emph>density</emph> and
                        <emph>clustering</emph> as ways to measure social bonds or connectedness at
                    the level of the theatrical discourse, or the language structuring the
                    relationships of characters and their bodies in the space of performance.</p>
                <p> The network visualizations thus demonstrate spatially that the anti-social
                    explosions of violence tearing apart the social order of the play’s world
                    require the assembly of a dense social network on stage in order to be
                    represented to the audience. Shakespeare’s plays represent systems of increased
                    disorder in these paradigmatic scenes of tragedy by creating a different form of
                    order - the network - on stage. The clustering patterns of the network differ
                    substantially from the social order of the beginning of the plays, defined by
                    hierarchies characterized by a neat hub and spoke organization in space. The
                    counterintuitive play of a disordering made possible by the ordering of a
                    network corresponds to actor network theory’s appropriation of Michel Serres’
                    definition of social systems. As John Law describes, ANT has embraced Serres’
                    description of the social world as <quote rend="inline" source="#law2009"
                        >patches of order in a sea of disorder</quote> as an organizing principle of
                    networks <ptr target="#law2009" loc="5"/>.<note> Also note <ptr
                            target="#latour1996" loc="4"/>: <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#latour1996">Universality or order are not the rule but the
                            exceptions that have to be accounted for. Loci, contingencies or
                            clusters are more like archipelagos on a sea than like lakes dotting a
                            solid land.</quote></note> For Law, the form of the network traces the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#law2009">boundaries between order and
                        disorder</quote> and is capable of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#law2009">imagining the uncertain messengers
                            that pass between different orders or between order and disorder</quote>
                        <ptr target="#law2009" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. For theorists such as Law and Latour, then, the network structure can
                    represent social systems forged in the interaction of order and disorder in a
                    way that traditional models built upon the assumption of order as the absence of
                    disorder (such as hierarchies, rankings, organizational charts, or dendrograms)
                    cannot. The interface between order and disorder also functions as a central
                    concept in Niklas Luhmann’s influential alternative account of the network as a
                    boundary between an organized system and the arbitrary, complex, and chaotic
                    world surrounding it. For Luhmann as for network theorists, the network
                    represents a space of order and the <quote rend="inline" source="#luhmann1995"
                        >reduction of complexity</quote> in a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#luhmann1995">sea</quote> of disorder and maximum entropy <ptr
                        target="#luhmann1995" loc="27"/>. Both influential network models define the
                    social system as a pocket of order and reduced chaos in a vast universe defined
                    by randomness and disorder. </p>
                <p> The present analysis of the networks traced within Shakespeare’s plays reverses
                    these precedents set by actor network theory and by Luhmann. The Shakespearean
                    networks do not create order as something different or partitioned from a
                    surrounding state of disorder, and networks do not represent an oasis of order
                    in a bleak entropic desert of disorder. Rather, Shakespeare’s plays present a
                    dramatic social world that turns the logic of the empirical networks suggested
                    by Law, Latour, and Luhmann on its head. Shakespearean tragedy stirs the reader
                    and audience by representing a state of chaotic social disorder emerging from
                    the assembly of a densely organized network of bodies and characters on stage.
                    The characteristic disordering of the social world in the plot of Shakespearean
                    tragedy requires the construction of an ever-increasingly dense social network
                    of actors, agents, bodies, witnesses, combatants, interlocutors, or characters
                    crowding the theatrical space where the chaos unfolds. Tearing apart the
                    relationships structuring the play’s initial social world - ordered by laws,
                    decrees, rules, ranks, filial bonds, gender norms, national or geographical
                    allegiances, and hierarchies - requires a new form of social order that
                    represents the complete overthrow of that original hierarchy. The new social
                    order resulting from Shakespeare’s tragedies is a state of disorder most
                    appropriately represented in the form of the network that visualizes this
                    counterintuitive spatial organization that is not based upon sharp boundaries
                    between order and disorder. In this seemingly paradoxical inversion of social
                    cause and effect, a new order captured by the network rises from a state of
                    chaotic tragic disorder, which is defined in terms of the asymmetrical,
                    seemingly chaotic form of network complexity, density, and clustering. The
                    network coalesces according to a logic best described as diffuse, non-linear,
                    intercalcated, non-hierarchical, multidimensional, and perhaps rhizomatic <ptr
                        target="#deleuze1987"/>. Understanding the network in this manner thus
                    revises an old story in Shakespeare studies echoed by several generations of
                    critics that describes the overthrow of the social order as a unifying theme of
                    the Shakespearean corpus. According to our reading, what seems to be an
                    explosion of chaos and disorder in the plot in fact sets the stage for tracing a
                    new social order of the non-hierarchical network on stage. Shakespeare’s plays
                    therefore do not destroy the social regime through a chaotic disordering, but
                    rather unbuilds the old social order based upon hierarchy, family, or law so as
                    to reimagine the social in terms of the rhizomatic branching of the network
                    through performance. The network, then, is not only a tool to explain the social
                    structure of Shakespeare’s plays. By the end of the tragedies, its concatenated,
                    non-linear form becomes the structure of a disordered social world itself,
                    leading us to a new imagination of social organization on stage based on density
                    and clustering.</p>
                <p> What can we make of network theory after this analysis of Shakespeare’s plays?
                    This analysis of Shakespeare's tragedies reveals a more nuanced model of a
                    social network, which does not simply describe a mode of reduced complexity or
                    heightened organization (as Luhmann argues) or shape the relationships between
                    subjects and objects (as argued by Latour and Law). The network demonstrates a
                    counterintuitive mechanism where actors perform a disordering of the basic
                    coherence of the social by organizing bodies together into a network.
                    Shakespeare’s plays use these eruptions of social disorder as an occasion to
                    forge a new mode of non-hierarchical, non-linear sociality in the form of the
                    network. This analysis stands as an early modern revision of network theories
                    that have been created with contemporary data, and have not adequately studied
                    the historicity of networks across time. </p>
                <p> Our case study on Shakespearean tragedy performs the methodological shift from
                    network theory to the description and analysis of actual networks that Bruno
                    Latour has proposed. Latour laments that although the scholarly community has
                    access to a <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2011">mass of data,</quote> this
                    information is only <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2011">accessible through an incredibly
                            poor visual landscape</quote>
                        <ptr target="#latour2011" loc="809"/>
                    </cit>. He has recently asserted that the next horizon in analyzing the social
                    networks composing our world involves a methodological shift from network theory
                    to actual networks that <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2011">transform the mass of
                        quali-quantitative data</quote> into a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#latour2011">visual datascape</quote>
                        <ptr target="#latour2011" loc="809"/>
                    </cit>. What is needed to enact this shift are more robust and accurate
                    visualizations of networks built upon a combination of qualitative and
                    quantitative data that can represent the intercalcated lattice of
                        <q>performances,</q>
                    <q>parts</q> and <q>actors</q> working in relation to one another, precisely in
                    the way that the dramatic performance visualizes the playtext as an embodied,
                    visual performance of actors interacting on stage. </p>
                <p> We have argued that the network method suggested by Latour is a way to harness
                    the technical resources of the digital humanities to bridge the age-old divide
                    between text and stage in the study of Shakespeare. The networks decipher how
                    Shakespeare encodes within the text the spatial relationships of characters in
                    performance space, and his plays give us a rule book of sorts to accomplish
                    this, by meta-theatrically meditating upon how this translation of word to
                    bodies in space occurs. The digital method reveals a network structure that
                    allows us to revise a widely accepted story on social disorder and the overthrow
                    of law in Shakespeare’s plays, but this is by no means exhaustive, and it
                    represents the beginning of new readings made possible by network visualization.
                    The network method allows us to tell new stories about Shakespeare, and provides
                    us a different technical vantage point fusing textual close reading and the
                    study of performance in space. As a critical tool, the networks open up a
                    multi-tiered method that tests the digital visualizations against the results of
                    close readings and staged theatrical productions of the same scenes. Our case
                    study of the social networks of Shakespeare’s tragedies proposes a hybrid
                    methodology that investigators and students can use to engage in several
                    parallel techniques so as to gain multiple critical perspectives on a single
                    literary problem. Ultimately, we propose that the network methodology opens a
                    new perspective on Shakespeare’s dramatic art. Far from turning his body of work
                    into a cold, inert dataset that seems antithetical to humanistic inquiry, the
                    network method enlivens the text, allowing a wide range of readers - from
                    scholars publishing research to undergraduates encountering his plays for the
                    first time - to perceive the subtle manner by which the movements and energies
                    of embodied theatrical performance inhere within the Shakespearean text.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>James Lee was generously supported by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation’s Digital
                    Bridges for Humanistic Inquiry Grant. The authors would like to thank Erik
                    Simpson, Blaine Greteman, Steve Andrews, Tim Arner, and Bill Ingram for their
                    input and useful discussions along the way.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aristotle1936" label="Aristotle">Aristotle<title rend="italic">On the
                        Soul</title>, W.S. Hett (tr). Loeb Classical Library, Cambridge
                    (1936).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aebischer2004" label="Aebischer 2004">Aebischer, Pascale. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare's Violated Bodies: Stage and Screen
                        Performance</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bakhtin1984" label="Bakhtin 1984">Bakhtin, Mikhail. <title
                        rend="italic">Rabelais and his World.</title> Indiana University Press,
                    Bloomington (1984).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bergeron1991" label="Bergeron 1991">Bergeron, David M. <title
                        rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Richard II</title> and Carnival
                        Politics,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly,</title> 42, no. 1 (1991): 33.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry1972" label="Berry 1972">Berry, Ralph. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Shakespearean Comedy and Northrop Frye,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Essays in Criticism,</title> 22, no. 1 (1972):
                    33–40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgatti2011" label="Borgatti 2011">Borgatti, Stephen and Halgin,
                    Daniel. <title rend="quotes">On Network Theory,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Organization Science</title>, 22, no. 5 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley1909" label="Bradley 1909">Bradley, A.C. <title rend="italic"
                        >Oxford Lectures on Poetry</title>. Macmillan, London (1909). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bristol1983" label="Bristol 1983">Bristol, Michael D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Carnival and the Institutions of Theater in Elizabethan
                        England,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ELH,</title> 50, no. 4 (1983): 637.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buchel" label="Buchel">Buchel, Aernout, after a drawing of Johannes de
                    Witt. University Library, Utrecht, Ms. 842, fol. 132r.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cheney2008" label="Cheney 2008">Cheney, Patrick. <title rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare's Literary Authorship</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2008). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="claycomb2013" label="Claycomb 2013">Claycomb, Ryan. <title
                        rend="quotes">Here’s How You Produce This Play: Towards a Narratology of
                        Dramatic Texts,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Narrative,</title> 21.2 (May 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cook1997" label="Cook 1997">Cook, Ann Jennalie. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Audiences: Investigation, Interpretation, Invention.</title> In Cox and
                    Kastan (eds), <title rend="italic">A New History of Early English Drama</title>,
                    Columbia University Press, New York (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="danner2003" label="Danner 2003">Danner, Bruce. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Speaking Daggers,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly,</title> 54.1 (2003): 29-62.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="danson1984" label="Danson 1984">Danson, Lawrence. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Jonsonian Comedy and the Discovery of the Social Self,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PMLA,</title> 99.2 (March 1984).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="degrazia1993" label="De Grazia and Stallybrass 1993">De Grazia,
                    Margreta, and Peter Stallybrass. <title rend="quotes">The Materiality of the
                        Shakespearean Text,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly,</title> 44.3 (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deleuze1987" label="Deleuze and Guattari 1987">Deleuze, Gilles, &amp;
                    Guattari, Felix (1987). <title rend="italic">A Thousand Plateaus</title> (B.
                    Massumi, Trans.). Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DeMarinis1993" label="De Marinis 1993">De Marinis, Marco. <title
                        rend="italic">The Semiotics of Performance.</title> Indiana University
                    Press, Bloomington (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doran2008" label="Doran 2008">Doran, Gregory. <title rend="italic">The
                        Rehearsal Scrapbook.</title> The Royal Shakespeare Company,
                    Stratford-upon-Avon (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dubini1991" label="Dubini and Aldrich 1991">Dubini, Paola and Aldrich,
                    Howard. <title rend="quotes">Personal and Extended Networks are Central to the
                        Entrepreneurial Process,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Business Venturing</title>, 6, no. 5
                    (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="easley2010" label="Easley and Kleinberg 2010">Easley, David and
                    Kleinberg, Jon. <title rend="italic">Networks, Crowds, and Markets: Reasoning
                        about a Highly Connected World. </title>Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ebers1997" label="Ebers 1997">Ebers, Mark. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Explaining inter-organizational network formation,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The formation of inter-organizational networks,</title> 1
                    (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eliot1998" label="Eliot 1998">Eliot, T.S. <title rend="quotes">Hamlet
                        and his Problems.</title> In <title rend="italic">The Sacred Wood,</title>
                    Dover, Mineola, NY (1998). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="erne2013" label="Erne 2013">Erne, Lukas. <title rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare as Literary Dramatist.</title> Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ewbank1983" label="Ewbank 1983">Ewbank, Inga-Stina. <title>The Word in
                        the Theater.</title> In Muir, Halio, Palmer (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare, Man of the Theater</title>, University of Delaware Press,
                    Newark (1983). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fludernik2008" label="Fludernik 2008">Fludernik, Monika. <title
                        rend="quotes">Narrative and Drama.</title> In Pier and Landa (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Theorizing Narrativity,</title> Walter de Gruyter, Berlin
                    (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foakes2003" label="Foakes 2003">Foakes, Reginald Anthony. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare and Violence</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2003).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldberg2013" label="Goldberg 2013">Goldberg, Jonathan. <title
                        rend="quotes">Carnival in The Merchant of Venice,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Postmedieval,</title> 4.4 (December 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldman1985" label="Goldman 1985">Goldman, Michael. <title
                        rend="italic">Acting and Action in Shakespearean Tragedy.</title> Princeton
                    University Press, Princeton (1985).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gorfain1991" label="Gorfain 1991">Gorfain, Phyllis. <title
                        rend="quotes">Toward a Theory of Play and the Carnivalesque in
                        Hamlet,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hamlet Studies,</title> 13, no. 1-2 (1991): 25-49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grady2001" label="Grady 2001">Grady, Hygh. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Falstaff: Subjectivity between the Carnival and the Aesthetic,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Modern Language Review,</title> 96, no. 3 (July
                    2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grandjean2015" label="Grandjean 2015">Grandjean, Martin. <title
                        rend="quotes">Network visualization: mapping Shakespeare’s
                        tragedies,</title>
                    <ptr target="http://www.martingrandjean.ch/network-visualization-shakespeare"/>,
                    (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="granovetter1973" label="Granovetter 1973">Granovetter, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Strength of Weak Ties,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">American Journal of Sociology</title>, 78, no. 6
                    (1973).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="granovetter1983" label="Granovetter 1983">Granovetter, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Strength of Weak Ties: A Network Theory Revisited,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sociological Theory</title>, 1 (1983).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greteman2015" label="Greteman 2015">Greteman, Blaine. <title
                        rend="quotes">Milton and the Early Modern Social Network: The Case of the
                            <title rend="italic">Epitaphium Damonis,</title></title>
                    <title rend="italic">Milton Quarterly,</title> 50 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gurr1992" label="Gurr 1992">Gurr, Andrew. <title rend="italic">The
                        Shakespearean Stage, 1574-1642.</title> Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foakes2006" label="Foakes 2006">Foakes, R. A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Performance Theory and Textual Theory: A Retort Courteous,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare,</title> 2, no. 1 (2006): 47–58.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hammond1992" label="Hammond 1992">Hammond, Antony. <title
                        rend="quotes">Encounters of the Third Kind in Stage-Directions in
                        Elizabethan and Jacobean Drama,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Studies in Philology,</title> 89.1 (Winter 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hegel1975" label="Hegel 1975">Hegel, G.W.F. <title rend="italic">Hegel
                        on Tragedy,</title> Anne and Henry Paolucci (eds). Harper and Row, New York
                    (1975).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heller2005" label="Heller 2005">Heller, Jennifer Louise. <title
                        rend="quotes">Space, Violence, and Bodies in Middleton and Cary,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Studies in English Literature 1500-1900,</title> 45, no. 2
                    (2005): 425-441.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hodges1947" label="Hodges 1947">C. Walter Hodges collection of
                    Elizabethan and other theatre drawings, Folger ART Box H688, Folger Shakespeare
                    Library, Washington, DC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hodges1953" label="Hodges 1953">Hodges, C. Walter. <title
                        rend="italic">The Globe restored : a study of the Elizabethan
                        theater.</title> E. Benn, London (1953). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ichikawa2013" label="Ichikawa 2013">Ichikawa, Mariko. <title
                        rend="italic">The Shakespearean Stage Space.</title> Cambridge University
                    Press, Cambridge (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jahn2001" label="Jahn 2001">Jahn, Manfred. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Narrative Voice and Agency in Drama: Aspects of a Narratology of
                        Drama,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Literary History,</title> 32.3 (Summer 2001):
                    659–79.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kastan2001" label="Kastan 2001">Kastan, David Scott. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Book</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                    Cambridge (2001). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kastan1985" label="Kastan 1985">Kastan, David Scott. <title
                        rend="quotes">All’s Well That Ends Well and the Limits of Comedy,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ELH,</title> 52, no. 3 (1985).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kidnie2004" label="Kidnie 2004">Kidnie, Margaret Jane. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Staging of Shakespeare’s Drama in Print Editions.</title>
                    In Erne and Kidnie (eds), <title rend="italic">Textual Performances,</title>
                    Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knowles1998" label="Knowles 1998">Knowles, Ronald. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare and Carnival.</title> Palgrave, London:
                    (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour2011" label="Latour 2011">Latour, Bruno. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Networks, Societies, Spheres: Reflections of an Actor-Network
                        Theorist,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Communication,</title> 5
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour2007" label="Latour 2007">Latour, Bruno. <title rend="italic"
                        >Reassembling the Social</title>. Oxford University Press, Oxford (2007). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour1996" label="Latour 1996">Latour, Bruno. <title rend="quotes">On
                        actor-network theory. A few clarifications plus more than a few
                        complications,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Soziale welt,</title> 47.4 (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="law2009" label="Law 2009">Law, John. <title rend="quotes">Actor
                        Network Theory and Material Semiotics.</title> In Bryan S. Turner (ed),
                        <title rend="italic">The New Blackwell Companion to Social Theory,</title>
                    John Wiley &amp; Sons, Oxford (2009). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lin2012" label="Lin 2012">Lin, Erika T. <title rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare and the Materiality of Performance.</title> Palgrave Macmillan,
                    London (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="logan1982" label="Logan 1982">Logan, Thad Jenkins. <title
                        rend="quotes">Twelfth Night: The Limits of Festivity,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Studies in English Literature, 1500-1900,</title> 22.2
                    (1982).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="long2013" label="Long and So 2013">Long, Hoyt and So, Richard. <title
                        rend="quotes">Network Analysis and the Sociology of Modernism,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">boundary 2,</title> Volume 40, Number 2 (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="luhmann1995" label="Luhmann 1995">Luhmann, Niklas. <title
                        rend="italic">Social Systems,</title> Bednarz and Baecker (tr). Stanford
                    University Press, Stanford (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marshall2002" label="Marshall 2002">Marshall, Cynthia. <title
                        rend="italic">The Shattering of the Self: Violence, Subjectivity, and Early
                        Modern Texts</title>. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore
                    (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="McAlindon2013" label="McAlindon 2013">McAlindon, Tom. <title
                        rend="quotes">What is a Shakespearean Tragedy.</title> In Claire McEachern
                    (ed), <title rend="italic">The Cambridge companion to Shakespearean
                        tragedy,</title> Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="McAlindon1991" label="McAlindon 1991">McAlindon, Tom. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Tragic Cosmos</title>. Cambridge University
                    Press, Cambridge (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="McGann1991" label="McGann 1991">McGann, Jerome. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Textual Condition.</title> Princeton University Press, Princeton
                    (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2011" label="Moretti 2011">Moretti, Franco. <title
                        rend="quotes">Network Theory, Plot Analysis,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Pamphlets of the Stanford Literary Lab</title>
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="newman1987" label="Newman 1987">Newman, Karen. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Portia’s Ring: Unruly Women and Structures of Exchange in The Merchant of
                        Venice,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly,</title> 38.1 (1987).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="newman2010" label="Newman 2010">Newman, Mark. <title rend="italic"
                        >Networks: An Introduction. </title>Oxford University Press, Oxford
                    (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="newman2003" label="Newman 2003">Newman, Mark. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Structure and Function of Complex Networks,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SIAM Review,</title> 45.2 (2003).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nietzsche1956" label="Nietzsche 1956">Nietzsche, Friedrich. <title
                        rend="italic"><title rend="quotes">The Birth of Tragedy</title> and the
                            <title rend="quotes">Genealogy of Morals,</title></title> Francis
                    Golffing (tr). Doubleday, New York (1956).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nünning2008" label="Nünning 2008">Nünning, Ansgar, and Sommer, Roy.
                        <title rend="quotes">Diegetic and Mimetic Narrativity: Some further Steps
                        towards a Transgeneric Narratology of Drama.</title> In Pier and Landa
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">Theorizing Narrativity,</title> Walter de Gruyter,
                    Berlin (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="paul2008" label="Paul 2008">Paul, J Gavin. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Imprinting Performance: Editorial Mediations of Page and Stage,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare,</title> 4, no. 1 (2008): 22–40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pierson2014" label="Pierson 2014">Pierson, Emma. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Parsing is Such Sweet Sorrow,</title>
                    <ref target="fivethirtyeight.com/features/parsing-is-such-sweet-sorrow"
                        >fivethirtyeight.com/features/parsing-is-such-sweet-sorrow</ref>,
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pikli2010" label="Pikli 2010">Pikli, Natália. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Across Cultures: Shakespeare and the carnivalesque shrew,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">European Journal of English Studies, </title>14, no. 3
                    (2010): 235-248.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prendergast2005" label="Prendergast 2005">Prendergast, Christopher.
                        <title rend="quotes">Derrida's Hamlet,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SubStance,</title> 34, no. 1 (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richardson2007" label="Richardson 2007">Richardson, Brian. <title
                        rend="quotes">Drama and Narrative.</title> In David Herman (ed), <title
                        rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to Narrative,</title> Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richardson1987" label="Richardson 1987">Richardson, Brian. <title
                        rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Time Is Out of Joint</title>: Narrative
                        Models and the Temporality of the Drama,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Poetics Today,</title> 8.2 (1987).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richmond2004" label="Richmond 2004">Richmond, Hugh. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Theatre: A Dictionary of His Stage
                        Context</title>. Bloomsbury, London (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salingar1976" label="Salingar 1976">Salingar, Leo. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Traditions of Comedy.</title> Cambridge
                    University Press, 1976.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="santayana1968" label="Santayana 1968">Santayana, George. <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet.</title> In Henfrey, Norman (ed), <title rend="italic"
                        >The Selected Critical Writings of George Santayana,</title> Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (1968). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scott2000" label="Scott 2000">Scott, J. <title rend="italic">Social
                        Network Analysis: A Handbook.</title> Sage Publications, London
                    (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stiller2003" label="Stiller, Nettle, and Dunbar 2003">Stiller, J.,
                    Nettle, D., &amp; Dunbar, R. I. (2003). The small world of Shakespeare’s plays.
                        <title rend="italic">Human Nature, 14</title>(4), 397-408.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doran2009" label="Doran 2009">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, directed by Gregory Doran, performed by the
                    Royal Shakespeare Company. The British Broadcasting Corporation, London
                    (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="branagh1996" label="Branagh 1996">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, directed by Kenneth Branagh. Castle Rock
                    Entertainment, New York (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gielgud1964" label="Gielgud 1964">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, directed by John Gielgud. Theatrofilm, New
                    York (1964).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olivier1948" label="Olivier 1948">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, directed by Laurence Olivier. Two Cities
                    Films, London (1948).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nunn1990" label="Nunn 1990">Shakespeare, William. <title rend="italic"
                        >Othello</title>, directed by Trevor Nunn. The British Broadcasting
                    Corporation, London (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burge1965" label="Burge 1965">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Othello</title>, directed by Stuart Burge. National Theatre of
                    Great Britain, London (1965).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parker1995" label="Parker 1995">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">Othello</title>, directed by Oliver Parker. Castle Rock
                    Entertainment, New York (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wells2005" label="Wells and Taylor 2005">Shakespeare, William. <title
                        rend="italic">The Oxford Shakespeare</title>, Wells and Taylor (eds). Oxford
                    University Press, Oxford (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2013" label="Smith et al. 2013">Smith, et al. <title
                        rend="italic">Visualizing Theatrical Text: From Watching the Script to the
                        Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET),</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly,</title> 7.3 (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2009" label="Smith 2009">Smith, Emma. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Elizabethan and Jacobean Popular Theatre,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Oxford Podcast Lecture Series</title> (11/2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spenser2006" label="Spenser 2006">Spenser, Edmund. <title
                        rend="italic">The Faerie Queene,</title> Hamilton, A.C. (ed). Routledge, New
                    York (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stern2009" label="Stern 2009">Stern, Tiffany. <title rend="italic"
                        >Documents of Performance in Early Modern England.</title> Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (2009). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stern2004" label="Stern 2004">Stern, Tiffany. <title rend="italic"
                        >Making Shakespeare: From Stage to Page.</title> Psychology Press (2004). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2002" label="Taylor 2002">Taylor, Gary. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Shakespeare Plays on Renaissance Stages.</title> In Wells and Stanton
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to Shakespeare on
                        Stage</title>, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2002). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wasserman1994" label="Wasserman and Faust 1994">Wasserman, S. and
                    Faust K. <title rend="italic">Social Network Analysis.</title> Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (1994).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weingust2007" label="Weingust 2007">Weingust, Don. <title
                        rend="italic">Acting from Shakespeare’s First Folio: Theory, Text and
                        Performance</title>. Routledge, New York (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weimann2000" label="Weimann 2000">Weimann, Robert. <title
                        rend="italic">Author’s Pen and Actor’s Voice: Playing and Writing in
                        Shakespeare’s Theatre</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
                    (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weimann1999" label="Weimann 1999">Weimann, Robert. <title
                        rend="quotes">Playing with a Difference: Revisiting <q>Pen</q> and
                            <q>Voice</q> in Shakespeare's Theater,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly,</title> 50.4 (Winter, 1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weimann1987" label="Weimann 1987">Weimann, Robert. <title
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Popular Tradition in the Theater.</title>
                    Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore (1987). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilson1987" label="Wilson 1987">Wilson, Richard. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><title rend="quotes">Is This a Holiday?</title>: Shakespeare’s Roman
                        Carnival,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ELH,</title> 54, no. 1 (1987).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilson1909" label="Wilson 1909">Wilson, Thomas. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Arte of Rhetorique</title>, G.H. Mair (ed). Clarendon Press, Oxford
                    (1909). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="woloch2003" label="Woloch 2003">Woloch, Alex. <title rend="italic">The
                        One vs. The Many.</title> Princeton University Press, Princeton (2003). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yau2015" label="Yau 2015">Yau, Nathan. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Shakespeare tragedies as network graphs,</title>
                    <ptr
                        target="http://flowingdata.com/2015/12/30/shakespeare-tragedies-as-network-graphs"
                    />, (2015).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
