<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Attention Ecology: Trend Circulation and the Virality
                    Threshold</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Nicholas M <dhq:family>Van Horn</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Capital University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nvanhorn@capital.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Nicholas M. Van Horn is a professor in the Department of Psychology at
                            Capital University, where he teaches and researches in the
                            interdisciplinary field of computational cognitive neuroscience. His
                            work in this area represents the convergence of advances in a number of
                            related fields, including neuroscience, psychology &amp; psychophysics,
                            computer vision, artificial intelligence, mathematical modeling, as well
                            data science more broadly construed. In parallel with this work, he
                            researches online and networked data, including its effect on our
                            privacy and rights, actively writing and maintaining open source
                            software related to data mining, writing and productivity, statistical
                            analysis, and other software tools for automated analysis of text and
                            images. (<ref target="http://www.nicholasvanhorn.com"
                                >http://www.nicholasvanhorn.com</ref>)</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Aaron <dhq:family>Beveridge</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Florida</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>aaronbev79@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Aaron Beveridge is a PhD candidate in the Department of English at the
                            University of Florida. Aaron's teaching and research focus on the use of
                            data science tools and methods to research digital rhetoric and
                            networked writing. Grounded primarily in the study of social network
                            trends, his teaching and research interests also include media ecology,
                            the rhetoric of science, technical communication, and maker culture.
                        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sean <dhq:family>Morey</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>smorey@utk.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sean Morey is an assistant professor in the Department of English at the
                            University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Sean's work focuses on the
                            intersections of rhetoric, digital technologies, and environmental
                            studies with applications for the humanistic development of emerging
                            technologies. Sean's publications include <title rend="italic"
                                >Rhetorical Delivery and Digital Technologies: Networks, Affect,
                                Electracy</title> (Routledge 2015), <title rend="italic">Ecosee:
                                Image, Rhetoric, Nature</title> (SUNY 2009, co-edited with Sid
                            Dobrin), and <title rend="italic">Augmented Reality: Perspectives Across
                                Art, Industry, and the Humanities</title> (Parlor Press 2016,
                            co-edited with John Tinnell). </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000271</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2016-10-10">10 October 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>data mining</item>
                        <item>social media</item>
                        <item>twitter</item>
                        <item>viral</item>
                        <item>trend</item>
                        <item>circulation studies</item>
                        <item>writing studies</item>
                        <item>digital media</item>
                        <item>methodology</item>
                        <item>ecology</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2016-08-30">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article demonstrates the use of data mining methodologies for the study and
                    research of social media in the digital humanities. Drawing from recent
                    convergences in writing, rhetoric, and DH research, this article investigates
                    how trends operate within complex networks. Through a study of trend data mined
                    from Twitter, this article suggests the possibility of identifying a
                        <term>virality threshold</term> for Twitter trends, and the possibility that
                    such a threshold has broader implications for attention ecology research in the
                    digital humanities. This article builds on the theories of Jacques Derrida,
                    Richard Lanham, and Sidney Dobrin to suggest new theories and methodologies for
                    understanding how attention operates within complex media ecologies at a
                    macroscopic level. While many various theories and methods have investigated
                    writing, rhetoric, and digital media at the microscopic level, this article
                    contends that a complimentary macroscopic approach is needed to further
                    investigate how attention functions for network culture.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Data mining in Twitter in search of a <term>virality threshold</term> for
                    trends.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The phrase <q>this is trending</q> is so common, so deceptively innocent, that it
                often passes from speaker to listener without an opportunity to interrogate its
                validity. Nearly every broadcast of cable news, sports journalism, or entertainment
                media relies on this phrase to justify the attention paid to a particular event or
                topic of interest. For many forms of digital rhetoric, having <q>this is
                    trending</q> attached to a digital artifact is, in and of itself, the desired
                end goal for producing those artifacts — millions, and possibly, billions of visits,
                views, likes, or shares. This phrase quantifies attention and repackages it as a
                statement of value. Indeed, <q>this is trending</q> is no mere economics of
                attention. This phrase suggests that the object it describes has, during the process
                of attention accretion, become more than its accounting — the trending object
                acquires value. If attention somehow creates value for trending objects, then this
                process becomes even more powerful for digital artifacts that hyper-circulate at a
                viral level. </p>
            <p>Such questions of circulation and virality are of interest within writing studies,
                but writing-related fields are nascent in the use, approach, and methods related to
                the digital humanities. Recent conversations in writing studies, rhetoric, and
                composition have attempted to predict and understand how these fields might pursue
                research questions made possible by digital humanities tools, methods, and
                resources, or, at least, better understand where these fields intersect with the
                digital humanities. For instance, in their collection <title rend="italic">Rhetoric
                    and the Digital Humanities</title>, Jim Ridolfo and William Hart-Davidson write
                that although writing studies has a rich tradition in performing analysis with
                digital tools, building new tools, and securing National Endowments for the
                Humanities (NEH) Office of Digital Humanities (ODH) Digital Humanities Start-Up
                grants, there has been little understanding of how these fields intersect: <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#ridolfo2015">Despite the lengthy history of the
                        term <term>digital humanities</term> outside rhetoric and writing studies,
                        inside the field of rhetoric and writing studies there has been, up until
                        recently, very limited mention of it</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ridolfo2015" loc="2"/>
                </cit>. In addition, many DHers within English departments might be unfamiliar with
                how writing studies has made strides toward this field. Ridolfo and Hart-Davidson
                argue that this is, in part, due to the field’s concern with the teaching of writing
                within composition and professional writing classes, this concern mostly focusing on
                how such classes might adopt computers and other technology as part of its pedagogy.
                However, as writing studies moves away from researching writing primarily in terms
                of students and pedagogy, toward researching writing without subjects, digital
                humanities tools provide even more opportunity for looking at large data sets of
                writing that are not tied to questions of student agency or learning outcomes. </p>
            <p>Despite this turn away from writing subjects, the concept of audience remains central
                to research in rhetoric and writing studies. But in the era of Big Data and
                information overflow, it is increasingly difficult to identify an audience. While
                recent work with the canon of delivery, such as Collin Brooke’s work in <title
                    rend="italic">Lingua Fracta</title>
                <ptr target="#brooke2009"/> or Jim Ridolfo and Dànielle Nicole DeVoss’s concept of <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#ridolfo2009">rhetorical velocity</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ridolfo2009"/>
                </cit> attempt to account for audience reception via electronic delivery and the
                digital circulation of multimodal writing, these theories often focus on
                audience-as-user, how audience members, as individuals, receive and then
                re-circulate writing toward other audiences. Such theories are useful in thinking
                through how an audience remixes and re-delivers writing, but do not address the
                larger scales across which digital writing now circulates. </p>
            <p>In his work <title rend="italic">Postcomposition</title>, Sidney I. Dobrin argues
                that writing studies needs to push its investigations into these larger scales, into
                complex understandings of hyper-circulation and writing-as-system <ptr
                    target="#dobrin2011"/>. Dobrin’s argument parallels those made about literature
                studies, lately by Matthew Jockers, who proposes a methodology of macroanalysis to
                account for how patterns or trends emerge across large data sets of literary texts
                    <ptr target="#jockers2013"/>. The macroscopic perspective has often been
                understood in terms of <q>distance</q> and <q>artificial constructs</q> within the
                humanities — what Franco Moretti has termed <q>distance reading.</q> As Moretti
                explains, <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2007">abstraction is not an end in itself,
                        but a way to widen the domain of the literary historian, and enrich its
                        internal problematic</quote>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2007" loc="1"/>
                </cit>. </p>
            <p>Toward a macroanalysis of writing, this article performs a macroanalysis of Twitter
                in order to extend a theory of hyper-circulation that can help explain how
                macro-audiences engage with digital writing technologies. This article builds on
                Dobrin’s network theory by looking at how the concept of attention provides a
                macroscopic understanding of audience in complex networks of mediation. If many of
                the attempts underway to rewrite rhetorical concepts, such as delivery, focus on the
                microscopic invention and delivery of digital texts (the agency of individual
                users/writers), then attention ecology is the attempt to understand the macroscopic,
                aggregate trends occurring within social media as a way of identifying an audience
                in complex networks of mediation. Ultimately, the authors identify the term
                    <term>virality threshold</term> as a concept that may be useful for future
                researchers interested in macroscopic analyses of writing and audience. </p>
            <p>Certainly, the use of contagion metaphors (such as virality) to understand the spread
                of ideas and information among social groups is not new. Likewise, the threshold
                concept is also not a new addition to the discourse of idea circulation. Prior to
                the Internet and the subsequent invention of contemporary social networks, the terms
                    <term>contagion</term> and <term>threshold</term> were core concepts for
                Diffusion of Innovations (DoI) theory. Like the digital humanities, DoI was
                necessarily interdisciplinary as it sought to understand how new ideas were spread
                and adopted within various areas such as rural sociology, communication, education,
                marketing, general sociology, anthropology, economics, political science,
                agriculture, psychology, statistics, engineering, and others <ptr
                    target="#rogers1983" loc="53"/>. Everett M. Rogers' <title rend="italic"
                    >Diffusion of Innovations</title>, originally written in 1962, is credited with
                collating a diverse array of ideas from various disciplines to better understand <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#rogers1983">the process by which an innovation is
                        communicated through certain channels over time among the members of a
                        social system</quote>
                    <ptr target="#rogers1983" loc="6"/>
                </cit>. Rogers’ initial description of DoI theory focuses on the relationship
                between the concept of adoption and the idea of the threshold. Certainly, there are
                similarities between Rogers’ use of the term adoption and this article’s use of the
                term attention. For example, Rogers uses the example of people considering whether
                or not to join a riot or protest. In this example, an individual’s threshold is
                determined by the number of other people a person needs to observe taking part in
                the protest before they too will join. The concept of threshold, for DoI, thus
                refers to the amount of other adoptions a particular person needs to observe before
                they will adopt an innovation or action themselves. Someone who may be described as
                an early adopter will have a low threshold for the number of people they need to
                observe before choosing to take part in the protest. However, a person who needs to
                observe a large amount of people taking part in the protest would be described as
                having a high threshold according to Rogers — and therefore, they would be a defined
                as a late adopter. </p>
            <p>DoI theory remains active and relevant today for the study of social networks. Thomas
                W. Valente’s <title rend="italic">Network Models of the Diffusion of
                    Innovations</title> applies DoI theory to network analysis, and recent
                scholarship that applies DoI to the study of Twitter and other social networks
                builds on his work. Valente defines network analysis as <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#valente1995">a technique used to analyze the
                        pattern of interpersonal communication in a social system by determining who
                        talks to whom</quote>
                    <ptr target="#valente1995" loc="2"/>
                </cit>. While this article draws upon the interdisciplinary history and terminology
                made available by DoI theory, it also diverges from DoI theory in two key ways.
                First, recent theoretical work in writing studies puts pressure on network theories
                that are non-ecological — meaning, network theories that focus on individual users
                within individual networks, rather than focusing on the complex interactions of
                multiple networks. Therefore, this article replaces the user-as-node (person to
                person transmission of ideas within an individual network) with the location-as-node
                model (the circulation of ideas among and within multiple locations — among and
                within multiple networks). In contrast to user-as-node approaches, this article
                looks neither at users (or the adoption of ideas or innovations by users) nor does
                this article focus on any specific trend. Instead, this study considers only that a
                trend occurred, and that it was circulated among locations. </p>
            <p>As a result of the focus on locations rather than users (or subjects, or agents), the
                term <term>adoption</term> from DoI theory is replaced with the term
                    <term>attention</term> in this study — this is the second divergence from DoI
                theory. We argue that one way of analyzing how hyper-circulation occurs is by
                searching for indicators of attention and the degree to which such attention
                escalates. Using data science methodologies, we introduce a preliminary operational
                definition of <q>virality threshold</q> as one concept for beginning to think about
                macroscopic attention for writing studies and digital humanities
                    research.<note>While Valente does reference macroscopic methods, the framework
                    is only used to address the ways that network saturation and critical mass
                    effect potential changes in the adoption threshold of individuals within a
                    network. In other words, it only serves to reinforce DoI’s microscopic analyses
                    (user-as-node/adoption), rather than standing on its own as a separate framework
                    for analyzing networks from the top-down or at a distance.</note> If attention
                is to provide an effective framework for thinking about networked writing and
                macroscopic audiences, then scholars must begin to carefully investigate the
                terminology used within such a framework. The term <q>viral</q> is often used to
                indicate that a text, topic, or digital artifact has hyper-circulated among multiple
                networks of mediation and gained a significant amount of attention. But what is the
                difference between something that is merely trending and something that has become
                viral? Why might such determinations be critical to writing studies and digital
                humanities research?</p>
            <p>Trends themselves have become the basis for news reports — CNN, ESPN, Fox, MSNBC —
                all of these media networks now use the phrase <q>this is trending</q> as the basis
                for discussing a topic or bringing something to viewers’ attention. This phenomenon
                is not an altogether new occurrence. Viewer polls — asking viewers to give an
                opinion or respond to a questionnaire — have provided a similar form of feedback for
                television and print journalism. Exit polls in elections also provide similar
                feedback, because voters provide immediate feedback about their choices or opinions
                while the voting process is still underway. The immediate question raised by trend
                feedback is whether trends are popular (and sometimes viral) because of the content
                of the trends, or whether some trends become popular because they gain enough
                momentum and inertia to continue acquiring attention as circulation increases. Does
                trend feedback become a veritable snowball effect that may, at times, lead to
                virality? The obvious answer to this question is yes, trend feedback is no doubt
                occurring. People care about what is popular or trendy merely because those things
                are popular and trendy — even if viewers disagree with the actual content of their
                feeds and networks, the question of whether content merits trending in the first
                place seems to now be secondary to the question of whether content has gained
                attention. This is why operational definitions for terms like <term>trend</term>,
                    <term>virality</term>, and <term>attention</term> are crucial for understanding
                and critiquing network culture.</p>
            <div>
                <head>A Differential Typology of Iteration: Theory</head>
                <p>Thomas H. Davenport and John C. Beck — in their management studies book, <title
                        rend="italic">The Attention Economy</title> — use the phrase <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#davenport2002">human bandwidth</quote> to discuss
                    the limited attention humans have in the face of an overflowing feed of text,
                    image, and video — all of which are constantly vying for a meaningful portion of
                    the available <quote rend="inline" source="#davenport2002">bandwidth</quote>
                    of <quote rend="inline" source="#davenport2002">human</quote> attention <ptr
                        target="#davenport2002"/>. This term, <term>attention</term>, has become
                    useful to rhetoric and writing studies as well. Richard A. Lanham understands
                    human attention in similar economic terms to Davenport and Beck’s, but rather
                    than seeing attention as an issue of human management, Lanham’s attention
                    framework operates with the assumption that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lanham2007">devices that regulate attention
                            are stylistic devices</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lanham2007"/>
                    </cit>. Lanham’s <title rend="italic">The Economics of Attention</title>
                    explains that while information is widely available, human attention is a scarce
                    resource to be carefully allocated through broad rhetorical applications of
                        <term>style</term> — one of the five canons of rhetoric. Attention is a
                    crucial term for research into digital media because an attentive audience can
                    no longer be assumed — the mind numbing noise of information overflow is the new
                    norm. Constantly updated social network feeds, 24 hour news networks, movies,
                    blogs, ebooks, digital media, print media, ubiquitous screens, and always
                    available interfaces — all fighting for attention — try to shock, entertain, or
                    scare users into viewing for as long as possible.</p>
                <p>In fact, attention itself acquires attention — the <q>tipping point</q> as it has
                    commonly been called of late — when humans notice that a significant number of
                    other humans are paying attention to something specific. In DoI theory, this is
                    called <q>critical mass.</q> Critical mass, in innovation diffusion theory, is
                    achieved when <q>the minimum number of
                        participants needed to sustain a collective activity</q> has been
                    reached. However, the problem with critical mass, as Thomas W. Valente notes, is
                    that often critical mass is achieved shortly after a disproportionately small
                    number of people within a social system have adopted an innovation. Like a
                    school of fish avoiding a predator when only a fraction of the fish actually see
                    the predator with their own eyes, the rest of the group moves in coordinated
                    association with the group as a whole. The changes in direction are chaotic on a
                    micro level, but it is a patterned and organized flow of movement from a macro
                    perspective. </p>
                <p>Sidney I. Dobrin argues in <title rend="italic">Postcomposition</title> that
                    purely rhetorical approaches to complex media ecologies — in this case, the
                    ecology of attention — may misidentify <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#dobrin2011">pauses in the system</quote> or <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#dobrin2011">delays in fluctuation</quote> as more traditional
                    causal/rhetorical relationships between parts and wholes <ptr
                        target="#dobrin2011" loc="141–142"/>. As Dobrin argues, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">the whole of writing can never be
                            explained by way of its parts but instead through the properties of its
                            interconnectedness</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dobrin2011" loc="144"/>
                    </cit>. Therefore, the question of trend content, as the rhetorical question of
                    exigence, is only one aspect of a much broader ecology of attention, and
                    focusing on this question in isolation fails to account for broader ecological
                    and technological issues pertaining to digital media. That is not to say that
                    the questions regarding trend content ought to be ignored or drastically reduced
                    in their importance, but limiting analyses of mediation to relationships between
                    human attention and <q>content</q> will no doubt overlook key cybernetic and
                    non-human technological factors that may account for a significant portion of
                    the networked forces affecting what becomes a trend. As Dobrin argues, the
                    human-as-node model of network research cannot currently explain the complex
                    fluctuating-flow of writing that occurs during <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#dobrin2011">hyper-circulation</quote> and <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">network saturation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dobrin2011" loc="181–186"/>
                    </cit>. Attention ecology, therefore, works to understand how complex networks
                    of mediation restructure the reception of compositions through hyperactivity and
                    continuously-fluctuating flow.</p>
                <p>When attention acquires or redirects attention, this functions as a feedback loop
                    within all the various interfaces and mediums vying for attention. In DoI
                    theory, one explanation for this phenomenon is known as <q>weak ties.</q> As
                    Valente explains, <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#valente1995">weak ties facilitates critical
                            mass because it permits innovation to be spread to otherwise unconnected
                            subgroups. Size, centralization, and characteristics of early adopters
                            may be immaterial in their effect on critical mass if weak ties are not
                            present in the network to insure that subgroups share information with
                            one another.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#valente1995" loc="85"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Dobrin’s <title rend="italic">Postcomposition</title>, however, resists the weak
                    ties theory in order to <q>abandon</q> the notion that total-connectedness
                    through weak ties of all subgroups, within a particular network or among
                    multiple networks, explains attention feedback and hyper-circulation <ptr
                        target="#dobrin2011" loc="152"/>. As Dobrin explains, <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#dobrin2011">we may be able to achieve a more
                            ecologically based view of writing by examining the spaces of strange
                            loops as dynamic spaces in which systems establish internal order and as
                            locations in which interrelations take hold. Given that strange loops
                            contribute to the openness of autopoietic systems, we must concede that
                            it is in the strange loop space where interrelations with other systems
                            are most likely to occur.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dobrin2011" loc="166"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>There are many parallels between Dobrin’s description of strange loops and the
                    function of weak ties theory in DoI, but the crucial difference is the shift in
                    focus from the subject (user-as-node) to location and place. </p>
                <p>Certainly, it is easy to understand attention at a personal or experiential
                    level, but attempting to explain how attention may be regulated, redirected, or
                    acquired within complex systems of mediation requires a more careful and
                    well-tested definition. The primary reason this study does not limit attention
                    to <q>humans</q> (whatever that may mean) is because a composition or
                    inscription may jump from a human network to a nonhuman network (not that these
                    are ever totally inseparable) due to the reiteration of bot readers/writers and
                    the activity of weak artificial <q>intelligences</q> already at work among the
                    many available networks of mediation. The more intensely studied canons of
                    rhetoric — invention, arrangement, and style — may have very little to do with
                    what gains attention, and certainly even less of an effect on what <q>goes
                        viral.</q> Many of our art, literature, and film studies colleagues often
                    lament the artistic quality and cultural benefit of what becomes popular in
                    film, music, literature, and art. Part of this can be explained by massive
                    marketing campaigns and corporate agendas regarding media and entertainment
                    choices available to consumers, but a large amount of what becomes popular on a
                        <q>grassroots</q> or <q>viral</q> level of attention is just as difficult
                    for critics to applaud as quality art or meaningful cultural contribution.
                    Although Lanham’s preferred rhetorical canon is <emph>style</emph>, in an
                    attention ecology, temporal and spatial notions associated with the canon of
                        <emph>delivery</emph> are necessarily pushed to the forefront.<note>Of
                        course, the canons of rhetoric are highly interconnected, and elements of
                        style may certainly contribute to delivery. However, we make such
                        distinctions here to differentiate from Lanham’s focus on style.</note></p>
                <p>At the most basic level, operational definitions depend on identifying methods of
                    measurement for specific phenomenon. The phenomenon we attempt to measure in
                    this article is the <emph>iteration</emph> of writing in social media as a way
                    of understanding how attention is redirected or acquired within complex
                    networks. Writing in social media is not limited to the modality of unicode text
                    that appears on computer screens, but writing is understood in the broader sense
                    of any digital modality (text, image, audio, video, etc.) that may be used to
                    make meaning. The basic unit of analysis for this article — iteration — is taken
                    from Jacques Derrida’s work in <title rend="italic">Signature Event
                        Context</title>
                    <ptr target="#derrida1988"/>. In <title rend="italic">Signature</title>, Derrida
                    uses the concept of iteration — the movement of writing through time and space —
                    to undercut simplistic notions of communication derived from speech act theory.
                    For Derrida, iteration is <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">the
                        spacing</quote> that (re)moves writing from its original determinate <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">context,</quote> and this movement or
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">force of rupture</quote> is
                    what <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">constitutes writing.</quote>
                    Writing moves through time (iterates) because of its ability to repeat and
                    reproduce an <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">alterity</quote> of
                    its prior form in <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">absence</quote>
                    of any original intent of meaning or content <ptr target="#derrida1988" loc="9"
                    />. This removal, or spacing, occurs because writing reiterates its collection
                    of signifiers at a later point in time. Social networks provide the possibility
                    of locating iterations of writing across time and space. Of course, this
                    possibility is not unique to social networks, but the availability of temporal
                    and location-based data, provided by social media networks, makes this study
                    more feasible through expedient access to large amounts of networked
                        writing.<note>Traditionally, such data was not always available to scholars,
                        which is one reason the authors used MassMine, which allowed the authors to
                        archive social media data independent of the social media
                    platforms.</note></p>
                <p>This article builds on what Derrida calls a <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988"
                        >typology</quote> of iteration: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#derrida1988">Rather than oppose citation or
                            iteration to the noniteration of an event, one ought to construct a
                            differential typology of forms of iteration, assuming that such a
                            project is tenable and can result in an exhaustive program, a question I
                            hold in abeyance here</quote>
                        <ptr target="#derrida1988" loc="18"/>
                    </cit>. Raúl Sánchez, in <title rend="italic">The Function of Theory in
                        Composition Studies</title>, argues that the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#sanchez2006">exhaustive program</quote> described by Derrida suggests the
                    possibility for some kind of future <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sanchez2006">empirical investigation,
                            resulting in a mapping or organizing of the various ‘forms of iteration’
                            one might find</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sanchez2006" loc="36"/>
                    </cit>. A typology is a classification or categorization according to general
                    types. A differential typology integrates the various classes or categories of
                    which it is comprised. Therefore, the differential typology utilized in this
                    study is as follows: iterative writing is writing that moves, but this movement
                    is a derivative of two other basic components: time and space. While time and
                    space are relative to one another, time is iteration’s constant. In other words,
                    even if writing does not move spatially (from one space, place, or location to
                    another), it is always reiterating temporally (it is always moving through
                    time). </p>
                <p>Movement through time is a necessary condition of writing, while movement through
                    space is not, although writing, in practice, usually moves spatially as well.
                    Even prior to the Gutenberg press, monks passed exemplars from monastery to
                    monastery for other scribes to copy in order to expand the available texts in
                    their libraries. The Internet and digital technologies have not substantially
                    changed the functional integration of writing and movement — writing has never
                    existed in a temporal or spatial vacuum. However, spatial movement has not
                    always been an <emph>inherent</emph> component of the various technologies
                    available for communication. In digital and electronic media, movement and
                    circulation among users and their respective locations are often the driving
                    force behind the development of new writing networks. Codex technologies (often,
                    paper books) require something else to move them from one space to another, and
                    historically this role was often provided by publishers, book stores, and
                    libraries. Technologies like Twitter, on the other hand, were developed to move
                    and circulate writing among a network of users — Facebook, Instagram, YouTube,
                    and Vine were all built with this core functionality in mind. This intentional
                    circulation to encourage more circulation is what Jim Ridolfo and Dànielle
                    Nicole DeVoss call <quote rend="inline" source="#ridolfo2009">rhetorical
                        velocity,</quote> where new combinations of digital delivery and multimodal
                    production form the basis for understanding writing as it relates to movement
                    and circulation <ptr target="#ridolfo2009"/>. Ridolfo and DeVoss focus on
                    microscopic deliveries, what we are here calling user-as-node or the individual
                    choices made by single authors, and this is categorically different from the
                    macroscopic analyses of delivery and circulation we attempt with this article.
                    Microscopic user-as-node analyses are no doubt still crucial to ongoing research
                    in rhetoric and writing studies, and to the digital humanities more broadly
                    conceived. However, as humanities researchers continue to push their
                    investigations of writing and circulation into theories of complex networks and
                    network culture, ongoing work is needed to expand digital research methodologies
                    beyond the scope provided by rhetorical and pedagogical methods. </p>
                <p>Therefore, this article seeks to investigate one of the lingering questions
                    regarding media ecology and complex networks from Dobrin’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Postcomposition</title>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#dobrin2011">For a number of reasons, including
                            the desire not to make “scientific” the ecology of ecocomposition
                            postcomposition beyond perhaps a grammatological science, I am not going
                            to distinguish between micro and macro approaches in establishing
                            complex ecological theories of writing, though there may be potential
                            for doing so in future theoretical work.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dobrin2011" loc="142"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>This <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">potential</quote> that Dobrin describes for
                    distinguishing between <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">micro and macro</quote>
                    approaches to <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">complex ecological theories of
                        writing</quote> is the basis for the following differential typology of
                    iteration. Thus, we define the microscopic approach in complex networks as
                    attempting to understand individual users within specific networks. This is what
                    we refer to as the user-as-node concept of network research. This reductive
                    concept understands network behavior as affecting the choices of the user within
                    the network — often leading to reductive cause/effect relationships between
                    users and the information that flows within a single network. </p>
                <p>Alternately, the macroscopic approach attempts to understand aggregate activities
                    of groups of users across an interactive ecology of multiple interactive
                    networks. We see this as the environment that allows for Dobrin’s
                    hyper-circulation and network saturation. We know that most users, if not all,
                    interact within multiple networks of mediation. A single user, for example, will
                    watch television while writing on Twitter and posting images to Instagram with
                    their mobile phone, and monitoring Facebook on their laptop — one user, three
                    screens, and four networks. If we analyzed this particular <emph>user</emph>
                    only within Twitter, for example, then that user’s tweet about a particular
                    television show may appear to be motivated (caused) by another Twitter user who
                    previously tweeted about the same show, when, in the case of this example, the
                    tweet about the television show may have been motivated instead by a Facebook
                    post or by the show itself. Or, maybe the user received a text message from a
                    friend who was watching the show at the same time (a fifth network). The problem
                    with the user-as-node in a single network model is that it often ignores this
                    broader media ecology of multiple interactive networks, and it too easily allows
                    for simplistic cause/effect claims about circulation and determinate reductions
                    of agency. Accounting for users as nodes within complex ecologies may be
                    theoretically possible, but it is likely a pragmatic impossibility when
                    considering that any user’s actual position within multiple interactive networks
                    may be too indeterminate and ever-shifting to predict a future position.</p>
                <p>The preface to the ten volume <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Complexity and
                        Systems Science </title>defines complex systems as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#meyers2009">systems that comprise many
                            interacting parts with the ability to generate a new quality of
                            collective behavior through self-organization, e.g. the spontaneous
                            formation of temporal, spatial or functional structures</quote>
                        <ptr target="#meyers2009" loc="iii"/>
                    </cit>. Individual social networks, like Twitter for example, certainly fulfill
                    the requirements for being defined as complex networks: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#meyers2009">They are therefore adaptive as
                            they evolve and may contain self-driving feedback loops</quote>
                        <ptr target="#meyers2009" loc="iii"/>
                    </cit>. However, the user-as-node within Twitter (within a single complex
                    network) does not account for the cybernetic post-subject within a complex
                        writing <term>ecology</term>. That is, the user-as-node model typically
                    focuses on a single user in a single network and cannot adequately account for
                    the information flow between networks. Complex ecologies of writing must work to
                    understand, as Dobrin explains, that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">the whole of writing can never be
                            explained by way of its parts but instead through the properties of its
                            interconnectedness</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dobrin2011" loc="144"/>
                    </cit>. This does not mean that we do not look at parts and wholes, but we do so
                    with the theoretical understanding that complex networks are so dynamic and
                    ever-changing that there is no practical way to ever recreate a user’s
                    cybernetic position or to capture an all-encompassing macroscopic ecology. And
                    even if we could recreate or map that positioning, it would only represent
                    that single moment in time — a <quote rend="inline" source="#dobrin2011">pause in
                        flow</quote> as Dobrin calls it — and it would likely tell us very little
                    about that user’s future position and attention. As the <title rend="italic"
                        >Encyclopedia of Complexity</title> explains, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#meyers2009">complex systems are much more than
                            a sum of their parts. Complex systems are often characterized as having
                            extreme sensitivity to initial conditions as well as emergent behavior
                            that are not readily predictable or even completely
                            deterministic</quote>
                        <ptr target="#meyers2009" loc="iii"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Therefore, if identifying the flow of information for individual users within
                    individual networks represents the microscopic perspective for media ecology,
                    the macroscopic perspective looks at how users are aggregated or moved by large
                    trends of information flow. In other words, the microscopic sees the user as
                    directing the flow (what is often thought of as agency), and the macroscopic
                    sees groups of users as following trends or hyper-circulation (being redirected
                    by the flow). Certainly, for writing studies and digital humanities scholars who
                    are interested in affecting audiences within a singular network, Diffusion of
                    Innovation theory applications for Twitter research (also applicable to other
                    individual networks) continue to produce useful models for understanding how
                    ideas circulate among specific social groups within an individual network (see,
                    for example, <ptr target="#lee2010"/>, <ptr target="#wu2011"/>, <ptr
                        target="#guille2012"/>. However, the work forwarded in this article looks
                    for ways to begin moving beyond such microscopic studies, and start moving
                    toward macroscopic social network research in its own right (rather than merely
                    using macroscopic analyses to reinforce micro/user-as-node research).</p>
                <p>To return to our earlier metaphor, while fish in a school all act individually
                    based on other fish around them, we can also learn about their movements by
                    watching the school as a whole. However, in terms of complex networks, no grand
                    unifying theory yet exists to account for the integrated operations between
                    micro and macro levels of research. We propose no grand unifying theory in this
                    article, but we also do not see the two as conflicting or contradictory. Much
                    effort and research in rhetoric and writing studies has been given to questions
                    of agency and individual users’ (writers) ability to direct the delivery of
                    writing — the theory of <q>rhetorical velocity</q> is a great example of this.
                    We see no inherent problem with microscopic research — it is important
                    pedagogical work, and it ought to continue. Rather, our research attempts to
                    make the macroscopic (large scale, aggregate) perspective of writing useful for
                    media ecology and writing studies as well: ours is an inclusive agenda, and an
                    attempt to expand the available methods for studying networked writing. </p>
                <p>The type of iteration at the core of our research is what is commonly called a
                        <q>trend.</q> As mentioned above, trends identify large scale, aggregate
                    information flow. Trends occur within social media technologies when users
                    repeat similar words, or hashtags (#), over the same period of time, or when
                    large groupings of similar words or phrases iterate together. The period of time
                    and systems used to identify trends are always arbitrary. There is no positivist
                    basis or claims of capturing social reality forwarded by this research. Data
                    science, in many of its variations, may be understood as postmodern in the ways
                    it conducts its research — the scopes constructed are always folding back on
                    themselves, always limited by the self-identifying archives they create, and
                    always self-modified to tentatively answer exploratory questions. As Cary Wolfe
                    explains in <title rend="italic">What is Posthumanism?</title>, building on the
                    work of Niklas Luhmann, the combination of systems theory and Derridean theories
                    of writing provide the basis for <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#wolfe2009">reconstruction</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wolfe2009" loc="8"/>
                    </cit>. While Wolfe’s work with critical animal studies takes a far different
                    trajectory than does our own research, the same underlying theory is applicable
                    to this study. The reconstruction of trend flow in this article — of macroscopic
                    information flow — is limited by the scope that allows or recreates its very
                    possibility. The acknowledgement and study of such limitations is what makes
                    data science — the operational methodology of measurement deployed in this
                    article — amenable for humanities scholars who have long theorized the
                    generative possibilities of the archive. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Writing Data: Methods</head>
                <p>In order to conduct a macro-analysis, we decided to focus on micro-blogging,
                    specifically the social media site Twitter. Although each tweet is only 140
                    characters, the total number of tweets provide the opportunity to test a massive
                    data set. In addition, since tweets are often shared, linked, and tagged, the
                    larger Twitterverse provides a rich source of information in which to understand
                    how writing circulates as writing. </p>
                <p>Although no history of Twitter is <q>long,</q> much research has been done in
                    order to determine how Twitter may be used for a variety of purposes and a
                    variety of users. For example, most research on Twitter falls into at least six
                    methods: content analysis, topic modeling, clustering, sentiment analysis,
                    opinion mining, and audience exposure analysis. Content analysis analyzes
                    Twitter for a variety of purposes, but mainly to research what users tweet and
                    for what purposes. Topic modeling looks for specific topics or conversations
                    which are then used to model other phenomena or events. For example, Michael J.
                    Paul and Mark Dredze have analyzed tweets related to public health and shown
                    that such data can provide quantitative correlations with public health data,
                    suggesting that Twitter can be applied to public health research <ptr
                        target="#paul2011"/>. Clustering provides a methodology for showing
                    relationships or natural groupings between Twitter users, hashtags, or specific
                    terms: who retweets or follows whom, how hashtags relate to each other, etc., in
                    order to show how information circulates on small scales and how users relate to
                    each other. Sentiment analysis <ptr target="#bifet2010"/> attempts to determine
                    the feelings of users toward a particular story or subject, often toward ends
                    such as brand management. Relatedly, opinion mining attempts to search Twitter
                    for the opinions of users on particular topics, which may range across a
                    continuum on the level of emotion such opinions contain (in other words, some
                    opinions may be more measured or more reactionary). While such research can be
                    useful, it does little to show macroscopic trends across a network (or between
                    networks) as a whole. Coming closest to this study, audience exposure attempts
                    to determine the number of users who have seen an individual tweet. While the
                    number of times a tweet is retweeted is relatively easy to find, the number of
                    actual users who have viewed the tweet is not. Tom Emerson, Rishab Ghosh, and
                    Eddie Smith offer one method through their investigation into a tweet by the Bin
                    Laden Live Tweeter <ptr target="#emerson2012"/>, but, again, such a method still
                    only accounts for a single tweet, a single user-as-node, and does not attempt
                    data analysis on the scale required to best understand hyper-circulation and how
                    the structure of the network as a whole (and its connections to other networks)
                    influence how hyper-circulation occurs. </p>
                <p>While there are many websites that assist in accessing social network data, most
                    of the applications and websites that provide access to archived or streaming
                    data charge a fee, provide limited or already processed data, and usually are
                    focused entirely on brand management and marketing research. This happens
                    primarily for two reasons: (1) it is common practice for social networks and
                    search engines to license their data for resale, providing an additional source
                    of revenue, and (2) other companies are willing to pay for this data because it
                    provides a specialized form of brand management and marketing research that
                    cannot be acquired elsewhere. While some of the current web applications that
                    provide access to social network data have started to <q>grant</q> free access
                    to a limited number of academic institutions <ptr target="#krikorian2014"/>,
                    depending on the types of research that may be completed with the given data,
                    the built-in commerce/marketing focus of these web archives limits the scope of
                    research questions that may be asked. Therefore, while the cost of access to
                    data continues to be a significant gate-keeper for social network research, the
                    larger issues are the questions raised by the types of restrictions placed on
                    data because of a systematic preference for marketing and commerce related
                    research.</p>
                <p>Because of these limitations, we opted for an open-source academic research
                    software called MassMine, as it accesses and collects data from social network
                        APIs.<note>For more information about MassMine (or to download it), visit
                            <ref target="http://MassMine.org">MassMine.org</ref>.</note> Many of the
                    top social networks, such as Twitter and Facebook, provide an API (application
                    programming interface) for application and software development. Access to APIs
                    is generally provided free of charge in order to encourage software developers
                    to write mobile apps and to provide the infrastructure for companies to create
                    web applications and supplementary services that are not provided by the
                    networks themselves. For example, the photo sharing application/network
                    Instagram initially gained momentum as an API application that provided the
                    ability to easily take, edit, and post photos to other social networks. Now,
                    Instagram is its own viable social network and is owned by Facebook, but
                    Instagram’s initial function of interacting with user data through access to an
                    API allowed it to develop its primary photo sharing feature. APIs are useful in
                    that they can be re-purposed for social media research, using this access to
                    collect and analyze data on the network, its users, and the content circulated
                    therein.</p>
                <p>Despite this accessibility, APIs are not beyond reproach for they subject the
                    researcher to their own limitations. We believe this trade-off results in a net
                    benefit for the academic investigator as the limitations are based more so on
                    bandwidth restrictions and less on prescribed end-uses for the data. Network
                    access through APIs is typically limited by the constraints of big data itself.
                    Put simply, existing network infrastructure cannot support unfettered access to
                    social network databases. Indeed, API functionality for large-scale services
                    like Twitter is often rolled out incrementally as internal engineers solve the
                    problems of big data one step ahead of users. The types of limitations created
                    by an API are different than the access issues, costs, and research limitations
                    of data types that are common to existing commerce and marketing tools. In other
                    words, APIs do not generally limit the kinds of data or what you can do with the
                    data, nor do APIs charge for data, but they do limit how often data access may
                    occur (because of bandwidth restrictions) and how much (or how far back in time)
                    data may be acquired each time an API is accessed. Anyone with the right
                    programming skills may access publicly available data through APIs, thus
                    eliminating the immediate cost barriers involved in using APIs. However, the
                    bandwidth restrictions do create access issues. For example, historical data
                    beyond a certain point in time may not be accessible with many social network
                    APIs, but if a researcher knows what they want to research ahead of time (i.e.,
                    they have pre-established a well-formed research question), then it is possible
                    to mine data on a regular basis and create a large historical archive over a
                    period of time. MassMine, as an open-source research tool created for academics,
                    allows such pre-determined archiving of data by providing full API data access
                    to users unaccustomed to programming low-level software solutions.</p>
                <p>The data collected for this study was pulled from Twitter’s API over seventy-four
                    days. Analysis and visualizations were conducted using both MassMine and the
                    open source R statistical computing language. During the period of time in which
                    we were pulling data from Twitter, we collected data on over 17,343 unique
                    trends, including the Christmas, New Year’s, and Valentine’s Day holidays, the
                    deaths of numerous celebrities and culturally significant figures, and Super
                    Bowl Forty-Eight. Our measures of interest in the rise and fall of trends across
                    geographic regions emphasized the need for temporal precision. MassMine was set
                    to retrieve and archive the top ten trends every five minutes from nine
                    different locations across the US, and an additional top ten trends for the
                    entire US as a whole. The choice of five minutes represents the maximum refresh
                    rate of Twitter’s trend data.</p>
                <p>Geolocation of information on our data was made possible via data filtering,
                    specified as Yahoo Where On Earth IDentifier (WOEID) codes, which allowed us to
                    track the location of trends across space and time. Twitter’s API allows for
                    trends to be identified as either (1) keywords specified as literal #hashtags
                    (for example: #superbowl) that are defined by users, or (2) trends that are
                    defined according to the most common phrases appearing in user statuses. We
                    decided to pull trends based on both, rather than limiting our analyses to
                    prescribed #hashtag trends. This approach ensured that we identified
                    organically-arising trends, in addition to more explicit #hashtag events.
                    Moreover, sometimes a singular trend may use multiple #hashtags. For example,
                    there were numerous #hashtags surrounding the death of Nelson Mandela (e.g.,
                    “Nelson Mandela”; “#MandelaMemorial”; “#NelsonMandela”; “Mandela”;
                    “#MandelaFuneral”), but Mandela’s death could be interpreted as a singular
                    trending topic. To be sure, both kinds of data were collected and jointly
                    analyzed.</p>
                <p>Trends provide one particular way of understanding attention, but we want to be
                    careful not to equate trends with attention. In fact, one of our current
                    limitations is that we are only looking at trends as they appear on Twitter.
                    Ideally, attention ecology would look at data from multiple social networks,
                    search trends from search engines, and other information that may help to
                    identify attention — such as data mining the tickers that appear at the bottom
                    of twenty-four hour news networks as a way of identifying what <q>news</q> is
                    given attention at various times of the day, looking at ratings numbers and
                    movie box office returns to get an idea of how entertainment events may be
                    accounted for, and certainly finding ways to understand how print media and oral
                    culture (word-of-mouth) continue to be a significant aspect of attention
                    ecology. There are potentially infinite ways of reconstructing an ecological
                    understanding of how attention may function with complex networks of mediation,
                    but when we account for place and time the problem becomes finite. It is in this
                    way that Twitter trends provide a useful starting point for understanding how to
                    attach the concept of attention to time and place. As more tools become
                    available to humanities researchers studying digital media and complex networks,
                    a broader macroscopic understanding of attention ecology will emerge.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Circulation Analytics: Results</head>
                <p>Our interpretation of the analysis is deliberately narrow for two reasons: first,
                    we are only accounting for trends within one particular network. Even though
                    Twitter has almost thirty-seven million active monthly users in the US, it is
                    unlikely that a significant number of those users restrict their use to Twitter
                    and do not acquire/circulate similar information through other networks. Second,
                    the temporal resolution of Twitter trends is necessarily fixed at some minimum
                    span (currently, five minutes), as defining trends tacitly implies aggregating
                    content across time. Further, within a unit of analysis repetition of content is
                    tabulated, with the ten most active topics selected as <q>trending</q> by
                    Twitter’s ranking algorithm. This means that a trend only becomes available for
                    data collection through API access once it has hit the top ten in a particular
                    location. Conceivably, it is reasonable to assume that many trends reside at the
                    eleventh or lower ranked position in numerous geographical locations before
                    being revealed in the top ten of a particular location. Therefore it is
                    problematic to understand the first appearance of a trend in Twitter’s system as
                    showing where a trend begins or which locations seem to be the most influential
                    in <q>causing</q> trends to <q>spread</q> to other locations. Another difficulty
                    can arise due to the magnification of the scope of analysis. That is, trends
                    that are initially below the level of detection at city-level could, in
                    aggregate, reveal their circulation at the national level before appearing on
                    any individual location’s top ten. This can occur, for example, when network
                    attention is broad and diffuse across a wide geographical region. Indeed, an
                    analysis of our own data revealed that over 29% of the trends that occurred in
                    all ten locations were identified at the national level first.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Average duration of trends (in hours) as a function of the number of
                        locations. The number of trends included in each estimate is depicted under
                        each point on the curve.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>


                <p>Our collection efforts constituted samples of 10 trends for each of ten
                    geographical locations: Chicago, IL; Columbus, OH; Denver, CO; Houston, TX;
                    Jacksonville, FL; Los Angeles, CA; New York, NY; Seattle, WA; Washington D.C.;
                    and the United States. These locations were chosen because they were large
                    cities with good geographical and cultural spread. The sample trends in these
                    locations were identified every five minutes, for just over seventy-four days.
                    At 288 samples per day, this amounts to 288×74×10×10≈2,131,200 records. Because
                    trends are a spatial and temporal phenomenon, there is a great deal of
                    redundancy across regions and time spans of analysis. Table 1 describes the
                    breakdown of unique trends as identified across all samples. In total, 17,343
                    unique trends were observed across all locations, with decreasingly fewer topics
                    reaching trending levels at multiple locations. For example, 14.3% of trends
                    (2472) appeared in all ten locations. This 14.3% of trends is important because
                    these are the trends that appeared in the top ten trends of every single
                    location and the top ten trends of the broader US location, and thus can be more
                    confidently compared to one another.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Frequency of trends identified across one or more locations.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell># of observed locations</cell>
                        <cell># of trends</cell>
                        <cell>% of total trends</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>17343</cell>
                        <cell>100.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>12939</cell>
                        <cell>74.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>10747</cell>
                        <cell>62.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>8931</cell>
                        <cell>51.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>7483</cell>
                        <cell>43.1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6187</cell>
                        <cell>35.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>5152</cell>
                        <cell>29.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>4259</cell>
                        <cell>24.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>3412</cell>
                        <cell>19.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>2472</cell>
                        <cell>14.3</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Table 2 summarizes trend duration at the group level, with group defined
                    according to the number of locations at which individual trends were observed.
                    For example, the median duration of trends that appeared at only one location
                    across their entire lifespan was 0.08 hours (4.8 minutes), while trends that
                    were identified at all ten locations had a duration of 20.43 hours. While this
                    result might conform to reasonable expectations, it is not at all logically
                    necessary. All measures of central tendency suggest an overall increase in the
                    longevity of trending information corresponding to its geographic spread.
                    However, the effect of spread is small in all estimates, with the exception of
                    the mean, which is subject to large variations contingent on
                    uncharacteristically large or small values. Figure 1, which shows average
                    duration above the number of values used in each calculation, illustrates this.
                    Fluctuations in duration estimates for positions 8-10 move in tandem with
                    corresponding changes in the underlying counts, particularly for the mean.
                    Still, an increase in the lifespan of a trending topic commensurate with its
                    reiteration is fundamental to discussions and theories of virality. How then,
                    can observations regarding the behavior of trends — topics that, by definition,
                    are already popular within a network — lead to further understanding of the
                    mechanisms and conditions behind the rise and fall of viral trends? The
                    insensitive nature of our measure prohibits us from inferring the origin of
                    trends, both spatially and temporally. As discussed above, trends only reach a
                    level of identification after they’ve achieved top ten level popularity.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Group-level duration estimates (in hours) for trends occurring in one or
                        more locations.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell># of observed locations</cell>
                        <cell>Median</cell>
                        <cell>Mean</cell>
                        <cell>Geometric Mean</cell>
                        <cell>Max</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0.08</cell>
                        <cell>34.38</cell>
                        <cell>1.04</cell>
                        <cell>1759</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0.18</cell>
                        <cell>45.12</cell>
                        <cell>0.40</cell>
                        <cell>1713</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0.25</cell>
                        <cell>68.69</cell>
                        <cell>0.78</cell>
                        <cell>1731</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0.34</cell>
                        <cell>77.37</cell>
                        <cell>1.24</cell>
                        <cell>1761</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0.50</cell>
                        <cell>86.33</cell>
                        <cell>1.76</cell>
                        <cell>1654</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>1.26</cell>
                        <cell>109.18</cell>
                        <cell>3.29</cell>
                        <cell>1681</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>1.56</cell>
                        <cell>131.79</cell>
                        <cell>4.41</cell>
                        <cell>1683</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>14.93</cell>
                        <cell>284.44</cell>
                        <cell>18.34</cell>
                        <cell>1726</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>4.28</cell>
                        <cell>174.87</cell>
                        <cell>7.97</cell>
                        <cell>1726</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>20.43</cell>
                        <cell>327.25</cell>
                        <cell>26.40</cell>
                        <cell>1776</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Despite the limitations inherent in trend analysis, we believe that it is
                    possible to approach an analysis of trend circulation with those trends already
                    identified as such. The risk arises from including sparse trends, defined as
                    topics that appear in only a subset of measured locations. Such data cause
                    systematically biased estimates of trend location, duration, and genesis when
                    leveraging averaged, group-level investigations of this sort. For example, a
                    trending topic that persists for a long time only at the national level, but
                    never at city-based levels, can grossly underestimate its apparent geographical
                    spread, while simultaneously skewing the apparent duration of similarly grouped
                    trends with much shorter lifespans. Likewise, a social phenomenon linked to a
                    given city (e.g., trends unique to a state fair) that lasts for an extended
                    period may exaggerate its apparent value in the greater national or social
                    context.</p>
                <p>To avoid such pitfalls, we conducted an analysis on the subset of trend topics
                    that appeared, at some point in their lifespan, in all measured locations — nine
                    cities and at the national level. This ensured that trends were not
                    systematically binned for analysis based on geospatial restriction alone. Put
                    clearly, in the following analyses, all trends appear at each level of analysis.
                    This reduces the risk of spurious trend profiles due to uncharacteristically
                    short or long duration, and/or narrow or diffuse movements during recirculation
                    and reiteration. Duration distributions for these <q>ubiquitous</q> trends were
                    notably shifted toward a greater length of time, largely due to the removal of
                    single-instance trends that populated (11% of) the full data set. Median and
                    mean duration among ubiquitous trends was 20.43 hours and 327.25 hours,
                    respectively, compared to the corresponding duration of the full data set
                    (median = 0.50 hours; mean = 111.75 hours).</p>
                <p>Figure 2 provides an overview of group-level ubiquitous trend duration as a
                    function of what we call geotemporal sequencing. Each curve corresponds to one
                    of the ten measured locations, with national-level data depicted in red. The
                    horizontal axis represents the temporal sequence, or order in which trends
                    appeared at a given location. For example, the first point on the red curve
                    depicts the average lifespan duration of trends that appeared first at the
                    national level before appearing at any other location. By contrast, trends
                    contained in the final point of the red curve were observed at every other
                    measured location before they appeared at the national level. Critically, by
                    restricting this analysis to so-called ubiquitous trends, which appeared at all
                    locations by definition, each curve in Figure 2 is composed of the exact same
                    data. The only difference is the order in which the data were grouped for
                    analysis. This approach ensures that our comparisons reflect underlying patterns
                    in recirculation/reiteration rather than artifacts of the particular data chosen
                    for analysis.</p>
                <p>Several interesting patterns are revealed by the geotemporal sequencing results.
                    Most notably, the red curve (national-level trends) reveals a marked increase in
                    duration contingent upon when a trend appears at the national level. This result
                    is remarkably consistent across the entire geotemporal sequence. That is, trends
                    that begin their journey at the national level have the shortest overall
                    lifespan — shorter than trends beginning at every other city-level location (as
                    evidenced by the fact that all gray curves begin higher than the red curve).
                    Continuing along the red curve, a clear increase in duration is observed, one
                    that remains higher than all other locations after the fifth position in the
                    curve. Increase in mean duration as a function of order was found to have a
                    significant linear trend. The coefficient of order was estimated to be
                    approximately twenty-six hours (p &lt; .0002). Thus, in our data, each
                    additional shift to the right in the national-level curve reflected an increase
                    in staying-power of just over a day’s length. Put simply, the longer it takes a
                    trend to reach the national level, the longer that trend’s overall lifespan is
                    likely to last.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Geotemporal analysis of trend duration.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>



                <p>This result mirrors the pattern observed in Table 2, and once again compliments
                    what common sense might predict. However, as previously mentioned, this result
                    is not a logical consequence of the analysis. Unlike Table 2, our geotemporal
                    analysis reveals why this is so. Consider the nine gray curves in Figure 2. Each
                    of the gray curves is composed of exactly the same data as the red curve.
                    Furthermore, points near the end of each curve reflect the averages of trends
                    that arrived late to each location. Applying similar logic to these data, we
                    might also suspect that average duration should increase commensurately with how
                    long it takes to reach each location. In other words, we would expect each curve
                    to have a slope &gt; 0. Instead, we find no systematic change in duration across
                    ordering for any city-level location (as evidenced by the relatively flat
                    curves). The only possible exception to this finding involves New York City
                    (NYC). Trends in our data that appeared first in NYC tended toward much longer
                    lifespans. A likely explanation for this is the disproportionately large
                    population of NYC, which establishes it as a cultural, technological, and social
                    juggernaut relative to our other locations. Regardless, the remainder of the
                    curve associated with NYC is flat and indistinguishable from our other cities,
                    and lies in stark contrast to the pattern observed at the national level.</p>
                <p>If each curve represents the same data, why do we observe such a striking
                    difference in the functional form of trend lifespans when our investigative lens
                    shifts from local city-level perspectives to a national one? The key to this
                    result lies in the effect of geotemporal order. By design, each trend included
                    in our analysis appears at all ten locations. However, it is entirely possible —
                    likely, even — that trends quickly spread and gain attention at multiple
                    locations, only to quickly diminish in popularity shortly thereafter. Indeed,
                    this is the predominate life-cycle of trends observed in our data. Most topics
                    quickly recede into obscurity — roughly 50% of the topics we measured
                    disappeared in less than 21 hours. Because all trends identified as such by
                    Twitter reflect topics receiving attention in social media, the question of
                    interest becomes what separates popular sentiment from so-called viral
                    trends?</p>
                <p>Given the sheer number of active users and their tweets, virality can no longer
                    be defined according to raw counts. Rather, the hyper-circulatory nature of
                    viral information should reflect the underlying social attention itself, which
                    in turn can lead to reiteration and recirculation. A metric of attention would
                    ideally factor in activities and influences across multiple social networks,
                    news media, popular culture outlets such as television, podcasts, and radio, as
                    well as the impossible-to-measure aspects of interpersonal interactions between
                    users and their <q>real-life</q> friends and family. Despite the untenable
                    nature of such an analysis, we believe the geotemporal analysis provided here
                    gives us a glimpse into the nature of such hyper-circulating information. This
                    glimpse is reflected in the behavior of trends grouped according to their
                    appearance at the national level. Notice again that trends that appear first at
                    the national level do not particularly fair well from a sustainability
                    standpoint, relative to any other location. This observation holds for trends
                    that appear at the national level in position one through five of their
                    life-cycle. However, a tipping point occurs around position six, after which
                    trends generally persist for much greater periods of time. It is worth noting
                    that this striking increase holds for all metrics — mean, median, and geometric
                    mean — strongly indicating that this effect is not an artifact of measurement
                    alone (e.g., the effect is not due to random outliers). The effect is correlated
                    with the number of trends observed at each position in the geotemporal curve of
                    the national-level analysis (see Panel D of Figure 2). This reduction in the
                    number of trends should not be viewed as the cause of the increased durations
                    observed, but rather as a by-product of the mechanisms mediating the lifespan
                    pattern. Put simply, fewer trends are likely to achieve <q>viral</q> status, so
                    we should expect increasingly fewer observations as we move rightward along the
                    red curve.</p>
                <p>We are careful to not draw cause and effect conclusions, particularly given the
                    limited scope of our analysis. A future investigation might include monitoring a
                    greater number of city-level locations, as well as foreign locales. Nonetheless,
                    we speculate that this uptick in trend sustainability might reflect an
                    underlying change in the nature of the attention driving the mechanisms of
                    reiteration and recirculation. We refer to this critical mass as the <q>virality
                        threshold.</q> At this point it is not possible to say with certainty what
                        <q>causes</q> topics to surpass the virality threshold, if such a notion is
                    even meaningful. One difference between <q>normal</q> trends and viral trends is
                    apparent though: trends that quickly rise to detectable levels at the national
                    level tend to be volatile in nature — quick to rise, and quick to fall. By
                    contrast, topics that bubble up slowly, growing and spreading across the country
                    in systemic fashion are much more likely to persist. The next logical question
                    then becomes what characterizes such topics in today’s world of ubiquitous
                    technology and information overload? We can only speculate, but we believe that
                    identifying such information will require simultaneous analysis of both inter-
                    and intra-network connectivity. For example, it is impossible to fully
                    understand hyper-circulation activity on Twitter without considering chatter on
                    Facebook, the news, television, etc. A look at Table 3 provides a tantalizing,
                    albeit anecdotal confirmation of our suspicions. In the left-most column we
                    report the twenty shortest-lived trends that made their first appearance at the
                    national level. The twenty trends listed in the second column represent the
                    topics with the longest lifespans, taken from those trends that made their tenth
                    and final appearance in our data at the national level. By contrast to the
                    shortest-lived trends, long-lived trends tend to center around celebrities and
                    corporate identities more likely to be circulating on more <q>controlled</q>
                    networks, such as television and news media. A more careful investigation into
                    the mechanisms dictating the nature of the virality threshold is left to future
                    research.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Forty trends observed with the shortest and longest lifespans. The
                        shortest-lived trends were taken from those topics that appeared at the
                        nation level as their first location. The longest-lived trends were those
                        identified at the national level as their tenth location. These correspond
                        to the shortest and longest trends depicted in the first and last points on
                        the red curve in Figure 2.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>20 Shortest-lived trends</cell>
                        <cell>20 Longest-lived trends</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hanna and Emily</cell>
                        <cell>Jordan Hill</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>ASC</cell>
                        <cell>#WCW</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Dumb Hoers</cell>
                        <cell>Jordan Crawford</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>#AskAngie</cell>
                        <cell>Jimmy Kimmel</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Evil Ryu</cell>
                        <cell>#coupon</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>William James</cell>
                        <cell>Florida</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Wifey Material Or Nah</cell>
                        <cell>#MCM</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>#NFLIndoors</cell>
                        <cell>Tyler</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>AIM</cell>
                        <cell>Holtby</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Leonard Fournette</cell>
                        <cell>World Cup</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Ron Baker</cell>
                        <cell>#PLL</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>#BartTo40K</cell>
                        <cell>Freaky Friday</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50% of Americans</cell>
                        <cell>Kendrick</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Pickle Eggs</cell>
                        <cell>Keenan Allen</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>If She Eat</cell>
                        <cell>Jamaal Charles</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>#SOYJOY</cell>
                        <cell>Vegas</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Tekele Cotton</cell>
                        <cell>Tom Hanks</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Shane Larkin</cell>
                        <cell>WCW</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>South Carolina State University</cell>
                        <cell>#gameday</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Powerball</cell>
                        <cell>Steve Harvey</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Future Writing Studies: Final Thoughts</head>
                <p>As noted above, the results from this study suggest that the longer a trend takes
                    to reach a national audience, the longer that trend is likely to last.
                    Long-lasting trends tend to be slow and steady, systematically circulating from
                    city to city until finally reaching the national level, while trends that first
                    appear at the national level are more volatile and chaotic. To use a metaphor
                    often found in politics, trends that initiate from a <q>grass roots</q> level
                    (city-level rather than national level) have a greater potential to be sustained
                    over time. Or, to use another metaphor, a bottom-up approach lasts longer than
                    top-down, if we think of the <q>top</q> as national conversations driven by
                    celebrities, large-scale institutions, mass media, etc. </p>
                <p>If <q>rhetorical velocity</q> can be a practical tool of digital rhetorics, and
                    if velocity is defined in physics as <q>speed with direction,</q> then this
                    study suggests that the goal that any user might want to achieve through digital
                    delivery is a direction with slow and steady speed. As much as digital
                    technologies are lauded (or cursed) for their ability to create near
                    instantaneous ubiquity, such high speed can be followed quickly by relative
                    obscurity.</p>
                <p>Such findings might also suggest that, like performance-based modes of delivery
                    through a human body, digital delivery requires a rhythm: it cannot simply rise
                    and crescendo forever, but works best when alternating between upbeats and
                    downbeats, perhaps picking up the pace from time to time, but slowly building
                    toward a chorus where multiple voices join in and tweet along. However, just as
                    not all trends are the same, not all <q>viruses</q> are the same, either. If
                    attention is in fact becoming a justification, in and of itself, then we need to
                    begin to better differentiate between kinds and types of attention — or, another
                    way to put it, we need to develop a differential typology of iteration. This
                    article suggests one type of differentiation by using the virality threshold to
                    tell the difference between normal trends, and trends that have become
                    viral.</p>
                <p>Specific to this study, there’s also a geographical component at play for how
                    trends might circulate — another possible form of differentiation. Although this
                    study didn’t look at the individual content of tweets beyond a trend analysis,
                    nor why one tweet might circulate from one location to another (only that they
                    circulated), future research might investigate the reasons why one trend might
                    move from one location to another. Animal studies describes one form of animal
                    navigation as <q>path integration,</q> where an animal integrates continuous
                    path cues throughout its travels and uses them to navigate back to a starting
                    point. A theory of <q>trend integration</q> might be developed in order to track
                    the movement of trends and determine the various cues that help spread a trend
                    from one location to the next. However, given that animals use a variety of
                    senses to achieve path integration (inertial cues, proprioception, motor
                    efference, optic flow, and sensitivity to the earth’s magnetic field), and given
                    that social network activity occurs in a complex system, any practical attempt
                    to evaluate <q>trend integration</q> would require additional development in the
                    tools and techniques for studying social network trends. </p>
                <p>Such research would require an integration of the macroscopic (what we have
                    proposed here) with the microscopic. To return once again to our school of fish,
                    an ichthyologist can look at how fish behave individually, as a school, or how
                    these two levels operate together to create a whole, organized movement. Our
                    contention is that this kind of analysis <emph>could</emph> be done with
                    large-scale writing systems, but not at this time, for too little research has
                    looked at the macroscopic perspective to understand exactly how a whole school
                    of tweets moves. Even an individual fish (tweeter) cannot be abstracted into a
                    generalized higher-level operator (trend) without some sense of the larger
                    scale. We cannot integrate micro to macro until we first understand them
                    separately. </p>
                <p>As for our introduction of the term <term>virality threshold</term>, we think
                    this concept, and others like it, are the first steps toward critical frameworks
                    for investigating how attention functions in network culture. If attention
                    itself, more so than the content of any trend, is the driving force of
                    hyper-circulation and network saturation, then we need to develop operational
                    methodologies for determining whether or not something actually is <q>viral.</q>
                    If a digital object’s status as <q>trending</q> or <q>viral</q> is the basis for
                    developing narratives in news media and entertainment journalism, then it is
                    important to make sure other trends and viral topics are not being ignored —
                    especially ones attached to social movements and cultural critique. Eunsong Kim,
                    in the <title rend="quotes">Politics of Trending</title>, reminds readers that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kim2015">Trending is visibility granted by a
                            closed, private organization and their proprietary algorithms</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kim2015"/>
                    </cit>. Twitter’s system for locating and identifying trends, for example, is a
                    black box; Twitter does not explain how they quantify trends. Therefore, it may
                    be even more necessary to develop methodologies for showing that something is
                        <emph>not</emph> trending or viral — even though news media, advertising,
                    and marketing campaigns may try to start a trend by pretending it has already
                    gained momentum. If our research accomplishes nothing else, we hope it
                    encourages critical responses to the phrases <q>this is trending</q> or <q>this
                        is viral</q> with questions like: How do you know it was a trend or viral
                    topic? Within how <emph>many</emph> networks did this actually trend or become
                    viral? Is this an organic/grassroots trend, or has it been manufactured?</p>
                <p>While the virality threshold opens the possibility of differentiating between
                    popular trends and those cultural artifacts that become viral in nature, much
                    future work is needed to determine how such differentiations may be investigated
                    operationally across multiple networks. Also, the question remains unanswered as
                    to whether virality is simply a case of attention garnered, or does the content
                    have a significant effect on which trends reach and surpass the virality
                    threshold? We think there is a tipping point when the content becomes less
                    important than the attention itself, but it is not clear whether that will ever
                    be predictable. This question is a new spin on the age-old form/content debate,
                    but in this case the form is a given typology of iteration and the content is
                    whatever text, topic, or digital/cultural artifact motivated a given trend in
                    the first place. This is not a classic chicken/egg problem, because without a
                    doubt a cultural artifact must be delivered to a network before it can gain
                    attention. Rather, the questions raised here are how does the content gain
                    attention <emph>after</emph> its initial delivery, how much of a role in
                    attention-gathering does content play, and/or does sizable attention itself
                    aggregate attention and play a far more significant role in what eventually
                    becomes viral? We offer no answers to these questions, but we hope this study
                    shows the possibility of using operational research methodologies to understand
                    macroscopic attention. Certainly, these questions will never have a final answer
                    — as networked culture and media ecologies are always dynamic, shifting, and
                    changing over time — but this does not mean that writing studies and the digital
                    humanities cannot expand the available methodologies for investigating these
                    questions and provide tentatively effective descriptions for how attention
                    functions. </p>
            </div>


        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Bifet and Frank 2010" xml:id="bifet2010">Bifet, A. and Frank, E.
                    (2010). <title rend="quotes">Sentiment Knowledge Discovery in Twitter Streaming
                        Data</title>. <title rend="italic">Discovery Science</title>. Eds. Bernhard
                    Pfahringer, Geoff Holmes, and Achim Hoffmann. New York: Springer. 1-15.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Brooke 2009" xml:id="brooke2009">Brooke, C. G. (2009). <title
                        rend="italic">Lingua Fracta: Toward a Rhetoric of New Media</title>. New
                    York: Hampton Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Davenport and Beck 2002" xml:id="davenport2002">Davenport, T. H. and
                    Beck, J. C. (2002). <title rend="italic">The Attention Economy: Understanding
                        the New Currency of Business</title>. Boston: Harvard Business Review
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Derrida 1988" xml:id="derrida1988">Derrida, J. (1988). <title
                        rend="italic">Limited Inc</title>. Evanston: Northwestern University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Dobrin 2011" xml:id="dobrin2011">Dobrin, S. I. (2011). <title
                        rend="italic">Postcomposition</title>. Carbondale: Southern Illinois
                    University Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Emerson et al. 2012" xml:id="emerson2012">Emerson, T., Ghosh, R., and
                    Smith, E. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Case Study: Predicting Exposure of Social
                        Messages: The Bin Laden Live Tweeter</title>. <title rend="italic">Practical
                        Text Mining and Statistical Analysis for Non-Structured Text Data
                        Applications</title>. Eds. Gary Miner, John Elder, Andrew Fast, Thomas Hill,
                    Robert Nisbet, and Dursun Delen. Waltham: Academic Press, 2012. 797-802. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Guille and Hacid 2012" xml:id="guille2012">Guille, A., and Hacid, H.
                    (2012). <title rend="quotes">A Predictive Model for the Temporal Dynamics of
                        Information Diffusion in Online Social Networks</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on World Wide
                        Web</title> (pp. 1145–1152). New York, NY, USA: ACM. <ref
                        target="http://doi.org/10.1145/2187980.2188254"
                        >http://doi.org/10.1145/2187980.2188254</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Jockers 2013" xml:id="jockers2013">Jockers, M. L. (2013). <title
                        rend="italic">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>.
                    Champaign: Illinois University Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Kim 2015" xml:id="kim2015">Kim, E. <title rend="quotes">The Politics of
                        Trending</title>. <title rend="italic">Model View Culture</title>. March 19,
                    2015. <ref target="https://modelviewculture.com/pieces/the-politics-of-trending"
                        >https://modelviewculture.com/pieces/the-politics-of-trending</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Krikorian 2014" xml:id="krikorian2014">Krikorian, R. <title
                        rend="quotes">Introducing Twitter Grants</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Twitter Blog</title>. February 5, 2014. <ref
                        target="https://blog.twitter.com/2014/introducing-twitter-data-grants"
                        >https://blog.twitter.com/2014/introducing-twitter-data-grants</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Lanham 2007" xml:id="lanham2007">Lanham, R. A. (2007). <title
                        rend="italic">The Economics of Attention: Style and Substance in the Age of
                        Information</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Lee, Kwak, Park, and Moon 2010" xml:id="lee2010">Lee, C., Kwak, H.,
                    Park, H., and Moon, S. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Finding Influentials Based
                        on the Temporal Order of Information Adoption in Twitter</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on World Wide
                        Web</title> (pp. 1137–1138). New York, NY, USA: ACM. <ref
                        target="http://doi.org/10.1145/1772690.1772842"
                        >http://doi.org/10.1145/1772690.1772842</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Meyers 2009" xml:id="meyers2009">Meyers, R. A. (Ed.) (2009). <title
                        rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Complexity and Systems Science, 2009
                        edition</title>. New York: Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Moretti 2007" xml:id="moretti2007">Moretti, F. (2007). <title
                        rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for Literary
                        History</title>. New York: Verso.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Paul and Dredze 2011" xml:id="paul2011">Paul, M. J., and Dredze, M.
                    (2011). <title rend="quotes">You Are What You Tweet: Analyzing Twitter for
                        Public Health</title>. <title rend="italic">ICWSM</title>, July:
                    265-272.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ridolfo and DeVoss 2009" xml:id="ridolfo2009">Ridolfo, J. and DeVoss,
                    D. N. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Composing for Recomposition: Rhetorical
                        Velocity and Delivery</title>. <title rend="italic">Kairos: A Journal of
                        Rhetoric, Technology, and Pedagogy</title>, 13 (2).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ridolfo and Hart-Davidson 2015" xml:id="ridolfo2015">Ridolfo, J. and
                    Hart-Davidson, W. (2015). <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Rhetoric and the Digital Humanities</title>. Eds. Jim Ridolfo
                    and William Hard-Davidson. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 1-12.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rogers 1983" xml:id="rogers1983">Rogers, E. M. (1983). <title
                        rend="italic">Diffusion of Innovations</title>. New York: Free Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sánchez 2006" xml:id="sanchez2006">Sánchez, R. (2006). <title
                        rend="italic">The Function of Theory in Composition Studies</title>. Albany:
                    State University of New York Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Valente 1995" xml:id="valente1995">Valente, T. W. (1995). <title
                        rend="italic">Network Models of the Diffusion of Innovations</title>.
                    Cresskill, N.J: Hampton Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wolfe 2009" xml:id="wolfe2009">Wolfe, C. (2009). <title rend="italic"
                        >What is Posthumanism?</title> Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Wu, Hofman, Mason, and Watts 2011" xml:id="wu2011">Wu, S., Hofman, J.
                    M., Mason, W. A., and Watts, D. J. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Who Says What to
                        Whom on Twitter</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 20th
                        International Conference on World Wide Web</title> (pp. 705–714). New York,
                    NY, USA: ACM. <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1145/1963405.1963504"
                        >http://doi.org/10.1145/1963405.1963504</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
