<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Open Access and the Theological
                    Imagination<!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Talea <dhq:family>Anderson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Washington State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>talea.anderson@wsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Talea Anderson is the scholarly communications librarian at Washington
                            State University and works on Open Educational Resources at the Center
                            for Digital Scholarship and Curation.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Squires</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Louisiana at Lafayette</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>david.squires@louisiana.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David Squires is an assistant professor of American literature at the
                            University of Louisiana at Lafayette.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000340<!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --></idno>
                <idno type="volume">011<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">4<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date when="2017-12-22">22 December 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>open access</item>
                        <item>open source</item>
                        <item>scholarly communications</item>
                        <item>digital publishing</item>
                        <item>religion</item>
                        <item>rhetoric</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-11-02">Created File</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The past twenty years have witnessed a mounting crisis in academic publishing.
                    Companies such as Reed-Elsevier, Wiley-Blackwell, and Taylor and Francis have
                    earned unprecedented profits by controlling more and more scholarly output while
                    increasing subscription rates to academic journals. Thus publishers have
                    consolidated their influence despite widespread hopes that digital platforms
                    would disperse control over knowledge production. Open access initiatives dating
                    back to the mid-1990s evidence a religious zeal for overcoming corporate
                    interests in academic publishing, with key advocates branding their efforts as
                        <term>archivangelism</term>. Little attention has been given to the legacy
                    or implications of religious rhetoric in open access debates despite its
                    increasing pitch in recent years. This essay shows how the Protestant imaginary
                    reconciles–rather than opposes–open access initiatives with market economics by
                    tracing the rhetoric of openness to free-market liberalism. Working against the
                    tendency to accept the Reformation as an analogy for the relationship between
                    knowledge production, publishers, and academics, we read Protestantism as a
                    counterproductive element of the archivangelist inheritance.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This essay shows how the Protestant imaginary reconciles–rather than opposes–open
                    access initiatives with market economics by tracing the rhetoric of openness to
                    free-market liberalism.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Another Reformation?</head>
                <p> The past twenty years have witnessed a mounting crisis in academic publishing.
                    Companies such as Reed-Elsevier, Wiley-Blackwell, and Taylor and Francis have
                    earned unprecedented profits by controlling more and more scholarly output while
                    increasing subscription rates to academic journals. Harvard’s Faculty Advisory
                    Council signaled the severity of the problem in 2012 when it announced that the
                    university’s library could no longer afford the rising cost of journal
                    subscriptions. <q>Prices for online content from two providers have increased by
                        about 145% over the past six years,</q> the Council memo reported, <q>which
                        far exceeds not only the consumer price index, but also the higher education
                        and the library price indices.</q> The memo goes on to cite publisher profit
                    margins of 35% as one consideration leading to the Council’s conclusion: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#fac2012">Costs are now prohibitive</quote>
                        <ptr target="#fac2012"/>
                    </cit>. The announcement marked a key moment in debates about scholarly
                    publishing not only because Harvard Library has one of the largest library
                    budgets in the world but also because the story elicited attention from the
                    popular press. As the <title rend="italic">Guardian</title> reported, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sample2012">The extraordinary move thrusts one of the world’s
                            wealthiest and most prestigious institutions into the centre of an
                            increasingly fraught debate over access to the results of academic
                            research</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sample2012"/>
                    </cit>. An issue once confined to library budgets suddenly appeared to threaten
                    agendas in scientific research, to encroach upon monograph budgets for
                    humanities acquisitions, even to jeopardize public interests. </p>
                <p> In their memo, Harvard’s Faculty Advisory Council encouraged faculty to consider
                    open access publishing as one means of alleviating the high cost of journal
                        subscriptions.<note> Other suggestions included publishing in journals with
                        sustainable subscription costs, moving journals to sustainable pay-per-use
                        systems, unbundling subscriptions, and encouraging professional
                        organizations to take control of scholarly literature <ptr target="#fac2012"/>.</note> In the context offered by <title rend="italic">The
                        Guardian</title> report, however, open access surfaces as the only solution.
                    And as the news began circulating around the academic blogosphere, open access
                    grew from a single part of Harvard’s strategy for combating inflated journal
                    prices to become, in the words of one advocate, an <q>economic imperative</q>
                    and a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2012">moral imperative</quote>
                        <ptr target="#taylor2012"/>
                    </cit>. The dramatic incline of rhetorical pitch is symptomatic of a pervasive
                    feeling that corporate publishers systematically exploit academic labor. The
                    feeling is understandable. Corporate publishing companies profit from
                    state-sponsored research and the work of university-supported researchers using
                    the neoliberal economic model of public-private partnerships. Public
                    institutions assume the risk and much of the labor while private interests
                    pursue strong market position and high returns. Even if they do not use the term
                        <term>neoliberal</term>, critiques of for-profit academic publishers assume
                    what political theorist Wendy Brown describes as one of the key arguments
                    against neoliberalism, the claim <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#brown2015">that marketization contributes to human exploitation or
                            degradation… because it limits or stratifies access to what ought to be
                            broadly accessible and shared</quote>
                        <ptr target="#brown2015" loc="29"/>
                    </cit>. Advocates of open access publishing raise it as an ethical alternative
                    to a neoliberal tendency toward unprincipled commercialization of public goods. </p>
                <p>We argue, in part, that open access has served less as an alternative to
                    commercialized academic research than as a moral cover for increasingly
                    neoliberal policies. Brown’s analysis of neoliberalism is especially helpful
                    because, beyond identifying new forms of exploitation, she outlines <q>an order
                        of normative reason</q> that organizes progressive solutions to the
                    injustices of capitalism just as much as the economic policies aggravating those
                    injustices <ptr target="#brown2015" loc="30"/>. That normative reason comes into
                    view when Elsevier reports ending 2015 as the fourth largest open access
                    publisher–the same year one of its major divisions reported 37% profit margins
                        <ptr target="#reller2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#relxgroup2015"/>. Far from a moral force for counteracting the
                    avarice of corporate publishers, open access initiatives have exposed new
                    strategies for raising revenue, such as collecting author-paid Article
                    Publishing Charges (APCs) that range from $500 to $5,000 USD [Elsevier <title rend="italic">OA</title>]. The ability of corporate publishers to easily
                    assimilate open access into their profit model merits more attention, especially
                    as open access moves to occupy a dominant position among scholarly
                    communications in digital media. That move manifested in 2013 when the Research
                    Councils UK (RCUK) mandated an implementation policy to make all
                    government-supported research in the United Kingdom freely available online <ptr target="#rcuk2014"/>. Canada’s three major research agencies mandated a
                    similar open access requirement in 2015 <ptr target="#canada2016"/>. In 2016,
                    the European Union Competitive Council followed suit <ptr target="#enserink2016"/>.<note> We want to make clear here that we do not oppose all open access
                        mandates. While critics such as Jeffrey Beall make generalizations against
                        open access initiatives, we mention them here only as an index of the
                        growing importance of open access. We do, however, argue that the growing
                        prominence of open access publishing requires more attention to the details
                        of policy and more skepticism in the face of idealistic rhetoric, whether
                        that rhetoric expresses a pro- or anti-open access position.</note></p>
                <p> These policies arrive after nearly two decades’ worth of work to imagine and
                    create digital communications systems that would disperse control over knowledge
                    production. Each mandate has its strengths and its limitations. But none of them
                    quite fulfills the desire for non-commercial research and less restrictive
                    publishing contracts that motivated many open access advocates. As Daniel
                    Allington, a long-time advocate in the United Kingdom, wrote after the Research
                    Councils mandate, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#allington2013">I feel like a man with a beard in a country where
                            shaving has just been banned</quote>
                        <ptr target="#allington2013"/>
                    </cit>. His oblique reference to biblical law hints at the fervent rhetoric
                    framing open access issues. Since the mid-1990s, when cognitive scientist Stevan
                    Harnad coined the term <term>archavengelism</term> to describe his work to
                    promote open scholarship, the open access movement has incorporated religious
                    rhetoric to organize the terms of debate over how and where academics publish.
                    Evangelical strains of open access advocacy follow the trend of situating open
                    scholarship in opposition to the rapacious excesses of commercial publishers. In
                    this formulation, open access publishing carries the power to reform scholarly
                    communications along the same lines that the Protestant Reformation intervened
                    in papal control over salvation. The analogy likens the institutionalized
                    gatekeeping that allowed the church to sell indulgences to the institutionalized
                    gatekeeping that allows publishers to grossly inflate the cost of producing
                    scholarly journals. The Internet, unsurprisingly, stands in as a technological
                    equivalent of the printing press because it allows for the relatively
                    inexpensive reproduction of text <ptr target="#graham2016"/>. Assuming a moral
                    universe, the story ends with a social revolution that curtails the corporate
                    monopoly on knowledge production much as the Reformation ended the papal
                    monopoly on God’s forgiveness. That conclusion, at least, would fulfill the
                    non-commercial aspirations archivangelism claims for open access publishing.</p>
                <p> Unfortunately, our capitalist world appears more ascendant than a moral
                    universe. We must take stock of our current situation even as many academics
                    continue to work for viable not-for-profit publishing models against the grain
                    of corporate profiteering. How did an apparently anti-corporate project to make
                    scholarship freer coincide with corporate innovations for extracting wealth from
                    scholarly communication systems? Part of the answer lies in how different types
                    of open access achieve the end result of free, online content. While
                    archivangelists such as Harnad promoted open access delivered by voluntary
                    repositories–designated as <term>green OA</term>–companies such as Elsevier
                    created versions of open access delivered by journals–designated as <term>gold
                        OA</term>. In some cases gold OA takes a form similar to <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, which uses Creative
                    Commons licensing that leaves authors with permanent ownership of their work and
                    lets them reprint that work without seeking permission or paying fees. In other
                    cases, gold OA takes a form more like <title rend="italic">Ampersand: An
                        International Journal of General and Applied Linguistics</title>, which
                    requires authors to license exclusive rights to Elsevier and charges $1,000 USD
                    to publish articles ($250 USD for book reviews) <ptr target="#guideforauthorsnd"/>. With the advent of processing fees, some publishers now offer something
                    designated as <term>hybrid OA</term>, which lets authors comply with open access
                    mandates (by paying a fee) while publishing in subscription journals. Many
                    authors choose this option when subscription journals hold a prominent place in
                    their field. Thus publishers can advertise hybrid OA as an option that gives
                    authors more freedom to publish where they want while collecting processing fees
                    for material that appears in journals already paid for by institutional
                    subscriptions–a phenomenon Research Libraries UK calls double dipping <ptr target="#prosser2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Unscrupulous uses of hybrid OA manifest a particular problem linked to the more
                    general problem of academic institutions ceding control over scholarly
                    communications to corporate interests. Recent controversies involving companies
                    such as Academia.edu, ResearchGate, and Mendeley point to a scenario where free
                    online distribution of scholarship consolidates rather than displaces corporate
                    control over academic publishing <ptr target="#matthews2016"/>. As David
                    Golumbia argues in a recent article, open access mandates not only fail to
                    resist for-profit publishing but tend to provide more control to the
                    corporations that own search platforms and databases so central to contemporary
                    academic research. <q>OA as it is currently formulated,</q> writes Golumbia, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#golumbia2016">works to hand more power and profit to these corporate
                            interests while systematically denying individual producers the right to
                            much more modest ownership interests in their own work product</quote>
                        <ptr target="#golumbia2016" loc="78"/>
                    </cit>. The central issue missing from the open access debates, according to
                    Golumbia, is academic labor. He points to the dismissive rhetoric marshalled by
                    many open access advocates against so-called gatekeepers as evidence of a
                    pervasive ideology at odds with the vested interests of researchers, non-profit
                    publishers, and libraries. Similarly, in the seminal <title rend="italic">Open
                        Access and the Humanities</title>, Martin Eve cautions against rhetoric that
                    dismisses the <soCalled>necessary labour</soCalled> provided by editors,
                    reviewers, and publishers <ptr target="#eve2014" loc="151"/>. Building on these
                    critiques, we intend to show how, in addition to lending neoliberal policy the
                    weight of morality, religiously inflected rhetoric has enabled open access
                    debates to imagine a world of free information somehow unfettered by the
                    institutions that produce and organize research. </p>
                <p>The model of the Reformation, in particular, dovetails with neoliberal logic by
                    reimagining institutionally granted access to research materials as an obstacle
                    to individual participation in a global marketplace of ideas. The religious
                    imaginary lending credence to anti-institutional sentiment draws on the
                    theological innovation known as a priesthood of all believers. Martin Luther
                    placed at the foundation of Protestant reform the idea that all Christians are
                    priests. While the Catholic Church insisted that the laity needed ordained
                    priests to mediate their relationship to God, Luther argued that clergy merely
                    minister to the laity by facilitating access to religious rites. As he put it,
                    if any clergy <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#luther1520">wrest this right from the laity and forcibly withhold
                            it, they are tyrants</quote>
                        <ptr target="#luther1520"/>
                    </cit>. The grounding belief that faith alone grants laity a right to practice
                    the sacraments–putting all Christians in direct relationship to God–had
                    far-reaching consequences for Protestantism. It inspired unsanctioned vernacular
                    translations of the Bible and produced a scathing view of indulgences.
                    Ultimately, many scholars connect Reformation theology to the rise of liberal
                    democracy and laissez-faire economics.<note> Most famously, Max Weber (2001)
                        argued that Protestant ethics spurred the development of capitalism. For
                        more recent examples see: <ptr target="#engeman2004"/>
                        <ptr target="#waldron2002"/>
                        <ptr target="#woodberry2012"/>. The affinity linking the Protestant
                        Reformation, liberal democracy, and capitalism need not be understood as
                        natural to be understood as a defining condition of modernity. That
                        historical condition is important to understanding why the seeming
                        anti-corporate rhetoric of religious reform tends nonetheless to reconcile
                        capitalist goals with open access.</note>
                </p>
                <p>When academics draw on this tradition to frame open access as a moral and
                    political issue, they do so rhetorically, without methodically addressing
                    substantive historical connections or analogical correspondences. For that
                    reason, we identify a theological imaginary operating in open access discourse
                    rather than a proper theology.<note> There are exceptions. For instance, Gee
                        (2010) does attempt to bring theological analysis to bear on deciding where
                        to publish academic articles when he asks, without irony, <q>Where Would
                            Jesus Publish?</q>
                        <ptr target="#gee2010"/>.</note> Harnad does not offer a Christian
                    perspective on corporate publishing so much as mobilize the memory of Luther’s
                    critical theology when he describes his own <title rend="quotes">Subversive
                        Proposal</title> for green open access as part of a <soCalled>prophetic
                        vision.</soCalled> Framed in those religious terms, open access resonates
                    unmistakably with the priesthood of all believers when Harnad references the
                    Catholic Church’s imprimatur system for ratifying print, predicting scholars <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#harnad1991">will surely realize that it is they, not the publishers
                            who merely give it the imprimatur, who are the controllers of the
                            quality of the scholarly literature through peer review</quote>
                        <ptr target="#harnad1991"/>
                    </cit>.<note> For Harnad’s <soCalled>Subversive Proposal</soCalled> see <ptr target="#okerson1995"/>.</note> As Luther insisted Christians need not
                    ask the Catholic Church for license to publish religious texts, so Harnad
                    insists academics need not ask publishers for permission to share their own
                    writing online. The analogy fails to recognize how publishers enable particular
                    kinds of complex knowledge production — from assigning DOIs and promoting
                    circulation to organizing peer review and providing editorial feedback — because
                    it reduces them to an illegitimate supervisory role.</p>
                <p> Given the fraught debates surrounding open access publishing, we want to make
                    clear that we too think academics should have the right to share their work
                    online if they so desire. Our contention aims to clarify the mystification at
                    work when a theological imaginary imbues open access rhetoric with an ethos of
                    freedom that actual open access policies do not warrant. We focus here on the
                    religious rhetoric coloring open access advocacy because it has attracted little
                    critical attention even as the mandates continue to inspire discussions
                    saturated with religious rhetoric. Those rhetorical transactions perform what
                    philosopher Hans Blumenberg describes as a <soCalled>reoccupation</soCalled> of
                    historical concerns no longer consistent with present circumstances.<note> For
                        an introduction to the concept of <term>reoccupation</term>, see <ptr target="#blumenberg1983"/>. For an explanation of how reoccupation
                        necessarily involves a rhetorical transaction, see <ptr target="#blumenberg1987"/>.</note> When open access advocates position
                    their cause as a secularized continuation of religious reform, they attempt to
                    reoccupy a historical moment when new publishing technologies catalyzed the
                    democratization of knowledge. Such metaphorical comparisons linking Reformation
                    ideals with the open access movement show how the normative logic of
                    neoliberalism works beyond policy at the level of rhetorical appeal, doing more
                    to fit open access publishing for the intellectual marketplace than to clarify
                    the socioeconomic consequences of free online distribution for
                        scholarship.<note> Graham (2016) makes a similar point about the rhetorical
                        value of the printing press as a metaphor for understanding the Internet
                            <ptr target="#graham2016"/>.</note> Blumenberg diagnoses this sleight of
                    historical rhetoric when he writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#blumenberg1983">A certain specific content is explained by another one
                            preceding it, and indeed in such a way that the asserted transformation
                            of the one into the other is neither an intensification nor a
                            clarification but rather an alienation from its original meaning and
                            function</quote>
                        <ptr target="#blumenberg1983" loc="10"/>
                    </cit>. When the content of open access gets explained in terms of the
                    Reformation, we begin to feel how acute is the need for reform in the field of
                    academic publishing even as the specific politics of reform grow faint. </p>
                <p>Advocates have every reason to want open access to instigate change. However, the
                    theological imaginary informing expectations for open access moves in exactly
                    the wrong direction; it accommodates scholarly communications to techniques of
                    wealth extraction rather than insulating research from market economics.
                    Legitimizing open access as an evangelical cause forces open idealism to
                    reoccupy the impossible theological position of our one true salvation in
                    academic publishing. Blumenberg’s theory of reoccupation pushes us to explicate
                    unnecessary–and ultimately unhelpful–metaphorical conflations in open access
                    rhetoric. His view of rhetoric as not merely deceptive but productive of
                    theoretical thought also encourages us to recognize in rhetorical uses of
                    metaphor the opportunity to reoccupy worthwhile positions seemingly foreclosed
                    by the current field of debate, thus reanimating marginalized traditions of
                    information sharing for our present circumstances. The open concept as derived
                    from commercial imperatives, rather than moral or intellectual imperatives, has
                    been assimilated by the rhetoric of open access. Yet we nonetheless see an
                    opportunity to find a different inheritance in access to libraries. As
                    institutions designed to support publics rather than markets, libraries can
                    affirm a need for communities to control their own cultural heritage and
                    knowledge production. Our hope is that the stewards of knowledge in a digital
                    age might regain scholarly communications as a public good dependent on public
                    institutions. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Evil Empire and Protestant Ethics</head>
                <p>One of the easiest ways to see how open access advocates edge toward
                    evangelism–even when using different terms–is to note the Manichean thinking
                    that animates the field of debate. Manichaeism, for instance, has transformed
                    the historic Elsevier logo into a mythological symbol. Subject to derision among
                    communities that see it as diametrically opposed to the company’s actual
                    publishing practices, that artifact of print history now illustrates the
                    alienated meaning that Blumenberg describes as the result of reoccupation. Isaac
                    Elzevir first introduced the icon used today in 1620 to represent the
                    interdependent relationship between publishers and scholars <ptr target="#elseviernd"/>. It features a tree entwined in grape vines providing
                    fruit and shade to an old man, with a banner hanging near the bottom branches
                    inscribed <term>non solus</term> (not alone). Four hundred years later, the
                    company’s critics have begun to reimagine the icon to convey other meanings
                    entirely. Alexandra Elbakyan, founder of the pirate site Sci-Hub, has compared
                    Elsevier’s icon to the tree of knowledge in the Garden of Eden. By her
                    reckoning, Elsevier forbids access to scholarly knowledge much as God forbade
                    Adam and Eve from partaking in the fruit of knowledge [Elbakyan 2016]. The
                    historical and still necessary partnership between publishers and writers gets
                    sidelined as Elbakyan raises Elsevier to the status of universal creator. She
                    proceeds to refashion God as a tyrant, giving us a story of good and evil that
                    suggests publishers somehow prohibit knowledge production. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Official Elsevier logo (Elsevier 1620)<note> Elsevier, I. <title rend="quotes">Logo des Verlags Elsevier,</title> image (1620).
                            Available at <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AElsevier.svg">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AElsevier.svg</ref>. [11
                            April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>Elsevier logo used by Alexandra Elbakyan in her presentation at the
                        Library Publishing Coalition conference in 2016 (Elbakyan 2016)<note>
                            Elbakyan, A. <title rend="quotes">Why Science Is Better with Communism?
                                The Case of Sci-Hub,</title> presentation slide (2016). Available at
                                <ref target="https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc850001">https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc850001</ref>. [11
                            April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Like many others in academia, Elbakyan blames Elsevier for restricting access to
                    scholarly literature by setting exorbitant prices. Certainly the exorbitant
                    prices deserve criticism. However, her disdain for academic publishing at large
                    exploits a Christian framework that leads to the untenable position of pitting
                    researchers and publishers against one another. Elbakyan appropriated the Eden
                    metaphor to suggest in a crude way that science, or academia more generally,
                    should take control of the means of production. Under the right circumstances
                    open access could help fulfill that goal, but Sci-Hub comes up short because it
                    relies on the system of institutional subscriptions Elbakyan would see crumble.
                    Thumbing one’s nose at publishers and research services–even exploitative
                    ones–hardly displaces the structure of power organized by international
                    copyright law and academic research. Others have made more plausible suggestions
                    for undermining Elsevier’s near-monopoly on scientific publishing, but fall into
                    the same rhetorical trap of equating commercial publishing with a prohibition on
                    knowledge. British mathematician Timothy Gowers, for instance, organized an
                    ongoing boycott against Elsevier in 2012 under the name The Cost of Knowledge
                        <ptr target="#gowersnd"/>. He encouraged academics to take a
                        <soCalled>bottom-up</soCalled> approach to the publishing problem by
                    refusing to write for Elsevier, review the company’s articles, or serve on its
                    editorial boards <ptr target="#gowers2012"/>. Although imperfect for academics
                    who need to publish in those journals, Gowers’s solution has the benefit of
                    acknowledging the academic labor of 16,000 researchers as something worth
                    leveraging. Like Elbakyan, however, the boycott falls into disingenuous rhetoric
                    when it suggests Elsevier prevents research, as it does with the viral image of
                    Elsevier’s logo redrawn with locks and chains on the tree of knowledge where
                    fruit should hang <ptr target="#fakeelsevier2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#gowersnd"/>.<note> For more on @FakeElsevier and the serious
                        concerns motivating the parody account, see <ptr target="#dearelsevier2012"/>.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Adapted Elsevier logo encouraging Elsevier boycott (Forsythe, 2012)<note>
                            Forsythe, G. <title rend="quotes">Boycott Elsevier,</title> logo (2012).
                            Available at <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gforsythe/6799831691">https://www.flickr.com/photos/gforsythe/6799831691</ref>. [11 April
                            2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In reality, of course, Elsevier creates outlets for distributing scholarship
                    according to institutional and economic privilege. The company has created
                    serious problems for academic publishing, but those problems cannot resolve in
                    the current rhetorical tendency to use the company’s name as shorthand for evil.
                    Invectives against Elsevier are all too common amongst proponents of open access
                    publishing, if only because mythologizing the company inevitably caricatures the
                    immoral power structures as dualistic. That quasi-religious dualism emerges when
                    open access advocates name Elsevier as the Galactic Empire, the big bad wolf,
                    Halliburton, the Borg, Sauron, Scrooge, Goliath, a parasite, a snake, and
                        <soCalled>sort of the Death Star of academic publishing</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#circasella2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#ingram2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#froelich2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#dobbs2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#taylor2013c"/>
                    <ptr target="#brembs2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#harnad2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#northrup2009"/>. Critics have reason to worry about corporate
                    publishers that create fake journals or support international arms tradeshows
                        <ptr target="#suber2009"/>. Couching criticism in dualistic terms, however,
                    means those same critics end up in the role of open access prophets, publishing
                    reformers, martyrs, or missionaries with a higher moral calling. These chosen
                    few, the rhetoric suggests, will oust corporate publishers in favor of
                    publishing tactics that exemplify egalitarianism, transparency, and access–that
                    is, openness. </p>
                <p>Advocates of open access draw on a range of mythological references to critique
                    corporate publishers. Popular examples such as <title rend="italic">The Lord of
                        the Rings</title> and <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> easily mix with
                    biblical examples such as Goliath and Eden. The combination of secular and
                    religious dualisms finds a common thread in the Protestant ethic of universal
                    priesthood. By metaphorically opposing publishers and researchers, they suggest
                    the entire world can have access to knowledge if only we circumvent
                    publisher-controlled databases in favor of supposedly unmediated online access.
                    They propose a polarizing narrative–either support authoritarian publishers or
                    oppose them, join or delete, buy in or boycott. Those who flirt with evil
                    provide a cautionary tale inspiring further protests, campaigns, and boycotts.
                    These narratives suggest that even if formerly independent services like
                    Mendeley and Social Science Research Network cannot resist the allure of
                    corporate money, Elsevier users can nonetheless redeem themselves by deleting
                    their accounts and pledging themselves to open access publishing. Open access
                    evangelism thus reenacts the old call for repentance and conversion, inviting
                    academics to set aside their former love for corrupt companies in favor of
                    intellectual morality. </p>
                <p>A few high-profile advocates for open access in particular rely on the language
                    of morality to make their case. Mike Taylor demonstrates this style of
                    evangelical rhetoric when he testifies in the <title rend="italic">Guardian</title> article, <title rend="quotes">Hiding Your Research Behind
                        a Paywall Is Immoral.</title> Taylor portrays himself as a convert to open
                    access. He is a <q>sinner who has repented</q> rather than a <q>righteous man
                        speaking to sinners.</q> Beginning with a confession about having once
                    published in toll-access journals, he treats readers to a first-person account
                    of his transformation. He links to his early closed-access articles as evidence
                    of his sins, writing, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2013a">I heartily wish I’d never done it, and I won’t do it
                            again</quote>
                        <ptr target="#taylor2013a"/>
                    </cit>. Taylor uses the language of transgression and repentance to set the
                    stakes of discussions about open access, with salvation or damnation as the
                    implied consequences of one’s decisions to embrace or reject openness. This
                    language recalls religious testimonies wherein the sinner publicly confesses his
                    wrongdoing while affirming the theology held in common by the congregation. The
                    testimony leverages guilt and community identity to encourage others to follow
                    the path of the testimony-giver <ptr target="#knowlton1991"/>. Like a pastor
                    making an altar call, Taylor exhorts other researchers to emulate him in
                    rejecting priestly authority to publish in more democratic, open access venues. </p>
                <p>Mike Taylor is not alone in calling researchers to faith as an open access
                    evangelist. Michael Eisen–co-founder of the Public Library of Science
                    (PLOS)–likewise plays on religious tropes to support his ideas about scholarly
                    publishing. In 2014, he satirically portrayed himself as a disappointed convert
                    to open access in <title rend="quotes">Why I, a Founder of PLOS, Am Forsaking
                        Open Access.</title> In this April Fools post, Eisen acts as a former
                    adherent to the <soCalled>religion</soCalled> of open access, which he once led
                    as a <soCalled>personal crusade</soCalled> while wearing a gaudy <soCalled>Where
                        Would Jesus Publish?</soCalled> t-shirt to stir up attention <ptr target="#eisen2014"/>.<note> Eisen sells <soCalled>Where Would Jesus
                            Publish?</soCalled> t-shirts on Zazzle for $18.95. Available at:<ref target="http://www.zazzle.com/mbeisen">
                            http://www.zazzle.com/mbeisen</ref>. [11 April 2017].</note> Eisen uses
                    his personal account–an anti-conversion narrative–to satirize opposition to open
                    access and declare his continued adherence to open access principles. While he
                    references his <soCalled>Where Would Jesus Publish?</soCalled> t-shirt
                    self-deprecatingly in the April Fools post, Eisen has used the slogan with
                    consistent conviction, if also flippant humor, since 2008 when he first debuted
                    his WWJP? graphic in a blog post <ptr target="#eisen2008"/>. The apparent irony
                    of using religious messaging to proselytize for scientific publishing dissipates
                    when he explains his career-long mission to harness <q>the Internet’s power</q>
                    to make scientific research <q>more widely available by using a different
                        business model</q> than scientific society journals <ptr target="#eisen2016"/>. Circumventing hallowed institutional control over publishing resonates
                    clearly with a Protestant ethics of reform.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>“Where Would Jesus Publish?” icon developed by Michael Eisen (Eisen,
                            2008)<note> Eisen, Michael. <title rend="quotes">Where Would Jesus
                                Publish?</title> image. <title rend="italic">it is NOT junk</title>
                            (9 October 2008). Available at <ref target="http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=64">http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=64</ref>. [11 April
                            2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Moving in a similar but more devout direction, some scholarly communications
                    professionals have earnestly solicited Jesus’s guidance in sorting out the
                    ethics of academic publishing. Librarian C. William Gee poses Eisen’s question
                    in the title of his 2010 article, <title rend="quotes">WWJP?,</title> suggesting
                    Jesus likely would oppose traditional publishers in the same way he opposed the
                    power structures of his day–namely cheaters and thieves in the form of the
                    Sadducees and Pharisees. Gee argues further that Christ would have favored
                    non-traditional, seemingly unmediated forms of communication, like podcasts <ptr target="#gee2010"/>. Another librarian, Malina Thiede, likewise compares
                    open access to an upstart religion in the short article, <title rend="quotes">On
                        Open Access Evangelism.</title> As a librarian and open access supporter,
                    she recommends converting faculty members and students to open access by
                    distributing petitions and pamphlets or by sponsoring public speaking
                    engagements on university campuses. She continues by cautioning organizers to
                    select speakers carefully to avoid <soCalled>preaching to the choir.</soCalled>
                    Undergraduates, she explains, are <q>particularly fertile ground for the
                        message</q> because most are <q>idealistic and not jaded by the publishing
                        system.</q> Continuing with the metaphor, she names institutional open
                    access mandates as the <soCalled>holy grail</soCalled> of campus outreach
                    efforts <ptr target="#thiede2014" loc="22"/>. While Taylor, Eisen, Gee, and
                    Thiede create their own religious imaginaries for their own contexts, each
                    suggests academia should regard open access as a moral issue. The language of
                    reformation, conversion, and evangelism lets advocates perform an ethics of
                    religious reform that invites audiences to set aside old loyalties to the
                    authoritarian publishing priesthood and enter into a purer, less hindered
                    relationship with the products of academic research.</p>
                <p>In keeping with its evocation of religious ideals, the open access movement has
                    coupled stories of conversion and redemption with examples of asceticism and
                    sacrifice. No figure exemplifies that role better than Aaron Swartz, who appears
                    in open access discourse as a martyr for having suffered dearly in his fight for
                    the cause. Swartz was a programmer and Internet activist who, in 2010,
                    downloaded some 4.8 million articles from JSTOR. Federal prosecutors indicted
                    him under the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act of 1986 for the potential infraction.
                    While still facing thirteen felony charges, Swartz committed suicide on January
                    11, 2013.<note> Charges against Swartz included breaking and entering, wire
                        fraud, computer fraud, unlawfully obtaining information from a protected
                        computer, and recklessly damaging a protected computer. See <ptr target="#kirschbaum2011"/>. </note> The headlines following his death
                    formed a public consensus: <title rend="quotes">Freedom’s Martyr: The Story of
                        Aaron Swartz</title>
                    <ptr target="#smith2014"/>, read one, while another contemplated <title rend="quotes">Aaron Swartz and 21st-Century Martyrdom</title>
                    <ptr target="#stoller2014"/>.<note> For further examples of the tendency to
                        beatify Swartz, see <ptr target="#day2013"/> and <ptr target="#wihbey2015"/>.</note> The tragedy of Swartz’s death makes the outpouring of praise for
                    his work both understandable and sympathetic. Yet the hagiographic terms of that
                    praise contribute to misplaced contempt for the so-called gatekeepers of
                    knowledge by situating researchers against any research tool that charges a
                    subscription fee. As Golumbia puts it, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#golumbia2016">The contempt looks as if it is directed at a for-profit
                            publisher that gouges authors and customers alike, yet without
                            difficulty it turns into an attack on an entity whose purpose is to
                            support, not profit from, academic work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#golumbia2016" loc="97"/>
                    </cit>. The universalizing ethics of open access–befitting the universal ethics
                    of Protestantism–fail to recognize important distinctions between JSTOR and
                    Elsevier. Elsevier owns and publishes journals, while JSTOR merely digitizes and
                    distributes them; Elsevier is a corporation, while JSTOR is a nonprofit;
                    Elsevier charges exorbitant prices, while JSTOR provides its services for
                    relatively low costs. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Aaron Swartz dedication inviting viewers to “Be Free” (Newby, 2013)<note>
                            Newby, K. <title rend="quotes">Aaron Swartz Graphic,</title> image
                            (2013). Available at <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Aaron_Swartz_Graphic.png">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Aaron_Swartz_Graphic.png</ref>.
                            [11 April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The rough comparison makes clear how JSTOR can achieve a symbiotic rather than
                    parasitic relationship to academic publishing, although we would hesitate to
                    raise it as a paragon. Rather, we want to suggest how dualistic constructions,
                    putting subscription tools on one side of a conflict against open access
                    initiatives, fail to appreciate the complex field of research services. Further,
                    by lumping together companies like Elsevier and JSTOR, the animus against
                    toll-access resources fallaciously implies we might secure access to research
                    materials without the institutions responsible for producing and disseminating
                    them. Evidence of Swartz’s anti-institutional sentiments appear in a <title rend="quotes">Guerilla Open Access Manifesto</title> that he published
                    online in 2008. A representative passage captures the style and message of the
                    manifesto: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#swartz2008">We need to take information, wherever it is stored, make
                            our copies and share them with the world….We need to download scientific
                            journals and upload them to file sharing networks. We need to fight for
                            Guerilla Open Access. With enough of us, around the world, we’ll not
                            just send a strong message opposing the privatization of knowledge —
                            we’ll make it a thing of the past.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#swartz2008"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>Prosecuting attorneys viewed these statements as evidence of Swartz’ intentions
                    to open access forcibly and illegally to copyrighted information. The charges
                    they brought against him, had they been carried out, could have sent him to
                    prison for over 50 years <ptr target="#cushing2012"/>. The aggressive–indeed,
                    excessive–prosecution contributes to the martyrdom narrative by embattling
                    law-and-order copyright against open access. Swartz’s Manifesto participates by
                    setting its own bellicose terms for circulating scholarship online as part of a
                    crusade. Accepting those terms perpetuates the idea that sharing journal
                    articles outside of toll-access databases can somehow sidestep the difficult
                    problems facing academic publishing simply by making intellectual property
                    rights and publishers <soCalled>a thing of the past.</soCalled>
                </p>
                <p>The idea of relegating copyright to the past invites the mistaken presumption
                    that we no longer need the institutions designed to share copyrighted materials.
                    Libraries in particular can appear as just so many obstacles along the path
                    toward unlimited access. To question that view of research institutions,
                    however, one need only point to the file sharing networks that let academics
                    circulate research outside the legal structure of copyright. Those networks
                    inevitably remind us that protest piracy relies on the very systems it hopes to
                    end, as in the case of Sci-Hub, or on private companies that have no
                    responsibility to academics. An example of the latter circumstance emerged in
                    response to Swartz’s death when Micah Taylor, Eva Vivalt, and Jessica Richman
                    created #pdftribute to honor his legacy. The hashtag invited Twitter users to
                    post full-text copies of articles in memory of Swartz, thus opening access to
                    that work for public use. By January 13, 2013, the hashtag had garnered some
                    15,000 tweets and 40 million impressions <ptr target="#murphy2013"/>. Although a
                    heartening tribute, Twitter links to articles hosted at Academia.edu hardly
                    offer a sound alternative to the organized collections and discovery tools that
                    libraries make available to researchers. Trading the library catalog for several
                    thousand tweets would spell disaster for access. That fact seems surprisingly
                    counterintuitive in a rhetorical situation that celebrates open access by
                    imagining Swartz will <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#vignesh2013">live on, a glorious son</quote>
                        <ptr target="#vignesh2013"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Tweets from the #PDFTribute honoring Aaron Swartz (Anderson, 2016).<note>
                            Postsoftware. <title rend="quotes">Aaron Swartz Memorial,</title> image
                            (2013). Available at <ref target="http://postsoftware.org/2013/01/25/aaron-swartz-memorial">http://postsoftware.org/2013/01/25/aaron-swartz-memorial</ref>. [11
                            April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>Aaron Swartz memorial (postsoftware, 2013)<note> Weinstein, P. <title rend="quotes">Saint IGNUcius of the Church of Emacs,</title> image
                            (2002). Available at <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pdweinstein/16857951635">https://www.flickr.com/photos/pdweinstein/16857951635</ref>. [11
                            April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>From Free to Open</head>
                <p>One reason Swartz presents such a compelling figure for so many different
                    constituencies is because he worked comfortably between the world of hackers and
                    the world of researchers. Swartz’s facility in different intellectual spheres
                    contributed to his tremendous impact as an activist. At the same time, that
                    capacity makes him a clear vector for tracing the flow of ideas about open
                    access between hacker communities, popular pundits, and academics. Here Timothy
                    Brennan’s notion of <term>flow</term> elucidates the circulation of ideas as
                    more than mere influence. In Brennan’s words, flow <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#brennan2006">suggests a market-generated excitement for concepts
                            where the borrowing of ideas is concealed in order to enact an
                            individualized rediscovery of a dominant cliché</quote>
                        <ptr target="#brennan2006" loc="37"/>
                    </cit>. The cultural clichés Brennan questions have to do with globalization and
                    many of the same neoliberal policies propelling open access mandates. For our
                    purposes, dominant ideas about the Internet as a global force for opening
                    knowledge flow between different intellectual communities, each with its own
                    motivations yet all trading on the generally positive and far-ranging
                    connotations of <term>open</term> as unregulated, clear, free, accessible,
                    candid, public, and transparent. Different affiliations to openness coalesce in
                    the term’s vague sanguinity and manifest in the rhetorical move to reoccupy an
                    oppositional stance to corrupt institutions, imagined most dramatically as a new
                    Reformation. Tracing the flow of open advocacy not just through academic debates
                    but through a broader appeal to openness in popular discourses will clarify how,
                    rather than insulating scholarly publishing from market forces, open access
                    squares with commercial interests.</p>
                <p> To appreciate how market-generated excitement can energize a theological
                    imaginary around open access, it helps to recall that we experience the Internet
                    differently today than we did in the late 1990s. Those of us who lived through
                    it probably do not need any reminder of dial-up modems, AOL chat rooms,
                    Angelfire and GeoCities websites, or the novelty of sharing MP3 files. However,
                    even folks who feel a twinge of nostalgia at reading those names might need to
                    check Wikipedia–first launched in 2001–to recall that Wi-Fi was the name of a
                    brand new trade alliance in 1999 or that the ubiquity of touchscreen technology
                    was about a decade off yet. The rapid naturalization of such brand names and the
                    digital technologies they commercialize can complicate the work of recapturing
                    the heady days of early Internet culture. Yet that historical moment bears some
                    consideration for understanding debates about open access publishing.
                    Best-selling titles like <title rend="italic">The Cluetrain
                    Manifesto</title>–featuring the popular 95 Theses–and, more recently, Douglas
                    Rushkoff’s <title rend="italic">Ten Commandments for a Digital Age</title> make
                    clear how the turn of the millennium laid the foundation for exploring digital
                    publishing models in academia according to religious metaphors. With regard to
                    rhetorical strategy, many of the negotiations over open access publishing replay
                    in an academic context the contentious debates over open source software in the
                    1990s.</p>
                <p>The most notorious of those debates produced the term <term>open source</term>.
                    The idea of open source software, much like the idea of open access publishing
                    that it inspired, took shape in response to increasing corporate monopoly.
                    Hackers and archivangelists both saw the Internet as a way around
                    corporate-controlled information access. For hacker communities, the web
                    provided a means of mass collaboration and distribution that could circumvent
                    regular software markets. Corporate attempts to control Internet access
                    threatened to stifle that realm of non-commercial exchange and Microsoft came to
                    represent the worst of corporate overreach when it cornered the browser market
                    with Internet Explorer.<note> The United States brought an anti-trust suit
                        against Microsoft in May 1998. The decision, handed down in an appellate
                        court three years later, found Microsoft in violation of the Antitrust Act.
                        For a full analysis of the case, see <ptr target="#weinstein2002"/>.</note>
                    Microsoft’s biggest competitor, Netscape, lost most of its customer base to
                    Internet Explorer in what is now known as the first browser war. In January
                    1998, as a last-ditch effort to recoup favor among hackers, Netscape announced
                    plans to release all future versions of their web browser for free and to
                    license their base code for public use. The idea cut against the grain of
                    commercial software models by drawing inspiration from the free software
                    movement, which championed the idea of giving users access to the source code
                    and distribution rights to encourage people to hack–that is, tinker with an
                    application’s functionality <ptr target="#kelty2008" loc="105–7"/>.</p>
                <p>The plan did not gain traction fast enough to save Netscape. It did, however,
                    create a rift among hackers and proponents of free software. Netscape’s
                    announcement inspired a contingent of the free software movement to pursue, as
                    influential hacker Eric S. Raymond put it, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1998">the serious push to get ‘free software’ accepted in the
                            mainstream corporate world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1998"/>
                    </cit>. Before Netscape’s decision to pursue a free software model, Raymond
                    assumed the emphasis on <term>free</term> and the unabashedly left-leaning
                    tradition of <term>copyleft</term> activism unnecessarily kept commercial
                    enterprises at arm’s length. Hackers took pains to clarify how free software
                    might be compatible with for-profit business models. The founder of the Free
                    Software Foundation, Richard Stallman, famously encouraged people <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lessig2006">to think free as in free speech, not free beer</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lessig2006"/>
                    </cit>. When Netscape invited more mainstream interest, however, Raymond decided
                    the free software movement needed a makeover that would neutralize its
                    anti-commercial rhetoric. He started the Open Source Initiative with
                    business-minded supporters and began the work of rebranding <term>free
                        software</term> as <term>open source</term>, laying the rhetorical ground
                    for open access publishing.</p>
                <p>Definitions of open source software resonate with the aims of early open access
                    initiatives and look nearly identical to standard criteria for free software. In
                    general, open source licensing allowed users to access, edit, and distribute
                    software without restrictions. The Open Source Initiative aimed at reforming the
                    cultural politics of free software, not the engineering practices it enabled.
                    Stallman articulated the critical difference between <term>free</term> and
                        <term>open</term> software precisely when he expressed concern that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#stallman1999">the rhetoric of ‘Open Source’ focuses on the potential
                            to make high quality, powerful software, but shuns the ideas of freedom,
                            community, and principle</quote>
                        <ptr target="#stallman1999"/>
                    </cit>. Where Stallman championed a philosophy of users’ rights, Raymond
                    championed pragmatism geared toward developing better software. The different
                    motivating philosophies caused a schism that marginalized free software and
                    aligned open source with corporate interests. Raymond explained that goal with a
                    short call-to-arms published in the weeks after Netscape announced its historic
                    plans. There he described the idea of free software as inimical to marketing: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1998">The term makes a lot of corporate types nervous</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1998"/>
                    </cit>. Later he clarified his view that the Free Software Foundation failed
                    because <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1999b">its evangelism had backfired</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999b" loc="206"/>
                    </cit>. He suggested by contrast that the Open Source Initiative <q>should be
                        evangelizing top-down</q> to convert <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1999a">CEO/CTO/CIO types</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a" loc="207"/>
                    </cit>. In important ways, the battle over terminology occurred at the
                    rhetorical level of publicity. As popular Internet skeptic Evgeny Morozov put
                    it, the open source camp <q>won with better PR,</q> not better ideas <ptr target="#morozov2013"/>. </p>
                <p>The narrative carried forward by the Open Source Initiative allowed its vision of
                    free labor, faster innovation, and better software to flow from a relatively
                    marginal hacker community into the mainstream tech industry on its way toward
                    the business world. Raymond’s most influential writings, collected in <title rend="italic">The Cathedral and the Bazaar</title>, argued for alternatives
                    to proprietary software development by appealing to readers frustrated with
                    Microsoft’s dominance. With Microsoft playing the role of corporate giant,
                    Raymond used language strikingly close to Harnad’s to cast himself as an
                        <soCalled>accidental revolutionary</soCalled> and the open source operating
                    system Linux as <soCalled>subversive</soCalled> of slow, centralized development
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a" loc="21"/>.<note> The claim that <q>Linux is
                            subversive</q> serves as the opening line of Raymond’s original essay,
                            <title rend="quotes">The Cathedral and the Bazaar</title>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a"/>, and survives in the book editions. </note>
                    That move fitted his critique for commercial assimilation even as it also
                    painted him as an iconoclast disruptive of sacred idols. His signature piece,
                    the title essay in <hi rend="italic">The Cathedral and the Bazaar</hi>,
                    established the dichotomy that convinced decision-makers in the business world
                    that open source could structure <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1999a">a succession of miracles</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a" loc="30"/>
                    </cit>. Raymond’s parable characterizes proprietary software like Windows as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1999a">cathedrals, carefully crafted by individual wizards or
                            small bands of mages working in splendid isolation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a" loc="29"/>
                    </cit>. In contrast to those <q>quiet, reverent</q> cathedrals, he explains,
                    open source communities <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1999a">resemble a great babbling bazaar</quote>
                        <ptr target="#raymond1999a" loc="30"/>
                    </cit>. That Raymond champions bazaars–marketplaces–announces his difference
                    from the Free Software movement while also positioning him as critical of big
                    software corporations. His iconoclasm adopts particularly Protestant
                    characteristics by objecting to symbols of Catholic hierarchy while arguing for
                    direct input from autonomous individuals who determine their own mode of
                    participation.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Visual notes created at the Open Education Conference in 2012,
                        illustrating Raymond’s <title rend="italic">The Cathedral and the
                            Bazaar</title> (Forsythe, 2012)<note> Forsythe, G. <title rend="quotes">The Cathedral and the Bazaar,</title> visual notes (2012).
                            Available at <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gforsythe/7985992388">https://www.flickr.com/photos/gforsythe/7985992388</ref>. [11 April
                            2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Raymond’s deprecation of a quintessentially Catholic symbol linked his essay to a
                    late-90s zeitgeist of tech writing. That body of literature took the Protestant
                    Reformation as a model for understanding how the Open Source Initiative engaged
                    government and corporate powers. Popular publications such as <title rend="italic">Salon</title> chronicled the open source saga with titles like
                        <title rend="quotes">The Saint of Free Software</title> and <title rend="quotes">Let My Software Go!</title>
                    <ptr target="#fss1999"/>. Thomas Scoville offered one of the more systematic
                    analogies in his <title rend="italic">Salon</title> article, <title rend="quotes">Martin Luther, Meet Linus Torvalds.</title> Torvalds, sponsor
                    of Linux, not only meets Luther in Scoville’s account but also becomes Luther
                    for the digital age. Luther’s challenge to papal authority sets the stage for an
                    elaborate analogy situating the Open Source Initiative as heir to the Protestant
                    Reformation. Why? <q>Because Torvalds wants to shift power back in your
                        direction,</q> Scoville writes. <q>Because Torvalds’ God, like Luther’s,
                        wants you to know Him on a first-name basis.</q> He goes on to explain why <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#scoville1998">the Microsoft papacy is not amused</quote>
                        <ptr target="#scoville1998"/>
                    </cit>. Linux users, the idea goes, had a unique opportunity to reform the tech
                    industry and individual users’ relationship to personal computing. </p>
                <p>The great, insular tech companies stood between users and their computers,
                    according to this analogy. And worse, they created institutional barriers
                    between computing platforms that need not exist. The computing reformation led
                    by open source evangelists promoted self-organized hacker communities that
                    seemed to operate without such institutional barriers. Nobody was more emphatic
                    over the Internet’s apparent ability to make corporate institutions obsolete
                    than David Weinberger in <title rend="italic">The Cluetrain Manifesto</title>.
                    He expressed the zeitgeist when he wrote, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#weinberger2000">The spiritual lure of the Web is the promise of the
                            return of voice</quote>
                        <ptr target="#weinberger2000" loc="39"/>
                    </cit>. In the Cluetrain’s 95 Theses, we see a crystallization of Protestant
                    ethics aligned with the spirit of capitalism in the celebration of individual
                    access to markets unimpeded by corporations. Extending the logic forwarded by
                    the Open Source Initiative, Weinberger characterized all corporations as
                    cathedrals working to control rather than enable market transactions.</p>
                <p>With help from tech journalism, the Open Source Initiative planted the seed for
                    what has since become a universalizing call for <soCalled>open source
                        everything.</soCalled><note> For further evidence of this trend, see a
                        series of TED talks from 2005: <ptr target="#benkler2005"/>
                        <ptr target="#leadebeater2005"/>
                        <ptr target="#rheingold2005"/>
                        <ptr target="#shirky2005"/>.</note> One leader of that call, Robert David
                    Steele, makes plain the high stakes advocates place on open source information
                    technology. His 2012 book titled <title rend="italic">The Open-Source Everything
                        Manifesto</title> proclaims the belief that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#steele2012">a public able to access all information all the time”
                            can build “a prosperous world at peace</quote>
                        <ptr target="#steele2012" loc="xiv"/>
                    </cit>. Extending his vision of open everything beyond the material world, he
                    goes on to suggest that universal access to information will let humans <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#steele2012">become One with God through transparency, truth, and
                            trust</quote>
                        <ptr target="#steele2012" loc="xix"/>
                    </cit>. Steele’s mysticism takes mass collaboration as <emph>the</emph> cultural
                    practice leading to transcendent forms of knowledge unavailable under current
                    conditions. With a background in government and military intelligence, Steele
                    bends his suggestions toward better solutions for informing public officials,
                    such as an open source intelligence agency separate and independent from the
                    CIA. How mass collaboration would work in such a context remains vague, yet
                    Steele’s religious conviction in the efficacy of mass collaboration determines
                    his account of openness as not just a method for sharing computer code but also
                    a fundamental value for modifying, to his mind, literally everything. Its
                    tendency toward universalist formulations of open access makes this manifesto a
                    utopian example of the genre. As implausible as Steele’s political vision
                    appears, however, the spirit of openness informing it has given shape to new
                    experiments in state governance, such as Barack Obama’s Open Government
                    Initiative and the Public Data Group in the United Kingdom. </p>
                <p>Open initiatives have entered the political sphere. Yet no single movement or
                    coherent politics organizes under the sign <term>open</term>. If the initial
                    rift among hackers implied divergent positions on open source as a concept for
                    organizing economic resources and social relations, the more recent trend toward
                    open everything implies an even more diverse field of investment in the term.
                    That is one reason publishing companies like Elsevier can market themselves as
                        <q>unleashing the power of sharing</q> at the same time they sue university
                    libraries for disclosing subscription rates <ptr target="#wise2016"/>.<note> For
                        more on Elsevier’s lawsuit see: <ptr target="#hadro2009"/>. </note>
                    Accusations of so-called openwashing suggest such claims amount to empty
                    branding. As Nathaniel Tkacz has argued, however, the problem of emptiness may
                    run deeper than Elsevier’s intentions. He calls <term>open</term> an empty
                    signifier, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#tkacz2013">one whose very function and appeal rests precisely on
                            its ultimate vacuity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#tkacz2013"/>
                    </cit>. The vacuity, or at least the pliability, of openness as an intellectual
                    or political ideal helps account for its traction in spheres as diverse as
                    software development, government policy, and academic publishing. As sociologist
                    Christopher Kelty observes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kelty2008">While <term>free</term> tends toward ambiguity...
                                <term>open</term> tends toward obfuscation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kelty2008" loc="143"/>
                    </cit>. By pointing to strategic obfuscation, Kelty reminds cultural critics
                    that the rhetoric of open access exceeds the problem of signification to
                    encompass political positioning as well. Openness, from its conceptualization as
                    a marketing solution for hackers to its political arrival in the form of new
                    initiatives and mandates, operates as what political analysts once called a
                    glittering generality: a vague term with generally positive connotations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Politics of Publishing</head>
                <p>The antiquated but nonetheless germane concept of a glittering generality
                    explains the rhetorical success of openness. Who could accept its
                    opposite–closed access? The idea is not only uninviting but also contradictory,
                    all the better to ensure the positive value associated with open initiatives.
                    The Institute of Propaganda Analysis introduced the term <soCalled>glittering
                        generality</soCalled> in their 1937 publication <title rend="italic">The
                        Fine Art of Propaganda</title>, which may be the first text to raise
                    openness to a political ideal. In the course of rejecting undemocratic political
                    developments in the United States and Europe, the Institute argued for public
                    discourse <soCalled>out in the open</soCalled>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ipa1939">Around the cracker barrel, a spirit of friendly good
                            sportsmanship has been the treasured tradition</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ipa1939" loc="3–4"/>
                    </cit>. Their defense of democratic principles took aim in particular at
                    Catholic extremist Father Charles Coughlin. As an anti-Semitic socialist, Father
                    Coughlin epitomized everything the United States opposed in the years leading up
                    to World War II. His newspaper and radio program, repugnant in the extreme,
                    certainly existed <soCalled>out in the open</soCalled> in the sense that he made
                    them available for public consumption. The sense of open that the Institute
                    advocated did not mean, primarily, accessible. Rather, the authors of <title rend="italic">The Fine Art of Propaganda</title> gave openness an
                    ideological value constellated with other democratic virtues such as independent
                    thought and research. In a world split <q>as never before between two
                        faiths,</q> the foreword explained, open discussion offered a mode of
                    sincere communication that could resist the deceptions associated with autocracy
                        <ptr target="#ipa1939" loc="vii"/>.</p>
                <p>The ideological sense of openness intended by the Institute for Propaganda
                    Analysis found philosophical footing in the work of Karl Popper. During the same
                    years the Institute worked to discredit the rhetorical sleights of
                    propagandists, Popper wrote his best-known work of political philosophy, <title rend="italic">The Open Society and Its Enemies</title>.<note> In the preface
                        to the second edition, Popper writes that he worked on the book from March
                        1938 to 1943 <ptr target="#popper1962" loc="viii"/>. The Institute for
                        Propaganda Analysis remained active from 1937 to 1942.</note> And like the
                    Institute, Popper understood openness as a political solution to the historical
                    problem of defending liberal democracy against totalitarianism as it manifested
                    in fascist and communist states. This line of thinking made open discourses–that
                    is, discourses open to critique, revision, negotiation–the cornerstone of
                    democracy. While discourse moves into the foreground, the democratic
                    institutions that support them appear as abstractions, as when Popper described
                    an ideal political process as rational: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#popper1962">Only democracy provides an institutional framework that
                            permits reform without violence, and so the use of reason in political
                            matters</quote>
                        <ptr target="#popper1962" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. Given the context of its historical moment, one can appreciate how
                    Popper’s opposition to unreasonable discourse and violent reform would appear as
                    implicitly anti-Nazi even without staking out a political position. More than
                    any institutional program or framework, however, the first volume of <title rend="italic">The Open Society and Its Enemies</title> concludes with a
                    strong emphasis on <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#popper1962">the new faith of the open society, the faith in man, in
                            equalitarian justice, and in human reason</quote>
                        <ptr target="#popper1962" loc="189"/>
                    </cit>. By mustering social faith in opposition to totalitarianism, Popper left
                    the problem of an open politics implicitly linked to liberal democracy and free
                    market economics as if openness constituted the animating spirit of capitalism.
                    That meaning of the <soCalled>open society</soCalled> grew more prominent in the
                    second half of the twentieth century within a Cold War context.</p>
                <p>The influence of Popper’s legacy on open access debates started to take shape in
                    the mid-1980s under the direction of billionaire businessman George Soros. While
                    Popper left the question of institutions abstract but implicitly related to
                    state power, Soros made them concrete and explicitly geared toward commercial
                    enterprise. Soros began implementing an economic version of Popper’s open
                    society in 1984 with an alliance between his primary foundation in New York City
                    and the Hungarian Academy of Science to establish the Soros Foundation Budapest.
                    Other foundations in the region followed as Soros labored under the influence of
                    what he described as <q>rather potent messianic fantasies</q> to open communist
                    states up to neoliberal, capitalist influence <ptr target="#soros1990" loc="3"/>. <q>I fancied myself as some kind of god or economic reformer,</q> he wrote
                    in 1987 <ptr target="#soros1987" loc="362"/>. By 1993 Soros had created the Open
                    Society Institute (later renamed the Open Society Foundations) to manage various
                    foundations operating in the former Soviet Union with his financial support <ptr target="#hoduskiabbott2003" loc="75–77"/>. In this way, Popper’s
                    philosophical faith in reason inspired a push to shape political and economic
                    forces that, after the Cold War, would create the material conditions of
                    international knowledge production. </p>
                <p>The Open Society Institute’s $3 million grant to support the Budapest Open Access
                    Initiative (BOAI) illustrates one avenue of influence it used to achieve that
                    mission. Widely understood as coining the term open access as well as defining
                    its scope, BOAI first invited universities, libraries, and professional
                    associations to <q>embrace open access as a means of advancing their
                        missions</q> in 2002 <ptr target="#boai2002"/>. Inspired by the theological
                    imaginary that some of its most prominent signatories helped popularize (notably
                    Eisen and Harnad), the Budapest initiative struggled to imagine libraries and
                    universities as anything other than a barrier to scholarly communications in
                    need of reform. Since their first meeting the initiative has periodically
                    reaffirmed their goal <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#boai2017">for Open Access (OA) to all new peer reviewed
                            research</quote>
                        <ptr target="#boai2017"/>
                    </cit>. The universal sweep of the mission betrays a misunderstanding of
                    different institutional missions and different fields of research. Such
                    extravagant aims conferred urgency and simplicity to the open access message
                    while it remained a marginal force in academic publishing. Fifteen years and
                    several important mandates later, BOAI proclaims the same message as if its
                    implications have not changed.</p>
                <p> Part of what we have argued is that the implications of open access advocacy did
                    change as it moved into the mainstream, starting with the 2012 Research Councils
                    UK mandate. The religious, especially Protestant, rhetoric that once conveyed
                    moral opposition to excessive profit margins and unnecessary restrictions on
                    scholarly communication just as easily informed a neoliberal argument for open
                    access on the basis of economic development and free trade. David Willetts, UK
                    Minister of State for Universities and Science, demonstrated the smooth
                    rhetorical pivot from attacking the so-called cathedrals of corporate publishing
                    to attacking academic institutions when he made the case for open access in a
                        <title rend="italic">Guardian</title> op-ed titled, <title rend="quotes">We
                        Cannot Afford to Keep Research Results Locked Away in Ivory Towers</title>
                    <ptr target="#willetts2013"/>. Willetts blamed academic institutions for
                    sequestering research behind paywalls, as if university libraries conspired with
                    faculty to devise that system of payment. Calling for more
                        <soCalled>transparency,</soCalled> he invoked openness in Popper’s sense of
                    enlightenment rationality and state accountability as a justification for
                    mandating pay-to-publish gold open access. His argument obscures the fact that
                    libraries have a method of delivering free content to users, one that
                    extraordinary inflation and privately controlled online databases threaten to
                    break. Nowhere does Willetts mention those problems associated with the
                    corporatization of academic publishing that the open access movement sought to
                    redress, yet the anti-institutional force of open advocacy carries his argument
                    all the way to its concluding appeal <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#willetts2013">to commercialise the fruits of [British] research more
                            quickly</quote>
                        <ptr target="#willetts2013"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>The archivangelists generally do not object to commercial interests comingling
                    with academic research. Yet, despite including familiar watchwords, the RCUK’s
                    mandate did not impress them. Mike Taylor greeted a revised form of the mandate
                    on his blog with a vomiting stickman and called it <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2013b">the result of lobbying by a truly regressive publishing
                            industry</quote>
                        <ptr target="#taylor2013b"/>
                    </cit>. Harnad issued an equally disgusted statement arguing that the new
                    policies would waste money while propping up the status quo in publishing <ptr target="#harnad2012"/>. In April 2015, <title rend="italic">Times Higher
                        Education</title> reported that UK research organizations spent more than
                    £10 million on article processing charges in the first year of the policy <ptr target="#else2015"/>. The trajectory toward corporate assimilation of open
                    access drove Harnad to declare his retirement from archivangelism in early 2016.
                        <q>I fought the fight and lost,</q> he tweeted in an exchange with Michael
                    Eisen, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#harnad2016a">and now I’ve left the #OA arena</quote>
                        <ptr target="#harnad2016a"/>
                    </cit>. Even in that farewell note his rhetoric borrowed from a theological
                    imaginary, this time reoccupying the position of Apostle Paul. <q>I have fought
                        the good fight,</q> wrote Paul as he faced martyrdom. <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#timothykjv">I have finished my course, I have kept the
                            faith</quote>
                        <ptr target="#timothykjv"/>
                    </cit>. Harnad confirmed his retirement in a subsequent interview that featured
                    a picture of the <q>open access archivangelist</q> pointing to the heavens. His
                    alienation from open advocacy, he explained, grew over time as he repeated the
                    same arguments to no avail <ptr target="#harnad2016b"/>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Mike Taylor’s reaction to RCUK mandates (Taylor, 2013)</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>Stevan Harnad, archivangelist (Poynder, 2007)<note> Poynder, R. <title rend="quotes">Stevan Harnad,</title> image (2007). Available at <ref target="http://poynder.blogspot.com/2007/07/oa-interviews-stevan-harnad.html">http://poynder.blogspot.com/2007/07/oa-interviews-stevan-harnad.html</ref>.
                            [11 April 2017].</note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>If repeating the same rhetoric of archivangelism did not succeed in achieving
                    what Harnad hoped, one might fairly suggest a new approach. Protestant metaphors
                    have provided a convenient rallying point for open access advocates but these
                    same stories emerged from western socioeconomic traditions that marry well with
                    aggressive corporate profiteering and suspicion of intermediary
                    institutions–publishers, certainly, but also libraries and non-profit
                    organizations like JSTOR. In doing so, open rhetoric has mobilized individual
                    action without imagining how sustained change in academic publishing might build
                    on existing information infrastructures. By way of conclusion, we want to
                    propose a different understanding of online access that does not resort to a
                    dogmatic universalism bound up with the Protestant imaginary. If the
                    anti-cathedral rhetoric of open access reoccupies the perspective of one true
                    religion to offer one true access solution, we want to suggest a
                    community-oriented perspective that draws on a tradition of public support for
                    organizing and disseminating knowledge.<note> A few recent initiatives
                        associated with the digital humanities mark positive steps toward library
                        support for community-driven access. Importantly, these initiatives avoid
                        replicating the theological imaginary of open access. See the Open Library
                        of Humanities for an example that encourages collaboration between
                        libraries, publishers, and scholarly associations <ptr target="#olh"/>. For
                        a discussion of how Traditional Knowledge labels and the Mukurtu CMS
                        represent more nuanced perspectives on access, see <ptr target="#christen2015"/>. In the sciences, SciELO and Redalyc offer
                        models of open access that rethink the mandate model for encouraging free,
                        online access to research. See <ptr target="#packer2014"/>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We recognize in libraries a centuries-long tradition of caring for
                    information–its access and regulation; its organization and contextualization–as
                    a public good that can incorporate various political, cultural, and religious
                    values. Although neither simple nor unproblematic, the tradition of public
                    libraries carries with it an ideal of democratic education currently under
                    threat by a broken model for academic publishing. More practically, libraries
                    have a variety of access solutions from onsite use and traditional lending to
                    online viewing and download. More than cathedrals, bazaars, or evangelical
                    missions, libraries have the potential to support research communities by
                    investing in not-for-profit knowledge systems. By contrast, the rhetorical
                    tradition inherited from open source computing weakens democratic publishing
                    solutions by providing moral legitimacy to neoliberal trends that political
                    theorists such as Wendy Brown link to an erosion of self-governance. In that
                    sense, open evangelists, like many missionaries before them, find themselves
                    implicated in furthering exploitative traditions even as they spread the good
                    news of equality, democracy, and universal access <ptr target="#hathcock2016"/>.
                    We hope to see open access advocacy invest itself less in circumventing public
                    institutions–even if their power structures deserve critique–and invest more in
                    new systems for sharing knowledge that place publishers, libraries, and authors
                    in functional relation to one another.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allington2013" label="Allington 2013">Allington, D. <title rend="quotes">On Open Access, and Why It’s Not the Answer,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Culture: Digital and Otherwise</title>, blog post, 15
                    October 2013. Available at: <ref target="http://www.danielallington.net/2013/10/open-access-why-not-answer/">http://www.danielallington.net/2013/10/open-access-why-not-answer/</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="benkler2005" label="Benkler 2005">Benkler, Y. <title rend="quotes">The
                        New Open-Source Economics,</title> TEDGlobal, July 2005. Available at: <ref target="https://www.ted.com/talks/yochai_benkler_on_the_new_open_source_economics">https://www.ted.com/talks/yochai_benkler_on_the_new_open_source_economics</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blumenberg1983" label="Blumenberg 1983">Blumenberg, H. <title rend="italic">The Legitimacy of the Modern Age</title>, Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts Institute of Technology Press (1983). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blumenberg1987" label="Blumenberg 1987">Blumenberg, H. <title rend="quotes">An Anthropological Approach to the Contemporary Significance
                        of Rhetoric,</title> in <title rend="italic">After Philosophy: End or
                        Transformation?</title> Cambridge, Massachusetts Institute of Technology
                    Press (1987), pp. 429-458.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brembs2016" label="Brembs 2016">Brembs, B. <title rend="quotes">Sci-Hub as Necessary, Effective Civil Disobedience,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Björn Brembs Blog</title>, 25 February 2016. Available
                        at:<ref target="http://bjoern.brembs.net/2016/02/sci-hub-as-necessary-effective-civil-disobedience/">
                        http://bjoern.brembs.net/2016/02/sci-hub-as-necessary-effective-civil-disobedience/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brennan2006" label="Brennan 2006">Brennan, T. <title rend="italic">Wars of Position: The Cultural Politics of Left and Right</title>, New
                    York, Columbia University Press (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2015" label="Brown 2015">Brown, Wendy. <title rend="italic">Undoing the Demos: Neoliberalism’s Stealth Revolution</title>, New York,
                    Zone Books (2015). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boai2002" label="BOAI 2002">Budapest Open Access Initiative <title rend="quotes">Read the Budapest Open Access Initiative,</title> 14 February
                    2002. Available at: <ref target="http://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/read">http://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/read</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boai2017" label="BOAI 2017">Budapest Open Access Initiative <title rend="quotes">BOAI15,</title> 14 February 2017. Available at: <ref target="http://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/boai15-1">http://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/boai15-1</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="christen2015" label="Christen 2015">Christen, K. <title rend="quotes">Tribal Archives, Traditional Knowledge, and Local Contexts: Why the ‘S’
                        Matters,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Western Archives</title>, vol. 6, no, 1 (2015),
                    pp. 1-19. Available at: <ref target="http://digitalcommons.usu.edu/westernarchives/vol6/iss1/3/">http://digitalcommons.usu.edu/westernarchives/vol6/iss1/3/</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="circasella2015" label="Circasella 2015">Circasella, J. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier: Ever More Evil (aka, Why Do Authors Boycott
                        Elsevier?),</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open @ CUNY</title>, 20 May 2015. Available at:<ref target="https://openaccess.commons.gc.cuny.edu/2015/05/20/elsevier-ever-more-evil/">
                        https://openaccess.commons.gc.cuny.edu/2015/05/20/elsevier-ever-more-evil/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cushing2012" label="Cushing 2012">Cushing, T. <title rend="quotes">U.S. Government Ups Felony Count in JSTOR/Aaron Swartz Case from Four to
                        Thirteen,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">TechDirt</title>, 18 September 2012. Available at: <ref target="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120917/17393320412/us-government-ups-felony-count-jstoraaron-swartz-case-four-to-thirteen.shtml">https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120917/17393320412/us-government-ups-felony-count-jstoraaron-swartz-case-four-to-thirteen.shtml</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="day2013" label="Day 2013">Day E. <title rend="quotes">Aaron Swartz:
                        Hacker, Genius…Martyr?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Guardian</title>, 1 June 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/jun/02/aaron-swartz-hacker-genius-martyr-girlfriend-interview">
                        http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/jun/02/aaron-swartz-hacker-genius-martyr-girlfriend-interview</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dearelsevier2012" label="Dear Elsevier 2012">
                    <title rend="quotes">Dear Elsevier Employees, with Love, from
                        @FakeElsevier,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Real Fake Elsevier</title>, blog post, 19 February
                    2012. Available at: <ref target="https://fakeelsevier.wordpress.com/">https://fakeelsevier.wordpress.com/</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dobbs2013" label="Dobbs 2013">Dobbs, D. <title rend="quotes">When the
                        Rebel Alliance Sells Out,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Yorker</title>, 12 April 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/when-the-rebel-alliance-sells-out">
                        http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/when-the-rebel-alliance-sells-out</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eisen2008" label="Eisen 2008">Eisen, M. <title rend="quotes">Where
                        Would Jesus Publish?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">it is NOT junk</title>, blog post, 9 October 2008.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=64">http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=64</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eisen2014" label="Eisen 2014">Eisen, M. <title rend="quotes">Why I, a
                        Founder of PLOS, Am Forsaking Open Access,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">it is NOT junk</title>, blog post, 1 April 2014. Available
                        at:<ref target="http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1580">
                        http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1580</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eisen2016" label="Eisen 2016">Eisen, M. <title rend="quotes">PLOS,
                        Open Access and Scientific Societies,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">it is NOT junk</title>, blog post, 21 March 2016. Available
                    at: <ref target="http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1890">http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1890</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elbakyan2016" label="Elbakyan 2016">Elbakyan, A. <title rend="quotes">Why Science Is Better with Communism? The Case for Sci-Hub,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open Access @ University of North Texas</title>, 19 May
                    2016. Available at: <ref target="http://openaccess.unt.edu/symposium/2016/info/transcript-and-translation-sci-hub-presentation">http://openaccess.unt.edu/symposium/2016/info/transcript-and-translation-sci-hub-presentation</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="else2015" label="Else 2015">Else, H. <title rend="quotes">Publishers
                        Share £10m in APC Payments,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Times Higher Education</title>, 16 April 2015. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/publishers-share-10m-in-apc-payments/2019685.article">https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/publishers-share-10m-in-apc-payments/2019685.article</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elseviernd" label="Elsevier n.d."> Elsevier, n.d. <title rend="italic">History</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.elsevier.com/about/company-information/history">https://www.elsevier.com/about/company-information/history</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elsevieroand" label="Elsevier OA n.d.">Elsevier n.d. <title rend="italic">Open Access</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.elsevier.com/about/open-science/open-access">https://www.elsevier.com/about/open-science/open-access</ref> [10 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="engeman2004" label="Engeman and Zuckert 2004">Engeman, T. S. and
                    Zuckert, M. P. eds. <title rend="italic">Protestantism and the American
                        Founding</title>. Notre Dame, University of Notre Dame Press (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="enserink2016" label="Enserink 2016">Enserink, M. <title rend="quotes">In Dramatic Statement, European Leaders Call for ‘Immediate’ Open Access to
                        All Scientific Papers by 2020,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science</title>, 27 May 2016. Available at: <ref target="http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/dramatic-statement-european-leaders-call-immediate-open-access-all-scientific-papers">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/dramatic-statement-european-leaders-call-immediate-open-access-all-scientific-papers</ref>.
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eve2014" label="Eve 2014">Eve, M. <title rend="italic">Open Access and
                        the Humanities.</title> Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2014.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781316161012">https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781316161012</ref>. [30 August 2017]. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fac2012" label="Faculty Advisory Council 2012">Faculty Advisory
                    Council <title rend="quotes">Faculty Advisory Council Memorandum on Journal
                        Pricing,</title> The Harvard Library, 17 April 2012. Available at: <ref target="http://gantercourses.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Faculty-Advisory-Council-Memorandum-on-Journal-Pricing-%C2%A7-THE-HARVARD-LIBRARY.pdf">http://gantercourses.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Faculty-Advisory-Council-Memorandum-on-Journal-Pricing-%C2%A7-THE-HARVARD-LIBRARY.pdf</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fakeelsevier2012" label="@FakeElsevier 2012"> Fake Elsevier,
                    [@FakeElsevier] February 2012, Twitter account. Available at: <ref target="https://twitter.com/FakeElsevier">https://twitter.com/FakeElsevier</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fss1999" label="Free Software Story 1999"><title rend="quotes">The
                        Free Software Story: Complete Salon Technology Coverage of Linux, the
                        Open-Source Movement and Free Software’s Ideas and Personalities,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Salon</title>, 4 May 1999. Available at:<ref target="http://www.salon.com/1999/05/04/opensource/">
                        http://www.salon.com/1999/05/04/opensource/</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="froelich2013" label="Froelich 2013">Froelich, T. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier Takes Over Mendeley: And You, What Do You Think?</title> trans.
                    Laurence Bianchini, <title rend="italic">MNIScience</title>, 11 April 2013.
                    Available at:<ref target="https://www.mysciencework.com/omniscience/elsevier-takes-over-mendeley-and-you-what-do-you-think">
                        https://www.mysciencework.com/omniscience/elsevier-takes-over-mendeley-and-you-what-do-you-think</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gee2010" label="Gee 2010">Gee, C. W. <title rend="quotes">WWJP: ‘Where
                        Would Jesus Publish?’</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Christian Librarian</title>, vol. 53, no. 3 (2010), pp.
                    98-100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="golumbia2016" label="Golumbia 2016">Golumbia, D. <title rend="quotes">Marxism and Open Access in the Humanities: Turning Academic Labor Against
                        Itself,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Workplace</title>, vol. 28 (2016), pp. 74-114.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="canada2016" label="Government of Canada 2016">Government of Canada
                        <title rend="italic">Tri-Agency Open Access Policy on Publications</title>,
                    21 December 2016. Available at: <ref target="http://www.science.gc.ca/default.asp?lang=En&amp;n=F6765465-1">http://www.science.gc.ca/default.asp?lang=En&amp;n=F6765465-1</ref> [10
                    April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gowersnd" label="Gowers n.d.">Gowers, T. <title rend="italic">The Cost
                        of Knowledge</title>, n.d. Available at: <ref target="http://www.thecostofknowledge.com/">http://www.thecostofknowledge.com/</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gowers2012" label="Gowers 2012">Gowers, T. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier–My Part In Its Downfall,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Gowers’s Weblog</title>, blog post, 21 January 2012.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://gowers.wordpress.com/2012/01/21/elsevier-my-part-in-its-downfall/">https://gowers.wordpress.com/2012/01/21/elsevier-my-part-in-its-downfall/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="graham2016" label="Graham 2016">Graham, E. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Printing Press as Metaphor,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, vol. 10, no. 3
                    (2016). Available at: <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000264/000264.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000264/000264.html#</ref> [10
                    April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guideforauthorsnd" label="Guide for Authors n.d.">Guide for Authors
                    n.d. <title rend="italic">Ampersand</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.elsevier.com/journals/ampersand/2215-0390/guide-for-authors">https://www.elsevier.com/journals/ampersand/2215-0390/guide-for-authors</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hadro2009" label="Hadro 2009">Hadro, J. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier
                        Motion to Block Public-Records Request of Washington State University
                        Denied,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Library Journal</title> 25 June 2009. Available at: <ref target="http://lj.libraryjournal.com/2009/06/academic-libraries/elsevier-motion-to-block-public-records-request-of-washington-state-university-denied/">http://lj.libraryjournal.com/2009/06/academic-libraries/elsevier-motion-to-block-public-records-request-of-washington-state-university-denied/#</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harnad1991" label="Harnad 1991">Harnad, S. <title rend="quotes">Post-Gutenberg Galaxy: The Fourth Revolution as the Means of Production of
                        Knowledge,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Public-Access Computer Systems Review</title>, vol. 2, no.
                    1 (1991), pp. 39-53. Available at: <ref target="http://cogprints.org/1580/1/harnad91.postgutenberg.html">http://cogprints.org/1580/1/harnad91.postgutenberg.html</ref> [10 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harnad2012" label="Harnad 2012">Harnad, S. <title rend="quotes">There’s No Justifying the Research Council UK’s Support for Gold Open
                        Access,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 3 September 2012. Available at: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/higher-education-network/blog/2012/sep/03/rcuk-gold-open-access-research-unjustified">https://www.theguardian.com/higher-education-network/blog/2012/sep/03/rcuk-gold-open-access-research-unjustified</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harnad2015" label="Harnad 2015">Harnad, S. <title rend="quotes">A
                        Caricature of Its Own Making,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open Access Archivangelism</title>, blog post, 29 December
                    2015. Available at:<ref target="http://openaccess.eprints.org/index.php?/archives/1170-A-caricature-of-its-own-making.html">
                        http://openaccess.eprints.org/index.php?/archives/1170-A-caricature-of-its-own-making.html</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harnad2016a" label="Harnad 2016a">Harnad, S. [@AmSciForum] <title rend="quotes">but I agree-I fought the fight and lost and now I've left the
                            <ref target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OA?src=hash">#OA</ref>
                        arena,</title> Twitter post, 23 March 2016. Available at: <ref target="https://twitter.com/amsciforum/status/712852714389172224">https://twitter.com/amsciforum/status/712852714389172224</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harnad2016b" label="Harnad 2016b">Harnad, S. <title rend="quotes">Open
                        Access Archivangelist: The Last Interview?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">CEON: Otwarta Nauka</title>, blog post, 2016. Available at:
                        <ref target="http://otwartanauka.pl/in-english/experts-on-open-access?id=1090">http://otwartanauka.pl/in-english/experts-on-open-access?id=1090</ref> [11
                    April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hathcock2016" label="Hathcock 2016">Hathcock, A. <title rend="quotes">Making the Local Global: The Colonialism of Scholarly
                        Communication,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">At the Intersection</title>, blog post, 27 September 2016.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2016/09/27/making-the-local-global-the-colonialism-of-scholarly-communication/">https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2016/09/27/making-the-local-global-the-colonialism-of-scholarly-communication/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hoduskiabbott2003" label="Hoduski-Abbott 2003">Hoduski-Abbott, B.
                        <title rend="italic">Lobbying for Libraries and the Public’s Access to
                        Government Information: An Insider’s View</title>, Lanham, MD, Scarecrow
                    Press (2003). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ingram2013" label="Ingram 2013">Ingram, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Empire Acquires the Rebel Alliance: Mendeley Users Revolt against Elsevier
                        Takeover,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">GIGAOM</title>, 9 April 2013. Available at: <ref target="https://gigaom.com/2013/04/09/the-empire-acquires-the-rebel-alliance-mendeley-users-revolt-against-elsevier-takeover/">
                        https://gigaom.com/2013/04/09/the-empire-acquires-the-rebel-alliance-mendeley-users-revolt-against-elsevier-takeover/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ipa1939" label="IPA 1939">The Institute for Propaganda Analysis,
                        <title rend="italic">The Fine Art of Propaganda: A Study of Father
                        Coughlin's Speeches</title>, New York, Harcourt, Brace and Company
                    (1939).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kelty2008" label="Kelty 2008">Kelty, C. M. <title rend="italic">Two
                        Bits: The Cultural Significance of Free Software</title>, Durham, Duke
                    University Press (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschbaum2011" label="Kirschbaum 2011">Kirschbaum, C. <title rend="quotes">Swartz Indicted for JSTOR Theft,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Tech</title>, 3 August 2011. Available at: <ref target="http://tech.mit.edu/V131/N30/swartz.html">http://tech.mit.edu/V131/N30/swartz.html</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knowlton1991" label="Knowlton 1991">Knowlton, D. <title rend="quotes">Belief, Metaphor, and Rhetoric: The Mormon Practice of Testimony
                        Bearing,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sunstone</title>, 1 April 1991, pp. 20-27. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://www.sunstonemagazine.com/pdf/081-20-27.pdf">https://www.sunstonemagazine.com/pdf/081-20-27.pdf</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="leadebeater2005" label="Leadebeater 2005">Leadebeater, C. <title rend="quotes">The Era of Open Innovation,</title> TEDGlobal, July 2005.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://www.ted.com/talks/charles_leadbeater_on_innovation">https://www.ted.com/talks/charles_leadbeater_on_innovation</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lessig2006" label="Lessig 2006">Lessig, L. <title rend="quotes">Free,
                        As In Beer,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Wired</title>, 1 September 2006. Available at: <ref target="https://www.wired.com/2006/09/free-as-in-beer/">https://www.wired.com/2006/09/free-as-in-beer/</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="luther1520" label="Luther 1520">Luther, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Babylonian Captivity of the Church,</title> section 2, paragraph 21 (1520).
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.lutherdansk.dk/Web-babylonian%20Captivitate/Martin%20Luther.htm">http://www.lutherdansk.dk/Web-babylonian%20Captivitate/Martin%20Luther.htm</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="matthews2016" label="Matthews 2016">Matthews, D. <title rend="quotes">Do Academic Social Networks Share Academics’ Interests?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Times Higher Education</title>, 7 April 2016. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/features/do-academic-social-networks-share-academics-interests">https://www.timeshighereducation.com/features/do-academic-social-networks-share-academics-interests</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="morozov2013" label="Morozov 2013">Morozov, E. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Meme Hustler: Tim O’Reilly’s Crazy Talk,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Baffler</title>, vol. 22, April 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://thebaffler.com/salvos/the-meme-hustler">
                        http://thebaffler.com/salvos/the-meme-hustler</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murphy2013" label="Murphy 2013">Murphy, D. <title rend="quotes">Twitter Campaign “#pdftribute” Roars to Life in Tribute to Aaron
                        Swartz,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">PCMag</title>, 13 January 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2414241,00.asp">
                        http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2414241,00.asp</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="northrup2009" label="Northrup 2009">Northrup, L. <title rend="quotes">Academic Publisher Pays Professors for Shill Amazon Reviews,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Consumerist</title>, 13 July 2009. Available at:<ref target="https://consumerist.com/2009/07/13/academic-publisher-pays-professors-for-shill-amazon-reviews/">
                        https://consumerist.com/2009/07/13/academic-publisher-pays-professors-for-shill-amazon-reviews/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="okerson1995" label="Okerson and O'Donnell 1995">Okerson, A. S. and
                    O’Donnell, J. J. <title rend="italic">Scholarly Journals at the Crossroads: A
                        Subversive Proposal for Electronic Publishing</title>, Association of
                    Research Libraries, Washington D.C. (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olh" label="Open Library of Humanities">Open Library of Humanities,
                        <title rend="quotes">The OLH Model,</title> n.d. Available at <ref target="https://www.openlibhums.org/site/about/the-olh-model/">https://www.openlibhums.org/site/about/the-olh-model/</ref> [27 September
                    2017]. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="packer2014" label="Packer et al. 2014">Packer, A. L., Cop, N.,
                    Luccisano, A., Ramalho, A., Spinak, E. <title rend="quotes">SciELO: 15 Years of
                        Open Access: An Analytic Study of Open Access and Scholarly
                        Communication,</title> Paris, UNESCO (2014). Available at <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.7476/9789230012373">http://dx.doi.org/10.7476/9789230012373</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="popper1962" label="Popper 1962">Popper, K. <title rend="italic">The
                        Open Society and Its Enemies: Volume I, The Spell of Plato</title>,
                    Princeton, Princeton University Press (1962).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prosser2015" label="Prosser 2015">Prosser, D. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Costs of Double Dipping,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Research Libraries UK</title>, blog post, 11 February 2015.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.rluk.ac.uk/about-us/blog/the-costs-of-double-dipping/">http://www.rluk.ac.uk/about-us/blog/the-costs-of-double-dipping/</ref> [10
                    April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raymond1998" label="Raymond 1998">Raymond, E. S. <title rend="quotes">Goodbye, ‘free software’; hello, ‘open source,’</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Eric S. Raymond’s Home Page</title>, 8 February 1998.
                    Available at:<ref target="http://www.catb.org/~esr/open-source.html">
                        http://www.catb.org/~esr/open-source.html</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raymond1999a" label="Raymond 1999a">Raymond, E. S. <title rend="quotes">The Cathedral and the Bazaar,</title> 30. Available
                        online:<ref target="http://www.catb.org/esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/"> http://www.catb.org/esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raymond1999b" label="Raymond 1999b">Raymond, E. S. <title rend="quotes">The Revenge of the Hackers,</title> in <title rend="italic">The Cathedral and the Bazaar</title>, Cambridge, O’Reilly (1999), pp.
                    167-92. Available online:<ref target="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/hacker-revenge/ar01s05.html">
                        http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/hacker-revenge/ar01s05.html</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reller2016" label="Reller 2016">Reller T. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier Publishing–A Look at the Numbers, and More,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Elsevier Connect</title>, blog post, 22 March 2016.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://www.elsevier.com/connect/elsevier-publishing-a-look-at-the-numbers-and-more">https://www.elsevier.com/connect/elsevier-publishing-a-look-at-the-numbers-and-more</ref>
                    [10 April 2017]</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="relxgroup2015" label="RELX Group 2015">RELX Group <title rend="italic">Annual Reports and Financial Statements</title> (2015). Available at: <ref target="http://www.relx.com/investorcentre/reports%202007/Documents/2015/relxgroup_ar_2015.pdf">http://www.relx.com/investorcentre/reports%202007/Documents/2015/relxgroup_ar_2015.pdf</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rcuk2014" label="RCUK 2014">Research Councils UK <title rend="italic">RCUK Policy on Open Access</title> (2014). Available at: <ref target="http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/research/openaccess/policy/">http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/research/openaccess/policy/</ref> [10 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rheingold2005" label="Rheingold 2005">Rheingold, H. <title rend="quotes">The New Power of Collaboration,</title> TED2005, February
                    2005. Available at: <ref target="https://www.ted.com/talks/howard_rheingold_on_collaboration">https://www.ted.com/talks/howard_rheingold_on_collaboration</ref> [11 April
                    2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sample2012" label="Sample 2012">Sample, I. <title rend="quotes">Harvard University Says It Can’t Afford Journal Publishers’ Prices,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Guardian</title>, 24 April 2012. Available at: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2012/apr/24/harvard-university-journal-publishers-prices">https://www.theguardian.com/science/2012/apr/24/harvard-university-journal-publishers-prices</ref>
                    [10 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scoville1998" label="Scoville 1998">Scoville, T. <title rend="quotes">Martin Luther, Meet Linus Torvalds.</title> 12 November 1998. No longer
                    available at Salon.com; use Way Back Machine at Archive.org: <ref target="http://www.salon.com/21st/feature/1998/11/12feature.html">http://www.salon.com/21st/feature/1998/11/12feature.html</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shirky2005" label="Shirky 2005">Shirky, C. <title rend="quotes">Institutions vs. Collaboration,</title> TEDGlobal, July 2005. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://www.ted.com/talks/clay_shirky_on_institutions_versus_collaboration">https://www.ted.com/talks/clay_shirky_on_institutions_versus_collaboration</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2014" label="Smith 2014">Smith, S. <title rend="quotes">Freedom’s
                        Martyr: The Story of Aaron Swartz,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Huffington Post</title>, 30 July 2014. Available at:<ref target="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/sean-d-smith/freedoms-martyr-the-story_b_5631239.html">
                        http://www.huffingtonpost.com/sean-d-smith/freedoms-martyr-the-story_b_5631239.html</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="soros1987" label="Soros 1987">Soros, G. <title rend="italic">The
                        Alchemy of Finance: Reading the Mind of the Market</title>, New York, John
                    Wiley and Sons, Inc. (1987).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="soros1990" label="Soros 1990">Soros, G. <title rend="italic">Underwriting Democracy: Encouraging Free Enterprise and Democratic Reform
                        Among the Soviets and in Eastern Europe</title>, New York, Public Affairs,
                    (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stallman1999" label="Stallman 1999">Stallman, R. <title rend="quotes">The GNU Operating System and the Free Software Movement,</title> in <title rend="italic">Open Sources: Voices from the Open Source Revolution</title>.
                    Cambridge, O’Reilly Media (1999). Available at:<ref target="http://www.oreilly.com/openbook/opensources/book/stallman.html">
                        http://www.oreilly.com/openbook/opensources/book/stallman.html</ref> [11
                    April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stallman2000" label="Stallman 2000">Stallman, R. <title rend="quotes">St. IGNUcius,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Richard Stallman’s Personal Site</title>, blog post, 15
                    August 2000. Available at: <ref target="https://stallman.org/saint.html">https://stallman.org/saint.html</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="steele2012" label="Steele 2012">Steele, R. D. <title rend="italic">The
                        Open-Source Everything Manifesto: Transparency, Truth and Trust</title>,
                    Berkeley, CA., Evolver Editions (2012). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stoller2014" label="Stoller 2014">Stoller, M. <title rend="quotes">Aaron Swartz and 21st-Century Martyrdom,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Vice</title>, 9 July 2014. Available at:<ref target="https://www.vice.com/print/aaron-swartz-and-21st-century-martyrdom-709">
                        https://www.vice.com/print/aaron-swartz-and-21st-century-martyrdom-709</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="suber2009" label="Suber 2009">Suber, P. <title rend="quotes">Elsevier
                        and Merck Published Fake Medical Journal,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open Access News</title>, blog post, 5 May 2009. Available
                    at: <ref target="http://legacy.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/2009/05/elsevier-and-merck-published-fake.html">http://legacy.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/2009/05/elsevier-and-merck-published-fake.html</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="swartz2008" label="Swartz 2008">Swartz, A. <title rend="quotes">Guerrilla Open Access Manifesto,</title> July 2008. Available at:<ref target="https://archive.org/stream/GuerillaOpenAccessManifesto/Goamjuly2008_djvu.txt">
                        https://archive.org/stream/GuerillaOpenAccessManifesto/Goamjuly2008_djvu.txt</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2012" label="Taylor 2012">Taylor, M. <title rend="quotes">Harvard’s Library Can’t Afford Journal Subscriptions,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sauraopod Vertebra Picture of the Week</title>, blog post,
                    23 April 2012. Available at: <ref target="https://svpow.com/2012/04/23/harvards-library-cant-afford-journal-subscriptions/">https://svpow.com/2012/04/23/harvards-library-cant-afford-journal-subscriptions/</ref>
                    [10 April 2017]. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2013a" label="Taylor 2013a">Taylor, M. <title rend="quotes">Hiding Your Research Behind a Paywall Is Immoral,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Guardian</title>, 17 January 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/science/blog/2013/jan/17/open-access-publishing-science-paywall-immoral">
                        http://www.theguardian.com/science/blog/2013/jan/17/open-access-publishing-science-paywall-immoral</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2013b" label="Taylor 2013b">Taylor, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Progressive Erosion of the RCUK Open Access Policy,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sauropod Vertebra Picture of the Week</title>, blog post,
                    22 February 2013. Available at: <ref target="https://svpow.com/2013/02/22/the-progressive-erosion-of-the-rcuk-open-access-policy/">https://svpow.com/2013/02/22/the-progressive-erosion-of-the-rcuk-open-access-policy/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2013c" label="Taylor 2013c">Taylor, M. <title rend="quotes">Seriously, Mendeley People, What Did You Expect?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sauropod Vertebra Picture of the Week</title>, blog post,
                    15 April 2013. Available at: <ref target="https://svpow.com/2013/04/15/seriously-mendeley-people-what-did-you-expect/">
                        https://svpow.com/2013/04/15/seriously-mendeley-people-what-did-you-expect/</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thiede2014" label="Thiede 2014">Thiede, M. <title rend="quotes">On
                        Open Access Evangelism,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Serials Librarian</title>, vol. 67 (2014), p.
                    22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="timothykjv" label="Timothy KJV">2 Timothy 4:7-8, Holy Bible: King
                    James Version.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tkacz2013" label="Tkacz 2013">Tkacz, N. <title rend="quotes">Open
                        Sesame,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Aeon</title>, 28 January 2013. Available at:<ref target="https://aeon.co/essays/bazaar-the-rise-and-rise-of-open-source-politics">
                        https://aeon.co/essays/bazaar-the-rise-and-rise-of-open-source-politics</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vignesh2013" label="Vignesh 2013">Vignesh, S. <title rend="quotes">Remember Aaron Swartz,</title> 21 January 2013. Available at:<ref target="http://www.rememberaaronsw.com/memories/">
                        http://www.rememberaaronsw.com/memories/</ref> [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="waldron2002" label="Waldron 2002">Waldron, J. <title rend="italic">God, Locke, and Equality: Christian Foundations in Locke’s Political
                        Thought</title>. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weber2001" label="Weber 2001">Weber, M. <title rend="italic">The
                        Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism</title>, New York, Roxbury
                    Publishing Company (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weinberger2000" label="Weinberger 2000">Weinberger, D. <title rend="quotes">The Longing,</title> in <title rend="italic">The Cluetrain
                        Manifesto</title>, Basic Books, New York (2000), pp. 39-46.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weinstein2002" label="Weinstein 2002">Weinstein, S. N. <title rend="quotes">United States v. Microsoft Corp,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Berkeley Technology Law Journal</title>, vol. 17, no.1
                    January 2002, pp. 273-94. Available at:<ref target="http://scholarship.law.berkeley.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1352&amp;context=btlj">
                        http://scholarship.law.berkeley.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1352&amp;context=btlj</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wihbey2015" label="Wihbey 2015">Wihbey, J. <title rend="quotes">Public
                        Knowledge for the Public Good: Working toward Digital Access in the Spirit
                        of Aaron Swartz,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Shorenstein Center</title>, blog post, 28 January 2015.
                        <ref target="https://medium.com/@ShorensteinCtr/public-knowledge-for-the-public-good-working-toward-digital-access-in-the-spirit-of-aaron-swartz-51659d311228#.ayj7z0eei">https://medium.com/@ShorensteinCtr/public-knowledge-for-the-public-good-working-toward-digital-access-in-the-spirit-of-aaron-swartz-51659d311228#.ayj7z0eei</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="willetts2012" label="Willetts 2012">Willetts, D. <title rend="quotes">Government to Open Up Publicly Funded Research,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Gov.uk,</title> 16 July 2012. Available at:<ref target="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research">
                        https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="willetts2013" label="Willetts 2013">Willetts, D. <title rend="quotes">We Cannot Afford to Keep Research Results Locked Away in Ivory
                        Towers,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Guardian</title>, 9 April 2013. Available at:<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/apr/09/open-access-scientific-publishing-peer-review-scientific-publishing">
                        https://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/apr/09/open-access-scientific-publishing-peer-review-scientific-publishing</ref>
                    [11 April 2017]. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wise2016" label="Wise 2016">Wise, A. <title rend="quotes">Still
                        Unleashing the Power of Sharing,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Elsevier Connect</title> 5 August 2016. Available at: <ref target="https://www.elsevier.com/connect/still-unleashing-the-power-of-sharing?sf32899399=1">https://www.elsevier.com/connect/still-unleashing-the-power-of-sharing?sf32899399=1</ref>
                    [11 April 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="woodberry2012" label="Woodberry 2012">Woodberry, R. D. <title rend="quotes">The Missionary Roots of Liberal Democracy,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">American Political Science Review</title>, vol. 106, no. 2
                    (May 2012), pp. 244-74.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>