<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Using structured text corpora in Parliamentary
                    Metadata Language for the analysis of legislative
                    proceedings<!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Richard <dhq:family>Gartner</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Warburg Institute, London, UK</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>richard.gartner@sas.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr Richard Gartner is the Digital Librarian at the Warburg Institute,
                            School of Advanced Study at the University of London.  He is both a practising
                            librarian and an academic specializing in digital librarianship. Previously he
                            has worked as a lecturer in the Department of Digital Humanities at King’s College London
                            and as the New Media Librarian at the Bodleian Library, Oxford. His primary area of research
                            is metadata theory and practice and he is the author of a recent book on this subject 
                            <title rend="italic">Metadata: Shaping Knowledge from Antiquity to the Semantic Web</title> (Springer, 2016). 
                            He also has research interests in the creation and curation of digital collections.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"
                    ><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000392</idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 -->012</idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 -->2</idno>
                <date when="2018-09-18">18 September 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>metadata</item>
                        <item>parliamentary metadata</item>
                        <item>text analysis</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="GP" when="2018-08-01"> Created document, all c/e but code blocks</change>
            <change who="GP" when="2018-08-19">code blocks, added to TOC</change>
            <change who="GP" when="2018-08-22">fixed headers</change>
            <change who="GP" when="2018-08-25">added bio and citations from author</change>
            <change who="GP" when="2018-09-18">incorporated final author changes</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article examines the potential of employing structured texts, encoded in the
                    Parliamentary Metadata Language XML schema, for the machine-readable analysis of
                    substantial corpora of legislative proceedings. It demonstrates the potential of
                    using PML corpora for combining the results of sentiment analysis with
                    contextual metadata to establish and visualise patterns of divergent attitudes
                    towards a topic such as immigration as they correlate with such features as
                    party affiliation or geographic location. This is readily achieved using such
                    simple techniques as XSLT transformations or XQUERY searches.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>The author demonstrates the potential for text analysis of corpora encoded in the
                    Parliamentary Metadata Language (PML) XML schema.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Large-scale digitisation projects in many countries over the last twenty years
                    have generated significant machine-readable textual corpora of the proceedings
                    of their parliaments or legislative assemblies. In the United Kingdom, for
                    instance, a number of projects have enabled seven hundred years of records to be
                    made available in digital form, including the full text of the official Hansard
                    record of debates from 1803 <ptr target="#ukparliament2012"/>. These corpora are
                    potentially highly significant resources for large-scale machine-based analysis,
                    although at present studies of this type are rendered more difficult by the
                    heterogeneity of approaches to markup and encoding taken by the projects that
                    created them.</p>
                <p>In recent years, a number of projects have attempted to address the issues raised
                    by this heterogeneity and formalise schemes for rationalising approaches to the
                    encoding of these texts and their associated metadata. In Portugal, for
                    instance, Dublin Core (DC) is used as the basis for a digital library of
                    parliamentary records <ptr target="#pinto2005"/> and in Chile the National
                    Library has produced an extended DC element set to act as the underlying
                    descriptive metadata for its digitisation programme <ptr
                        target="#fuentesmartínez2005"/>. A more ambitious approach has been
                    undertaken by the Akomo Ntoso project for African legislative, parliamentary and
                    judiciary documents <ptr target="#cervone2015"/> which has created a formal XML
                    schema and controlled vocabularies.</p>
                <p>More recently, the LIPARM (Linking the Parliamentary Record through Metadata)
                    project <ptr target="#gartner2012"/> attempted to define a more
                    sophisticated methodology for parliamentary metadata by devising an XML schema,
                    PML (Parliamentary Metadata Language) <ptr target="#gartner2013"/> that is
                    intended to provide a means of semantically linking core facets of legislative
                    proceedings into a single coherent framework. The schema was intended primarily
                    as a resource discovery tool, allowing a diverse range of previously
                    incompatible digitised resources to be conjoined using common semantic linkages
                    and so become interoperable at a search level. The schema was tested on a corpus
                    of UK Parliamentary materials and proved itself capable of allowing
                    sophisticated searching and browsing of parliamentary records in a prototype
                    interface to PML records constructed for the project <ptr target="#gartner2013"
                        loc="32"/>.</p>
                <p>These approaches are primarily aimed at resource discovery rather than the
                    analysis of the textual content of proceedings of the type that has become
                    established in fields such as corpus linguistics. Such studies have been
                    relatively rare in the past: until the last five years, most historical research
                    on parliamentary proceedings has tended to take the form of qualitative analyses
                    based on manual readings. There appears to be have been considerable suspicion
                    of corpus-driven analyses of political vocabulary in particular; some argue that
                    this stems from a prevalent post-structuralist emphasis in the historical
                    community on the micro reading of texts rather than the analysis of broad trends
                        <ptr target="#blaxill2014"/>. </p>
                <p>Despite these suspicions, more quantitative approaches have begun to emerge in
                    recent years, the most sophisticated of which have been those conducted in the
                    Netherlands using the Political Mashups schema, a TEI extension which is based
                    on the latter's elements sets for theatrical performance <ptr
                        target="#gielissen2009" loc="19"/>. This has been used, for instance, to
                    examine attitudes expressed in the country’s parliamentary proceedings over a
                    lengthy time period towards a well-known party of the far-right <ptr
                        target="#piersma2014"/>.</p>
                <p>Although not designed primarily as an analytical tool, the semantic linkages
                    encoded within a PML file, when used in conjunction with the texts whose
                    contents they synthesise, clearly offer the potential for moving beyond resource
                    discovery alone towards something more analytical. Instead of merely allowing
                    these texts to be found, it should allow them to become the raw material for
                    machine-based analyses, using the mechanisms associated with a discipline such
                    as corpus linguistics. The corpora on which this field of study relies integrate
                    texts with metadata, usually the syntactical information associated with each of
                    their constituent words. In a similar way, PML integrates data and metadata and
                    so should be able to facilitate analyses of the same type.</p>
                <p>This paper aims to demonstrate how PML can be used in this way; by analysing the
                    content of parliamentary proceedings and using its associated metadata to put
                    the results of these analyses into context, it becomes possible to generate
                    correlations revealing high-level patterns within these texts. In this study,
                    the tools used for this are relatively simple. Sentiment analysis tools are used
                    on a small corpus of materials encoded in a slightly extended version of the PML
                    schema and nothing more sophisticated than basic XSLT (eXtensible Stylesheet
                    Language Transformation) stylesheets are employed to create visualisations and
                    analyses based on the output of these tools.</p>
                <p>The aim is to demonstrate that, even with these simple techniques, sophisticated
                    and revealing results can readily be obtained from a PML corpus. Extensive
                    synchronic and diachronic studies across substantial datasets are achieveable
                    with these techniques which add a layer of context to the results of standard
                    tools for analysing textual corpora; this additional layer has the potential
                    significantly to enrich these studies, particularly by enabling correlations
                    between the purely linguistic and the contextual to be investigated with
                    relative ease.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliamentary Metadata Language (PML)</head>
                <p>The Parliamentary Metadata Language (PML) schema <ptr target="#liparmproject2012"
                    /> was originally devised as the key component of the LIPARM project mentioned
                    above. It was conceived as a rigidly structured framework, encoded in XML
                    syntax, for semantically linking core facets of records of legislative
                    proceedings. Seven such facets are incorporated into the schema, most of which
                    are defined very broadly and at a high level of abstraction: they include such
                    concepts as <title rend="italic">Unit</title> (covering everything from
                    political parties, chambers of the legislature, parliamentary constituencies and
                    even gender) and <title rend="italic">Proceedings Object</title> (covering
                    everything that occurs within the proceedings themselves, from procedures such
                    as prayers to speeches and other contributions by individual members). The
                    semantic breadth of most of these facets requires them to be narrowed in use by
                    employing controlled vocabularies of sub-facets — for instance, <title
                        rend="italic">Unit</title>s are refined by these vocabularies into type of
                    unit. A fuller description of the architecture of PML may be found in <ptr
                        target="#gartner2013"/>.</p>
                <p>PML is designed to act as integrative mechanism for parliamentary proceedings,
                    allowing their textual content to be conjoined with structured metadata: in
                    doing so, it allows diverse content of this kind to be linked into a coherent
                    and interoperable whole. It acts in this way as an <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gartner2011">intermediary schema</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gartner2011"/>
                    </cit>, a mediator between resources that would otherwise be difficult to treat
                    as an integrated resource. The primary mechanism to achieve this is an element
                    available to most facets within a PML document: this <gi>source</gi> element,
                    contains an attribute <att>sourceRef</att> which allows a link to an external
                    resource via such mechanisms as URI, Xlink or Xpointer. A speech in a
                    parliamentary debate might, for instance, be linked to its text in a digitised
                    version of <title rend="italic">Hansard</title> as follows:</p>
                <quote rend="block" source="#gartner2013">
                    <dhq:example>
                        <head>Sample PML contribution element (from <ptr target="#gartner2013" loc="29"/> (truncated))</head>
                        <eg>
&lt;contribution
    type="speech"
    typeURI="http://liparm.ac.uk/contributions/speech"
    contributorID="hh-1980015-person0002"&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Speech&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;sources&gt;
            &lt;source sourceRef="http://hansard.com/commons/1980/jan/15/e-comm-act-amendment#column_1436" sourceType="URL"&gt;
            &lt;label&gt;HC Deb 15 January 1980 vol 976 cc1436-41&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;/sources&gt;
&lt;/contribution&gt;
                    </eg>
                    </dhq:example>
                </quote>
                <p>This example also demonstrates the mechanism by which the broad element
                        <gi>contribution</gi> is narrowed semantically to a type of contribution
                    (here a speech) by the use of the <att>typeURI</att> attribute, the use of a
                        <gi>contributorID</gi> element to indicate the identity of the member giving
                    the speech and the use of <gi>label</gi> elements to provide human-readable
                    handles for each component.</p>
                <p> As originally conceived in the LIPARM project, PML was intended primarily as a
                    resource-discovery mechanism, allowing the diversely-encoded set of digitized UK
                    parliamentary proceedings to be integrated semantically at a fine level of
                    granularity. For this reason, the PML architecture did not itself incorporate
                    the textual content of the proceedings themselves within its element set:
                    instead, the <att>sourceRef</att> attribute established linkages to this
                    content. This method was employed in the experimental interface to PML data
                    constructed for the LIPARM project <ptr target="#liparmproject2012"/>: this
                    linked PML files to simple HTML renderings of the original text.</p>
                <p>The rich set of semantic linkages made possible by the LIPARM architecture
                    should, however, prove amenable to more sophisticated uses than resource
                    discovery alone. It can also be used to support and enrich analyses of the type
                    which are in common usage in the fields of corpus linguistics. In particular,
                    this network of linkages has the potential to put the results of linguistic
                    analyses in context by relating them to the rich set of facets encoded within
                    the PML architecture and, via semantic linkages, to external metadata. The next
                    sections of this article discuss how this can be done using such simple tools as
                    XSLT transformations or XQUERY searches.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Creating a PML corpus</head>
                <p>To demonstrate the capabilities of PML, a corpus of encoded files was created
                    that covers the period of the last parliament in the UK (2010-2015). This
                    corpus, part of a larger collection covering seventy years of UK parliamentary
                    proceedings, was generated by integrating data from a number of sources: most of
                    the texts themselves were derived from a set of files encoded in the Political
                    Mashups XML schema, which were themselves parsed from the HTML files generated
                    by the Hansard project mentioned above. Other data came from the controlled
                    vocabularies encoded in MADS (Metadata Authority Description Schema) which were
                    produced by the LIPARM project: these included data on Members of Parliament and
                    geographical constituencies. Three consecutive XSLT transformations collected
                    this data from these diverse sources (12,086 files in all) and integrated them
                    into a series of PML files, one covering each day of proceedings.</p>
                <p>A minor amendment was made to the PML schema to facilitate its use as the basis
                    for an analytical corpus. The <att>sourceRef</att> attribute discussed above was
                    supplemented by the addition of a new element under its parent <gi>source</gi>
                    to allow the text of the proceedings to be incorporated directly into the PML
                    file. This <gi>content</gi> element is used here to include the text of a
                    member’s contribution to a debate:
                    <dhq:example>
                        <head>Sample contribution record with text of contribution
                            included in <gi>content</gi> element
                        </head>
                        <eg>
&lt;contribution typeURI="http://liparm.ac.uk/id/contributions/speech"
        type="speech"
        contributorID="hh-1980015-person0002"
        regURI="http://uk.proc.d.2010-03-04.2.2.2"&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Kevin Brennan&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;sources&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;
            &lt;content&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;On 2 July 2009 the Government published the consumer White Paper, which details plans for more effective enforcement against those who deliberately set out to defraud consumers. I recently announced funding of &#163;4.3 million for the Office of Fair Trading and trading standards to tackle those who use the internet to con consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/content&gt;
        &lt;/source&gt;
    &lt;/sources&gt;
&lt;/contribution&gt;</eg>
                </dhq:example>
                </p>
                <p>Although the <gi>content</gi> element in this example contains simple <gi>p</gi>
                    (paragraph) elements only, XML data conforming to any namespace would be valid
                    here.</p>
                <p>The addition of this element allows XML-encoded text of any degree of complexity
                    to be integrated within the heavily structured metadata architecture of PML in
                    a manner analogous to the integrated text and metadata used in many e-text
                    projects. Integrating the text in this way is, of course, not strictly necessary
                    to perform the type of analysis discussed in this article: the linkages
                    established by the <att>sourceRef</att> attribute would allow the disparate
                    corpora of PML and text files readily to be treated as a single entity. The XSLT
                    and XQUERY mechanisms by which the corpora may be interrogated will work just as
                    effectively on such a distributed corpus.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Applying sentiment analysis to the PML corpus</head>
                <p>To test the feasibility of using PML as an analytical tool, simple sentiment
                    analysis was carried out on a portion of the corpus that covered a single topic,
                    attitudes to immigration. Like all sentiment analysis, this attempted to discern
                    the perspective or attitude of the speaker but was limited to a basic
                    categorization of their expressed views in terms of polarity, whether they were
                    positive, negative or neutral. It did not try to discern more complicated
                    sentiments such as emotional moods or states.</p>
                <p>This sub-corpus was generated by a simple XQUERY search to extract members'
                    contributions during this period in which the stems <code>immig* </code>or
                        <code>migr* </code>were present. This sub-corpus was then run through the
                        <title rend="italic">OpinionFinder</title> sentiment analysis software <ptr
                        target="#mpqaproject"/> to tag these contributions for positive, negative or
                    neutral sentiments within the same paragraph as the search terms.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">OpinionFinder</title> is a Java-based application devised by
                    the Universities of Pittsburgh, Cornell and Utah. It can rapidly process
                    multiple files to identify subjective linguistic elements which are then
                    automatically tagged using inline SGML elements <ptr target="#wilson2005"/>. A
                    paragraph element from a PML file tagged in this way might appear in this
                    (slightly simplified) form:</p>
                <dhq:example>
                    <head>sample OpinionFinder output (simplified)</head>
                    <eg>&lt;p&gt;Immigration has &lt;MPQAPOL autoclass="positive"&gt;enriched&lt;/MPQAPOL&gt; our culture and &lt;MPQAPOL autoclass="positive"&gt;enhanced&lt;/MPQAPOL&gt; our society. Britain can benefit from immigration, but not &lt;MPQAPOL autoclass="negative"&gt;uncontrolled&lt;/MPQAPOL&gt; immigration. The levels of net migration seen under the previous Government-an annual figure of almost a quarter of a million at its peak in 2004-were &lt;MPQAPOL autoclass="negative"&gt;unprecedented&lt;/MPQAPOL&gt; in recent times. &lt;/p&gt;
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example>
                <p>For the illustrative purposes of this article, these tags were used to generate a
                    basic measure of the degree of positive or negative sentiment per paragraph by
                    counting the relative numbers of positive, neutral and negative sentiments
                    marked. Clearly more sophisticated techniques are available for analysing output
                    of this type, but these simple measures are sufficient to illustrate the
                    capabilities of PML for contextualising these results.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Using the PML architecture to contextualise sentiment analysis data</head>
                <p>The primary function of using the network of semantic links embedded within a PML
                    file is to enable data extracted from the textual content encoded within its
                        <gi>content</gi> elements, or referenced by the <att>sourceRef</att>
                    attribute, to be contextualised. A number of ways in which this can be done will
                    illustrate something of its potential for enriching the output of linguistic
                    analyses.</p>
                <p>Interrogating the corpus of PML data can be done by simple XPATH expressions
                    which follow the chain of linkages between data and metadata: although, for the
                    purpose of the tests documented here, these were used on the modified PML files
                    which included the texts of proceedings, they would work equally well using
                    externally held texts referenced by PML’s <att>sourceRef</att> attribute. These
                    XPATH expressions may be used with XQUERY queries or within XSLT transformations
                    to produce the same results. For the purpose of this study, XSLT stylesheets
                    were written to generate the results shown although XQUERY can be just used as
                    effectively.</p>
                <p>One obvious line of enquiry is to examine the sentiments expressed by individual
                    MPs. This is readily done by using the <att>contributorID</att> attribute shown
                    in Example 2 which links a contribution to the person making it. A simple XQUERY
                    or XSLT transformation can be used to extract the contributions made by a member
                    and perform a statistical analysis of the sentiments recorded within them. Here,
                    for instance, the positivity or negativity of comments on immigration by each
                    member for each of the years 2010-2014 are calculated and colour-coded by an
                    XSLT transformation to HTML:<figure>
                        <head>Extracted sentiment data for MPs on topic of immigration
                            2010-2014</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>In this chart the colour black indicates the most negative attitudes, reddish
                    brown those which tend to be more neutral and orange the most positive. Where no
                    comments on immigration were made by a member, <code>N/A</code> is shown.</p>
                <p>Although this example shows only a very simple analysis, it does reveal some
                    interesting results. The then Home Secretary, Theresa May, tended initially to
                    express relatively neutral sentiments towards immigration but these grew
                    significantly more negative as the parliamentary term progressed. As Prime
                    Minister she has subsequently committed the country to leave the European single
                    market, the so-called <soCalled>hard Brexit</soCalled>, primarily to exert more
                    control on immigration. This simple analysis reveals that her negative views on
                    immigration formed over a number of years.</p>
                <p>Although this is a relatively broad analysis which conflates all contributions by
                    a given member in a given year, more detailed ones may be carried out at any
                    level of granularity down to individual sessions or parts of sessions; this is
                    because PML incorporates a temporal element, <gi>calendarObject</gi>, to which
                    any contribution can be linked.</p>
                <p>Another level of analysis may be carried out by the same simple statistical
                    technique and colour coding to visualise patterns of sentiment by political
                    party. This time use is made of an attribute, <att>categoryID </att> within
                    PML’s <gi>person</gi> element: this includes an attribute which notes a member’s
                    place within a category such as party affiliation. Again a simple HTML table can
                    be generated by an XSLT transformation or an XQUERY query, although here the
                    breakdown of data is by month rather than year:<figure>
                        <head>Extracted sentiment data by party (per month)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>This analysis, which uses the same colour coding as Figure 1, shows the possibly
                    surprising result that there is little difference between the parties in their
                    (predominantly negative) sentiments expressed towards immigration during the
                    first year of this Parliament. The left-of-centre Labour party appears as
                    negative as the right-wing Conservative party. This may reflect the beginnings
                    of an initiative by the then Labour leader to attempt to make his party appear
                    tougher on immigration, which some at the time felt was an issue that had lost
                    them votes in the General Election of 2010, and which later led to more
                    pronounced comments and policies on this subject <ptr target="#miliband2012"
                    />.</p>
                <p>A further level of analysis could extend this breakdown by party to incorporate
                    gender. This is readily done as the same categoryID mentioned above may be used
                    to delineate by gender. A simple modification of the XSLT stylesheet used to
                    generate Figure 2 produces the following breakdown by party and gender, again
                    using the same colour coding; this reveals little variation by this criterion
                    within each party:<figure>
                        <head>Extracted sentiment data by party and gender (per month)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>More sophisticated analyses may be achieved by utilising a further feature of
                    PML, its extensive use of URIs to reference almost every component: these may
                    readily be used to interface with externally-held data. One interesting approach
                    to examining patterns of sentiment expressed in the proceedings is to consider
                    their geo-spatial dimension. Each constituency recorded in a PML file, for
                    instance, may be labelled with a URI which in turn can be used to generate
                    geo-data to enable visualisations demonstrating the geographical patterning of
                    the sentiments recorded in parliamentary speeches.</p>
                <p>One approach to enabling this is to use files encoded in Keyhole Markup Language
                    (KML) <ptr target="#google2015"/> which have already been published to
                    cover UK parliamentary constituencies. These files, produced by MapIt UK <ptr
                        target="#mapit2015"/> cover all 650 UK constituencies and include detailed
                    boundary information for each of these. For the purpose of this demonstration,
                    the seventy-two files representing constituencies for Greater London were used.
                    To interface with the PML data, they had to be edited slightly to incorporate
                    the same URIs for constituencies as those found in the PML files.</p>
                <p>Each KML file is run through an XSLT transformation or XQUERY query which
                    retrieves contributions by the member for each constituency, calculates the
                    relative weights of the positive, negative and neutral values in the sentiments
                    expressed within these, assigns a score from 1 to 100 based on these sentiments
                    and generates a colour code based on this value. This value then replaces the
                    one already present in the KML element that designates the fill colour for the
                    polygon defining the boundaries of each constituency. This process may be used
                    across the whole corpus or be restricted by date, down to a fine level of
                    granularity if required.</p>
                <p>The resulting set of KML files may be used to generate colour-coded maps using
                    any compliant software. A sample output using Google Earth and covering Greater
                    London in the year 2010 is shown in Figure 4: the legend at the bottom of the
                    image indicates the range on the negative/positive spectrum within which the
                    MP's contributions fell during that year. <figure>
                        <head>geo-spatial representation of sentiments on immigration expressed by
                            London MPs in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>As may be expected in the most diverse and multi-cultural city in the United
                    Kingdom, most sentiments expressed towards immigration by London MPs tend
                    towards the positive, the only exception being those from the member for Mitcham
                    and Morden. Most London’s MPs did not comment on immigration during this period
                    and most of those who did come from the outer ring of constituencies, which are
                    generally more affluent and slightly more conservative than those of inner
                    London, but were nevertheless generally positive in their comments on this issue.
                    This is, of course, a visualisation of data from a single year, the year of the
                    General Election: it would be relatively simple to generate animated
                    visualisations representing any changing sentiments within this geographic area
                    over time.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Comparison with other approaches to parliamentary metadata</head>
                <p>PML's rich set of semantic linkages for parliamentary metadata offers a
                    potentially more powerful base for machine-readable analysis than the other
                    approaches detailed above. At this point, it is useful to compare how its
                    approach differs from these.</p>
                <p>Compared to the Portuguese metadata system discussed by <ptr target="#pinto2005"
                    />, PML offers much finer granularity and more sophisticated linking. Pinto et
                    al's approach, designed to support an audiovisual delivery system of
                    parliamentary proceedings, only offers granularity down to the page level and a
                    simple XHTML encoding of the textual data <ptr target="#pinto2005" loc="2"/>.
                    Its mapping of facets of the parliamentary record to DC is limited to a small
                    number (including legislature and session) and it includes none of the
                    contextual information, such as the information on members, gender and
                    geographical data, that PML can support. While functioning very efficiently in
                    its purpose to enable the audiovisual system it supports, it provides very
                    limited facilities for analysis of the type described here.</p>
                <p>The Akomo Ntoso scheme provides a richer metadata set than the Portuguese for the
                    purpose of marking-up parliamentary documents, as it includes not only debates
                    but also acts, bills, reports and a number of other document types. Its element
                    set is, however, highly document-centred and its potential for encoding wider
                    contextual linkages more limited than PML’s. Much of its element set is derived
                    from XHTML and so most of its linking mechanisms use this schema's
                        <att>href</att> attribute to point to externally-held ontologies. Much of
                    the contextualised analytic power of Akomo Ntoso will therefore depend on these
                    external sources and the semantic linkages that they enable: its internal
                    features remain limited for analyses of the type discussed here.</p>
                <p>The Political Mashup (PM) schema is designed more specifically for analysis but
                    contains limited facilities within its architecture for encoding
                    machine-readable contextual information. The schema is designed specifically for
                    examining the structure of debates as events, and so adapts element sets from
                    the TEI designed for describing theatrical performance: it relies heavily, for
                    instance, on a semantically-imprecise element <gi>stage-direction</gi> used to
                    describe most features of the proceedings except for speeches. As is the case
                    for Akomo Ntoso, the schema also uses simple identifiers to externally-held
                    metadata on which it relies for contextualisation: a speech, for instance, may
                    open as follows:
                <dhq:example>
                    <head>sample Political Mashups element</head>
                    <eg>
&lt;speech pm:speaker="Andrew Miller" pm:party="Lab" pm:role="mp" pm:party-ref="uk.p.Lab" pm:member-ref="uk.m.10435"pm:id="uk.proc.d.2011-11-23.1.3.6"&gt;
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example></p>
                <p>None of the referents for these attributes are contained within the PM file: the
                    only metadata components within its architecture are simple Dublin Core elements
                    providing document-level descriptive metadata. Nor does the schema allow the
                    detailed voting analyses provided by PML as it encodes votes as procedural
                    markup, the application of which is inconsistently applied over time.</p>
                <p>PML appears to offer a better alternative to these other XML approaches for
                    providing the contextual information by which the results of machine-generated
                    linguistic analyses may be enhanced. It offers more powerful and effective
                    mechanisms for contexualising the results of analyses within its
                    tightly-constrained but flexible structures.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Other potential uses of PML data</head>
                <p>The above discussion is intended to illustrate the potential of using the PML
                    architecture and its semantic linkages in order to contextualise the results of
                    analyses based on the textual content of proceedings. The discussion
                    deliberately concentrates on using simple tools, notably XSLT transformations or
                    XQUERY queries, to extract and visualise the data.</p>
                <p>Even with these simple tools interesting and revealing results can readily be
                    obtained. There is much scope for further analyses which could exploit the
                    potential of PML to provide new insights into the parliamentary record. Debates
                    currently taking place (at the time of writing) in the UK Parliament on
                        <soCalled>Brexit</soCalled>, the UK’s departure from the European Union, for
                    instance, may well yield interesting results when subjected to sentiment-based
                    analyses of this type. Similarly, in the current climate within the US, where
                    much debate appears to take place via Twitter, some potentially valuable
                    research could be undertaken on tracing sentiments within Congressional
                    proceedings and relating them to social media. Robust analyses of this type with
                    a quantitative evidence base could be most valuable and revealing in the current
                    political climate.</p>
                <p>Some other avenues for research are possible within the PML architecture,
                    although at present these are limited because of the quality of textual corpora
                    available. A potentially powerful area would be to correlate a linguistic
                    analysis of a member's contributions to debates with their voting record. PML
                    allows for the detailed recording of voting patterns using an number of
                    attributes to <gi>voteEvent</gi>;, its container element for information on
                    votes or divisions. Using these a complete pattern of an individual's voting
                    record can be derived which could then be incorporated into such an analysis.
                    Unfortunately at present the voting data within most corpora is often a simple,
                    unstructured transcription of the proceedings text itself: to generate an
                    accurate set of data would require manual editing for which sufficient resources
                    have not yet been available. A complete and accurate set of voting data encoded
                    in PML would represent a valuable resource for historians and social
                    scientists.</p>
                <p>The simple XSLT transformations used to visualise PML data could also be used as
                    the basis of interactive web-based services for presenting parliamentary data
                    for non-specialist users. They could, for instance, to used to provide
                    on-the-fly visualisations across the corpus, potentially enhancing web services
                    which are designed to enhance citizens’ access to legislative proceedings (such
                    as the service <title rend="italic">They Work For You </title>in the UK <ptr
                        target="#mysociety2015"/>). Projects such as these could be facilitated
                    perhaps by producing modularised XSLT stylesheets for diverse sets of queries or
                    analyses. The sharing of such stylesheets throughout the academic and
                    extra-academic communities could significantly augment the usability of
                    PML-encoded data and make its potential for sophisticated access to the
                    parliamentary record more widely realised.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>Being able to contextualise the results of fine-grained machine-generated
                    analyses of linguistic data offers the potential to enrich greatly their
                    findings. For the specific area of parliamentary proceedings, the approach
                    offered by Parliamentary Markup Language appears to offer great potential for
                    new avenues of research by allowing contextualisation of this type to be readily
                    achieved. When combined with resources external to the PML file itself, for
                    instance the MADS-encoded controlled vocabularies produced by the LIPARM
                    project, the scope for large-scale studies becomes readily achievable.</p>
                <p>The range of potential analyses that could be performed with PML is wide-ranging:
                    they could include extensive diachronic historical analyses or on-the-fly
                    visualisations of current proceedings. PML corpora can provide an substantial
                    evidence base for sophisticated machine-readable analyses which extend well
                    beyond the resource discovery functions for which the schema was initially
                    devised. The use of electronic text corpora for parliamentary studies remains
                    relatively nascent, but its potential for seeding future research is clear.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blaxill2014" label="Blaxill 2014">Blaxill, L. 2014. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digging into Linked Parliamentary Data</title>. Available
                    from: <ref target="http://dilipad.history.ac.uk/2014/09/"
                        >http://dilipad.history.ac.uk/2014/09/</ref> (accessed 6.23.14).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cervone2015" label="Cervone et al. 2015">Cervone, L. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Akoma Ntoso | Akoma Ntoso Site</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.akomantoso.org/">http://www.akomantoso.org/</ref>
                    (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fuentesmartínez2005" label="Fuentes Martínez 2005">Fuentes Martínez,
                    M. A. <title rend="quotes">Metadata at the Library of the National Congress of
                        Chile: a multidisciplinary experience</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DC-2005: Proceedings of the International Conference on
                        Dublin Core and Metadata Applications</title> (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gartner2011" label="Gartner 2011">Gartner, R. <title rend="quotes">Intermediary
                    schemas for complex XML applications: an example from research information management</title>,
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Information</title>, 12.3 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gartner2012" label="Gartner 2012">Gartner, R. <title rend="quotes">The LIPARM project: a new approach
                    to Parliamentary metadata</title>, <title rend="italic">Ariadne</title>, 70. Available from:
                    <ref target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue70/gartner">http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue70/gartner</ref> (2012).
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gartner2013" label="Gartner 2013"> Gartner, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Parliamentary Metadata Language: an XML approach to integrated metadata for
                        legislative proceedings</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Library
                        Metadata</title>, 13.1 (2013): 17–35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gielissen2009" label="Gielissen and Marx 2009">Gielissen, T. and Marx,
                    M. J. <title rend="quotes">Exemelification Of Parliamentary Debates</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 9th Dutch-Belgian Information
                        Retrieval Workshop (DIR 2009)</title> (2009): 19–25.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="google2015" label="Google Developers 2015">Google Developers. <title
                        rend="quotes">Keyhole Markup Language</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://developers.google.com/kml/"
                        >https://developers.google.com/kml/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liparmproject2012" label="LIPARM Project 2012">LIPARM Project. <title
                        rend="quotes">Controlled Vocabularies | Linking Parliamentary Records
                        through Metadata</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.liparm.ac.uk/?page_id=61"
                        >http://www.liparm.ac.uk/?page_id=61</ref> (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mapit2015" label="MapIt UK 2015">MapIt UK. <title rend="quotes"
                        >MapIt : map postcodes and geographical points to administrative
                        areas</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://mapit.mysociety.org/"
                        >http://mapit.mysociety.org/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="miliband2012" label="Miliband 2012"><title rend="quotes">Ed Miliband’s
                        immigration speech in full</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.politics.co.uk/comment-analysis/2012/06/22/ed-miliband-s-immigration-speech-in-full
                        (2012)"
                        >http://www.politics.co.uk/comment-analysis/2012/06/22/ed-miliband-s-immigration-speech-in-full</ref>
                    (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mpqaproject" label="MPQA Project n.d."><title rend="quotes"
                        >OpinionFinder | MPQA</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://mpqa.cs.pitt.edu/opinionfinder/"
                        >http://mpqa.cs.pitt.edu/opinionfinder/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mysociety2015" label="mySociety 2015"><title rend="quotes"
                        >TheyWorkForYou: Hansard and Official Reports for the UK Parliament,
                        Scottish Parliament, and Northern Ireland Assembly - done right</title>.
                    Available from: <ref target="http://www.theyworkforyou.com/"
                        >http://www.theyworkforyou.com/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piersma2014" label="Piersma et al. 2014">Piersma, H. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">War in Parliament: What a Digital Approach Can Add to the
                        Study of Parliamentary History</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title>, 8.1 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pinto2005" label="Pinto et al. 2005">Pinto, J. S. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Portuguese Parliamentary Records: a Multimedia Digital Library
                        Distributed Architecture, based on Web Services</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Conference on Next Generation Web Services
                        Practices</title> (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ukparliament2012" label="UK Parliament 2012"><title rend="quotes"
                        >HANSARD 1803–2005</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/"
                        >http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/</ref> (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilson2005" label="Wilson et al. 2005">Wilson, T. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">OpinionFinder: A system for subjectivity analysis</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of hlt/emnlp on interactive
                        demonstrations</title> (2005): 34–35.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
