<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="issue">Methods of quality, quality of methods. What does Roberto Busa
                    have to communicate to digital humanists in the 21st century? From hermeneutics
                    to performativity.</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Marinella <dhq:family>Testori</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>King's College London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>testorimarinella@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Marinella Testori is a Digital Humanist with specialism in linguistic
                            annotation and lexicography for Latin. Since 2010 she has been
                            collaborating as Linguistic Annotator of the Index Thomisticus Treebank
                            Project (<ref target="http://itreebank.marginalia.it/"
                                >http://itreebank.marginalia.it/</ref>), and since 2017 as
                            Lexicographer at the CIRCSE (Catholic University of Milan, Italy). She
                            received two MM.AA. in Humanities and Historical Sciences at the
                            Catholic University of Milan, a Biblical Diploma at the Pontifical
                            University of the Holy Cross in Rome, and a postgraduate degree in Text
                            Informatics and Digital Scholarly Edition at the University of
                            Arezzo-Siena (Italy). She is currently working on her Ph.D. dissertation
                            regarding corpus linguistics methods applied to the language of Thomas
                            Aquinas at the Department of Digital Humanities at King’s College
                            London.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000329</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2017-08-28">28 August 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>hermeneutic informatics</item>
                        <item>treebanks</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-03" who="DD">Validation Check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Despite being also known as the <q>Father of Digital Humanities</q> owing to his
                    pioneering contribution to the application of informatics to the whole ensemble
                    of texts by the medieval philosopher and theologian Thomas Aquinas (1225-1274),
                    the Jesuit Italian priest Roberto Busa (1913-2011) has still not been fully
                    appreciated with regard to his development of a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">hermeneutic informatics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1999" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. Indeed this may represent a key concept to clarify what makes a
                    difference between the common usage of computers in order to speed up
                    procedures, and high-quality practices enhancing the role of informatics in
                    shaping human interaction with machines. In other terms, Busa’s interpretation
                    of informatics may impact not only on the way in which digital resources and
                    tools are developed, but also on the epistemological reflection about Digital
                    Humanities. In this paper, by drawing from many of his texts, I will outline how
                    this innovative <q>hermeneutics</q> is explained by Busa in terms of language
                    dynamisms potentially leading to the development of what Johanna Drucker has
                    described as a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2012">humanistic-informed theory of the
                            making of technology</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2012" loc="87"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Studies the impact of Roberto Busa's interpretation of informatics on DH.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In his article titled <title rend="quotes">What is humanities computing and what is
                    not?</title>, John Unsworth suggests looking at humanities computing <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth">as a practice of representation</quote>
                    <ptr target="#unsworth"/>
                </cit>, which he has articulated according to six propositions, among which are
                those concerning <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth">humanities computing as a way of
                    reasoning</quote> and <quote rend="inline" source="#unsworth">humanities computing as
                    shaped by the need for human communication</quote>. The basis for these
                suggestions outlined in 2002 may be found in the article <title rend="quotes">What
                    is a Knowledge Representation?</title> by Randall Davis, Howard Shrobe and Peter
                Szolovits, which appeared around a decade before in <title rend="italic">Al
                    Magazine</title> and in the light of which Unsworth has developed his
                considerations: in this contribution, in fact, the authors have reasoned about the
                features of knowledge representation, which, among others, they have defined as
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#davis1993">a set of ontological commitments</quote>,
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#davis1993">a medium for efficient computation</quote> and <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#davis1993">a medium of human expression</quote>
                    <ptr target="#davis1993"/>
                </cit>. </p>
            <p>It is worth noticing that, with their discussion, Davis and colleagues have
                anticipated the current debates regarding what digital humanities is and, more
                specifically, the boundary between a generic, widespread use of computers to do
                things, and computer applications adding value to academic research in humanistic
                disciplines because of their capability of representing human knowledge more
                effectively. Interestingly, in the second half of the twentieth century Roberto Busa
                (1913-2011), the groundbreaking developer of the <title rend="italic">Index
                    Thomisticus</title><note> See the website <ref
                        target="http://www.corpusthomisticum.org/it/index.age"
                        >http://www.corpusthomisticum.org/it/index.age</ref>
                </note>, a linguistic corpus for Thomas Aquinas' texts, already proposed ideas with
                the potential to enlighten and steer the contemporary discussion in the field.
                Although Busa is known for having been one of the early pioneers to bring problems
                in language together with computing machinery, his contribution to the development
                of a <soCalled>hermeneutic informatics</soCalled><note> This
                    expression was used by Roberto Busa himself in his keynote speech, <title
                        rend="quotes">From Punched Cards to Treebanks: 60 Years of Computational
                        Linguistics, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Eighth International
                            Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories</title>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >4-5 December 2009, Milan</hi></title>
                    <ptr target="#busa2009"/>. The full text of the intervention is not available in
                    the Proceedings, but it can be acquired through the C.I.R.C.S.E., Centro
                    Interdisciplinare di Ricerche per la Computerizzazione dei Segni
                    dell’Espressione, at the Catholic University of Milan (Italy), <ref
                        target="http://centridiricerca.unicatt.it/circse_index.html?rdeLocaleAttr=en"
                        >http://centridiricerca.unicatt.it/circse_index.html?rdeLocaleAttr=en</ref>.
                </note> is not so appreciated and recognised. There is the risk of pigeonholing his
                work under constraining labels or confining it only to specific sectors (for
                example, computing techniques applied to ancient languages). It appears to me
                significant, instead, that, since he worked on the development of a linguistic
                corpus, Busa established in this way a vital connection between humanities computing
                and the reflection on language. </p>
            <p>In this article, I am going to outline the salient ideas put into practice by Busa by
                discussing some of his contributions as a common thread. It is not a coincidence
                that in 1998 Busa admonished that <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">Informatics is already an ocean</quote>
                    <ptr target="#busa1999"/>
                </cit>, so we need to be careful not to get lost. For this reason, I also propose
                many quotations from Busa's texts as a deliberate choice to let the reader know many
                worthy reflections provided by the scientist that are not so well-known so as to
                stimulate a debate. At the same time, I will be pointing out how my current
                experience of work on Busa’s legacy is leading me to move ahead with the development
                of new perspectives requiring further consideration. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Methods of quality: Roberto Busa and the computing in the humanities</head>
                <p>In his keynote speech <title rend="italic">From Punched Cards to Treebanks: 60
                        Years of Computational Linguistics</title> at the Eighth International
                    Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories (Milan, 2009), Busa sketched three
                    main typologies of informatics currently in use: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#busa1999">documentaristic</quote> informatics, comprising all the
                    informatic services allowing efficient <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999"
                        >information retrieval</quote>; <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999"
                        >editorial</quote> informatics, referring to the wide range of <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#busa1999">multimedia</quote> devices for reading books,
                    watching films, browsing the Internet; and <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999"
                        >hermeneutic informatics</quote>, considering the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">computerized text analysis, or
                            language hermeneutics, i.e. interpretation, […] of all our ways of
                            questioning the <hi rend="italic">whys</hi> of language</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1999" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. This latter was the informatic typology to which Busa devoted his
                    inexhaustible attention during all his life. The focus on language, according to
                    him, is strictly required by the nature of the relationships between man and
                    computers, which interact by means of specific programming codes. Moreover, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">the computer allows and exigently
                            demands, as its specific capacities, an exhaustive, detailed, deep,
                            quantitative knowledge, derived from huge amounts of natural
                            texts</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1999" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. As a consequence, it is arguable that computers and human beings,
                    technological devices and humanities are not competitors or antagonists, but
                    they are potential allies, insofar as they both are <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">human expressions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1999" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. Nevertheless, what do we really know about the language (our language)
                    on which human communication is based and by which it is conveyed? Are we really
                    aware of the intrinsic logic, the inner dynamism, and the psychological
                    implications which are put in motion every time we communicate? Roberto Busa
                    defined the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1999">language that [is] unknown</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1999" loc="6"/>
                    </cit><note>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">Language that unknown</quote> is a literal
                        translation from Italian. The meaning is that, generally, we do not have a
                        full, conscious awareness of the language in all its components.</note>, as
                    signifying that establishing an interaction with the computer/machine implies a
                    more profound level of language awareness than that to which we are accustomed.
                    This raising of consciousness is necessary to introduce consolidated
                    philological and linguistic methods to the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">new qualitative dimensions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1980"/>
                    </cit> made available by informatics. In the light of this, applying computer
                    methods to the humanities <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">can help us to be more humanistic
                            than before</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1980" loc="89"/>
                    </cit> because it leads us, first, to an inner journey through rational paths
                    triggered by language expression. This conviction mirrors the current debate
                    regarding the necessity of an epistemological reflection on the making of the
                    digital humanities: for example, Stephen Ramsay and Geoffrey Rockwell have
                    recently stated that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2012">the understanding of underlying
                            theoretical claims is the <foreign xml:lang="la">sine qua non</foreign>
                            of humanistic enquiry</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2012"/>
                    </cit>. Roberto Busa would have certainly confirmed this vision and reasserted
                    that these <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">underlying theoretical
                        claims</quote> primarily involve language dynamisms and linguistic issues.
                    More specifically, these underlying implications concern the meaning, the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#busa1980">semantics</quote> of words and sentences, which is
                    not attainable by a mere quantitative production of a certain amount of data.
                    Busa claimed that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">we do not speak in words but in
                            sentences. A sentence has a global meaning which is not the pure sum of
                            the values of its single components. The heart of this problem is
                            whether we are able to formalise the global meaning of sentences with
                            something less than the whole sentence itself; in other words, whether
                            we can succeed in identifying in each sentence something which can be
                            taken as characteristic of its global meaning</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1980" loc="88"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Quality of methods: Roberto Busa and the hermeneutics of informatics</head>
                <p>According to Busa’s experience, a high-quality methodology in computing for the
                    humanities should be focused on an accurate reflection on communication, because
                    man and computer interact with the help of sophisticated languages which differ
                    from common grammar and syntax and require constant development. Charles L.
                    Isbell et al. have confirmed the language-oriented nature of the interaction
                    established by human beings with the machine and suggested a reciprocal
                    shaping-power of the language on the outside reality (the computer) and,
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">vice versa</foreign>, of the external world (the
                    computer) to the language itself <ptr target="#isbell2009"/>.<note>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#isbell2009">The computing machine or artifact is
                            typically manipulated through some language that provides a combination
                            of symbolic representation of the features, objects, and states of
                            interest as well as a visualization of transformations and interactions
                            that can be directly compared and aligned with those in the world. The
                            centrality of the machine makes computing models inherently executable
                            or automatically manipulable and, in part, distinguishes computing from
                            mathematics. Therefore, the computationalist acts as an intermediary
                            between models, machines, and languages and prescribes objects, states,
                            and processes</quote>.</note>. A more conscious remark of this
                    communicative essence may contribute to illuminating a controversial point in
                    computing for the humanities: as Johanna Drucker has pointed out, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2012">the challenge is to shift
                            humanistic study from attention to the <emph>effects</emph> of
                            technology (from readings of social media, games, narrative, personae,
                            digital texts, images, environments), to a humanistic-informed theory of
                            the <emph>making</emph> of technology</quote>
                        <ptr target="#drucker2012"/>
                    </cit>. With respect to this question, Busa's message is that the development of
                    an <q>informed theory of the
                            <emph>making</emph> of technology</q> cannot elude a renewed,
                    unremitting consideration of language features and issues, which, in a kind of
                    virtuous circle, are positively related to the <emph>effects</emph> of
                    technology on our life. In this sense, the fruit sprouting from the <q>hermeneutic informatics</q> to
                    which Busa referred in his last keynote speech <title rend="italic">From Punched
                        Cards to Treebanks</title> mentioned previously is what I propose to
                    indicate as a <emph>language-based hermeneutics of informatics</emph>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Moving ahead of Busa: from hermeneutics to performativity</head>
                <p>This type of theoretical approach, along with the scepticism Busa expressed
                    regarding possibilities for a machine to fully develop it <ptr
                        target="#busa1990"/><note>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1990">Language is living, open and continually
                            evolving. It is in tune with everything that is beautiful and new.
                            Consequently, the epistemological methodologies of mathematical and
                            physical sciences, which measure quantifiable physical entities, are not
                            sufficient to dominate and grasp the logic of the signs we use to
                            communicate knowledge</quote>.</note>, clears an unexpected,
                    irreplaceable space for the human role: in fact, although <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa1980">the computer has even improved the
                            quality of methods in philological analysis, because its brute physical
                            rigidity demands full accuracy, full completeness, full
                            systematicity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa1980" loc="88"/>
                    </cit>, investigating the meaning of a discourse, as well as the mind processes
                    involved, requires that man instructs the machine to work at this level. </p>
                <p>Busa found in the so-called <foreign xml:lang="la">arbor Porphyrii</foreign> (the
                        <q>Porphyrian tree</q>, suggested by the ancient philosopher Porphyry to
                    explain the Aristotelian <title rend="italic">Categories</title><note> For a
                        first, general information regarding the <q>Porphyrian Tree</q> see <ref
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porphyrian_tree"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porphyrian_tree</ref> . See also what is
                        proposed about <q>Transcendentals and Predication</q> in <ptr
                            target="#goris2013"/>.</note>), an effective way of representing how the
                    human way of reasoning works. This is perfectly interpreted by the <q>trees</q>
                    which constitute a treebank, a linguistic corpus characterised by a specific
                    focus on the relationships between words and sentences. Busa was aware of the
                    difference among the <q>Porphyrian trees</q>, expressing <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">a graduated scalarity of
                            similarities and differences</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa2009"/>
                    </cit><note> The word <q>scalarity</q> appears in the original text, but the
                        most proper term here would be <q>scale</q>.</note> among genres and
                    species, and the <q>treebanks</q>, illustrating <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">relations of real and true
                            dependency</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa2009"/>
                    </cit> from a linguistic point of view; nevertheless, he asserts that
                    dependency-trees, provide <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">a syntax extracted inductively from
                            computerised texts and workable by the computer according to its
                            boundless capacities</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa2009"/>
                    </cit> that is a pedagogically powerful means for clarifying our interior logic
                    and way of thinking and, consequently, of communicating<note>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">Dependency trees are very useful and very
                            educative. They train us in an internal <q>speleology</q> on our own
                            logic, which in each of us is the spiritual centre of our own personal
                            consistency and dignity. <q>Knowing yourself</q> is a process that is
                            never really exhausted</quote>.</note>.</p>
                <p>Building a treebank for the syntactic and semantic annotation of the 11 million
                    words constituting the <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title>, as it is
                    currently being performed by the Research Group committed to Busa’s legacy with
                    the <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus Treebank</title> Project<note>The
                        website of the <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus Treebank</title>
                        Project is <ref target="http://itreebank.marginalia.it/"
                            >http://itreebank.marginalia.it/</ref>.</note>, is thus a method of
                    quality <foreign xml:lang="fr">par excellence</foreign>, not only for the
                    enhancement of linguistic properties in a text but also for casting light on
                    some mental paths connected with language. My current experience as annotator of
                    the IT-TB, in fact, has been increasingly persuading me about what I propose to
                    define as the <hi rend="italic">performative nature of linguistic
                        annotation.</hi> While working in Busa’s footsteps, I have been practically
                    experiencing first-hand the insights he advanced in <title rend="italic">From
                        Punched Cards to Treebanks: 60 Years of Computational Linguistics</title>
                    and, at the same time, I have been realizing how these insights can lead us
                    ahead of what Busa himself could not have completely foreseen. The most
                    intriguing fact of annotation of a treebank is that it enables the human
                    annotator to deal with a living, branching and constantly evolving tree. Making
                    a tree live, by establishing relations between words until it has reached its
                    accomplished form, is the amazing vocation I have discovered, since, in the very
                    act of annotating, I can make the text live. It really represents a kind of
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#beaken2011">making of language,</quote> to
                    recall the title of the book by Mike Beaken, <title rend="italic">The Making of
                        Language</title>
                    <ptr target="#beaken2011"/>, in which is proposed an alternative view of looking
                    at the origins of language, rooted not so much in biological features, rather
                    than in cultural and technological developments. Treebanks, in my vision,
                    represent one of these contemporary, worth exploring and pursuing developments,
                    made available by the advancements of linguistics not only for modern, but also
                    for no-longer spoken languages.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>Language-based models of interpreting and building a language, along with the
                    development of new technologies in the field of computing applied to the
                    humanities, may represent theoretically and practically valid methods of
                    contributing to the above-quoted challenges explained by Unsworth and Davis.
                    Despite being software-embedded, in fact, these models and related technologies
                    may be able to overcome the inherent limitations (e.g., strong
                    object-orientation) of mere computational approaches not capturing the
                    performative value of human acts of linguistic expression. In addition, owing to
                    our language-shaped minds, they may offer a remedy to that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">universal lament about the
                            fragmentation of knowledge</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa2009"/>
                    </cit> that Busa ascertained, because <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#busa2009">the human hunger for syntheses
                            derived from microanalysis, continues to surge up, and not only in
                            technologies, but also in linguistics, philosophy, psychology and
                            theology</quote>
                        <ptr target="#busa2009"/>
                    </cit> — in other words, in the context of general human knowledge.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beaken2011" label="Beaken 2011">Beaken, Mike. 2011. <title
                        rend="italic">The Making of Language</title>. Edinburgh: Dunedin
                    Academic.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1980" label="Busa 1980">Busa, Roberto. 1980. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Annals of Humanities Computing: The Index Thomisticus</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title> 14: 83–90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1990" label="Busa 1990">Busa, Roberto. 1990. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Informatics and New Philology</title>. <title rend="italic">Computers and
                        the Humanities</title> 24: 339-343.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1999" label="Busa 1999">Busa, Roberto. 1999. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Picture a Man…Busa Award Lecture, Debrecen, Hungary, 6 July 1998</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 14:
                    5-9.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa2009" label="Busa 2009">Busa, Roberto. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Punched Cards to Treebanks: 60 Years of Computational Linguistics</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Eighth International Workshop on
                        Treebanks and Linguistic Theories</title>, <hi rend="italic">4-5 December
                        2009, Milan</hi>. Edited by Marco Passarotti, Adam Przepiórkowski, Savina
                    Raynaud and Frank Van Eynde, <ref
                        target="http://convegni.unicatt.it/meetings_Proceedings_TLT8.pdf"
                        >http://convegni.unicatt.it/meetings_Proceedings_TLT8.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis1993" label="Davis, Shrobe, and Szolovits 1993">Davis, Randall,
                    Howard Shrobe, and Peter Szolovits. <title rend="quotes">What is a Knowledge
                        Representation?</title>. 1993. <title rend="italic">AI Magazine</title> 14:
                    17-33, <ref target="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/medg/ftp/psz/k-rep.html"
                        >http://groups.csail.mit.edu/medg/ftp/psz/k-rep.html</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2012" label="Drucker 2012">Drucker, Johanna. <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanistic Theory and Digital Scholarship</title>. 2012. In
                        <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by
                    Matthew K. Gold. Minneapolis/London: University of Minnesota Press, <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/34"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/34</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goris2013" label="Goris and Aertsen 2013">Goris, Wouter, and Aertsen,
                    Jan. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Medieval Theories of Transcendentals</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>, edited
                    by Edward N. Zalta, <ref
                        target="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/transcendentals-medieval/"
                        >http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/transcendentals-medieval/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="isbell2009" label="Isbell et al. 2009">Isbell, Charles L., Lynn Andrea
                    Stein, Robb Cutler, Jeffrey Forbes, Linda Fraser, John Impagliazzo, Viera
                    Proulx, Steve Russ, Richard Thomas, and Yan Xu. 2009. <title rend="quotes"
                        >(Re)Defining Computing Curricula by (Re)Defining Computing</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">SIGCSE Bulletin</title> 41, 4: 195–207, <ref
                        target="http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~isbell/papers/p195-isbell.pdf"
                        >http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~isbell/papers/p195-isbell.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2012" label="Ramsay and Rockwell 2012">Ramsay, Stephen, and
                    Geoffrey Rockwell. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Developing Things: Notes toward an
                        Epistemology of Building in the Digital Humanities</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew
                    K. Gold. Minneapolis/London: University of Minnesota Press, <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/part/3"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/part/3</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unsworth" label="Unsworth">Unsworth, John. <title rend="italic">What
                        is Humanities Computing and What is Not?</title>. <ref
                        target="http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg02/unsworth.html"
                        >http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg02/unsworth.html</ref>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
