<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">From Distracted to Distributed Attention:
                    Expanded Learning through Social Media, Augmented Reality, Remixing, and
                    Activist Geocaching</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Marina <dhq:family>Hassapopoulou</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>New York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mh193@nyu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Marina Hassapopoulou is Assistant Professor in the Department of Cinema
                            Studies and Co-Associate Director of the Moving Image Archiving and
                            Preservation program, at the New York University Tisch School of the
                            Arts. She has published articles and book chapters on topics including
                            interactive cinema, digital spectatorship, border cinemas, experimental
                            and Hollywood production, fan studies, representations of Hellenism in
                            U.S. media, hybrid pedagogy, expanded television, and digital
                            humanities. She teaches film, theory/philosophy, digital media, European
                            cinema, digital humanities, cultural studies and theory-practice
                            courses. Working on a range of media besides print, her projects include
                            cultural videos for the University of Oregon's folklore archives,
                            multimedia scholarship, as well as online open-access collaborative
                            initiatives including the student-focused Interactive Media Archive &lt;
                                <ref target="https://interactivemediaarchive.wordpress.com"
                                >https://interactivemediaarchive.wordpress.com</ref> &gt; and the
                            online directory focused on cross-pollinations between Cinema, Media
                            Studies and Digital Humanities &lt; <ref
                                target="https://transformationsconference.net"
                                >https://transformationsconference.net</ref> &gt;. She is currently
                            working on her book, <title rend="italic">Interactive Cinema: An
                                Alternative History of Moving Images</title>, which focuses on
                            participatory multimedia experiments in the history of cinema and
                            develops new frameworks for spectatorship in the digital age. She is
                            also working on a number of digital humanities and mixed media projects
                            on topics including local activism, youth cinemas, and experimental
                            pedagogy. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000386</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2018-09-12">12 September 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="dxnguyen48" when="2018-07-11">Article encoded.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>With the increasing proliferation of digital technologies into our daily
                    routines, long-standing debates have resurfaced on the potential of prosthetic
                    devices to extend our cognitive capacities and distribute intelligence across
                    human and non-human agents. This article will propose ways in which we, as
                    educators, can harness the distractions that new technologies can pose to
                    teaching and research towards productive models of distributed attention and
                    collective intelligence.</p>
                <p>By reflecting on the relationship between play and pedagogy through critical
                    theory, as well as on the benefits of hyper-connected and collaborative
                    learning, this article hopes to expand the branch of Digital Humanities that
                    Holly Willis terms as the <quote rend="inline" source="#willis2015">cinematic
                        humanities.</quote> Remixing, recontextualization, and the
                    non-linear/non-sequential reconfiguration of information can provide us with new
                    modes of distributed attention and critical making in the digital age.</p>
                <p>This article focuses on low and no-budget process-oriented collaborative projects
                    for Cinema, Media Studies, and Digital Humanities courses (adjustable to other
                    subject matters) that incorporate remixing, social and locative media, and
                    augmented reality into experimental modes of connected and collaborative
                    learning. The first assignment is a live film scoring remix, where students
                    collectively brainstormed on picking sound clips/samples to add new soundtracks
                    to early silent films. Remixing practices can offer new insights into cinema's
                    legacy and challenge ocularcentric notions of film spectatorship by, in this
                    case, reversing the conventional hierarchy of image-sound into sound-image and
                    reflecting on how our minds attempt to process the impulse of sensory
                    synchronization in cinema. The second sample assignment proposes new ways of
                    using easy-to-learn and accessible GIS (Geographic Information System) and AR
                    (Augmented Reality) tools to create projects related to civic engagement and
                    local/online activism.</p>
                <p>The drifts from pre-determined learning outcomes are meant to be active
                    disruptions to any prescribed limitations that delimit what digital humanities
                    should or should not be, and other issues that often undermine the potential
                    contributions to digital humanities that derive from the intellectual and
                    material labor that happens in the networked, expanded and distributed
                    classroom. The remix aesthetic, the <soCalled>unfinished</soCalled> and
                    makeshift nature of these projects is something that I find adds value to this
                    kind of process-oriented pedagogy because it remains in touch with the
                    pre-institutionalized experimental ethos that prompted the formation of the
                    digital humanities and other disciplinary cross-pollinations.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article proposes ways in which we, as educators, can harness the
                    distractions that new technologies can pose to teaching and research towards
                    productive models of distributed attention and collective intelligence.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction: Gamifying Learning</head>
                <p>With the increasing proliferation of digital technologies into our daily
                    routines, long-standing debates have resurfaced on the potential of prosthetic
                    devices to extend our cognitive capacities and distribute intelligence across
                    human and non-human agents. In this article, I will propose ways in which
                    digital humanities pedagogy can harness the distractions that new technologies
                    pose to teaching and research towards productive models of distributed attention
                    and collective intelligence. I will focus my analysis on some collaborative
                    class assignments for Cinema and Media Studies courses that incorporate social
                    media, remixing, GIS tools, and augmented reality into new modes of connected
                    and collaborative learning. By reflecting on the relationship between play and
                    pedagogy through critical theory, as well as on the benefits of hyper-connected
                    learning, this article hopes to expand the branch of digital humanities that
                    Holly Willis terms as the <quote source="#willis2015" rend="inline">cinematic
                        humanities</quote> — an interdisciplinary field that embraces critical media
                    practices that are <quote rend="inline" source="#willis2015">immersive,
                        embodied, gestural, and virtual,</quote> and produces modes of inquiry that
                    emerge from the creative experimentation with the affordances of new media
                    platforms <ptr target="#willis2015" loc="74"/>. </p>
                <p>In the context of higher education, distraction often goes hand in hand with the
                    idea of play, and both of these are sometimes dismissed as counterproductive in
                    terms of learning, partly because it is difficult to evaluate their outcomes
                    within traditional and standardized models for assessment <ptr
                        target="#stommel2013"/>. Pre-industrialization, work and play were not as
                    compartmentalized and segregated as in post-industrialized capitalist societies
                    (see for example <ptr target="#imre2009"/>). In recent years, however, there has
                    been a widespread trend towards the conflation of work and play in various
                    industries. While play used to be historically regarded as a subversive response
                    to capitalist ideology by activist artists and intellectuals, it is now being
                    standardized, institutionalized, and packaged for mass marketing. Gamification —
                    a neologism referring to the convergence of gaming mechanics (such as scoring,
                    competition, and rules) with non-gaming contexts particularly related to labour
                    production and product consumption – has become a massive corporate buzzword in
                    several industries, ranging from advertising to education. And yet, the
                    principles behind gamification should not simply be condemned as what Ian Bogost
                    calls <quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2011">marketing bullshit</quote> that
                    profits on the popularity of videogames and the billion-dollar gaming industry
                        <ptr target="#bogost2011"/>. In education, there have already been numerous
                    case studies that demonstrate the productive outcomes of gamification in terms
                    of student engagement and learning motivation (e.g. <ptr target="#kapp2012"/>;
                        <ptr target="#huang2013"/>; <ptr target="#petrucco2016"/>). Non-profit
                    educational technology association Educause even goes as far as arguing that
                    gamification <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#educause2011">is most effective as a
                            pedagogical tool where it forms part of a well-planned strategy to
                            encourage research, inspire creativity, teach basic principles, or hone
                            problem-solving skills</quote>
                        <ptr target="#educause2011"/>
                    </cit>. While I do not wish to overstate the educational value of game-oriented
                    learning, I consider playful experimentation and distracted acts of reading
                    integral components of pedagogy and critical thinking/acting in the digital age.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Productive Dissonance: Remix as Hybrid Historiography</head>
                <p>The most challenging courses to teach are those where students feel they cannot
                    contribute anything original to canonical discourses, which, in this case,
                    includes classes on film history and theory. In this section, I will focus on a
                    two-part collaborative experiment I performed with my Film Theory graduate
                    students, with the objective of exploring pop cultural connections to film
                    historiography and creating new types of collaborative amateur archives that
                    enable younger generations to productively engage with the past. The idea for
                    this project began through a problem-oriented approach centered around a
                    methodological and phenomenological issue: in the field of Film and Media
                    Studies, sound is usually analyzed in relation to moving images and, conversely,
                    mainstream film audiences are habitually conditioned to think of sound and image
                    as synchronous and interdependent. Accordingly, in film theory, sound is mostly
                    treated as an element that is dependent on the reception of the image rather
                    than critiqued in its own right. As film theorists Thomas Elsaesser and Malte
                    Hagener assert, <cit>
                        <quote source="#elsaesser2015" rend="inline">in classical cinema sound is
                            usually analyzed strictly in relation to (and in dependence on) the
                            image</quote>
                        <ptr target="#elsaesser2015" loc="154"/>
                    </cit>. The privileging of visual-oriented approaches to media is further
                    indicated by the fact that sound studies is still regarded as an under-developed
                    subfield within Film and Media Studies and, by extension, the digital humanities
                    (as noted, for instance, in <ptr target="#elsaesser2015"/>). </p>
                <p>The first project I will analyze is a live film scoring remix, where students
                    collectively brainstormed on picking sound clips (as audio samples) to add new
                    soundtracks to early films. Remixing practices can offer new insights into
                    cinema's legacy and challenge ocularcentric notions of film spectatorship by, in
                    this case, reversing the conventional hierarchy of image-sound into sound-image
                    and reflecting on how our bodies attempt to process the impulse of sensory
                    synchronization in cinema. For this collaborative film (re)scoring assignment, I
                    wanted to challenge students to reverse this sound-image relationship – that is,
                    to inverse the typical hierarchy of image-sound into that of sound-image, with
                    sound being at the forefront of their cinematic experience, in order to propose
                    different ways of analyzing acoustics in cinema and other media. The project had
                    an open-ended investigative component that was not fixed on a single predictable
                    outcome: it challenged the students to consider whether and/or how spectatorship
                    changes when images are understood in relation to sound. Further, the students
                    were asked to reflect on whether the class could collectively come up with our
                    own version of an <emph>acoustic visuality</emph>, where sound subverts the
                    ocular-centric primacy in audiovisual analysis. </p>
                <p>With these thoughts in mind, I challenged my students to spontaneously brainstorm
                    for a new score for a transitional sound film from 1930 titled <title
                        rend="italic">Tomatos Another Day</title> (or, <title rend="italic">Tomatoes
                        Another Day/ Tomato is Another Day/ It Never Happened</title>) by James
                    Sibley Watson Jr. and Alec Wilder<note> Some sources, such as the DVD anthology
                            <title rend="italic">Unseen Cinema: The Devil’s Plaything</title>
                        (Anthology Film Archives, 2005), credit Watson and Wilder as the directors
                        of the film, while other sources like Andrew Grossman (cited below) credit
                        Watson and Webber as the film's directors, and others like the Internet
                        Movie Database only credit Watson as the director. The film has also been
                        indexed under different variations of its title, which might partly explain
                        why it has escaped critical attention, in addition to Watson’s alleged
                        dislike (and subsequent neglect) of his film after it was unsuccessfully
                        screened.</note>, which centers on a love triangle between a married couple
                    and the cheating wife’s lover. I consider this rather historically neglected
                    film to be an appropriate case study for analyzing intertextuality and
                    referentiality in cinema, and for considering the historicity of parodic works
                    in a contemporary context. Before I describe the remixing activity, I would like
                    to explain why I picked this particular film, and how it helped forge a
                    connection between film history and modern-day spectatorship. It is important to
                    provide students with the necessary critical background prior to introducing
                    unconventional learning activities so that they are able to effectively connect
                    theory to practice. </p>
                <p>The original film itself is an excellent example of early sound experimentation
                    at a time when cinema was entering a transitional phase brought about by the
                    introduction of synchronized film sound. The title is a play on the phrase
                        <q>tomorrow is another day,</q> with the <title rend="italic"
                        >Tomatos</title> actors phonetically approximating this phrase in the way
                    silent cinema actors would visually mimic the sound of words. <title
                        rend="italic">Tomatos</title> conveys an ambivalent critique of the use of
                    sound in transitional sound films of the late 1920s and early 1930s. Innovations
                    in sound-on-sound film led to the first mainstream synchronized movies in 1923.
                    Similar (but far less documented) debates had occurred in the early years of
                    cinema about the use of intertitles in narrative films; once text was
                    incorporated into filmic narratives, cinema had arguably ceased to be a
                    universal medium because of the language-specific intertitles that added layers
                    of meaning to the then-silent moving images. The question at the time <title
                        rend="italic">Tomatos</title> was made was whether synchronized sound was
                    the next step to rendering spectators less active by attempting to shape – in
                    more sensory ways than before – their response to moving images. Film theorists
                    such as Andre Bazin, Sergei Eisenstein, and Hugo Münsterberg had offered diverse
                    insights into the impact of synchronized sound on cinema's recording capacities
                    and its status as an art medium, particularly in relation to notions of realism,
                    montage, and audience reception. Although some early film theorists cautiously
                    regarded sound as a potential asset to the cinematic experience, it is fair to
                    say that the introduction of synchronized sound was initially largely regarded
                    as a hinder to the expressive qualities of the medium. <title rend="italic"
                        >Tomatos</title> reflects on this widespread anxiety about sound cinema in a
                    humorous manner that was, unfortunately, too close to home for its contemporary
                    audiences to fully appreciate its nuances. </p>
                <p>Upon first viewing, <title rend="italic">Tomatos</title> seems to criticize
                    certain conventions of the talkies, particularly in its exaggerated and
                    unnecessary use of sound to state the obvious. It seems as though the
                    incorporation of sound into the love triangle of <title rend="italic"
                        >Tomatos</title>' narrative only serves to highlight what the moving images
                    make plainly obvious, and to unnecessarily describe the emotional state of the
                    characters, which is already exaggerated through their dramatic performances.
                    However, the directors manage to turn what initially seems to be an overt
                    critique of cinematic cliches (going beyond the talkies and also critiquing
                    narrative and performative conventions) into avant-garde experimentation and,
                    ultimately, a meditation on the productive uses of sound in cinema. Acoustic and
                    temporal experimentation is particularly manifest in moments in the film that
                    highlight the disjunctions between what is shown (and how) and what is heard,
                    such as an extreme close up on a match that throws off the rhythm and temporal
                    linearity of continuity editing. Disjunctive temporality, reflected in
                    conspicuous editing and visible/shock cuts, is especially noticeable when the
                    husband shoots his gun in the direction of his cheating wife and laments on what
                    he has done, while a few seconds later his wife appears on the screen unharmed,
                    as if the shooting had never occurred. The temporal disjunctions in the
                    narrative necessitate an active viewer and listener, thus suggesting new modes
                    of participatory spectatorship. </p>
                <p>The film’s rebellion against the conventions of sound and continuity editing
                    resonates even more strongly, as Andrew Grossman argues, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#grossman2014">in a media age intolerant of
                            aesthetic ‘dissonance’ and intent on madly synchronizing nearly every
                            aspect of thought, culture, and behavior</quote>
                        <ptr target="#grossman2014"/>
                    </cit>. The incongruity of sound, image and temporal sequencing in <title
                        rend="italic">Tomatos</title> suggests productively dissonant uses of sound,
                    for instance with the objective of subverting mainstream ideologies and
                    transcending industry confines. <title rend="italic">Tomatos</title>' dissonance
                    lends itself well to remixing and audio sampling, which I chose as the main
                    critical practices through which students would interact with the film in the
                    class activity. By treating <title rend="italic">Tomatos</title> as a remixable
                    database, students spontaneously proposed several songs to re-score the film in
                    class, and I assembled them into a makeshift YouTube playlist that would serve
                    as the film’s new score. We re-played the film on mute, and layered the new
                    audible soundtrack alongside the muted version of the film, with students giving
                    me cues whenever they wanted me to switch to the next track. The audio samples
                    chosen by the students ranged from classical to Korean pop (K-pop) music, and
                    reflected the diverse musical tastes of the multicultural student cohort. This
                    participatory mode of spectatorship has resulted in some interesting moments of
                    re-synchronization between the sound clips and the moving images, and encouraged
                    students to think of other inter-relations between sound and image that surpass
                    ocularcentric paradigms.<note> You can watch the remixed version on Critical
                        Commons: <ref
                            target="http://www.criticalcommons.org/Members/marinahass/clips/tomatos-another-day-live-scoring-sound-remix-final/"
                            >http://www.criticalcommons.org/Members/marinahass/clips/tomatos-another-day-live-scoring-sound-remix-final/</ref>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Since this collaborative activity was enthusiastically received by the class, we
                    tried a second, more elaborate and pre-meditated version using a different film,
                    an early silent film called <title rend="italic">Dream of a Rarebit
                        Fiend</title> (Wallace McCutcheon and Edwin S. Porter, 1906). This time,
                    students had more time to collectively brainstorm on picking the sound clips for
                    the new soundtrack in an online forum. The online forum also helped me quantify
                    participation (since each student was using their name under their contribution)
                    and dissect in more detail how students’ creativity works individually and
                    collectively. I then assembled their choices into a flowchart visualization
                        (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). Using a visualization for audio
                    samples is far more challenging to do when working with sound, so I decided to
                    use the film’s timecode and a screenshot from the beginning of each segment to
                    visually and temporally cue the corresponding audio transitions; this can be
                    easily done with a free online timeline flowchart program such as SmartDraw
                    Cloud. The second version of this sound remix ultimately escalated into a live
                    DJ performance in class, where the student DJ had downloaded mp3s of all the
                    chosen songs using KeepVid [set to mp3 download for sound-only audio files] and
                    brought his mixing console to class (<ref target="#figure02">Figure
                        2</ref>).<note> For part 2 of this live scoring experiment, see video: <ref
                            target="http://www.criticalcommons.org/Members/marinahass/clips/dream-of-a-rarebit-fiend-live-film-scoring-remix/view"
                            >http://www.criticalcommons.org/Members/marinahass/clips/dream-of-a-rarebit-fiend-live-film-scoring-remix/view</ref></note>
                    While the more pre-meditated version of this assignment helped me keep better
                    track of participation and encouraged some quiet students to contribute more
                    online, the first version was also useful in terms of providing a more
                    spontaneous example of collective intelligence in the classroom. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>Flowchart visualization of audio sampling</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>Live DJ performance in class</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>While remixing practices usually result in context collapse, I wanted students to
                    alternatively explore remixing as an active act of recontextualization, and as a
                    process of building new connections between the old and the new. In the case of
                    silent film history, Paolo Cherchi Usai argues that the producers and
                    contemporary audiences of those films, and today’s viewers, are separated by <cit>
                        <quote source="#usai2010" rend="inline">too many material and historical
                            variables, and our patterns of perception of moving images have
                            remarkably changed in the meantime</quote>
                        <ptr target="#usai2010" loc="166"/>
                    </cit>. New engagements with older media can therefore revive student interest
                    in <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hutcheon1985">that rich and intimidating
                            legacy of the past</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hutcheon1985" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. Remixing and sampling as active modes of critical engagement with media
                    require familiarity with the contexts and contents that are being remixed in the
                    first place. Watching the remixed version inevitably evokes comparisons between
                    the original film and the altered version, and establishes more intimate
                    connections to films that are of the distant past for younger generations of
                    viewers. In retrospect, it became even more apparent that the different sound
                    clips the students picked were not arbitrary: they demonstrated familiarity with
                    the filmic narrative (e.g. the love triangle in the film), and awareness of each
                    film’s historical and technological contexts, as well as a sophisticated
                    understanding of each film’s fluctuating dynamic between visual aesthetics and
                    acoustics. </p>
                <p>In re-watching the recordings of the remixes, students felt a special connection
                    to the film and said that by watching their remixed version they simultaneously
                    and comparatively thought of the original version as well as the personalized
                    experience of watching the film. Blair Davis has also observed this process of
                    thinking of the past and present simultaneously – or, in new media terms,
                    hypertextually – when he screened silent films with anachronistic soundtracks
                    such as techno music <ptr target="#davis2008" loc="92"/>. Anachronisms become
                    contemplative and self-reflexive for students, and compel them to carefully
                    consider other compositional elements in these films, as well as become more
                    aware of the films’ variable materialities, their diverse
                    exhibition/distribution contexts, and media ecology at large. As Katherine Groo
                    argues, deviations from the original work can serve as an act of <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#groo2012">metahistorical thinking</quote> that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#groo2012">productively counters the
                            [perceived] stability of film historiography with the possibility of
                            manifold and imaginative alternatives, each of which produces new forms
                            of historical knowledge</quote>
                        <ptr target="#groo2012"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>In addition, the resulting remixes indicate the students’ shared ability to think
                    of narrative as recombinatory elements in a remixable database, a process that
                    is consistent with the non-linear and/or modular logic of the various media they
                    interact with on a daily basis, and something that opens up new multimodal
                    possibilities for audiovisual studies in the digital age. Several media
                    theorists, including Douglas Rushkoff, have argued that modern popular culture
                    and/or new media stimulate a new cognitive and sensory <quote
                        source="#rushkoff2006" rend="inline">evolutionary leap</quote> in their
                    younger consumers, and many behavioral psychologists have claimed that modern
                    audiences have shorter attention spans <ptr target="#rushkoff2006" loc="36"/>.
                    While in education shorter attention spans are typically regarded as
                    counterproductive, Rushkoff and Davis posit that new cognitive skills have
                    emerged from this, such as the ability to process information more rapidly as a
                    result of a less linearly-constrained and more interactive thought process <ptr
                        target="#rushkoff2006" loc="38–9"/>
                    <ptr target="#davis2008" loc="91"/>. Moreover, moving beyond ocular-centric
                    paradigms of media reception challenges our bodies to, literally, make
                        <emph>sense</emph> of mediated information using other modes of perception
                    besides vision or, at least, alongside the culturally dominant visual paradigms
                    we are conditioned to unquestionably internalize. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Augmented Classroom: Geocaching, Urban Drifts, and Activist
                    Pursuits</head>
                <p>Multimodal ways of processing information is also at the core of this next
                    digital humanities project I will analyze. GIS (Geographic Information System),
                    GPS (Global Positioning System), and AR (Augmented Reality) technologies have
                    helped forge new connections between locality, spatial navigation, and remote
                    access. Consequently, some neologisms have emerged to conceptualize our
                    relationship to a technologically-assisted sense of place, such as <emph>net
                        locality</emph>, defined by <ptr target="#gordon2011"/> as ubiquitous
                    networked information that surrounds our everyday life (at least for those
                    living in the so-called Global North), and <emph>hyper-locality</emph>, a term
                    that alludes to the relationship between specific localities and/or
                    temporalities, and the ways in which they are socially mediated and remotely
                    experienced individually and collectively <ptr target="#hu2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#hochman2014"/>. Hochman, Manovich and Yazdani consider the
                    applicability of Umberto Eco’s 1980s writings on the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#hochman2014">hyper-real world</quote> in discussions of social
                    media, where simulations and audiovisual mediations of an event acquire greater
                    significance than the actual site where the event took place <ptr
                        target="#hochman2014"/>. These notions of socially mediated, hyper-local and
                    networked places provide a useful foundation for thinking about our social and
                    phenomenological relationships to not only geography, but also to cartographic
                    and navigational tools. </p>
                <p>Since GIS technology and other cartographic tools are widely used in digital
                    humanities research, I wanted to create a group project for my graduate course
                    on Interactive Cinema and New Media that would inspire students to think beyond
                    the computational and impersonal aspects of these tools. Through experimental
                    critical practice, I wanted students to consider the human aspects of digital
                    interfaces that are typically regarded as universal and standardized in related
                    theoretical discourses. I also wanted to challenge them to repurpose those
                    geolocative tools towards playful critique and activist objectives. The
                    following assignment proposes new ways of using augmented reality (AR) apps to
                    expand collaborative and experiential learning beyond the classroom through a
                    type of educational geocaching. Geocaching refers to the process of hiding and
                    finding objects with the help of geolocative devices such as GPS technology. AR
                    enables the combination of physical and digital information through the use of
                    different electronic devices. With the use of a mobile AR app, for instance,
                    users can use their cell phone to superimpose digital images and other data onto
                    real locations. For this collective geocaching project, the class were asked to
                        <soCalled>hide</soCalled> AR messages in specific New York City landmarks
                    and/or cultural events that relate to themes covered in the course (e.g.
                    expanded cinema, street art, feminist media-making, gentrification,
                    gamification, urban architecture, activism, and historiography) and then share
                    clues online (hinting at the location of their AR) before embarking on a quest
                    to uncover each other’s virtual hidden messages in real locations. In order to
                    receive participation credit, each student had to contribute at least 1 AR to
                    the project, accompanied by a brief rationale of their choice of location and
                    landmark. The app we chose through trial-and-error was walla.me (after trying
                    out other AR apps like Aurasma and Blippar), which is a free and easy-to-use
                    locative AR app that has the added feature of enabling its users to connect and
                    monitor each other’s walla.mes on a digital map, and also alerts users when
                    there are hidden ARs in nearby locations (<ref target="#figure03">Figure
                    3</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>Creating connected cartographies: locative walla.me map with thumbnails of
                        some the students’ walla.mes</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The AR class project provided students the opportunity to foster new conceptual
                    connections to place, and to transform the physical into a virtual-material
                    space with emotional and historical resonance. Student Karen Sadler was inspired
                    by the idea of AR as a disruptive practice that subverts spatiotemporal
                    boundaries. The site of her AR was a locked bookcase that showcases pioneering
                    books written by Cinema Studies professors in NYU’s Cinema Studies department.
                    Karen hinted at the location of her AR to her classmates by dubbing it as a
                    container of <soCalled>dangerous books,</soCalled> since the books showcased
                    deal with subversive forms of cultural critique. Karen created her own virtual
                    graffiti that included the access date and the abbreviated address of the
                    bookcase’s physical location. [<ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>]. The use
                    of graffiti-like AR text transformed the notion of automated geo-tagging into
                    something playful and subversive. AR provided a phenomenological and subjective
                    dimension to otherwise impersonal cartographic modes of urban navigation. The
                    act of virtual defacement through AR was meant to metaphorically
                        <soCalled>unlock</soCalled> the books from their fixed and protected
                    physical location, and to emphasize the transcendental value of the
                    revolutionary ideas expressed in these books. Instead of using AR to distract
                    from the significance of the physical location, Karen used it to amplify and
                    virtually disseminate the value of this locale that ultimately transcends its
                    physicality. Using AR at school gave Karen the chance to reflect on the ethical
                    implications of her virtual intervention, and to regard the concrete
                    consequences of using AR to virtually alter private, publically displayed
                    intellectual and material property.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Karen’s DIY graffiti tag juxtaposed a screenshot of its location on the
                        walla.me map</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Student Shirley Ogolla chose to explore the potential of AR as a tool for
                    political activism, after our class discussions on digital democracy and
                    cyber-ethics. The desire to utilize technology for political activism became
                    even more pressing for many students in the wake of the 2016 U.S. presidential
                    election, and several members of my class found it cathartic and liberating to
                    repurpose the technology at their disposal for sociopolitical reflection.
                    Shirley used as her AR site a politically themed photography exhibition in NYU’s
                    Tisch School of the Arts to provide her own virtual critique of the two main
                    presidential candidates. Shirley’s most effective walla.mes centered on the
                    theme of walls and boundaries. For instance, she focused one of her walla.mes on
                    a photo collage of a Donald Trump poster on top of a picket fence (visibly
                    alluding to the proposed building of the U.S.-Mexico wall), and added the
                    caption: <q>I don’t even know where to begin…</q> (<ref target="#figure05"
                        >Figure 5</ref>). Shirley’s own AR annotations to the photographed images
                    ironically convey her inability to adequately verbalize her post-election shock.
                    By using additional wall and fence-related objects and locations on campus,
                    Shirley’s AR interventions on physical boundaries suggest the irreversible
                    associations our culture now attaches to such images as symbols of oppression
                    and segregation.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>One of Shirley’s political walla.mes</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Inspired by the empowering potential of AR as a tool of social critique, Shirley
                    went on to use AR in her final, multimedia project of tracing gentrification in
                    her Williamsburg neighborhood in Brooklyn (<ref target="#figure06">Figure
                        6</ref>). Shirley’s final project focuses on virtually preserving
                    pre-gentrification memories of Williamsburg by layering digitized archival and
                    resident-submitted photos onto the newer architectural façades of the area. The
                    subversive use of AR for social critique and historical preservation is becoming
                    more commonplace as an artistic counter-cultural practice, as evidenced, for
                    instance, in projects such as <title rend="italic">Mi Querido Barrio</title> (My
                    Beloved Community, Caribbean Cultural Center African Diaspora Institute, NYC,
                    2016), an augmented reality tour of East Harlem that aims to make visible
                    gentrification’s unseen implications of cultural erasure. Thinking of emerging
                    technologies as tools for cultural critique and activism – rather than as
                    obstructions to meaningful interactions – gives students the chance to produce
                    meaningful interventions that connect real locations to memory, history,
                    culture, and collective identity.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>Screenshot from Shirley’s AR component to her project, which can be
                        accessed here: <ref target="https://methegentrifier.wordpress.com"
                            >https://methegentrifier.wordpress.com</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Another student, Elyse Singer, picked the Brown Building on the NYU campus as the
                    physical location of her AR. The Brown Building is the site of the Triangle
                    Shirtwaist factory, where the worst industrial disaster in New York City
                    occurred in 1911. Elyse used the keyword <q>palimpsest</q> and three emojis to
                    hint at the location of her AR online: a triangle, a shirt, and a factory (<ref
                        target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref>). She utilized AR to pay tribute to some
                    of the victims of the factory fire by superimposing some of the immigrant
                    workers’ photographs onto the physical location of the memorial plaques (<ref
                        target="#figure08">Figures 8 &amp; 9</ref>). When this location is visited
                    with a walla.me enabled smartphone, the impersonal memorial plaques come to life
                    through the virtually superimposed photographs of some of the victims that
                    spring up like ghosts from the distant past. AR here possesses a
                    historiographical and commemorative function that serves to experientially
                    connect visitors to the legacy of that specific location. Furthermore, Elyse
                    wanted to particularly highlight and memorialize the labor performed by the
                    young immigrant women (mostly Jewish and Italian) who died in the fire – an act
                    that gained even more significance in the context of the 2016 U.S. presidential
                    election and the impending threats to the rights of women and immigrants. The
                    virtual superimposition of images and text onto real places evoked a palimpsest
                    aesthetic. As Elyse observed, the palimpsest – an effaced piece of writing or
                    manuscript on which later writing has been superimposed, with traces of the
                    older form still visible – served as an apt metaphor for AR (<ref
                        target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>Elyse’s AR geocaching clue</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head>The Brown Building description and memorial plaques, with archival photos
                        of the victims superimposed in AR</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure09">
                    <head>The Brown Building description and memorial plaques, with archival photos
                        of the victims superimposed in AR</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <head>The palimpsest in full effect: tilting the phone upwards towards the top
                        of the Brown Building brings up a new pop-up of more photographs of the
                        victims</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The palimpsest, <quote rend="inline" source="#old">something reused or altered
                        but still bearing visible traces of its earlier form,</quote> provided a
                    lens through which to examine diverse interactive works throughout the semester
                    that collapse distinctions between past and present to propose new modes of
                    participatory historiography <ptr target="#old"/>. The evocation of the
                    palimpsest metaphor and its layered aesthetic in the students’ AR creations was
                    thus a productive extension to, and practical application of, some of the
                    concepts studied in the course. Further, the composite aesthetic resulting from
                    the palimpsest-like intermingling of visually inassimilable physical objects and
                    virtual interventions provides a suitable metaphor for the experience of
                    simultaneously navigating virtual and real locations. Larissa Hjorth and Sun Sun
                    Lim observe that the different modes of mobility and intimacy afforded by
                    digital media have enabled <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hjorth2012">multiple cartographies of space in
                            which the geographic and physical space is overlaid with an electronic
                            position and relational presence, which is emotional and social</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hjorth2012" loc="478"/>
                    </cit>. This overlaying is not only mediated virtually, but also mapped out
                    cognitively: individuals navigate electronic-social spaces while cognitively and
                    experientially relating them to the experience of being present in their
                    material-geographic equivalents, and vice versa. Contrary to the argument that
                        <quote source="#hochman2014" rend="inline">hyper-local social media data is
                        actually a manifestation of [the] temporalization and de-territorialization
                        [of visual experience],</quote> this class project actually de-temporalized
                    and re-territorialized our experience of virtually augmented real space by
                    maintaining connections to site-specificity <ptr target="#hochman2014"/>. Such
                    participatory uses of AR and other locative media challenge the notion that
                    digital technologies disconnect and alienate their subjects from the physical
                    experience of space.</p>
                <p>The ability to see each other’s contributions on a single map is a feature that,
                    up to this point, very few free AR apps offer, and I found this feature useful
                    in not only connecting students to the history and legacy of their urban
                    environment, but also to each other’s subjective connections to the
                        <soCalled>same</soCalled> physical locations. Eric Gordon and Adriana de
                    Souza e Silva argue that, historically, the practice of geocaching has been <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gordon2014">effective in connecting people to
                            locations, [but] it has been less effective in connecting people to each
                            other</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gordon2011" loc="66"/>
                    </cit>. In light of this, the AR group project aimed to assist students in not
                    only forging a one-on-one connection to the urban landscape through AR, but to
                    also gain a multimodal understanding of social space as experientially
                    interconnected. Even though the sense of net locality is now more
                    technologically disseminated, it is important to remember that it is primarily
                    socially and subjectively, rather than technologically, determined. The
                    multilayered navigation of space puts Guy Debord’s idea of psychogeography into
                    new contexts of techno-cultural mobility. Debord uses the term psychogeography
                    to allude to the emotional and psychological effects of geographical locations
                    on individual behavior <ptr target="#debord1989" loc="139"/>. AR can potentially
                    create new modes of psychogeography by allowing individuals to prescribe their
                    own unconventional ways of navigating their environment that diverge from the
                    ordinary ways we are socially and architecturally conditioned to experience
                    modern space.</p>
                <p>The use of AR provided a playful way of <soCalled>testing</soCalled> and
                    extending students’ applied knowledge of the course material, and its use was
                    contextualized through our cinematic exploration of psychogeography, urban
                    drifts (dérives), misappropriations/urban hijacks (détournements), and locative
                    media. The multiple distractions of the urban landscape, something that my
                    students had become accustomed to, became de-routinized and re-examined in a new
                    light. I would also add here that the urban milieu might have been more
                    instrumental than technology in training students on how to navigate, multitask
                    and re-focus their attention, since some of the students did not consider
                    themselves as <soCalled>digital natives</soCalled> (either due to their age or
                    their minimal interactions with technology). This offers an expanded perception
                    of distracted reading, beyond it being only digitally and/or
                    generationally-conditioned, and might provide some encouraging
                    cross-generational counterpoints to the so-called <soCalled>digital
                        divide.</soCalled></p>
                <p>Furthermore, AR gave students the opportunity of exploring the connections
                    between new and experimental media practices, and their relationship to the
                    urban landscape and long-standing Expanded Cinema and avant-garde traditions in
                    NYC. As with any new tool introduced in the classroom, I find it crucial to
                    provide students with examples that illustrate its potential uses. Therefore,
                    students became familiar with some creative approaches to cinematic uses of AR
                    and GPS technology through the work of groundbreaking artists such as activist
                    Amir Baradaran, Heidi J. Boisvert, and the Blast Theory collective. These
                    artists utilize geo-locative tools to explore, as Baradaran’s FutARist manifesto
                    states, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#baradaran">the experiential, conceptual and
                            legal shifts suggested by the advent of AR within the modalities of
                            contemporary art, its practice and reception</quote>
                        <ptr target="#baradaran"/>
                    </cit>. With the intention of exploring the subversive subjectivities that
                    emerge when AR is utilized to virtually alter and deface public space, students
                    were challenged to interrogate first-hand notions of ownership, surveillance,
                    social agency, and urban architecture through this new form of virtual graffiti.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Locative Media as Participatory Archives of Civic Engagement</head>
                <p>The concepts of psychogeography and its provocative premise has helped me
                    structure assignments for other courses, including a group project for a
                    graduate seminar on Digital Humanities and Cinema Studies. Even though
                    psychogeography did not play a significant or long-lasting role in the history
                    of the Lettrist International and the Situationists, its <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#coverley2010">pleasing vagueness</quote> has stimulated diverse and
                    politicized adaptations of unconventional and imagined cartographical
                    explorations of space <ptr target="#coverley2010" loc="89"/>. Debord’s
                    definition of psychogeography has been criticized for its apolitical and
                    frivolous nature, yet many of its subsequent reincarnations embody <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#coverley2010">the spirit of political
                            radicalism, allied to a playful sense of subversion and governed by an
                            inquiry into the methods by which we can transform our relationship to
                            the urban environment</quote>
                        <ptr target="#coverley2010" loc="14"/>
                    </cit>. This transformation of play into subversive and transformative practice
                    is in line with Adeline Koh’s argument that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#koh2014">play and games have tremendous
                            rhetorical power that can be harnessed for a plethora of unexplored
                            social, political and pedagogical purposes</quote>
                        <ptr target="#koh2014"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>The idea of creating an educational psychogeographic scavenger hunt thus seemed
                    like an effective way of repurposing GIS and other locative platforms to create
                    new participatory archives and alternative cartographies that connect students
                    to their immediate environment. The main tool for this class project was
                    Fulcrum, which is an easy-to-use mobile data collection platform. Even though
                    Fulcrum is not open-source, institutional access allows for students to all
                    contribute data (such as photos, videos, and location information) on the same
                    map in real-time, and edit them easily; the data can then be exported and
                    publicly published on other platforms like Esri’s ArcGIS Online (AGOL). Fulcrum
                    is both a web-based platform and a mobile app. Users can customize the online
                    data collection form for the mobile Fulcrum app with the information required
                    for specific projects, such as a description of each data point and extra fields
                    for audiovisual location-based data.</p>
                <p>The objective of my class scavenger hunt was for students to use the customized
                    data form on their mobile Fulcrum app to document examples of ongoing
                    activism/resistance and civic engagement on and near the NYU campus, and to
                    archive those in the form of videos, photos, audio, hyperlinks and participant
                    interviews. With the assistance of NYU technology expert Kyle Greenberg, we
                    added some required fields to the customizable mobile Fulcrum form builder, such
                    as a mandatory field for a description of the data point (with the prompt
                        <q>What do you see?</q>), a classification of the type of activism
                    (reductively labeled as either <q>Active</q> for ongoing protests and current
                    events, or <q>Passive</q> for more subjective interpretations of
                    activism/resistance), a justification (<q>Why is this activism/resistance?</q>),
                    and a field for uploading at least one form of audiovisual data such as
                    photographs, video, or audio. The option of incorporating mandatory fields that
                    students need to fill out is useful in terms of prompting more on-the-spot
                    critical reflection whenever students enter a new data point, and making sure
                    that every addition to the database has a specific and thought-out purpose. To
                    stimulate some healthy competition among the students, I set up a points system
                    to award each finding. For instance, 10 points were awarded for data on active
                    acts of resistance (such as a live protest march or demonstration), 5 points for
                    passive activism (such as activist posters or signs), 3 points for interviews, 3
                    points for uploading more than one form of media documentation (video, audio,
                    image), and -3 points for returning to class after the 1 hour deadline that was
                    assigned for the scavenger hunt. </p>
                <p>By adding these categories and requirements to the scavenger hunt, students were
                    able to approach data as more than just singular bits of information in a
                    database (<ref target="#figure11">Figure 11</ref>). This helped them visualize
                    the real-time data points that were added on our Fulcrum map as referents to
                    multiple media and social relations, and gave them the opportunity to reflect on
                    their individual and collective trajectories as alternative modes of
                    thematically and psychogeographically mapping their surroundings. The abstract
                    space on the map and the information in the Fulcrum database thus became endued
                    with heterogeneous points of social difference and possibilities for personal
                    intervention. In navigating the campus and surrounding areas with the objective
                    of documenting signs of resistance to the status quo, students were able to
                    collectively re-imagine their surroundings as vibrant hubs for everyday acts of
                    activism and social engagement. Furthermore, the resulting data formed an
                    archive of ephemeral and ongoing activities that are testament to the changing
                    post-election climate in present-day NYC. Their findings included multimedia
                    documentation of a pledge to collect signatures for turning NYU into a sanctuary
                    campus (a cause close to the students’ hearts), a campus leadership initiative
                    for students of color, artistic forms of resistance, and inspirational quotes
                    etched on nearby landmark sites. The images below show an annotated compilation
                    of some of the media contributed by the students (<ref target="#figure12"
                        >Figures 12-14</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure11">
                    <head>Fulcrum database of student data, updated in real-time and plotted on an
                        area map</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure12">
                    <head>A call for inclusive religion by Rev. Bobbi Jean Baker, outside the Judson
                        Memorial Church near campus,</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure13">
                    <head>One of the many stickers found on campus promoting the pledge for NYU
                        becoming a sanctuary campus.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure14">
                    <head>Video of Louise Boatwright’s data bias visualization installation, <title
                            rend="quotes">Deviations and Interference,</title> NYU Department of
                        Photo and Imaging Senior Thesis show.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The requirement of having to describe and explain why each data point qualified
                    as activism/resistance motivated students to provide concrete accompanying
                    arguments for their chosen data, especially in cases where it was not
                    immediately apparent why they chose that particular site or artifact. For
                    instance, student Leonard Cortana took a photograph of a defaced Chaplin poster
                    in the Tisch building, and tagged it as a <q>mash up</q> with the data
                    description <q>not my dictator</q> (<ref target="#figure15">Figure 15</ref>).
                    Adding further explanation, Leonard uploaded an audio recording of himself
                    explaining why the defaced Chaplin poster – which is significantly from
                    Chaplin’s 1940 film <title rend="italic">The Great Dictator</title> – resonates
                    with his own experience of the current political climate in the U.S. The
                    classification of the poster as a political mashup also demonstrated the
                    student’s ability to relate this example of DIY mashup graffiti to the
                    historical exploration of subversive practices of resistance covered in the
                    course. Olusola Babajide-Kassam, a Nigerian student invested in issues of
                    everyday racial discrimination, uploaded a series of images from a Black Lives
                    Matter photo exhibition on campus, and described it as a pronouncement of <q>the
                        essence of our lives as blacks…[who] have been undermined in several facets
                        of the community…[by] whites not in the sense of color but in terms of
                        mentality</q> (<ref target="#figure16">Figure 16</ref>). Olusola also
                    contributed audio with his own commentary on Black Lives Matter, and recorded
                    video and audio-only interviews with predominantly white NYU students. In the
                    audio-only files, the color of the interviewees becomes apparent through the
                    challenging questions about race posed by Olusola; the choice of using only
                    audio to document these interviews helped illustrate his idea of an internalized
                        <soCalled>white mentality</soCalled> that transcends external appearance. In
                    his video interviews, Olusola documented the rather typical responses to Black
                    Lives Matter by white students, who stated solidarity with the cause but could
                    not further elaborate on what needs to be done to practically ensure racial
                    equality. Despite the young students’ expected responses, though, Olusola’s
                    confrontational questions caused them to actively acknowledged their own racial
                    and class privilege, and to reflect on deep-set and institutionalized forms of
                    racism that cannot easily be reversed. Going beyond the objective of
                    documentation and reflecting on calls to action, several students in the class
                    uploaded resources on how to make a change. The Political Resources poster in
                    the Cinema Studies department lounge, for instance, was an image that most of
                    the students chose to include in hopes of turning the documentation of civic
                    protests into an active tool for multiple modes of organized civic participation
                        (<ref target="#figure17">Figure 17</ref>). </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure15">
                    <head>DIY Chaplin mashup.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure16">
                    <head>Black Lives Matter photo exhibition in Tisch lobby.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure17">
                    <head>Political Resources poster in NYU Cinema Studies department</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.JPG"/>
                </figure>
                <p>During the turbulent post-election period, students found the scavenger hunt to
                    be a positive and encouraging experience in terms of the future of critical
                    thinking and the defense of human rights. Being able to witness and document the
                    many instances of civic protests made students feel part of the shared struggles
                    for equality, and this experience also made them reflect on other potential uses
                    of social media tools beyond their so-called distracting and trivializing
                    aspects. Through this project, not only did students learn more about locative
                    media such as GIS and GPS through practice, but they also created their own
                    archive that makes visible and virtually permanent the multiple efforts for
                    civic participation and free speech. The ability to capture ephemeral moments of
                    protest further added to the meaningful aspects of the project, and helped the
                    students experiment with different ways of documenting and sharing transient
                    experiences. The scavenger hunt also gave the class a chance to interact with
                    their community (e.g. through interviews with protest organizers and
                    participants) and become more aware of how their seemingly neutral surroundings
                    become politically charged in times of crisis. I decided to leave this project
                    open-ended even after the end of the course since students are still
                    periodically adding to it whenever they encounter something worth adding to the
                    database. The next step to this project would be extracting the stored Fulcrum
                    data into an Esri platform such as StoryMaps for an interactive and publicly
                    accessible visualization of the students’ collective cartography of local
                    activism.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>As Marion Thain has historicized, distracted acts of reading and short attention
                    spans have been historically dismissed as frivolous and counterproductive,
                    dating back to, for instance, early 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century
                    debates on long-form prose poetry <ptr target="#thain2016"/>. Instead of
                    resisting and rejecting emerging technologies and their (debatably) new
                    cognitive demands, this essay has proposed some strategies for adapting pedagogy
                    to embrace innovative modes of inquiry and practice (both in terms of technology
                    and methodology), while at the same time maintaining and amplifying certain
                    standard learning objectives such as critical thinking. These digital humanities
                    group projects provide examples of expanded learning tools that can be modified
                    for teaching other subjects, and also enable students to make contributions to
                    cultural research, participatory historiography, and civic engagement through
                    experimental critical practice. The drifts from pre-determined learning outcomes
                    are meant to be active disruptions to any prescribed limitations that delimit
                    what digital humanities should or should not be, and other issues that often
                    undermine the potential contributions to digital humanities that derive from the
                    intellectual and material labor that happens in the networked, expanded and
                    distributed classroom. The remix aesthetic, the productive distractions from
                    predictable learning outcomes, as well as the <soCalled>unfinished</soCalled>
                    and makeshift nature of these projects is something that I find adds value to
                    this kind of process-oriented pedagogy because it remains in touch with the
                    pre-institutionalized experimental ethos that prompted the formation of the
                    digital humanities in the first place. </p>
                <p>The author would like to thank all the students from <title rend="quotes"
                        >Interactive Cinema and New Media</title> and <title rend="quotes">Cinema
                        and the Digital Humanities</title> courses; without their willingness to
                    experiment and keep an open mind, these projects would not have been possible.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baradaran" label="Baradaran">Baradaran, Amir. <title rend="quotes"
                        >FutARism Manifesto</title> [Accessed 30 Sept. 2016]. <ref
                        target="http://amirbaradaran.com/ab_futarism.php"
                        >http://amirbaradaran.com/ab_futarism.php</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bogost2011" label="Bogost 2017">Bogost, Ian. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Gamification is Bullshit,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Altantic</title>, 9 Aug. 2011 [Accessed 14 Jun. 2017].
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2011/08/gamification-is-bullshit/243338/"
                        >https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2011/08/gamification-is-bullshit/243338/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coverley2010" label="Coverley 2010">Coverley, Merlin. <title
                        rend="italic">Psychogeography</title>. Harpenden, UK: Oldcastle Books,
                    2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis2008" label="Davis 2008">Davis, Blair. <title rend="quotes">Old
                        Films, New Sounds: Screening Silent Cinema with Electronic Music,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Revue Canadienne d'Études cinématographiques</title>/<title
                        rend="italic">Canadian Journal of Film Studies</title>, 17 (2008) 2, pp.
                    77-98.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="debord1989" label="Debord 1989">Debord, Guy. <title rend="quotes">Two
                        Accounts of the Dérive,</title> in <title rend="italic">On the Passage of a
                        Few People Through a Rather Brief Moment in Time: The Situationist
                        International 1957-1972</title>, ed. Elisabeth Sussman. Cambridge, MA: The
                    MIT Press, 1989, pp. 135-9.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="educause2011" label="Educause 2011">Educause. <title rend="quotes">7
                        Things You Should Know About Gamification,</title> 2011 [Accessed 2 May
                    2017]. <ref
                        target="https://library.educause.edu/~/media/files/library/2011/8/eli7075-pdf.pdf"
                        >https://library.educause.edu/~/media/files/library/2011/8/eli7075-pdf.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elsaesser2015" label="Elsaesser and Hagener 2015">Elsaesser, Thomas
                    and Malte Hagener. <title rend="italic">Film Theory: An Introduction through the
                        Senses</title>, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edn. New York: Routledge,
                    2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gordon2011" label="Gordon and de Souza e Silva 2011">Gordon, Eric, and
                    Adriana de Souza e Silva. <title rend="italic">Net Locality: Why Location
                        Matters in a Networked World</title>. New York: Wiley-Blackwell,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="groo2012" label="Groo 2012">Groo, Katherine. <title rend="quotes">Cut,
                        Paste, Stutter, Glitch: Remixing Silent Film History,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Frames Cinema Journal</title> 1 (2012) 1, [Accessed 10 Feb.
                    2016]. <ref
                        target="http://framescinemajournal.com/article/cut-paste-glitch-and-stutter/"
                        >http://framescinemajournal.com/article/cut-paste-glitch-and-stutter/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grossman2014" label="Grossman 2014">Grossman, Andrew. <title
                        rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">Tomatoes Another Day</title>: The
                        Improbable Ideological Subversion of James Sibley Watson and Melville
                        Webber,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Bright Lights Film Journal</title>, 28 Nov. 2014 [Accessed
                    10 Jun. 2017]. <ref
                        target="http://brightlightsfilm.com/tomatoes-another-day-improbable-ideological-subversion-james-sibley-watson-melville-webber/#.VyUzYT85g4p"
                        >http://brightlightsfilm.com/tomatoes-another-day-improbable-ideological-subversion-james-sibley-watson-melville-webber/#.VyUzYT85g4p</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hjorth2012" label="Hjorth and Lim 2012">Hjorth, Larissa, and Sun Sun
                    Lim. <title rend="quotes">Mobile Intimacy in an Age of Affective Mobile
                        Media,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Studies</title> 12 (2012) 4,
                    pp.447-484.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hochman2014" label="Hochman, Manovich, and Yazdani 2014">Hochman,
                    Nadav, Lev Manovich, and Mehrdad Yazdani. <title rend="quotes">On
                        Hyper-locality: Performances of Place in Social Media,</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of 2014 International AAAI Conference on Weblogs
                        and Social Media (ICWSM)</title>, 2014 [Accessed 10 Feb. 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hu2013" label="Hu, Farnham, and Monroy-Hernández 2013">Hu, Yuheng,
                    Shelly D. Farnham, and Andrés Monroy-Hernández. <title rend="quotes">Woo.ly:
                        Facilitating Information Seeking for Hyperlocal Communities using Social
                        Media,</title> in <title rend="italic">CHI’13: Proceedings of the SIGCHI
                        Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>, 2013, pp.
                    3481-3490.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huang2013" label="Huang and Soman 2013">Huang, Wendy Hsin Yuan, and
                    Dilip Soman. <title rend="italic">A Practitioner’s Guide to Gamification of
                        Educaiton</title>. Toronto: Rotman School of Management, University of
                    Toronto, 10 Dec. 2013 [Accessed 10 Jun. 2017]. <ref
                        target="https://inside.rotman.utoronto.ca/behaviouraleconomicsinaction/files/2013/09/GuideGamificationEducationDec2013.pdf"
                        >https://inside.rotman.utoronto.ca/behaviouraleconomicsinaction/files/2013/09/GuideGamificationEducationDec2013.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hutcheon1985" label="Hutcheon 1985">Hutcheon, Linda. <title
                        rend="italic">A Theory of Parody</title>. London: Methuen, 1985.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="imre2009" label="Imre 2009">Imre, Anikó. <title rend="italic">Identity
                        Games: Globalization and the Transformation of Media Cultures in the New
                        Europe</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2009. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kapp2012" label="Kapp 2012">Kapp, Karl M. <title rend="italic">The
                        Gamification of Learning and Instruction: Game-based Methods and Strategies
                        for Training and Education</title>. New York: Pfeiffer, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koh2014" label="Koh 2014">Koh, Adeline. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Political Power of Play,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hybrid Pedagogy</title>, 3 Apr. 2014 [Accessed 2 June
                    2017]. <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/hybridped/political-power-of-play/"
                        >http://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/hybridped/political-power-of-play/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="old" label="Oxford Living Dictionaries"><title rend="quotes"
                        >Palimpsest.</title> Oxford Living Dictionaries [Accessed 20 Jun. 2017].
                        <ref target="https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/palimpsest"
                        >https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/palimpsest</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="petrucco2016" label="Petrucco and Agostini 2016">Petrucco, Corrado,
                    and Daniele Agostini, <title rend="quotes">Teaching Our Cultural Heritage Using
                        Mobile Augmented Reality,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of e-Leaning and Knowledge Society</title>, 12
                    (2016) 3, pp. 115-128.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rushkoff2006" label="Rushkoff 2006">Rushkoff, Douglas. <title
                        rend="italic">Screenagers: Lessons in Chaos From Digital Kids.</title> New
                    York: Hampton Press, 2006. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stommel2013" label="Stommel, Rorabaugh, and Morris 2013">Stommel,
                    Jesse, Peter Rorabaugh, and Sean Michael Morris, <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                        Rigor,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hybrid Pedagogy</title>, 9 Oct. 2013 [Accessed 14 Jun.
                    2017]. <ref target="http://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/hybridped/beyond-rigor/"
                        >http://www.digitalpedagogylab.com/hybridped/beyond-rigor/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thain2016" label="Thain 2016">Thain, Marion. Introduction to <title
                        rend="quotes">Distracted Reading: Acts of Attention in the Age of the
                        Internet</title> symposium, New York University Center for the Humanities,
                    Sept. 27, 2016. Online recording: <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDVJTj7KKjg&amp;t=2745s"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDVJTj7KKjg&amp;t=2745s</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="usai2010" label="Usai 2010">Usai, Paolo Cherchi. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Silent Cinema: An Introduction</title>. London: BFI, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="willis2015" label="Willis 2015">Willis, Holly. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Writing Images and the Cinematic Humanities,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visible Language</title>, 49 (Dec. 2015) 1,
                    pp.63-77.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
