<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Stealing a Corpus: Appropriating Aesop’s Body in the
               Early Age of Print </title>
            <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Alex <dhq:family>Mueller</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Massachusetts Boston</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alex.mueller@umb.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Alex Mueller is Associate Professor of English in the College of Liberal Arts
                     at the Universty of Massachusetts Boston. His research areas include literature
                     pedagogy, digital rhetoric, medieval literature, Arthurian romance, and book
                     history.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000382</idno>
            <idno type="volume">012</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2018-07-28">28 July 2018</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>The fate of the medieval Aesop during the early age of print reveals the tensions
               that arise between <emph>corporeal</emph> and <emph>proprietary</emph> understandings
               of artistic production. Building upon the highly accumulative, various, and
               expandable Aesopic tradition that thrived in the Middle Ages within scholastic
               manuscripts, the fifteenth-century fables of Robert Henryson and William Caxton
               confront movements to consolidate and transform Aesop’s sprawling literary corpus
               into a singular printable property. At the same time that a single series of Aesop’s
               fables, now known as the <title rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title>, became
               increasingly standardized within printed books, woodcut illustrations and textual
               descriptions increasingly beautified Aesop’s body, transforming him from an
               inarticulate slave to an eloquent aristocrat. The simultaneous metamorphosis of
               Aesop’s poetic and visual corpus reveals the premodern underpinnings for current
               efforts by publishing industries to immunize digital work from rogue acts of
               appropriation, mashup, and remix, practices which had previously defined Aesopic
               textuality. As a response to this textual vulnerability, the collapse of Aesopic work
               into a singular entity reimagines the allegorical relationship between the author or
               publisher and the work as proprietary, not corporeal. Rather than an extension of a
               generative, deeply somatic, and grotesque process of multiple fabular authors and
               commentators, the modernized Aesop obtains value as a <soCalled>property,</soCalled>
               paving the way for the notion that creative corpuses can be
                  <soCalled>owned,</soCalled> effectively stealing away corporeal features from
               intellectual production. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Argues that the modernized Aesop obtains value as a <soCalled>property,</soCalled>
               paving the way for the notion that creative corpuses can be
                  <soCalled>owned,</soCalled> effectively stealing away corporeal features from
               intellectual production.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head/>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p> Perhaps the most overwhelming aspect of digital writing is its vulnerability to all
               kinds of intellectual theft, from illicit copying to database hacking. While the
               threats to artistic autonomy and intellectual property are significant, many forms of
               digital appropriation are undeniably innovative, creative, and valuable. Even if we
               set aside the privacy/security debates surrounding efforts to make information
               transparent, especially given the volatile responses to WikiLeaks and Edward Snowden,
               we can recognize the artistic potential of hacking, which often results in stunning
               music remixes and viral video mashups. The result, of course, has led to much
               handwringing, especially from self-interested corporations crying foul over
               violations of copyright <ptr target="#lessig2005"/>
               <ptr target="#vaidhyanathan2003"/>. Yet, such artistic acts of appropriation have
               become so <soCalled>cool</soCalled> that they have led scholars such as Alan Liu to
               suggest that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004">[s]trong art will be about the
                        <soCalled>destruction of destruction</soCalled> or, put another way, the
                     recognition of the destructiveness of creation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="9"/>
               </cit>. Within the digital world, such a neo-avant garde aesthetics of destruction
               has fostered an environment of textual vulnerability, in which texts are, radically,
               at the will of their users.</p>
            <p> At the same time, it is crucial to acknowledge that such an emphasis on
                  <soCalled>creative destruction</soCalled> can lead to an uncritical acceptance of
               all forms of <soCalled>innovation,</soCalled> one of the most powerful euphemisms for
               capitalistic enterprise. As Joseph A. Schumpeter pointed out in 1943, the desire for
               new markets leads to <quote rend="inline" source="#schumpeter1994">industrial
                  mutation,</quote> part of what he later calls a <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#schumpeter1994">perennial gale of creative destruction</quote> that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#schumpeter1994">incessantly revolutionizes the
                     economic structure <emph>from within</emph>, incessantly destroying the old
                     one, incessantly creating a new one</quote>
                  <ptr target="#schumpeter1994" loc="83"/>
               </cit>. This phoenix-like logic, in which a new power rises from the ashes of the
               old, also undergirds medieval theories of sovereignty – what is often referred to as
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">translatio imperii</foreign>, or the translation of power
               from one civilization to the next <ptr target="#mueller2013" loc="3–4"/>
               <ptr target="#robinson1997"/>. Histories of imperialism teach us that such an
               optimistic view of destruction often serves the interests of the elite who benefit
               from such <soCalled>innovation</soCalled> while disenfranchising others, especially
               those cultures or industries that have been <soCalled>mutated</soCalled> or
                  <soCalled>superseded.</soCalled> Liu turns to the writings of the Critical Art
               Ensemble (CAE), as an example of neo-avant-garde collective that will use their
               technical skills of <quote rend="inline" source="#cae1996">disturbance</quote> and
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cae1996">hacktivism</quote> as a means to disrupt
               these forces of exclusion, but even the CAE adopts the elitist logic of creative
               destruction by claiming that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004">the only groups that will successfully
                     confront power are those that locate the arena of contestation in cyberspace,
                     and hence an elite force seems to be the best possibility</quote>
                  <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="367"/>
               </cit>
               <ptr target="#cae1996"/>. As Patricia Ingham warns in her recent book, <title
                  rend="italic">The Medieval New</title>, such an embrace of complete destruction
               and confrontation means that <quote rend="inline" source="#ingham2015">we have bought
                  entirely the notion that innovation lays waste to what has come before,</quote> as
               opposed to the practices of <quote rend="inline" source="#ingham2015">ambivalent
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">homage</foreign></quote> that define many medieval
               perspectives on innovation <ptr target="#ingham2015" loc="14"/>.</p>
            <p> In this essay, I argue for the importance of understanding the politics and ethics
               of medieval forms of appropriation, which are rarely acts of destruction and more
               often premodern forms of sampling, remix, and mashup, which rely on degrees of
                  <soCalled>homage</soCalled> to ancient authorities. As Kathleen Kennedy has
               demonstrated in her book, <title rend="italic">Medieval Hackers</title>, we encounter
               early evidence of <quote rend="inline" source="#kennedy2015">hacker culture</quote>
               during the later Middle Ages when governmental, educational, and ecclesiastical
               institutions attempted to control information <ptr target="#kennedy2015" loc="4"/>.
               Reactions to these forms of control varied, but graduates of medieval schools had
               already been trained to appropriate texts critically, a practice many of them learned
               in their writing exercises, which emphasized citation and reuse of existing
               authorities. While the salience of this point could be made with the commentary
               traditions of a number of theological texts, such as the <title rend="italic">Glossa
                  Ordinaria</title>
               <ptr target="#saloman2012"/>, or legal books, such as the <title rend="italic"
                  >Decretum</title>
               <ptr target="#winroth2004"/>, I have selected one canon of pedagogical texts, Aesop’s
               fables, as a representative example for analysis. These animal tales are known for
               their moral lessons, but they were primarily utilized in medieval classrooms for
               reading and writing instruction. Students and teachers would insert interlineal
               glosses, usually Latin synonyms, to challenge their expanding vocabulary and then
               rewrite these fables, both in abbreviated and elaborated forms. Most crucially,
               though, students and teachers appended extensive commentaries to fables in their
               manuscripts, which regularly occupied more space on the page then the fables
               themselves. These rhetorical amplifications often became acts of appropriation,
               revisions of fables that bear the names of Aesopic authors that range from Avianus to
               Walter of England to Robert Henryson. </p>
            <p> Within the context of 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> century copyright law, this
               combination of critical commentary and literary <soCalled>theft</soCalled> challenges
               current understandings of <q>fair use.</q> As Robin Wharton has demonstrated about
               the Court of Appeals for the Eleventh Circuit’s decision in <title rend="italic"
                  >Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin</title>, 286 F.3d 1257 <ptr
                  target="#suntrust2001"/>, interpretations of copyright have begun to separate
               literary <q>critique</q> from <q>creative</q> work <ptr target="#wharton2013"
                  loc="32–8"/>. In an attempt to distinguish parody from satire as a literary genre
               that falls within fair use, the court in <title rend="italic">Suntrust</title>
               determined that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#suntrust2001">[a] parody is a work that seeks to
                     comment upon or criticize another work by appropriating elements of the
                     original. <quote rend="inline" source="#suntrust2001">Parody needs to mimic an
                        original to make its point, and so has some claim to use the creation of its
                           <hi rend="italic">victim’s (or collective victims’)</hi>
                        imagination</quote></quote>
                  <ptr target="#suntrust2001"/>
               </cit>. Revisions of medieval fables also incorporated commentaries within their
               elaborations on the Aesopic imagination, but the result was hardly parodic and the
               previous fables were rarely victims of critique. Rather, new fables became new
               members attached to the Aesopic corpus, a ceaselessly expandable body of fabular work
               composed by innumerable Aesopic authors and commentators. As the fable traditions
               begin to appear in print, we see acts of <soCalled>hacking</soCalled> emerge in the
               form of mashups and remixes of fables – an especially poignant phenomenon in the
               printed life of Henryson’s <title rend="italic">Morall Fabillis</title>. Within these
               early printed contexts, we see striking evidence of critical appropriation, in which
               printers and readers remix fables for new audiences, all the while paying
                  <soCalled>ambivalent <foreign xml:lang="fr">homage</foreign></soCalled> to their
               origins. In this essay, I ultimately want to suggest that a premodern orientation
               toward intellectual bodies, instead of properties, may produce more responsible uses,
               critiques, and reuses of artistic work and ultimately offer formidable challenges to
               self-interested uses of copyright law, as well as idealistic fantasies of a
                  <soCalled>creative commons.</soCalled></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>From Corpus to Locus</head>
            <p>As staples of medieval grammar and composition instruction, readers paraphrased and
               elaborated upon Aesop’s fables in extensive commentaries that subsequent readers
               could associate with other classroom texts and extend through marginal and
               interlineal glosses. After the twelfth century, the fable series known as the <title
                  rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title> became the canonical <title rend="quotes"
                  >Aesop,</title> which students and their teachers paraphrased and expanded through
               extensive glosses that accumulated in manuscripts and early printed books. The <title
                  rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title> was composed of sixty verse fables that
               survive in at least 170 manuscripts and fifty printed editions published in five
               countries by the end of the fifteenth century <ptr target="#hervieux1960" loc="1:472"/>
               <ptr target="#dicke1987" loc="lxvi–lxviii"/>. Because of the popularity of this
               Aesopic corpus, the textual spaces that housed this fable series became read-write
               platforms in which individual fables were compiled, rearranged, and mashed up,
               stretching the limits of what we now call <q>intellectual property.</q></p>
            <p>Within an Anglo-American legal context, proprietary language for creative production
               did not emerge until 1624, when the English Parliament approved an act to prevent
               commercial monopolies and enhance the Crown’s power over the issuing of patents <ptr
                  target="#johns2010" loc="28"/>. And it was not until 1666 that booksellers
               embraced the language of authorial <soCalled>property</soCalled> in their defense
               against royalist claims that the Stationer encouraged piracy against the Crown. The
               booksellers and printers collectively argued that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#booksellers1666">the Author of every manuscript or
                     copy hath (in all reason) as good right thereunto, as any Man hath to the
                     Estate wherein he has the most absolute property</quote>
                  <ptr target="#booksellers1666"/>
               </cit>. Rather than allow the Crown to destroy the Stationer and its control over the
               registry of printings, this statement empowered authors to sell the rights of their
               works over to booksellers. As Adrian Johns contends, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johns2010">This may be the earliest explicit
                     articulation of the idea of literary property – of an absolute right generated
                     by authorship, which could serve as the cornerstone of an entire moral and
                     economic system of print. Certainly the idea had no clear precedent behind
                     it</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johns2010" loc="38"/>
               </cit>. For contemporaries unfamiliar with the Crown’s attempted publication
               land-grab, such a statement must have been stunning in its hyperbolic claims to
               written work as property. This statement is also striking in its advocacy for
               authors, not printers or booksellers. As Rebecca Curtin has pointed out, early
               printers were occasionally willing to engage in <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#curtin2014">alternative transactions,</quote> granting privileges to
               authors in order to encourage them to enter the book market, a situation that she
               claims has been replicated within open source software sharing movements in recent
               decades <ptr target="#curtin2014" loc="136"/>.</p>
            <p>Johns is likely correct that no explicit precedent exists for the printers and
               booksellers’ statement of 1666, but the transformation of the understanding of the
               book as a <foreign xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign> to the book as a <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">locus</foreign>, particularly for the medieval Aesop, in the
               preceding centuries suggests that the groundwork was already being prepared for such
               a claim. Quite literally, of course, the medieval book was a body with leaves of
               sheepskin, bound around a spine with animal glue, and enclosed with calfskin leather
                  <ptr target="#walker2013" loc="8"/>. Figuratively, the body played a central role
               in the medieval imagination, a role that Guillemette Bolens divides into two types:
               contained bodies and articulated bodies. Within the articulation model, bodies are
               designed for motion with limbs connected by joints – suggesting the potentiality of
               movement that can only be severed through destruction or mutilation, such as
               Beowulf’s wresting of Grendel’s arm from its socket <ptr target="#bolens2000"
                  loc="145–81"/>. This dynamic view of corporeality was an alternative to the
               containment model, in which the body’s outer layer would both define the body and
               prevent penetration from outside forces, such as weapons, poisons, or corruptions.
               This corporeal envelope was often understood to include protective or concealing
               clothing, such as skin, armor, or sacred garb <ptr target="#young1993"/>
               <ptr target="#rubin1994"/>
               <ptr target="#cohen2003"/>. The culture of books, in turn, provides its own rigorous
               structure of containment, words alphabetized and contained within the limited space
               of leaves of paper or parchment, selected folios bound together in discrete codices,
               held within bookcases within libraries. This containment model is continuous from the
               Middle Ages into the Renaissance and beyond, but as Paul Zumthor and Jan-Dirk Müller
               have argued, books began to shed their corporeal natures shortly after the arrival of
               the printing press <ptr target="#zumthor1987"/>
               <ptr target="#müller1994"/>. As Johns points out, the threat of piracy compelled
               early printers to protect their industry by enclosing it within the moral comfort of
               domestic spaces: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#johns2010">A printing house was to be a printing
                        <emph>house</emph>. At one point the law actually stipulated expressly that
                     presswork could only be done at home. The idea was that activities carried out
                     in a patriarchal household partook of the moral order implicit in that
                     place</quote>
                  <ptr target="#johns2010" loc="27"/>
               </cit>. Once books became associated more often with a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >locus</foreign> than a <foreign xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign>, they became ripe
               for the proprietary appropriations that would crescendo after the seventeenth
               century.</p>
            <p>When we refer to the medieval Aesop, we are referring both to the ramifying sets of
               beast fables inscribed into books used in classroom instruction and the various
               conceptions of the author himself. In both cases, Aesop is not a <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">locus.</foreign> The medieval Aesop is undoubtedly a <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign> and (to use Bolens’ term) a radically articulated
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign>, at that. In addition to the proliferating
               sets of fables and their commentaries, Aesop himself was a sprawling and monstrous
               figure, whom William Caxton in his 1484 <title rend="italic">Life of Aesop</title>
               described as having <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#lenaghan1967">a grete hede / large visage / longe
                     Iowes / sharp eyen / a short necke / corbe backed / grete bely / grete legges /
                     and large feet</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lenaghan1967" loc="27"/>
               </cit>. Moreover, this grotesquely articulated body is obsessed with linguistic modes
               of articulation, so much so that he serves cooked animal tongues to dinner guests
                  <ptr target="#lenaghan1967" loc="43–44"/>. By giving his animal protagonists human
               tongues, he essentially reverses their fate, engaging in an allegorical fantasy of
               monstrous speech. And, according to one young medieval reader, even this uncontained
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign> – and by proxy his schoolmaster – was
               subject to the figural violence of its students. An annotation to the explicit in
               Lambeth Palace MS 431 (fol. 136v) ends with a call to arms: <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#lambethms431">Finito libro, frangamus ossa magistro</quote> [Having
               finished this book, let us break the bones of the master] <ptr target="#lambethms431"/>
               <ptr target="#wheatley2000" loc="94"/>. Again and again, the medieval Aesop is
               described in corporeal terms, but as Aesop begins to appear in print, his body and
               fabular tradition are increasingly de-articulated and contained, inspiring
                  <soCalled>piratical</soCalled> acts of resistance designed to appropriate, mashup,
               and remix Aesopic work for new audiences. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Allegorical Body Snatching</head>
            <p> To understand the inextricable bond between Aesop’s poetic corpus and his authorial
               body, it is helpful to consider the following fable, whose unorthodox message and
               textual afterlife epitomize the corporeal nature of Aesopica. Here is a summary of
               the tale: Late one evening, while guarding the bodies of criminals hanging from
               crosses, a soldier overhears the pitiful cries of a woman distraught by the death of
               her husband. Despite the king’s warning that the theft of the crucified corpses would
               result in the death of the guard on watch, the soldier, unable to resist his
               attraction to the beautiful widow, relinquishes his post to comfort and feed her.
               Seduced by this compassionate gesture, she embraces the soldier and they copulate
               over her husband’s tomb. When he resumes his watch, he discovers to his dismay that
               one of the bodies has been stolen. The widow is so moved by his earlier kindness to
               her that she tells him, <quote rend="inline" source="#mueller1995">Malo mortuum
                  impendere quam vivum occidere</quote> [I would prefer to hang a dead man than kill
               a living one], offering to substitute the body of her dead husband for the missing
               criminal <ptr target="#mueller1995" loc="112.7–8"/>. At her urging, they remove the
               husband's corpse from his tomb and hang it on the cross in the criminal’s place (<ref
                  target="#figure01">fig. 1</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>The woodcut that accompanies <title rend="quotes">De Viro et Uxore</title>
                     in Heinrich Steinhöwel’s <title rend="italic">Aesop</title> (Basel: Jacob von
                     Pfortzheim, 1501).<note> Images of the woodcut illustrations from this edition
                        have been retrieved from the University of Mannheim, <ref
                           target="http://www.uni-mannheim.de/mateo/desbillons/esop.html"
                           >http://www.uni-mannheim.de/mateo/desbillons/esop.html</ref>.</note></head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of a widow and soldier replacing a criminal's missing body with
                     the widow's husband's.</figDesc>
               </figure></p>
            <p> This tale of grave robbing also serves as an allegory for the way this fable itself
               was exhumed, reshaped, and incorporated into other literary traditions. We may
               recognize this story as the <title rend="quotes">Matron of Ephesus</title> from the
                  <title rend="italic">Satyricon</title>, Petronius’ first century C.E. satire of
               Roman excess, but the tale was more frequently known throughout the Middle Ages as a
               standard fable in the <title rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title>
               <ptr target="#wheatley2000" loc="82–4"/>
               <ptr target="#wheatley1999"/>. This is surprising because we can identify next to
               nothing Aesopic in this one, which contains nary a talking non-human animal and
               includes lascivious content that cannot be easily moralized. While the <title
                  rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title> emerged as the predominant pedagogical
               series of fables and the basis for one popular printed version, known as the <title
                  rend="italic">Esopus moralizatus</title>, the number of variations of each fable
               and their commentaries suggest that the medieval fable corpus had been extensively
               revised and re-allegorized <ptr target="#wright2001" loc="xxiii"/>
               <ptr target="#wright1998"/>
               <ptr target="#cramer1995"/>. One reader of this fable, for example, was dissatisfied
               with the notion that the widow’s husband would not have been discovered to be a
               different corpse from that of the stolen criminal. To correct this <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">non sequitur</foreign>, this commentator revised the tale, adding a
               new scene in which the guard recalls that the criminal did not have any teeth,
               motivating the compliant widow to grab a stone nearby and smash out the teeth from
               her dead husband’s mouth <ptr target="#hervieux1960" loc="2:341n1"/>. This revision
               is simply one example, which suggests that these fables were considered to be
               flexible works in progress, ripe for correction and appropriation, rather than
               finished products to be consumed <q>as is.</q></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Mouvance and Premodern Remix</head>
            <p> Following the pioneering work of Paul Zumthor, medievalists have tended to
               characterize such textual malleability as <term>mouvance</term> or variance in an
               effort to distinguish the dynamic volatility of manuscript culture from the alleged
               fixity of print culture <ptr target="#zumthor1972"/>. Even scholars working outside
               of medieval studies in the 1980s, such as Gerald Bruns, began to make stark
               distinctions between <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bruns1982">the closed text of a print culture and
                     the open text of a manuscript culture</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bruns1982" loc="44"/>
               </cit>. Bernard Cerquiglini famously used the strongest terms, claiming that <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#cerquiglini1989">l’écriture médiévale ne produit pas de
                  variants, elle est variance</quote> [medieval writing does not produce variants;
               it is variance.] <ptr target="#cerquiglini1989" loc="111"/>. Such an emphasis on the
               radical elusiveness and multiplicity of texts within manuscript culture encouraged
               medievalists to revise their editorial procedures, sometimes eschewing emendation
               altogether, in an effort to better represent the often untidy experience of reading a
               medieval text. This movement was marked in 1990 by a special issue in <title
                  rend="italic">Speculum</title> devoted to <q>The New Philology,</q> in which
               contributors, led by Stephen Nichols, critiqued their predecessors’ <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#nichols1990">preoccupation with scholarly exactitude based
                  on edited and printed texts</quote> and embraced <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nichols1990">the representation of the past which
                     went along with medieval manuscript culture: adaptation or <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">translatio</foreign>, the continual rewriting of past works in
                     a variety of versions, a practice which made even the copying of medieval works
                     an adventure in supplementation rather than faithful imitation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nichols1990" loc="2–3"/>
               </cit>. This was a welcome paradigm shift for many medievalists, but it unfortunately
               led to simplifications and exaggerations about the supposed
                  <soCalled>static</soCalled> or <soCalled>exact</soCalled> nature of print culture.
               As Leah Price has pointed out, it even led to some convenient McLuhanism, which
               allowed scholars, <foreign xml:lang="la">pace</foreign> Bruns, to make essentialist
               claims about the nature of print, rather than historicize particular developments
               within the multiple print eras, from movable type to mass production <ptr
                  target="#price2006" loc="14"/>. In particular, it is clear that early printers
               continued to consider carefully variance and the difficulty of representing multiple
               textual traditions, leaving space for reader involvement by allowing marginal space
               for commentary and appending errata lists for correction. And as Daniel Wakelin has
               recently shown, scribes and readers of the later Middle Ages were often quite
               invested in emending manuscripts, making sure that variance did not undermine the
               authority of their projects <ptr target="#wakelin2014"/>. </p>
            <p>While the medieval Aesopic tradition may offer a convincing case study for students
               of <term>mouvance</term>, this <foreign xml:lang="la">corpus</foreign> is not defined
               by its <foreign xml:lang="la">locus</foreign> – the exigencies of its material
               environment. Nor do I think it is useful to distinguish the types of Aesopic
               authorship according to the stark Bonaventuran categories of scribe, compiler,
               commentator, and author <ptr target="#minnis2009" loc="94–5"/>. As Matthew Fisher has
               suggested, Bonaventure offers this fourfold schema within a sacred tradition of
               theological commentary, not as a taxonomy for understanding medieval textuality more
               broadly, which is how it has been too often applied <ptr target="#fisher2012"
                  loc="71–2"/>. Within literary and historical manuscripts, the identities of
               scribe, compiler, commentary, and author often become irretrievably blurred and
               incapable of being reduced to these categories. </p>
            <p>I want to suggest, instead, that Aesopic practices of fable revision and exegetical
               allegorization are premodern examples of the now pervasive digital practice of
               remixing. While remixing practices typically refer to music sampling and compilations
               of previously recorded material, the aesthetics of remixing draws on the allegorical
               logic of medieval school texts, of which Aesopica serves as an exemplar, or the
               musical <soCalled>master</soCalled> recording so to speak. While there are various
               kinds of sampling, such as the extended remix (i.e. an elaborated version of an
               original track), Aesopic textuality is most aptly characterized by what Eduardo Navas
               calls <quote rend="inline" source="#navas2012">reflexive</quote> remixing, which <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#navas2012">allegorizes and extends the aesthetic of
                     sampling, where the remixed version challenges the <q>spectacular aura</q> of
                     the original and claims autonomy even when it carries the name of the
                     original</quote>
                  <ptr target="#navas2012" loc="60"/>
               </cit>. To establish a distinction between what he calls the <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#navas2012">original</quote> and its remix, Navas invokes Walter
               Benjamin’s conception of the <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin1968">aura</quote>
               or cult authority of an art object, which is increasingly eliminated through new
               forms of mechanical reproduction <ptr target="#benjamin1968" loc="221"/>. Unlike
               Benjamin, who views the liquidation of the aura (or the destruction of art’s <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#benjamin1968">ritual</quote> value) as the creation of
               art’s political potentiality <ptr target="#benjamin1968" loc="224"/>, however, Navas
               suggests that the reflexive remix recognizes AND challenges the authority of the aura
               through allegory <ptr target="#navas2012" loc="67"/>. </p>
            <p>Such acts of appropriation and sampling have been characterized by Alan Liu as <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#liu2004">destructive creativity,</quote> a kind of
               neo-avant-garde aesthetics that responds to the neoliberal push for constant
               innovation through acts of <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004">creative destruction</quote>
                  <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="317–71"/>
               </cit>. This is an attractive way of understanding the subversive value of remixing,
               but such a destructive artistic disposition reflects an antipathy to the past that
               effaces the history of art objects and undermines the force and function of a remix.
               After all, acts of sampling and remixing gain power through their ability to preserve
               the material they are reconstructing, their facility to expose their sources at the
               same time that they are appropriating and revising them. If a source is destroyed, it
               becomes unrecognizable, thereby evacuating its potency as an <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#ingham2015">act of ambivalent <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                  >homage</foreign>.</quote> This is the creative and constructive process that
               describes the medieval development of the beast fable corpus, which clings to the
               aura of Aesop, all the while expanding the collection through elaborations,
               additions, and variations under other names such as Phaedrus, Avianus, and Walter of
               England <ptr target="#gibbs2008"/>.</p>
            <p>The reflexive remixes that are familiar to most of us, such as alternative versions
               of popular books, songs, or movies, have been produced for decades behind the closed
               doors of publishing houses, music studios, and film editing rooms, but the emergence
               of read-write platforms such as blogs and wikis render such textual and visual
               mashups much more visible. As Martin Irvine has astutely observed, remix <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#irvine2014">has become a convenient metaphor for a
                     mode of production assumed (incorrectly) to be specific to our post-postmodern
                     era and media technologies (though with some earlier
                        <soCalled>precursors</soCalled>), and usually limited to describing features
                     of cultural artifacts as <soCalled>outputs</soCalled> of software processes
                     (especially in music, video, and photography</quote>
                  <ptr target="#irvine2014" loc="15"/>
               </cit>. Rather than limit remixing to materials and genres, Irvine proposes a
               semiotic model, drawing on the work of C.S. Peirce, to demonstrate the generative,
               dialogic, and recursive nature of all meaning making. If we accept remixing as
               inherent to all types of expression, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#irvine2014">then the <emph>material form</emph> of
                     an expression appears as a <emph>moment of orchestrated combinatoriality</emph>
                     in the ongoing interpretive, collective, meaning-making processes that
                     necessarily precede and follow it</quote>
                  <ref target="#irvine2014">Irvine 2014, 33 [italics are mine]</ref>
               </cit>. Aesopic fables and commentary, as they appear within particular manuscripts
               and printed books, operate as orchestrated compilations, which both recognize and
               challenge its predecessors, inviting future readers to do the same. Irvine suggests
               that his semiotic model for remix <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#irvine2014">can counter misrecognitions about
                     original authorship and proprietary artifacts that sustain copyright law and
                     confuse the popular understanding of Remix as something outside the normative
                     and necessary structures of meaning-making in ordinary, daily
                     expression</quote>
                  <ptr target="#irvine2014" loc="33"/>
               </cit>. For Irvine, our obsessions with copyright and ownership are based on
               erroneous conceptions about artistic originality and intellectual property, which
               undermine remixing as a creative act. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Mixing Flowers and Fruit in Fables</head>
            <p> The medieval expansion and canonization of Aesopic fables, for example, would have
               been impossible without the capacity to remix previous textual corpora. And in at
               least one sense, <q>mixing</q> and <q>appropriation</q> have always been central
               values of fable writing and reading. Take for instance the opening lines of the
               standard prologue to the <title rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title>, which employs
               horticultural language to express the ways in which fables are composed and then used
               by their readers: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#busdraghi2005">This present work ventures to be
                     pleasurable and useful; serious things are more alluring when they are
                     embellished with sport [Dulcius arrident seria picta iocis]. This garden brings
                     forth fruit with flowers. The flower and the fruit win favor, the one by its
                     flavor and the other by its beauty. If the fruit pleases you more than the
                     flower, select [lege] the fruit; if the flower more than the fruit, select the
                     flower; if both, take [carpe] both</quote>
                  <ptr target="#busdraghi2005" loc="1–6"/>
               </cit>.<note>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#busdraghi2005">Ut iuvet et prosit conatur pagina
                     presens: / dulcius arrident seria picta iocis. / Ortulus iste parit fructum cum
                     flore, favorem / flos et fructus emunt: hic sapit, ille nitet. / Si fructus
                     plus flore placet, fructum lege, si flos / plus fructu, florem, si duo, carpe
                     duo.</quote>
               </note> This textual enterprise mixes the serious with the playful, and more
               precisely the serious <soCalled>embellished</soCalled> by the playful. The Latin used
               here is <q>picta,</q> which would normally refer to something <q>painted,</q>
               implying that the sport inherent in fable telling serves as a veneer for what lies
               underneath. Yet, the fruit (the serious message) is not privileged over the flower
               (the aesthetic attributes of the fables). Instead, the fabulist uses the verbs
                  <q>lege</q> [select] and <q>carpe</q> [take] to explain what readers might do to
               the fable text, taking either the fruit or the flower, or both. While we might expect
               that readers would select particular aspects of a text to take away, the writer
               perceives the material as an open source, in which <q>both</q> or <q>all</q> may be
               taken. This acknowledgement of the entirety and variety of produce that might be
               harvested from the text suggests that appropriation is a textual act expected of the
               fable reader.</p>
            <p> One reader who embraced this fable thievery was Robert Henryson. In his own version
               of the Romulan prologue, Henryson offers the following line, translated almost
               directly from his source: <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">And clerkis
                  sayis, it is richt profitabill / Amangis ernist to ming ane merie sport</quote>
               [And clerks say that it is very profitable to mix merry sport amongst serious things]
                  <ptr target="#fox1981" loc="20–21"/>. By claiming that he learned this mantra from
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">clerkis,</quote> he characterizes the
                  <title rend="italic">elegiac Romulus</title> as a collection collaboratively
               compiled by a number of unnamed authorities. Perhaps more interestingly, he alters
               the relationship between <q>sport</q> and <q>ernist</q> [serious things] slightly,
               moving away from the Latin <q>seria picta iocis,</q> or <q>sport painted upon serious
                  matter,</q> towards a more balanced <q>mix,</q> the result of Henryson’s <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">to ming.</quote> He appears to endorse
               appropriation and remixing as characteristics of fable writing, but his next use of
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">ming</quote> a few lines later is
               accompanied by a direct citation of a singular authority. <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#fox1981"><l> With sad materis sum merines to ming</l>
                     <l> Accordis weill; thus Esope said, I wis,</l>
                     <l> Dulcius arrident seria picta iocis.</l></quote>
                  <ptr target="#fox1981" loc="26–28"/>
               </cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#fox1981">[It is fitting to mix some merriments with
                  solemn matters; indeed Aesop said so. Serious things are more alluring when
                  embellished with sport.]</quote> By naming Aesop, Henryson recognizes the aura of
               his fabular object and reflexively remixes his source material, distilling the vast
               number of compilators and commentators who contributed to the <title rend="italic"
                  >elegiac Romulus</title> into the authority of a single author. </p>
            <p>On the one hand, it was conventional to cite Aesop as the origin for fables, but on
               the other, Henryson had just attributed the sentiment of mixing <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#henryson1571">merry sport amongst serious things</quote> to anonymous
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">clerkis.</quote> Aesop was a
               particularly elusive author to pin down since he was considered to be the singular
               progenitor of beast fables, all the while performing the <q>author-function</q> for a
               host of fabular authors and commentators. Even though the phenomenon of hanging a
               corpus on the name of an <foreign xml:lang="la">auctor</foreign>, such as Cato, was
               fairly common among medieval school authors, even Cato’s <title rend="italic"
                  >Distichs</title> was not attributable to other identifiable authors in the ways
               that beast fables were associated with multiple Aesopic authors such as Phaedrus and
               Avianus <ptr target="#huygens1970"/>
               <ptr target="#minnis1988"/>.<note> Compare, for example, the discussion of Cato as
                  author of the <title rend="italic">Distichs</title> to the discussion of Avianus
                  as an Aesopic author in the <title rend="italic">Accessus ad auctores</title>
                  <ptr target="#huygens1970"/>. For an English translation, see <title rend="italic"
                     >Medieval Literary Theory and Criticism c. 1100-c. 1375</title>
                  <ptr target="#minnis1988"/>.</note> In an act of excessive homage, Henryson
               recites three different versions of the same Romulan phrase within the space of ten
               lines. In the first instance, he offers a fairly faithful rendering of the aphorism,
               making just one significant substitution: rather than translate <q>dulcius</q> as
                  <q>sweeter</q> or <q>more alluring,</q> he selects <q>richt profitabill</q> [very
               profitable], which privileges the moral profit of the fables over their aesthetic
               delights. The second version, however, offers a more qualified perspective than the
               first: rather than suggest that any kind of frivolity may be mixed with serious
               things, he tweaks it slightly, saying <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571"
                  >With sad materis sum merines to ming</quote> [to mix some merriments with solemn
               matters]. As if he is dissatisfied with either translation, his third version is the
               original Latin line itself: <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">Dulcius
                  arrident seria picta iocis.</quote> While this kind of translation and citation
               might seem egregiously repetitive, this redundancy reflects the redundant nature of
               many fable collections, which offered multiple versions of the same fable in the same
               manuscript <ptr target="#codex303"/>.<note> For example, one fourteenth-century
                  Austrian manuscript, Codex Vindobonensis Palatinus 303 is a veritable cornucopia
                  of Aesopica, containing six different versions, and even one set, known as the
                     <title rend="italic">prose Romulus</title>, appears twice.</note> Henryson may
               have been influenced by his immersion in this pedagogical tradition, but it is also
               important to note that his three renderings of the line cleverly mimic the three
               levels of appropriation encouraged by the Romulan prologue: selecting one, or
               selecting another, or taking the whole thing. Understood this way, Henryson first
               takes the fruit, next takes the flower, and then, having decided he wants them both,
               he takes both, offering his own remix of the Aesopic mantra.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Aesopic Mashups in the Early Age of Print</head>
            <p> In addition to serving as a source for Henryson to sample and remix, the medieval
               fable offered practice in literary amplification and collaborative constructions of
               knowledge that set the stage for the fifteenth- and sixteenth-century printers of
               Aesop, who attempted to codify their editions through compilation, or what could be
               likened to the digital mashup. Within remix culture, the mashup is an aesthetic mode
               that combines two or more discrete and recognizable artistic products (e.g. images,
               sounds, words) to extend or elaborate upon their meaning or significance. One of the
               best examples in the world of music is Danger Mouse’s <title rend="italic">Grey
                  Album</title>, which is a mashup of Jay-Z’s <title rend="italic">Black
                  Album</title> and the Beatles’ <title rend="italic">White Album</title>. In the
               case of early printers, they combined previously disparate series of fables,
               commentaries, and images into single editions, expecting readers to play an active
               role in their reception and interpretation. </p>
            <p>Henryson’s adoption of remixing as a central fabular practice also encouraged his
               early readers and illustrators to appropriate his text in kind. One manuscript in
               particular, British Library MS Harley 3865, is an intriguing case in point because it
               is a handwritten copy/adaptation of the 1571 Bassandyne print, published
               approximately a century after Henryson likely composed it [ca. 1485] <ptr
                  target="#harley3865"/>
               <ptr target="#henryson1571"/>.<note> For more on the dating of the manuscript and its
                  relationship to printed editions, see Fox’s discussion in <title rend="italic">The
                     Poems of Robert Henryson</title>, lii-lxiv, especially lix-lxiv.</note> The
               handcrafted illumination that accompanies the fable, <title rend="quotes">The
                  Preaching of the Swallow,</title> presents a scene that serves as a mashup of
               previous elements from a variety of previously published woodcut images (<ref
                  target="#figure02">fig. 2</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>The illustration that accompanies Robert Henryson’s <title rend="quotes">The
                        Preaching of the Swallow</title> © British Library Board, Harley MS 3865,
                     43v.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a man on a pedestal, birds atop a tree, and a hand holding a
                     bird.</figDesc>
               </figure> To begin to comprehend the peculiar nature of this copied/adapted
               illustration, a brief summary of the fable is in order: The narrator, happening upon
               a flock of birds gathering around a swallow perched in a hawthorn tree, hides behind
               a hedge to listen to their conversation. Warning fellow birds to dig up the hempen
               seed that a fowler has just sown, the swallow predicts that these seeds will
               eventually become the rope that the fowler will use to fashion a net, which he will
               then use to catch and kill the birds that feed on the crops. Mocking the swallow’s
               prudence, the birds ignore her advice and allow the seeds to germinate in the soil. A
               year passes and the narrator returns to the scene to find the seeds have now sprouted
               short stalks, which the swallow again implores the birds to pull up. Spurning her
               counsel once again, the birds allow the stalks to grow to full bloom, until the
               fowler harvests them to construct a net. He places the net on the ground and casts
               fresh seed for the birds to eat. For the third time the swallow warns the birds, but
               they greedily devour the new seed as the fowler catches them up in his net and kills
               them. Henryson offers an allegory for this fable, in which the swallow represents a
               preacher, who warns his flock (the birds) against the entrapments of the devil (the
               fowler). </p>
            <p>Given the presence of the human preacher at the pulpit and the gaggle of birds in the
               tree, it is clear that the Harley illustrator tried to accommodate both literal and
               allegorical elements of the fable. This conflation might seem appropriate for a genre
               heavily inflected by allegory, but this combination of two interpretive modes is
               actually a radical departure from the standard image that would accompany this fable,
               which depicts the fowler casting seed in view of the swallow and the birds (<ref
                  target="#figure03">fig. 3</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>The woodcut that accompanies <title rend="quotes">De hyrundine et ceteris
                        auibus</title> in Steinhöwel's <title rend="italic">Aesop</title> (Basel:
                     Jacob von Pfortzheim, 1501).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of birds and a man.</figDesc>
               </figure> The unique nature of the Harley illustration might motivate us to call it
               an <soCalled>original</soCalled> creation, but upon further inspection, it would be
               more appropriately called a <q>reflexive mashup</q> of other previously published
               Aesopic figures. Navas defines the reflexive mashup as a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#navas2012">form [that] uses samples from two or more
                     elements to access specific information more efficiently, thereby taking them
                     beyond their initial possibilities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#navas2012" loc="93"/>
               </cit>. To understand how this illustration operates as a reflexive mashup, the
               printing history of these Aesopic images must be carefully considered. </p>
            <p>I want to suggest that three of the elements of the Harley illustration, the bird in
               the hand, the preacher at a pulpit (that looks more like a pedestal), and the
               disembodied head on the hill (lower left corner), were redrawn as imitations of
               symbols that originate in the standard frontispiece to the earliest printed book of
               fables, first compiled by Heinrich Steinhöwel in 1476, which contained not only the
               standard Latin fables of the medieval curriculum, but also their German translations
                  <ptr target="#carnes1986" loc="4"/> (<ref target="#figure04">fig. 4</ref>).
                  <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>Frontispiece to Steinhöwel's <title rend="italic">Aesop</title> (Basel:
                     Jacob von Pfortzheim, 1501).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of a fowler.</figDesc>
               </figure> The frontispiece that serves as the primary source for the Harley
               illustrator, however, was not Steinhöwel’s edition, but rather that of Thomas
               Bassandyne, the resemblances of which are clear through visual comparison (<ref
                  target="#figure05">fig. 5</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>Frontispiece to Bassandyne’s edition of Henryson’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Morall Fabillis</title> (Edinburgh, 1571).<note> This frontispiece image
                        has been retrieved from the National Library of Scotland, <ref
                           target="http://digital.nls.uk/morall-fabillis-of-esope-the-phyrgian/pageturner.cfm?id=74507412"
                           >http://digital.nls.uk/morall-fabillis-of-esope-the-phyrgian/pageturner.cfm?id=74507412</ref>.</note></head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of a man with <q>ESOPVS</q> printed at top and <q>EDINBVRGH</q>
                     printed at bottom.</figDesc>
               </figure> In the lower right hand corner is a clear depiction of the bird in the hand
               and in the lower left hand corner a preacher in pulpit-pedestal can be spotted
               adjacent to the lower left edge of Aesop’s toga. A head on a hill is not readily
               apparent in this frontispiece, but a man falling down an embankment can be seen to
               the left of the pulpit-pedestal. </p>
            <p> Let us consider first the preacher in the pulpit-pedestal, which is the most
               striking and complicated image in the Harley illustration. While the preaching figure
               matches exactly the preacher in Bassandyne’s frontispiece, Bassandyne’s preacher
               differs significantly from Steinhöwel’s statuesque man atop the pedestal that
               occupies the same position on the page. We know this figure to be Aesop because many
               of the images represented in Steinhöwel’s frontispiece refer directly to scenes in
               the <title rend="italic">Vita Aesopi</title> that commonly prefaced fable collections
               after the thirteenth century and served as the source for Caxton’s <title
                  rend="italic">Aesop</title>. The episode in question, in which the Babylonian King
               constructs a statue in Aesop’s honor, is also illustrated in one of Steinhöwel’s
               other woodcuts (<ref target="#figure06">fig. 6</ref>), as is the case for most of the
               images that appear in the frontispiece. <figure xml:id="figure06">
                  <head>Illustration of the Babylonian King's creation of a statue of Aesop in
                     Steinhöwel's <title rend="italic">Aesop</title> (Basel: Jacob von Pfortzheim,
                     1501).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of small man on pedestal and two figures nearby.</figDesc>
               </figure> In this sense, this titular collage of Aesopic images serves as a visual
               index for the illustrations to come. We can easily imagine, for example, a hypertext
               version of the frontispiece, in which the viewer would click the images to gain
               access to episodes in the life of Aesop. Henryson’s fables, however, do not include
               the <title rend="italic">Vita Aesopi</title>, making the Bassandyne frontispiece a
               partial homage (or an orphaned link, if you will) to Steinhöwel’s woodcuts. The
               preacher in the pulpit-pedestal, which appears to originate in the Bassandyne
               edition, complicates this reflexive relationship to the Steinhöwel frontispiece and
               recasts Aesop on the pedestal as a preacher, who will appear in a remediated form in
               the <title rend="quotes">Preaching of the Swallow</title> fable that appears in
               Henryson’s collection. The Harley illustrator, by contrast, viewed the titular
               collage less as a set of premodern hyperlinks to prior or subsequent Aesopic texts
               than as raw material to be <soCalled>photo-shopped</soCalled> for a new use. In the
               case of Henryson’s fable, the actual appearance of Aesop at a pulpit-pedestal would
               have seemed entirely appropriate, particularly because of his direct invocation at
               the outset of the <foreign xml:lang="la">moralitas</foreign>, in which he is
               described as a <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571">nobill clerk . . . [a]ne
                  poet worthie to be lawreate</quote> [noble clerk . . . a poet worthy to be a
               laureate] who composed this fable for <quote rend="inline" source="#henryson1571"
                  >gude morall edificatioun</quote> [good moral edification] <ptr target="#fox1981"
                  loc="1893"/>. The tension identified earlier in Henryson’s prologue – between
               fables produced by many anonymous clerks and a singular Aesop – emerges again, this
               time in a vexed attempt to cast laurels on the fable. This shift in textual authority
               from the multiple clerical collaborators to classroom <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >auctor</foreign> is dramatized in the Harley illustration, which includes an
               accretive figure that is a swallow, a preacher, and finally Aesop himself. </p>
            <p> The third remixed element of the Harley illustration, the disembodied head, is
               perhaps the most peculiar contributor to this increasing tension between multiple and
               singular models of authorship. Given the fact that the head is bereft of any
               discernible body and lacking the color of other figures in the illustration, it is
               easy to overlook. It is quite possible, in fact, that the illustrator remained
               undecided about what to do with this head, leaving it unfinished. After all, the only
               reasonable explanation for its existence is its juxtaposition with what appears to be
               the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#fox1981">hedge</quote>
                  <ptr target="#fox1981" loc="1729"/>
               </cit> that the narrator hides behind in order to eavesdrop on this parliament of
               fowls. The insertion of a witness into a fable is a departure from the conventions of
               the genre and a complication of point of view that Henryson champions throughout his
               collection. Despite his deferral to Aesop's authority throughout his fables, Henryson
               consistently asserts himself as an interpretive interloper in one way or another. The
               Harley illustrator seemed to sense the authorial conflict represented by a narrative
               figure who could threaten the credibility and coherence of Aesop, the
               well-established author of the fable. As a possible compromise, the illustrator
               returns to the frontispiece, but this time to a low point in Aesop’s life, his
               violent demise – or what we might view as an allegorical or Barthean moment of
               authorial death. This image of a man falling down a hill is actually an illustration
               of Aesop being tossed over a cliff, an episode from the <title rend="italic">Vita
                  Aesopi</title> absent from Henryson’s fables and the Bassandyne print (<ref
                  target="#figure07">fig. 7</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure07">
                  <head>Illustration of Aesop's death in Steinhöwel's <title rend="italic"
                        >Aesop</title> (Basel: Jacob von Pfortzheim, 1501).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut of a falling man.</figDesc>
               </figure> The correspondence between the two images in their entirety, a floating
               head and a prostrate body, are not convincing replicas of each other, but if we
               examine the position of Aesop’s body in relationship to his statue, we can see that
               his head is placed in a similar position as the disembodied head, both situated below
               the pulpit-pedestal. If we are expected to associate these two images, a crisis of
               textual authority arises because the head behind the hedge would presumably be the
               narrator or Henryson, himself. Furthermore, his disembodiment, and arguably his
               botched erasure from the scene, reflects an attempt by the illustrator to privilege
               the figure of the preacher Aesop, a figure who would increasingly become the
               exclusive author of all beast fables.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Aesop’s Grotesque Body in an Early Age of Print Reproduction</head>
            <p> During the latter part of the fifteenth century when Henryson was composing his
               fables, the Aesopic corpus experienced a transformation that coincided with the
               arrival of the printing press. This newly mechanized system of textual production
               witnessed a division and dismemberment of fable collections into discrete textual
               traditions, now available in a variety of vernaculars, including English, French,
               German, and Italian. Printers were then faced with the daunting prospect of
               distilling a highly dynamic and encyclopedic genre, which contained multiple sets and
               variations of fables and their commentaries, into a reproducible form that could be
               easily absorbed by a new reading public. Despite Aesop’s new public façade, readers
               were increasingly faced with what Benjamin called <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#benjamin1968">graduated and hierarchized mediation,</quote> still a far
               cry from his description of the state of the press in the late-nineteenth century, in
               which <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin1968">an increasing number of readers became
                     writers</quote>
                  <ptr target="#benjamin1968" loc="235, 232"/>
               </cit>. Rather, I would suggest, this unstable moment of transition in the fifteenth
               century between script and print led to increasing efforts to contain the authorial
               aura of Aesop, which can be witnessed in the changing nature of descriptions and
               illustrations of his physical body. And even more fascinatingly, this corporeal
               transformation is accompanied by attempts to consolidate the widely varied and
               dynamic fable corpora into a singular and reproducible Aesopic corpus. </p>
            <p>One text mentioned at the outset of this essay that was often retained from earlier
               manuscripts, but absent in the Bassandyne Henryson, was the biographical <title
                  rend="italic">Vita Aesopi</title>, the standard preface to the curricular fables,
               which provides a surprisingly monstrous illustration of Aesop's physical body, as
               recounted by Caxton (see above, paragraph 8). It is no accident, of course, that
               Caxton’s striking description matches the figure of Aesop in Steinhöwel’s
               frontispiece to the fables, crafted only eight years earlier. Perhaps more than any
               other depiction of Aesop, this humpbacked barefoot giant could be described as
               grotesque, incompatible with the traditional image of the classical author
               represented in Romanesque sculpture. Furthermore, his status as a venerated medieval
               classroom authority is belied by what is described in the text as his initial
               stuttering of a language comprehensible only to himself, an impediment that
               highlights the corporeality of poetic production and threatens the very possibility
               of an Aesopic literary corpus. </p>
            <p> As printed Aesops were reproduced over time, the grotesque corporeal features of
               Aesop became increasingly difficult to detect. For example, if we turn to the 1571
               frontispiece of the Bassandyne print of Robert Henryson’s fables, we find a more
               normalized authorial figure (see <ref target="resources/images/figure05.png">fig.
                  5</ref>). This more shapely Aesop is still, however, an odd match for Henryson’s
               own physical description of the fabulist that appears in his <title rend="quotes">The
                  Lion and the Mouse</title> fable. The narrator even goes so far as to present
               Aesop as the most beautiful man he had ever seen <ptr target="#fox1981" loc="1348"/>: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#fox1981"><l>His gowne wes off ane claith als quhyte
                        as milk,</l>
                     <l>His chymmeris wes off chambelate purpour broun,</l>
                     <l>His hude off scarlet, bordowrit weill with silk</l>
                     <l>On hekillit wyis untill his girdill doun,</l>
                     <l>His bonat round, and off the auld fassoun,</l>
                     <l>His beird wes quhyte, his ene wes grit and gray,</l>
                     <l>With lokker hair quhilk over his schulderis lay.</l></quote>
                  <ptr target="#fox1981" loc="1349–55"/>
               </cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#henryson1571">[His gown was of a cloth as white as milk,
                  his shirt was of a deep purple fabric, his hood was scarlet, bordered skillfully
                  with silk, fringed unto his girdle below, his bonnet was round like the old
                  fashion, his beard was white, his eyes were large and grey, with curly hair which
                  lay over his shoulders.]</quote> While we can easily identify the <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#travis2011">spectacular aura</quote> of the corporeal
               metamorphosis between the Aesops that appear in the frontispieces of the Steinhöwel
               (1476) and the Bassandyne (1571) printed editions, Henryson’s bearded and grey-eyed
               Aesop bears no likeness to the bumbling <quote rend="inline" source="#travis2011"
                  >disruptive anti-hero</quote> of Caxton’s <title rend="italic">Aesop</title>
               <ptr target="#travis2011" loc="46"/>. </p>
            <p> Like the insertion of disparate graphical features of Aesop into the remixed Harley
               illustration of <title rend="quotes">The Preaching of the Swallow,</title> Henryson’s
               introduction of a curly-haired fabulist is a symptom of a growing conflict between
               competing notions of textual authority in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries. On
               the one hand, textual and visual fabular corpora had largely been open sources, ripe
               for conversion for new uses and audiences. On the other, the encyclopedic
               accumulation and expansion of fable collections required printers to develop
               editorial apparatus to create an appearance of textual control. In Henryson, this
               tension is palpable, simultaneously acknowledging appropriation as a core value of
               fabular production while offering a singular model of authorship through a beautified
               Aesop. Moreover, it is hardly a coincidence that the physical body of Aesop
               experiences a dramatic makeover at the same time that the Aesopic corpus becomes
               increasingly codified and closed.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Corporate Textuality and the Aesopic Commons</head>
            <p> As the Harley illustrator demonstrates through a remixing of manuscript and print
               technologies, it would be enormously reductive and technologically deterministic to
               conclude that the printing press ushered in this move towards singular authorship and
               literary property. After all, the Aesopic corpus experienced a number of educational
               and political transformations throughout the late-sixteenth and seventeenth
               centuries, as can be witnessed in the printed editions of John Brinsely (1617 and
               1624), John Ogilby (1651 and 1668), Sir Roger L’Estrange (1692), and Jean de la
               Fontaine (1668-94) <ptr target="#patterson1991"/>
               <ptr target="#blake2017" loc="13–28"/>. Within late-seventeenth-century pedagogical
               discourse, however, we begin to see less of an emphasis on fable interpretation and
               more of a focus on the fable itself, particularly as it would relate to childhood
               development <ptr target="#lerer2008" loc="104–28"/>. And throughout the subsequent
               centuries, Aesopica would play a central role within the development of the speaking
               animal tale of children’s literature, a progenitor for Lewis Carroll’s <title
                  rend="italic">Alice in Wonderland</title> (1865) and Kenneth Grahame’s <title
                  rend="italic">The Wind in the Willows</title> (1908). By the mid-twentieth
               century, the effacement of the fabular interpretative tradition had become so acute
               that the classicist Lloyd W. Daly could publish a collection entitled <title
                  rend="italic">Aesop Without Morals</title>, an English translation of the fables
               with their morals relegated to an appendix, much in the manner of answers in the back
               of a schoolbook <ptr target="#daly1961" loc="267–307"/>. Condemning the simple
               one-line morals as an <quote rend="inline" source="#daly1961">encumbrance</quote> and <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#daly1961">little more than an insult to our
                     intelligence</quote>
                  <ptr target="#daly1961" loc="12"/>
               </cit>, Daly offers the fables in isolation as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#daly1961">mirror[s] of self-reflection</quote>
                  <ptr target="#daly1961" loc="11"/>
               </cit>. While he acknowledges the variability of the Aesopic tradition, he refers to
               the fables as both a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#daly1961">literary product</quote>
                  <ptr target="#daly1961" loc="12"/>
               </cit> and a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#daly1961">floating, common property</quote>
                  <ptr target="#daly1961" loc="15"/>
               </cit>, suggesting that the fables are designed to promote individual intellectual
               development. By unmooring the fables from their morals, Daly’s fables
                  <soCalled>float</soCalled> as unified objects of reflection, affording them a
               romantic completeness that suggests that their artistic evolution had come to an end.
               Aesop’s fables could now become common products designed for select, private, and
               individual consumption. </p>
            <p> While we might be tempted to view Daly’s <soCalled>amoral</soCalled> approach as
               idiosyncratic, even more recent editions, such as Olivia and Robert Temple’s <title
                  rend="italic">Aesop: The Complete Fables</title> (1998), reflect this modern
               tendency to reduce Aesop to a containable property. As a Penguin paperback designed
               for the mass market, the translators bypass the unruly medieval Latin tradition
               entirely and rely exclusively on Émile Chambry’s 1927 edition of the Greek prose
               fables. They justify their choice in a <title rend="quotes">Note on the Text</title>
               this way: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aesop1998">We have taken Chambry’s text to represent
                     the <soCalled>complete</soCalled> fables for the purposes of this volume,
                     although every scholar would probably alter the text by taking away some and
                     adding others according to his or her own personal choices . . . the
                        <soCalled>complete fables of Aesop</soCalled> is whatever the editor of its
                     Greek text chooses to say it is</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aesop1998" loc="xxiv"/>
               </cit>. By claiming that the <soCalled>completeness</soCalled> of the corpus – the
               qualifying scare-quotes of which are eliminated in the title and back cover
               description of the edition – is determined by the editor, Aesop becomes a commodified
               property with boundary lines that are defined by <soCalled>personal
                  choices</soCalled> and particular <soCalled>purposes,</soCalled> euphemisms for
               market demands that ride on hyperbolic claims such as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aesop1998">the first translation <hi rend="italic"
                        >ever</hi> to make available the complete corpus</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aesop1998" loc="back cover"/>
               </cit>. This contention relies upon both the denigration of Aesopic authors such as
               Babrius and Phaedrus, whom Robert Temple calls <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aesop1998">second- or third-rate adapters</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aesop1998" loc="xviii"/>
               </cit>, and the devaluation of the dynamic commentary tradition, represented by some <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aesop1998">appalling, even idiotic</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aesop1998" loc="xv"/>
               </cit> morals that the Temples separate from the fables. Such an attempt to purify
               the Aesopic corpus from its grotesque literary history and messy commentary tradition
               effectively makes Aesop a property defined by mass-market aims and idiosyncratic
               editorial limitations. </p>
            <p> This transformation of Aesop from literary body to literary property, I want to
               suggest, represents the way open source material, particularly creative work produced
               before (or outside of the restrictions of) copyright, can become consolidated and
               redefined as intellectual <soCalled>property,</soCalled> often at the expense of its
               corporeal identity, as well as its free and <soCalled>open</soCalled> use. Consider
               the example of incunabules, the first texts printed during the latter half of the
               fifteenth century. While these printed volumes are often available to the public
               within rare book archives, most of us only know incunabules through their
               availability via the online database, <title rend="italic">Early English Books
                  Online</title> (EEBO 2003-2017). Produced centuries before the introduction of
               copyright, these books were regarded as open sources that scholars could easily
               reproduce and use without restriction . . . until 2011. The terms of service
               developed by ProQuest, the publishing company that owns <title rend="italic"
                  >EEBO</title>, now state: <quote rend="inline" source="#EEBO2017">The electronic
                  versions of any public domain works that may be included in EEBO are the copyright
                  of ProQuest LLC. For all works in the collection, the printing or saving of texts
                  is permitted only for private or educational use. Further reproduction is
                  prohibited.</quote> This attempt by ProQuest to control an entire digitized corpus
               of microfilmed early editions demonstrates how far we have moved away from the
               corporeal nature of textual production, in which hands and bodies produce, embody,
               and perform texts <ptr target="#boyle2012" loc="2"/>. And to some extent, even the
               early association of books with libraries perpetuated this shift. As Michael Camille
               suggests, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#camille1997">The whole history, development, and, to
                     some extent, the institutional aims of the modern library have been to exclude
                     the body from the site of reading, to make a silent desomatized optics of the
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">biblioteca</foreign> the simulacrum of purely mental
                     experience, a process that will only accelerate in the future with the
                     increasing incorporeality of the electronic word</quote>
                  <ptr target="#camille1997" loc="40"/>
               </cit>. Within the recent emergence of digital libraries, texts have migrated even
               further from the body to become consolidated into the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >loci</foreign> of databases, hidden behind the most indulgent proprietary fantasy
               of all: the <soCalled>paywall.</soCalled> To protect the online value of these
               intellectual properties, publishers have erected password-protected screens that
               require readers to pay a premium for full access to content. Blaming the decline of
               print subscription and advertisement, scholarly journals and the news media justify
               the blocking of free access as their only means of revenue generation. The paywall is
               also a proprietary metaphor that reveals the foundation of many institutions that
               produce knowledge, from the university to the newsroom: an artificial barrier that
               creates scarcity, enhances value, and accumulates capital. Moreover, the forms of
               access the paywall regulates are unevenly distributed across universities, and even
               across fields in ways that map onto the unequal structures of funding that have come
               to define the modern university. In this sense, the paywall not only offers a means
               toward understanding how the contemporary university has become an engine of
               inequality, but also contributes to it directly.<note> I am indebted to my colleague
                  Emilio Sauri for these observations about the social function of the paywall and
                  its effects on access within higher education.</note> Given the high institutional
               cost of subscribing to EEBO, ProQuest perverts the Romulan <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#canonical">take both</quote> mantra in order to recast this incunabular
               body as a an intellectual property whose doors are closed to many users. It is
               locked, fixed, monetized, and controlled by a singular entity, a move presaged by
               Aesopic printers and modern editors, who increasingly consolidated Aesop’s expandable
               corpus into one classical figure.</p>
            <p> Many have now joined the <soCalled>open access revolution,</soCalled> which seeks to
               resist the increasing author-facing charges and subscription fees imposed by academic
               publishers. Yet, even for digital initiatives such as the Text Creation Partnership
               (TCP), which creates freely available XML/SGML encoded editions of a number of early
               printed books, including those on EEBO, the access to the books is limited to their
               textual transcriptions. And while the EEBO-TCP is enormously valuable for
               cross-corpus searching, lexicographical study, and textual analysis, these printed
               codices are effectively reduced to data, alphabetic texts that have shed their
               codicological features. These <soCalled>books</soCalled> are now encoded text files
               of digital scans available on EEBO, which are, themselves, de-somaticized images of
               individual pages from early printed books. As Rebecca Welzenbach notes, for users <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#welzenbach2011">who want to quickly get at the
                     content of the texts, not work with the data itself, XML files are not useful
                     unless they are indexed by a search engine and presented in a web
                     interface</quote>
                  <ptr target="#welzenbach2011" loc="5"/>
               </cit>. By reducing them to data, the physical features of the books that are
               represented visually on EEBO – namely, the marginalia, the illustrations, the textual
               layouts, the fonts, and even handwritten corrections – are eliminated, effectively
               stripped of the corporeal traces of author, printer, or reader. The texts are now
               available to be transmitted to new locations and uploaded to new interfaces: EEBO-TCP
               users are even encouraged <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#welzenbach2011">not to worry about where they
                     discover the data, but where it comes from</quote>
                  <ptr target="#welzenbach2011" loc="12"/>
               </cit>. While the TCP clearly provides a valuable resource for many digital humanists
               and early book scholars, it also perpetuates the increasingly proprietary character
               of the digital book, which has become defined more by <q>where</q> we find it, than
                  <q>who</q> created it or <q>what</q> it is. For example, Henryson is not even
               listed as the author of the <title rend="italic">Morall Fabillis</title> on
               EEBO-TCP’s <q>Author</q> browse feature. Instead the credit is given to Aesop, yet
               another example of the consolidation of this corpus into one authorial figure <ptr
                  target="#EEBO-TCP2003"/>. More importantly, these text files are in danger of
               becoming metonyms for the books themselves, just one member of the corpus standing in
               for all. </p>
            <p> From the perspective of Aesopic poets and early humanists like Henryson, this
               privileging of one member of a corpus (i.e. one author, one text) at the expense of
               the others (i.e. illustrators, commentators, etc.) would have seemed inimical to the
               common good, especially to many in the fifteenth century who had been thoroughly
               schooled in Ciceronian notions of the body politic. In his <title rend="italic">De
                  Officiis</title>, Cicero uses a corporeal metaphor to describe the danger of
               self-interested proprietary claims: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cicero1947">Suppose, by way of comparison, that each
                     one of our bodily members should conceive this idea and imagine that it could
                     be strong and well if it should draw off to itself the health and strength of
                     its neighboring member, the whole body would necessarily be enfeebled and die;
                     so if each one of us should seize upon the property of his neighbors and take
                     from each whatever he could appropriate to his own use, the bonds of human
                     society must inevitably be annihilated</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cicero1947" loc="3.5.22"/>
               </cit>.<note>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cicero1947">Ut, si unum quodque membrum sensum hunc
                     haberet, ut posse putaret se valere, si proximi membri valetudinem ad se
                     traduxisset, debilitari et interire totum corpus necesse esset, sic, si unus
                     quisque nostrum ad se rapiat commoda aliorum detrahatque quod cuique possit,
                     emolumenti sui gratia, societas hominum et communitas evertatur necesse
                     est.</quote></note> For Cicero, if the act of appropriation itself can be
               appropriated and limited to one member, the communal body cannot thrive. His
               insistence on the body as a symbol of a republic is, in turn, replicated in the fable
                  <title rend="quotes">The Belly and the Members</title> that became a central
               feature in many Aesopic collections, including the <title rend="italic">elegiac
                  Romulus</title> and Caxton’s <title rend="italic">Aesop</title>, as well as a
               contentious political metaphor in England for the relationship between a monarch and
               her subjects throughout the seventeenth century <ptr target="#patterson1991"
                  loc="111–37"/>. Henry Turner calls this hierarchical conflict <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#turner2006">the problem of the <q>more-than-one,</q></quote> or the
               tension between the part and the whole, as well as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#turner2006">the laws and power necessary to regulate
                     relationships among people and the values that justify this regulation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#turner2006" loc="416–417"/>
               </cit>. Just as this conflict arises for artists caught between the protections of
               copyright law and the free culture of the creative commons, this struggle is palpable
               for Henryson and his contemporaries, who were caught in the cradle of their
               incunabular moment, vying with printers for their share of the marketplace. According
               to Turner, this contention gave rise to the sixteenth century
                  <soCalled>corporation,</soCalled> which attempted to actualize the corporeal
               identity of political and knowledge communities: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#turner2006">At once an <q>artificial person</q> and
                     a fictive community, the corporation is both <q>one</q> and <q>many,</q>
                     enjoying rights and freedoms that are simultaneously rights of persons and
                     rights of collectivities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#turner2006" loc="427n46"/>
               </cit>. As both a singular figure and a textual community of authors and
               commentators, the medieval Aesop serves as a prototype of the early modern
               corporation and a representative an intellectual gift economy, in which scholarly or
               artistic work is transparently shared and used. But just as medieval practices of
               appropriation have become exploited for privatized and monetized within digital
               databases, the corporation has become too often an entity that immunizes stakeholders
               against risks at the exclusion of others.</p>
            <p> Even if we were to agree to reclaim the corporeal nature of intellectual work, how
               might we move beyond the proprietary language that grips our conception of a
                  <q>creative commons</q>? On the one hand, if we perceive of a creative commons as
               shared property, appropriation cannot exist. We cannot appropriate what is already
                  <soCalled>proper</soCalled> to us. If, on the other hand, we agree with Roberto
               Esposito that our understanding of the commons is <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#esposito2010">the totality of persons united not by a <q>property</q> but
                  precisely by an obligation or a debt,</quote> then any assertion of subjectivity
               or interpretation cannot exist either <ptr target="#esposito2010" loc="6"/>. Any
               contribution to the community is defined by a duty to be performed, not the
               participation of a desiring subject. The opposite of community, for Esposito, is
               immunity, which negates any participation or indebted fulfillment of office <ptr
                  target="#esposito2010" loc="6"/>. This cynical impulse drives restrictive claims
               to intellectual <soCalled>ownership</soCalled> championed by copyright attorneys and
               publishing corporations like ProQuest. Immunity opens the space for subjectivity, but
               it is exclusively hostile to any notion of a creative community.</p>
            <p> And while some communities, especially those that oppress others, should be subject
               to critique and sanction, creative communities cannot survive on cycles of
               destruction and immunization. If we want such artistic communities to thrive, we must
               reject, following Esposito, any understanding of community based in common property,
               since such a proprietary conception of knowledge production only leads to restrictive
               claims to intellectual property and copyright, which are often at odds with creative
               and interpretive practices, particularly within the contexts of Aesopic textuality
               and digital remix. We might go so far as to challenge the very use of the term
                  <q>appropriation,</q> or taking for one’s own what is proper to another, since
               this fundamentally suggests the use of someone else’s property. Yet, as postcolonial
               analyses have shown, even cultural appropriation may not be simply reduced to
                  <q>theft</q> and often becomes, as Kathleen M. Ashley and Véronique Plesch
               suggest, a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#ashley2002">two-way process, one in which exchange
                     and creative response may take place</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ashley2002" loc="6"/>
               </cit>. Such dialogic artistic practices may indeed operate as acts of <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#ingham2015">ambivalent <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                     >homage</foreign>,</quote> obscuring the language of property within the act of
               appropriation. </p>
            <p> Aesop’s fables and EEBO’s incunables are now available in more libraries and
               databases than ever before, but the cost of their massive distribution has been the
               gradual diminution of their corporeal character. Whereas Aesopica had been produced
               by multiple fabulists and commentators and early printed books had been mashed up by
               their readers and illustrators, these corpuses have increasingly become a <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#esposito2010">floating, common property</quote> and a
               textual landscape to be <soCalled>mined.</soCalled> Within the <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                  >longue durée</foreign> of remixing and the increased assertion of intellectual
               property rights, it is difficult to imagine a neo-Aesopic corporation through which
               appropriation and interpretation are no longer immunized, or without office. There
               may be, however, a <emph>munificent</emph> way to conceive of creative communities
               that synthesizes Esposito’s biopolitics with Turner’s theorization of the early
               modern <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#turner2016">group person</quote>
                  <ptr target="#turner2016"/>
               </cit>. As Esposito notes, the Latin root <foreign xml:lang="la">munus</foreign> of
               community can mean both an obligation and a gift. And while he goes to great lengths
               to reject the <q>voluntary</q> connotation of <foreign xml:lang="la">munus</foreign>
               by demonstrating the gift’s requirement of gratitude <ptr target="#esposito2010"
                  loc="4–5"/>, we only need to turn to the Aesopic invitation to <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#canonical">take both</quote> to find a communal body based
               in generosity, goodwill, and the production of new fabulists, such as Avianus, Marie
               de France, and Robert Henryson. This addition of <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >auctores</foreign> to Aesopica is a model of what we might call an articulated
               corporation, a singular artistic corpus that invites and accumulates new members.
               Within such a grotesque vision of artistic production, intellectual work is no longer
               a property to be owned, but a multi-membered body to be fed, nurtured, and
               continually reshaped and redressed for new occasions and new creators. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aesop1998" label="Aesop 1998"><title rend="italic">Aesop: The Complete
                  Fables</title>. Trans. Olivia and Robert Temple. New York: Penguin, 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ashley2002" label="Ashley and Plesch 2002">Ashley, Kathleen M. and
               Véronique Plesch. <title rend="quotes">The Cultural Processes of
                     <q>Appropriation.</q></title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies</title> 32.1
               (Winter 2002): 1-15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin1968" label="Benjamin 1968">Benjamin, Walter. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Illuminations</title>. Trans. Harry Zohn. Ed. Hannah Arendt.
               Shocken: New York, 1968. 217-51.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blake2017" label="Blake and Santos 2017">Blake, Liza and Kathryn Vomero
               Santos, eds. <title rend="italic">Arthur Golding’s A Moral Fabletalk and Other
                  Renaissance Fable Translations</title>. Cambridge: Modern Humanities Research
               Association, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bolens2000" label="Bolens 2000">Bolens, Guillemette. <title rend="italic"
                  >La Logique du Corps Articulaire: Les articulations du corps humain dans la
                  littérature occidentale</title>. Rennes: Presses Universitaires de Rennes,
               2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boyle2012" label="Boyle and Foys 2012">Boyle, Jen and Martin Foys. <title
                  rend="quotes">Becoming Media.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Postmedieval: A Journal of Medieval Cultural Studies</title> 3
               (2012): 1-6.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bruns1982" label="Bruns 1982">Bruns, Gerald. <title rend="italic"
                  >Inventions: Writing, Textuality, and Understanding in Literary History</title>.
               New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1982.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="busdraghi2005" label="Busdraghi 2005">Busdraghi, Paola, ed. <title
                  rend="italic">L'Esopus attribuito a Gualtero Anglico</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Favolisti Latini Medievali</title> X. Genoa, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="camille1997" label="Camille 1997">Camille, Michael. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Book as Flesh and Fetish in Richard de Bury’s <title rend="italic"
                     >Philobiblon</title>.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Book and the Body</title>. Ed. Dolores Warwick Frese and
               Katherine O’Brien O’Keeffe. University of Notre Dame Press: Notre Dame and London,
               1997. 34-77.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carnes1986" label="Carnes 1986">Carnes, Pack. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Heinrich Steinhöwel and the Sixteenth-Century Fable Tradition.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Humanistica Lovaniensia: A Journal of Neo-Latin Studies</title>
               35 (1986): 1-294.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="booksellers1666" label="The case of the booksellers and printers 1666"
                  ><title rend="italic">The case of the booksellers and printers stated with answers
                  to the objections of the patentee</title>, 1666. British Library, Wing / C1017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cerquiglini1989" label="Cerquiglini 1989"> Cerquiglini, Bernard. <title
                  rend="italic">Eloge de la variante: Histoire critique de la philologie.</title>
               Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1989.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cicero1947" label="Cicero 1947">Cicero, Marcus Tullius. <title
                  rend="italic">De Officiis</title>. Trans. Walter Miller. London: William
               Heinemann, 1947.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="codex303" label="Codex Vindobonensis Palatinus 303">Codex Vindobonensis
               Palatinus 303, Vienna, Manuscript, Österreichische Nationalbibliothek.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2003" label="Cohen 2003">Cohen, Jeffrey Jerome. <title rend="italic"
                  >Medieval Identity Machines.</title> Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
               2003. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cramer1995" label="Cramer 1995">Cramer, Thomas. <title rend="quotes">Æsopi
                  wolff.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Festschrift Walter Haug und Burghart Wachinger</title>. Ed
               Johannes Janota et al. Tübingen: Niemeyer, 1995. 955-66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cae1996" label="Critical Art Ensemble 1996 ">Critical Art Ensemble. <title
                  rend="italic">Electronic Civil Disobedience and Other</title>
               <title rend="italic">Unpopular Ideas</title>. Brooklyn: Autonomedia, 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="curtin2014" label="Curtin 2014">Curtin, Rebecca Schoff. <title
                  rend="quotes">Hackers and Humanists: Transactions and the Evolution of
                  Copyright.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Legal Studies Research Paper Series</title> 54.1 (March 21,
               2014): 105-57. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="daly1961" label="Daly 1961">Daly, Lloyd W, trans. and ed. <title
                  rend="italic">Aesop Without Morals: The Famous Fables, and a Life of
               Aesop</title>. New York &amp; London: A.S. Barnes and Company, Inc., 1961. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dicke1987" label="Dicke and Grubmüller 1987">Dicke, Gerd and Klaus
               Grubmüller. <title rend="italic">Die Fabeln des Mittelalters und der Frühen Neuzeit:
                  Ein Katalog der deutschen Versionen und ihrer latenischen</title>
               <title rend="italic">Entsprechungen</title>. Munich: Wilhelm Fink, 1987.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="EEBO2017" label="EEBO 2003-2017">Early English Books Online. <title
                  rend="quotes">Terms of Service.</title> ProQuest LLC. Retrieved from <ref
                  target="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/about/terms.htm"
                  >http://eebo.chadwyck.com/about/terms.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="EEBO-TCP2003" label="EEBO-TCP 2003">Early English Books Online – Text
               Creation Partnership. <title rend="quotes">Aesop. <title rend="italic">The morall
                     fabillis of Esope the Phrygian</title>.</title> Ann Arbor and Oxford: Text
               Creation Partnership, 2003. Retrieved from <ref
                  target="http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A08136.0001.001"
                  >http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A08136.0001.001</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="esposito2010" label="Esposito 2010">Esposito, Roberto. <title
                  rend="italic">Communitas: The Origin and Destiny of Community</title>. Trans.
               Timothy Campbell. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fisher2012" label="Fisher 2012">Fisher, Matthew.<title rend="italic">
                  Scribal Authorship and the Writing of History in Medieval England</title>.
               Columbus: Ohio State University Press, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fox1981" label="Fox 1981">Fox, Denton, ed. <title rend="italic">The Poems
                  of Robert Henryson.</title> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1981.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gibbs2008" label="Gibbs 2008">Gibbs, Laura. <title rend="italic">Aesopica:
                  Aesop’s Fables in English, Latin, and Greek </title>(2008). Retrieved from <ref
                  target="http://mythfolklore.net/aesopica/index.htm"
                  >http://mythfolklore.net/aesopica/index.htm</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harley3865" label="Harley MS 3865">Harley MS 3865, London, Manuscript,
               British Library.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="henryson1571" label="Henryson 1571">Robert Henryson. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Morall Fabillis of Esope</title>. Edinburgh: Thomas Bassandyne, 1571.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hervieux1960" label="Hervieux 1960">Hervieux, Léopold, ed. <title
                  rend="italic">Les Fabulistes Latins depuis le siècle d'Auguste jusqu'a la fin du
                  moyen âge</title>. New York: Burt Franklin, 1960.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="huygens1970" label="Huygens 1970 ">Huygens, R.B.C., ed. <title
                  rend="italic">Accessus ad auctores</title>. Leiden: Brill, 1970.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ingham2015" label="Ingham 2015">Ingham, Patricia Clare. <title
                  rend="italic">The Medieval New: Ambivalence in an Age of Innovation</title>.
               Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="irvine2014" label="Irvine 2014">Irvine, Martin. <title rend="quotes">Remix
                  and the Dialogic Engine of Culture: A Model for Generative
                  Combinatoriality.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Routledge Companion to Remix Studies</title>. Ed. Eduardo
               Navas, Owen Gallagher, and xtine burrough. London: Routledge, 2014. 15-42.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johns2010" label="Johns 2010">Johns, Adrian. <title rend="italic">Piracy:
                  The Intellectual Property Wars from Gutenberg to Gates</title>. 2<hi
                  rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kennedy2015" label="Kennedy 2015">Kennedy, Kathleen E. <title
                  rend="italic">Medieval Hackers.</title> Brooklyn: Punctum Books, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lambethms431" label="Lambeth MS 431">Lambeth MS 431, London, Lambeth
               Palace.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lenaghan1967" label="Lenaghan 1967">Lenaghan, R.T., ed. <title
                  rend="italic">Caxton’s Aesop</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
               1967.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lerer2008" label="Lerer 2008">Lerer, Seth. <title rend="italic">Children’s
                  Literature: A Reader’s History, from Aesop to Harry Potter</title>. Chicago and
               London: University of Chicago Press, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lessig2005" label="Lessig 2005">Lessig, Lawrence. <title rend="italic"
                  >Remix: Making Art and Commerce Thrive in the Hybrid Economy</title>. New York:
               Penguin, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2004" label="Liu 2004">Liu, Alan. <title rend="italic">The Laws of
                  Cool: Knowledge Work and the Culture of Information</title>. Chicago and London:
               University of Chicago Press, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="minnis2009" label="Minnis 2009">Minnis, Alastair. <title rend="italic"
                  >Medieval Theory of Authorship: Scholastic Literary Attitudes in the Later Middle
                  Ages</title>. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed. Philadelphia: University of
               Pennsylvania Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="minnis1988" label="Minnis and Scott 1988">Minnis, A.J. and A.B. Scott,
               eds. <title rend="italic">Medieval Literary Theory and Criticism c. 1100-c. 1375: The
                  Commentary Tradition</title>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1988.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mueller2013" label="A. Mueller 2013">Mueller, Alex. <title rend="italic"
                  >Translating Troy: Provincial Politics in Alliterative Romance</title>. Columbus:
               Ohio State University Press, 2013. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mueller1995" label="K. Mueller 1995">Mueller, Konrad, ed.<title
                  rend="italic"> Petronii Arbitri Satyricon reliquiae</title>. 4th ed. Stuttgart:
               1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="müller1994" label="Müller 1994">Müller, Jan-Dirk. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Body of the Book: The Media Transition from Manuscript to Print.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Materialities of Communication</title>. Ed. Hans Ulrich
               Gumbrecht and K. Ludwig Pfeiffer. Trans. William Whobrey. Stanford: Stanford
               University Press, 1994. 32-44. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="navas2012" label="Navas 2012">Navas, Eduardo. <title rend="italic">Remix
                  Theory: The Aesthetics of Sampling</title>. Wien: Springer, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nichols1990" label="Nichols 1990">Nichols, Stephen G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Introduction: Philology in Manuscript Culture.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Speculum </title> 65.1 (January 1990): 1-10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="patterson1991" label="Patterson 1991">Patterson, Annabel. <title
                  rend="italic">Fables of Power: Aesopian Writing and Political History</title>.
               Durham and London, Duke University Press, 1991. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="price2006" label="Price 2006">Price, Leah. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Introduction: Reading Matter.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 121.1 (January 2006): 9-16.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson1997" label="Robinson 1997">Robinson, Douglas. <title
                  rend="italic">Western Translation Theory from Herodotus to Nietzsche</title>.
               Manchester, UK: St. Jerome Publishing, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rubin1994" label="Rubin 1994">Rubin, Miri. <title rend="quotes">The Person
                  in the Form: Medieval Challenges to Bodily <q>Order.</q></title>
               <title rend="italic">Framing Medieval Bodies</title>. Ed. Sarah Kay &amp; Miri Rubin.
               Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1994. 100-22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="saloman2012" label="Saloman 2012">Saloman, David A. <title rend="italic"
                  >An Introduction to the Glossa Ordinaria as Medieval Hypertext</title>. Cardiff:
               University of Wales Press, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schumpeter1994" label="Schumpeter 1994">Schumpeter, Joseph A. <title
                  rend="italic">Capitalism, Socialism, and Democracy</title>. 5<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> edition. London and New York: Routledge, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="steinhöwel1501" label="Steinhöwel 1501">Steinhöwel, Heinrich. <title
                  rend="italic">Aesop</title>. Basel: Jacob von Pfortzheim, 1501.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="suntrust2001" label="Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin 2001"><title
                  rend="italic">Suntrust Bank v. Houghton Mifflin</title>. 286 F.3d 1257.
               2001.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="travis2011" label="Travis 2011">Travis, Peter. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Aesop's Symposium of Animal Tongues.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Postmedieval: A Journal of Medieval Cultural Studies</title> 2.1
               (2011): 33-49.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2016" label="Turner 2016">Turner, Henry. <title rend="italic">The
                  Corporate Commonwealth: Pluralism and Political Fictions in England,
                  1516-1651</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2016. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2006" label="Turner 2006">Turner, Henry. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Problem of the More-than-One: Friendship, Calculation, and Political Association
                  in <title rend="italic">The Merchant of Venice</title>.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title> 57.4 (Winter 2006): 413-42.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vaidhyanathan2003" label="Vaidhyanathan 2003">Vaidhyanathan, Siva. <title
                  rend="italic">Copyrights and Copywrongs: The Rise of Intellectual Property and How
                  It Threatens Creativity</title>. New York and London: New York University Press,
               2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wakelin2014" label="Wakelin 2014">Wakelin, Daniel. <title rend="italic"
                  >Scribal Correction and Literary Craft: English Manuscripts, 1375-1510</title>.
               Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="walker2013" label="Walker 2013">Walker, Alison Tara. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Boundless Book: A Conversation between the Pre-Modern and the
                  Posthuman.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7.1 (2013). Retrieved from
                  <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/7/1/000140/000140.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/7/1/000140/000140.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="welzenbach2011" label="Welzenbach 2011">Welzenbach, Rebecca. <title
                  rend="quotes">Making the Most of Free, Unrestricted Texts: A First Look at the
                  Promise of the Text Creation Partnership.</title> Deep Blue (2011). University of
               Michigan. <ref
                  target="https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/handle/2027.42/87997/Welzenbach-DHCS-2011.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y"
                  >https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/handle/2027.42/87997/Welzenbach-DHCS-2011.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wharton2013" label="Wharton 2013">Wharton, Robin. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Humanities, Copyright, and the Literary.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7.1 (2013). Retrieved from
                  <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000147/000147.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000147/000147.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wheatley1999" label="Wheatley 1999">Wheatley, Edward. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Aesopic Corpus Divided Against Itself: A Literary Body and Its
                  Members.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Early Book Society for the Study of Manuscripts
                  and Printing History</title> 2 (1999): 46-72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wheatley2000" label="Wheatley 2000">Wheatley, Edward. <title rend="italic"
                  >Mastering Aesop: Medieval Education, Chaucer, and His Followers.</title>
               Gainesville: University Press of Florida, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="winroth2004" label="Winroth 2004">Winroth, Anders. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Making of Gratian’s Decretum</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
               2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wright2001" label="Wright 2001">Wright, A.E. <title rend="italic"><title
                     rend="quotes">Hie lert uns der meister</title>: Latin Commentary and the German
                  Fable, 1350-1500</title>. Medieval and Renaissance Texts and Studies. Vol. 218.
               Tempe: Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wright1998" label="Wright 1998">Wright, A.E. <title rend="quotes">Readers
                  and Wolves: Late-Medieval Commentaries on <title rend="quotes">De lupo et
                     capite.</title></title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Medieval Latin</title> 8 (1998): 72-9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="young1993" label="Young 1993">Young, Katherine, ed. <title rend="italic"
                  >Bodylore</title>. Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1993.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zumthor1972" label="Zumthor 1972">Zumthor, Paul. <title rend="italic"
                  >Essai de poétique medieval.</title> Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zumthor1987" label="Zumthor 1987">Zumthor, Paul. <title rend="italic">La
                  letter et la voix</title>. Paris, 1987.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
