<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">How Technology Means: Texts, History, and Their
                    Associated Technologies</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Joshua L. <dhq:family>Mann</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Expositus</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>josh@expositus.org</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Joshua Mann is President and CEO of Expositus, a research and education
                            501(c)(3) nonprofit working in the area of digital humanities.
                            Previously he was a Research Fellow at CODEC Research Centre for Digital
                            Theology at the University of Durham (UK). His research engages subjects
                            in digital humanities and biblical studies. He is particularly
                            interested in the hermeneutics of technology, i.e., how technology
                            itself means and has politics.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000398</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2018-09-12">12 September 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <!-- 
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                -->
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front>

            <!-- what to do w/ [special issue...] -->

            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Technologies used to study and represent the past are not hermeneutically
                    neutral. Since technologies have illocutionary force, we should ask of any
                    representation of history, <hi rend="italic">In what ways are the associated
                        technologies conveying meaning?</hi> In this article, the question will be
                    asked of a particular kind of history, textual history, taking biblical texts as
                    an illustrative example. The goal is to better understand how textual
                    technologies of yesterday, today, or tomorrow capture or obscure the material
                    history of their texts. The article proceeds in two main parts. First, two kinds
                    of technologies commonly used are examined and compared: the non-digital book
                    and its familiar digital counterparts. Second, we will consider ways in which
                    augmented reality and virtual reality have been used and might be used to
                    represent texts. It will be suggested that these new technologies may overcome
                    some of the limitation of previous book technologies in capturing a text’s
                    history. In conclusion, practical suggestions will be made for those who read,
                    study, or produce digital textual objects. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>

            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>In what ways are the technologies associated with textual history conveying
                    meaning?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>

        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">People worked together to make the Bible. I can tell
                            because of all the names.</quote>
                        <ref target="#private">Naomi (age 5)</ref>
                    </cit>
                    <note>As reported by a colleague, shared with permission.</note>
                </epigraph>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">...forms effect meaning</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mckenzie1999" loc="13"/>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#galey2010">[Digital Humanities’] tool-building
                            enterprise risks falling into a binary in which digital tools represent
                            innovation, dynamism, and provocative instability, while the materials
                            they operate upon — very often literary texts — represent availability,
                            continuity, and unproblematic stability.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#galey2010" loc="100"/>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p>It should come as no surprise that technologies used to study and represent the
                    past are not hermeneutically neutral. To state this positively: the technologies
                    themselves <emph>mean</emph> something; they have illocutionary force. In
                    considering technologies through which the past might be apprehended, it is
                    important to remember that the past is only ever <emph>approximately</emph>
                    apprehended: one cannot simply <soCalled>go back,</soCalled> but must rely on
                    constructed memories, artifacts, written accounts, recordings, etc. Further, as
                    these examples indicate, most of our means of apprehending the past rely on
                    technology, broadly defined. Consider Ferré’s broad understanding of technology: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ferre1995">...technology involves (i)
                            implements used as (ii) means to practical ends that are somehow (iii)
                            manifested in the material world as (iv) expressions of
                            intelligence</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ferre1995" loc="25"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>Thus when history is studied or represented, one must ask, <hi rend="italic">In
                        what ways are the associated technologies conveying meaning? </hi></p>
                <p>This article will direct the question toward a particular kind of history,
                    textual history, taking biblical texts as an illustrative example. The goal is
                    to better understand how textual technologies of yesterday, today, or tomorrow
                    capture or obscure the material history of their texts. Biblical texts are
                    particularly useful since they feature prominently during major media shifts in
                    the past two millennia (from scroll to codex, script to print, print to
                    digital). First, two technologies widely used are considered and compared: the
                    (non-digital) book and its digital counterparts. This analysis will suggest ways
                    in which the associated paratexts affect the reader’s understanding of the
                    text’s past. Second, technologies increasingly available but less commonly used
                    for texts, augmented reality (AR) and virtual reality (VR), will be considered
                    along the same lines. These technologies are particularly interesting because,
                    although they are digital, they represent 3D physical space quite realistically.
                    It will be seen that each technology examined conveys certain elements of
                    textual history while obscuring others. These observations will lead to more
                    general considerations for those creating, using, and studying texts. </p>
                <p>It should be said at the outset that in order to understand and describe what is
                    or is not unique about a text mediated by <emph>this</emph> or <emph>that</emph>
                    technology, we necessarily describe features of texts that are normally taken
                    for granted. As Willard McCarty reminds, this is a difficult exercise: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2013">In consequence of the rigours of
                            using this language, which requires complete and explicit specification,
                            there arises...the struggle to articulate what normally goes without
                            saying in our editions and editing practices</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2013" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>. To aid in the task, we will look through the lens of
                        <emph>paratext</emph>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The Paratexts of Book Technology</head>
                <p>Roughly, paratexts are to texts what a frame is to a picture. Gérard Genette, who
                    has coined the literary use of the term, explains: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#genette1997">A literary work consists, entirely
                            or essentially, of a text, defined (very minimally) as a more or less
                            long sequence of verbal statements that are more or less endowed with
                            significance. But this text is rarely presented in an unadorned state,
                            unreinforced and unaccompanied by a certain number of verbal or other
                            productions, such as an author’s name, a title, a preface,
                            illustrations. And although we do not always know whether these
                            productions are to be regarded as belonging to the text, in any case
                            they surround it and extend it, precisely in order to
                                <emph>present</emph> it, in the usual sense of this verb but also in
                            the strongest sense: to <emph>make present</emph>, to ensure the text’s
                            presence in the world, its <soCalled>reception</soCalled> and
                            consumption in the form (nowadays, at least) of a book. These
                            accompanying productions, which vary in extent and appearance,
                            constitute what I have called elsewhere the work’s
                            <emph>paratext</emph>....</quote>
                        <ptr target="#genette1997" loc="1"/>
                    </cit> The key is that paratexts themselves have meaning; they are
                    hermeneutically significant: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#jansen2014">Far from being an issue that
                            preoccupies only the theoretically minded, the matter of the paratext is
                            always — albeit often imperceptibly — already at work in the hermeneutic
                            process</quote>
                        <ptr target="#jansen2014" loc="1"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>In considering <emph>digital</emph> paratexts, we will deviate from Genette in
                    two respects: (1) It matters very little in the following analysis whether or
                    not the <soCalled>author</soCalled> legitimates (or accepts responsibility) for
                    a paratext;<note> Cf. <ptr target="#genette1997" loc="2"/>: <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#genette1997">By definition, something is not a paratext unless
                            the author or one of his associates accepts responsibility for
                            it...</quote>.</note> and (2) the <emph>para</emph> of
                        <emph>paratexts</emph> receives the emphasis, not the <emph>texts</emph>. In
                    other words, paratexts are framing features of the text but not necessarily
                    texts themselves.<note> Whereas Genette seemed to envision that most paratexts
                        were themselves textual (e.g., table of contents, publisher’s name, etc.).
                        For a similar approach as I take for digital paratextuality, see <ptr
                            target="#vandijk2014"/>.</note> For the purposes of this article, then,
                    paratexts are the productions that accompany, present, or contain the text,
                    including productions that facilitate the engagement of a reader.<note> Compare
                        a recent narrow definition in reference to the paratexts of biblical
                        manuscripts: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#wallraff2015">...all contents in biblical
                                manuscripts except the biblical text itself are a priori
                                paratexts</quote>
                            <ptr target="#wallraff2015" loc="239"/>
                        </cit>.</note> Paratexts may be produced by an author, publisher, software
                    developers, editors, and the like, and also include visual features associated
                    with typography, page layout, book design or, in software, the interface. These
                    paratexts affect readerly expectations of encountering a text and, indeed, the
                    encounter itself. In the following section, we begin to explore how paratexts
                    affect the reader’s sense of a text’s history.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Technologies and the History of Biblical Texts</head>
                <p>The purpose here is to sufficiently explore the subtle
                        <soCalled>messages</soCalled> various book technologies send a reader of
                    biblical texts; that is, to consider the illocutionary force of the various
                    paratexts. For heuristic purposes, let us begin by considering the form of
                    biblical texts that most people encounter today: The printed Bible in
                    translation. Such a book is generally a collection of 66 or more ancient
                    documents bound together in a single volume (<ref target="#figure01">Figure
                        1</ref>)<note> The number of documents or <soCalled>books</soCalled> vary by
                        tradition, e.g., Hebrew (Jewish Rabbinic) Canon (24), Protestant Canon (66),
                        Roman Catholic Canon (73). For simplicity, this article will use the
                        Protestant Canon unless otherwise stated.</note>. <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>A typical black-leather bound Bible. Image copyright owned by the
                            author.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure> Right away we should note that the binding itself is significant. The
                    binding is a paratext that conveys a message: these documents
                        <emph>belong</emph> together. But in terms of the text’s history, the
                    binding paratext of a codex potentially obscures the fact that the documents
                    within were completed at various times over the course of 1,500 or more years by
                    authors who almost certainly did not envision that their work would be read
                    alongside of these other works. Indeed, the texts of these documents were
                    transmitted by copying and came to be collected together and assorted in various
                    ways over the centuries by diverse groups, many of whom did not agree about the
                    documents’ relation to one another.<note> For an introduction to the textual
                        history and criticism of biblical texts, for the Hebrew Bible see <ptr
                            target="#tov2012"/>, and for the New Testament see <ptr
                            target="#metzgeretal2005"/>.</note> Even where an introduction or
                    marginal note gives an account of the composition of a particular document, the
                    paratextual message of <emph>belonging</emph> remains.</p>
                <p>Early in the textual history of many of the biblical texts, however, especially
                    those of the Hebrew Bible, the scroll, not the codex, was the book technology of
                        choice.<note> In spite of literary preference for the scroll in the first
                        few centuries CE, the codex was very quickly and extensively taken up by
                        early Christian communities, perhaps as they sought to collect multiple
                        documents, such as the Apostle Paul’s letters or the Gospels, into a bound
                        collection. Scholars have offered various explanations for why Christians
                        preferred the codex. See <ptr target="#gamble1995"/>; <ptr
                            target="#richards1998"/>; <ptr target="#skeat1994"/>. For our purposes,
                        we need not determine the reason.</note> We might therefore ask: Does a
                    scroll have a similar binding or boundary paratext as a codex? Of course, each
                    end of the scroll serves as a boundary, and if multiple texts are contained in a
                    single scroll, these texts are related to one another by virtue of the boundary
                    paratext analogous to the binding of a codex. Perhaps a closer equivalent to the
                    binding paratext of the codex would be the receptacle of a group of scrolls,
                    perhaps a shelf, a chest, or a jar.<note> See <ptr target="#small1997"
                            loc="43, 48"/>.</note> For example, the <title rend="italic">Torah
                        Ark</title>, a special receptacle for Torah <!-- italicized name --> scrolls
                    used in some synagogues, represents a similar kind of canonical paratext as the
                    binding of the Bible earlier described. But note that a collection of scrolls is
                    far less fixed than a collection of texts bound in a codex, and the paratextual
                    message of belonging is less overt. Thus a canonical collection of scrolls
                    captures the distinctiveness of individual documents, obscuring to a lesser
                    extent the collection’s textual history.</p>
                <p>What, then, is the binding or boundary paratext of a <emph>digital</emph>
                    biblical text? Technically, a computer file containing the text exists, usually
                    marked (or tagged) at document boundaries. Since a reader is generally unaware
                    of this technical boundary, its hermeneutical significance is more difficult to
                        discern.<note> I do not deny that the code <emph>is</emph> hermeneutically
                        significant. For the purposes of this article, however, I am focusing on the
                        readerly encounter with a text.</note> In terms of the electronic display of
                    a biblical text, boundaries might include title pages and chapter or page
                    numbers that indicate a beginning or a scroll bar that indicates the user’s
                    relative location within the document.<note> Note that the interface typically
                        includes a <soCalled>window</soCalled> within which one scrolls or otherwise
                        moves through the text, but this boundary is not <emph>binding</emph> in the
                        same way.</note> It is instructive to compare the boundary paratexts
                    illustrated in Figures 2 and 3 below. In Accordance Bible Software, if a user
                    navigates to the beginning of the Gospel of Luke — a distinct ancient document —
                    scrolling up will display the ending of the Gospel of Mark — another distinct
                    document, usually bound just before Luke in a print Bible — with little
                    indication of a boundary between them (<ref target="#figure02">Figure
                        2</ref>).<note> I am using Accordance Bible Software version 11.1.5 on Mac
                        OS X El Capitan.</note> But in YouVersion’s popular Bible app, navigating to
                    the beginning of the Gospel of Luke, the user is presented with the first
                    chapter of that document, unable to scroll up to any previous text (<ref
                        target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>).<note> I am using YouVersion Bible app
                        version 6.5 on iOS 7.1.2. It has been installed on over 200 million smart
                        devices worldwide (<ref target="#https://www.youversion.com/"
                            >https://www.youversion.com/</ref> [accessed 14 Jan 2016]).</note> To
                    advance within the text of chapter one, the user must scroll down. To advance to
                    chapter two, the user must tap the right arrow button. However, pressing the
                    left arrow button <emph>will</emph> take the user to the last chapter of the
                    Gospel of Mark (similar to the scrolling navigation in Accordance). Thus in both
                    examples, the user can navigate back one chapter <emph>in canonical
                        sequence</emph>, from Luke 1 to Mark 16, not unlike most printed Bibles.
                    YouVersion’s app presents more of a boundary between the two documents, the
                    Gospels of Mark and Luke, by virtue of its chapter boundaries. But in both
                    cases, the canonical sequence is fixed and the boundaries between documents are
                    not overt. <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>The beginning of the Gospel of Luke in Accordance Bible Software.
                            Screenshot taken by the author.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure03">
                        <head>YouVersion's iOS app, open to the beginning of the Gospel of Luke.
                            Screenshot taken by the author.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>

                <p>Consider also the uniformity of modern printed books in terms of typography, page
                    layout, and other elements of book design — paratextual properties according to
                    my definition — reinforcing the message that the documents are related and
                    belong together since each document (or <soCalled>book</soCalled> within) looks
                    and feels exactly the same.<note> Note that while it is true that <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#eisenstein1979">...early printed copies
                                were not all precisely alike...[t]hey were sufficiently uniform for
                                scholars in different regions to correspond with each other about
                                the same citation and for the same emendations and errors to be
                                spotted by many eyes</quote>
                            <ptr target="#eisenstein1979" loc="81"/>
                        </cit>; and further: <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline">[Standardization] also involved the
                                    <soCalled>subliminal</soCalled> impact upon scattered readers of
                                repeated encounters with identical type-styles, printers’ devices,
                                and title page ornamentation</quote>
                            <ptr target="#eisenstein1979" loc="82"/>
                        </cit>.</note> Similarly, printed Bibles typically have consecutive page
                    numbering <emph>across</emph> the bound collection, another paratextual message
                    suggesting the unity and progression of its contents.<note> The covers of a
                        Bible, usually made of durable material like leather, also reinforce that
                        the bound collection is significant and belongs together.</note> An
                    additional numbering system is commonly used for referencing larger units of
                    each document (consecutively numbered <soCalled>chapters</soCalled>) under which
                    are smaller units (consecutively numbered <soCalled>verses</soCalled>, per
                        chapter).<note> These paratexts invite a reader to make reference to quite
                        small units of text, a subtle paratextual message that the details are
                        important.</note> The consistency of this reference system across biblical
                    texts, including various editions, versions, and translations of modern Bibles,
                    and even anachronistically used in online editions of digitized manuscripts,
                    subtly suggests readerly, possibly even authorial, agreement about the unit -
                    delineation, and therefore the argument, of the texts. These numbering systems
                    are intentionally absent in some printed Bibles, often called Reader’s Bibles,
                    in order to present the reader a text formatted like familiar modern books. Some
                    Bible applications likewise allow the user to <soCalled>hide</soCalled> verse
                    and chapter numbers (and manipulate certain other visual paratextual features).
                    Even so, print and digital versions alike present an extremely uniform text
                    which subtly obscures its textual history.</p>
                <p>The physical binding of a Bible also fixes the sequence (or canonical order) of
                    the documents. Imagine the hermeneutical difference, for example with a
                    Protestant Bible, if a reader had a series of 66 unnumbered volumes on a shelf,
                    each corresponding to one ancient document (e.g., Genesis, Exodus, etc.), rather
                    than a one-volume bound collection. At a glance, it would become immediately
                    clear that the documents vary greatly in size, which reduces the sense of
                    uniformity, even if slightly. The reader could also then order the collection in
                    a multitude of ways: by putative date of composition, by genre, by size, and so
                        on.<note> In the textual history of biblical texts, the canonical sequence
                        of documents varies somewhat, but has remained relatively fixed in recent
                        times. Interestingly, one Protestant organization, Biblica, has recently
                        produced a curriculum which includes printed biblical texts without chapter
                        and verse numbers, without columns, and in a different canonical order, in
                        an attempt to alter the engagement of the reader (see <ref
                            target="#http://www.biblica.com/en-us/cbe/"
                            >http://www.biblica.com/en-us/cbe/</ref>).</note> While digital biblical
                    texts often utilize hyperlinking in such a way that navigation is not linear,
                    they nevertheless retain traditional canonical sequencing through the prominent
                    navigational features (e.g., scrolling, contents menu, etc.).</p>
                <p>Similarly, there is finality to a printed Bible, like any printed book — a
                    paratextual message that suggests a pure, original text. This
                        <soCalled>finality</soCalled> enabled by the printing press was celebrated
                    by science and religion alike from an early period. In 1702, Bishop Thomas Sprat
                    could say: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sprat1702">[Both the Royal Society and the
                            Church]...have taken a like cours[e] to bring this about; each of them
                            passing by the corrupt Copies, and referring themselves to the perfect
                            Originals for their instruction; the one to Scripture, the other to the
                            large Volume of the Creatures</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sprat1702" loc="371"/>
                    </cit>; cf. <ptr target="#eisenstein1979" loc="696"/>).<note> This notion of a
                        pure <q>original</q> text persists in many quarters, but most textual
                        critics of the biblical texts have for some time dropped the language of
                            <soCalled>original text</soCalled> and prefer to speak of the
                            <soCalled>earliest recoverable text</soCalled>, <soCalled>initial
                            text</soCalled>, or <title rend="italic">Ausgangstext</title>
                        <ptr target="#ehrmanetal2012"/>.</note> That sense of finality is far less
                    acute in Bible software.<note> Outside the scope of this discussion is a
                        consideration of the longevity of any given digital (biblical) text in terms
                        of data storage. It is worth noting, however, that researchers at the
                        University of Southampton recently demonstrated 5D data storage using a
                        laser on quartz, a technology that they estimate will outlast humanity.
                        Among the four <soCalled>headlining</soCalled> digital documents recorded by
                        the team is the King James Bible. Interestingly, the quartz disc of the
                        Bible contains the imprint <q>Holy Bible</q> on its surface — a fitting but
                        hermeneutically loaded paratext. See: <ref
                            target="#http://spie.org/newsroom/technical-articles/6365-eternal-5d-data-storage-via-ultrafast-laser-writing-in-glass"
                            >http://spie.org/newsroom/technical-articles/6365-eternal-5d-data-storage-via-ultrafast-laser-writing-in-glass</ref>.</note>
                    Accordance Bible Software, for example, periodically alerts the user to
                    available updates, listing specific modules that might include a biblical text —
                    a text that is updated, changed with the click of a button! <figure
                        xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Update window in Accordance Bible Software. Screenshot taken by the
                            author.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure> Not only does this diminish the sense of finality present in a printed
                    text; it also reminds the user that textual transmission of the Bible is
                    perpetual. One is, as it were, standing in it. As David Parker, a New Testament
                    textual critic, once observed after creating an electronic transcription of
                    Codex Sinaiticus: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#parker2003">...textual critics, under the
                            guise of reconstructing original texts, are really creating new
                            ones</quote>
                        <ptr target="#parker2003" loc="401"/>
                    </cit>.<note> Along these lines Claire Clivaz has recently suggested some of the
                        ways that digital texts are challenging modern assumptions about
                            <soCalled>text</soCalled> inherited from the printing press, especially
                        an assumed stability of the text <ptr target="#clivaz2015"/>.</note> Parker
                    suggests that as technologies give more ability to the user to manipulate a
                    scholarly edition of a text (like the New Testament), <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#parker2003">The result will be a weakening of
                            the status of standard editions, and with that a change in the way in
                            which users of texts perceive their tasks</quote>
                        <ptr target="#parker2003" loc="404"/>
                    </cit>. Note, however, that even in Parker’s advanced software, Collate, there
                    is a smoothing over of textual materiality for the sake of the machine. This
                        <soCalled>smoothing over</soCalled> is the effect of any attempt to produce
                    a critical edition, creating the tension, described by Alan Galey, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#galey2010">...between the surface orderliness
                            of scholarly resources and the stubborn irregularity of textual
                            materials</quote>
                        <ptr target="#galey2010" loc="93"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>How else might the <quote rend="inline" source="#galey2010">stubborn irregularity
                        of textual materials</quote> be represented and their paratexts captured?
                    Images have for a long time been an important means of capturing the materiality
                    of manuscripts. Given the scope of this article, we limit ourselves to
                    considering <emph>digital</emph> images. For a manuscript of more than a few
                    pages, most digitized versions present a series of images, one per page (of a
                    codex) or per section (of a scroll). For example, the Center for the Study of
                    New Testament Manuscripts provides a web interface that simply presents
                    thumbnail images of the pages of a manuscript.<note> See, e.g., <ref
                            target="http://www.csntm.org/Manuscript/View/Rahlfs_961"
                            >http://www.csntm.org/Manuscript/View/Rahlfs_961</ref>.</note> Clicking
                    on a thumbnail will open a larger version of the same image in a viewer in which
                    the user can zoom to view even greater detail. Other interfaces juxtapose
                    manuscript images, transcriptions, and translations. One Bible software program,
                    BibleWorks, links manuscript sigla, transcriptions, and images of select
                        manuscripts.<note> See, e.g., a screenshot available at the company’s
                        website: <ref target="http://www.bibleworks.com/content/ss/macss5.png"
                            >http://www.bibleworks.com/content/ss/macss5.png</ref>.</note> In an
                    example of one of the more sophisticated web interfaces, the Codex Sinaiticus
                    Project displays a zoomable manuscript image (per codex page), a transcription
                    formatted in columns corresponding to the manuscript, and a translation in one
                    of a few languages — each linked to the other word by word.<note> See: <ref
                            target="http://codexsinaiticus.org/en/manuscript.aspx"
                            >http://codexsinaiticus.org/en/manuscript.aspx</ref>. Cf. the New
                        Testament Virtual Manuscript Room by the Institut für Neutestamentliche
                        Textforschung: <ref
                            target="http://ntvmr.uni-muenster.de/manuscript- workspace"
                            >http://ntvmr.uni-muenster.de/manuscript- workspace</ref>.</note>
                    Navigation <!-- footnotes --> is possible either by book/chapter/verse (like a
                    modern printed Bible) or quire/folio/verso-recto. The latter method is a good
                    example of a navigational paratext that captures the materiality of the
                    manuscript. In spite of the sophistication, however, the user’s relative
                    location within the document is not obvious. Contrast this limitation with a
                    series of digitized scrolls in The Digital Dead Sea Scrolls project by The
                    Israel Museum, Jerusalem.<note> See: <ref
                            target="http://dss.collections.imj.org.il/"
                            >http://dss.collections.imj.org.il/</ref>.</note> The Isaiah Scroll, for
                    example, can be read by moving a slider at the bottom of the window — a scroll
                    bar that is itself an image of the scroll, rolled out, and numbered, column by
                    column (<ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>). The greater part of the window
                    is taken by a zoomable image of the scroll, each end of which appears to be
                    unrolled or rolled up, depending on the direction of navigation. Hovering over a
                    line of the original text causes a shaded box to appear which, upon clicking,
                    displays a pop up English translation of the highlighted text. This interface,
                    more than any other I have encountered online, captures the original paratexts
                    of the object.<note> Note that capturing and representing the original paratexts
                        of these texts may be more obviously useful for scholars than, say, the
                        popular readership of the YouVersion Bible app. However, the point here is
                        to simply show that the paratexts themselves indicate (or obscure) much
                        about the text’s history, impacting upon our apprehension of the
                        past.</note></p>

                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>The Isaiah Scroll, The Israel Museum, Jerusalem. Screenshot taken by the
                        author.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>


                <p>A final interesting example to consider is the British Library’s virtual display
                    of the Lindsfarne Gospels.<note> See <ref
                            target="http://www.bl.uk/turning-the-pages/?id=fdbcc772-3e21-468d-8ca1-9c192f0f939c&amp;type=book"
                            >http://www.bl.uk/turning-the-pages/?id=fdbcc772-3e21-468d-8ca1-9c192f0f939c&amp;type=book</ref>.
                        The interface uses <title rend="quotes">Turning the Pages</title> software
                        developed by Armadillo Systems. See <ref
                            target="http://ttp.onlineculture.co.uk/history/"
                            >http://ttp.onlineculture.co.uk/history/</ref>.</note> Here individual
                    images of select pages of the manuscript appear to turn. Shading and lighting
                    effects are also used to create a 3D feel, not unlike the Isaiah Scroll
                    interface in Figure 5.</p>

                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>The British Library’s virtual display of the Lindsfarne Gospels.
                        Screenshot taken by the author.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>In summary, a number of paratextual features of the codex book form, especially
                    in print, obscure the textual history of the Bible by inviting assumptions about
                    the unity and cohesion of the various documents contained therein. Most digital
                    counterparts to the book similarly smooth over the variegated history of the
                    texts. Critical editions suffer from this tendency, even as they explicitly
                    represent the details of the text’s history. Digitized manuscripts, however, are
                    increasingly produced in a way that preserves their original paratextual
                    properties and material features, and may help overcome the tendency of printed
                    texts to obscure textual history. This leads us to consider the potential of two
                    image-based technologies, AR and VR.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The Potential of Augmented and Virtual Reality for Textual History</head>
                <p>Growing interest in consumer VR technology since the release of the Oculus Rift
                    DK1 in 2012 has been matched by the development of many consumer VR applications
                    and VR (360) videos, including some that relate to the biblical text. During
                    roughly this same period, the proliferation of mobile devices with
                    accelerometers and ever-faster processing capabilities has been met with the
                    development of consumer-level AR applications, including some related to the
                    Bible. The trajectory of this 3D technology development suggests that scholars
                    begin seriously, if cautiously, considering its deployment for their own
                    activities. </p>
                <p>It is perhaps unsurprising to find the Bible being taken up in these new
                    technologies in light of its own textual history. However, most of the
                        <soCalled>biblical</soCalled> AR and VR applications appear to be less
                        <emph>textual</emph> and more related to providing immersive experiences of
                    the stories of the Bible. For example, the Bible VRX Lite, a proof-of-concept
                    app available for iOS and Android devices, lets a user experience a handful of
                    relatively well known biblical scenes, such as the moment before Adam and Eve
                    eat the forbidden fruit, Moses facedown before the burning bush, Jonah submerged
                    in the sea with a whale-like creature nearby, or the nativity.<note> See <ref
                            target="http://biblevrx.com/">http://biblevrx.com/</ref>; demo: <ref
                            target="https://youtu.be/w6CgdDVfRKw"
                        >https://youtu.be/w6CgdDVfRKw</ref>.</note></p>

                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>In one scene from the Bible VRX app, Eve is depicted as reaching out for
                        the forbidden fruit as Adam turns, as if to see if God is watching. This iOS
                        screenshot was taken by the author.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                </figure>

                <p>Similarly, in the Immersive Faith Project app, one can experience an imagined
                    scene from Jesus’ <title rend="quotes">Sermon on the Mount</title>.<note> See
                            <ref target="http://www.immersivefaith.com/"
                            >http://www.immersivefaith.com/</ref>; demo: <ref
                            target="https://youtu.be/D3UApkIgjIk"
                        >https://youtu.be/D3UApkIgjIk</ref>.</note> One large publisher recently
                    developed an AR app for use with a Children’s storybook Bible.<note> See <ref
                            target="http://www.bhpublishinggroup.com/press-release/augmented-reality-hits-the-bible-bh-kids-announces-the-big-picture-interactive-bible-storybook"
                            >http://www.bhpublishinggroup.com/press-release/augmented-reality-hits-the-bible-bh-kids-announces-the-big-picture-interactive-bible-storybook</ref>;
                        demo: <ref target="https://youtu.be/nArrZ4gr7gE"
                            >https://youtu.be/nArrZ4gr7gE</ref>.</note> The mobile app is used to
                    scan an illustration from the physical book, thereby causing the illustration to
                        <soCalled>pop up</soCalled> virtually on the screen. Simultaneously, an
                    audio narration of the story begins to play. Likewise, a Shanghai company has
                    recently released a number of AR products for children, including the <title
                        rend="quotes">Children’s First AR Bible,</title> a coloring book of 40
                    well-known biblical scenes that <soCalled>come to life</soCalled> with the
                    corresponding app.<note> See <ref
                            target="http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/childrens-first-ar-bible-lets-children-bring-bible-stories-to-life-300211437.html"
                            >http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/childrens-first-ar-bible-lets-children-bring-bible-stories-to-life-300211437.html</ref>;
                        demo: <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d_vSBL2p6o4"
                            >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d_vSBL2p6o4</ref>.</note> Another
                    company attempted a Kickstarter campaign to raise funds for an AR app that
                    displays a short Bible text when one of its 3D printed objects (such as a cross)
                    is scanned.<note> See <ref
                            target="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/692439852/proven-reality"
                            >https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/692439852/proven-reality</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>Three other examples of AR and VR call for greater attention. First, and slightly
                    difficult to classify, is The New Jerusalem Virtual Reality exhibit by Michael
                    Takeo Magruder (<ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>).<note> See: <ref
                            target="http://www.takeo.org/nspace/2014-dta-new-jerusalem/index.html"
                            >http://www.takeo.org/nspace/2014-dta-new-jerusalem/index.html</ref>.
                        For a demo: <ref target="https://vimeo.com/131471303"
                            >https://vimeo.com/131471303</ref>. Note a panel discussion of the
                        exhibit at Kings College London: <ref target="https://vimeo.com/114447276"
                            >https://vimeo.com/114447276</ref>.</note> In a sense it is
                        <emph>unreal</emph>, an intentional <soCalled>vitual unreality</soCalled>
                    that attempts to represent both the text of Revelation 21 (a biblical text), as
                    well as a significant event described by that text: the descent of the heavenly
                    New Jerusalem, described in Revelation 21 as a cube-like city. <figure
                        xml:id="figure08">
                        <head>The New Jerusalem Exhibition by Michael Takeo Magruder. Screenshot
                            taken by the author.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure> The biblical text was divided into 16 units and translated into 16
                    corresponding QR codes that, as the cube-shaped city descends, appear as 3D
                    skyscraper-like edifices through which the user can navigate. The kaleidoscopic
                    texture for the city is derived from Google map data of present day Jerusalem.
                    There is little indication of the text’s history — only the subtle clue that
                    textual information is contained in the QR codes. What is useful about this
                    example, however, is the challenge it presents us when considering how a text
                    may be represented and experienced. The exhibit is visual, multi-sensory, and
                    may tap into something of the <emph>emotion</emph> of the biblical scene,
                    perhaps in a way not unlike the illuminations of ancient or medieval
                    manuscripts.</p>
                <p>Second, the Museum of the Bible in the USA has contracted a Jerusalem-based
                    software developer, Compedia, to create an AR app that is designed to be used
                    with a Bible curriculum. This app has not been publically released, but a demo
                    available online indicates some of the ways that the textual history of the
                    Bible might be represented.<note> Demo: <ref
                            target="https://youtu.be/-mbP88oQLgc"
                        >https://youtu.be/-mbP88oQLgc</ref>.</note> In one example, a user scans a
                    printed icon in a textbook using the camera of an iPad, causing the printed
                    image of the 1611 King James Bible title page to transform itself on the screen
                    into a 3D 1611 King James Bible (<ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>).
                        <figure xml:id="figure09">
                        <head>A 1611 King James Bible rendered in an AR app on the iPad. The image
                            is a screenshot taken by the author from the YouTube video referenced
                            above.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure> In the video, the user then <soCalled>flips</soCalled> the pages using
                    gestures on the touchscreen, causing the pages to flip, bend, and fall
                    realistically. Eventually the Bible falls open to the New Testament title page,
                    slightly rounded as one would expect of a thickly bound book. Notice in <ref
                        target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref> the ways in which the paratexts are
                    virtually presented: The binding, the thickness of the book, the presence of
                    other pages, etc. One can further imagine that in a VR environment, the relative
                    size of the object could be more realistically rendered by the added depth
                    perception.</p>
                <p>In another example from the same app demo, a cuneiform prism is displayed and
                    appears to be <soCalled>standing up</soCalled> relative to the page displayed on
                    the iPad through the camera. The artifact is the Weld-Blundell Prism which
                    contains a Sumerian King-List on four roughly equal sides. <figure
                        xml:id="figure10">
                        <head>The Weld-Blundell Prism represented on the iPad in an AR app. The
                            screenshot was taken by the author from the demo video.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure> In Figure 10, notice the details captured in the AR representation of
                    the prism in contrast to the four 2D images on the textbook page.</p>
                <p>Third, Adi Keinan-Schoonbae, a Fellow at the British Library who specializes in
                    Hebrew Manuscripts, has created a number of 3D models available on SketchFab, a
                    publishing platform for such projects (see <ref target="#figure11">Figure
                        11</ref>).<note> Keinan-Schoonbae’s profile may be found at <ref
                            target="https://sketchfab.com/adiks"
                        >https://sketchfab.com/adiks</ref>.</note> These models can be viewed and
                    manipulated on most digital devices, as well as rendered in VR on appropriate
                    mobile devices. <figure xml:id="figure11">
                        <head>Depiction of the Esther Scroll in ivory case, modelled by Adi
                            Keinan-Schoonbaert. Screenshot taken by the author.<note> Available on
                                sketchfab: <ref
                                    target="https://sketchfab.com/models/95b1c036b67a43aab027a8a024fb4c7c"
                                    >https://sketchfab.com/models/95b1c036b67a43aab027a8a024fb4c7c</ref>.</note></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                    </figure> In early 2016, new models of ancient texts appear to be uploaded to
                    SketchFab every week, and major cultural institutions are beginning to explore
                    the platform. The Harvard Semitic Museum, for example, has recently uploaded a
                    number of models, including a Cuneiform tablet from its collection.<note> See
                            <ref
                            target="https://sketchfab.com/models/e33282e3992f43fd9dc1b0161ecffd29"
                            >https://sketchfab.com/models/e33282e3992f43fd9dc1b0161ecffd29</ref>.</note>
                    These models showcase the potential of creating publically accessible 3D models
                    of textual objects. One limitation is that, as far as I can tell, the objects
                    cannot be manipulated in a way that would represent the opening of a scroll or
                    the turning of the pages of a book.<note> Another concern about SketchFab is the
                        sustainability of the platform as it is something of a startup, having begun
                        in 2012 and dependent, it appears, on venture capital. See <ref
                            target="https://sketchfab.com/about"
                        >https://sketchfab.com/about</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>Finally, it is worth imagining a few other possibilities that could be realized
                    given current technology. Stephen Smith, a developer for Bible Gateway, recently
                    envisioned the use of AR akin to Microsoft’s HoloLens, an untethered (wearable)
                    holographic computer.<note>See <ref
                            target="https://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-hololens/"
                            >https://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-hololens/</ref>; cf. the similar
                        technology being developed by Magic Leap, a secretive but much-hyped
                            <q>Mixed Reality</q> start-up (<ref
                            target="https://www.magicleap.com; http://www.wired.com/2016/04/magic-leap-vr/"
                            >https://www.magicleap.com;
                            http://www.wired.com/2016/04/magic-leap-vr/</ref>).</note> With the
                    HoloLens, a user looks through a lens, seeing the real world, while the computer
                    projects images upon the lens in 3D, creating a holographic effect. In Smith’s
                    example, a physical desk upon which sits an open Bible is overlaid with
                    holographic digital texts and tools that a user can manipulate (<ref
                        target="#figure12">Figure 12</ref>). It is not difficult to also imagine a
                    holographic display of a scroll, a codex, or even the site of a manuscript’s
                    discovery.</p>

                <figure xml:id="figure12">
                    <head>Holographic display of reference helps projected onto a desk
                        (hypothetical). Photo modified by Stephen Smith, used with permission.<note>
                            Original photo and description appears on Smith’s blog: <ref
                                target="https://www.openbible.info/blog/2015/01/your-next-bible-will-be-a-hologram/"
                                >https://www.openbible.info/blog/2015/01/your-next-bible-will-be-a-hologram/</ref></note></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>Imagine a virtual reading room in which is stored all of the extant manuscripts
                    of the biblical text that have been digitized — a kind of virtual critical
                    edition. The user, seated at a desk, can <soCalled>open</soCalled> and read any
                    of the objects, perhaps using a printed Bible in translation as the
                    point-of-entry. When selected, Codex Sinaiticus appears on the desk, rendered in
                    3D and in true-to-life relative size to the Bible, the desk, and, say, a measure
                    on the desk. If a particular manuscript is, in reality, distributed in various
                    parts across different libraries, then in the virtual world, a user could either
                    view each part separately or view a virtual reconstruction of the whole. A fully
                    fledged critical edition seems technically feasible, although the computing
                    power required may be beyond the capacity of today’s personal VR devices.</p>
                <p>What these real and hypothetical AR and VR examples suggest is that these
                    technologies have the potential to capture textual history in a way that current
                    book technologies do not. These also show that the employment of AR and VR for
                    the texts creates engagement that is not only more visual (in the sense of added
                    depth perception and dimensionality) but auditory and kinesthetic.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>This exploration leads us to make some practical suggestions. First, we must not
                    underestimate the <emph>meaningfulness</emph> of paratexts, not least on our
                    apprehension of the text’s past. Thus, when creating any representation of a
                    text or manuscript (a digital representation, a critical edition, etc.), care
                    should be taken in preserving the original paratexts, and consideration should
                    be given to the new paratexts created in the production of the digital
                    representation. For digitized manuscripts especially, representations should
                    attempt to imitate the original paratexts as closely as possible (an excellent
                    example is the Isaiah Scroll in <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> above). </p>
                <p>Second, those undertaking digitization projects should consider cutting edge
                    technologies and their future trajectories and, accordingly, capture as much
                    information as possible in their digitization work. Along these lines, David
                    Parker says: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#parker2003">In transcribing Codex Sinaiticus, I
                            found myself seeking new ways of indicating just what I found. ...Should
                            I indicate which letters were written smaller at the end of a line? How
                            should I indicate punctuation, paragraphing, the Eusebian apparatus, and
                            the running titles? ...At the end of this process it was clear that the
                            activity on which I was engaged was quite different in character from
                            collating. I was trying to decide what features in the manuscript I
                            could and should represent in my transcription, and then finding ways of
                            doing so. And I was thinking not only about the possibilities
                            immediately available to me, but also about possibilities that might be
                            available to scholars at a future date, if only I had the forethought to
                            set out my material in such a way that they could capture it for their
                            own ends.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#parker2003" loc="398"/>
                    </cit> In view of AR, VR, and other 3D applications, this means that digital
                    photos of manuscripts and books should include the outside of the book at
                    multiple angles. Related to this, efforts to establish digital standards that
                    directly or indirectly affect texts (e.g., protocols, file types, markup
                    languages, etc.) would likewise benefit from such future-looking considerations. </p>
                <p>Third, textual critics should consider the potential of 3D technologies like AR
                    and VR for the analysis of textual objects. VR and holographic AR especially
                    have the potential to represent manuscripts in a compelling real-to-life and
                    true-to-size manner. Fourth, we have seen that many AR applications are used in
                    educational contexts. Educators will thus want to think critically about how AR
                    and VR may enhance and restrict the learning experiences they wish to create,
                    and for texts, the ways in which the technology captures or obscures textual
                    history. </p>


                <p>Finally, design specialists should have a crucial role in the productions of
                    digital texts. As Alan Galey rightly says: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#galey2010">If textual scholars tend to position
                            themselves at the threshold between the surfaces of texts and their
                            mysterious depths...then digital materials may lead them to new kinds of
                            thresholds. As in bibliography, questions about preserving and reading
                            digital artefacts lead inevitably to the topic of their design. Reading
                            the human presence in a digital artefact requires knowledge of markup,
                            encoding, and even programming, raising the problem of negotiating
                            multiple fields: on the one hand, textual scholarship (which some take
                            to include book history, or at least to overlap substantially with it);
                            and on the other, <emph>interface design</emph> as a catch-all term for
                            a practice that brings together human-computer interaction, information
                            design, usability studies, and programming. Textual scholarship’s close
                            ties with book history significantly complicate its relationship with
                            design — though such complexity can be productive.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#galey2010" loc="107"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>In sum, we have sought to demonstrate a few ways in which technology
                        <emph>means</emph>. This was done by observing some of the ways that book
                    technologies, by virtue of their paratexts, convey meaning about their texts’
                    histories, often obscuring that history. In real and hypothetical examples, it
                    was suggested that AR and VR technologies have great potential for overcoming,
                    or at least offsetting, some of the limitations of common textual technologies.
                </p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clivaz2015" label="Clivaz 2015">Clivaz, C. 2015. <title rend="quotes"
                        >New Testament in a Digital Culture: A <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                            >Biblaridon</foreign> (Little Book) Lost in Web?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Journal of Religion, Media and Digital Culture</title>
                    3 (3): 20–38.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ehrmanetal2012" label="Ehrman et al. 2012">Ehrman, B.D. and Holmes M.
                    W. 2012. <title rend="italic">The Text of the New Testament in Contemporary
                        Research: Essays on the Status Queastionis. Second Edition.</title>
                    Brill.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eisenstein1979" label="Eisenstein 1979">
                    <title rend="italic">The Printing Press as an Agent of Change: Communications
                        and Cultural Transformations in Early Modern Europe</title> Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ferré 1995" xml:id="ferre1995">Ferré, F. 1995. <title rend="italic"
                        >Philosophy of Technology</title>. Athens: University of Georgia.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galey2010" label="Galey 2010">Galey, A. <title rend="quotes">The Human
                        Presence in Digital Artefacts.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Text and Genre in Reconstruction: Effects of Digitalization
                        on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and Institutions</title>, edited by Willard
                    McCarty, Open Book Publishers, 2010, pp. 93–117.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gamble1995" label="Gamble 1995">Gamble, H.Y. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction</title>. <title rend="italic">Books and Readers in the Early
                        Church: A history of Early Christian Texts</title>. Yale University Press,
                    1995.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="genette1997" label="Genette 1997">Genette, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >Paratexts: Thresholds of Interpretation Literature, Theory,
                    Culture</title>, Cambridge University Press, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jansen2014" label="Jansen 2014">Jansen, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction: Approaches to Roman Paratextuality</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">The Roman Paratext: Frame, Texts, Readers</title>, edited by
                    Jansen L. Cambridge, 2014, pp. 1–19.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccarty2013" label="McCarty 2013">McCarty, W. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction</title>. <title rend="italic">Text and Genre Reconstruction:
                        Effects of Digitalization on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and
                        Institutions</title> Cambridge University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mckenzie1999" label="McKenzie 2005">McKenzie, D.F. <title
                        rend="italic">Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts</title>. Cambridge
                    University Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="metzgeretal2005" label="Metzger 2005">Metzger, B.M. and B.D. Ehrman.
                        <title rend="italic">The Text of the New Testament: Its Transmission,
                        Corruption, and Restoration</title>. 4th ed. New York: Oxford University
                    Press, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parker2003" label="Parker 2003">Parker, D.C. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Through a Screen Darkly: Digital Texts and the New Testaments</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal for the Study of the New Testament</title> 25
                    (4), 2003, pp. 395–411.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richards1998" label="Richards 1998">Richards, E.R. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Codex and the Early Collection of Paul's Letters</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Bulletin for Biblical Research</title> 8, 1998, pp.
                    151–166.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sprat1702" label="Sprat 1702">Sprat T. <title rend="italic">The
                        History of the Royal Society of London for the Improving of Natural
                        Knowledge</title>. London: T.R., 1702.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="skeat1994" label="Skeat 1994">Skeat, T.C. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Origin of the Christian Codex</title>. <title rend="italic">Zeitschrift fur
                        Papyrologie und Epgraphik</title>. 1994. pp. 263–268.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="small1997" label="Small 1997">Small, J.P. <title rend="italic">Wax
                        Tablets of the Mind: Cognitive Studies of Memory and Literacy in Classical
                        Antiquity</title>. London: Routledge, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tov2012" label="Tov 2012">Tov E. <title rend="italic">Textual
                        Criticism of the Hebrew Bible</title>. Fortress Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vandijk2014" label="van Dijk 2014">van Dijk, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Margins of Bookishness: Paratexts in Digital Literature</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Examining Paratextual Theory and its Applications in Digital
                        Culture</title>. Edited by N. Desrochers and D. Apollon, Hersey, PA: IGI
                    Global, 2014, pp. 24–45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wallraff2015" label="Wallraff 2015">Wallraff, M. and P. Andrist.
                        <title rend="quotes">Paratexts of the Bible: A new Research Project on Greek
                        Textual Transmission</title>. <title rend="italic">Early
                        Christianity</title> 6 (2), pp. 237–243.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
