<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Model of Versions and Layers</title>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Desmond <dhq:family>Schmidt</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Charles Harpur Critical Archive</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>desmond.allan.schmidt@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>Desmond Schmidt trained as a classicist, graduating from the
                        University of Queensland in 1981, obtaining his first PhD at the
                        University of Cambridge, UK on the Greek lyric poet Bacchylides in
                        1987, and his second in Information Technology from the University of
                        Queensland in 2010. He has worked as a software engineer in
                        information security, text-mining and user interface design. He has
                        also worked on a number of digital editions including the Vienna
                        Edition of Wittgenstein, Digital Variants at University Roma Tre and
                        the Charles Harpur Critical Archive.</p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000430</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2019-10-14">14 October 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability><cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-10-11" who="murelj">Added vol nos. and author edits</change>
            <change who="murelj" when="2019-11-05">Created article</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Our libraries are full of manuscripts, many of them modern. However, the
                    digitisation of these unique documents is currently very expensive. How can
                    we reduce the cost of encoding them in a way that will facilitate their
                    study, annotation, searching, sharing, editing, comparison and reading over
                    the Web? Unlike new documents prepared for the Web, historical manuscripts
                    frequently contain internal variation in the form of erasures, insertions,
                    substitutions and transpositions. Variation is also often expressed
                    externally between copies of one work: in successive print editions, in
                    manuscript copies or successive drafts. Current practice is to prepare
                    separate transcriptions of each physical document and to embed internal
                    variation directly into the transcribed text using complex markup codes.
                    This makes the transcriptions expensive to produce and hard to edit, limits
                    text reuse and requires that transcriptions be first disentangled via
                    customised software for reading, searching, or comparison.</p>
                <p>An alternative approach, described here, is to separate out the internal
                    variation of each document into notional layers. This is done primarily in
                    order to facilitate the recording of revisions at any one point. The move
                    is, of course, counter-intuitive since these document-wide layers were not
                    intended by the author as texts to be read. But it proves itself in practice
                    by radically simplifying the tasks of editing, searching and comparison.
                    Versions, on the other hand, are higher-level constructs that do represent
                    the state of a text as it was left at some point in time by an author or
                    scribe.</p>
                <p>By employing layers to record complex revisions, the task of computing
                    differences among intra-document layers and against versions of the same
                    work in multiple documents may be delegated to the machine rather than
                    having to be recorded laboriously by hand. The ensuing simplification of
                    markup reduces transcription and editing costs, boosts text reuse and
                    searching, and, by removing the need for customised software, increases the
                    longevity of digital transcriptions.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Presents a critique of current text-encoding practices centered on difficulties
                concerning the encoding of multiple versions of individual texts</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
                <head>A Model of Versions and Layers</head>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>The task of the modern editor often starts with a digital recording of the
                        contents of original documents written on a variety of physical media. If
                        produced by a machine, such as a printing press, text presents itself for
                        encoding as a sequence of characters arranged into evenly spaced lines
                        contained in one or more columns per page. In practice, though, even the
                        printed text of a single document will contain many errors: obvious
                        misspellings, gaps, duplicated words, misprints etc. <ptr target="#shillingsburg1996" loc="134f"/>.
                        Depending on its age it may also contain ligatures and
                        abbreviations whose expansion into more modern forms may seem necessary to
                        its editor <ptr target="#greetham1994" loc="159"/>. The corrected and expanded text thus
                        represents another version of what seemed at first glance to be easily
                        representable via a simple sequence of character codes.</p>
                    <p>Another class of documents that contain hidden internal variation is the
                        professionally produced medieval manuscript. Trained scribes worked in
                        scriptoria to laboriously copy out each line neatly for reading. Although
                        they were careful, mistakes were common. Haplography or dittography are two
                        well-known types (where material was inadvertently left out or added).
                        Incorporating readings from a second exemplar when the first one was
                        deficient, corrections by a second hand and of course numerous ligatures are
                        just some of the textual phenomena that complicate the transcription process
                        <ptr target="#greetham1994" loc="279ff"/>.</p>
                    <p> A further type of document containing internal variants is the modern
                        holograph manuscript revised by its author. Since in most cases the changes
                        are in the same hand and ink-colour, it may be difficult to discern a clear
                        sequence of revisions. The writer may have tinkered with the text over an
                        extended period of time. The result may not be entirely legible, but even if
                        it is, unravelling the sequence of script-acts that created it is usually
                        conjectural <ptr target="#pierazzo2009"/>.</p>
                    <p>To transcribe each text fully, no matter its provenance, thus requires some
                        way to represent textual variation both within the document and also between
                        documents: original and successive manuscript drafts, fair copies and, for
                        printed works, typescripts and proofs, first and later editions.</p>
                    <p>There is still no satisfactory commercial solution to these two linked
                        problems, and even if there were, any tools would necessarily be subject to
                        the commercial software lifecycle, which for major products is estimated to
                        last around 8–12 years <ptr target="#sandborn2012" loc="143–155"/>. Although open source
                        software is immune to some of its effects, it is still subject to platform
                        and media obsolescence, that is, to the obsolescence of dependent services
                        and tools <ptr target="#jenab2014"/>. This situation is not at all what humanists
                        want. Ideally, they would like digital texts and the software that goes with
                        them to have the same stability as printed books.</p>
                    <p>Our libraries are replete with manuscripts. For example, the National Library
                        of Australia has 16 kilometres of shelf space dedicated to manuscripts <ptr target="#nla2016"/>,
                        and other large libraries have similar holdings. What is to become of
                        even the smallest proportion of this material deemed worthy to be digitised
                        one day, not as hard-to-read image files, but with their contents
                        transcribed for editorial purposes and sophisticated end-use? Will they have
                        to be remade every 10–20 years because technology has moved on? In that case
                        the cost alone of maintaining existing transcriptions and software is likely
                        to consume all available resources. By contrast, the shelf life of the
                        printed book extends back to its inception in the 15th century. Anyone who
                        has handled an incunable will marvel at the quality of the paper, the
                        clarity (if antiquated appearance) of its type. How can our digital texts
                        even begin to approach this kind of longevity?</p>
                    <p>The problem reduces to this: any technology beyond the most common and stable
                        variety is doomed to become obsolete within its normal lifecycle of around
                        10–20 years. Beyond the mere recording of data, customised computer programs
                        required to manipulate and present the textual data will become obsolete
                        even sooner without constant maintenance. Continuously seeking after a
                        supposedly final technology that will immortalise new editorial work is thus
                        unlikely to succeed. In practice, change is constant, and may come so fast
                        that the chosen technology becomes obsolete even before an editorial project
                        ends <ptr target="#göbel2015"/>.</p>
                    <p>Is there any answer to this problem, or is it simply the natural property of
                        digital text and the software needed to manipulate it that renders both
                        ephemeral? Fortunately, certain digital technologies seem to endure far
                        longer than others. For example, the Unicode standard arose by incorporating
                        earlier smaller character encoding standards like ASCII (1963) then
                        ISO-8859-1 (1987), culminating in the Unicode standard itself (1991). To
                        change the assignation of letters to codes in this basic character set would
                        invalidate billions of texts worldwide for no overall benefit. So it is not
                        far-fetched to suppose that in, say, 100 years time, a digital file
                        containing nothing but Unicode character codes will continue to be readable.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, what is proposed here is a simple use of the most basic and
                        stable digital technologies to encode the contents of complex historical
                        documents. If the approach is successful, any software of current or future
                        design would then be able to manipulate those documents into useful forms.
                        The guiding idea is that the less technology we put into our digitally
                        recorded texts the more useful and durable they will be in the future.</p>
                    <p>This proposal has nothing to do either with the technology used to manipulate
                        encoded texts, or with the editorial method for creating them. It is
                        orthogonal to both; and is, rather, a simple but effective strategy for
                        recording transcriptions of complex original documents in digital form. To
                        explain how this works in practice, the second section below develops a
                        model of versions and layers through a series of real-world examples. The
                        third and fourth sections then describe the advantages and disadvantages of
                        this rearrangement of digital textual data as it relates to the scholarly
                        edition. Finally, the fifth section explains in abstract terms how these
                        texts can be used to make digital scholarly editions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. A model of versions and layers</head>
                    <p>This model of versions and layers originally developed out of the author’s
                        own work on the manuscripts of Ludwig Wittgenstein <ptr target="#nedo1993" loc="73–77"/>.
                        It is most closely related to what Hans Walter Gabler calls the <quote rend="inline">German
                        school of editorial scholarship</quote>, including the historical-critical edition,
                        in which the <quote rend="inline">critical</quote> component referred not so much to the establishment
                        of the text but to the analysis or critique of the text’s genesis and
                        history <ptr target="#gabler"/>. Gabler perhaps coined the term <q>layers</q> in his 1986
                        edition of Ulysses <ptr target="#gabler1986"/> although the concept seems to apply only
                        to levels of local revision. The same concept was taken over into the
                        HyperNietzsche Markup Language <ptr target="#saller2003"/>. A similar approach is also
                        taken in genetic editions like Dietrich Sattler’s Hölderlin, where the
                        apparatus is placed inline by graphically arranging variants above the line
                        of text they pertain to. As Sattler says, this results in a text where the
                        variants are readable in their true context, not removed to a distant
                        apparatus <ptr target="#sattler1979"/>. The concept is basically the same here, except
                        that it has been translated from the printed page into a simple arrangement
                        of plain-text files.</p>
                    <p>Out of the three classes of texts described in the introduction: printed
                        books, medieval manuscript copies of earlier texts and modern holographs,
                        the examples explored below use mostly the third category. This is because
                        the model pertains to the process of writing itself, not to a particular
                        text-type. Holographs were chosen because they typically exhibit higher
                        levels of internal variation than the other two, and for the model to be
                        universal it has to cater for the worst-case scenario. This is not meant to
                        imply that the three classes of text are equivalent, except in so far as
                        they all represent the phenomena of writing or printing on paper, parchment
                        or other physical surfaces.</p>
                    <p>The examples are mostly taken from the manuscripts of the Australian poet
                        Charles Harpur (1813-1868). The Charles Harpur Critical Archive <ptr target="#eggert2019"/>
                        has obtained permission from their owner, the State Library of New
                        South Wales, to publish the images and content of all Harpur-related
                        material in its possession. Also, thanks to recent changes in Australian
                        copyright law, from 2019 unpublished manuscripts will have the same
                        copyright duration — 70 years after the death of the author — as printed
                        works <ptr target="#nla2017"/>. So these texts form a very useful set of freely available
                        examples from which to develop the model described here. They are also very
                        varied in nature, consisting of newspaper cuttings, printed pamphlets and
                        books, drafts of corrected manuscripts and letters. As will be demonstrated
                        below, only a very small number of basic editing operations on handwritten
                        texts are needed to put the proposed model of versions and layers into
                        practice. The focus on Harpur does not introduce a bias because all the
                        textual phenomena being explored here
                        <note><p><hi rend="superscript">1.</hi> i.e. transpositions, connected
                                    variants, open variants, incoherent corrections, separately
                                    revised test-blocks, and restoration of previously deleted
                                    text.</p></note>
                        are common to virtually all handwritten
                        texts, and examples of each phenomenon have been verified as also existing
                        in the manuscripts of Melville’s <title rend="italic">Typee</title> <ptr target="#bryant2009"/>,
                        Wittgenstein <ptr target="#pichler2016"/>, Samuel Beckett <ptr target="#vanhulle2015"/>,
                        the Faust Edition <ptr target="#bohnenkamp2016"/> and the Shelley-Godwin
                        Archive <ptr target="#fraistat2018"/>. The markup schema described in the Text
                        Encoding Initiative Guidelines Chapter 11 <title rend="quotes">Transcription of Primary Sources</title>
                        provides higher-level or finer grained descriptions of these same basic
                        textual phenomena <ptr target="#tei2017"/>. They can also be found in Bryant
                        <title rend="italic">The Fluid Text</title> <ptr target="#bryant2002"/>.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/image1.jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Figure 1 shows one stanza taken from Harpur’s poem <title rend="quotes">Vestibulary Stanzas</title> in
                        manuscript B78 written in 1855 <ptr target="#harpur1855" loc="11"/>. Seven changes can be
                        discerned:</p>
                    <list type="simple">
                    <item><p>line 2: the transposition of <q>is strung</q> and <q>too high</q></p></item>
                    <item><p>line 2: the replacement of the entire line by line 1</p></item>
                    <item><p>line 4: the replacement of <q>thy</q> by <q>his</q></p></item>
                    <item><p>line 4: the replacement of <q>I do mark in</q> by <q>all may guess from</q></p></item>
                    <item><p>line 4: the replacement of <q>beaming eye</q> by <q>fervent tongue</q></p></item>
                    <item><p>line 5: the replacement of <q>blaze</q> by <q>fire</q></p></item>
                    <item><p>line 5: the replacement of <q>The inward rolling fire</q> by <q>How
                        burns the fire within</q></p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The temporal order of these changes can be determined in only two cases. It
                        is clear that the transposition in line 2 preceded its replacement by line
                        1. Also the replacement of <q>blaze</q> by <q>fire</q> in line 5 preceded the
                        replacement of <q>The inward rolling fire</q> by <q>How burns the fire within</q>.
                        Other than these inferences, the exact sequence of changes here is
                        unrecoverable. For instance, it is not clear if the poet changed line 2
                        before lines 4 and 5. All remaining changes have thus to be treated as
                        independent of one another.</p>
                    <p>Some definitions may now be put forward:</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Definition 1:</hi> A change is <term>independent</term> if it can be carried out without
                        affecting the sense, grammar or metre of the rest of the text.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Definition 2:</hi> A <term>state</term> is a hypothetical or
                        actual reading of part of the text before or after one or more independent
                        changes have been carried out or not. <note><p><hi rend="superscript">2.</hi> Scholarly editors typically
                            use the term ‘state’ to indicate a document- or version-wide
                            text. The technical requirement addressed here suggests its
                            adaptation for local sites of textual revision. In fact this
                            parallels, theoretically if not practically, the detection by
                            bibliographers from the 1940s of in-press correction during the
                            printing of Shakespeare’s First Folio. Printed sheets were not
                            discarded, leading to variation in states of the text among
                            copies made during the same print run. In the handpress period,
                            no two surviving copies of the same edition of a printed work
                            need necessarily bear the same state of the text.</p></note></p>
                    <p>For example, line 4 may have once been in any of the following states:</p>
                    <list type="simple">
                    <item>And I do mark in thy too beaming eye</item>
                    <item>And I do mark in thy too fervent tongue</item>
                    <item>And I do mark in his too beaming eye</item>
                    <item>And I do mark in his too fervent tongue</item>
                    <item>And all may guess from thy too beaming eye</item>
                    <item>And all may guess from thy too fervent tongue</item>
                    <item>And all may guess from his too beaming eye</item>
                    <item>And all may guess from his too fervent tongue</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>All possibilities are equally valid here, but the final
                        <q>state</q> of the entire line is clearly <quote rend="inline">And all may guess from his
                        too fervent tongue</quote>.</p>
                    <p>Also, following Bryant’s terminology, we offer:</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Definition 3:</hi> A <term>revision site</term> is a <term source="#bryant2002">hot-spot</term>
                        <ptr target="#bryant2002" loc="151"/> or cluster of
                        dependent changes at some point in the text-stream.</p>
                    <p>In Figure 2 the substitutions and deletions <q>the/his</q>, <q>whereon they/on which
                        his spirit</q>, <q>to burn</q>, <q>the/some</q>, <q>to burn</q> and <q>,</q> are revision-sites.
                        Changes that are local to one revision-site are less likely to be connected
                        with changes elsewhere in the same manuscript the further apart they are. A
                        change at the start of a document is very probably (although not certainly)
                        unrelated to a change at its end. Even changes in the same stanza, as in the
                        example above, are more likely to be unrelated than related.</p>
                    <p>Figure 2, from the same manuscript <ptr target="#harpur1855" loc="75"/>, is an example where
                        several changes are related by grammar and sense.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/image2.jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The two layers here are:</p>
                    <lg><label>1:</label> <l>(Each in the age, whereon they rose</l>
                    <l>To burn, like the peculiar stars of night,</l>
                    <l>Eternally apart, — )</l></lg>
                    <lg><label>2:</label> <l>(Each in his age, on which his spirit rose</l>
                    <l>like some peculiar star of night,</l>
                    <l>To burn Eternally apart — )</l></lg>
                    <p>The substitutions: <q>whereon they</q> by <q>on which his spirit</q> and <q>stars</q> by
                        <q>star</q> are related by grammar, and were presumably carried out at the same
                        time, not independently — the plural <q>stars</q> according with <q>they</q> and not
                        <q>his</q>. Similarly, the deletion of <q>To burn</q> and its reinsertion on the final
                        line are related by sense. However, each of these two sets of changes taken
                        as a whole is independent of the other, and thus acts as a single
                        independent change.</p>
                    <p>This independency of individual or grouped dependent changes has an
                        unfortunate mathematical consequence for storage. Each independent change
                        consists of at least two states (carried out or not), so over the entire
                        document the number of possible texts obtainable will be at least 2×2...or
                        2<hi rend="superscript">N</hi>, where N is the total number of
                        independent changes. In the single stanza in Figure 1, as described above,
                        there were 3 independent changes and two pairs of temporally dependent
                        changes, each having 3 states, for a total of 2<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>
                        ×3<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> = 72 possible texts. Over an
                        entire document the total number of possible texts will be exponentially
                        large. For just 100 independent changes we have 2<hi rend="superscript">100</hi>
                        or approximately 1.267 × 10<hi rend="superscript">30</hi>
                        possible texts or 1267 with 27 zeroes after it. Many documents will contain
                        far more changes than that. So any attempt to store all possible states of a
                        document’s contents in this exhaustive fashion is bound to fail.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.1 Layers</head>
                        <p>As already noted, the changes in lines 2 and 5 in Figure 1 are related in
                            time. In certain texts there may be temporal sequences of up to 10 or
                            more local substitutions, as in the Magrelli poem <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="it">La campagna Romana</title>
                            <ptr target="#fiormonte2010"/>. Each change belongs to a local point in time
                            or level, and the state of the text at each stage includes the context
                            that surrounds it. Since it is not possible to record all local states
                            separately in their version-wide contexts (because they are
                            exponentially too many) a simple solution is to assign all changes in
                            the document occurring at the same position in the <emph>local</emph>
                            temporal sequence to the <emph>same</emph>
                            numbered layer.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Definition 4:</hi> A <term>layer</term>
                            is a tracing of the documentary text from start to
                            finish that includes all the changes in each revision-site at a given
                            level, the unchanged text that lies between them and the final state of
                            other revision-sites that end at a lower level.</p>
                        <p>So instead of 72 layers for this stanza — the total number of possible
                            combinations of independent changes — only three are needed: the initial
                            state of each segment of text that undergoes change and its subsequent
                            states. For example, line 2 admits of three such states:</p>
                        <list type="simple">
                        <item><label>1:</label> Ah Poet! thy young heart is strung too high</item>
                        <item><label>2:</label> Ah Poet! thy young heart too high is strung</item>
                        <item><label>3:</label> But ah! too high his harp-like heart is strung</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Thus, to record the stanza’s text in its entirety requires only three
                            layers. The unrelated changes noted above require only 2 layers each,
                            and line 5 requires 3. If all the local states at a particular level are
                            merged into one layer, then each layer becomes a <emph>record</emph>
                            of the local states of change. Layer-1 would be the
                            text as it was originally throughout. Layer-2 is its state after the
                            first local change, and Layer-3 or Layer-final its state after a second
                            local change. This makes no claim that Layer-1 or Layer-2 ever existed
                            as a version-wide text: more on this, below. It is merely a way of
                            recording and storing all of the text of this complex document using
                            only the technology needed to record unchanged text. For clarity, here
                            are all the layers of Figure 1 written out in full:</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                        <item><lg><head>Layer-1</head>
                        <l>Ah Poet! thy young heart is strung too high</l>
                        <l>To bear the jars of this harsh world’s estate!</l>
                        <l>And I do mark in thy too beaming eye</l>
                        <l>The inward rolling blaze that bodes a wayward fate.</l></lg></item>
                        <item><lg><head>Layer-2</head>
                        <l>Ah Poet! thy young heart too high is strung</l>
                        <l>To bear the jars of this harsh world’s estate!</l>
                        <l>And all may guess from his too fervent tongue</l>
                        <l>The inward rolling fire that bodes a wayward fate.</l></lg></item>
                        <item><lg><head>Layer-final</head>
                        <l>But ah! too high his harp-like heart is strung</l>
                        <l>To bear the jars of this harsh world’s estate!</l>
                        <l>And all may guess from his too fervent tongue</l>
                        <l>How burns the fire within that bodes a wayward fate.</l></lg></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>An obvious objection here is that the author almost certainly never wrote
                            layers 1 and 2. Mathematically, the chances that he did so in this case
                            are just 1 in 72. However, so long as it is remembered that the only
                            layer that ought to be considered a <soCalled>version</soCalled> is
                            <q>Layer-final</q>, the objection is moot. Layers are merely a mechanism to
                            record local changes, <emph>not</emph> a record of how the
                            scribe or author wrote the document as a whole. They do not constitute
                            an ontological claim. So long as it is remembered which transcriptions
                            are layers, and which can be considered versions, no confusion should
                            arise.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.2 Deletion, insertion, substitution and transposition</head>
                        <p>The key advantage — the true efficiency — of layers is that they do away
                            with the need to explicitly record deletions, insertions, substitutions
                            and transpositions. Any text present in one layer and absent from a
                            subsequent layer can be assumed to be deleted. Likewise any text that
                            appears in a subsequent layer, where it was previously absent, is an
                            insertion. Text that is replaced by other text at the same location in a
                            subsequent layer can be regarded as substituted. Similarly, text that
                            appears transposed in a later layer can be considered transposed. On the
                            other hand, using current encoding techniques, text must be manually
                            labelled as <term>deleted</term>, <term>inserted</term>, <term>substituted</term> or <term>transposed</term> using
                            explicitly entered, complex markup codes <ptr target="#pierazzo2014a" loc="12"/>. This
                            considerable human effort is not needed if it can instead be undertaken
                            by a computer.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, by marking the text as <term>deleted</term> or <term>inserted</term> etc., current
                            digital encoding practice conflates the membership of an internal
                            variant in a particular layer with its graphical status, in effect
                            declaring that deleted text is in a <term>crossed-out</term> format, just as, say,
                            underlining is a format. But, unlike underlining, crossed-out text is
                            also replaced, perhaps by nothing (a deletion) or by something else (a
                            substitution). That these two operations — the assignment of a format
                            and the substitution — are separate and distinguishable is proven by the
                            case of open variants, where the earlier version of the text is not
                            crossed-out <ptr target="#vanhulle2011" loc="804"/>.</p>
                        <p>An example in Harpur can be found in <title rend="quotes">The Bard of Paradise</title> <ptr target="#harpur1863" loc="4"/>:</p>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image3.jpeg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Harpur first wrote <q>speckless</q> before squeezing in <q>gleaming</q> above it.
                            But <q>speckless</q> is not crossed-out and the added pair of brackets
                            indicates that the author considered them both viable alternatives that,
                            in this manuscript, he did not go on to resolve. For the proposed
                            layering approach the usual assumption that text in an earlier layer is
                            deleted may be resolved via markup. By this means the earlier variant
                            can be labelled as <q>undeleted</q> without overly complicating the encoding
                            of the layer itself. As we have seen, the layering approach is justified
                            by its efficiency: even in the very uncommon case of open variants when
                            markup cannot be avoided considerable savings in coding can nevertheless
                            be realised.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.3 Versions</head>
                        <p>Although the term <q>version</q> has been used variously by scholarly editors,
                            the definition proposed here is practical and simple:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Definition 5:</hi> A <term>version</term>
                            is a single document-wide state of the text,
                            determinable with reasonable certainty, in which the author or scribe
                            completed or abandoned the entire documentary text at some point in
                            time.</p>
                        <p>Although in most holographs the only determinable version is the final
                            layer or state of a manuscript, in some cases an individual manuscript
                            may be witness to more than one version. This section describes some
                            examples of this.</p>
                        <p>Harpur’s first draft of his sonnet <title rend="quotes">Trust in God</title> was written on the
                            inside back cover of a copy of his 1853 book <title rend="italic">The
                            Bushrangers</title> <ptr target="#harpur1853a"/>. He then
                            redrafted it on the inside front cover. Figure 4 shows this latter text,
                            which is mostly written in a dark-coloured ink with some corrections in
                            lighter ink. Disregarding the lighter corrections, the final layer of
                            the dark-ink version corresponds closely to the copy published in the
                            <title rend="italic">Empire</title> newspaper of 20 June 1853 as shown in
                            Figure 5 <ptr target="#harpur1853b"/>. A subsequent publication in the
                            <title rend="italic">Australian Home Companion</title> of 1859 (Figure 6)
                            accords with the state of the text after the final corrections in
                            lighter ink, with some changes to the pentultimate line <ptr target="#harpur1859"/>.
                            It can thus be seen that this manuscript contains two discernable
                            document-wide states of the text – two versions – each of which has its
                            own local corrections or layers.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image4.jpeg" />
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image5.jpeg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image6.jpeg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Professionally produced manuscripts may contain similar internal
                            versions. Many medieval manuscripts were corrected at different times,
                            sometimes by a corrector by comparison with an exemplar or with another
                            manuscript <ptr target="#pauly2003" loc="Copy"/>. An example known to the author is
                            the Ancient Greek Bacchylides papyrus written in the first century BC
                            <ptr target="#jebb1905" loc="126"/>, a section of which is shown in Figure 7
                            <ptr target="#jebb1905" loc="plate 1"/>.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image7.jpeg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The baseline text A was revised in three distinct hands
                            A<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, A<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> and A<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>.
                            A<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> is probably the scribe himself, fixing
                            simple mistakes of spelling. A<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> is probably
                            a different but contemporary hand in which titles are added in the
                            margins. A<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> is a Roman cursive hand of the
                            second century or later <ptr target="#jebb1905" loc="133"/>. So
                            A<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> is probably a layer of the first version, while
                            A<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> and A<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> form
                            two new versions, which subsume the final corrected texts of
                            A<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> and A<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                            respectively. In Figure 7 the three lines inserted at the top are by
                            A<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> (a faint marginal mark inserts them
                            before line 6), the title in the left margin <foreign xml:lang="grc">ΙΩ ΑΘΗΝΑΙΟΙΣ</foreign> was added by
                            A<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> and the correction of
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">ΧΑΛΚΕΝΤΥΠΟΥ</foreign> to
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">ΧΑΛΚΕΟΤΥΠΟΥ</foreign> in line 7 was by A<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Bryant likewise sees three internal versions in Melville’s
                            <title rend="italic">Typee</title> manuscript, which he calls <quote rend="inline">transcription,
                            transformation, and translation</quote> <ptr target="#bryant2008"/>. Van Hulle and Neyt
                            call internal versions <quote rend="inline">revision campaigns</quote> when they can be
                            reliably distinguished by a new writing instrument or change of ink <ptr target="#vanhulle2015"/>.</p>
                        <p>However, in the absence of such information about discernible pens or
                            differences in handwriting or style most holographs contain only one
                            version. It is up to the human editor to decide whether a correction
                            belongs to a specific layer or version.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Advantages of versions and layers</head>
                    <p>This model of versions and layers has certain advantages. These can be
                        appreciated through a comparison of the versions and layers model with the
                        current method of recording variants in manuscripts using inline embedded
                        markup.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.1 Problems with embedded markup</head>
                        <p>In the embedded markup method variants within a document are inserted
                            directly into the text-stream wherever the transcriber encounters a
                            revision-site.</p>
                        <p>Many markup languages have been proposed that adopt an embedded or inline
                            approach to recording variants. (In what follows the terms <q>inline</q> and
                            <q>embedded</q> are used interchangeably.) One of the earliest was MECS
                            (<term>multi-element encoding system</term>), which evolved from the Wittgenstein
                            markup developed at Tübingen in the 1970s <ptr target="#huitfeldt1993"/>. The same
                            technique was later used in the TEI (Text Encoding Initiative)
                            Guidelines, and in many ad hoc markup systems developed for individual
                            editions, such as the Tagore Bichitra <ptr target="#tagore"/>. In order to
                            illustrate the disadvantages of inline recording of variants, a simple
                            hypothetical markup language may be used that maintains the generality
                            of the argument, while ensuring clarity, without reference to any
                            specific system of markup. The language is defined by four rules:</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Deletions are enclosed in <q>[</q> and <q>]</q>.</item>
                        <item>Insertions are enclosed in <q>&lt;</q> and <q>&gt;</q>.</item>
                        <item>Insertions and deletions may nest: inner ones are earlier than those
                            on the outside.</item>
                        <item>Insertions and deletions that immediately follow one another with no
                            intervening spaces indicate a temporal succession from left to
                            right.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Although they may use different syntaxes these simple rules are followed
                            by all markup languages that are used to record inline variants. For
                            example, the text of Figure 1 could be transcribed in this markup
                            language as follows:</p>
                        <lg>
                        <l>[Ah, Poet! thy young [heart is strung too high]&lt;too high
                            is strung&gt;]&lt;But ah! too high his harp-like heart is strung&gt;</l>
                        <l>To bear the jars of this harsh world’s estate!</l>
                        <l>And [I do mark in]&lt;all may guess from&gt;
                            [thy]&lt;his&gt; too [beaming eye]&lt;fervent tongue&gt;</l>
                        <l>[[The inward rolling][blaze]&lt;fire&gt;]&lt;How burns the
                            fire within&gt; that bodes a wayward fate.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p>The presence of the embedded variants here makes it difficult for a human
                            editor to see in what state the text was at any stage in its revision,
                            and requires him or her to visualise a complex series of steps using
                            abstract symbols. The heavier the corrections the harder this task
                            becomes. Occasionally our trained Harpur transcribers would even decline
                            to encode Harpur’s more complex passages. For instance, one noted:
                            <quote rend="inline">Lines 15 and 31 contain numerous additions and deletions; only the
                            final intentions have been transcribed here.</quote></p>
                        <p>Searching will also be impaired, since the inline variants interfere with
                            the retrieval of literal expressions. Search engines typically don’t see
                            the markup. All they see is the text in the nonsensical word-order given
                            above. As a result, searching for the literal phrase <q>All may guess from
                            his too fervent tongue</q>, as finally formulated by the author, will
                            <emph>not</emph> be found, while the expression ‘rolling blaze
                            fire How burns the fire within’ <emph>will</emph> be found,
                            even though the author never wrote it.
                        <note><p><hi rend="superscript">3.</hi>While keyword search will
                                        retrieve all documents containing all or most of the words
                                        in a search expression but in any order, literal search is
                                        more useful for finding specific expressions. A survey by
                                        the author of 30 digital scholarly editions revealed that
                                        only 10% of editions could find literal expressions that
                                        span inline substitutions <ptr target="#schmidt2016b"/>.</p></note></p>
                        <p>When comparing two versions of a text, inline variants get in the way and
                            must first be removed <ptr target="#juxta2013"/><ptr target="#dekker2015"/>. Computer
                            algorithms commonly used in the humanities for collating texts such as
                            Heckel (1978) and Myers (1987) are not designed to handle inline
                            variants. And no one has yet demonstrated a reliable method for
                            comparing texts that contain them, or proven that it is technically
                            feasible.
                        <note><p><hi rend="superscript">4.</hi>Dekker et al. 2015 attempt to
                                        overcome this problem by treating internal variants either
                                        as formats, or by marking them up as variant clusters to be
                                        passed through the collation engine without change. However,
                                        as yet they have offered no mathematical model that might
                                        vindicate this approach as a general solution for comparing
                                        texts containing embedded variants. Schäuble and Gabler
                                        (2018) achieved a partial success by extracting the first
                                        and last layers of document transcriptions containing
                                        embedded variants, and then used a collation tool to compute
                                        the differences between versions which were then used to
                                        create an intermediary transcription between documents
                                        <ptr target="#schäuble2018" loc="167"/>. The <quote rend="inline">first</quote> layer includes
                                <term xml:lang="la">currente calamo</term> corrections <ptr target="#schäuble2018" loc="170"/>, both
                                        deletions and their replacements.</p></note></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.2 Difficulty of overcoming these problems</head>
                        <p>One obvious solution to some of these problems would be to write a
                            program to extract coherent texts from the embedded encoding, retrieving
                            either the first, last or intermediary stages in the text’s evolution.
                            However, in practice this is either difficult or impossible to achieve,
                            for three main reasons.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>3.2.1 <term xml:lang="la">Currente calamo</term> corrections</head>
                            <p>The original state of a text before any changes were made might seem
                                to be one that could be readily recovered from an embedded encoding
                                of variants, by simply accepting only first-level variants and
                                simple deletions, and rejecting all others. However, the presence of
                                corrections made in the process of writing, or
                                <term xml:lang="la">currente calamo</term>, as shown in Figure 8
                                <ptr target="#harpur1863" loc="359"/>, makes this difficult or impossible. </p>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image8.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>Here the author progressively revised the text as he wrote it. He
                                started the sentence with <quote rend="inline">All his</quote>, then corrected this immediately
                                to <quote rend="inline">The whole of his poetry</quote>. Later he started writing <quote rend="inline">his
                                political effusions lack th...</quote> then corrected this to <quote rend="inline">his
                                political effusions are wanting...</quote> then corrected the last two
                                words to: <quote rend="inline">are greatly wanting</quote>. All these changes were carried out
                                    <term>on the baseline</term>. Simply encoding them as
                                deletions — as they appear on the page — and then writing a program
                                to extract the <soCalled>original</soCalled> text before deletion would result in the
                                nonsense: <quote rend="inline">All his The whole of his poetry would be better for more
                                plainness; while his political effusions lack th are wanting greatly
                                wanting....</quote></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>3.2.2 Interpretation in markup</head>
                            <p>Marking up a text is generally agreed to be an interpretative act
                                <ptr target="#sperberg-mcqueen2000"/> <ptr target="#durusau2006"/> <ptr target="#bauman2011"/>.
                                Interpretation must therefore govern the choice of codes and their
                                application to the representation of inline variants. Extracting
                                coherent texts for searching, reading, or comparison from such
                                transcriptions thus requires, at the very least, the writing of
                                customised software for each set of documents encoded in a
                                project-specific set of conventions. This is further complicated by
                                the fact that even trained encoders have different understandings of
                                what they are looking at on the page and therefore how to encode it.
                                They may even change their encoding practice from day to day
                                <ptr target="#durusau2006"/>. For Harpur we found that over 30 different ways had
                                been used by just three transcribers to record second-level
                                corrections. Even if an encoding can be made syntactically
                                consistent we must ask can it also be made <emph>semantically</emph>
                                consistent: i.e. does each specific instance
                                of an encoding always mean exactly the same thing, and is the same
                                kind of textual phenomenon always encoded in the same way?</p>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image9.jpeg"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>An example of the potential for semantic variation is shown in Figure
                                9. Taken from an early manuscript of <title rend="quotes">Dawn and Sunrise in the Snowy
                                Mountains</title> <ptr target="#harpur1849-63" loc="573"/>, the revisions at the start
                                of the line might be validly encoded in our simplified markup
                                language as <q>And Then [And]</q> or equally as <q>&lt;And Then&gt;[And]</q>
                                or as <q>&lt;And &lt;Then&gt;&gt;[And]</q>. However, the use of capitals
                                at the start of all three words indicates that Harpur revised the
                                text by gradually adding words to the left, so a better encoding
                                might be to reverse the order: [And][&lt;Then&gt;]&lt;And Then&gt;.
                                The question then becomes, how can software process alternative
                                formulations of the same thing in a consistent fashion, and how can
                                it determine the context of each change?</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>3.2.3. Conflict between graphical and temporal encoding</head>
                            <p>Recording the graphical appearance of the text on the page via the
                                embedded markup method described above makes the extraction of the
                                temporal succession of local changes virtually impossible <ptr target="#schmidt2014" loc="§5"/>.
                                For example, most transcribers would record line 1 of
                                Figure 1 before line 2, but the temporal sequence is actually 2, 1.
                                Another example is the use of inserted blocks of text. Like many
                                authors, Harpur sometimes redrafts heavily revised portions of his
                                text in the margins or on separate pages, as shown in Figure 10
                                <ptr target="#harpur1855-62" loc="44–45"/>. Due to the complex encoding required
                                for inline variants in such cases, encoders tend to record such
                                blocks separately and to specify their graphical layout (e.g.
                                position, orientation) rather than integrate the textual changes
                                they contain as part of the main text <ptr target="#muñoz2015"/>,
                                and then record their temporal sequence, if ascertainable.</p>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image10.jpeg"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>The temporal sequence of local changes is usually recoverable.
                                Authors provide many cues such as the position of inserted text,
                                deletion marks, sense, the carrying over of changes into revised
                                blocks, etc. that make this possible, even in extreme cases like
                                that shown in Figure 10. A survey of 1,247 local revision-sites in
                                the manuscripts of Harpur revealed that the temporal sequence of
                                changes could be recovered with a high degree of probability in
                                99.45% of cases. In the doubtful cases, while the layering approach
                                does require the assignment of variants to specific layers, there is
                                no comparative disadvantage. This is because the embedded variant
                                method also requires the assignment of variants to an explicit
                                sequence or nesting of markup.</p>
                            <p>Writing software to reliably process transcriptions coded for the
                                graphical layout of text into a coherent sequence of temporal layers
                                is ‘challenging’, even for a single project. Such software requires
                                the transcription either to be weighed down with extra encoding in
                                addition to the already heavy markup needed to describe the text’s
                                graphical layout <ptr target="#muñoz2015"/>, or to be encoded
                                twice: once for the graphical layout and once to describe the
                                temporal or <soCalled>linear</soCalled> sequence <ptr target="#rehbein2013"/> <ptr target="#vanhulle2015"/>.
                                The editing of transcriptions and their subsequent
                                reuse are thus impaired <ptr target="#muñoz2015"/> <ptr target="#brüning2013"/>.</p>
                            <p>It looks then as if embedding variants directly into the text-stream
                                at each revision-site leads to serious and insurmountable problems,
                                which can only be resolved by <emph>not</emph> embedding
                                variants into the transcription in the first place. What the layered
                                approach offers instead is a far simpler data model that has no need
                                of customised software to make text readable, searchable and
                                comparable — for it already is.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.3 Ease of Editing</head>
                        <p>The model of versions and layers also has other advantages. Since the
                            text no longer contains complex markup to describe internal variation it
                            can be edited easily. The only remaining textual features that need to
                            be represented via inline markup are fairly simple textual formats at
                            the paragraph or character levels. Having a readable text mostly devoid
                            of complex markup to compare with the facsimile of the original speeds
                            up initial transcription too. Although as many as nine layers may be
                            required for complex cases, this is mostly confined to a few heavily
                            revised poetical texts. For longer works, such as chapters of a novel,
                            one to three layers should suffice.</p>
                        <p> Layers are not definitive, and like all text files can be easily changed
                            after initial transcription by the human editor to reflect changing
                            interpretations of the text or increased knowledge of the author’s
                            habits. Layers offer an alternative way of organising the same data as
                            inline markup seeks to encode but in a far simpler form.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.4 Longevity</head>
                        <p>Another key advantage is longevity. The representation of versions and
                            layers generated by the model requires only Unicode text, than which, as
                            already pointed out, there is nothing more stable in the digital
                            world.</p>
                        <p>Although text is one of the most compact forms of data, each layer
                            requires a complete copy of the document, including its local changes.
                            In most cases this is limited to two or three layers. In the case of
                            Charles Harpur, one poem, <title rend="quotes">Sir Gilbert Blount</title>, required nine layers
                            <ptr target="#harpur1865-67" loc="68–69"/>. Apart from a few cases like this, out a
                            corpus of 4,596 manuscript pages, the average number of layers needed
                            per manuscript version was only 2.1. Modern computers have many
                            gigabytes of storage to accommodate movies, images and sound files that
                            are many times larger than such simple text files as these.</p>
                        <p>Layers can be grouped within folders or directories, one folder for each
                            version, and one over-arching folder for each work containing the
                            versions. The use of file directories likewise goes back to Multics in
                            the 1960s and hence has a similar pedigree to ASCII. Like Unicode, it
                            can be assumed it will continue to exist into the distant future.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Disadvantages of versions and layers</head>
                    <p>The main disadvantage of the layering and versioning approach is, at present,
                        its unfamiliarity. Current editors of modern manuscripts who, are used to
                        embedding variants in the transcription as they encounter them, would need
                        to adjust their practice. Technicians who process the transcriptions would
                        also need to learn new, albeit simpler, techniques. To be adapted to the new
                        approach existing texts would have to be converted by splitting them into
                        layers. Although practicable, this would involve some customisation of the
                        conversion software to accommodate different encoding conventions, as well
                        as manual intervention in difficult cases of textual variation. These costs
                        would not be insignificant, but they would all be short-term, and outweighed
                        by the longer-term benefits. For new projects using layers from the start
                        these problems would not exist.</p>
                    <p>The computation of differences between versions and layers is sometimes
                        imperfect. For example, in the text of Figure 11 <ptr target="#harpur1836-68" loc="410"/>:
                        <quote rend="inline">Nought might reward <hi rend="strikethrough">the his</hi> the
                        <hi rend="strikethrough">aim</hi> blow, however true;</quote> a difference tool
                        would compute the second <q>the</q> to be shared by layers 1 and 3, whereas in
                        fact it was deleted and then restored.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/image11.jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In the Harpur manuscripts about 2% of inline variants are restorations of
                        earlier readings. Although this detail is not recorded in the layer
                        representation itself it will still be visible in the facsimile, and if the
                        page image is connected closely with the text this can easily be checked by
                        the reader or editor. Although small inaccuracies such as these may be
                        inherent in the layer model they are very much dwarfed by the widely
                        recognised inaccuracies and limitations of hierarchical markup systems for
                        representing internal variation <ptr target="#pierazzo2014b" loc="131"/> <ptr target="#fiormonte2010"/> <ptr target="#neyt2006"/>.
                        Heavily revised holographs are also extremely difficult
                        to record using embedded markup, because the encoding quickly becomes too
                        complex, but this difficulty is not shared by the layering technique, where
                        the text of each layer is always simple, however complex the revisions.
                        Variants are also not allowed to overlap when using embedded hierarchical
                        markup, but with layering they are. This is a significant advantage.</p>
                    <p>As a consequence of delegating to a piece of software the task of computing
                        differences between versions and layers, the accuracy of that process is
                        obviously determined by the efficiency of the software. While no program
                        based on a heuristic algorithm can be perfect, the degree of error
                        introduced in this way can be reduced by subsequent versions of the
                        software, or by new and better programs, while retaining exactly the same
                        versions and layers. Biologists have progressively improved both the speed
                        and accuracy of their sequence alignment programs since the 1970s. Adopting
                        this new strategy of organising textual data will encourage the same process
                        of progressive improvement to play out in textual archiving and editing.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Implementation</head>
                    <p>Although the model of versions and layers presented here greatly simplifies
                        the encoding of the textual content of documents, it does not reduce it to
                        plain text. For example, what is to be done about features like underlining,
                        semantic metadata, print formatting like italics, divisions into stanzas,
                        paragraphs, speeches, page numbers etc.? Since the concept of versions and
                        layers is unrelated to the technology used to represent them, each layer may
                        be represented in HTML, the markup language of the Web, or digital humanists
                        may prefer XML, the eXtensible Markup Language, or LMNL the layered markup
                        notation language <ptr target="#piez2014"/>. Alternatively, and for greatest longevity, a
                        standoff representation where all external annotation and feature markup is
                        kept separate from the text will insulate it from the rapidly changing
                        technological standards that govern such markup and annotation technologies
                        <ptr target="#schmidt2016a"/>. Using this approach all external annotation may be stored
                        in the form of a layer of markup corresponding to a single layer of text, or
                        using any other desired system. Such markup systems will probably be
                        replaced by something else in the future. This may lead to data loss, but
                        with the standoff representation the text at least will remain coherently
                        readable, searchable and reusable.</p>
                    <p>The preparation of versions and layers can be accomplished using a simple
                        plain text editor. The transcriber may display the source document as an
                        image on one side of the computer screen, and copy the transcribable text on
                        the right, starting with the text’s final state. Once a complete copy of
                        this has been obtained it may be regarded as sufficient in itself. If not,
                        further layers can be transcribed by copying the final layer, and then
                        undoing the topmost change at each local revision-site to record,
                        successively, the lower layers. If the deleted text in some layer is
                        unreadable due to being obscured by overwriting or crossing-out, such cases
                        can be dealt via markup (internal or external) to indicate unclear or
                        missing text.</p>
                    <p>Embedded mathematical formulae and graphics, as found for example in the
                        Wittgenstein manuscripts <ptr target="#pichler2016"/>, can be treated similarly. An
                        approximation of the formula or graphic in plain text can be used to serve
                        as a placeholder. For example, the formula x<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                        could be written <q>x^2</q> or an image as <q>[picture of a ship]</q>. This
                        placeholder can then be marked up externally with the actual formula or
                        graphic, and rendered using appropriate software into more elegant forms
                        that replace the placeholder with the actual formula or graphic. In this way
                        all content, textual or otherwise, can be recorded successfully in
                        layers.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.1 Comparison of versions and layers</head>
                        <p>The final piece of technology needed to make this model work is the
                            ability to compute differences. Since the versions and layers are plain
                            texts (or, if marked-up may be recovered as plain texts) they can simply
                            be compared with each other. Such software is available now and will be
                            in the future, since computation of differences is a fundamental
                            computing problem. For example, computer scientists use
                            difference-computing tools to save revisions of computer code for later
                            restoration. Difference-computing software can evolve over time without
                            affecting the simple representation of the textual data as versions and layers.
                            <note><p><hi rend="superscript">5.</hi>While striving to keep the argument
                                        on a purely theoretical footing, some examples of suitable
                                        textual alignment tools would establish the practicality of
                                        the alignment process. Bourdaillet and Ganascia (2006) with
                                        MEDITE were the first to show that Ukkonen’s suffix tree
                                        algorithm (1995) could be applied to humanities texts for
                                        the detection of transpositions <ptr target="#bourdaillet2006"/>.
                                    Schäuble and Gabler (2018) used the TUSTEP collate tool to align versions of Virginia
                                    Woolf’s <title rend="quotes">A Sketch of the Past</title> <ptr target="#schäuble2018"/>. The author’s own program,
                                        nmerge (2009), has been used to align the texts in the
                                        Charles Harpur Critical Archive <ptr target="#eggert2019"/>.</p></note></p>
                        <p>The display of versions and layers can be accomplished by using
                            comparison software to compute the differences between layers, or
                            between versions. When comparing layers the shared text may be
                            greyed-out as a reminder to the reader-user that the text does not have
                            the status of a full version. Full versions may have their text
                            displayed in black. An example where this has been done can be seen in
                            the edition of Harpur’s multi-versioned poem <title rend="quotes">Creek of the Four Graves</title>
                            <ptr target="#eggert2019"/>. The display of both versions and layers employs red (to
                            indicate deletion) and blue (to indicate insertion).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6. Conclusion</head>
                    <p>If we are to make any significant progress in transcribing the vast
                        collection of manuscript and early-print material in our libraries and
                        museums, a much more efficient and durable method of recording their content
                        than embedding internal variation data into the text is needed. The latter
                        established method requires us to revise the transcriptions we already have
                        and the software that manipulates them as technology continues to evolve.
                        This prospect is unviable, and a change in our practice is needed. The
                        present model of versions and layers provides a justification for change.</p>
                </div> 
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Bauman 2011" xml:id="bauman2011">Bauman, S 2011. <title rend="quotes">Interchange vs. Interoperability</title>, Proceedings of
                            Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011. Montréal, Canada. 2–5 August 2011.
                            Available from: <ref target="https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol7-Bauman01.html">
                                https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol7-Bauman01.html</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bohnenkamp 2016" xml:id="bohnenkamp2016">Bohnenkamp, A., Henke, S., and Jannidis, F 2016.
                    <title rend="italic">Johann Wolfgang Goethe: Faust Historisch-kritische Edition</title>.
                    <ref target="http://beta.faustedition.net/">http://beta.faustedition.net/</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bourdaillet 2006" xml:id="bourdaillet2006">Bourdaillet, J. and Ganascia, J.P 2006. <title rend="quotes">MEDITE: A
                            Unilingual Textual Aligner</title>, Advances in Natural
                                Language Processing: 5th International Conference on NLP, FinTAL,
                                Turku, Finland, 23-25 August 2006 Proceedings, pp. 458-469. Available from:
                            <ref target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/221314746_MEDITE_A_Unilingual_Textual_Aligner">
                                https://www.researchgate.net/publication/221314746_MEDITE_A_Unilingual_Textual_Aligner</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Brüning 2013" xml:id="brüning2013">Brüning, G., Henzel, K. and Pravida, D 2013.
                        <title rend="quotes">Multiple Encoding in Genetic Editions: The Case of <title rend="quotes">Faust</title></title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 4. Available from:
                        <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/697">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/697</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Bryant 2002" xml:id="bryant2002">Bryant, J 2002. <title rend="italic">The Fluid Text A Theory of Revision and Editing for
                            Book and Screen</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2002).</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Bryant 2008" xml:id="bryant2008">Bryant, J 2008. <title rend="italic">Melville Unfolding. Sexuality, Politics, and the
                            Versions of <title>Typee</title></title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2008).</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Bryant 2009" xml:id="bryant2009">Bryant, J 2009. <title rend="quotes">Herman Melville’s Typee A Fluid Text Edition</title>. 
                           Available from: <ref target="http://rotunda.upress.virginia.edu/melville/">http://rotunda.upress.virginia.edu/melville/</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Dekker 2015" xml:id="dekker2015">Dekker, R.H.,Van Hulle, D., Middell, G., Neyt V., and
                            Van Zundert, J 2015. <title rend="quotes">Computer-supported collation of modern manuscripts:
                            CollateX and the Beckett Digital Manuscript Project</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in
                            the Humanities</title> 30.3 (2015): 452–470.</bibl>
               <bibl label="Durusau 2006" xml:id="durusau2006">Durusau, P 2006. <title rend="quotes">Why and how to document your markup choices</title>. In
                            L. Burnard, K. O’Brien O’Keefe, and J. Unsworth (eds), <title rend="italic">Electronic Textual
                            Editing</title>, New York: MLA, pp. 299–309.</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Eggert 2019" xml:id="eggert2019">Eggert, P 2019. <title rend="quotes">Charles Harpur Critical Archive</title>. Available from:
                     <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Compare/?docid=english/harpur/poems/h080&amp;version1=/h080a/layer-final">
                         http://charles-harpur.org/View/Compare/?docid=english/harpur/poems/h080&amp;version1=/h080a/layer-final</ref> [11 January 2019].</bibl>
              <bibl label="Fiormonte 2010" xml:id="fiormonte2010">Fiormonte, D., Matiradonna, V. and Schmidt, D 2010.
                            <title rend="quotes">Digital Encoding as a Hermeneutic and Semiotic Act: The Case of Valerio
                            Magrelli</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 4.1. Available from:
                               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000082/000082.html">
                                http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000082/000082.html</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Fraistat 2018" xml:id="fraistat2018">Fraistat, N., Denlinger, E. and Viglianti, R 2018. (n.d.).
                            <title rend="quotes">The Shelley-Godwin Archive</title>. Available from:
                             <ref target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
               <bibl label="Gabler 1986" xml:id="gabler1986">Gabler, H. W 1986. <title rend="quotes">Afterword</title>. In <title rend="italic">James Joyce Ulysses The Corrected
                            Text</title>. Bodley Head, London (1986), pp. 647–650.</bibl>
               <bibl label="Gabler" xml:id="gabler">Gabler, H. W. (n.d.). <title rend="quotes">Textual Criticism and Theory in Modern German
                            Editing</title>. <ref target="http://www.academia.edu/856505/Textual_Criticism_and_Theory_in_Modern_German_Editing">
                                http://www.academia.edu/856505/Textual_Criticism_and_Theory_in_Modern_German_Editing</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
               <bibl label="Göbel 2015" xml:id="göbel2015">Göbel, M 2015. <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Das TextGrid Laboratory: Zehn Jahre
                            Software-Entwicklung</title>. In Neuroth, H., Rapp, A. and Söring S. (eds),
                            <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">TextGrid: Von der Community – für die Community Eine Virtuelle
                            Forschungsumgebung für die Geisteswissenschaften</title>. Werner Hülsbusch,
                            Glückstadt (2015), pp. 251–259.</bibl>
             <bibl label="Greetham 1994" xml:id="greetham1994">Greetham, D 1994. <title rend="italic">Textual Scholarship: An Introduction</title>. Garland,
                            New York and London (1994).</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Harpur 1836-68" xml:id="harpur1836-68">Harpur, C 1836–1868. <title rend="quotes">A87-2</title> Available from:
                               <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A87-2">
                              http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A87-2</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Harpur 1849-63" xml:id="harpur1849-63">Harpur, C 1849–1863.
                            <title rend="quotes">C376</title> Available from:
                              <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/C376">http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/C376</ref>.
                               [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Harpur 1853a" xml:id="harpur1853a">Harpur, C 1853a. <title rend="italic">The Bushranger: A Play in Five Acts and Other
                            Poems</title>. W. R. Piddington, Sydney (1853). Available from: <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A87-2">
                                http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A87-2</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Harpur 1853b" xml:id="harpur1853b">Harpur, C 1853b. <title rend="quotes">Trust in God</title>, <title rend="italic">Empire</title>, 20 June 1853, p. 2410.
                              Available from: <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/corpix/english/harpur/EMP/20-JUN-1853-P2410-H646A.jpg">
                                http://charles-harpur.org/corpix/english/harpur/EMP/20-JUN-1853-P2410-H646A.jpg</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Harpur 1855" xml:id="harpur1855">Harpur, C 1855. <title rend="quotes">B78</title>.
                                <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/B78">
                                http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/B78</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Harpur 1855-62" xml:id="harpur1855-62">Harpur, C 1855–1862. <title rend="quotes">C384</title>. Available from:
                                 <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/C384">
                            http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/C384</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Harpur 1859" xml:id="harpur1859">Harpur, C 1859. <title rend="quotes">Trust in God</title>, <title rend="italic">Australian Home Companion</title> IV, 5
                            November 1859, p. 467. Available from: <ref target="http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/72486054">
                                http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/72486054</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
              <bibl label="Harpur 1863" xml:id="harpur1863">Harpur, C 1863. <title rend="quotes">A89</title>. Available from:
                                       <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A98">
                                    http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A89</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Harpur 1865-67" xml:id="harpur1865-67">Harpur, C 1865-1867. <title rend="quotes">A95</title> Available from:
                                    <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A95">
                                   http://charles-harpur.org/View/Pages/?docid=english/harpur/A95</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Heckel 1978" xml:id="heckel1978">Heckel, P 1978. <title rend="quotes">A technique
                            for isolating differences between files</title>, <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>
                            21.4: 264–268.</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Huitfeldt 1993" xml:id="huitfeldt1993">Huitfeldt, C 1993. <title rend="quotes">The Wittgenstein Archives at the University
                            of Bergen: Project Report 1990-1993 and Critical Evaluation</title>. Available from:
                            <ref target="http://wab.uib.no/1990-99/reports/no9.htm">
                                http://wab.uib.no/1990-99/reports/no9.htm</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Jebb 1905" xml:id="jebb1905">Jebb, R. C 1905. <title rend="italic">Bacchylides: The Poems and Fragments</title>. Cambridge
                            University Press, Cambridge (1905).</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Jenab 2014" xml:id="jenab2014">Jenab, K., Noori, K., Weinsier, P. D. and Khoury, S 2014. <title rend="quotes">A
                            dynamic model for hardware/software obsolescence</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                            Quality &amp; Reliability Management</title>, 31.5: 588–600.</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Juxta 2013" xml:id="juxta2013">Juxta Commons 2013. <title rend="quotes">Advanced Options for
                            XML Texts</title> Available from: <ref target="http://juxtacommons.org/guide#advanced">
                                http://juxtacommons.org/guide#advanced</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Muñoz 2015" xml:id="muñoz2015">Muñoz, T., and Viglianti, R 2015. <title rend="quotes">Texts and Documents: New Challenges for TEI
                            Interchange and Lessons from the Shelley-Godwin Archive</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the
                            Text Encoding Initiative</title> 8. Available from: <ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/1270">
                                http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1270</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                   <bibl label="Myers 1987" xml:id="myers1987">Myers, E. W 1987. <title rend="quotes">An O(ND) difference algorithm and its variations</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">Algorithmica</title>, 1: 251–266.</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Nedo 1993" xml:id="nedo1993">Nedo, M 1993. <title rend="italic">Ludwig Wittgenstein Wiener Ausgabe,
                            Einführung/Introduction</title>. Springer, Vienna, New York (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Neyt 2006" xml:id="neyt2006">Neyt, V 2006. <title rend="quotes">Fretful Tags Amid the Verbiage: Issues in the
                            Representation of Modern Manuscript Material</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                            Computing</title> 21, supplement: 99–111.</bibl>
               <bibl label="NLA 2016" xml:id="nla2016">NLA 2016. National Library of Australia. <title rend="quotes">Collection Statistics</title>. Available from:
                              <ref target="https://www.nla.gov.au/collections/statistics">https://www.nla.gov.au/collections/statistics</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
               <bibl label="NLA 2017" xml:id="nla2017">NLA 2017. <title rend="quotes">Preparing for copyright term changes in 2019</title>.
                               Available from: <ref target="https://www.nsla.org.au/sites/default/files/documents/nsla.copyright-preparing-changes-2019.pdf">
                                https://www.nsla.org.au/sites/default/files/documents/nsla.copyright-preparing-changes-2019.pdf</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Pauly 2003" xml:id="pauly2003">Brill’s New Pauly 2003. <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of the Ancient World</title>. Brill,
                            Leiden (2003).</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Pichler 2016" xml:id="pichler2016">Pichler, A 2016. <title rend="quotes">Wittgenstein Source</title>. Available from:
                                <ref target="http://wittgensteinsource.org/">http://wittgensteinsource.org/</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                  <bibl label="Pierazzo 2009" xml:id="pierazzo2009">Pierazzo, E 2009. <title rend="quotes">Digital genetic editions: The encoding of time
                            in manuscript transcription</title>. In M. Deegan and K. Sutherland (eds), <title rend="italic">Text
                            Editing, Print and the Digital World</title>. Ashgate, Farnham (2009), pp.
                            169–186.</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Pierazzo 2014a" xml:id="pierazzo2014a">Pierazzo, E 2014a. <title rend="quotes">Digital Documentary Editions and the Others</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</title> 35. Available from: <ref target="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html">
                                http://www.scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pierazzo 2014b" xml:id="pierazzo2014b">Pierazzo, E 2014b. <title rend="quotes">Digital Scholarly Editing:
                            Theories, Models and Methods</title>, London: Routledge. Available from: <ref target="http://hal.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/hal-01182162">
                                http://hal.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/hal-01182162</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Piez 2014" xml:id="piez2014">Piez, W 2014. <title rend="quotes">TEI in LMNL</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 8
                            (2014). Available from: <ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/1337">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1337</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rehbein 2013" xml:id="rehbein2013">Rehbein, M. and Gabler, H. W 2013. <title rend="quotes">On Reading
                            Environments for Genetic Editions</title>, <title rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication</title>
                            4.3: 1–21. Available from: <ref target="http://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/viewFile/123/260">
                                http://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/viewFile/123/260</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Saller 2003" xml:id="saller2003">Saller, H 2003. HMNL <title rend="quotes">The HyperNietzsche Markup Language</title>, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Jahrbuch
                            für Computerphilologie</title> 5. Available from: <ref target="http://computerphilologie.digital-humanities.de/jg03/saller.html">
                                http://computerphilologie.digital-humanities.de/jg03/saller.html</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
               <bibl label="Sandborn 2012" xml:id="sandborn2012">Sandborn, P 2012. <title rend="quotes">Software Obsolescence</title>. In B. Bartels, U.
                            Ermel, M. Pecht, P. Sandborn (eds), <title rend="italic">Wiley Series in Systems Engineering and
                            Management, Strategies to the Prediction, Mitigation and Management of
                            Product Obsolescence</title>. Wiley, Hoboken, NJ (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sattler 1979" xml:id="sattler1979">Sattler, D. E 1979. <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Marginalien zur Frankfurter
                            Hölderlin-Ausgabe</title>, <title rend="italic">MLN</title>
                            94.3: 601–606. Available from: <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2906534">
                                http://www.jstor.org/stable/2906534</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Schäuble 2018" xml:id="schäuble2018">Schäuble, J. and Gabler, H.W 2018. <title rend="quotes">Encodings and
                            Visualisations of Text Processes across Document Borders</title>. In R. Bleier, M.
                            Bürgermeister, H. W. Klug, F. Neuber, G. Schneider (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly
                            Editions as Interfaces</title>, BoD: Norderstedt (2018), pp. 165–191.</bibl>
              <bibl label="Schmidt 2009" xml:id="schmidt2009">Schmidt, D 2009. <title rend="quotes">Merging Multi-Version Texts: a Generic Solution
                            to the Overlap Problem</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
                            2009. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</title>, 3. Available from: <ref target="http://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol3.Schmidt01">
                                http://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol3.Schmidt01</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                   <bibl label="Schmidt 2014" xml:id="schmidt2014">Schmidt, D 2014. <title rend="quotes">Towards an
                            Interoperable Digital Scholarly Edition</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                                Initiative</title> 7. Available from: <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/979">
                                https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/979</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
               <bibl label="Schmidt 2016a" xml:id="schmidt2016a">Schmidt, D 2016a. <title rend="quotes">Using standoff properties
                            for marking-up historical documents in the humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">it – Information
                            Technology</title> 58.2 (2016): 63–69.</bibl>
                    <bibl label="Schmidt 2016b" xml:id="schmidt2016b">Schmidt, D 2016b. <title rend="quotes">Enhancing Search for
                            complex historical texts</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Digital Humanities Australasia
                            2016: Working with Complexity, Hobart 20–23 June 2016</title> Available from:
                            <ref target="http://charles-harpur.org/presentations/dha2016.search.pdf">
                            http://charles-harpur.org/presentations/dha2016.search.pdf</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Shillingsburg 1996" xml:id="shillingsburg1996">Shillingsburg, P 1996. <title rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age
                            Theory and Practice Third Edition</title>. University of Michigan, Ann Arbor
                            (1996).</bibl>
               <bibl label="Sperberg-McQueen 2000" xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen2000">Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., Huitfeldt, C. and
                            Renear, A 2000. <title rend="quotes">Meaning and Interpretation of Markup —not as simple as you
                            think</title>. In <title rend="italic">Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing Newsletter, IEEE</title> 2.3
                            (2000): pp. 215–234.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Tagore" xml:id="tagore">Tagore, R (n.d.). <title rend="quotes">Bichitra: Online Tagore Variorum: School of
                            Cultural Texts and Records</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://bichitra.jdvu.ac.in/bichitra_user_manual.php">
                                http://bichitra.jdvu.ac.in/bichitra_user_manual.php</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="TEI 2017" xml:id="tei2017">TEI Consortium 2017. <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                            Interchange</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/P5/">http://www.tei-c.org/P5/</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Ukkonen 1995" xml:id="ukkonen1995">Ukkonen, E 1995. <title rend="quotes">Online construction of suffix trees</title>,
                         <title rend="italic">Algorithmica</title> 14.3 (1995):
                            249–260. Available from: <ref target="http://www.cs.helsinki.fi/u/ukkonen/SuffixT1withFigs.pdf">
                                http://www.cs.helsinki.fi/u/ukkonen/SuffixT1withFigs.pdf</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Van Hulle 2011" xml:id="vanhulle2011">Van Hulle, D 2011. <title rend="quotes">Modern Manuscripts and Textual Epigenetics:
                            Samuel Beckett’s Works between Completion and Incompletion</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">Modernism/modernity</title> 18.4 (2011).</bibl>
                 <bibl label="Van Hulle 2015" xml:id="vanhulle2015">Van Hulle, D., and Neyt, V 2015. <title rend="quotes">Samuel Beckett Digital
                            Manuscript Project</title>. Available from: <ref target="http://www.beckettarchive.org/">
                                http://www.beckettarchive.org</ref>. [11 January 2019].</bibl>
            </listBibl>   
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
