<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Visual Communication and the promotion of
                    Health: an exploration of how they intersect in Italian education</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Viviana <dhq:family>De Angelis</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Università degli Studi di Bari Aldo Moro</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>viviana.deangelis@uniba.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Patricia Mannix
                        <dhq:family>McNamara</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Limerick</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>Patricia.M.McNamara@ul.ie</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Rosa <dhq:family>Gallelli</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Università degli Studi di Bari Aldo Moro</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email> rosa.gallelli@uniba.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Gemma <dhq:family>Pichierri</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Media Training Expert</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>gemma.pichierri@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000407</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-07-26">26 July 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The use of new technologies, media and computational methods in Humanities may
                    evolve and indeed it is already changing the <soCalled>contents</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>forms</soCalled> of contemporary education, opening new scenarios
                    previously unimaginable. Nowadays Visual Mobile Devices, smartphones, tablets,
                    etc, contribute to a range of computer-mediated activities, which are related to
                    specific locations and times. But for such critical reflection, we need a closer
                    look to deeper layers of our culture to unveil the characteristics of new
                    technologies and devices. This paper describes some emerging aspects of the
                    teaching use of visual communication techniques in primary and secondary
                    schooling. In particular it reviews the evidence of the efficiency of visual
                    communication for learning both in varied curriculum disciplines and of
                    transversal socio-ethical affective skills necessary for the promotion of health
                    and the construction of a planetary citizenship. The paper illuminates the
                    didactic applicability and unique potential of images for the epistemological
                    peculiarities of different disciplines, highlighting how educational use of
                    images in creative pedagogy can be more focused given the function they perform
                    in the more general cognitive process of individuals. The theoretical analysis
                    of the teaching validity of the use of visual communication, as reported in the
                    international literature, seems to receive confirmation from a case study, which
                    provides detailed analyses of how this technique can enhance specific projects
                    and demonstrates its significance for wider practitioners.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>How might visual communication techniques be used in primary and secondary
                    education?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>1. Images and Learning </head>
                <p>In the last decade societies have witnessed the sudden and widespread
                    introduction of new technologies, all of which involve sophisticated and complex
                    processes of communication. This phenomenon has been described as a digital
                    revolution that, on a daily basis, transforms contemporary life. However, the
                    increasing spread of technologies for managing information and communication in
                    effect runs parallel to the changing learning needs and learning modes of
                    individuals. This in effect has resulted in the need to plan and organize new,
                    more flexible and responsive pedagogical approaches <ptr target="#gallelli2011"
                        loc="13"/>. We live in a society increasingly dominated by communication via
                    images. In recent years, new information technologies have significantly
                    expanded the possibilities for representing information. The Internet
                    facilitates speedier access to and downloading of images, as well as their
                    manipulation and reuse. It makes great use of visual and multimedia formats in
                    all areas, particularly that of education. Ease of production and consumption,
                    however, does not always lead to educationally conscious and/or indeed moral or
                    ethical use of images. Innovations produced in the Internet era, and the impact
                    of the World Wide Web on science, commerce and entertainment, are certainly
                    evident for all to see. Less understood are the long-term effects of the digital
                    era on humanity and indeed how it inexorably changes human life. It will take
                    many years, in fact, to fully understand how these changes affect the human
                    cognition <ptr target="#veen2006"/> or indeed to understand the changes
                    occurring in the relations between individuals <ptr target="#burgess2009"/>.
                    Despite these problems, in the last two decades, studies that investigate the
                    relationship between image use and learning have increased and this led to the
                    development of an initial survey of the <soCalled>state of the art</soCalled>
                    that can help practitioners to be more aware of the function that image
                    consumption performs in the more general cognitive process of individuals. The
                    desire to help practitioners to be more aware of the real potential that visual
                    communication offers as learning support drove this project. When an image is
                    used to promote learning, it is necessary to consider whether and how it will
                    become functional in the general cognitive process of students. It is also
                    important to consider whether it is even possible to assess its impact and
                    usefulness. In-depth analysis of the existing literature on the evidence of
                    effectiveness of visual communication on human learning is an important first
                    step in developing understanding of the degree of functionality of image usage
                    and should also serve to inform guiding principles for the education of
                    practitioners, so as to prompt more effective and educationally aware choices. </p>
                <p>There are clearly myriad variety in image types, and Calvani advocates that a
                    first distinction can be made between static and dynamic images and the degree
                    of realism they contain. Calvani differentiated between realism, realism adapted
                    and symbolization <ptr target="#calvani2011"/>. Initially it may appear easy to
                    distinguish static and dynamic figures if one refers to the surface
                    characteristics of the image itself, i.e. how it is done. However, if one
                    transfers the discourse to a more cognitive (even philosophical) plane, one
                    might argue that there is dynamism even in stillness. In fact, in many
                    physically static diagrams there can exist a dynamic plane, because cognitively
                    they may indicate the occurrence of an action, and the representation of a
                    graphical model encourages the onlooker to think laterally toward some changes
                        <ptr target="#calvani2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#paoletti2011"/>. For example <ref target="#figure01">figure
                        1</ref> represents a physically static diagram: the water cycle. However,
                    note what the arrows represent; they encourage the onlooker to think of the
                    changes taking place and therefore imply an intellectual dynamism.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>Example of dynamic image: the water cycle. Source: <ref
                            target="http://educazionetecnica.dantect.it/tag/idrico/"
                            >http://educazionetecnica.dantect.it/tag/idrico/</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig1.png"/>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>
                <p>Bearing in mind that the idea of reproduction of an objective reality is rather
                    naïve, one can still explore the concept of <q>realism</q> when referring to
                    representations that maintain a direct and explicit connection with the object
                    represented. This realism category includes artifacts such as photographs,
                    imitative drawings, maps, video sequences in real time, which have not been
                    manipulated in any form. Educationally relevant cognitive operations that are
                    associated with the use of these types of images are those such as object
                    recognition, comparison, classification, spatial orientation, discovery of the
                    types of views experienced and measurement. Calvani’s second category is defined
                    as <q>adapted realism</q>. In adapted realism, an alteration is intentionally
                    sought for specific purposes; it maintains a discreet relationship with the
                    original image (concrete referent) and is still recognizable, but there are
                    specific amendments in order to further understanding. This category usually has
                    an educational motivation. In this case selected operations are performed on the
                    image such as highlighting or schematization. This type of endeavour includes
                    the majority of the diagrams in scientific texts that simplify the complexity of
                    an object being represented, or which highlight particular aspects of it.
                    Dynamic representations can include endeavours such as demonstration videos,
                    which have been subjected to mounting, with specific space-time manipulation, in
                    order to highlight and communicate the relationship between elements or between
                    the parts and the whole. The educational functions prompted by these resources
                    are related to the focus of attention on internal aspects and recognition of
                    relationships and internal connections.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>Photo (a) and drawing (b) of the cardiac system (Source: <ref
                            target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cuore.jpg"
                            >http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cuore.jpg</ref>) </head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the images shown here (<ref target="#figure02">Fig . 2</ref>), one can discern
                    a photo and a drawing of the cardiac system. Both represent the same concrete
                    referent, but in design one notes changes or differences to some features of the
                    system, simplifying them and enlarging them. This is done because non-experts,
                    for example, would possibly have difficulty interpreting photos alone.
                    Therefore, to prompt better understanding of the structure and operation of the
                    system that is being viewed the drawing or symbolisation is used. This is the
                    third dimension that Calvani articulated, that of symbolization in the strictest
                    sense. According to the existing literature, symbolism concerns the
                    representation of complex phenomena. The representation adheres to the rules of
                    an entirely conventional code, through the use of lines, arrows, blocks,
                    organized patterns, or data and numbers arranged in specific orders. In this
                    context they include most of the diagrams with which one is familiar,
                    (conceptual maps, flowcharts, etc.). The cognitive functions that connect to
                    this type of images include: symbolizing, correlating, interpreting,
                    hypothesizing, deducing, constructing and testing models and systems <ptr
                        target="#calvani2011"/>. A pie chart, for example, provides immediate
                    quantitative and qualitative information on a phenomenon (<ref
                        target="#figure03">Fig . 3</ref>) that one subsequently interprets and
                    applies to one’s prior understanding. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>Example of a pie chart. Source: <ref
                            target="http://www.rischiocalcolato.it/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/globalenergypie-650x573.png"
                            >http://www.rischiocalcolato.it/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/globalenergypie-650x573.png</ref>
                    </head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Dual Coding Theory</head>
                <p>Further study is required on the potential of the use of visual communication and
                    on the potential that images have to affect cognitive processes. The
                    relationship between images, words and thoughts were examined by Canadian
                    psychologist Allan Paivio in his seminal work on <title rend="italic">Dual
                        Coding Theory</title> that has significantly influenced theories of
                    multimedia learning <ptr target="#paivio1991"/>. Dual Coding Theory argues that
                    there are two different encoding systems for processing and presentation of
                    information: a verbal system that takes care of verbal information and
                    linguistics and a nonverbal system that processes visual information and mental
                    images. When a stimulus, such as a word, is presented audibly, it is encoded by
                    the verbal system that uses the auditory subsystem. Because the word is
                    identified, it is compared with a basic representation unit, called
                        <term>logogen</term>, that is the representation of the word contained in
                    long-term memory. The same type of structure also characterizes the nonverbal
                    system, therefore image is encoded in the visual subsystem and is compared with
                    the <term>imagens</term> units of representation of the images. The
                        <term>logogens</term> and the <term>imagens</term> are related to each
                    other. For example, one can apprehend the mental image of a tree and then
                    describe it with the word tree, or hear the word tree and then form a
                    corresponding mental image. Various studies have shown the effect of superiority
                    of images or figures in remembrance <ptr target="#calvani2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#paivio1991"/>. When asked to recall a list of figures and words,
                    memory is better served by figures. With words, also, those referring to a
                    concrete object are remembered better than abstract ones. This happens,
                    according to Paivio, because the figures are processed by both systems. This
                    awareness may render more efficient designing of formative and learning
                    essentials for students in different age groups. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. The Multimedia Representation Theory </head>
                <p>Theoretical relationships between images and learning have been enhanced by the
                    work of German researcher Wolfgang Schnotz who proposed a model of multimedia
                    learning, noting the role of external representations, i.e. text and figure, and
                    internal, mental models in building a multimedia knowledge <ptr
                        target="#schnotz2001"/>. External representations can be divided into verbal
                    and descriptive or pictorial representations or visual representations. External
                    ones can be descriptive or pictorial<note> i.e. images</note> solely or
                    exclusively. Internal representations can be both descriptive and pictorial.
                    Mental models<note> Mental models are internal representations that people use
                        for understanding, reasoning and prediction.</note> are in fact verbal
                    representations, because they are descriptions of inner language, but they are
                    also pictorial representations, as a mental model maintains the structural
                    characteristics of the object represented, that is, the object based on a
                    structural or functional analogy. Learning more effectively takes place in an
                    integrated model of such representations. Paoletti also has dealt with this
                    issue explaining that both text and shape can give life to a mental model, but
                    realize it by different routes. The first goes through the reading and
                    understanding of the text and this is the most challenging, because there are
                    several levels to be navigated, firstly the representation of the surface
                    structure of the text, then the representation of the ideas expressed in the
                    text and finally the formation of the mental model. A figure is more immediate
                    and direct; in fact the visual perception passes directly to the mental model.
                    In this case the figure, being an external analog representation, isomorphic to
                    the situation described by the text, can drive the process of elaboration of the
                    text, and so facilitate the construction of a mental model <ptr
                        target="#paoletti2011"/>. Another theory that has made a great contribution
                    to the understanding of the relationship between images and learning is the
                    Cognitive Load Theory (CLT) by Chandler and Sweller<note> The theory is best
                        known as CLT, <title rend="italic">Cognitive Learning Theory</title>.
                    </note>. This theory focuses on the concept of cognitive resources available
                    during the execution of a task and how those resources are used and directional
                    during learning <ptr target="#chandler1991"/>. For the Cognitive Load Theory,
                    learning involves the construction of mental schemes and their automation. The
                    schemes are internal representations capable of mediating between the
                    information coming from the environment and knowledge that the subject already
                    possesses. The memory system is the tool that makes this possible link. It is
                    formed of three major subsystems: the sensory memory (MS), the working memory
                    (ML) and the long-term memory (LTM). For the CLT learning can be optimized if
                    the subject efficiently employs its working memory in the construction of mental
                    schemes required by the task. </p>
                <p>In this respect, Sweller has developed the concept of cognitive load, which was
                    defined as the load imposed on the working memory from information presented
                        <ptr target="#sweller1988"/>, also understood as the mental effort perceived
                    by the student during learning. The cognitive load can be of three types: alien,
                    inherent and relevant. The extraneous cognitive load is associated with
                    processes that are not directly necessary for learning. That is instead
                    determined by the interaction between the intrinsic nature of the contents to be
                    learned and the student's pre-knowledge while the relevant concerns processes
                    that are directly associated with learning, namely the construction and
                    automation of patterns in the working memory. The theory was first concentrated
                    on the reduction of external loads and later studied the treatment of intrinsic
                    load which must be adapted to the student's needs through simplification
                    operations of the material to be learned. Such material can be considered more
                    or less complex in relation to the differences in the level of experience of the
                    subject and, therefore, the presentation mode should be selected on the basis of
                    pre-knowledge of the student <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. The cognitive theory of multimedia learning</head>
                <p> One of the most comprehensive theoretical models that try to explain the
                    cognitive dynamics underlying multimedia learning is that proposed by Richard
                    Mayer <ptr target="#mayer2000"/>. The author, taking into account the concept of
                    double-encoding by Paivio and of the concept of cognitive load by Chandler and
                    Sweller, has developed an integrated model. Cognitive theory of multimedia
                    learning is based on three basic assumptions. The first states that visual and
                    auditory information processing takes place through two different channels. The
                    second states that the amount of information we can process in each channel is
                    limited so an undue burden hampers processing. The third basic assumption
                    observes that learning takes place when the subject develops actively the
                    information, i.e. when selecting the relevant information in each channel,
                    organizes them into consistent representations and integrates them with each
                    other and with those already held <ptr target="#cornoldi2005"/>. The cognitive
                    load theory and cognitive theory of multimedia learning have developed some real
                    operational guidelines for multimedia design. In particular the first identified
                    the effects produced on learning on the basis of how texts and figures are put
                    together and on the basis of the characteristics of the user and Mayer advocated
                    a number of fundamental principles to be taken into account in the
                    implementation of products. The first is the principle of multimedia, which adds
                    appropriate figures to a text, making it easier to understand. The second is the
                    spatial and temporal contiguity principle that enhances the closeness between
                    text and illustration. The third is the principle of consistency that highlights
                    negative effects of irrelevant information. The fourth is the modality principle
                    demonstrating the benefit of bimodal presentation (auditory and visual). The
                    fifth is the principle of redundancy that critiques lodged information in many
                    formats, such as: image, text and audio. The sixth and last is the segmentation
                    principle according to which it is better to present the multimedia material in
                    short segments controllable <ptr target="#mayer2000"/>
                    <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Communication and psychological functions of images</head>
                <p>Sometimes a figure is enough to understand a message, but more often than not the
                    interpretation of a message also requires some text. It is therefore appropriate
                    to examine the relationship of figure-text, which is accomplished through the
                    function that takes place within the text and vice versa. Many authors have
                    ventured into typological classification of the forms of visual communication
                    with different criteria. The authors distinguish between the surface
                    characteristics of an image and its psychological and communicative functions.
                    The surface characteristics affect the appearance of an image and the way in
                    which it was created; communicative functions are for image transmission
                    aspects, i.e. how the image conveys information. Psychological ones, however,
                    relate to the way in which visual elements interact with the human cognitive
                    system and provide useful information in relation to the purposes with which
                    images can be used in teaching. The surface characteristics affect teaching
                    effectiveness only marginally. The communicative functions and psychological
                    ones, instead, make more effective use of the photo from the point of view of
                    learning. According to the taxonomy of Clark and Lyons the communicative
                    functions are: decorative, mnemonic, organizational, relational, representative,
                    transformative and interpretive; while psychological functions are: support for
                    the attention, enabling knowledge, cognitive load minimization, construction of
                    mental models, support for the transfer of learning and support for motivation
                        <ptr target="#clark2010"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. From theory to practice: the results of a research-ethics education and
                    health promotion in Italy</head>
                <p>Using some basic principles of visual communication, Cognitive Load Theory and
                    Cognitive Theory of Multimedia Learning, the authors have designed and built an
                    educational workshop for ethical values within an international project of
                    health promotion focused on: <title rend="quotes">Developmental Trajectories of
                        Pedagogy of Care Applied to Training Subjects</title>, which involves
                    Italian students (and some students from Ireland), between 9 and 18 years old.
                    The first educational workshop of ethical values in Italy project involved 132
                    students in fifth grade curriculum and experienced experts (pedagogues,
                    philosophers, psychologists and experts in graphic design) in collaboration with
                    teachers in a southern Italian primary school in the first educational cycle:
                        <title rend="quotes">G. Bovio</title> in Ruvo di Puglia (Ba). The premise
                    for the project was based upon reflection on cultural and social contexts
                    underlined by the previous two surveys of the juvenile condition in Italy
                    Istituto IARD <q>at the beginning of the new century</q>. They reveal the
                    restlessness and confusion of youth in the face of the profound changes that
                    characterize post-modernity and provide a mass of data of particular interest to
                    pedagogical reflection <ptr target="#buzzi2002"/>
                    <ptr target="#buzzi2007"/>. A trait that characterizes the profile of young
                    people currently is the loss of strong role models and the propensity to take
                    references identity as flexible combined with the changing beliefs that include
                    that there are no more qualities that are not transient, that our mortal soul <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bellingreri2014">is rather a thousand
                            fragments physiognomy</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bellingreri2014"/>
                    </cit>. Other traits that characterize the profile of young contemporaries are:
                    lack of stability in interpersonal relationships; difficulties in communication;
                    lack of shared languages; marked individualisation; narcissism; paroxysmal
                    defense of personal freedom; subjectivation and misunderstanding of social
                    standards; relationship difficulties with parents and teachers; widespread
                    social and political disengagement; lack of guilt; sunset superego; aesthetic
                    culture spread; hedonistic culture spread; attention to live in the present
                    moment; great trust in the possibilities; and lack of hope towards the
                    future.</p>
                <p>This data confirmed, moreover, by the latest European research <ptr
                        target="#EMCDDA2014"/> appears even more worrisome if matched to the World
                    Drugs Report data <ptr target="#WDR2015"/>. In particular, the report entitled
                        <title rend="quotes">Prevalence of drug use in the youth population</title>
                    <ptr target="#REPORT2015"/> reports the following data on the use of soft drugs,
                    which cannot but cause concern among families and educators in various
                    capacities: 39 % (10-12 years) North America (Canada), using cannabis at least
                    once in 2014; 35 % (15-16 years) Czech Republic; 28 % (9-10 years) United
                    States; 20% (15-16 years), Chile and Bulgaria; 11% (15-19 years), Italy. The
                    SAR, the European agency that investigates the diffusion of psychoactive
                    substances has reported a total of 101 new substances in 2014. These trends are
                    clearly worrisome. </p>
                <p>Thus it was in this context that the research question was born: What type of
                    educational provision in the early years of schooling for pupils is necessary to
                    prevent these trends and to promote the integral formation and the well-being of
                    the human person? In tandem with the research focus was the desire for an
                    integrated educational project, namely an active network that links formal and
                    informal educational agencies to promote integral health and human wellbeing
                    from the early years of life. In the school year 2015-2016 the <title
                        rend="quotes">Quality of life</title> network was developed, involving
                    different grade schools, institutions' families, local health authorities,
                    associations of the municipality of Ruvo di Puglia, coordinated by the
                    University of Bari. Following the suggestions of Edgard Morin, who advocates the
                    importance of a new kind of education that can really teach people to live a
                    good life, the educational workshop followed a twofold purpose: primarily aimed
                    at youth health promotion, and included a pedagogy of cooperation between formal
                    and informal training agencies, through a process of growing awareness of the
                    potential and the risks that young people now face <ptr target="#morin2015"/>.
                    Secondly, the project aimed to explore with young people how to take care of
                    themselves and others through the means of visual communication, writing fiction
                    and autobiographical writing, to chart a new path of sustainable development
                    ethics and inclusive education in a shared model. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>7. Materials and methods</head>
                <p> We believe the positivistic paradigm is inadequate to investigate some areas of
                    education. Much of the essence of the educational phenomenon is as a unique and
                    unrepeatable epistemic device that does not lend itself easily to the positivist
                    lens. Epistemic ecological paradigm-related guidelines are best suited to
                    investigate the world of education. That is why we chose to use
                    quanti-qualitative tools and standards to investigate the particular scope of
                    educational research represented by the ethical education of values, within a
                    framework of full welfare and health promotion. There were several epistemic
                    ecological paradigm-related underpinnings, which included a phenomenological
                    approach, a critical approach and a participatory approach. These approaches
                    express different philosophies which are not mutually exclusive. In this
                    research work, in particular, we favored a phenomenological-hermeneutic
                    interpretive approach, which takes account of empirical data. The
                    phenomenological hermeneutic paradigm aims at the elaboration of scientific
                    reports defined as <q>interpretative descriptions</q>. It's mostly this
                    paradigm, which has developed theories of phenomenological research as it
                    applies to education. The starting point was the experience, to investigate
                    networks and meanings that participants identified. The phenomenological
                    methodology excludes generalizations. The essence of the phenomenological
                    orientation is to be faithful to the phenomenon itself; the epistemic imperative
                    is to <soCalled>go to the things themselves</soCalled>. Things are not perceived
                    as factual, but as elements of consciousness, objects of intuition, the essence
                    of things revealed to consciousness. The researcher should, according to this
                    paradigm, study things in their setting, knowing that they can manifest
                    themselves in different ways according to the ways of accessing them. In order
                    to be faithful to the phenomenon researchers should refer to the principle of
                    evidence: and the authors adhered to this principle. They also recognized that
                    phenomena do not always appear to be completely transparent to one’s gaze, but
                    rather that everything has its own specific way of transcending appearance. This
                    makes the researcher humble and modest in the results obtained and motivates
                    further research that can identify and promote empowering strategies that can
                    contribute to new improvements for the human person. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>8. An innovative teaching program with some principles and tools of visual
                    communication</head>
                <p> In the workshop, along with some Mexican folk patterns, representing some
                    virtues indispensable for the integral development of the human person, we used
                    the interactive whiteboard (IWB) that is a device that, when compared to other
                    similar technological tools, is designed specifically for the school and with
                    the school. As is with the size of a traditional whiteboard, on the surface it
                    is possible to write, manage files, images, videos and browse the web resources.
                    A projector projects the computer's desktop on the surface of the Board, on
                    which one can interact through the use of a pen, a finger, a stylus or other
                    device (Wikipedia 06/2013). The students were very interested in using the IWB.
                    Our research shows that the digital whiteboard has a direct effect on the degree
                    of students' participation in the lesson. The digital whiteboard has made
                    possible a better presentation of content based on the use of images and movies
                    that have attracted students' attention. </p>
                <p> In the first lesson we explained to the pupils the purpose of the pedagogical
                    laboratory. Projecting on the interactive whiteboard (IWB) the image replayed
                    below (Figure 4), we presented the laboratory as an interesting research path to
                    understand content and form of <soCalled>virtue</soCalled> according to a simple
                    philosophical definition. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Image of children looking for something</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig4.png"/>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>
                <p> A questionnaire was administered at the entrance to evaluate the socio-ethical
                    affective literacy of the students involved in the project. The questions
                    concerned: <list type="ordered">
                        <item> The definition of the concept of virtue according to the Western
                            philosophical tradition. </item>
                        <item> The Aristotelian definition of cardinal human virtues. </item>
                        <item> The reason for the importance given by the Western philosophical
                            tradition to the <foreign xml:lang="gr">paideia</foreign> of virtues in
                            the education of the young generations. </item>
                        <item> The perception of pupils of a possible gap between education and
                            training, theory and educational practice. </item>
                        <item> The perception of the existence, by the students, of possible gaps in
                            the education given by the school. </item>
                        <item> The behavioral habits of pupils inside and outside the school. </item>
                        <item> The quality of interpersonal relationships with teachers, classmates
                            and family members. </item>
                        <item> The importance of reading and reflection. </item>
                        <item> The use of new technologies inside and outside the school. </item>
                        <item> The influence of mass media, social networks and of the dominant
                            culture over one's way of thinking. </item>
                        <item> Sense of satisfaction and well-being in the school. </item>
                        <item> Sense of satisfaction and well-being outside the school. </item>
                        <item> Possible educational needs not completely satisfied by the curriculum
                            disciplines. </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p> In the second lesson, according to the data from the questionnaire, a
                    mini-course of socio-ethical-affective literacy was proposed. Using the means of
                        <title rend="italic">Visual Communication</title> (in particular the digital
                    whiteboard, images, audio, video clips) we created an interesting experience of
                    rapid literacy and interactive and cooperative learning. Subsequently, the
                    pupils were divided into small groups and realized an artistic production
                    related to the contents learned. The moment of final sharing was particularly
                    appreciated by the students who had shown a team spirit in the groups. Only in
                    one case, a child refused to work with their group mates and worked alone. </p>
                <p> In the third meeting an interview was held by the children with the headmaster,
                    the councilor for the education of the municipality to which he belongs, a
                    psychologist and a doctor on the fascinating and little-known theme of the
                    fundamental human virtues that help one to live well with oneself and with
                    others. At the end of the interviews there arose a lively debate that involved
                    the guests of the lesson and the interviewers. The simplicity and the frankness
                    of the new questions of the children, who now went beyond the outline of the
                    questions proposed at the beginning of the debate, questioned the same
                        <soCalled>experts</soCalled>. The principal of the school and the
                    commissioner thanked the students for this meeting and promised to continue to
                    question themselves on these issues so crucial for their private life and for
                    the important profession that they play. </p>
                <p> In the fourth lesson, the virtue of generosity was presented to the students
                    through the story of Oscar Wilde's <title rend="quotes">Little Prince</title>.
                    Animated video clips kept pupils glued to their chairs for almost an hour. At
                    the end of the viewing, the children were invited to enter their past, to look
                    for an episode of generosity, the most significant and unforgettable, really
                    experienced as spectators / protagonists. After completing this mnemonic effort,
                    the children were asked to write down individually the event that would then be
                    shared freely with their fellow students. The stories told were simple, but one
                    more beautiful than the other. </p>
                <p> In the fifth meeting the gratuitousness of love was explained through the vision
                    of part of <title rend="quotes">Beauty and the Beast</title>. Below we have
                    created an artistic workshop in small groups. The best job was put on the school
                    website. The <soCalled>homework</soCalled> was, like at the end of each meeting,
                    the imitation of virtuous models to be happy. The smiles and serene faces of the
                    children seemed to us a sign of their interest and satisfaction. Also the fact
                    that the students often remained in the classroom after the bell sounded and
                    that some shouted: <q>We are still a bit</q>, seemed to us a sign of their
                    interest in the themes and teaching methods. </p>
                <p> For the last lesson we organized an educational experience of Intergenerational
                    Exchange between the students and the elderly, guests of a retirement home.
                    During the meeting-party there was the mutual presentation of pupils and elders,
                    through the support of a video clip, the interview, made by some students to the
                    elderly, the delivery of a flower, drawings and poems of children and the
                    sharing an ice cream. The children and the elderly were smiling and some held
                    hands and sang. At the end of the party we again gave the students the initial
                    questionnaire to perform a comparative analysis. </p>
                <p> At the end of the educational experiment we can affirm, in agreement with what
                    is said in the literature (<ptr target="#wall2005"/>; <ptr target="#slay2008"
                    />), that using the means of <title rend="italic">Visual Communication</title>
                    (in particular the digital whiteboard, images, audio, video clips) we pursued
                    the following purposes: <list type="ordered">
                        <item> INCREASE MOTIVATION AND PARTICIPATION: <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Make the most engaging lessons;</item>
                                <item>Keep the student’s attention and make the most interesting
                                    content;</item>
                                <item>Promote interaction with content, teachers, within the
                                    class.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>RESPONDING TO THE BEST TO DIFFERENT COGNITIVE STYLES AND LEARNING:
                                <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Integrate different languages ​​(oral and written, iconic,
                                    multimedia, etc.).</item>
                                <item>Allowing the manipulation of learning objects and the
                                    activation of all the sensory channels.</item>
                                <item>Allow and encourage various forms and multiple approaches to
                                    learning.</item>
                                <item>Allow to overcome the digital divide.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>PROMOTE COLLABORATIVE AND COOPERATIVE LEARNING</item>
                    </list></p>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>Resilience</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig6.png"/>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>Prudence</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig7.png"/>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>
                <p> Fig. 5 and Fig. 6 are examples of patterns that were used to explain to children
                    aged between 9 to 10 some modern cardinal virtues expressed by the philosophical
                    concepts of <hi rend="italic">resilience</hi> (Fig. 5) and <hi rend="italic"
                        >prudence</hi> (Fig. 6). Figures and texts have been put together on the
                    basis of the characteristics of the users. We also followed three basic
                    principles: <list type="ordered">
                        <item> The <title rend="italic">Principle of the Multimediality</title> by
                            Landriscina <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/> which involves the use of
                            appropriate shapes to the texts presented, useful to facilitate the
                            understanding of the texts themselves. </item>
                        <item> The <title rend="italic"> Principle of Spatial-Temporal Contiguity
                            </title> by Landriscina <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/> which values
                            ​​the proximity between text and figure in view of learning content. </item>
                        <item> The <title rend="italic">Principle of Segmentation</title> by Mayer
                                <ptr target="#mayer2011"/> who states that it is better to present
                            the material in short controllable segments.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p> Referring to <title rend="italic">Dual Coding Theory</title>
                    <ptr target="#paivio1991"/> and to <title rend="italic">Multimedia
                        Representation Theory</title> we designed and implemented an educational
                    workshop for primary school students. In the educational workshop we selected
                    relevant information and organized it into coherent representations, so as to
                    complement the knowledge already possessed by pupils <ptr target="#cornoldi2005"
                    />. The presentation of the multimedia material, into small segments, has been
                    alternating with the reading, by the teacher, of texts related to the subject.
                    Each lesson ended with a graphic-pictorial production realized in small groups. </p>
                <p> The guiding principle of the whole educational workshop was the <title
                        rend="italic">Principle of Bimodality of Cognitive Learning Theory</title>
                    <ptr target="#mayer2001"/>
                    <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/>. It states that it is possible to demonstrate
                    the advantage of bimodal presentation (auditory and visual). Following, also,
                    the <title rend="italic">Principle of Redundancy</title> of the same theory,
                    which criticizes the presentation of the same information in too many formats,
                    we avoided using the third format (audio), preferring the <hi rend="italic"
                        >bimodal presentation</hi>
                    <ptr target="#mayer2001"/>
                    <ptr target="#landriscina2011"/>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A virtues meter questionnaire</head>
                <p> Our studies reveal that actually there is not a test to assess ethical literacy
                    literature-values as this area of investigation is still little investigated,
                    despite the recent bloom of research conducted in Italy around these important
                    issues <ptr target="#moscato2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#mortari2015"/>. This is the reason why at the beginning of the
                    workshop activities we elaborated and used a virtues meter questionnaire to
                    verify whether the educational activity carried out from school (the first
                    educational cycle: <title rend="quotes">G. Bovio</title>) and family was
                    efficient in relation to what Morin defines as the main objective of education:
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#morin2015">teaching to live</quote>. In
                    particular, through a set of questions that investigate thought and action of
                    young people we verified whether the educational activity is capable of focusing
                    the heart of the educational issue: the development of a thought useful for
                    life. The basic hypothesis, confirmed by the international literature and
                    statistical data (<ptr target="#baumann2011"/>; <ptr target="#bellingreri2014"
                    />; <ptr target="#morin2015"/>; <ptr target="#ISTAT2014"/> on behavioral habits
                    in young people; <ptr target="#IARD2014"/>; <ptr target="#wrd2015"/>), was that
                    there are serious gaps in the current educational system, which is too much
                    inclined towards the specialization and fragmentation of knowledge and
                    marginally interested in the integral formation of the human person. In
                    particular, the questionnaire pursued two principal research objectives: <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item>Evaluation of the level of metacognition and ethical-valorial
                            literacy;</item>
                        <item>Evaluation of behavioral habits, of futurization and level of
                            satisfaction and wellness.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p> In detail: <list type="simple">
                        <item>a) In order to evaluate the concept of metacognition the following
                            indicators have been utilized: Reading; Listening; Ability to remain in
                            silence; Ability of reflecting on own actions; Ability to fix own
                            errors. Instead, (<ref target="#table01">Table 1</ref>).</item>
                        <item>b) in order to evaluate the ethical-valorial literacy the following
                            indicators have been utilized: knowledge of Moral; knowledge of Virtue;
                            good life habits; relations with Religion; relationship with Philosophy
                            and with classic literature (<ref target="#table02">Table
                            2</ref>).</item>
                        <item>c) In order to evaluate the behavioral habits, the following
                            indicators have been utilized: Use of profanities; Critical issues in
                            relationships, educational profit, the number of good deeds performed
                            during the last week (<ref target="#table03">Table 3</ref>).</item>
                        <item>d) In order to evaluate the futurization, the following indicators
                            have been utilized: dreams; work/fight (<ref target="#table04">Table
                                4</ref>).</item>
                        <item>e) In order to evaluate the level of satisfaction and wellness, the
                            following indicators have been utilized: to love and to be loved;
                            resilience (<ref target="#table05">Table 5</ref>).</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p> The present questionnaire has been validated based on the following criteria: 1)
                    face validity or apparent validity; 2) content validity; 3) construct validity
                    and, in detail, factorial validity. Face validity or apparent validity refers to
                    the perception of detecting instrument on the part of those involved in the data
                    collection and for which we have adapted questions to the subject of the search
                    so that those questions were then recognized as valid in relation to the
                    objectives of the research. The content validity refers to contents expressed by
                    indicators, which should be consistent with how you plan to detect and represent
                    the objectives of the survey. In our study the set of indicators chosen for a
                    concept actually covers the entire domain of meaning of the concept in question.
                    To do this we have controlled on a purely theoretical basis, decomposing
                    analytically the concept studied in all its dimensions and ensuring that the
                    indicator covers all through a review of the literature and listening to the
                    opinion of several courts. Factorial validity can be seen in the correspondence
                    between the contents of the hypothesis (the gaps in moral education) and
                    empirical data that we obtained by the indicators (see T 1; T 2; T 3; T 4; T 5).
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>10. Results and discussion</head>
                <p> These are the levels of the indicators obtained before and after the educational
                    health promotion workshop. In particular, Table 1-5 show the levels of the
                    indicators for the concept of <hi rend="italic">metacognition</hi> (<ref
                        target="#table01">Tab. 1</ref>); for the <hi rend="italic">ethical-valorial
                        literacy</hi> (<ref target="#table02">Tab. 2</ref>); for the <hi
                        rend="italic">behavioral habits</hi> (<ref target="#table03">Tab. 3</ref>);
                    for the <hi rend="italic">futurization</hi> (<ref target="#table04">Tab.
                    4</ref>); for the <hi rend="italic">wellness/satisfaction</hi> (<ref
                        target="#table05">Tab. 5</ref>). </p>
                <table xml:id="table01">
                    <head>Evaluation of the concept of metacognition. Average increase 11.2%.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Reading</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Listening</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Ability to remain in silence</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Ability of reflecting on own actions</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Ability to fix own errors </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Before the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">7%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">19%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">11%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">After the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">10%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">21%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">9%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">31%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">27%</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table xml:id="table02">
                    <head>Validation of the concept of ethical-valorial literacy. Average increase
                        37%.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Knowledge of moral</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Knowledge of virtues</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Good life habits</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Relationship with religion</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Relationship with Philosophy and with classic
                            literature</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Before the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">9%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">11%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">17%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">2%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">After the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">70%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">83%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">21%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">41%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">13%</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table xml:id="table03">
                    <head>Validation of the concept of behavioral habits. Average increase
                        25%.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Use of profanities</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Critical issues in relationships</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Educational profit</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Number of good deeds performed during the last
                            week</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Before the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">21%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">15%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">27%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">3%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">After the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data">7%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">4%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">35%</cell>
                        <cell role="data">7%</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table xml:id="table04">
                    <head>Validation of the concept of futurization</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Dreams</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Work and fight</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Before the Course</cell>
                        <cell>12%</cell>
                        <cell>14%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">After the Course</cell>
                        <cell>47%</cell>
                        <cell>29%</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table xml:id="table05">
                    <head>Validation of the concept of wellness/satisfaction. Average increase
                        21%.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Level of satisfaction</cell>
                        <cell role="label">To love and to be loved</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Resilience</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Before the Course</cell>
                        <cell role="label">15%</cell>
                        <cell role="label">15%</cell>
                        <cell role="label">4%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">After the Course</cell>
                        <cell>39%</cell>
                        <cell>41%</cell>
                        <cell>17%</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p> It is clearly seen as the execution of the course has a positive effect on all
                    investigated indicators. </p>
                <p> In particular, an average increase of 11,2% was obtained for the indicator of
                        <hi rend="italic">metacognition</hi>. For the indicator of <hi rend="italic"
                        >behavioral habits</hi> we obtained an average decrease of 11,2% in <hi
                        rend="italic">use of profanities</hi> among pupils. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Educational profit</hi> increased by 8% and the <hi rend="italic">number of
                        good deeds performed during the last week</hi> increased by 4%. The
                    indicator of <hi rend="italic">futurization</hi> increased on average by 25%.
                    The indicator of <hi rend="italic">satisfaction/wellness</hi> increased on
                    average by 21%. The empirical analyses revealed educational changes which cannot
                    be enclosed in rigid tables and on which it is worthy to reflect: <list
                        type="unordered">
                        <item>Recurrent use of kind words;</item>
                        <item>enthusiasm; </item>
                        <item>curiosity; </item>
                        <item>desire to learn new things; </item>
                        <item>cooperativeness; </item>
                        <item>industry; </item>
                        <item>commitment.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p> The increase of the indicators combined with some qualitative observations
                    encourages us to believe that the educational workshop achieved the planned
                    objectives. The level of the concept of metacognition indicators (<ref
                        target="#figure07">Fig. 7</ref>) reveal a significant increase in capacity
                    of <hi rend="italic">reading and listening, ability to remain in silence,
                        ability of reflecting on own actions, and ability to fix own errors</hi>
                    after the Course. Probably, as Luigina Mortari states, the ethical-valorial
                    literacy acting on the cognitive and emotional level of the human person allows
                    the development of silent and unused human potentials in our postmodern culture,
                    which can convey true well-being <ptr target="#mortari2015"/>. </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>Level of the indicators of the concept of metacognition</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig7.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head>Level of the indicators of the concept of wellness/satisfaction</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/fig8.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Figure 8 shows the results of the level of the concept of wellness/satisfaction
                    indicators. The increase in level of satisfaction, the ability to love, and the
                    level of resilence encourages us to continue the research in the direction of
                    ethico-values ​​education supported by tools of <hi rend="italic">Visual
                        Communication.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>We consider as truthful the postulate hinge of the scientific method according to
                    which from the observation we pass to the theory. For what concerns the
                    educational, we consider as truthful the postulate which affirms that the
                    verification of the validity of a hypothesis takes place through educational
                    practice. From this it derives that, given the results of the empirical survey
                    conducted with the quali-quantitative method described, significantly unbalanced
                    towards the confirmation of the receptivity and plasticity of intentional will
                    or conscience and of the intelligence of the individual, it is legitimate to
                    affirm, with an appreciable degree of scientific certainty, that: <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Visual Communication Tools</hi> are able to support
                            and intersect education;</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Visual Communication Tools</hi> are useful for
                            promoting health and well-being in schools;</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Visual Communication Tools</hi> keep the pupils'
                            interest alive for a time much longer than the oral and literary
                            instruments of traditional learning;</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Visual Communication Tools</hi> are particularly
                            suitable for stimulating the intentionality of conscience in the search
                            for truth and in socio-ethical-affective literacy. </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Furthermore, the empirical experience conducted on the Italian sample leads us to
                    consider the effectiveness of a socio-ethical-affective literacy for the
                    development of metacognitive skills, proto-social skills and individual ethical
                    postures of health and well-being within and outside the school.</p>
                <p> These deductions, as we have shown in the previous arrays, are, however, in
                    harmony and do not contrast with what was recently reported in the international
                    literature. </p>
                <p> An element of particular originality of the present work can be grasped in the
                    choice of the application field in which to test the effectiveness of the new
                    technologies in the didactic field. </p>
                <p> The didactic use of new technologies to promote, through a
                    socio-ethical-affective literacy, a new kind of wellbeing and the integral
                    health of the students appears in Italy as an absolutely novel fact. </p>
                <p> From the ability to convey new contents of education through new methodologies
                    that complement, without replacing, the more traditional teaching methods, the
                    integral renewal of education that can train man and the citizen of tomorrow may
                    depend. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ausubel1978" label="Ausubel 1978">Ausubel, D.P. Educazione e processi
                    cognitivi. Guida psicologica per gli insegnanti, tr. it. di Daniela Costamagna
                    (a cura di), Milano: Franco Angeli (1978).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonaiuti2007" label="Bonaiuti et al. 2007">Bonaiuti, G., Calvani, A.
                    and Ranieri M. Fondamenti di didattica: teoria e prassi dei dispositivi
                    formativi. Roma: Carocci editore (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonaiuti2011" label="Bonaiuti 2011">Bonaiuti, G. Organizzatori grafici
                    e apprendimento in Calvani, A. (A cura di) Principi di comunicazione visiva e
                    multimediale. Fare didattica con le immagini. Roma: Carocci editore
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="botta2005" label="Botta 2005">Botta, M. Estetica dell'informazione:
                    introduzione alla teoria grafica-autonomatica. Milano: Ebook Apogeo
                    (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burgess2009" label="Burgess and Green 2009">Burgess, J., and Green, J.
                    Youtube: Digital Media and Society Series. Malden , MA: Polity Press
                    (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buzan1993" label="Buzan 1993">Buzan, T. The Mind Map Book: How to
                    Radiant Thinking to Maximize Your Brain's Untapped Potential, Plume, New York
                    (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvani2001" label="Calvani 2001">Calvani, A. Educazione,
                    comunicazione e nuovi media. Sfide pedagogiche e cyberspazio. U Torino: UTET
                    (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvani2011" label="Calvani 2011">Calvani, A. Principi dell’istruzione
                    e strategie per insegnare. Criteri per una didattica efficace. Roma: Carocci
                    editore (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvani2011b" label="Calvani 2011b">Calvani, A. Principi di
                    comunicazione visiva e multimediale. Fare didattica con le immagini. Roma:
                    Carocci editore (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvani1999" label="Calvani and Rotta 1999">Calvani, A., and Rotta, M.
                    Comunicazione e apprendimento in Internet: didattica costruttivistica in rete.
                    Torino: Erickson (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvani2000" label="Calvani and Rotta 2000">Calvani, A., and Rotta, M.
                    Fare formazione in Internet: manuale di didattica online. Trento: Erickson
                    (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chandler1991" label="Chandler and Sweller 1991">Chandler, P., and
                    Sweller, J. Cognitive load theory and the format of instruction, Cognition and
                    Instruction, 8 (1991): 293-332.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark2010" label="Clark and Lyons 2010">Clark, R.C. and Lyons, C.
                    Graphics for Learning: Proven Guidelines for Planning, Designing, and Evaluating
                    Visuals in Traning Materials. San Francisco: Pfeiffer (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cornoldi2005" label="Cornoldi et al. 2005">Cornoldi, C., Mammarella,
                    N., and Pazzaglia, F. Psicologia dell’apprendimento multimediale. E-learning e
                    nuove tecnologie. Bologna: il Mulino (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deangelis2017" label="De Angelis 2017">De Angelis, V. Educare al bene.
                    Appunti per una pedagogia del coraggio. Bari: Progedit (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deangelis2017b" label="De Angelis 2017b">De Angelis, V. Etica, fede e
                    formazione dell’umano: alleate nella cura della casa comune in Volume
                    collettaneo: <title rend="quotes">Trame di sostenibilità. Pedagogia
                        dell’ambiente, sviluppo umano, responsabilità sociale</title> di Birbes, C.
                    (a cura di). Lecce: Pensa Multimedia (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deangelis2017c" label="De Angelis and Gallelli 2017">De Angelis, V.
                    and Gallelli, R. Il sogno dell’inclusione nella scuola italiana: tra utopia ed
                    eutopia Pedagogia e Vita. Anno 75 (2017/2).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deangelis2015" label="De Angelis 2015">De Angelis, V. Nuove
                    tecnologie, fede e formazione dell’umano in Rivista Metis Progedit
                    (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deangelis2015b" label="De Angelis 2015b">De Angelis, V. The Challenge
                    of Faith. Media Education Studies &amp; Research (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="farne2002" label="Farnè 2002">Farnè, R. Iconologia didattica. Bologna:
                    Zanichelli (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallelli2011" label="Gallelli and Annacontini 2011">Gallelli, R. and
                    Annacontini, G. (a cura di) e.brain Sfide formative dai <soCalled>nativi
                        digitali</soCalled>. Franco Angeli (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallelli2007" label="Gallelli 2007">Gallelli, R. La scuola tra
                    individualizzazione e collaborazione, Roma: Editori Riuniti University Press
                    (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ganino2007" label="Ganino 2007">Ganino, G. Immagini per la didattica:
                    metodologie e tecnologie dell’audiovisivo digitale. Roma: Anicia (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gineprini2004" label="Gineprini and Guastavigna 2004">Gineprini, M.
                    and Guastavigna, M. Mappe per capire. Capire per mappe. Roma: Carocci
                    (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guastavigna2008" label="Guastavigna 2008">Guastavigna, M.
                    Graficamente. Roma: Carocci (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ID2000" label="ID 2000">ID. Immagini fatte ad arte: idee ed esperienze
                    per educare alla comunicazione visiva. Roma: Carocci (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="johnson-laird1980" label="Johnson-Laird 1980">Johnson-Laird, P.N.
                    Mental Models in Cognitive Science, in <title rend="quotes">Cognitive
                        Science</title>, 4 (1980): 71-115.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="landriscina2011" label="Landriscina 2011">Landriscina, F. Modelli di
                    riferimento per l'uso didattico della comunicazione visiva in Calvani A. (a cura
                    di). Principi di comunicazione visiva e multimediale. Fare didattica con le
                    immagini. Roma: Carocci editore (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="landriscina2007" label="Landriscina 2007">Landriscina, F. Carico
                    cognitivo e impiego della tecnologia per per apprendere, in A. Calvani (a cura
                    di), Tecnologia, scuola, processi cognitivi. Per una ecologia dell'apprendere.
                    Milano: Franco Angeli (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marini2001" label="Marini et al. 2001">Marini, D., Bertolo, M. and
                    Rizzi, A. Comunicazione visiva digitale: fondamenti di eidomatica. Milano:
                    Addison Wesley Longman Italia Editoriale (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="martine1999" label="Martine 1999">Martine, J. Introduzione all'analisi
                    dell'immagine. Torino: Lindau (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="massironi2002" label="Massironi 2002">Massironi, M. Psychology of
                    Graphic Images. Seeing, Drawing, Communicating. Mahwah (NJ): Lawrence Erlbaum
                    Associates (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mayer1989" label="Mayer 1989">Mayer, R.E., Models for Understanding,
                    in <title rend="quotes">Review of Educational Research</title>, 59 (1989):
                    43-64.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mayer2001" label="Mayer et al. 2001">Mayer, R.E., Heiser, J. and Lonn,
                    S. Cognitive Constraints on Multimedia Learning: When Presenting More Material
                    Results in Less Understanding, in “Journal of Educational Psychology”, 93
                    (2001): 187-98.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mayer2000" label="Mayer 2000">Mayer, R. Intelligence and Education, in
                    Handbook of Intelligence, a cura di R. J. Sternberg, New York, Cambridge
                    University Press (2000): 519-533.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mayer2001b" label="Mayer 2001b">Mayer, R. Multimedia Learning,
                    Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mortari2014" label="Mortari 2014">Mortari, L. Virtù a scuola,
                    Raffaello Cortina Editore (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="munari1999" label="Munari 1999">Munari, B. Design e comunicazione
                    visiva: contributo a una metodologia didattica. Bari: Laterza (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="novak2001" label="Novak 2001">Novak, J. L'apprendimento significativo.
                    Le mappe concettuali per creare e usare la conoscenza. Trento: Centro Studi
                    Erickson (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ogle1986" label="Ogle 1986">Ogle, D. KWL: A teaching Model that
                    Develops Active Reading of Expository text, in <title rend="quotes">The Reading
                        Teacher</title>, 32 (1986): 564-570.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="paivio1991" label="Paivio 1991">Paivio, A. Dual coding theory:
                    Retrospect and current status, in <title rend="quotes">Canadian Journal of
                        Psycology</title>, 45 (1991): 255-287.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="paoletti2011" label="Paoletti 2011">Paoletti, G. Comprendere testi con
                    figure Immagini, diagrammi e grafici nel design per l'istruzione. Milano: Franco
                    Angeli (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rovelli2014" label="Rovelli 2014">Rovelli, C. Sette brevi lezioni di
                    fisica. Milano: Adelphi (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="seel2003" label="Seel 2003">Seel, N.M., Model-Centered Learning and
                    Instruction. in <title rend="quotes">Technology, Instruction,cognition and
                        Learning</title>, I (2003): 59-85.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sweller1988" label="Sweller 1988">Sweller, J. Cognitive load during
                    problem solving: Effects on learning, in <title rend="quotes">Cognitive
                        Science</title>, 12 (1988): 257-285.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="trinchero2004" label="Trinchero 2004">Trinchero R., (2004), Modelli
                    mentali e costruzione di competenze sulla formazione on-line. in Form@re, 26,
                    aprile (<ref target="http://formare.erickson.it/wordpress/it/2004/"
                        >http://formare.erickson.it/wordpress/it/2004/</ref>).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="veen2006" label="Veen and Vrakking 2006">Veen, W. and Vrakking, B.
                    Homo Zappiens. Growing up in a digital age. London: Network Continuum education
                    (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zelazny2002" label="Zelazny 2002">Zelazny, G. Say It With Charts,
                    trad. it. Dillo con le slide: guida alla comunicazione visiva. Il Sole 24 Ore,
                    Milano (2002).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
