<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Dendrography and Art History: a
                    computer-assisted analysis of Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                    >Bathers</title>.</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Melinda <dhq:family>Weinstein</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Lawrence Technological University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mweinstei@ltu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Melinda Weinstein is Associate Professor of English at Lawrence
                            Technological University in Southfield, MI.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Edward <dhq:family>Voss</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Iowa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>Edward-voss@uiowa.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Edward Voss is Senior Research Associate at the W. M. Keck Dynamic Image
                            Analysis Facility at the University of Iowa.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Soll</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Iowa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>David-soll@uiowa.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David R Soll is Director of the Developmental Studies Hyridoma Bank, a
                            NIH National Resource, and Carver Professor at the University of
                            Iowa.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000423</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2019-10-14">14 October 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-10-11" who="p:murelj">Added issue nos.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Using DIAS and DENDRON, computer applications designed for the study of
                    infectious fungi and cancer cells, we forge a connection in color, composition,
                    and theme between Paolo Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                        Cana</title> and Paul Cézanne’s <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout,
                        s’essuyant les cheveux.</title> From this connection, we bring to light a
                        <quote rend="inline">hidden</quote> compositional structure, heretofore
                    unidentified, in Cézanne’s Bathers as a series. Using computer-assisted systems
                    such as DIAS and DENDRON allowed us to detect relatedness in these paintings not
                    necessarily visible to the human eye. With DIAS and DENDRON, we generated
                    dendrograms that clustered paintings related in brightness, saturation,
                    complexity, and color. After studying color, we applied DIAS to the study of
                    Cézanne’s composition. Because Cézanne expressed Neoplatonic ideals regarding
                    paintings in his conversations and letters, we programmed DIAS to compute axial
                    lines and <soCalled>golden sections</soCalled> according to the dimensions of
                    the square or rectangular painting under scrutiny. Using DIAS we identified the
                    golden rectangle for Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>,
                    Cézanne’s <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>
                    and Ingres’ <title rend="italic">La Source</title> (another likely model for
                        <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>). From
                    the similarities and differences between the three paintings we identified,
                    regarding their use of axial symmetry and the golden section, we have formulated
                    a new approach to <soCalled>seeing</soCalled> Cézanne’s composition in his
                    Bather series.   Cézanne’s noumenal bodies, formerly perceived as
                        <soCalled>awkward</soCalled> and composed with <quote rend="inline">baffling
                        imbalance,</quote> we can now see as <quote rend="inline"
                    >golden.</quote></p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <figure>
                    <head>L. Paolo Veronese, <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, 1563,
                        oil on canvas, 22 ft. x 3 in. x 32 ft. Louvre (before conservation) R. Paul
                        Cézanne, <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                            cheveux</title>, 1869-71, oil on canvas, 11 3/8 in. x 5 1/8 in. Private
                        Collection. A computer-assisted comparison using the newly developed
                        DIAS/DENDRON ART (DDA) software of fifty-five oil paintings by Paul Cézanne,
                        exhibited at the Galerie Vollard, Paris, in 1895, suggests that Cézanne’s
                            <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>,
                        is highly related to Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title>, in color, saturation, brightness, and complexity (Figures
                        2-4). Further computer-assisted analysis using DDA suggests that Cézanne
                        drew from Veronese a <soCalled>hidden</soCalled> compositional structure to
                        organize his Bather paintings</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Wölfflin V.2</head>
                    <p>Art history as an academic discipline is relatively new <ptr
                            target="#bod2013" loc="311–325"/>. <note>In <title rend="italic">A New
                                History of the Humanities: The Search for Principles and Patterns
                                from Antiquity to the Present</title> (Oxford: Oxford University
                            Press, 2013), Rens Bod maps art history’s trajectory in the western
                            world. For Bod, the formal study of art history begins with Vitruvius’s
                            theory of harmonious proportion in <title rend="italic">On
                                Architecture</title> (15 BCE) and continues with Pliny’s discussions
                            of illusionism in <title rend="italic">Natural History</title> (77 CE).
                            Though China had a thriving field of art historical scholarship in the
                            Middle Ages, the western world produced few written discussions of art
                            between Pliny and Alberti’s works. Bod cites Alberti’s <title
                                rend="italic">On Painting</title> (1435) as the first theoretical
                            treatise on art, followed by Piero della Francesca’s <title
                                rend="quotes">On the Perspective for Painting</title> (1435), A
                            Treatise on Painting, attributed to Leonardo da Vinci and compiled by
                            Francesco Melzi (1540), then Vasari’s <title rend="italic">Lives of the
                                Most Excellent Painters, Sculptors and Architects</title> (1550).
                            Bod views the advent of the digital humanities as a natural extension of
                            the general search for principles and patterns that directs humanistic
                            inquiry. 311-325.</note> Formally established in 1834 at the University
                        of Berlin with the appointment of Franz Kugler (1808-1858) as the first
                        professor of art history, Kugler and his successors Jacob Burkhardt
                        (1818-1897), and Heinrich Wölfflin (1864-1945) instituted methods for the
                        formal analysis of art and specified many categories used today for
                        classifying art <ptr target="#bod2013" loc="316"/>. <note>Kugler divided art
                            history into pre-Greek, classical, romantic and modern periods.
                            Burkhardt identified the features of Renaissance art. Wölfflin
                            distinguished Baroque from Renaissance art through the relations of
                            differences principle employed in structural linguistics. In
                            analytically comparing paintings, Wölfflin showed that Renaissance art
                            is <q>linear, flat, and closed,</q> while Baroque art is <q>painterly,
                                deep, and open.</q></note> Wölfflin is noted for <quote
                            rend="inline">using parallel projectors in the delivery of art history
                            lectures so that images could be compared.</quote>
                        <note>Wikipedia contributors, <q>Heinrich Wölfflin,</q> Wikipedia, The Free
                            Encyclopedia, (accessed September 13, 2017). <ref
                                target="#https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_W%C3%B6lfflin"
                                >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_W%C3%B6lfflin</ref>.</note>
                        If art history is relatively new as an academic course of study in the west,
                        computer-assisted analysis of art is in its <soCalled>infancy,</soCalled>
                        with Wölfflin, aided by slide projectors, as the first scholar to
                        demonstrate the utility of technology in the field. <note>Bod, p. 320.
                                <quote rend="inline">No matter how much the digital, computational
                                approach is in its infancy, it provides a powerful tool for testing
                                hypotheses relating to paintings.</quote></note> As the editors of
                            <title rend="italic">Digital Art History</title> note in their 2015
                        inaugural issue, Wölfflin’s mode of comparison <quote rend="inline">changed
                            the method of art history for good:</quote>
                        <quote rend="inline">His scientific achievements were a game changer in
                            perceiving, analyzing, and presenting works of art in the scientific
                            world and beyond</quote>
                        <ptr target="#klinke2015" loc="7"/>.</p>
                    <p>To say that comparisons have produced the categories that structure art
                        history as we know it today is not overstating the case. In <title
                            rend="quotes">Collections and/of Data: Art History and the Art Museum in
                            the DH Mode,</title> Matthew Battles and Michael Maizels stress the
                        centrality of the comparative slide lecture in the discipline. They write:
                            <quote rend="inline">The slide lecture maintains a powerful grip on the
                            collective art-historical imagination; it is the format through which
                            art historical [sic] training begins, and it is by far the most popular
                            means by which the discipline spreads its views and virtues to the mass
                            of uninitiated undergraduates.</quote>
                        <note>Matthew Battles and Michael Maizels, <title rend="quotes">Collections
                                and/of Data: Art History and the Art Museum in the DH Mode</title>
                            in <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
                            (2016). <ref target="#http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2"
                                >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2</ref>.</note> Lev Manovich,
                        in the first issue of <title rend="italic">DAH</title> concurs: <quote
                            rend="inline">to explore is to compare. And to compare, we first need to
                            see</quote>
                        <ptr target="#manovich2015" loc="33"/>. While computer-assisted text
                        analysis has a robust history since the 1950’s, the <title rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of Computer Vision and Image Analysis of Art</title> in
                        2008, 2010 and 2011 are the only journals devoted to exploring
                        computer-assisted methods for art analysis prior to <title rend="italic"
                            >DAH</title> in 2015. In the 2008 <title rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings</title>, editors David Stork and Jim Coddington propose
                        that computers <quote rend="inline">can reveal the fallibility in our
                            perception and teach all of us to see with a more informed eye and
                            mind</quote>
                        <ptr target="#stork2008"/>. <note>See also Vols. 7531 (2010) and 7869
                            (2011).</note> Computer-assisted methods of analysis can <quote
                            rend="inline">question the categories we already have, generate new
                            ones, or create cultural maps that relate cultural artifacts in original
                            ways</quote>
                        <ptr target="#stork2008" loc="24"/>. Since 2008, computer scientists in
                        collaboration with museum curators have applied computational methods to art
                        for conservation, reconstruction, and restoration. X-ray imaging, infrared
                        reflectography, UV-induced fluorescent imaging, and photo-induced
                        luminescence photography can reveal the under-layers of paintings, identify
                        the properties of pigments and binders, authenticate artworks, detect
                        forgeries, and gauge optimal designs for museum and digital displays.
                        Computer algorithms are used to measure and count brushstrokes, sort and
                        classify artworks by style, identify the salient features of an artist’s
                        style, and produce three-dimensional models that illustrate an artist’s
                        working methods.</p>
                    <p>Even though digital tools make art available for viewing, pedagogy, and
                        research like never before, <note>The New York Times announced that The
                            Metropolitan Museum is making 375,000 images from its collections
                            available online <quote rend="inline">for however you want to use
                                them.</quote> The National Gallery of Art in Washington, The
                            Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam, and the Museum of Modern Art in New York have
                            also made their collections freely available to the public for
                            downloading. Joshua Baron, <title rend="quotes">MET Museum Makes
                                350,0000 Images Free.</title>
                            <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, February 7, 2017.</note>
                        the use of data-enabled science, or algorithms, to interpret digitized art
                        and compare painting styles continues to provoke skepticism among humanists.
                                <note><quote rend="inline">It should be difficult today to conceive
                                of the computer as any more than a speedy idiot obeying a set of
                                precise instructions; but many in the humanities do indeed continue
                                to regard it as a black and magical (or black-magical) box — throw
                                the data at it, and somehow the computer will make sense of
                                them.</quote> Michael Greenhalgh, <title rend="italic">A Companion
                                to Digital Humanities</title>. <ref
                                target="#http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/"
                                >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/</ref>. Stephen Ramsay
                            in <title rend="italic">Humane Computation,</title> summarizes
                            objections to DH: <quote rend="inline">There are many who think scatter
                                plots filled with data points drawn from, say, English novels, are
                                already a crime against the humanities — the death of all that is good
                                and pure about humanistic study. For them, the problem is positivism
                                in its properly technical sense. They fear an epistemology that does
                                not merely value empirical data, but which (in its extreme
                                philosophical forms) considers empirical data to be the only valid
                                form of evidence. They imagine a computationally driven history or
                                French literature curriculum that forsakes the ancient circle of the
                                seminar for the modern angles of the server room. They imagine
                                humanistic conversation debasing itself in the form of technical
                                cavils, humanistic ethics becoming nothing more than <q>practical
                                    business ethics,</q> and teaching degenerating into mere
                                training.</quote></note> As Stephen Ramsay observes in <title
                            rend="quotes">Humane Computing</title>: <quote rend="inline">They fear
                            an epistemology that does not merely value empirical data, but which (in
                            its extreme philosophical forms) considers empirical data to be the only
                            valid form of evidence</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2016"/>. We believe that the visualizations produced by
                        computer applications do not replace direct experience of the artifact.
                        Correlations do not necessarily indicate causality or an ultimate
                        relationship in every instance. While a computer may place together certain
                        artists with similar styles in a cluster, this does not always imply that
                        there is a historical relationship between them, as their styles may have
                        simply undergone convergent evolution. The computer’s lack of historical and
                        artistic context means that the process always has a requirement of human
                        interpretation.</p>
                    <p>We propose here computer-assisted techniques for comparing color, saturation,
                        brightness and complexity between digitized paintings that updates
                        Wölfflin’s method. No studies of digitized art to date use dendrography, a
                        well-established method in computational biology since 1990. DIAS <ptr
                            target="#soll1995" loc="43–104"/>, an image analysis program, and
                        DENDRON <ptr target="#soll2000" loc="332–370"/>, a method for generating
                        trees reflecting relatedness, are patented, tried-and-true software
                        programs. Over 400 citations in peer-reviewed literature for the basic
                        methods paper describing DENDRON support efficacy <ptr target="#soll1995"/>.
                        Dendrography pre-dates the bourgeoning field of artificial intelligence and
                        machine learning. The efficacy of the very latest computer cognition systems
                        based in machine learning is viewed at this time as inconclusive. As <title
                            rend="italic">Science Daily</title> (1/7/19) reports in <quote
                            rend="inline">Can artificial intelligence tell a teapot from a golf
                            ball? Severe limitations of <q>deep learning</q> machines</quote> — even
                        the latest programs cannot accurately identify shape when a pattern
                        associated with another shape is grafted onto it. Machine learning systems
                            <quote rend="inline">are easily fooled.</quote>
                        <note><ref target="www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/01/190107131236.html"
                                >www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/01/190107131236.html</ref>.
                            Accessed 1/9/19.</note> Dendrography is a traditional computer-assisted
                        method of comparing images and patterns. To that end, we believe that the
                        computer applications DIAS and DENDRON, having been validated in many
                        fields, may reliably <quote rend="inline">extend the senses,</quote>
                        <note>In the context of book history, and the shift from orality to
                            literacy, Marshall McLuhan discusses the way technology
                                <soCalled>extends</soCalled> the senses in <title rend="italic">The
                                Gutenberg Galaxy: The Making of Typographic Man</title>. Toronto:
                            University of Toronto Press, 1965. 40.</note> of the art historian. The
                        visualizations they produce suggest similarities between paintings easily
                        missed by human beings whose capacity to compare is limited by conceptual
                        and subjective bias, lack of access to a work, or any number of reasons that
                        make creating interesting comparisons challenging.</p>
                    <p> Dendrography has enormously productive applications for the comparison of
                        formal and iconographic elements in paintings. Since formal analysis is
                        often viewed as outdated in today’s art history, its potential as a subject
                        for computational analysis has been overlooked (except for the few
                        curatorial forays in this direction). As such, our approach not only
                        attempts to see the value of the computational method, but also what DENDRON
                        and DIAS may do to open up in surprising new ways what has been considered a
                        finished part of the field. This may be the first study in digital art
                        history that uses dendrography to cluster similar paintings and that employs
                        computer programs to calculate golden rectangles in paintings for
                        comparative purposes. The ever-growing raft of digitized paintings online,
                        and the continual improvement of digital photography, calls for
                        computer-assisted methods as long as these programs are reliable, the
                        questions posed are appropriate for computer-assisted investigation, and the
                        final interpretations are considered just that, namely interpretations.</p>
                    <p>Using the newly customized DIAS/DENDRON (DDA) programs (<ref
                            target="#appendix1">Appendix I</ref>), we investigate in Part I a
                        persistent connection between <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>
                        by Veronese and Cézanne’s first female bather <title rend="italic">La
                            Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>. <title rend="italic"
                            >Les Noces de Cana</title> is enormous in scale, more than twenty-two
                        feet by thirty-two feet in height and length, while the <title rend="italic"
                            >baigneuse</title> is tiny, only eleven inches in height and five inches
                        in width. <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>’s subject matter is
                        biblical, Christ transforming water into wine at the marriage feast, while
                        Cézanne’s work is prosaic, a woman drying her hair after a bath. A
                        traditional art historian, guided by genre expectations, might conclude that
                        scale and theme obviate potential connections between the works, but using
                        DDA, which normalizes scale, we can grasp surprising connections. Now, using
                        DDA analysis, we can see how Cézanne capitalizes on Veronese’s color scheme
                        in his first female <title rend="italic">baigneuse</title>. We may also use
                        DDA to suggest new approaches to old problems. For example, Cézanne painted
                        over eighty bathers in his lifetime, but these paintings continue to mystify
                        scholars. To date, they are mostly interpreted in psychanalytic terms as
                        representing Cézanne’s repressed sexuality and/or aggression.<note>J.T.
                            Clark’s famous <title rend="quotes">Cézanne’s Freud</title>. <title
                                rend="italic">Representations</title> 52. Fall 1995 is
                            representative of this approach. Of Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                                >Baigneurs en repose</title> he writes, <quote rend="inline">never,
                                for a start, has a picture declared itself so openly — so awkwardly
                                — made out of separate, overdetermined parts coexisting only in
                                sufferance.</quote> 94.</note> When we saw that Cézanne’s <title
                            rend="italic">baigneuse</title> might be intimately connected to <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, we then employed DDA to explore
                        potential similarities in composition. In Part 2, using DDA analysis, we
                        discovered that the composition of <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title> is based on axial symmetry and the golden ratio (phi). When
                        we apply DDA to identify axial symmetry and the golden ratio to <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and the
                        rest of Cézanne’s bathers, we find that Cézanne imitates the composition of
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> in virtually every bather
                        painting. Based on axial symmetry and the golden section, then, we have
                        formulated a computer-assisted approach to <soCalled>seeing</soCalled>
                        Cézanne’s composition in his Bather series. Cézanne’s bathers, formerly
                        perceived as <quote rend="inline">awkward</quote> and composed with <quote
                            rend="inline">baffling imbalance,</quote> can now be viewed as <quote
                            rend="inline">golden</quote>
                        <ptr target="#danchev2013" loc="11"/>. With DDA, we find that Cézanne is
                        more likely guided by mathematics in designing his bather paintings, rather
                        than by unconscious drives or motives.</p>
                    <p> This approach is an intervention in the newly established trend within the
                        digital humanities of the <soCalled>micro-digital
                                humanities.</soCalled><note><quote rend="inline">The practices
                                include the embrace of minimal computing, small data sets, local
                                archives, and freely available platforms for creating small-scale
                                digital humanities projects while working with undergraduate
                                students.</quote> Roopika Risam and Susan Edwards, <title
                                rend="quotes">Micro DH: Digital Humanities at the Small
                                Scale</title>
                            <ref target="#https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/196/196.pdf"
                                >https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/196/196.pdf</ref>.</note> We are
                        not, as Michael Greenhalgh imagines of digital art historians, <q>throw[ing]
                            data</q> at the computer while hoping that somehow <quote rend="inline"
                            >the computer will make sense of them</quote>
                        <ptr target="#greenhalgh"/>. We are not sifting <quote rend="inline">the
                            great unknown</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cohen2009"/> for connections between texts or visual images,
                        instead, we are comparing smaller curated datasets in order to measure
                        influence between a master and student, a source and a re-imagining.<note>
                            In <title rend="quotes">Distant Reading and Intellectual
                            History</title>, Ted Underwood writes that distant reading <quote
                                rend="inline">doesn’t overemphasize technology, and it candidly
                                admits that new methods are mainly useful at larger scales of
                                analysis.</quote> Our work here scales down a distant reading
                            approach. 138 paintings is still more than the brain can handle in
                            making comparisons, nevertheless, the data set is small enough to allow
                            the researcher to toggle between the images and graphical output to
                            verify hypotheses and make discoveries.</note> In this case, we are
                        comparing fifty-five curated digital facsimiles of Cézanne’s oil paintings
                        exhibited in Ambroise Vollard’s 1895 Salon to Veronese’s <title
                            rend="italic">Le Noces de Cana</title>, a source Cézanne
                            <emph>identified as influential to him as an artist</emph>.</p>
                    <p> Standing before <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, Cézanne is
                        reported to have said regarding its color: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block">That is what a painting should give us, a harmonious
                                warmth, an abyss in which the eye can sink, a silent germination. A
                                state of grace in colors…To love a painting, first you have to drink
                                it in this way, in long drafts, lose consciousness; descend with the
                                painter into the dark, complicated roots of objects come up again
                                with colors, bloom with them in the sun. You have to know how to
                                see, to feel, especially in front of a great machine such as the one
                                Veronese built</quote>
                            <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="133"/>. </cit> Art Historian Susan
                        Sidlauskas describes Cézanne’s experience of the Veronese painting as like
                            <quote rend="inline">a mystic’s fusion with the deity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sidlauskus2004" loc="12"/>. Cézanne thought of Veronese’s
                        colors as <quote rend="inline">great noumenal entities, living ideas,
                            creatures of pure reason…with whom we might correspond</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="124"/>. By <quote rend="inline">great
                            machine,</quote> we take Cézanne to mean that Veronese’s work delivers
                        to the aspiring painter figure studies, compositions, color combinations and
                        more, structures that an artist can imitate.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Quality of digital reproductions</head>
                    <p> As Philip Ball observes in <title rend="italic">Bright Earth</title>, <quote
                            rend="inline">all reproductions are approximations</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ball2001" loc="271"/>.<note>Can digital images replace
                            physical paintings as serious objects for study? Certainly, there are
                            irreducible elements to paintings that do not translate well
                            electronically or in print, and that demand first-person viewing, such
                            as the luminous and changing effects of varnishes and glazes on
                            paintings, and the layering and aging of paints. Whether in print or
                            online, all reproductions of paintings are
                                <soCalled>approximations</soCalled>. In even the most expensively
                            illustrated books, the same paintings may vary in color. Phillip Ball
                            discusses the limitations of print and the digital reproductions of
                            works of art in <title rend="italic">Bright Earth</title>. He observes
                            how <quote rend="inline">for a coloristically complex picture like
                                Danae, no two reproductions will look the same.</quote>
                            Nevertheless, <quote rend="inline">All written discourses of art must
                                rely on reproductions to make their point.</quote> Art Historians
                            depend on approximations for their work, and computer-assisted systems,
                            though they convert these approximations into numbers, can provide us
                            with data that is inaccessible subjectively, data that the researcher
                            must interpret.</note> And in regards to <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                            de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s bathers, we must ask of any facsimile
                        whether it is <quote rend="inline">well or badly reproduced</quote>
                        <ptr target="#latour2011" loc="278"/>. Digital reproductions must be as
                        close to the original as possible. Bruno Latour and Adam Lowe discuss at
                        length <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>’s complex
                            <soCalled>trajectory</soCalled> as an image. What Cézanne saw between
                        1861, his first trip to Paris, until his death in 1906 is not the <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> that we see now in the Louvre,
                        as conservationist efforts have modified the painting. Currently <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> exists in its
                            <soCalled>original</soCalled> (though repainted) version at the Louvre,
                        and it exists in a fully <soCalled>restored</soCalled> version, based on
                        digitization, housed in its <soCalled>original</soCalled> context, in a
                        Benedictine refectory in Venice. The Louvre <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                            de Cana</title> is considerably darker than the Benedictine digital
                        facsimile. The coat of the server depicted in the foreground of the Louvre
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> was originally red but
                        was changed to green in 1989. Thus, no version today is exactly what Cézanne
                        saw. For our purposes here, we use a digitized image of the pre-1989 <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, with the tabard in his
                            <soCalled>original</soCalled> red coat. This, perhaps begrimed with more
                        dust, is the closest <soCalled>approximation</soCalled> to what Cézanne
                        would have seen. However, we demonstrate that DDA grouped <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> in the
                        same cluster with both renditions of <title rend="italic">Le Noces de
                            Cana</title> in dendrograms (<ref target="#appendix2">Appendix
                        II</ref>).</p>
                    <p>Choosing Cézanne’s paintings for computer-assisted analysis is also
                        complicated. Cézanne left many works unfinished, therefore, we selected for
                        this study paintings exhibited during his lifetime. The paintings exhibited
                        in the 1895 Vollard exhibition is an exemplary dataset for computation, as
                        it was Cézanne’s first one-man show, with examples of paintings from every
                        stage of his development. Most important, we can presume Ambroise Vollard,
                        Cézanne’s friend and patron exhibited the works as
                            <soCalled>finished</soCalled> with the artist’s support. For information
                        about Cézanne’s paintings, and for digital facsimiles, we relied on John
                        Rewald’s printed <title rend="italic">Catalogue Raisonné</title> and Walter
                        Feichenfeldt, Jayne Warman and David Nash’s <title rend="italic">The
                            Paintings of Paul Cézanne: an Online Catalogue Raisonné</title>
                        <ptr target="#rewald1996"/>. <ref target="#supplementaltable1">Supplemental
                            Table I</ref> lists all paintings used for this study and their digital
                        and material provenance. All digital images are in the public domain for
                        research and educational use. When there were multiple versions of digitized
                        images on the web with different levels of brightness, saturation, and
                        coloring, we consulted the online <title rend="italic">Catalogue
                            Raisonné</title>, for the best match, or the websites of the museums
                        that housed the work. In many cases, we checked digital facsimiles against
                        original paintings on site in New York, Philadelphia, Chicago, and Detroit,
                        not only for accuracy in color, brightness, and saturation, but also for
                        correct margin between figure and frame for our geometric partitioning.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Generating dendrograms</head>
                    <p>The software program we have developed to compare digitized paintings is a
                        composite of two patented programs DIAS (US patent #5,655,028 1997) and
                        DENDRON (US patent #5,400,249 1995). The customized program DDA, allows the
                        user to store and sort digitized images of pictures in a data file, measure
                        parameters for comparison and then generate dendrograms, visual phylogenies
                        of relatedness based on one or any combination of parameters. Both DIAS and
                        DENDRON began development in the late 1980’s. DIAS was developed to analyze
                        cell morphology, shape, cell movement and the dynamics of populations of
                        cells, and has recently been used to study tumorigenesis in 2D and 3D.
                        Dendron was developed to analyze and compare DNA fingerprints of infectious
                        organisms and has been used to follow the progression of diseases in human
                        populations. In <title rend="quotes">The Ins and Outs of DNA Fingerprinting
                            the Infectious Fungi,</title> DENDRON is described in terms that we
                        apply here for the comparison of paintings between the same or different
                        painters. The combined programs, including the parameters we have measured
                        and compared, and the generation of dendrograms, are described in Appendix I
                        in more detail, with relevant references. In brief, images of a collection
                        of pictures were scanned into a DDA data file. The DIAS portion of the
                        program then automatically computed nine parameters, which included
                        brightness, saturation, complexity, redness, orangeness, yellowness,
                        greenness, blueness and purpleness. These parameters are described in
                        Appendix I. To assess a similarity coefficient between two pictures for any
                        one of these parameters or amongst any combination of these parameters, each
                        parameter is assessed in a range of 0.00 to 1.00, 0.00 representing no
                        relatedness and 0.01 to 1.00 representing progressively increasing values.
                        The similarity coefficient (S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>) for one or any
                        combination of parameters is then computed between all pairs of paintings in
                        a collection, generating a matrix of S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>’s as
                        demonstrated in Appendix I, Table A. Based on the matrix of S<hi
                            rend="subscript">AB</hi>’s, a dendrogram (i.e., a phylogenetic tree of
                        relatedness) is then generated by the unweighted pairgroup method based upon
                        the arithmetic averages (UPGMA), originally used by Rohlf <ptr
                            target="#rohlf1963"/>, discussed in detail by Sneath and Sokal <ptr
                            target="#sneath1973"/> and developed for DENDRON by Schmid et al. <ptr
                            target="#schmid1990"/>. The accuracy of the program was validated by
                        Pujol et al <ptr target="#lockhart1997"/>, with more than 410 citations in
                        the literature reported by Google Scholar just for the methods paper <title
                            rend="quotes">The Ins and Outs of Fingerprinting for Infectious
                            Fungi</title>
                        <ptr target="#soll2000"/>. In the generated dendrogram (e.g., in Figures 2
                        and 3), the nodes (i.e., vertical connections) approximate the hierarchy of
                        similarity. An arbitrary threshold is drawn as a black vertical line through
                        the dendrogram simply is a tool for visualizing the refutation of similarity
                        or clades, related groups and clusters of paintings.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Analysis of relatedness using dendrography</head>
                    <p>Using DDA, we compared Cézanne’s fifty-five oil paintings presented at the
                        Galerie Vollard in 1895 and Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title>. The S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>’s for all DIAS
                        parameters were used in generating the dendrogram in Figure 2. The
                        dendrogram generated in this case could be separated into seven clades, a
                        through f, using an S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> threshold of 0.83. Both
                        Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and six
                        additional Cézanne paintings were included in clade f (Figure 2).
                        Interestingly, of the three paintings painted in the 1860s by Cézanne after
                        first viewing <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, two of them,
                            <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>
                        (1869) and <title rend="italic">L’orgie de Nabuchodonosor</title> (1967),
                        resided in clade f, and were highly related. Since it was obvious that the
                        one color assessed by DIAS in the unrestored <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                            de Cana</title> that appeared disproportionally faded was <quote
                            rend="inline">green</quote>, (and since the painting lacks the heavy
                        green coat of the tabard as in post-1989 retouched versions), we generated a
                        dendrogram in which the composite S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> was computed
                        for all parameters but green (see table in the right lower corner of Figure
                        3). Using a high threshold, 14 clades were distinguished (Figure 3). One
                        clade, b, clustered six pictures, which included <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> in a subclade with a node of
                        0.92 and a subcluster of four paintings, three of which (<title
                            rend="italic">Les Begonias</title>, <title rend="italic">La
                            Baignade</title>, <title rend="italic">Nature Morte</title>) also
                        resided in the clade b, containing <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title> and <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                            cheveux</title>, using all parameters in Figure 2. Since a digital
                        version of the restored <title rend="quotes">Les Noces de Cana</title> is
                        widely accessable on the web, we generated a dendrogram using the complete
                        collection of parameters and obtained similar clustering of the restored
                        facsimile of <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s
                            <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>
                            (<ref target="#appendix2">Appendix II</ref>). Again, Cézanne’s <title
                            rend="italic">L’Orgie de Nabuchodonosor</title> clustered with
                        Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s
                            <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>.
                        The two Cézanne paintings were generated in 1969 and 1967, respectively, so
                        both reflect early works potentially highly related to <title rend="italic"
                            >Le Noce de Cana</title>. We also analyzed the restored <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> facsimile and the Cézanne
                        collection using all parameters but green, and found that the restored
                        facsimile was in a cluster containing Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and the other
                        clustered paintings (<ref target="#appendix2">Appendix II</ref>). We
                        generated a dendrogram of the Cézanne collection that included, both the
                        unrestored and restored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>. The
                            <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>
                        and both unrestored and restored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title> paintings clustered, and the cluster contained the same
                        additional paintings in the clusters of the dendrograms generated with
                        either the unrestored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> alone
                        or the restored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> (<ref
                            target="#appendix2">Appendix II</ref>, Figure A, B, C, D). In support of
                        the similarity assessed by DDA in the collection in Figure 2, we generated a
                        dendrogram that included Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title>, Cézanne’s <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout,
                            s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, and 19 paintings by other artists
                        including Delacroix, Rubens and Tintoretto, all of which were shown in the
                        Louvre between 1861 and 1906 (<ref target="#appendix3">Appendix III</ref>,
                        Figure A). The <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> paintings
                        grouped into a primary cluster, indicated by thick red lines, again
                        indicating not only the similarity between Veronese’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Les Noce de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse</title> paintings, but also the accuracy of the DDA
                        programs.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>1895 Galerie Vollard paintings and <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                                Cana</title>. The dendrogram sorted 56 digitized oil paintings (55
                            by Cézanne, 1 by Veronese) into clades based on relatedness defined by
                            six parameters. The vertical black line represents an arbitrary
                            threshold (.83) to define moderately related clusters of paintings based
                            on all parameters maximized. These major clades are noted (a through f)
                            by shorter and thinner vertical bars to the right of the dendrogram.
                            Paul Cézanne’s <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                                cheveux</title> and Paolo Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                                de Cana</title> are connected at .83.</head>
                        <figDesc/>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In our first experiment (Figure 2), we found potential correlation between
                        the <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and the <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse</title>, along with other paintings. In our
                        second experiment (Figure 3), we found that when we control for green,
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and the <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse</title> correlate more closely at .9.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>1895 Galerie Vollard paintings and the unrestored <title rend="italic"
                                >Les Noces de Cana</title>, controlled for green.</head>
                        <figDesc/>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In Figure 3, <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title
                            rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> cluster
                        with three other paintings: <title rend="italic">Les Bégonias</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">La Baignade</title>, <title rend="italic">Pommes et
                            Linge</title>, and <title rend="italic">Nature Morte</title> at .9 with
                            <title rend="italic">Le Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> further discriminating
                        as similar at .91. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Part 2. Hidden Patterns</head>
                    <p>Just like Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, Paul
                        Cézanne’s paintings continue to inspire wonder in his admirers. His
                        contemporaries, Renoir and Matisse, spoke of his deployment of color and
                        composition in godlike terms, while scholars today <soCalled>struggle to
                            know</soCalled> his secret. Cézanne’s last words in 1904 to the young
                        painter Emile Bernard heighten the sense of mystery and unknowability that
                        surround the painter’s process. Richard Shiff’s 2004 Introduction to
                        Conversations with Cézanne illustrates this mystery: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block">
                                <quote rend="inline">He takes his secret to the grave,</quote>
                                remarked Bernard to his wife, upon receiving word of Cézanne’s
                                death: <quote rend="inline">he wrote that he wanted to tell me
                                    everything, and I don’t know what he meant by that.</quote>
                                Regretting his failure to visit Aix in 1906 as planned, Bernard knew
                                that Cézanne, only a month before, had suggested that both men would
                                better <quote rend="inline">explain themselves</quote> whenever they
                                finally met again in person. Even more poignantly, Bernard could
                                recall the cryptic promise Cézanne included in a letter of the
                                previous year: <quote rend="inline">I owe you the truth in painting
                                    [en peinture], and I will tell it to you</quote></quote>
                            <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="xxxiv"/>.</cit></p>

                    <p>Shiff concludes, <quote rend="inline">Like Bernard-like Cézanne himself-we
                            struggle to know</quote> (my italics). We propose Cézanne worked from a
                        plan, and that his comments to Bernard indicate guardedness about sharing
                        his process. As he advised the fellow painter Maurice Denis: <quote
                            rend="inline">You have to have a method. My father [said], <q>People
                                have to play games.</q> That’s what I search for in
                            painting...theories, sensations and theories...I wanted to copy nature
                            but I never could do it</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="93–94"/>. In this second part of our analysis
                        we identified parameters for DDA which we believed would allow us to begin
                        to assess similarities based on composition. We tested whether <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> shared potential
                        compositional similarities, and we sought parameters related to composition
                        that could be quantified. Because of Cézanne’s frequent references to <quote
                            rend="inline">harmony</quote> in his conversations and letters, and his
                        documented love for classical Greek and Roman culture, we turned to
                        Classical conceptions of harmony, based on numbers and geometry, for
                        parameters that we could quantify.</p>

                    <p>In this section, we compare only the relationship between axial lines and
                        golden rectangles as determined by the picture’s frame in <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>. We decided to
                        automate identification of the center and central axis of a painting,
                        because of their technical importance to an artist, and because of their
                        semantic weight. For Rudolf Arnheim, the dead center of a painting is not
                        dead but <quote rend="inline">alive with tension</quote>
                        <ptr target="#arnheim1974" loc="11, 16"/>. The vertical and horizontal
                        bisecting lines emanating from the center establish a <quote rend="inline"
                            >solid spatial trellis in the brain.</quote> An artist must master the
                        axis first, according to Arnheim, as it <quote rend="inline">remains the
                            base of reference that alone make obliqueness possible. Obliqueness is
                            always perceived as a deviation [from the axis] hence its strongly
                            dynamic character.</quote> Computer-assisted methods for identifying
                        centers and axial lines are helpful as these can be mis-apprehended by a
                        viewer. For example, upon first glance, many people see Christ as the center
                        of <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, as opposed to the men
                        carving meat on the balustrade above him. Once we used DDA to identify the
                        center and the horizontal and vertical bisecting lines of <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, we chose to automate the
                        identification of golden sections in a painting as determined by the square
                        picture plane. In Appendix IV, we present the steps in the DDA program
                        employed to automatically identify a number of geometric landmarks including
                        what we have defined as the <soCalled>golden window,</soCalled> in a
                        painting. This involves identifying the <soCalled>golden
                            rectangle</soCalled> and the axial lines bisecting both vertically and
                        horizontally the picture plane.</p>

                    <p>Many scholars have attempted to find hidden patterns in art works based on
                        numbers. Most recently, Robert Bork’s studies of golden sections in medieval
                        cathedral ground plans show that for centuries, artists and architects have
                        used the mysterious divine proportion or golden ratio (1.618...) in their
                        designs <ptr target="#bork2012"/>. For Arnheim, the golden ratio is
                        satisfying <quote rend="inline">because of its combination of unity and
                            dynamic variety, whole and parts are nicely adjusted in strength so that
                            the whole prevails without being threatened by a split, but at the same
                            time, the parts retain some self-sufficiency</quote>
                        <ptr target="#arnheim1974"/>. Veronese and Cézanne would have been familiar
                        with Luca Pacioli’s handbook for artists, <title rend="italic">De Divina
                            Proportione</title>, published in 1509. Seventy-one chapters are
                        dedicated to demonstrating the <q>golden</q> section, a mathematical
                        proportion based on an equation that produces <q>phi</q> or the never-ending
                        value of 1.618... in artworks <ptr target="#pacioli2014"/>. Cézanne’s
                        contemporary Symbolists, Odilon Redon and Paul Serusier, considered Platonic
                        geometry, holy, or mystical, because it appeared in nature as repeated
                        numbers and patterns. Cézanne and Veronese absorbed the concept of divine
                        proportion in their training, and when they had the problem of creating a
                        two-dimensional structure that expressed <quote rend="inline">witnessing the
                            holy,</quote> they found a rule or <quote rend="inline">game</quote> in
                        the golden section that suited their purposes. Using DDA, as a tool to
                        section a painting geometrically, we show that the golden section may have a
                        formal and thematic purpose for Veronese in <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                            de Cana</title> (<ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>) and that
                        Cézanne might have elaborated on this compositional structure in his Bather
                        paintings.</p>


                    <p>While we could have discovered this hidden composition by applying a ruler
                        and compass to reproductions from books, the advantage of DDA in studying
                        composition is the mechanization of the geometer’s tools, and the quantity
                        of digital reproductions we can quickly, and more precisely, <q>rule</q>
                        than with human hands. It also allows for the quantification of parameters
                        from the digitized image for further comparison using DDA software. DDA
                        determines and saves golden ratio rectangles from any point on a painting,
                        drawing up to nine symmetrical vertical or horizontal staves across a
                        painting, and imposing and saving geometrical shapes on digital paintings.
                        Since these parameters are associated with Neoplatonic ideals and classical
                        harmony, we feel these might have bearing on Cézanne’s painterly concerns in
                        his <title rend="italic">Bathers</title> series. <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> achieves its
                        uniqueness not only from a masterful deployment of color modelled on
                        Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, but also from its
                        invisible scaffolding, based on Platonic geometry. We believe that Cézanne
                        hides this <q>game</q> in plain sight.</p>

                    <p>Cézanne left eighty <title rend="italic">Bather</title> paintings in various
                        states of completion after his death in 1906 at the age of 68. He repeats
                        this, heretofore unidentified, compositional structure throughout his Bather
                        series. Since Cézanne appears to have modeled his first female bather on
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, as our dendrograms
                        imply, it is likely that Cézanne is linking <title rend="italic">Les Noces
                            de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant
                            les cheveux</title> semantically. The subject of <title rend="italic"
                            >Les Noces de Cana</title> is a wedding feast at Canaan where Christ
                        performs the miracle of turning water into wine, a potent metaphor for the
                        artist translating raw materials into representations. Christ transmutes
                        water, something common, into something holy, strange, and magical;
                        likewise, Cézanne divinizes his bathers; he makes them noumenal, by way of
                        his predecessor Veronese — through color harmonies and divine geometry.</p>

                    <p>Cézanne viewed geometry as a divine architecture, and he understood the
                        center of a bounded four-sided square to be its axial eye. The center of a
                        painting represents the <quote rend="inline">truth</quote> or the <quote
                            rend="inline">eye of god</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hendrix2004"/>. In its aggressively axial construction <ref
                            target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>, Veronese appears to take account of
                        the square frame, its center, the golden rectangle, and the golden window in
                        organizing his composition for thematic effect (<ref target="#appendix4"
                            >Appendix IV</ref>). The sacrificial meat above Christ’s head is at the
                        exact center of <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>. Like a
                        blade, the vertical and horizontal axes divide the meat. The axis signifies
                        that the focus of the painting is sacrifice, and its cognates, Christ,
                        directly below the sacrificial meat, and the dog at the bottom of the
                        painting. The vertical axis bisecting the painting runs directly through
                        Christ’s right eye and the left eye of the dog. As a dog signifies loyalty
                        in medieval/renaissance Christian iconography, the implied vertical line
                        uniting sacrifice/Christ’s eye/loyalty appears to emphasize Veronese’s aim
                        of producing a sensually enlightening painting. To make the painting’s
                        purpose legible, he provides a strong horizontal balcony across the middle
                        of the painting above Christ’s head. The top of the balcony passes through
                        the exact center of the painting.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Figure 4. <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> (restored
                            version). Golden rectangle, golden window, horizontal and vertical
                            bisecting lines.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>In <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>
                        <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>, just as axial intersection
                        emphasizes theme, so too does the golden section. The golden section
                        intersects Christ’s eyes, and the eyes or mouths of the witnesses flanking
                        Christ. The <soCalled>golden window</soCalled> we have identified frames a
                        quarter of Christ’s face, partial faces of three witnesses to his left
                        (specifically through the mouth and eyes). Then, above and behind them,
                        three convex columns supporting the balustrade where butchers are preparing
                        sacrificial meat. Technically, the benefit of a <soCalled>golden
                            window</soCalled> for Veronese is that it allows him to represent depth
                        by mediating the distance between flat wall and blue sky with a band of
                        recessing modulations. In the golden window of Figure 4, we glimpse the
                        tablecloth behind the columns of the balustrade above Christ’s head, as well
                        as the robes of the butcher, and a building in the distance. In Figure 4,
                        the golden window underscores theme and creates a sense of depth or of
                            <soCalled>descended</soCalled> figures within the composition of the
                        painting. As Christ has <soCalled>descended</soCalled> from his godlike
                        nature to be among humans, the golden ratio becomes the line along which
                        Veronese arranges Christ and his witnesses at the feast. In Figure 5, we see
                        the lowering effect afforded by the golden window. Through the golden
                        window, we see Cézanne’s central bather (whose right knee and shoulder are
                        aligned with the vertical axis of the picture frame), descending into a pool
                        of water. We can now say that, in addition to discovering surprising
                        connections in color, saturation, complexity and brightness in paintings,
                        there are landmarks in paintings that DDA automatically computes. These are
                        the center of the painting, the horizontal and vertical bisecting lines
                        (axis), the golden rectangle, the golden strips (the space between the
                        vertical and horizontal bisecting lines and the golden sections of the upper
                        right and lower left sides of the picture plane), and the golden window
                        (located at the right base of the golden rectangle).</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure05">
                        <head>Figure 5. Golden Window: Cézanne signaling its
                                <soCalled>lowering</soCalled> effect. Paul Cézanne, <title
                                rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>, 1890, 15 3/8 x 20 7/8in. In
                            addition to being the source as life and the means of ritual
                            purification, water has literary associations with the bucolic poetry of
                            Theocritus and Virgil.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>Like Leonardo da Vinci, Cézanne thought paintings were superior to poems
                        because they inspired reverence in viewers <ptr target="#kemp1989" loc="28"
                        />. As he expressed to Leo Larguier, <quote rend="inline">Art is a religion.
                            Its goal is the elevation of thought</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="17"/>. He wanted to create in paintings a
                            <quote rend="inline">harmony parallel to nature,</quote> a noumenon, in
                        that the painting would be a thing in itself (with a life of its own) whose
                        purpose was to <quote rend="inline">enlighten</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="39"/>. Cézanne stated his commitment to the
                            <quote rend="inline">law of harmony,</quote> numerical patterns he saw
                        in nature, throughout his letters and conversations. He stated: <quote
                            rend="inline">To read nature is to see it beneath the veil of
                            interpretation as colored patches succeeding one another according to a
                            law of harmony. The major hues are thus analyzed through
                            modulations</quote>” <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="38"/>.</p>

                    <p>By harmony, Cézanne means harmonia in a Platonic sense of <quote
                            rend="inline">fitting together:</quote> not only the ideal forms and
                        proportional arrangements of forms based on number found in nature, but also
                        as <quote rend="inline">the reconciliation of opposites by a third element,
                            bringing them all into a new unity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#schneider1994" loc="236"/>. Cézanne synthesized contrasts: he
                            <quote rend="inline">modulated</quote> color as a way of building form.
                        He saw the task of reconciling opposites as a magician’s task. He stated:
                            <quote rend="inline">Painting is not beautiful if the surface plane
                            remains flat. Objects must turn, grow distant, live. That is the magic
                            of our art</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="66"/>. To restate, in the golden section,
                        Cézanne finds a way to represent infinity in his paintings, which for him,
                        like the Symbolists, was the essence of nature. In the synthesis of
                        opposites, whether in color contrasts, spatial <quote rend="inline">near and
                            far,</quote> or <quote rend="inline">up and down,</quote> Cézanne
                        creates a <quote rend="inline">harmonious</quote> painting.</p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Cézanne and Ingres</head>
                    <p>Certainly, <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> is not the sole
                        model for <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                            cheveux</title>. Relevant to our purposes here, a study of Cézanne’s
                        Bathers, as a series, from their origin and into their development,
                        Cézanne’s ambivalence toward French Neo-Classicism, and its
                        arch-representative Dominique Ingres is well-documented. Cézanne would have
                        seen <title rend="italic">La Source</title> at the Louvre (<ref
                            target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>).<note>The Louvre did not acquisition
                            Ingres’ <title rend="italic">La Source</title> until 1878, nine years
                            after <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                                cheveux</title> was painted. Nevertheless, the painting was
                            exhibited in the official Paris Salon in 1856 and was famous when
                            Cézanne was a young student in 1861.</note>
                        <title rend="italic">La Source</title>, begun by Ingres in 1820, and
                        completed in 1856, when Ingres was 76-years-old, was infamous to
                        impressionist painters as its graceful lines and classicism represented the
                        highest standard in Fine Art at the time. Cézanne did not care for the
                        painting. He called it <quote rend="inline">system and false spirit</quote>
                        <ptr target="#doran2001" loc="132"/>. Applying axial lines and golden
                        windows to <title rend="italic">La Source</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, we can now see
                        Cézanne copying and departing from his model in surprising ways.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure06">
                        <head>Figure 6. L. Dominque Ingres, <title rend="italic">La Source</title>,
                            1820-1856, 5’4 x 2’7 in. R. Paul Cézanne, <title rend="italic">Baigneuse
                                debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, 1869-71, 11 3/8 x 5 1/8
                            in.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>As Michael Baxandall observes, <quote rend="inline">influence</quote> works
                        in reverse <ptr target="#baxandall1985" loc="59"/>. Ingres’ <title
                            rend="italic">La Source</title> did not <soCalled>influence</soCalled>
                        Cézanne. Instead, Cézanne drew a pattern from Veronese and subjected another
                        model, Ingres’ <title rend="italic">La Source</title> to the pattern, then
                        dilated upon the results to suit his aims, the <quote rend="inline"
                            >harmonizing</quote> of the youthful nude body. First, we notice that
                        model and copy are mirror images. With arms raised, they form S shaped
                        figures in classical contrapposto. They are symmetrical only in that, when a
                        golden rectangle is formed over the rectangular plane of the canvasses, both
                        figures’ left breasts are framed by the middle vertical line and the golden
                        ratio vertical lines formed by the golden rectangle. The middle vertical
                        axis also runs through both figures’ left eyes. The golden window in Ingres’
                        work frames the girl’s left thigh. In Cézanne, the golden window alludes to
                        the girl’s thigh and hip by partially representing (yet with more convexity)
                        her right hip through tonal modulation. Pointedly, Cézanne uses the
                        subordinate horizontal line of the picture plane’s golden rectangle to
                            <quote rend="inline">lower</quote> his figure. In <title rend="italic"
                            >La Source</title> the axial eye (picture center) is the sex of the
                        young girl emptying the urn of water. The golden section runs across her
                        legs above her knees. Clearly, in <title rend="italic">La Source</title>,
                        the picture center, as the <soCalled>eye</soCalled> of
                            <soCalled>god,</soCalled> is Ingres’ visual pun on the source, water,
                        and female genitalia. In Cézanne’s work, the exact center is the nude
                        female’s hip swiveled in classical contrapposto, perhaps indicating that his
                            <soCalled>source</soCalled> is <soCalled>classical art,</soCalled> while
                        her sex is aligned with the golden section, making it
                            <soCalled>golden.</soCalled> In <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout,
                            s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, by aligning the female sex with the
                        golden section, within a theme that involves washing the body, and in the
                        case of <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                            cheveux</title>, a woman drying her hair, Cézanne is <q>harmonizing</q>
                        the <q>studio</q> erotism of Ingres’ young nude — he is bringing
                            <soCalled>the source</soCalled> back to nature.<note>On Cézanne’s famous
                            statement that he wished to bring <quote rend="inline">Poussin back to
                                nature</quote> see Richard Shiff, <title rend="quotes"
                                >Introduction,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Conversations with Cézanne</title>, xxi. His
                            footnote, p. 217 provides valuable bibliography on this topic.</note> He
                        also <soCalled>classicizes</soCalled> the nude human form by posing his
                        bathers in natural settings, and by associating them with the idealized
                        friendships and homo-social eroticism of the Classical world. In his
                        earliest male bathers as well, Cézanne aligns sex with the golden section of
                        the left side of the frame (<ref target="#figure07">Figure</ref> 7).</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure07">
                        <head>Figure 7: Early Male Bathers: Axiality and Golden Rectangles L. Paul
                            Cézanne, <title rend="italic">Baigneur aux bras écartés</title>, 1876, 9
                            1⁄2 x 5 1⁄2 in. M. Paul Cézanne, <title rend="italic">Baigneur aux bras
                                écartés</title>, 1876, 9 1⁄2 x 6 3/8 in. R. Paul Cézanne, <title
                                rend="italic">Baigneur aux bras écartés</title>, 1877-1878, 28 3⁄4 x
                            23 5/8 in. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>In Figure 7, as in female nudes, Cézanne encloses the left breast of an early
                        male bather (7.L.) in the golden rectangle and the vertical bisecting line
                        of the painting. In the middle painting (7.M.) he centers or aligns the left
                        male breast between the golden rectangle and the vertical bisecting line of
                        the painting. In the right painting (7.R), the bather’s left breast aligns
                        with the vertical bisecting line, while the bather’s left elbow aligns with
                        the golden rectangle. In all three works, the golden window captures thigh
                        and background. The navel aligns with the horizontal bisecting line and sex
                        aligns with phi (the bottom side of the golden rectangle determined by the
                        dimensions of the painting).</p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Golden Windows: Coming into Focus</head>
                    <p>Eighty Bather paintings exist in various states of completion out of
                        Cézanne’s extant oeuvre of 1300 oil paintings and watercolors <ptr
                            target="#feilchenfeldt"/>. Of the 80 Bathers, 64 are available online
                        for download for research and educational purposes. Using DDA, we identified
                        the axis determined by the picture plane of each digital image, and
                        identified the golden window. In <ref target="#supplementaltable2"
                            >Supplemental Table 2</ref>, we provide a snapshot image of all 64
                        golden windows we collected. Here we present twenty of these images that
                        suggest the <quote rend="inline">lowering or descending effect</quote>
                        afforded by the golden window. All feature a head, breast or rear end. Most
                        of the 64 paintings have a head, breast, thigh, or rear end framed by the
                        golden window, but some frame the brightest point in the painting, or a
                        faint structure in the far distance.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure08">
                        <head>Figure 8: Other <soCalled>Noumenal</soCalled> bodies. The golden
                            window frames the head, heart, thighs, hips and rear end of the
                            descending or descended body. Row 1: L-R: <title rend="italic">Trois
                                Baigneuses</title>, 1876-1877, 9 1⁄2 x 12 1⁄2 in.,<title
                                rend="italic">Trois Baigneuses</title>, 1876-1877, 20 1⁄2 x 21 1⁄2
                            in, <title rend="italic">Trois Baigneuses</title>, 1875, 12 x 13 in.,
                                <title rend="italic">Cinq Baigneurs</title>, 1879-1880, 13 5/8 x 15
                            in., <title rend="italic">Cinq Baigneurs</title>, 1880-1882, 23 5/8 x 28
                            3⁄4 in., <title rend="italic">Baigneurs et Baigneuses</title>, 1880, 7
                            1⁄2 x 8 1⁄4 in. Row 2: L-R: <title rend="italic">Baigneuses devant une
                                tente</title>, 1883-1885, 24 3⁄4 x 33 1/8 in., <title rend="italic"
                                >Baigneurs</title>, 1890, 23 5/8 x 31 7/8 in., <title rend="italic"
                                >Baigneurs</title>, 1890, 15 3/8 x 20 7/8 in., <title rend="italic"
                                >Baigneurs in Plein Air</title>, 1890-1891, 21 1⁄4 x 25 5/8 in.,
                                <title rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>, 1892, 8 5/8 x 13 in., <title
                                rend="italic">Baigneurs et Baigneuses</title>, 1890, 8 7/8 x 13
                            15/16 in., <title rend="italic">Groupe de Baigneuses</title>, 1895, 18
                            1⁄2 x 30 1⁄4 in. Row 3: L-R: <title rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>,
                            1890-1895, 7 1⁄2 x 10 1⁄4 in., <title rend="italic">Le Bain</title>,
                            1892-1894, 10 1⁄4 x 15 3⁄4 in., <title rend="italic">Les Grandes
                                Baigneuses</title>, 1894- 1905, 53 1⁄2 x 75 1⁄4 in., <title
                                rend="italic">Les Grandes Baigneuses</title>, 1896-1906, 52 3/8 x 81
                            1⁄2 in., <title rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>, 1898-1900, 10 5/8 x 18
                            1⁄4 in., <title rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>, 1900, 11 7/8 x 17 3/8
                            in. , <title rend="italic">Baigneurs</title>, 1902-1904, 9 x 10 1⁄2
                            in.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>The Golden Strips</head>
                    <p>Adjacent to the <q>golden window</q> (<ref target="#appendix4">Appendix
                            IV</ref>) are the <soCalled>golden strips</soCalled> which elaborate on
                        the point emphasized by the window. The <soCalled>golden strip</soCalled> in
                        a bather painting is between the axial and golden ratio horizontal lines or
                        vertical lines of the picture plane (<ref target="#appendix4">Appendix
                            IV</ref>). The golden strips allow for an alternation of frontal and
                        rear nude forms with their sexes aligned with the golden section. As with
                        Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, Cézanne aligns
                        the heads of the <q>descended</q> figures beneath the middle horizontal line
                        bisecting the picture. For Andre Lohte, Cézanne’s genius is in his
                        alternation of foreground and background figures. (What we call Cézanne’s
                            <quote rend="inline">game,</quote> he calls Cézanne’s <quote
                            rend="inline">ruse</quote>). Lohte stated of Cézanne: <quote
                            rend="inline">Genius consists in knowing how to compensate, through
                            constant repetition of each phenomenon, for every thrust into depth, by
                            an equal advance or return. Without this ruse the eye would immediately
                            find the horizon, the distance, without being excited by the successive
                            oppositions which retard its quest for space, and procure for it a
                            subtle pleasure</quote>
                        <ptr target="#loran1943" loc="32"/>. We can now consider Veronese’s <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> a masterful example of this
                        phenomenon in fine art painting, a strategy in painting with an endless
                            <quote rend="inline">trajectory.</quote><note>Bruno Latour and Adam Lowe
                            have discussed of the painting’s history as a material object and as a
                            facsimile.</note> In Figure 9, we present the horizontal golden strip of
                            <title rend="italic">Quatre Baigneuses</title> (1888-1890) which shows
                        Cézanne’s <quote rend="inline">alternation of foreground and
                            background</quote> described by Andre Lohte. In Figure 9, and in other
                        Bathers, Cézanne’s <quote rend="inline">successive oppositions</quote> have
                        semantic meaning. For us, this signals Cézanne’s reconciliation of opposites
                        in his windows and strips. Thematically, Cézanne reconciles body and mind
                        into a third <quote rend="inline">noumenal</quote> alliance. He aligns the
                        attentive and communicative heads, hearts, and sexes of his descended and/or
                        risen figures, along the golden section and the axial center of his Bather
                        paintings. In <ref target="#supplementaltable3">Supplemental Table 3</ref>,
                        we present the horizontal <soCalled>golden strips</soCalled> of the 64
                        bathers in this study.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure09">
                        <head>Figure 9: Golden Window, Golden Strip, and Complete Image. <title
                                rend="italic">Quatre Baigneuses</title>, 1888-1890, 28 3/8 x 36 1⁄4
                            in. In <title rend="italic">Quatre Baigneuses</title> Cézanne alternates
                            frontal and rear nudity. He aligns the heads of <quote rend="inline"
                                >descended</quote> bathers with the sex of <quote rend="inline"
                                >risen</quote> bathers along the axial center and horizontal golden
                            section of the picture plane.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Beyond the Church</head>
                    <p>Cézanne presents an affirmative and benedictory vision of youth and beauty in
                        his Bathers. In <title rend="italic">Les Grandes Baigneuses</title>, a 1906
                        painting left incomplete when he died, the church in the distance shows that
                        his bathers exist in an intermediate space between the viewer outside the
                        picture plane and the church (<ref target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>). The
                        bathers are in a space of their own, determined by the geometry that unites
                        them. When we apply the geometric analysis of DDA to the painting, we see
                        that the golden window frames a reality beyond the church. We feel this
                        illustrates Cézanne’s Neoplatonic leanings, and fuels his concept of art as
                        a religion. In his serial use of golden sections to structure his bather
                        series, we see an interest in the infinite, and an understanding of the
                        golden window as affording a glimpse of it.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure10">
                        <head>Figure 10. Imagining the infinite. In <title rend="italic">Les Grandes
                                Baigneuses</title> (1906), we see in the golden strip, frontal and
                            rear nudity, descended heads (frontal, side and rear views), brightest
                            points, and far distance.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Homage to the Classical World</head>
                    <p>Cézanne also uses sacred geometry to structure the imagined space of the
                        image. In <title rend="italic">Baigneurs en Plein Air</title> (<ref
                            target="#figure11">Figure 11</ref>), an unfinished painting from
                        1890-1891, the ground of the five figures forms a Pentagon, below the
                        horizontal line that bisects the painting.</p>

                    <figure xml:id="figure11">
                        <head>Figure 11: <title rend="italic">Baigneurs en Plein Air</title>,
                            1890-1891. Five figures form a pentagon in the imagined space of the
                            painting.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>As stated in Appendix IV, DDA will discriminate a variety of geometric shapes
                        within a picture. The figure emerging in the golden window represents it
                        triangular point. This implied pentagonal shape illustrates Cézanne’s advice
                        to artists throughout his letters and conversations: <quote rend="inline"
                            >Interpret nature in terms of the cylinder, the sphere, the cone; put
                            everything in perspective, so that each side of an object, a plane,
                            recedes toward a central point</quote>” <ptr target="#doran2001"
                            loc="29"/>. In addition to an implied pentagon, these bathers form an
                        imaginary cone, a large triangle parallel to the surface plane whose tip
                        coincides with the middle vertical axis of the paintings. This triangle
                        provides vertical armature for the five bodies, linking them together in one
                        unit with the armpits aligned at the diagonal lines. This compositional
                        triangle both dynamically lifts the figures, and stabilizes the
                        composition.</p>

                    <p>Cézanne suggests with a few blue and red strokes the figure whose breast is
                        framed in the golden window of Figure 11. Cézanne repeated this particular
                        composition in his search for a realization commensurate with his ideal. We
                        can now think of a man lowering himself into a body of water as a
                        compositional <soCalled>problem</soCalled> Cézanne was trying to solve in
                        his Bather series. Painted in four-sided constructive strokes, and in
                        Veronesian, <soCalled>noumenal</soCalled> blue and red color patches that
                        resemble a harlequin’s costume, the figure is in motion, and not fully
                        formed. He is an intermediate being, not yet concretized, nor fully
                        translated between here and there within the noumenal square of the
                        painting. Cézanne is clearly attuned to magical conceptions of the number
                        four as representing the fourth element of earth in Platonic doctrine and
                        inherent in the squares of the harlequin’s costume. He was also aware of the
                        five-sided figure of the pentagon as representing the regenerative aspects
                        of creation. The Harlequin’s checkerboard costume has been described as
                        symbolizing <quote rend="inline">a chthonic force</quote>
                        <ptr target="#schneider1994"/>. If so, this chthonic force’s heart is framed
                        in the golden window, a highly significant spot, charged with meaning, as we
                        now see in Cézanne’s Bathers, and particularly in this painting (Figure 11)
                        depicting five men in geometrical relationship to each other. In addition to
                        a sacred understanding of numbers and shapes, three (triangle: divinity),
                        four (square: earth) and five (pentagon: creation and regeneration), a means
                        to create a harmony <quote rend="inline">parallel</quote> to nature, this
                        painting’s composition is Cézanne’s special homage to the pastoral poetry of
                        Theocritus and Virgil, the classical literature he loved. It is well- known
                        that Cézanne translated Theocritus and Virgil as a pastime in his youth <ptr
                            target="#doran2001" loc="181"/>. The left side of Figure 11 appears to
                        represent the sympotic aspects of male fraternity with the seated figure
                        under the pine tree discoursing with the standing figure seen from behind.
                        The right side of the painting pays homage to the erotic aspects of
                        homo-sociality implied by Theocritus and developed in the bucolic poems of
                        Virgil. In the poems, herdsmen gather to sing songs about
                            <soCalled>Daphnis,</soCalled> a young man who drowns himself out of
                        erotic frustration, or his cognates in the classical tradition who die:
                        Hylas, Delphis, Adonis, and Narcissus, other beautiful boys, like the one in
                        Figure 11 <soCalled>posing</soCalled> in the foreground. Theocritus and
                        Virgil’s lost boys are the poets’ reflections on their own lost youth and/or
                        the loss of specific male friends, or lovers <ptr target="#weinstein"/>. For
                        Cézanne, <quote rend="inline">Nature is not on the surface; it is in
                            depth,</quote> hence, the man in the water (in the depths) crying on the
                        far right <ptr target="#doran2001"/>. Cézanne’s effort to divinize the nude
                        human body in company with other divinized bodies, whether
                            <soCalled>co-ed</soCalled> or segregated by sex, and in the many
                        paintings where difference in sex is not explicit, we see the artist’s
                        engagement with Neoplatonism, in that his goal is to create a harmoniously
                        simplified world with a playful, affirmative, benedictory vision of youthful
                        nudity.</p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>In this paper, using the automated tools afforded by DDA, we have forged a
                        connection in color, composition, geometry, and theme between <title
                            rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, and from this
                        connection, we have brought to light unifying characteristics in Cézanne’s
                        Bathers heretofore unidentified. We have identified the connection between
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout s’essuyant le cheveux</title> by producing dendrograms
                        of Cézanne’s fifty- five 1895 Galerie Vollard Exhibition oil paintings
                        compared to Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, a
                        painting we know Cézanne admired at the Louvre during his formative years as
                        a painter and throughout his life. Using computer-assisted methods we
                        generated dendrograms that clustered paintings related in color, saturation,
                        brightness and complexity. After studying these parameters, we applied the
                        geometric program of DDA to the study of Cézanne’s composition. Because
                        Cézanne expressed Neoplatonic ideals regarding paintings in his
                        conversations and letters, we programmed DDA to compute axial lines and
                        golden rectangles according to the dimensions of the square, rectangle, and
                        other geometric parameters to the painting under scrutiny. Using DDA we
                        identified the golden rectangle for <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                            Cana</title>, <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les
                            cheveux</title> and Ingres’ <title rend="italic">La Source</title>
                        (another likely model for <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant
                            les cheveux</title>). From the similarities and differences between the
                        three paintings identified, based on axial symmetry and the golden section,
                        we have formulated an approach to <soCalled>seeing</soCalled> Cézanne’s
                        composition in his Bather series. Cézanne’s noumenal bodies, formerly
                        perceived as <soCalled>awkward</soCalled> and composed with <quote
                            rend="inline">baffling imbalance,</quote> can now be viewed as <quote
                            rend="inline">golden</quote>
                        <ptr target="#danchev2013"/>. These are only the first parameters,
                        customized to the study of paintings that we have introduced to DDA. As we
                        continue to expand and use this computer program to compare influence
                        between painters, we will add new parameters such as measurements for
                        convexity, concavity, texture and composition, based on edge detection
                        technology in the original DIAS program. These tools will assist us in
                        investigating a variety of questions basic to art history.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                    <p>This research began with an AAC&amp;U TIDES (Teaching to Increase Diversity
                        and Equity in the Classroom) grant that supported applying technology to the
                        study of paintings from 2013-2017 at Lawrence Technological University. A
                        Howard Hughes Medical Institute’s Inclusive Excellence Initiative grant
                        (52008705) is sustaining LTU’s integration of computer-assisted analysis of
                        art, music, and literature into its undergraduate curricula until 2021. The
                        Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, an NIH National Resource, and the W.M.
                        Keck Dynamic Image Analysis Facility housed at the University of Iowa
                        provided the computational resources for this project. We thank LTU’s
                        Research Support Services for providing a Faculty Seed Grant for travel,
                        research assistants Liam Butler, Mary Cody, Irene Missler, and Neil
                        Fraylick. We thank Dean Hsiao-Ping Moore and Prof. Lior Shamir for guidance
                        and support, and LTU Provost Maria Vaz for approving a sabbatical leave
                        Spring 2018, to conduct this work at the W.M. Keck Dynamic Image Analysis
                        Facility at the University of Iowa.</p>
                </div>

            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix1">
                <head>Appendix I. Analyzing a collection of paintings using the customized
                    DIAS/DENDRON-ART (DDA) program</head>
                <p> The newly developed DIAS/DENDRON-ART (DDA) program integrates the 2D image
                    analysis program DIAS (Soll et al., US patent #5655028; Soll, D.R. 1995. The use
                    of computers in understanding how cell crawl. <title rend="italic">Int. Rev.
                        Cytol.</title> 163: 43-104; Soll, D.R. and Wessels, D. (eds.) 1998. Motion
                    Analysis of Living Cells John Wiley, Ive., New York, 298 pages; Kuhl, S., Voss,
                    E., Scherer, A., Lusche, D.F., Wessels, D., Soll, D.R. 2016. 4D tumorigenesis
                    model for quantitation of coalescence, identification of unique cell behaviors
                    and testing anti-cancer drugs. <title rend="italic">Chemotaxis Methods in Molec.
                        Biol.</title> 229-250), and the dendrography software program DENDRON.
                    Schmid, Jan, Edward Voss and David R. Soll. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Computer-Assisted Methods for Assessing Strain Relatedness in Candida
                        albicans by Fingerprinting with the Moderately Repetitive Sequence
                        Ca3.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Clinical Microbiology.</title> Vol 28.6 (June
                    1990). 1236-1243. Soll, D. R. <title rend="quotes">The ins and outs of DNA
                        fingerprinting the infectious Fungi.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Clinical Microbiology Reviews</title>. Vol.13.2 April 2000.
                    P.332-370. The programs originally written in C++ have been converted to JAVA
                    (Graphics Programming With Java, Second Edition. 2001. Steven’s Scott/Jones,
                    Inc.). Images of paintings are scanned into a DDA folder, with borders equal to
                    the inner edges of the frame and normalized for size. If a painting is faded,
                    hue will not be significantly affected since DDA employs HSB (hue, saturation,
                    brightness) color space (Oracle Java 7 documentation, online for <title
                        rend="quotes">Class Color</title>), as opposed to RGB (red, green, blue).
                    DDA then automatically computes nine parameters that include brightness,
                    saturation, complexity, redness, orangeness, yellowness, greenness, blueness and
                    purpleness. Additional parameters based on DIAS edge detection programs are now
                    under development and will be incrementally added. The
                        <soCalled>brightness</soCalled> parameter is computed by converting the
                    pixels of the entire image to HSB. A value of 0% is black and 100% is white. The
                    average % for the entire picture is computed and the value converted to a range
                    of 0.00 to 1.00. The <soCalled>saturation</soCalled> parameter is treated in a
                    similar fashion. It represents the average richness of all colors assessed, is
                    computed from 0 to 100%, then normalized to a value in the range of 0.00 to
                    1.00. For the <soCalled>complexity</soCalled> parameter, the image is first
                    converted to grays with pixel intensities ranging from 0 to 255. The average
                    value is then normalized to 0.00 to 1.00. The final parameters are six hues. On
                    the color or <soCalled>hue</soCalled> wheel, they vary from 0 to 360°. The
                    number of pixels with redness at 0° ± 5°, orange at 20 ± 5°, yellowness at 60 ±
                    5°, greenness at 120 ± 5°, blueness at 240 ± 5° and purpleness at 270 ± 5°, are
                    computed and divided by the total number of pixels in the image. These
                    individual pixel proportions are then converted to 0.00 to 1.00. The values of
                    each parameter, all converted to a range of 0.00 to 1.00, were then used to
                    generate a similarity coefficient (S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>) between every
                    pair of paintings in a collection, using the following formula: <figure>
                        <figDesc>The equation for the similarity coefficient.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
                    </figure> where a<hi rend="subscript">i</hi> and b<hi rend="subscript">i</hi>
                    are the values of a parameter I for paintings A and B respectively, and k is the
                    number of parameters. This formula was derived from that developed by Schmid,
                    J., Voss, E. and Soll, D.R. 1990. (J. Clin Microbiol. 28, 1236-1243) for banding
                    patterns of DNA fingerprints in which each band is a restrictive fragment length
                    polymorphism (RFLP) pattern representing a parameter (Soll et. al. 1997 US
                    Patent #5, 655, 028). An S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> of 0.00 represents
                    complete dissimilarity, an S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> of 1.00 identicalness,
                    and S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>s of 0.01 to 0.99, increasing levels of
                    similarity. For this study the average of the parameters of paintings are used
                    to generate the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>s between all paintings in a
                    collection, which are logged into a matrix, as presented for 18 pictures in
                    Appendix I Table 1.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>APPX. 1. Table 1. S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> matrix for 18 pictures in
                        collection</head>
                    <figDesc>A matrix showing the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> between all eighteen
                        paintings in the collection.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The matrix is then used to generate a dendrogram using the unweighted pair group
                    method based on arithmetic averages (UPGMA), first employed by Rohlf ,1963
                    Classification of <title rend="italic">Aedes</title> by numerical taxonomic
                    methods [Diptera, Culcidae]. (Ann. Entomal. Soc. Am. 56, 798-804) and discussed
                    in more detail for application by Snesth and Sokel (1973. Numerical Taxonomy
                    W.H. Freeman and Co., San Francisco, CA). In generating a dendrogram,
                    connections are identified in descending values. The matrix is first scanned for
                    the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi> with the highest value. The first two are
                    joined by a vertical node at that S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>. If two or more
                    pairs have the same highest S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>, one is picked
                    randomly to initiate the process of generating a tree. The system then grows the
                    tree of relatedness, connecting pairs, individual paintings and groups of two or
                    more, or groups. The node involving more than two paintings is computed as the
                    arithmetic mean of the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>s between the pictures
                    connected. This process continues until all pictures are connected to form a
                    relatedness tree (dendrogram). The accuracy of the dendrogram has been assessed
                    by goodness of fit (i.e., whether the distance in the dendrogram approximates
                    the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>s in the matrix (Avis, J.C. 1994. Molecular
                    numbers, natural history and evolution. Chapraon and Hull, New York, NY). By
                    using completely different methods to assess genetic relatedness between the
                    same collection of strains of an infectious fungus, the accuracy of the DENDRON
                    program was previously verified (Pujol, C., joly, S., Lockhart, S.R., Sebastian,
                    N., Tibayrenc, M., and Soll, D.R. 1977. J. Clin Microbiol, 2348-2358; Soll D.R.
                    2000. Clin Microbiol Rev 13, 332-370). The robustness of DIAS/DENDRON ART (DDA)
                    in clustering was also verified by the addition of the restored <title
                        rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> to the Cézanne collection and the
                    unrestored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, as described in
                    Appendix II.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2">
                <p>A comparison of the Cézanne Galerie Vollard collection with the unrestored
                    (Appendix II A) and restored (Appendix II B) versions of Veronese’s <title
                        rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, using all parameters but green.
                    Greenness was removed because in the restored version, a man’s cloak, which was
                    red, was converted by restoration to green. Both Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and Veronese’s <title
                        rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> reside in the same cluster with the
                    restored and unrestored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>. It
                    should be noted that the alternative clusters in the three dendrograms share a
                    majority of other related Cézanne pictures, as is evident in lists of the
                    paintings in the alternative clusters, presented in Appendix II D. These results
                    also demonstrate the accuracy of the clustering method of DIAS/Dendron, given
                    that the addition of different versions, in this case the unrestored and
                    restored <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title>, or the addition of
                    both, does not disrupt relationships, even though each dendrogram is generated
                    independently, using the unweighted pair-group method employing arithmetic
                    averages, as described in Appendix I.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2a">
                <figure>
                    <head>Appendix II. A</head>
                    <figDesc>The Cézanne Galerie Vollard collection with the unrestored versions of
                        Veronese's <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title></figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2b">
                <figure>
                    <head>Appendix II. B</head>
                    <figDesc>The Cézanne Galerie Vollard collection with the restored versions of
                        Veronese's <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title></figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2c">
                <head>Appendix II. C</head>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc>Lists of the paintings in the alternative clusters</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2d">
                <head>Appendix II. D</head>
                <p>Comparison of pictures in the resident clusters of Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> and either the unrestored
                    or restored versions of Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les Noces de
                        Cana</title>. Only the first word of the titles of the paintings are
                    included.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Appendix II. D</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Unrestored (Louvre) <title rend="italic">Cana</title></cell>
                        <cell>Restored (Venice) <title rend="italic">Cana</title></cell>
                        <cell>Unrestored and Restored <title rend="italic">Cana</title></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Baigneuse</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuse</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuse</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Les Bégonias</cell>
                        <cell>Les Bégonias</cell>
                        <cell>Les Bégonias</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>La Baignade</cell>
                        <cell>La Baignade</cell>
                        <cell>La Baignade</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Pommes</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Nature Morte</cell>
                        <cell>Nature Morte</cell>
                        <cell>Nature Morte</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Esquisse de M. Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse de M. Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse de M. Cézanne</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>La Jas de Bouffan</cell>
                        <cell>La Jas de Bouffan</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix3">
                <head>Appendix III. Further demonstration of clustering Veronese’s <title
                        rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s <title rend="italic"
                        >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title></head>
                <p>To further demonstrate the similarity of Veronese’s <title rend="italic">Les
                        Noces de Cana</title> and Cézanne’s <title rend="italic">Baigneuse debout,
                        s’essuyant les cheveux</title>, we generated a dendrogram based on the S<hi
                        rend="subscript">AB</hi>s between these two paintings and nineteen paintings
                    Cézanne would have viewed in the Louvre between 1861 and 1906. The artists
                    include Delacroix (green), Rubens (black), and Tintoretto (blue). <title
                        rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic">Baigneuse
                        debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title> again clustered, supporting the
                    relationship and accuracy of the dendrography program.</p>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc>A dendrogram featuring the S<hi rend="subscript">AB</hi>s between
                            <title rend="italic">Les Noces de Cana</title> and <title rend="italic"
                            >Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux</title>. The artist Delacroix
                        is shown in green; Rubens is shown in black; and Tintoretto is shown in
                        blue.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix4">
                <head>Appendix IV. How to identify a golden window</head>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc>A detailed graphic showing the steps to identify a golden window. Image
                        1 says <quote rend="inline">The cursor is manually moved in a diagonal from
                            the upper left to lower right corner of the painting.</quote> Image 2
                        says <quote rend="inline">DDA automatically computes phi along the upper and
                            left hand borders, and draws the golden rectangle.</quote> Image 3 says
                            <quote rend="inline">DDA then bisects the picture in four equal
                            quadrants by drawing a vertical line and a horizontal line, and defines
                            the exact center of the painting.</quote> Image 4 says <quote
                            rend="inline">Steps one through three are performed regardles of the
                            dimensions of the picture.</quote> Image 5 says <quote rend="inline">DDA
                            then identifies and color codes the golden window, and the horizontal
                            golden strip and the vertical golden strips.</quote> Image 6 says <quote
                            rend="inline">DDA then isolates the golden window for independent
                            analysis of parameters and comparison through dendrography.</quote>
                        Image 7 concludes by saying <quote rend="inline">DDA can expand independent
                            golden windows or archive for rapid comparison.</quote></figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure%2018.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="supplementaltable1">
                <head>Supplementary Table I: List of Works</head>
                <table>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Name of Artist</cell>
                        <cell>Title of Work</cell>
                        <cell>Medium</cell>
                        <cell>Size</cell>
                        <cell>Year</cell>
                        <cell>Location</cell>
                        <cell>Link to artwork used for analysis</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Maison abandonnée</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>19 5/16 x 23 in</cell>
                        <cell>1878-79</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads7.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Baie de Marseille, avec vue sur le village</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>26 3/16 x 32 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-79</cell>
                        <cell>Vollard Archives, Photo No. 604</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.moma.org/collection/works/80302?locale=en</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>L'Estaque</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>31 1/2 x 39 1/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-83</cell>
                        <cell>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.moma.org/meetme/artwork/index</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Campagne à Pontoise, près du Valhermeil</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>36 3/8 x 28 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1881-82</cell>
                        <cell>Fondation Sirina, Vaduz</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/main</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Marronniers et ferme du Jas de Bouffan</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>25 13/16 x 32 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads1.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Gardanne (vue verticale)</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>31 1/2 x 25 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1886</cell>
                        <cell>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://images.metmuseum.org/CRDImages/ep/original/DT1941.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Gardanne (vue horizontale)</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>25 X 39 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia (BF917)</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Grand Pin</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>33 1/16 x 36 3/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1887-89</cell>
                        <cell>Museu de Arte de São Paulo Assis</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads2.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/the-great-pine-1889.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Maison au bord de la Marne (l'Île Machefer)</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 11/16 x 35 13/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888-94</cell>
                        <cell>White House Collection, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Chemin de halage sur les bords de la</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>24 13/16 x 31 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888</cell>
                        <cell>Art Gallery of New South Wales, Sydney</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.artgallery.nsw.gov.au/media/collection</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Jas de Bouffan</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>29 3/8 x 21 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890-94</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, Japan</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads2.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/jas-de-bouffan-1887.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Au bord de l'eau</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 11/16 x 36 3/16 in</cell>
                        <cell>1890-92</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>https://images.nga.gov/en/search/do_quick_search.html?q=%221972.9.1%22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Pont sur la Marne à Créteil</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 x 35 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1894</cell>
                        <cell>Pushkin Museum, Moscow</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/bridge-over-the-marne-</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Sous-bois</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>45 11/16 x 31 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1893-94</cell>
                        <cell>Los Angeles County Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>https://collections.lacma.org/node/172409</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Nègre Scipion</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>42 1/8 x 32 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1867</cell>
                        <cell>Museu de Arte de São Paulo Assis</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads4.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/the-negro-scipio-1867.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Portrait de Victor Chocquet (buste)</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 13/16 x 10 11/16 in</cell>
                        <cell>1877</cell>
                        <cell>Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Richmond</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads6.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Portrait de l'artiste</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 3/16 x 5 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877</cell>
                        <cell>Musée d'Orsay, Paris</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads7.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/self-portrait-3.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Portrait de Louis Guillaume</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>22 x 18 1/5 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-80</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>https://images.nga.gov/en/search/do_quick_search.html?q=%221963.10.101</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Portrait de l'artiste</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>18 1/8 x 15 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1882</cell>
                        <cell>Pushkin Museum, Moscow</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.arts-museum.ru/data/fonds/europe_and_america</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Madame Cézanne en robe rayée</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>22 3/16 x 18 1/5 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1883-85</cell>
                        <cell>Yokohama Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads5.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse d'un portrait de madame Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 x 5 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1883</cell>
                        <cell>Richard Gray, Chicago</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads5.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse d'un portrait du fils de l'artiste</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 11/16 x 4 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1883-85</cell>
                        <cell>Von der Heydt Museum, Wuppertal</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/main_lg/R534.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Madame Cézanne au chapeau vert</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>38 1/2 x 31 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1891-92</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia (BF141)</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads8.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Garçon au gilet rouge</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>31 7/8 x 25 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888-90</cell>
                        <cell>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.moma.org/collection/works/79086?locale=en</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Garçon au gilet rouge</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>31 5/16 x 25 3/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888-90</cell>
                        <cell>Foundation E.G. Bührle Collection, Zürich</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads5.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/boy-in-a-red-vest-1889.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Garçon au gilet rouge</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>36 3/16 x 28 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888-90</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>https://images.nga.gov/en/search/do_quick_search.html?q=%221995.47.5%2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Madame Cézanne dans la serre</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>36 3/16 x 28 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1891-92</cell>
                        <cell>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://images.metmuseum.org/CRDImages/ep/original/DP317780.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cézanne coiffé d'un chapeau mou</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 5/8 x 19 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1894</cell>
                        <cell>Bridgestone Museum of Art, Tokyo</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Jeune fille à la poupée</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>36 3/16 x 28 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1895</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads5.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/young-girl-with-a-doll.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Festin – L'Orgie; Le Banquet de</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>51 3/16 x 31 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1867</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, France</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads4.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/the-feast-the-banquet-of</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Pêcheur à la ligne</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 5/8 x 14 3/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1868-70</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                        <cell>Unable to locate color version</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Déjeuner sur l'herbe</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 5/8 x 31 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/luncheon-on-the-grass-</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Au bord de l'étang</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>17 1/2 x 21 1/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-77</cell>
                        <cell>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.mfa.org/collections/object/download/50439</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Déjeuner sur l'herbe</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 3/8 x 15 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1878-80</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                        <cell>Unable to locate color version</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Lutte d'amour</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>14 7/8 x 18 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>https://images.nga.gov/en/search/do_quick_search.html?q=%221972.9.2%22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Moissonneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 3/16 x 16 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, Switzerland</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/main_lg/454.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Léda au cygne</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 x 28 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia (BF36)</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/leda-and-the-swan.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Vase rococo</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 11/16 x 23 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-77</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.</cell>
                        <cell>https://images.nga.gov/en/search/do_quick_search.htm</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Deux poires</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>6 1/2 x 9 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>Christie's, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.ecosia.org/images?addon=chrome&amp;addonversion=</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>5 x 10 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-78</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. and Mrs. Eugene V. Thaw, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.ecosia.org/images?addon=chrome&amp;addonversion</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 10 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1878</cell>
                        <cell>The Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads3.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/apples-1878.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Pommes et linge</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 13/16 x 17 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-80</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, Japan</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue/entry.php?id=335</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Bol et boîte à lait</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 7/8 x 7 1/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879</cell>
                        <cell>Bridgestone Museum of Art, Tokyo</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads2.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/still-life-bowl-and-milk-</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Verre et pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>12 3/8 x 15 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-80</cell>
                        <cell>Collection Rudolf Staechelin, Basel</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Bégonias </cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>18 1/8 x 21 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-80</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/catalogue_images/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Deux fruits</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 9 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, Japan</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Grenade et poires dans une assiette</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 5/8 x 14 3/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads7.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Nature morte</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 13/16 x 18 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>The State Hermitage Museum, St. Petersburg</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads7.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/still-life-with-apples-1.jpg</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Fruits et cruchon</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 x 16 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1893-94</cell>
                        <cell>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.mfa.org/collections/object/fruit-and-a-jug-on-a-table-33253
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Corbeille de pommes</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>25 5/8 x 31 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1893</cell>
                        <cell>The Art Institute of Chicago</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/ </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Nature morte</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>17 5/16 x 24 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1895</cell>
                        <cell>Sammlung Esther Grether, Basel</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Baigneuse debout, s'essuyant les cheveux</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 3/8 x 5 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1869</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads1.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Baignade</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 10 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-77</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur aux bras écartés</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 x 9 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-78</cell>
                        <cell>Jasper Johns, Sharon, Conn.</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads2.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Baigneurs au repos</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>31 1/8 x 38 3/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-77</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia (BF906)</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads3.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/bathers-at-rest-1877.jpg</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Quatre Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 13/16 x 15 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/paul-cezanne/four-bathers-1878.jpg
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses devant une tente</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>24 13/16 x 33 1/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1883-85</cell>
                        <cell>Staatsgalerie, Stuttgart</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Baigneur au Rocher</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>66 x 44 1/2 in. (part</cell>
                        <cell>1867-1869</cell>
                        <cell>Chrysler Art Museum Norfolk, VA</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 x 15 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Homme Etendu et Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 1/2 x 13 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1868-1870</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur et Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 7/8 x 15 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1870-1871</cell>
                        <cell>Travis Hanson, Fine Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuse au bord de la mer</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 1/4 x 8 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuse assise</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 5/8 x 4 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>Columbus Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>La Baignade</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 10 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur aux bras écartés</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 1/2 x 5 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876</cell>
                        <cell>Rose Art Museum, Brandeis University</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur aux bras écartés</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 x 6 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 3/8 x 9 13/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur aux bras écartés</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 3/8 in. x 6 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-1876</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 x 18 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>The Metropolitan Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneuses sous des arbre</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 5/8 x 28 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Trois Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 8 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1874-1875</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs au repose I</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 x 18 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-1876</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Art et d'Histoire, Geneva</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs au repose II</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 x 18 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-1876</cell>
                        <cell>Location Unknown</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur debout</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 13/16 in. x 6 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876</cell>
                        <cell>Sotheby's New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur assis au bord de l'eau</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 3/8 x 8 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876</cell>
                        <cell>Obersteg Collection, Basel</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Trois Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 3/8 x 12 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Trois Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 13/16 x 13 1/5 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Elliott Wolk, Scarsdale</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Trois Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>20 1/2 x 21 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Trois Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>12 x 13 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collections</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Quatre Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 5/8 x 13 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-1877</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadephia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions/entry.php?id=52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Quatre Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 x 18 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Pola Museum of Art, Kanagawa</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 1/2 x 16 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadephia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>17 7/8 x 21 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Musee Picasso, Paris</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 x 16 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuse</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 5/8 x 5 1/2 in</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Kuboso Memorial Museum of Arts</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur vu de dos</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 3/8 in. x 7 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur aux bras écartés</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 3/4 x 23 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 5/8 x 15 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-1880</cell>
                        <cell>The Detroit Institute of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 5/8 x 28 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880-1882</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>12 5/8 x 8 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-1878</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Bain</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 13/16 in. x 8 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880-1882</cell>
                        <cell>Staatsgalerie, Stuttgart</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur debout vu de dos</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 in. x 8 11/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-1882</cell>
                        <cell>The Art Institute of Chicago</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneur debout vu de dos</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 13/16 in. x 6 13/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-1882</cell>
                        <cell>Henry and Rose Pearlman Foundation</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Quatre Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 13/16 in. x 15 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs et Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 in. x 8 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>Ohara Museum, Kurashiki</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Cinq Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>25 5/8 x 25 5/8 in</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>Kunst Musuem, Basel</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Grand Baigneur</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>50 x 38 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1885</cell>
                        <cell>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Six Baigneuses also known as Les Ondines</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 x 17 3/8 in</cell>
                        <cell>1887</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection, Geneva</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>23 5/8 x 31 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>20 11/16 in. x 25 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890-1892</cell>
                        <cell>Saint Louis Art Museum</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Quatre Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>28 3/8 x 36 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1888-1890</cell>
                        <cell>Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek, Copenhagen</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 in. x 17 5/16 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>Musee D'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 1/4 x 20 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890-1895</cell>
                        <cell>Stiftung Langmatt Sidney and Jenny Brown</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>15 3/8 x20 7/8 in</cell>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs en plein air </cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>21 1/4 x 25 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890-1891</cell>
                        <cell>The State Hermitage Museum, St. Petersburg</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 5/8 x 13 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1892</cell>
                        <cell>Musee de Beaux-Arts, Lyon</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs et Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 7/8 x 13 15/16 in</cell>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>The Art Institute of Chicago</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Groupe de Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>18 1/2 x 30 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1895</cell>
                        <cell>Ordrupgaard Collection, Copenhagen</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 1/2 x 10 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1890-1895</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Groupe de Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 1/2 x 15 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1892-1894</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Le Bain</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 1/4 x 15 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1892-1894</cell>
                        <cell>Pushkin Museum, Moscow</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Groupe de Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 1/2 x 12 1/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1895</cell>
                        <cell>Philadelphia Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Grandes Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>53 1/2 x 75 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1894-1905</cell>
                        <cell>National Gallery, London</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Grandes Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>52 3/8 x 81 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1895-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Les Grandes Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>82 x 98 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1906</cell>
                        <cell>Philadelphia Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 x 14 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900-1904</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>20 1/8 x 24 1/4 in</cell>
                        <cell>1899-1904</cell>
                        <cell>The Art Institute of Chicago</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Groupe de Sept Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>14 5/8 x 17 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>Fondation Beyeler, Riehen, Basel</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 5/8 x 18 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1898-1900</cell>
                        <cell>The Baltimore Museum of Art</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 5/8 x 13 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1899-1900</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>10 5/8 x 8 5/8 in</cell>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>Location Unknown</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>16 5/8 x 21 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900-1904</cell>
                        <cell>Musee d'Orsay, Paris France</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 7/8 x 17 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>Location Uknown</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse deBaigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>7 7/8 x 13 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900-1902</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>11 1/2 x 9 1/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1902-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse de Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>12 5/8 x 15 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1902-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse de Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>25 5/8 x 31 7/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Fondazione Magnani-Rocca, Parma</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>13 3/4 x 8 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Esquisse de Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 x 6 5/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>Becon Collection, Greenwich</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneurs</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>9 x 10 1/2 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1902-1904</cell>
                        <cell>Barnes Foundation, Philadelphia</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Etude de Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>8 3/8 x 12 3/4 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1900-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Museum Rosengart, Lucerne</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paul Cézanne</cell>
                        <cell>Baigneuses</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>29 x 36 3/8 in.</cell>
                        <cell>1902-1906</cell>
                        <cell>Private Collection</cell>
                        <cell>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com/exhibitions</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paolo Veronese</cell>
                        <cell>Les Noces de Cana (before conservation)</cell>
                        <cell>Oil on Canvas</cell>
                        <cell>22 ft.3 in. x 32 ft</cell>
                        <cell>1563</cell>
                        <cell>Louvre (unrestored)</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.wikiart.org/en/paol
                            o-veronese/the-marriage-at-cana-</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>Paolo Veronese</cell>
                        <cell>Les Noces de Cana (digital facsimile)</cell>
                        <cell>Digital Reproduction</cell>
                        <cell>22 ft. 3 in. x 32 ft.</cell>
                        <cell>2006</cell>
                        <cell>Fondazione Giorgio Cini, Venice</cell>
                        <cell>https://www.cineclubdecaen.com/peinture/peintres/veronese/nocesdecana.jpg</cell>
                    </row>

                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="supplementaltable2">
                <head>SUPPLEMENTARY TABLE II: Golden Windows</head>
                <figure>
                    <head>SUPPLEMENTARY TABLE II</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure19.png"/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure20.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="supplementaltable3">
                <head>SUPPLEMENTARY TABLE III: Golden Strips</head>
                <figure>
                    <head>SUPPLEMENTARY TABLE III</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure21.png"/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure22.png"/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure23.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arnheim1974" label="Arnheim 1974">Rudolf Arnheim, <title rend="italic"
                        >Art and Visual Perception: a psychology of the creative eye</title>.
                    (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1974).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ball2001" label="Ball 2001">Ball, Phillip. <title rend="italic">Bright
                        Earth: Art and the Invention of Color</title>. (Chicago: University of
                    Chicago Press, 2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baron2017" label="Baron 2017">Baron, Joshua. <title rend="quotes">MET
                        Museum Makes 350,0000 Images Free.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, February 7, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="battles2016" label="Battle 2016">Battles, Matthew and Michael Maizels,
                        <title rend="quotes">Collections and/of Data: Art History and the Art Museum
                        in the DH Mode</title> in <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baxandall1985" label="Baxandall 1985">Baxandall, Michael. <title
                        rend="italic">Patterns of Intention: On the Historical Explanation of
                        Pictures</title> (New Haven: Yale University Press), 1985.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bod2013" label="Bod 2013">Bod, Rens. <title rend="italic">A New
                        History of the Humanities: The Search for Principles and Patterns from
                        Antiquity to the Present</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bork2012" label="Bork 2012">Bork, Robert. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Provisional Investigation of Geometric Proportions in 15th-century Cologne
                        Panel Painting,</title> Zeitschrift für Kunsttechnologie und Konservierung
                    1/2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bork" label="Bork">Bork, Robert. <title rend="quotes">The Geometry of
                        Bourges Cathedral.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Architectural Histories</title> 2(1):24</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark1995" label="Clark 1995">Clark, J.T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cézanne’s Freud.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Representations</title> 52. Fall 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2009" label="Cohen 2009">Cohen, Margaret. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Narratology in the Archive of Literature,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Representations</title>. Vol. 108 No. 1 (Fall 2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="danchev2013" label="Danchev 2013">Danchev, Alex. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Letters of Paul Cézanne</title>. (Los Angeles: The Paul Getty Museum,
                    2013.)</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doran2001" label="Doran 2001">Doran, Michael ed. <title rend="italic"
                        >Conversations with Cézanne</title>. Introduction by Richard Schiff.
                    (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="feilchenfeldt" label="Feilenfeldt">Feilchenfeldt, Walter, Jayne
                    Warman, and David Nash. <title rend="italic">The Paintings of Paul Cézanne: An
                        Online Catalogue Raisonne</title>. <ref
                        target="http://www.Cézannecatalogue.com"
                        >http://www.Cézannecatalogue.com</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greenhalgh" label="Greenhalgh">Greenhalgh, Michael. <title
                        rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heinrichwofflin" label="Heinrich Wofflin">Wikipedia contributors,
                        <title rend="quotes">Heinrich Wölfflin,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia</title>, <ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Heinrich_W%C3%B6lfflin&amp;oldid=789968401"
                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Heinrich_W%C3%B6lfflin&amp;oldid=789968401</ref>
                    (accessed September 13, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hendrix2004" label="Hendrix 2004">Hendrix, John. <title rend="italic"
                        >Platonic Architectonics: Platonic Philosophies and the Visual Arts</title>:
                    New York: Peter Lang, 2004. 200-201.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kemp1989" label="Kemp 1989">Kemp, Martin editor. <title rend="italic"
                        >Leonardo on Painting</title>. Selected and translated by Martin Kemp and
                    Margaret Walker. New Haven, Yale University Press, 1989. 28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klinke2015" label="Klinke 2015">Klinke, Harald and Liska Surkemper.
                        <title rend="quotes">Editorial,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DAH-Journal</title> 1 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour2011" label="Latour 2011">Latour, Bruno and Adam Lowe, <title
                        rend="quotes">The Migration of the Aura, or How to Explore the Original
                        through the Facsimiles,</title> in <title rend="italic">Switching Codes:
                        Thinking Through Digital Technology in the Humanities and the Arts</title>.
                    Eds. Thomas Bartscherer and Roderick Coover (Chicago: University of Chicago
                    Press, 2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lockhart1997" label="Lockhart et. al. 1997">Lockhart, Shawn R. et. al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Development and verification of fingerprinting probes
                        for Candida glabrata,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Microbiology</title> (1997) 143, 3733-3746.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loran1943" label="Loran 1943">Loran, Erle. <title rend="italic"
                        >Cézanne’s Composition</title>. (Berkeley: University of California Press,
                    1943).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2015" label="Manovich 2015">Manovich, Lev. <title
                        rend="quotes">Data Science and Digital Art History,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DAH-Journal</title> 1 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1965" label="McLuhan 1965">McLuhan, Marshall. <title
                        rend="italic">The Gutenberg Galaxy: The Making of Typographic Man</title>.
                    Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1965. 40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pacioli2014" label="Pacioli 2014">Luca Pacioli and Leonardo da Vinci.
                        <title rend="italic">De Divina Proportione</title>. Facsimile of the
                    original printing of 1509. (Lexington, KY: Leopold Publishing, 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2016" label="Ramsay 2016">Ramsay,Stephen. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Humane Computing,</title> in <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> (2016), ed. Lauren F. Klein and Matthew K. Gold. n.p.
                        <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/51"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/51</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rewald1996" label="Rewald 1996">Rewald, John. <title rend="italic">The
                        Paintings of Paul Cézanne: A Catalogue Raisonne</title>. Vols. 1 and 2. (New
                    York: Harry N. Abrams, Inc. 1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam" label="Risam">Risam, Roopika and Susan Edwards, <title
                        rend="quotes">Micro DH: Digital Humanities at the Small Scale</title>
                    <ref target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/196/196.pdf"
                        >https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/196/196.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rohlf1963" label="Rohlf 1963">Rohlf, F. James. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Classification of Aedes by Numerical Taxonomic Methods (Dipterai
                        Culicidae),</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Annals of the Entymological Society of America</title>.
                    Vol. 56. No. 6. 798-804.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schmid1990" label="Schmid 1990">Schmid, Jan, Edward Voss and David R.
                    Soll. <title rend="quotes">Computer-Assisted Methods for Assessing Strain
                        Relatedness in Candida albicans by Fingerprinting with the Moderately
                        Repetitive Sequence Ca3.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Clinical Microbiology</title>, Vol. 28 no. 6,
                    (June 1990).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schneider1994" label="Schneider 1994">Schneider, Michael. <title
                        rend="italic">A Beginner’s Guide to Constructing the Universe</title>. (New
                    York: Harper Perennial, 1994).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sciencedaily" label="Science Daily">
                    <title rend="quotes">Can artificial intelligence tell a teapot from a golf ball?
                        Severe limitations of <q>deep learning</q> machines</title>
                    <ref target="www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/01/190107131236.htm"
                        >www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/01/190107131236.htm</ref> Accessed
                    1/9/19.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sidlauskus2004" label="Sidlauskus 2004">Sidlauskus, Susan. <title
                        rend="quotes">Emotion, Color, Cézanne (The Portraits of Hortense),</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Nineteenth Century Art Worldwide</title> 3:2 (2004).
                    Accessed April 26, 2017. 12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sneath1973" label="Sneath and Sokal 1973">Sneath, P.H. and R.R. Sokal,
                        <title rend="italic">Numerical Taxonomy: The Principles and Practice of
                        Numerical Classification</title>. 1st edition, San Francisco: W.H.
                    Freeman.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="soll2000" label="Soll 2000">Soll, D.R. 2000. <title rend="quotes">The
                        ins and outs of DNA fingerprinting the infectious Fungi.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Clinical Microbiology Reviews</title>. Vol.13.2 April
                    2000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="soll1995" label="Soll 1995">Soll, D. R. <title rend="quotes">The use
                        of computers in understanding how animal cells crawl.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The International Review of Cytology</title> 163, 43-104
                    (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stork2008" label="Stork 2008">Stork, David and Jim Coddington, <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computer Image Analysis in the Study of Art</title>, edited
                    by David G. Stork, Jim Coddington, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        SPIE-IS&amp;T Electronic Imaging,</title> SPIE 6810 (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood" label="Underwood">Underwood, Ted. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Distant Reading and Recent Intellectual History</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities 2016</title>, ed. Matthew K.
                    Gold and Lauren Klein. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weinstein" label="Weinstein">Weinstein, Melinda. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Genealogy of Nature: Theocritean Poetics and the Origin of <title
                            rend="italic">Boukolikos</title>.</title> in revision. <title
                        rend="italic">Classical Antiquity</title>. 6/15/19.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
