<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="issue" xml:lang="en">Racism in the Machine: Visualization Ethics in
                    Digital Humanities Projects</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Katherine <dhq:family>Hepworth</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Nevada, Reno</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>khepworth@unr.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr Katherine Hepworth is an interdisciplinary design practitioner-scholar
                            with a passion for researching and teaching about how the designed world
                            influences people's lived experience, past and present. Currently
                            employed as an Assistant Professor of Visual Journalism at The Reynolds
                            School of Journalism, University of Nevada, Reno, she teaches
                            communication design, data visualization, innovation, and visual
                            communication. Specializing in theorizing how visual communication
                            mediates human power relationships, she applies that theory to assess
                            visual communication effectiveness in a range of professional and
                            pedagogical contexts. Her current research projects include the ethics
                            of data visualizations, effective visual communication in hospital
                            emergency departments, and a digital humanities project on the
                            interconnected sociopolitical and typographic legacies of twentieth
                            century American neon. Hepworth has over fourteen years professional
                            experience as a visual communication designer, focusing on information
                            design and user experience design. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Christopher <dhq:family>Church</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Nevada, Reno</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>christopherchurch@unr.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Christopher M. Church is an assistant professor of history at the
                            University of Nevada, Reno, where he teaches colonial, environmental,
                            and digital history. Specializing in disasters, collective action, and
                            civil unrest, his wider research agenda addresses the historical
                            relationship between citizens, the public sphere, and the state. He is
                            the author of <title rend="italic">Paradise Destroyed: Catastrophe and
                                Citizenship in the French Caribbean</title>, which won the Alf
                            Andrew Heggoy Book Prize in 2018. He has worked on numerous digital
                            humanities projects, including <title rend="italic">Pryor's
                                Peoria</title>, <title rend="italic">The Online Edition of the
                                Journals of Alfred Doten</title>, and an online archive of neon in
                            Northern Nevada. His current research project focuses on the historical
                            development of and resistance to our increasingly globalized world,
                            which includes, among other things, the cultural, social, and economic
                            ties between historical piracy and present-day hacking.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000408</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-02-04">4 February 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Data visualizations are inherently rhetorical, and therefore bias-laden visual
                    artifacts that contain both explicit and implicit arguments. The implicit
                    arguments depicted in data visualizations are the net result of many seemingly
                    minor decisions about data and design from inception of a research project
                    through to final publication of the visualization. Data workflow, selected
                    visualization formats, and individual design decisions made within those formats
                    all frame and direct the possible range of interpretation, and the potential for
                    harm of any data visualization. Considering this, it is imperative that we take
                    an ethical approach to the creation and use of data visualizations. Therefore,
                    we have suggested an ethical data visualization workflow with the dual aim of
                    minimizing harm to the subjects of our study and the audiences viewing our
                    visualization, while also maximizing the explanatory capacity and effectiveness
                    of the visualization itself. To explain this ethical data visualization
                    workflow, we examine two recent digital mapping projects, Racial Terror
                    Lynchings and Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Proposes an ethical data visualization workflow.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <note> Both authors contributed equally to this article.</note>
                <p>In March 2016, Microsoft’s Technology and Research division released an
                    artificial intelligence chatbot known as TayTweets under the handle @TayandYou
                    on Twitter. Microsoft had programmed the chatbot to interact with the online
                    community and subsequently learn from the tweets of users mentioning it, in
                    order to improve its natural language communication abilities. Though unlikely
                    to pass the Turing Test any time soon, TayTweets was nevertheless able to
                    generate its own internet memes, crack its own jokes, and participate in the
                    regular back-and-forth of online conversation. </p>
                <p>Microsoft presented TayTweets as a value-neutral project that would showcase the
                    technological achievements of its research division, and early on the AI was
                    seemingly innocuous, posting anodyne responses to tweets welcoming it to Twitter
                    and asking it mundane questions. With its first tweet of <q>hellooooooo
                        w¿¿¿¿rld!!!</q> — a riff on the traditional output of a computer
                    programmer’s first program — TayTweets had virtually stepped onto the world
                    stage and greeted the Twitterverse in a seemingly innocent, even youthfully
                    naive, way.</p>
                <p>Within 16 hours, however, the experiment had to be shut down, as TayTweets had
                    algorithmically learned to be racist. Posting inflammatory tweets championing
                    white supremacy and denigrating racial minorities and marginalized groups, the
                    artificial intelligence program had become an online menace and in fact a
                    cyberbully. TayTweets’s rapid descent into racist demagoguery serves as a
                    harrowing reminder that our digital productions are not free from the cultural
                    assumptions and prejudices that shape everyday human experience. Microsoft’s
                    designers had a blind spot about the depth and breadth of American racism, which
                    allowed TayTweets to replicate deep-seated preconceptions and prejudices without
                    critically examining them. </p>
                <p>For our purposes, what is interesting about TayTweets is not its experimentation
                    with artificial intelligence, but the project’s apparent assumption that an
                    algorithm — the set of rules by which any programmatic approach operates,
                    whether digital or analog — is value neutral and divorceable from human
                    prejudice and malice. On the contrary, humans are at the center of algorithms,
                    not only as their creators but, in the case of data-driven algorithms, as the
                    producers of the content they shape and present. Though an extreme example,
                    TayTweets clearly demonstrates how wider cultural assumptions, prevalent
                    political ideologies, and public discourses shape the output of our algorithmic
                    productions, potentially replicating what we already know instead of aiding us
                    to discover the new and uncover the unexamined. In other words, TayTweets tapped
                    into an American zeitgeist riddled with detrimental preconceptions with regard
                    to race. </p>
                <p>Ethical visualization is essentially a human-centric approach to algorithmic
                    production, considering the underlying biases, ideologies, and beliefs that
                    animate algorithms as they structure and reproduce past inequities and harmful
                    realities. All data visualizations — whether static or interactive, printed or
                    digital, computer-generated or hand-drawn — are algorithmic by nature, in
                    the sense that they solve complex problems of representation and require a set
                    of tree-based actions and decisions for their success. Ethical visualization
                    practices sit at the intersection of humanistic inquiry, ethics, and
                    communication design. We define ethical visualization as the presentation of
                    visualized information in ways that acknowledge and mitigate the potential for
                    harm engendered within the visualization form and content. While good design
                    practice forms the backbone of ethical visualizations, ethical visualization
                    practice goes one step further to consider the ultimate societal impact of such
                    design choices: do such choices cause harm or mislead, either intentionally or
                    unintentionally? Do they result in a net societal benefit, or do they prove
                    deleterious to marginalized individuals? These questions must be brought to the
                    forefront when considering good design, because a visualization can follow good
                    design practices and consequently be easy to understand, but still produce a
                    negative societal impact for its subject matter all the same.</p>
                <p>Considering the object lesson of TayTweets, this article proposes that digital
                    humanists must adhere to a form of visualization ethics that considers how both
                    choices about working with data and the rhetorical qualities of communication
                    elements — color, composition, line, symbols, type, and interactivity — shape
                    users’ understandings of represented people and places. Given the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#cairo2014">racism in the machine</quote> — the ways
                    in which our digital tools can inadvertently recreate the latent racism,
                    underlying prejudices, and cultural blind spots in our society — the goal of
                    this visualization ethics should be <quote rend="inline" source="#cairo2014"
                        >increasing understanding [for users] while minimizing harm</quote> to
                    represented people and places <ptr target="#cairo2014"/>.</p>
                <p>To propose a methodology for visualization ethics, this article examines two
                    projects that visualize the horrific history of racial lynching in the United
                    States, Lynching in America by the Equal Justice Initiative and Monroe Work
                    Today by Auut Studio, in order to show that no visualization is ideologically
                    neutral, but is instead part of an argument that must be critically examined. In
                    contrast to TayTweets’s outright bigotry, Lynching in America and Monroe Work
                    Today both present visualizations that demonstrate to varying degrees ethical
                    visualization practices, though one succeeds in producing an ethical
                    visualization to a greater degree than the other. This paper showcases ethical
                    visualization in practice to varying degrees in these two digital mapping
                    projects, demonstrating how choices about representation, interaction, and
                    annotation in their data visualizations either do harm in the sense described
                    above, or challenge dominant narratives. In comparing these two projects, the
                    article outlines a workflow that can ensure that data visualizations adhere to
                    best practices in visualization ethics and thereby present opportunities for
                    more inclusive and critical interaction with represented data.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Lynching in America (EJI) vs Monroe Work Today</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Example 1: Racial Terror Lynchings Map</head>
                    <p>Lynching in America (<ref target="https://lynchinginamerica.eji.org/"
                            >https://lynchinginamerica.eji.org/</ref>), a promotional website made
                        by Google for the Equal Justice Initiative, a mass incarceration
                        not-for-profit organization, contains an interactive map titled Racial
                        Terror Lynchings (<ref target="https://lynchinginamerica.eji.org/explore"
                            >https://lynchinginamerica.eji.org/explore</ref>). Drawing on a dataset
                        compiled by the EJI for their eponymous report of <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#LiA">4075 racial terror lynchings of African-Americans,</quote>
                        this interactive choropleth map of the United States purports to depict
                            <title rend="quotes">Reported lynchings by county</title>, occurring
                        between 1877 and 1950 <ptr target="#EJI2018"/>. Overall, the map has a
                        minimalist aesthetic, reminiscent of Google’s Material Design visual style
                            (<ref target="https://material.io/">https://material.io/</ref>) that
                        depicts topographical elevation as well as country, state, and county
                        borders, but not cities, towns, roads, rivers, lakes, or landmarks (see <ref
                            target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The data visualized is also
                        minimalist in presentation, and is tied directly to the state and county
                        borders depicted, as is typical of choropleth maps. </p>
                    <p>The map is focused on the southeastern United States. On first page load in
                        screen widths below 1500px, the map centers on the United States below the
                        Mason-Dixon line, while in larger screens the entire contiguous United
                        States is shown. However, in both cases, the American south grabs attention
                        with many southern counties highlighted. Users can click on any county or
                        state, and are taken to a zoomed-in view of the state, with the total
                        reported lynchings in that state displayed in large letters. The user can
                        then hover over individual counties to find out how many lynchings were
                        reported in that county (see <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>). This
                        zoomed-in view focuses on the number of lynchings per state and county —
                        represented by polygons shaped according to county boundaries — creating a
                        visual argument that encourages measurement of states and counties as more
                        or less reprehensible in terms of number of lynchings. It is focused on
                        lynchings in the context of political boundaries, and thereby presents a
                        strong geopolitical argument about recorded lynchings that appears
                        definitive and damning, particularly of the states with the most counties
                        marked in bright red: Alabama, Florida, Louisiana, and Mississippi. There is
                        a straightforwardness about this visual argument: racial terror was and is
                        morally wrong, and its contours are plain to any competent observer.</p>
                    <p>In terms of color, the map features a dark, almost monochrome color palette,
                        with a dark grey United States segmented by black state lines, placed in a
                        dark blue sea. This mostly dark color scheme is dramatically interrupted
                        with many counties highlighted in various shades of red, with bright red
                        indicating 20 or more lynchings recorded in the county (see <ref
                            target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The color scheme of red on an
                        otherwise dark, monochrome palette compounds the visual argument described
                        above, as it references the brutality and violence inflicted upon African
                        Americans in those locations, recalling the blood stains on United States
                        history as it relates to racial violence and white supremacy. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>Figure 1</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01a.png"/>
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Racial Terror Lynchings map in Lynching in America website. Top image
                                (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>) shows initial view of map
                            on page load. Bottom image (<ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>)
                            shows the zoomed-in view on Georgia, with mouse hover over Richmond
                            County. With 590 reported lynchings in Georgia, Richmond County’s 2
                            reported lynchings appear significantly less reprehensible than the
                            record of other counties in Georgia.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01b.png"/>
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Example 2: Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence</head>
                    <p>The second example, Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence (<ref
                            target="http://www.monroeworktoday.org/explore/"
                            >http://www.monroeworktoday.org/explore/</ref>), is a far more complex
                        visualization than the minimalist Racial Terror Lynchings. It is an
                        interactive map within Monroe Work Today (<ref
                            target="http://www.monroeworktoday.org"
                            >http://www.monroeworktoday.org</ref>), a website dedicated to
                        publicizing the research of sociologist Monroe Work, who systematically
                        documented lynchings in the United States. Created by education-focused
                        digital agency Auut Studio, this interactive map of the United States
                        depicts lynching records in the context of historical racial violence and
                        public discourses of white superiority, and is consequently subtitled <title
                            rend="quotes">The lynchings and riots to enforce racial superiority in
                            the US</title>. Upon first page load, Map of White Supremacy Mob
                        Violence stands in stark contrast to Racial Terror Lynchings, presenting the
                        entire contiguous United States center of screen, irrespective of screen
                        size, and representing each recorded case of lynching as a single grey dot
                        on a white national landmass background (see <ref target="#figure03">Figure
                            3</ref>). State borders are not visible in this view, and a single,
                        bright, attention grabbing color is only found on instructions for users.
                        This initial map view — including map framing, choice of colors, and the
                        carefully worded title and subtitle — provides a strong and markedly
                        different message than the Racial Terror Lynchings map. Collectively, these
                        elements present a strong visual argument that discourses of white supremacy
                        are a nationwide reality in the United States, one that has historically
                        been enforced through lynchings and riots by mobs. The geopolitical framing
                        of lynching as a nation-wide reality is balanced with the acknowledgement of
                        a crucial aspect of the historically pervasive intellectual climate, one of
                        white superiority, and an important aspect of the social behavioral climate,
                        mob violence. At the center bottom of the page is a key annotation: a label
                        that reads <q>Should I trust this? Find out.</q> If users click this
                        message, they are taken to a plethora of information about the veracity of
                        the data used, and a discussion of the importance of thinking critically
                        about the visualized data.</p>
                    <p>Although it is not entirely clear from this initial page view what the grey
                        dots represent, the user is presented with instructions to zoom in and click
                        on individual points. After the user follows these instructions, the map
                        gains more color, and individual dots become more visible, along with state
                        and county boundaries (see <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). In this
                        view, state and county lines are visible, as are the boundaries of Native
                        American reservations and areas that historically were Spanish colonies.
                        However, these geographic lines are indicated with subtlety, using pale
                        colors. In contrast, the dots representing each individual lynching are
                        highlighted using bright colors and an <hi rend="italic">onclick</hi>
                        interaction effect. Marking geopolitical boundaries but deemphasizing them,
                        combined with emphasizing each individual lynching with bright colors, makes
                        the visual argument that lynchings occurred in the context of geopolitical
                        boundaries, but that the individual deaths are of greater significance than
                        the boundaries themselves. </p>
                    <p>Along the bottom of the screen, supplemental information and interactive
                        features appear, including a timeline, a label stating the time span
                        represented in the current view, and a color-coded legend of dot colors. Six
                        different dot colors are used: five to represent races of lynched people,
                        and one to represent <q>other</q>, where the race recorded in the historical
                        records does not fall into one of the main five. Notably, the <q>other</q>
                        category includes lynchings of white abolitionists, thereby demonstrating
                        the complexity of the history of lynching in the United States, and that
                        white people were also, however rarely, victims of lynching in the name of
                        white supremacy. </p>
                    <p>Both the timeline and the legend serve two purposes: one functional, the
                        other persuasive. Users can select a time period using the timeline, which
                        then alters data presented on the map, so they can see how many lynchings
                        occurred in an area over a specific timeframe. Secondly, the timeline
                        provides a persuasive visual cue that racial superiority-motivated lynchings
                        occured continually over a long timespan, with some time periods seeing
                        evidence of significantly more racial superiority-motivated lynchings. The
                        legend also works on these two levels. It firstly allows the user to
                        identify the race of a lynched person based on the color of the dot used to
                        represent them, and secondly provides a strong visual counterargument to the
                        widespread public assumption that lynchings were perpetrated exclusively on
                        African Americans. These two elements, the timeline and the legend, confront
                        the user with the temporal and racial extent of white superiority-motivated
                        lynchings, both qualities that are absent from the Racial Terror Lynchings
                        map. </p>
                    <p>Most strikingly, the zoomed-in view of Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence
                        contains a list, in the bottom left hand corner of the screen, of the name
                        (where available) of every lynched person represented by a dot in the
                        current map view, and the year they were lynched. Clicking on any individual
                        dot brings up a <hi rend="italic">callout</hi> box containing extra details
                        of the lynching available in the historical record, including the county in
                        which it occurred, the details of mob violence in which the lynching
                        occurred, the accusation made before the lynching, and links to every
                        available historical source that verifies the record (see <ref
                            target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>). Naming individuals who were lynched,
                        and providing circumstances surrounding their death, focuses attention on
                        the humanity of victims of lynching and on the social circumstances in which
                        lynching was a viable possibility. In the present day context of many white
                        supremacists denying their racism, it is worth noting that these historical
                        records rarely mention race as a motivator for lynching. For example,
                        William B. Willis of Richmond County, Georgia, was accused of murder before
                        being lynched. The Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence does an exemplary job
                        of demonstrating that racism was indeed the motivating factor in lynchings,
                        and also that racism was largely hidden in the official historical record by
                        documenting other, non-racial reasons. Providing links to multiple
                        historical sources within the interactive map increases trust in the
                        veracity of data, while at the same time giving users the opportunity to
                        investigate the historical evidence themselves. Map of White Supremacy Mob
                        Violence uses multiple compelling strategies to both humanize the data it
                        represents, and to contextualize it in the societal racism and discourses of
                        white supremacy in the United States. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure03">
                        <head>Figure 3</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02a.png"/>
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Figure 4</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02b.png"/>
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure05">
                        <head>Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence in Monroe Work Today website. Top
                            image (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>) shows the initial view of
                            the map on page load. Center image (<ref target="#figure04">Figure
                                4</ref>) shows a zoomed-in view on Georgia. Richmond County is
                            highlighted in green by the authors, for comparison with the Racial
                            Terror Lynching map in <ref target="#figure01">Figures 1 and 2</ref>.
                            Bottom image (<ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>) shows a view of
                            clicking over an individual lynching record in Richmond County. Naming
                            individuals who were lynched and providing circumstances of their death
                            focuses attention on the humanity of victims of lynching, the cover up
                            of racist motivations for lynching documented in the historical record,
                            and deemphasizes geopolitical comparisons. Additionally, the context of
                            a large number of lynchings close across the border in South Carolina
                            suggests that the geographic area including Richmond county was no less
                            immune to racial superiority-motivated violence than the surrounding
                            areas, as the presentation of information in the Racial Terror Lynchings
                            map visually argues.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02c.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Comparison of both maps’ depictions of the West</head>
                    <p>The contrast between these two maps is even more striking when looking at the
                        west coast of the United States. For example, <ref target="#figure06">Figure
                            6</ref> shows a marked difference between the recorded lynchings in
                        California in the Racial Terror Lynchings map and the Map of White Supremacy
                        Mob Violence respectively. The difference in the representation can be
                        accounted for by the fact that the former only depicts lynchings of African
                        Americans, whereas the latter depicts lynchings of African Americans, Native
                        Americans, Latinos, Italians, and other races. The view of the American West
                        depicted in Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence in <ref target="#figure06"
                            >Figure 6b</ref> provides a compelling visual narrative that lynchings
                        were common across California in the name of enforcing white superiority.
                        The view of Racial Terror Lynchings Map depicted in <ref target="#figure06"
                            >Figure 6a</ref>, by its lack of clarity about exactly which data is
                        being represented (i.e. historical records of lynchings of African Americans
                        only), its use of a bold and expansive title that suggests comprehensive
                        coverage of lynchings of all races (i.e. Racial Terror Lynchings), and its
                        tonal emphasis on the south (California appearing grey, while visual
                        attention is drawn to the large amounts of red in the bottom right hand
                        corner of the map), makes a visual argument that California had few
                        instances of racial terror or lynchings. This is particularly problematic
                        because the Equal Justice Initiative’s stated goal is to challenge black
                        incarceration, and a key part of their organizational message is that this
                        goal is urgent and directly related to the history of lynchings motivated by
                        white supremacy. Black incarceration rates in California are among the
                        highest in the nation today: according to the U.S. Bureau of Justice,
                        California imprisons blacks 8.8 times more frequently than whites, well
                        above the national average of 5.5:1 <ptr target="#sp2015"/>. Consequently
                        EJI’s visual argument in the Racial Terror Lynchings Maps inadvertently
                        breaks down in advocacy regarding California prisons.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure06">
                        <head>Contrasting views of California in Racial Terror Lynchings Map (figure
                            6a, left) and Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence (figure 6b, right).
                            The map framing on the left suggests lynching occurred rarely in
                            California, whereas the map framing on the right indicates that lynching
                            was widespread in California. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                        <figDesc>Two maps compared.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Discussion</head>
                    <p>The emphases of these two maps are necessarily different because of the
                        different purposes of the sites in which they are situated. Lynching in
                        America is a promotional and advocacy tool for the Equal Justice Initiative,
                        primarily created to visualize data within (and thereby promote) the report
                            <title rend="quotes">Lynching in America</title>, which records
                        lynchings of African Americans and frames lynching as a societal tool —
                        enabled through mob violence and discourses of white superiority — to
                        subjugate African Americans between slavery and mass incarceration. It is in
                        the Equal Justice Initiative’s interests to visualize historical lynching
                        data in a way that draws attention to geopolitical divides, so that clear
                        links can be made between historical lynching events and present-day
                        constituencies of sitting politicians as well as county and state local
                        governments. The map provides compelling visual evidence for the
                        organization’s present-day advocacy work regarding the inequitable mass
                        incarceration of black Americans, the case of California notwithstanding.
                        The problematic aspect of this is that the Equal Justice Initiative’s
                        website, report, and Racial Terror Lynchings map are unfortunately named to
                        suggest that they cover all historical records of lynchings in the United
                        States. The Lynching in America report includes instructions for educators
                        who wish to use it as a teaching resource. In this context, the geopolitical
                        emphasis, use of color, use of summary data, and lack of links to sources
                        give a concerning impression that African-American lynchings were the
                        complete record of lynchings in the United States for the purposes of racial
                        terror.</p>
                    <p>The majority of both scholarship and public attention regarding lynchings
                        centers on the experience of African Americans in the Southern United
                        States, and for good measure: for blacks in the Jim Crow South, lynchings
                        represented a terrifying aspect of everyday life. In the grand scheme of
                        racial violence, however, lynchings represented one small piece in a complex
                        puzzle of individual, institutional, and structural racism. The conflation
                        of lynching with the full extent of racialized violence in United States
                        history obscures the historic depth and breadth of the oppression of people
                        of color. A black individual was far more likely to suffer public
                        humiliation, assault, rape, and murder than a public lynching. While
                        lynchings do not represent the totality of racial violence in America, they
                        come to the fore because they were highly symbolic affairs: gruesome
                        spectacles of white supremacy, racial violence, and bodily mutilation meant
                        to suppress and intimidate as much as they were meant to kill <ptr
                            target="#wood2009" loc="1–4"/>. Due to their highly symbolic nature and
                        the lasting implications of racist attitudes, policies, and actions for
                        African Americans today, lynchings have become synonymous with racial hatred
                        in the postbellum American south. </p>
                    <p>However, mob murder historically extended well beyond Dixie, representing a
                        form of prejudicial frontier <soCalled>justice</soCalled> in the Midwest,
                        West, and Southwest against minorities and immigrants of various backgrounds
                            <ptr target="#pfeifer2006"/>
                        <ptr target="#pfeifer2013"/>. Outside of the latest scholarship, such
                        victims, whom Carrigan and Webb describe as the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#carrigan2017">forgotten dead,</quote> are largely overshadowed
                        or overlooked in the public sphere, missing an opportunity to explore the
                        structural, cross-regional, and transethnic dimensions of American lynching.
                        In fact, lynch mobs murdered hundreds of Mexicans between 1848 and 1928 in
                        the American Southwest <ptr target="#carrigan2017"/>.</p>
                    <p>Moving beyond EJI’s limited focus on African-American populations in the
                        American South, Auut Studio acknowledges the historic violence committed
                        against Native American populations, which is noticeably absent from the
                        vast majority of lynching data sets. This general oversight plays into
                        present-day blind spots regarding violence against native populations, who,
                        despite suffering more state violence and community disruption than any
                        other minority group in 2016 according to data collected by the Centers for
                        Disease Control and Prevention, rarely garner the public spotlight <ptr
                            target="#counted"/>. To counteract the public oversight of this <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#ramey2017">forgotten minority,</quote> Auut
                        Studio included the boundaries of Native American reservations as <cit>
                            <quote source="#ramey2017" rend="inline">sovereignt[ies] deserving of
                                equal visual treatment on the map</quote>
                            <ptr target="#ramey2017"/>
                        </cit>. Similarly, Auut Studio included lynchings of the Chinese along the
                        frontier, namely in California, as well as Mexicans in the Southwest,
                        keeping in line with recent historical scholarship. </p>
                    <p>In order to ethically represent historical subjects, data visualization
                        techniques, particularly those geared toward public consumption, must remain
                        abreast of the insights made in two areas of the scholarly literature:
                        debates on the subjects they depict, and debates on design and
                        representational considerations in the ethical visualization literature.
                        Present-day academic debates on lynching challenge the widely accepted
                        notion that lynching was exclusively a Southern phenomenon, excusing those
                        regions of the United States outside of the South of their own racist
                        heritage. The small but growing ethical visualization literature emphasizes
                        the need for acknowledging and mitigating the potential for harm inherent in
                        visualizing data, particularly when it comes to selection of design
                        elements, visual style, and selections of data to annotate and visually
                        emphasize <ptr target="#cairo2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#hepworth2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#kostelnick2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#skau2015"/>.</p>
                    <p> Collectively, we tend to visualize old arguments, as visualization practices
                        have not kept pace with dominant arguments in the digital humanities
                        literature about the importance of critical practices. Visualization
                        practice in the digital humanities runs the risk of following a
                        functionalist methodological approach that assumes visualization to be an
                        impartial medium. This illusory functionalism has led others to charge that
                        data collection, processing, and visualization practices constitute mere
                            <soCalled>janitorial work</soCalled> in the service of
                            <soCalled>real</soCalled> humanities scholarship, ignoring the important
                        decisions made during such processes that critically shape historical
                        narratives. Construing digital humanities practice as a <quote
                            source="#allington2016" rend="inline">support field</quote> has led to
                        further accusations that the digital humanities simply show to us what we
                        already know, rather than challenging us to think critically about
                        historical topics in new, interesting, and socially responsible ways <ptr
                            target="#allington2016"/>. </p>
                    <p>Following Alan Liu’s charge that digital humanists have ignored cultural
                        criticism, which in turn has blocked <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2012"
                            >the digital humanities from becoming a full partner of the
                            humanities,</quote> data visualization practitioners need to critically
                        engage with the ways in which digital tools can <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#liu2012">communicate humanity</quote> rather than relegating it
                        to the margins, or worse, obscuring the human stories essential to
                        understanding structural racism today <ptr target="#liu2012"/>.</p>
                    <p>Visualizing data that exclusively focuses on the African-American experience
                        in the Southern United States provides an important argument about the
                        nature of Jim Crow racism. However, purporting such data to be an inclusive
                        representation constitutes a harm in the sense that it perpetuates common
                        narratives of racial violence as a southern exception to an otherwise
                        inclusive nation. After publishing their interactive map, the Equal Justice
                        Initiative itself recognized this oversight, acknowledging the 300 lynchings
                        of African Americans outside of the American south, though notably leaving
                        aside other ethnicities like Native Americans, Mexicans, and the Chinese
                        that fell victim to much of Western and Southwestern mob violence <ptr
                            target="#EJI2017"/>. This overlooks the depth of structural racism and
                        its support of white supremacy, thereby denying the experience of millions
                        of present-day Americans. Historical information has the capacity to
                        legitimize or delegitimize present-day experience, and visualizations of
                        historical data are a particularly compelling and resonant medium through
                        which such information can either harm or help. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Ethical Visualization Workflow</head>
                <p>We call for critical and practical analysis of the entire endeavor of data
                    collection and visualization in the digital humanities. Humanities scholars in
                    recent decades have critically examined the categories of scientific analysis
                    inherited from the enlightenment that presuppose essential differences (based on
                    sex, race, age etc) acknowledging that such pre-suppositions frame and
                    ultimately determine scholarly insight <ptr target="#knorr-cetina1981"/>.
                    However, digital humanists and data scientists rely heavily on these categories
                    in their visualization practices precisely because they animate the entirety of
                    the scientific endeavor. </p>
                <p>Similarly, visual communication has been studied for decades in terms of its
                    highly rhetorical qualities <ptr target="#barton1985"/>
                    <ptr target="#gallagher2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#tapia2003"/>. Despite early interventions by journalist Darrell
                    Huff and statistician Howard Wainer, data visualization literature and practice
                    seldom focus on the argument-altering, persuasive qualities of individual design
                    decisions or visualization conventions to a degree that allows for effectively
                    mitigating the harmful potential consequences of visualization <ptr
                        target="#huff1954"/>
                    <ptr target="#wainer1984"/>. One notable exception to this overall trend is the
                    work of cartography scholar Mark Monmonier, who has long advocated for
                    acknowledging the complexity and nuance inherent in the minutiae of
                    visualization design decisions <ptr target="#monmonier1991"/>
                    <ptr target="#monmonier1995"/>. Huff, Monmonier, and Wainer can be seen as the
                    grandfathers of a small, interdisciplinary body of work on ethical visualization
                    practices that directly tackles the challenge of mitigating the potential for
                    harm inherent in data visualization <ptr target="#cairo2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#hepworth2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#kostelnick2007"/>. We argue that there is an urgent need for this
                    ethical visualization literature to grow in detail and scope, particularly with
                    regard to digital humanities projects. It is imperative that ethical data
                    visualizers evaluate not only the rhetorical decisions of the analysis, but also
                    critically examine the entire process of working with data from collection to
                    final visualization and publishing. </p>
                <p>Visual theorist Johanna Drucker offers one proposal to address the challenge of
                    ethical representation. She argues that the humanities need their own forms of
                    visualization, distinct from those developed for administrative and scientific
                    purposes <ptr target="#drucker2011" loc="1"/>. She does this for good reason:
                    the standard visualization conventions that we are most familiar with — bar
                    charts, line charts, pie charts — were all created in European countries at the
                    height of their colonial expansion and industrial transformation. They were
                    created to track demographics, trade, war, and debt; all the trappings of their
                    growing empires <ptr target="#wainer2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#cole2000"/>. These visualization conventions carry this history,
                    and these associations, with them. </p>
                <p>However, in his work on the role of charts in the social sciences, historian
                    Howard S. Becker reminds us that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#becker2007">if we invent a new format every
                            time we have something to say, we risk alienating users</quote>
                        <ptr target="#becker2007" loc="169"/>
                    </cit>. Finding the right balance between visualization innovation and working
                    within established conventions is a complex procedure that demands a combination
                    of high visual literacy, advanced visualization production skills, intimate
                    understanding of the visualization context, and a critical perspective on the
                    entire data collection and visualization process. Much valuable work has been
                    done by geographers in terms of working critically with established
                    visualization formats, in the form of critical GIS <ptr target="#harvey2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#thatcher2016"/>. </p>
                <p>We argue that for pragmatic reasons, humanists must work with the visualization
                    formats that are familiar to their audiences much of the time. We encourage
                    innovation in visualization practices only insofar as innovations are both
                    intelligible to the intended audience, and that they foster consideration of the
                    dignity of the represented subjects. Therefore, we propose an ethical
                    visualization workflow (see <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref>) that
                    operates within existing data collection and information design frameworks but
                    ensures that any given visualization’s argument provides a compelling yet
                    ethical and accurate representation of historical subjects.</p>
                <p>Prior to creating a data visualization, a scholar following our ethical
                    visualization workflow would complete several critical steps: defining,
                    reviewing, collecting, pruning, describing, surveying, and pre-visualizing.
                    These steps involve processes that many digital humanities scholars will be
                    familiar with, with the important difference that they are suggested here with
                    alterations that we believe will result in an ethical data visualization. The
                    steps can be grouped into three standard digital humanities practice phases:
                    pre-data collection (defining, reviewing); data collection and curation
                    (collecting, pruning, describing); and data visualization and argumentation
                    (surveying, pre-visualizing, visualizing, publishing).</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Pre-Data Collection</head>
                    <p>In the pre-data collection phase, the first step involves clearly defining
                        the subject area that the data visualization will depict, while the second
                        step involves reviewing the latest secondary literature on the topic at
                        hand. Reviewing subject area literature would inform the remaining steps in
                        the ethical data visualization workflow, inviting the researcher to
                        compensate for the data set’s shortcomings by seeking out and including new
                        information, or to limit the scope of the visual argument to be produced
                        with said data. Doing so would avoid the glaring oversights and interpretive
                        overreach that plagued the EJI’s Racial Terror Lynchings Map. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data Collection and Curation</head>
                    <p>The second phase, data collection and curation, is perhaps most crucial in
                        producing an ethical data visualization, precisely because it is so
                        frequently overlooked. The third step in the ethical visualization workflow
                        involves collecting primary documents, artifacts, and datasets, as well as
                        secondary datasets of potential relevance, while the fourth step involves
                        checking the appropriateness, authenticity, veracity, and feasibility of use
                        of collected primary and secondary materials, and pruning those that don’t
                        hold up under scrutiny. Once these two critical data collection steps have
                        been finished, the researcher completes the fifth step, describing, by
                        creating their own dataset that combines the collected materials. </p>
                    <p>Creating a custom dataset for the researcher’s visualization in this way
                        eliminates other people’s and institutions’ biases from the data, ensuring
                        erroneous arguments are not unintentionally added through using unaltered
                        historical datasets. This process of collecting, pruning, and describing
                        data sets was undertaken by Auut Studios for ten years before visualization,
                        contributing to the particularly considerate treatment of ethical factors in
                        the Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence. Similarly, EJI created an extensive
                        dataset of over 4,000 public lynchings based on work done by Tuskegee
                        University and the research of E.M. Beck and Stewart E. Tolnay that
                        compellingly shows the long legacy of terroristic violence in the American
                        south. Nevertheless, decisions made about what counts or does not count as
                            <q>racial terror violence</q> made during the data collection phase —
                        namely to exclude the American frontier — ultimately shaped EJI’s visual
                        argument, making it overreach in its claims and thereby creating a narrative
                        around racial violence that excludes other minorities and other geographic
                        locales.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure07">
                        <head>The Ethical Visualization Workflow we propose for producing
                            visualizations that minimize harm to three groups: people using
                            visualizations, people represented in visualizations, and people
                            personally affected by the represented material.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                        <figDesc>A workflow chart.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data Visualization and Argumentation</head>
                    <p>The third and final phase of the visualization workflow, data visualization
                        and argumentation, is the main one associated with the ethics of data
                        visualization, and this phase involves four steps: surveying,
                        pre-visualizing, visualizing, and publishing. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Surveying &amp; Pre-visualizing</head>
                        <p>Once the custom data set has been created, the researcher moves onto the
                            sixth step: surveying the latest literature from the small but growing
                            interdisciplinary field of ethical visualization. Surveying this
                            literature allows the researcher to keep abreast of ethical
                            visualization innovations and recommended best practices. The seventh
                            step, pre-visualizing, involves considering the contextual factors
                            around the visualization: normalizing representations of the data;
                            selecting the publishing medium; identifying intended and potential
                            unintended audiences based on that medium; and discerning between
                            visualization formats possible in that medium. When making decisions
                            about the argument produced by the visualization, it is imperative to
                            consider the larger contextual framing and the story that it tells. For
                            instance, in the case of EJI’s Racial Terror Lynchings, the data isn't
                            normalized against census population data. Normalizing the data in this
                            way would show how frequent these lynchings were in a population of
                            people rather than a geographic space, thus showing the relative
                            societal impact of a lynching of two people in a county of 100 rather
                            than 5 people in a county of 10,000. </p>
                        <p>In considering these contextual factors, the researcher can then select
                            the most appropriate visualization format, creating test visualizations
                            (these are more rudimentary than, and distinct from, alpha prototypes)
                            and performing any necessary re-structuring of the dataset based on
                            findings of this prototyping. In the pre-visualizing step, the selection
                            of visualization format is particularly important. The mechanics and
                            conventions of specific visualization formats contribute to determining
                            meaning. For example, Mercator geographic projections have been
                            criticized for privileging Northern Europe and underemphasizing the
                            Global South <ptr target="#monmonier2010"/>. While they receive less
                            attention for their distortional effects, pie charts encourage a
                            comparison between visualized elements as if they make up a unified
                            whole, whether or not they actually do so in reality <ptr
                                target="#tufte1998"/>. It is not that such visualization formats are
                            by definition unethical to use, but that a critical perspective can
                            unearth the ways in which they limit or close off possibilities of
                            argumentation.</p>
                        <p>Critically examining each of the areas involved in pre-visualizing, and
                            making careful, considered choices on each area, can dramatically change
                            the ethical implications of a project. For example, if the Lynching in
                            America report and Racial Terror Map were printed documents, they would
                            have a much smaller audience than they have as web-based documents. This
                            would result in less reach for the organizations, but also less
                            potential harm in terms of the Racial Terror Lynching map being used in
                            contexts outside of lobbying for prison reform, and therefore giving an
                            erroneous presentation of the history of lynching in the United States. </p>
                        <p>The pre-visualizing step provides an opportunity to acknowledge the prior
                            understanding and cultural frame of the intended and unintended
                            potential audiences. The persuasive and culturally bound associations
                            those audiences necessarily have with design elements, explanatory text,
                            headers, legends and interaction experiences need to be considered. The
                            choice of colors and color ramps, as well as graphic or cartographic
                            elements like political boundaries, invariably influence the argument
                            produced by the visualization, as do map default views at certain screen
                            widths, and zoom options. To be ethical, these choices must be made with
                            the scholarly literature and the ethical visualization literature in
                            mind, as well as a critical perspective on the power of individual
                            design elements. To maintain visualization ethics, they should strive to
                            minimize harm while increasing understanding, and this can only be done
                            when the latest ethical developments in the field are factored into the
                            visualization at hand. </p>
                        <p>For instance, given the research on the dehumanization of deaths by
                            aggregating them into faceless statistics and the resulting inability to
                            enact meaningful social change <ptr target="#duwors1960"/>
                            <ptr target="#bernard1971"/>
                            <ptr target="#slovic2007"/>
                            <ptr target="#katz2011"/>, Monroe Work Today created an individual
                            marker for every person killed, so that their name and details could be
                            uncovered by the viewer. While more visually complex than a choropleth
                            map, as was used in Racial Terror Lynchings, creating individual markers
                            conveys the sheer gravity of the violence while not losing sight of the
                            individuals who suffered at the hands of white supremacy. As the
                            director of Auut Studio, RJ Ramey, explains, <cit>
                                <quote rend="block" source="#ramey2017">it was [a] conscious
                                    decision to include every person killed as their own marker on
                                    the map — so that their name could be discovered. I have
                                    received suggestions that a more <soCalled>efficient</soCalled>
                                    visualization would have been a choropleth map or graduated
                                    symbol size — and visualizers at EJI and the NYT have utilized
                                    these methods. However, for purposes of respecting the gravity
                                    of the violence and the humanity of the victims, I very much
                                    believed it was most appropriate to provide the audience a
                                    census of the lynching record, not a visual or numerical
                                    analysis.</quote>
                                <ptr target="#ramey2017"/>
                            </cit></p>
                        <p>In contrast, EJI replicates the conventions, and thereby the limitations,
                            of how the Tuskegee Institute has visualized their data by state and
                            county since 1931 (see, for example: <title rend="italic">Lynchings by
                                States and Counties</title>, 1931, <ref
                                target="https://www.loc.gov/resource/g3701e.ct002012"
                                >https://www.loc.gov/resource/g3701e.ct002012</ref>).</p>
                        <p>The visual argument produced must be a bounded one, explaining what it
                            does show while inviting the user to interrogate and explore what it
                            does not show. Effacing the data, along with its assumptions, within the
                            visualization itself, as Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence so
                            admirably does, invites the user to judge the veracity and scope of the
                            data themselves, providing an opportunity for users to build informed
                            trust in the visualized data. Auut Studio makes plain the decisions made
                            during all of these pre-visualization steps, encouraging the user to
                            take a critical stance toward the argument ultimately put forth by the
                            visualization itself. On the other hand, while EJI does provide a link
                            to its full lynching report, which goes into detail about how the
                            dataset was collected and why it was bounded in such a way as to exclude
                            the American frontier, this link stands apart from the visualization
                            itself, buried within the website’s navigation drawer. Moreover, the
                            report does not address the translation of those choices into the
                            rhetorical qualities of the visualization itself, which purports to show
                            the entirety of American Racial Terror Lynchings. As the argument
                            presenting the data, an ethical visualization should provide clear and
                            apparent options for users to investigate sources, so that the user will
                            be able to get a critical sense of the underlying data set. Showing the
                            data effectively equates to showing your work for the user, but it does
                            not necessitate providing the user with what amount to false choices
                            that obfuscate the rhetorical value of the visualization in the first
                            place. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Visualizing and Publishing</head>
                        <p>The eighth step involves development of the visualization itself. To be
                            as ethical as possible, this needs to be an iterative process, beginning
                            with an alpha prototype, ending with a final visualization, and
                            including rounds of user testing with intended and unintended audiences
                            after each round of iteration. While user testing is not commonplace in
                            the digital humanities, it is a long-established practice in the allied
                            fields of computer science and visual communication design <ptr
                                target="#nielsen1993"/>
                            <ptr target="#sanders2012"/>. Such rigorous prototyping and testing
                            ensures the research mitigates harm to audiences that may result from
                            drawing associations and conclusions that are false, and that the
                            researcher could not predict. Lastly, the ninth step involves publishing
                            the visualization, the culmination of a thorough and considered ethical
                            research practice. Finally, in the interest of reproducibility and data
                            interrogation, it is vital to publish alongside the visualization its
                            underlying datasets or, in the case of lacking the requisite rights, to
                            provide ample documentation and citation of those datasets.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Feasibility of Proposed Workflow</head>
                        <p>Digital humanities teams can implement this workflow by centering their
                            activity on ethical questions around their subject area and the
                            technology used to present it. This can be accomplished using a twofold
                            approach: firstly, by familiarizing themselves with the latest research
                            in the content field and adjacent fields; secondly, by including team
                            members familiar with the entirety of the data pipeline from collection
                            to cleaning to presentation, as well as communication design principles
                            and user experience methods. User experience design is particularly
                            important for evaluating the interpretive intervention made by the
                            visualization and mitigating harm caused by the final visualization. </p>
                        <p>We recognize that the combination of skills we advocate is not the norm
                            in digital humanities projects and that it is rare for any one single
                            humanist to possess all of these skills. However, these are skills that
                            are common in several disciplines, particularly in the humanities
                            (source interrogation and intellectual framing); social sciences (data
                            collection, curation, and analysis); and communication design
                            departments (interface design and user experience). Interdisciplinary
                            collaboration in teams that contain — or consult with — humanists,
                            social scientists, and communication designers is the most feasible way
                            to implement the ethical visualization workflow. There is strong
                            interest in digital humanities collaborations in the field of
                            communication design, as evidenced by a recent special issue of <title
                                rend="italic">Visible Language</title> (see volume 49, issue 3), and
                            there are exemplary collaborations between social scientists and
                            humanists that can serve as models for such teams (see the cooperation
                            between the Digital Humanities and the Social Science D-Lab at
                            University of California, Berkeley).</p>
                        <p>Ethical data visualization is much more about priorities and planning in
                            digital projects than about increasing the amount of resources, or using
                            the latest technology. Whereas EJI’s Lynching in America had the full
                            support of Google Labs, Auut Studio’s Monroe Work Today resulted from
                            the careful consideration of a single individual working in consultation
                            with domain-area experts. Auut Studio began as a single-person
                            operation, but through proper planning, interdisciplinary collaboration,
                            and attention to historiographical implications, it was able to present
                            a more ethically minded visualization of lynching data sets.</p>
                        <p>Digital humanists need to bring their skepticism toward their source
                            material to bear on visualizations themselves, and consultation with
                            communication design faculty will illuminate the design and interaction
                            elements that need to be interrogated. The medium matters as much as the
                            content in shaping the message, and thus it is essential to understand
                            the medium in order to fully appreciate a visualization’s societal
                            intervention. In other words, as we stated at the outset of this paper,
                            the technology is not itself value-neutral.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Data visualizations are inherently rhetorical, and therefore bias-laden visual
                    artifacts that contain both explicit and implicit arguments. The implicit
                    arguments depicted in data visualizations are the net result of many seemingly
                    minor decisions about data and design from inception of a research project
                    through to final publication of the visualization. Data workflow, selected
                    visualization formats, and individual design decisions made within those formats
                    all frame and direct the possible range of interpretation, and the potential for
                    harm of any data visualization. </p>
                <p>Considering this, it is imperative that we take an ethical approach to the
                    creation and use of data visualizations. Therefore, we have suggested an ethical
                    data visualization workflow — defining, reviewing, collecting, pruning,
                    describing, surveying, pre-visualizing, visualizing, and publishing — with the
                    dual aim of minimizing harm to the subjects of our study and the audiences
                    viewing our visualization, while also maximizing the explanatory capacity and
                    effectiveness of the visualization itself. To arrive at our ethical data
                    visualization workflow, we have examined two recent digital mapping projects,
                    Racial Terror Lynchings and Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence, to demonstrate
                    the potential pitfalls of data visualization, as well as suggest ethical ways to
                    avoid such pitfalls. </p>
                <p>While EJI’s Racial Terror Lynchings is an admirable project, it nevertheless
                    presents an incomplete picture of racial lynchings in the American South in a
                    way that forecloses meaningful discussions about racism and white supremacy in
                    the American North and West, leaving out the <q>forgotten dead</q> among
                    frontier populations. By contrast, Monroe Work Today’s Map of White Supremacy
                    Mob Violence is an example of the possibilities of ethical visualization,
                    precisely because of the extended period in which the data were interrogated in
                    line with the latest scholarship in the field. Auut Studio brought a critical
                    eye to the topic at hand, acknowledging the shortcomings of the data and
                    investing the time to ultimately create a more inclusive picture of white
                    supremacist violence. </p>
                <p>Monroe Work Today’s Map of White Supremacy Mob Violence is an exemplar of ethical
                    visualization, not because it is free of two centuries of baggage and biases,
                    but because it acknowledges them, while also acknowledging the potential
                    pitfalls of the very endeavor of transforming human beings into visualized
                    historical data. Unlike TayTweets, who consumed the racist prejudices and
                    ideologies of our modern society and became an intolerable digital bigot, Monroe
                    Work Today gives real thought to the quality and veracity of the data, the ways
                    in which that data represented (and did not fully stand in for) marginalized
                    persons, and the design decisions taken in visually representing that data. In
                    so doing, it presents an accessible, nuanced and compelling account of America’s
                    sordid history of lynching those on the margins. Likewise, by following our
                    process, readers can create similarly critical and self-effacing visualizations
                    that make apparent the argument, assumptions, and inherent flaws that animate
                    their digital humanities projects. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allington2016" label="Allington et al. 2016">Allington, Daniel, et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A Political History of
                        Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books.</title> 1 May 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="becker2007" label="Becker 2007">Becker, H.S. <title rend="italic"
                        >Telling About Society</title>. University Of Chicago Press, 2007, pp.
                    167–185.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cole2000" label="Cole 2000">Cole, Joshua. <title rend="italic">The
                        Power of Large Numbers: Population, Politics, and Gender in
                        Nineteenth-Century France</title>. Cornell University Press, 2000. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barton1985" label="Barton and Barton 1985">Barton, B.F. and M.S.
                    Barton. 1985. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Rhetoric of Visuals for the Computer
                        Era</title>. <title rend="italic">Technical Writing Teacher</title>, vol.
                    12, pp. 126–45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bernard1971" label="Bernard et al. 1971">Bernard, Viola W., et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Dehumanization.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sanctions for Evil</title>, edited by Nevitt Sanford and
                    Craig Comstock, Jossey-Bass, 1971.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cairo2014" label="Cairo 2014">Cairo, A. <title rend="quotes">Ethical
                        Infographics</title>. <title rend="italic">IRE Journal</title>, vol. 37,
                    2014, pp. 25–27.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carrigan2017" label="Carrigan and Webb 2017">Carrigan, W. D., and
                    Webb, C. <title rend="italic">Forgotten Dead: Mob violence against Mexicans in
                        the United States, 1848-1928</title>. London: Oxford University Press,
                    2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="counted" label="&quot;The Counted&quot;"><title rend="quotes">The
                        Counted: People Killed by the Police in the US.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, Guardian Media Group, n.d.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J., 2011. <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly,</title> vol. 5, no. 1. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duwors1960" label="Du Wors et al. 1960">Du Wors, Richard E. et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">The <q>Mass Society</q> and <q>Community</q> Analyses
                        of the Social Present</title>. <title rend="italic">Conference on Statistics
                        1960,</title> edited by E.F. Beach and J C. Weldon. University of Toronto
                    Press, 1962.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EJI2017" label="&quot;EJI Releases New Data&quot; 2017"><title
                        rend="quotes">EJI Releases New Data on Racial Terror Lynchings Outside the
                        South.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Equal Justice Initiative</title>. Equal Justice Initiative,
                    17 June 2017, <ref
                        target="eji.org/news/eji-releases-new-data-on-racial-terror-lynchings-outside-the-south"
                        >eji.org/news/eji-releases-new-data-on-racial-terror-lynchings-outside-the-south</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallagher2011" label="Gallagher et al. 2011">Gallagher, V.J. et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Visual Wellbeing: Intersections of Rhetorical Theory
                        and Design</title>. <title rend="italic">Design Issues</title>, vol. 27, no.
                    2, 2011, pp. 27–40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harvey2005" label="Harvey et al. 2005">Harvey, F. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction: Critical GIS</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Cartographica</title>, vol. 40, no. 4, 2005, pp. 1–4.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hepworth2016" label="Hepworth 2016">Hepworth, Katherine. <title
                        rend="quotes">Big Data Visualization: Promises and Pitfalls</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Communication Design Quarterly</title>, vol. 4, no. 4,
                    2016, pp. 7-19. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huff1954" label="Huff 1954">Huff, Darrell, <title rend="italic">How to
                        Lie with Statistics</title>, New York: W. W. Norton, 1954.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu 2012">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes">Where is
                        Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by
                    Michael K. Gold. University of Minnesota Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EJI2018" label="&quot;Lynching in America&quot;"><title rend="quotes"
                        >Lynching in America: Confronting the Legacy of Racial Terror.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Equal Justice Initiative</title>. Equal Justice Initiative.
                    n.d., Web. 2 February 2018. <ref target="eji.org/reports/lynching-in-america"
                        >eji.org/reports/lynching-in-america</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lynchings" label="Lynchings by States and Counties"><title
                        rend="italic">Lynchings by States and Counties in the United States,
                        1900-1931</title>: (data from Research Department, Tuskegee Institute);
                    Cleartype County Outline Map of the United States. New York, NY: American Map
                    Company, 1931.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="katz2011" label="Katz 2011">Katz, DL. <title rend="quotes">Facing the
                        Facelessness of Public Health: What's the Public Got to Do with It?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">American Journal of Health Promotion</title>, vol. 25, no.
                    6, 2011, pp. 361-362.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knorr-cetina1981" label="Knorr-Cetina 1981">Knorr-Cetina, K.D. <title
                        rend="italic">The Manufacture of Knowledge: An Essay on the Constructivist
                        and Contextual Nature of Science</title>. Pergamon Press, 1981.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kostelnick2007" label="Kostelnick 2007">Kostelnick, C., <title
                        rend="quotes">The Visual Rhetoric of Data Displays: The Conundrum of
                        Clarity</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Professional
                        Communication</title>, vol. 50, no. 4, 2007, pp. 280–294.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TPC.2007.908725"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1109/TPC.2007.908725</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kostelnick2016" label="Kostelnick 2016">Kostelnick, C. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Re-Emergence of Emotional Appeals in Interactive Data
                        Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">Technical Communication</title>
                    63, 2016, pp. 116–135.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="monmonier1991" label="Monmonier 1991">Monmonier, M.S. <title
                        rend="italic">How to Lie with Maps</title>. University of Chicago Press:
                    1991.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="monmonier1995" label="Monmonier 1995">Monmonier, M.S. <title
                        rend="italic">Drawing the Line: Tales of maps and cartocontroversy</title>,
                    Henry Holt &amp; Co, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="monmonier2010" label="Monmonier 2010">Monmonier, Mark. <title
                        rend="italic">Rhumb Lines and Map Wars: A Social History of the Mercator
                        Projection</title>. University of Chicago Press: 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nielsen1993" label="Nielsen 1993">Nielsen, J., <title rend="quotes"
                        >Iterative user-interface design</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Computer</title>, vol. 26, no. 11, 1993, pp. 32–41.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1109/2.241424"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1109/2.241424</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramey2017" label="Ramey 2017">Ramey, RJ. 2017. Personal
                    correspondence. 13 November, 2017. Email.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rushdy2014" label="Rushdy 2014">Rushdy, A. H. A. <title rend="italic"
                        >American Lynching</title>. Yale University Press, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pfeifer2006" label="Pfeifer 2006">Pfeifer, M. J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Rough Justice: Lynching and American society, 1874-1947</title>. University
                    of Illinois Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pfeifer2013" label="Pfeifer 2013">Pfeifer, M. J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Lynching Beyond Dixie: American Mob Violence Outside the South</title>.
                    University of Illinois Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanders2012" label="Sanders and Stappers 2012">Sanders, L., and P.J.
                    Stappers. <title rend="italic">Convivial Toolbox: Generative Research for the
                        Front End of Design</title>. BIS Publishers, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="skau2015" label="Skau, Harrison, and Kosara 2015">Skau, D., L.
                    Harrison, and R. Kosara. <title rend="quotes">An Evaluation of the Impact of
                        Visual Embellishments in Bar Charts.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computer Graphics Forum</title>. 34.3, 2015, pp.
                    221-230</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tapia2003" label="Tapia and Hodgkinson 2003">Tapia, A. and H.
                    Hodgkinson. <title rend="quotes">Graphic Design in the Digital Era: The Rhetoric
                        of Hypertext</title>. <title rend="italic">Design Issues</title> 19, 2003,
                    pp. 5–24.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thatcher2016" label="Thatcher 2016">Thatcher, J., et al. Revisiting
                    critical GIS. <title rend="italic">Environment and Planning A</title> 48, 2016,
                    pp. 815–824.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0308518X15622208"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0308518X15622208</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tufte1998" label="Tufte 1998">Tufte, Edward. <title rend="italic">The
                        Visual Display of Quantitative Information</title>. Graphics Press,
                    1998.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sp2015" label="&quot;The Sentencing Project&quot;"><title
                        rend="quotes">The Facts: State-by-State Data.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Sentencing Project</title>. The Sentencing Project.
                    2015. Web. 14 March 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.sentencingproject.org/the-facts/"
                        >https://www.sentencingproject.org/the-facts/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="slovic2007" label="Slovic 2007">Slovic, P. <title rend="quotes"><q>If
                            I look at the mass I will never act</q>: Psychic numbing and
                        genocide.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Judgment and Decision Making</title>, vol. 2, 2007 pp.
                    79-95.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wainer1984" label="Wainer 1984">Wainer, H.. <title rend="quotes">How
                        to Display Data Badly.</title> The American Statistician, 38(2), 1984, pp.
                    137- 147.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wainer2013" label="Wainer 2013">Wainer, H.. <title rend="italic"
                        >Graphic Discovery: A Trout in the Milk and Other Visual Adventures</title>.
                    Princeton University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wood2009" label="Wood 2009">Wood, A. L. <title rend="italic">Lynching
                        and Spectacle: Witnessing racial violence in America, 1890-1940.</title>
                    University of North Carolina Press, 2009.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
