<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The In/Visible, In/Audible Labor of Digitizing
                    the Public Domain</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Amelia <dhq:family>Chesley</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Northwestern State University of Louisiana</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>chesleya@nsula.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Amelia Chesley currently teaches technical communication as an Assistant
                            Professor in the Department of English, Foreign Languages, and Cultural
                            Studies at Northwestern State University of Louisiana. Her research
                            meanders among topics of intellectual property, digital archives and
                            public knowledge collections, online communities, and sonic rhetorics.
                            She loves podcasts, crafting, kayaking, yoga, and recording for
                            LibriVox.org.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000425</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2019-08-01">01 August 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In this article I call for more recognition of and scholarly engagement with
                    public, volunteer digital humanities projects, using the example of LibriVox.org
                    to consider what public, sustainable, digital humanities work can look like
                    beyond the contexts of institutional sponsorship. Thousands of volunteers are
                    using LibriVox to collaboratively produce free audiobook versions of texts in
                    the US public domain. The work of finding, selecting, and preparing texts to be
                    digitized and published in audio form is complex and slow, and not all of this
                    labor is ultimately visible, valued, or rewarded. Drawing on an ethnographic
                    study of 12 years of archived discourse and documentation, I interrogate digital
                    traces of the processes by which several LibriVox versions of <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> have come into being, watching
                    for ways in which policies and infrastructure have been influenced by variously
                    visible and invisible forms of work. Making visible the intricate, unique,
                    archived experiences of the crowdsourcing community of LibriVox volunteers and
                    their tools adds to still-emerging discussions about how to value
                    extra-institutional, public, distributed digital humanities work.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>The author discusses digital humanities beyond institutional sponsorshop with the
                    example of LibriVox.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>At LibriVox.org there are eight different audiobook versions of Lucy Maud
                    Montgomery’s <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>, all created by
                    volunteers for LibriVox’s public domain audiobook collection. The most recent of
                    these versions was begun and completed in 2016 — not in response to any great
                    need for another free digital audio version of the book, but explicitly because
                    such a well-loved story was seen as an unintimidating and fun way for those less
                    familiar with LibriVox to engage and become more familiar with the community’s
                    audiobook-making processes. Another children’s classic, <title rend="italic"
                        >Little Women</title>, was also being re-recorded in its fourth version that
                    summer, and veteran volunteers like MaryAnnSpiegel<note>When referring to
                        LibriVox volunteers in this article, I employ the usernames each uses within
                        the LibriVox forums, following exactly the capitalization and other
                        formatting chosen by each user. It is common for volunteers to use an alias
                        on the forums and yet use their real names in their recordings, though some
                        use aliases for both and some use real names (or close variations of real
                        names) for both. I have added parenthetical references to individuals’
                            <soCalled>real</soCalled> names when known, if they are significantly
                        different from volunteers’ forum names. In my reference list, forum members’
                        last names are cited when known and forum names are cited otherwise.</note>,
                    who coordinated the 2016 <title rend="italic">Anne</title>, recognized the
                    popularity of these works as potentially useful gateways through which newer
                    LibriVox volunteers could learn and engage with the production processes of the
                    LibriVox audiobook project <ptr target="#spiegel2016"/>.</p>
                <p>LibriVox workflows have developed in an ad hoc manner, across multiple online and
                    offline spaces, negotiated by volunteers who were learning together how best to
                    support and steward this open digital project. Built upon the affordances
                    provided by new models of collaborative production <ptr target="#howe2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#howe2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#shirky2010"/> and the increasing availability and accessibility of
                    digital tools and platforms, the LibriVox project invites any willing volunteers
                    to join in their mission <quote rend="inline">To make all books in the public
                        domain available, for free, in audio format on the internet</quote>
                    <ptr target="#librivoxnd"/>. LibriVox productions are most often deeply
                    collaborative, with several readers recording smaller sections of a text. All
                    languages, accents, and reading styles are welcome, and anyone willing to
                    propose, manage, and complete an audiobook project is encouraged to contribute.
                    Aside from an insistence on public domain content recorded in standard,
                    accessible file formats, there are no firm rules about how volunteers perform
                    this work. LibriVox volunteers operate collaboratively, but independently,
                    without institutional sponsorship and without much official direction or
                    management beyond their own transient, global, online community of practice.
                    However, there is a need for consistency and some degree of shared policy in
                    coordinating the contributions of thousands of diverse volunteers. Volunteers
                    must find ways to reliably coordinate the labor not only of recording and
                    distributing audiobooks, but also the labor of developing, documenting, and
                    maintaining a set of <soCalled>standard,</soCalled> inviting production
                    processes, while also allowing the project to remain open, flexible, and
                    relatively convenient for current and prospective members. The dual priorities
                    of maintaining an open, inviting community while also aiming for clear,
                    accessible, and consistently high-quality recordings from all volunteers can
                    occasionally seem at odds. Each volunteer confronts and negotiates her own sense
                    of balance within that tension, and along the way, subtly reinforces or
                    undermines the current status quo within the wider project. Within such a
                    context of production, where individuals from diverse cultures are encouraged to
                    contribute as much or as little as their time and interests allow, how do
                    LibriVox volunteers (collaboratively and individually) navigate the technical,
                    sociocultural, and material contexts in which their audio recording and editing
                    work takes place?</p>
                <p>By tracing the digital publishing history of LibriVox and examining how its
                    volunteers have managed and negotiated procedures and policies for their ongoing
                    collaborative work, I begin to make visible the intricate, unique, archived
                    experiences of these volunteer digital humanists, while acknowledging that there
                    are myriad ways in which volunteers’ efforts — whether with LibriVox or any
                    other public digital humanities endeavor — can never fully be accessed or
                    quantified. In what follows, I situate LibriVox as a valuable digital humanities
                    project and argue for more scholarly recognition of and engagement with public,
                    volunteer digital humanities projects. I ask that we consider what digital
                    humanities work can and does look like outside of the constraints and
                    affordances of institutional or scholarly sponsorship.</p>
                <p>Examining LibriVox, its history, and its modes of collaboration more closely
                    allows us to begin to understand the evolving workflows of this public, open
                    digitization work and to make visible the work that has helped support thirteen
                    years of functional, productive, and sustained collaboration across cultures,
                    languages, platforms, and media. Often the work of organizing, networking,
                    planning, meta-writing, negotiating change, accommodating new members,
                    moderating disputes, and other behind-the-scenes work that is often a part of
                    complex digital humanities projects can be erased or made less visible. Such
                    foundational, behind-the-scenes work can easily blend into the shapes of larger
                    tasks that leave deeper, more obvious traces. As Star and Strauss (1999)
                    discuss, what is <quote rend="inline">counted</quote> as work may be marked by a
                        <quote rend="inline">gamut of indicators</quote> — physical, social, legal,
                    and so on, and <quote rend="inline">All along this continuum, the visibility and
                        legitimacy of work can never be taken for granted</quote>
                    <ptr target="#star1999" loc="15"/>. Impressive finished projects can easily
                    eclipse the smaller, more thinly-spread negotiations and interpersonal work
                    taken on by multiple volunteers across weeks or months or years. Circumstances
                    of material or social privilege can also very easily be overlooked, made
                    invisible by the assumptions we make about the supposedly egalitarian nature of
                    digital technology and distributed, networked communities. Only in retracing the
                    archived conversations of the LibriVox community can the extent of volunteers’
                    collaborative thinking, rethinking, and working be made more consistently
                    visible.</p>
                <p>Drawing on an ethnographic study of 12 years of archived discourse and
                    documentation, I interrogate digital traces of the processes by which several
                    LibriVox versions of <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> have come
                    into being, watching for ways in which policies and infrastructure have been
                    influenced by variously visible and invisible volunteer efforts. Recognizing the
                    value of this interpersonal, tenuously connected, volunteer-supported work
                    within the context of LibriVox will allow us to more readily appreciate — and
                    potentially support and reward — such work in other arenas. I recognize LibriVox
                    and other social spaces of production (Project Gutenberg, the Internet Archive,
                    WikiSource, or Goodreads, for example) as sites of legitimate labor, not in
                    order to claim that such labor requires monetary compensation, nor that it
                    should necessarily be granted any of the recognition we tend to assign to work
                    in a traditional sense, but in order to showcase the significance and impact of
                    such work, and to begin thinking about more inclusive and intersectional ways of
                    valuing public, amateur contributions to the digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A Global, Digital Audiobook Picnic</head>
                <p>Many recent discussions of public, crowdsourced instances of digital humanities
                    production follow institutionally-sponsored projects seeking volunteers to help
                    complete especially laborious tasks such as tagging, transcribing, or
                    proofreading <ptr target="#causer2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#manzo2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#bilansky2015"/>. In contrast to these types of projects, LibriVox
                    has always employed an entirely volunteer-driven model of production, and its
                    processes and output are much more open. Any volunteer can join the project,
                    regardless of expertise or language background, and any internet-connected
                    listener can access and use the audiobooks that volunteers produced.</p>
                <p>As a crowdsourcing endeavor without institutional sponsorship and without
                    commercial incentive, the LibriVox project falls into a model that Shirky (2010)
                    describes as neither public (the way most roads are funded), nor private (the
                    way most cars are produced), but social — or <quote rend="inline">how most
                        picnics happen</quote>
                    <ptr target="#shirky2010" loc="118"/>. In the social sector, groups or
                    communities create value among themselves, primarily for themselves or
                    likeminded others, following their own norms and guidelines without direct
                    pressure from any outside economic or political interests. Within the strict
                    legal boundaries of the US public domain, LibriVox volunteers otherwise have the
                    freedom to determine their own policies and workflows amongst themselves. Five
                    fundamental principles frame the project’s mission and practices: <list>
                        <item>Librivox is a non-commercial, non-profit and ad-free project</item>
                        <item>Librivox donates its recordings to the public domain</item>
                        <item>Librivox is powered by volunteers</item>
                        <item>Librivox maintains a loose and open structure</item>
                        <item>Librivox welcomes all volunteers from across the globe, in all
                            languages <ptr target="#librivoxnd"/></item>
                    </list>Because all LibriVox audio editions are donated back into the public
                    domain, others are free to do whatever they like with them, whether for
                    personal, educational, or commercial purposes. Thus, in the case of LibriVox,
                    value produced within the group is also shared with non-members, who are welcome
                    to share and distribute that work further.</p>
                <p>The LibriVox catalog currently includes more than 12,500 audiobooks, read in more
                    than 90 different languages.<note>This data current as of February 1, 2019. Out
                        of 12,535 total LibriVox audiobooks, 1,617 (12.9%) are in languages other
                        than English, including Hindi, Hungarian, Korean, Kurdish, Sudanese,
                        Swedish, and even Esperanto.</note> Any previously published text free of
                    copyright restrictions is eligible for inclusion; volunteers have recorded
                    novels, plays, poetry, cookbooks, textbooks, and government documents. Included
                    among these are versions of well-known stories like <title rend="italic"
                        >Beowulf</title> and <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, as well as many
                    other more obscure texts that commercial publishers would have very little
                    incentive to reproduce. Monetary incentives and financial profit are not the
                    primary values driving community-based production models — the novelty of
                    participating, the social capital or ethos gained through providing service, and
                    personal enjoyment of the activity can be equally powerful motivations. Because
                    LibriVox functions so separately from commercial frames of value and production,
                    its production model and history are particularly valuable examples of
                    distributed, decentralized, extra-institutional work.</p>
                <p>Though LibriVox volunteers, for the most part, do not act as scholars, nor as
                    paid professionals or experts, their work does count as digital preservation, as
                    humanities work, and as generous public service. The work of finding, selecting,
                    and preparing texts to be digitized and published in audio form can be complex
                    and slow. According to the needs of each project, LibriVox volunteers may
                    perform the labor of curators, copyright sleuths, digital content managers,
                    voice artists, project managers, mentors and instructors, researchers,
                    translators, audio producers, and technical writers. Not all of this volunteer
                    labor ultimately remains visible (or audible) to those who download and listen
                    to finished LibriVox audiobooks, nor is it even visible to all volunteers.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Makings of Digital Audiobooks: Past and Present and Future</head>
                <p>LibriVox will celebrate fourteen years of existence on August 10, 2019. In the
                    time since its founding, the Librivox project has grown and shifted in response
                    to new technological developments and as a result of volunteers’ changing levels
                    of engagement and literacy with regard to what LibriVox is about. As LibriVox
                    founder Hugh McGuire reflected in a 2007 blogpost, <quote rend="inline">the
                        whole thing — the system — evolved like an organism, getting more complex in
                        response to environmental challenges. More readers, more books, more
                        languages, more projects required a slow evolution of a management</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mcguire2007"/>. Audio recording practices, project management
                    practices, and digital cataloging procedures at LibriVox have evolved under the
                    influence of past practices. Community norms and standards have been shaped by
                    small, ad hoc, or makeshift decisions influenced by the material circumstances,
                    constraints, and affordances of the project’s context overall and various
                    volunteers’ contexts individually. Some of this growth and evolution is recorded
                    and visible in the archived digital artifacts of the community. Some, however,
                    is more hidden, or has been lost, ultimately making a full recovery of
                    LibriVox’s distributed history impossible.</p>
                <p>Taking an ethnographic approach to the LibriVox project <ptr
                        target="#boellstorff2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#hine2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#adams2016"/>, I have observed and participated in the processes
                    required for making free, public domain audio. Immersing myself in LibriVox
                    processes has been crucial for learning more about the experience, norms, and
                    nuances of the community. As I have observed the community and <quote
                        rend="inline">learned-by-doing</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hine2015"/>, I have also followed Catherine Adams and Terrie Lynn
                    Thompson (2016) in attending to and <quote rend="inline">interviewing</quote>
                    digital artifacts, interfaces, practices, and micropractices by <quote
                        rend="inline">listening to things, observing them in action, discerning
                        their co-constitutive influences, as well as relations with other entities
                        and beings around them</quote>
                    <ptr target="#adams2016" loc="17-18"/>. Attending to aspects of intertextuality
                    and interactivity among various LibriVox participants, online spaces, and other
                    artifacts, particularly those records gathered by the catalog database, website,
                    and LibriVox forums, has helped me to reconstitute and triangulate details from
                    the history of LibriVox’s ongoing production and documentation work.</p>
                <p>LibriVox volunteers share and manage their recording and editing work in
                    generous, flexible, and sometimes idiosyncratic ways. They adopt and adapt
                    various applications, platforms, hardware, software, and multimodal file formats
                    as needed, requesting help and offering tutorials and advice in the LibriVox
                    forums along the way. No two volunteers will have the same recording space or
                    environment, nor will they follow the same processes exactly. While many
                    volunteers use the open source recording software Audacity, others have found
                    and continue to find their own ways to contribute using other platforms, tools,
                    and processes.</p>
                <p>My research has involved clearly articulating and representing the activities of
                    LibriVox volunteers as I retrace and untangle their past and present practices.
                    Using what evidence that remains of those practices, I must <quote rend="inline"
                        >inventively reconstruct anecdotes from a variety of sources in order to
                        provide a more co-constitutive account of humans thinking, dwelling, and
                        building with and through their nonhuman surround</quote> and <quote
                        rend="inline">gather observational threads and interview snippets, then
                        carefully weave human and nonhuman storylines back together</quote>
                    <ptr target="#adams2016" loc="29"/>. Importantly, this postmodern methodology
                        <quote rend="inline">means letting a thing retain its silence</quote> even
                        <quote rend="inline">while gently coaxing it into the light, giving it time
                        and space to speak so that we might take notice</quote>
                    <ptr target="#adams2016" loc="18"/>. The iterative process of coaxing LibriVox
                    artifacts into the light has involved tracing and retracing my steps through the
                    digital archives of this idiosyncratic community, cross referencing dates and
                    events that have been partially documented across forum posts (see Figure 1),
                    podcast episodes, website updates, and catalog pages (see Figure 2).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>A screenshot of the LibriVox forum project thread for LibriVox’s first
                        audio edition of <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>
                        <ptr target="#montgomery2006a"/>.</head>
                    <figDesc>A LibriVox forum post regarding a project for making an audio edition
                        of <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>A screenshot of the LibriVox catalog page for <title rend="italic">Anne of
                            Green Gables</title>
                        <ptr target="#montgomery2006a"/></head>
                    <figDesc>A LibriVox entry for <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>
                        including a synopsis, genre, and language of the text.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The eight LibriVox versions of <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>
                    serve as useful touchstones for this article’s exploration because their
                    production has spanned a wide range of LibriVox history (2005–2016) and a range
                    of project types (collaborative, individual, and one dramatic performance).
                    Together, all eight versions include contributions from 51 individual volunteer
                    readers, coordinators, and proof listeners who are part of a broad, global
                    contingent of LibriVox members. By reviewing this range of audio production
                    cases, I begin to uncover, recover, trace, and retrace what evidence is and is
                    not left behind by volunteers as they contribute to the living archive of
                    project documentation and public digitization work of LibriVox.</p>
                <p>Table 1 organizes evidence and theories as to the structure and infrastructure of
                    each <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> project, with details
                    drawn primarily from the original project threads for each version. These
                    project threads typically include a record of the volunteers who coordinated and
                    completed each project, instructions for collaborators, links to the original
                    e-text and to audio files in progress, and a series of back-and-forth updates
                    and conversations about each version’s progress over time. LibriVox’s public
                    forums help to preserve the shared knowledge and interactions of volunteers, old
                    and new, over time.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Details from eight LibriVox versions of <title rend="italic">Anne of Green
                            Gables</title>, for comparison</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Version</cell>
                        <cell>Version Image</cell>
                        <cell>Version Details</cell>
                        <cell>Date Begun</cell>
                        <cell>Total time in production*</cell>
                        <cell>Run time (hh:mm:ss)</cell>
                        <cell>Notes</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables <ptr target="#montgomery2006a"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref></cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Collaborative; <lb/>12 readers; <lb/>1,933,797 Views;<note>These
                                totals are taken from the LibriVox catalog as hosted at archive.org
                                and are current as of February 10, 2019. The Internet Archive
                                algorithms consider a <soCalled>view</soCalled> to be any
                                interaction with any form of content in their collection; one view
                                could reflect someone’s streaming a brief clip of a short story, or
                                someone downloading an entire .zip file of a
                                31-hours-and-44-minutes-long recording of <title rend="italic"
                                    >Ulysses</title>. The most recent Internet Archive statistics
                                appear to include views from May 2008 to the present. Any engagement
                                with these audio files by alternative means — via third-party apps,
                                torrents, YouTube streams, burned CDs, and so on — is not reflected
                                in this data.</note>
                            <lb/>42 Favorites; <lb/>1 Review</cell>
                        <cell>4 December 2005, 5:48 pm</cell>
                        <cell>114 days (~3.5 months); <lb/>153 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>10:30:11</cell>
                        <cell>The first LibrIVox <q>edition</q> was completed under the direction of
                            thistlechick (Betsie Bush), who (like all volunteers at the time) was
                            brand new to the LibriVox community. Interestingly, the cover art that
                            now attends the catalog entry for this version was not created until
                            2011, by volunteer Janette Brown. This version has the most views
                            according to Internet Archive, perhaps because it has been available the
                            longest. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=319"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=319</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 2) <ptr target="#montgomery2006b"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-2/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-2/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Solo by rachelellen; <lb/>446,567 Views;<lb/>16 Favorites;<lb/> 5
                            Reviews</cell>
                        <cell>10 October, 2006, 2:52 am</cell>
                        <cell>70 days (~2.5 months); <lb/>140 forum posts </cell>
                        <cell>9:34:43</cell>
                        <cell>Rachelellen began this project with some worry that she was
                            unnecessarily duplicating the concurrently in-progress solo that would
                            become Version 4. However, she was encouraged by the community to
                            continue anyway, in line with the LibriVox principle that readers should
                            read and record what they love. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=3810"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=3810</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 3) <ptr target="#montgomery2007"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-3/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-3/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Solo by gypsygirl (Karen Savage); <lb/>1,931,307 Views; <lb/>48
                            Favorites; <lb/>5 Reviews</cell>
                        <cell>2 June 2007, 7:48 am</cell>
                        <cell>10 days; <lb/>62 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>8:37:32</cell>
                        <cell>Very little discussion attended this version. Of the eight, it boasts
                            both the shortest production time and the shortest total running time.
                            The soloist, gypsygirl, also recorded several other Anne books in the
                            series. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=8890"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=8890</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 4) <ptr target="#montgomery2008"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-4/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-4/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Solo by LibraryLady (Annie Coleman Rothenberg); <lb/>136,161 Views;
                            <lb/>4 Favorites</cell>
                        <cell>3 August 2006, 1:34 am</cell>
                        <cell>754 days (2+ years); <lb/>22 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>10:52:22</cell>
                        <cell>Though this solo was started second, Versions 2 and 3 were completed
                            sooner. Sounds of LibraryLady’s material context as a reader, such pages
                            turning, are present in this recording. Various wordings also evidence
                            the evolving LibriVox policies regarding the introductory disclaimer.
                            Cover art for this edition, like that of Version 1, was created by
                            volunteer Janette Brown, but not added to the catalog entry until 2012.
                            Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=3083"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=3083</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 5) <ptr target="#montgomery2009"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-5-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-5-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Collaborative; <lb/>11 readers; <lb/>55,641 Views; <lb/>1
                            Favorites</cell>
                        <cell>10 November 2009, 5:12 pm</cell>
                        <cell>14 days (2 weeks); <lb/>75 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>9:31:36</cell>
                        <cell>This version was created as a special Christmas project, and so
                            required a much quicker turnaround. The usual LibriVox guidelines for
                            timing and flexibility were superseded by the coordinator’s
                            requirements. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=22359"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=22359</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 6) <ptr target="#montgomery2013"/>
                            Originally: <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-5/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-5/</ref>
                            Later updated: <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-6-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-6-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Solo by Woolly Bee (Sarah Parshall); <lb/>192,349 Views</cell>
                        <cell>10 January 2013, 8:14 pm</cell>
                        <cell>202 days (~6 months); <lb/>191 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>11:06:45</cell>
                        <cell>Initially, this project was (most likely mistakenly) cataloged as
                            Version 5. A significant database overhaul took place around the time it
                            was finished in late summer 2013, and apparently that shift affected the
                            project’s metadata and final URL. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=43837"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=43837</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (version 7) (dramatic reading) <ptr
                                target="#montgomery2010"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-dramatic-reading-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-dramatic-reading-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Dramatic; <lb/>20 readers; <lb/>629,786 Views; <lb/>11
                            Favorites</cell>
                        <cell>8 December 2010, 4:48 pm</cell>
                        <cell>55 days (~2.5 months); <lb/>244 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>9:39:29</cell>
                        <cell>The major roles for this dramatic reading were pre-cast by the
                            coordinator — that is, she invited particular volunteers to take on
                            those parts before opening the project to the community as a whole <ptr
                                target="#lipshaw2010"/>
                            <ptr target="#chesley2018a"/>. This practice has been discussed within
                            LibriVox Community Podcast episodes as somewhat controversial <ptr
                                target="#daly2012"/>. Version 7 may not have originally been
                            labelled with a version number; none is included in its URL, and the
                            mismatched cataloging with 2013’s <title rend="quotes">version 6</title>
                            suggests that the parenthetical <title rend="quotes">version 7</title>
                            here may have been added during later updates. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=30001"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=30001</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Anne of Green Gables (Version 8) <ptr target="#montgomery2016"/>
                            <ref
                                target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-8-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                                >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-8-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/></cell>
                        <cell>Collaborative; <lb/>14 readers; <lb/>8,707 Views; <lb/>1
                            Favorite</cell>
                        <cell>23 March 2016, 1:03 pm</cell>
                        <cell>118 days (~4 months); <lb/>196 forum posts</cell>
                        <cell>10:20:51</cell>
                        <cell>This recording was specifically undertaken as a way of familiarizing
                            new volunteers with the ins and outs of LibriVox. Project thread: <ref
                                target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=60342"
                                >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=16&amp;t=60342</ref>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Though all eight versions, according to their catalog listings, appear to have
                    been based on the same public domain source text — one digitized for Project
                    Gutenberg by David Widger and Charles Keller in 1992 <ptr
                        target="#montgomery1992"/> — the reader for Version 4 seems to have read
                    directly from a printed and bound copy. The sounds of pages turning leave
                    audible traces in her recordings. In her case, the catalog’s link to Project
                    Gutenberg’s e-text could be a convenient shorthand, seeming to overwrite the
                    true provenance of her performance. This instance in which the true embodied
                    practice of an individual LibriVox volunteer is hidden behind a screen of
                    metadata, presumed policy, or other project management convention, is one among
                    many. Conversely, there are also examples where community policies and
                    conventions are superseded by the specific needs or constraints of a volunteers’
                    material situation. Inconsistencies are prevalent across many of the very first
                    items cataloged. Only later in LibriVox’s development were readers regularly
                    given instruction to read from a specific digital text and only that text. Even
                    still, knowing precisely which text (or in which format, browser, or type of
                    screen) an individual reader read from in every particular case would be a
                    difficult matter to ascertain.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Incarnations of Anne of Green Gables at LibriVox: In/Visible
                    Chronologies</head>
                <p>Following my survey of all eight versions, I conducted a more detailed review of
                    four particular <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> versions,
                    noting specific changes in file storage and retrieval, recording protocol for
                    all audio sections, and other behind-the-scenes elements of LibriVox work. Each
                    of these projects has left behind time-stamped traces of both the individual and
                    the collective efforts involved in transforming alphabetic texts into accessible
                    audio content. Some of these traces, in combination with others scattered around
                    the LibriVox forums, reveal particularly interesting shifts in LibriVox’s
                    collaboratively-built digital infrastructure, procedures, and policies. Some
                    traces are much less scrutable, highlighting unpredictable contrasts between
                    visible and invisible work.<list>
                        <item>The very first version (2005–2006) has left prominent traces of the
                            highly transient, decentralized nature of LibriVox’s early
                            infrastructure. Works-in-progress were temporarily hosted on third-party
                            file storage sites or donated server space.</item>
                        <item>Over the two-year period (2006-2008) during which Annie Coleman worked
                            on Version 4 of Anne of Green Gables, her solo project absorbed several
                            changes in the policies and procedures of the still-evolving LibriVox
                            community.</item>
                        <item>A multitude of voices and volunteers came together for the most
                            labor-intensive version of the text — the dramatic reading, completed in
                            2011. The individuals and voices present and not present in the project
                            thread compared to those present (and not present) in the finished
                            catalog entry for this version illustrate core LibriVox principles of
                            openness, patience, and flexibility.</item>
                        <item>Anne of Green Gables Version 6 (originally mis-cataloged as Version 5)
                            was actually completed 3 years after what is currently labeled in the
                            catalog as Version 7. Such quirks and inconsistencies in metadata and
                            content management highlight deep complexities within the catalog’s
                            database infrastructure and its management/re-management over
                            time.</item>
                    </list> Through these example cases, I observe that LibriVox’s emergent,
                    community-made procedures variously accommodate and at times resist the changing
                    expectations of the project’s volunteers and its outside audiences.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>2005–2006: Scattered Seeds of Digital Infrastructure</head>
                    <p>The enthusiastic book coordinator, thistlechick (Betsie Bush), who opened the
                        very first collaborative <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>
                        project for LibriVox had been a member for only a week when, in December of
                        2005, she began inviting contributions to this collaborative reading.
                        LibriVox was roughly four months old at this stage, and much of its
                        infrastructure had yet to be built. That month, the number of active
                        volunteers fell just short of 200, and only a dozen audiobooks had been
                        completed <ptr target="#mowatt2007"/>. Standard technical specifications for
                        audio files had not yet been finalized, and discussions about creating a
                        searchable, database-driven catalog were still slowly progressing.</p>
                    <p>LibriVox’s early growth and development into an online community and
                        eventually an extensive global collaboration align with Wenger, White, and
                        Smith’s observations about communities of practice: <quote rend="inline"
                            >Unlike the trajectory of a team that’s planned from the start,
                            communities unfold over time without a predefined ending point.
                            Communities often start tentatively, with only an initial sense of why
                            they should come together and with modest technology resources</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wenger2009" loc="540"/>. The beginnings of LibriVox were
                        tentative, but also bold. Volunteers gathered first to a simple blog, then
                        to forums, making do with whatever other digital platforms and tools they
                        found useful. Several coordinators donated their own server space as
                        temporary storage for the audio files of projects-in-process, and others
                        used third-party file transfer sites such as <title rend="italic"
                            >yousendit.com</title> or <title rend="italic">megaupload.com</title>.
                        Hyperlinks to these temporary sites of storage are still present, but
                        broken, in this and many other early LibriVox project threads. Though no
                        longer useable as paths to the works-in-progress they once were, they leave
                        traces that evidence volunteers’ generosity, savvy, and resourcefulness in
                        the early days of LibriVox. The ability and willingness to share/donate
                        personal resources (such as time and server space) and the technical savvy
                        to do so were important factors in helping LibriVox grow and settle into the
                        robust volunteer space it has ultimately become.</p>
                    <p>The practice of relying on temporary file storage, whether from third-party
                        sites or from generous volunteers with their own server space, continued for
                        several months. It wasn’t until nearly two years later when LibriVox could
                        claim its own central server space (also maintained via donation, and also
                        meant to be temporary — all finished audiobooks are hosted more permanently
                        at <title rend="italic">archive.org</title>). Even still, to some extent,
                        the transient nature of works-in-progress at LibriVox persists. Completed
                        projects at LibriVox still bear consistent marks of a transience, since even
                        the central LibriVox file storage space is continually overwritten with new
                        works-in-progress as previous works are finished and moved to their final
                        catalog spaces. Evidence of this in-between labor is not meant to last, but
                        does leave behind traces of past infrastructure (or lack thereof) and
                        infrastructural development. As the LibriVox project has become more
                        established and developed more standardized, centralized procedures, its
                        community has also become more accessible to volunteers who may lack the
                        same levels of technical expertise that early volunteers were more likely to
                        need.</p>
                    <p>As this first <title rend="italic">Anne</title> project drew to a close,
                        LibriVox volunteers had begun discussing whether it would be worthwhile to
                        enforce a <quote rend="inline">prooflistening</quote> stage for all LibriVox
                        submissions. After much debate about whether the extra effort and potential
                        for inviting criticism <ptr target="#chesley2018b"/> would prove too
                        discouraging to future volunteers, the practice was gradually adopted and
                        eventually instituted as routine. By the time the next version of <title
                            rend="italic">Anne</title> was begun, in August 2006, prooflistening had
                        become fairly standard for all LibriVox works.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2006–2008: Negotiating and Enacting LibriVox Policies</head>
                    <p>The institution of the new practice of prooflistening was not the only
                        instance of LibriVox policies changing in response to volunteers’ discussion
                        and debate. During the two years that LibaryLady (Annie Coleman Rothenberg)
                        spent gradually recording what would become Version 4 of <title
                            rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>, another small but
                        significant change was successfully argued for and implemented — one that
                        would subtly mark her solo rendition of the text.</p>
                    <p>As a crucial marker of their public domain status and their origin from
                        within the LibriVox project, all LibriVox recordings begin with an
                        introductory disclaimer and invitation to listeners: <quote rend="block"
                            >This is a LibriVox recording. All LibriVox recordings are in the public
                            domain. For more information or to volunteer, please visit
                            librivox.org.</quote> This official disclaimer has remained
                        fundamentally the same in wording and in length since the beginning of
                        LibriVox, despite occasional attempts to shorten it. During LibriVox’s
                        earliest years, readers customarily pronounced the standard disclaimer first
                        before specifying the title, author, and chapter details of the section they
                        were recording. And so it continued until in December 2006, roughly four
                        months after LibraryLady began her version of <title rend="italic">Anne of
                            Green Gables</title>, another volunteer related the following in a new
                        thread in the <title rend="quotes">Suggestions, Comments, News, &amp;
                            Discussion</title> forum at LibriVox: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block">As I'm listening to my iPod Shuffle (admittedly,
                                with no screen) with shuffling switched off, iit [sic] takes a full
                                30 seconds to find out what track I am on. It would be helpful if we
                                could say right away, <q>Chapter 30 of Mark Twain's Innocents
                                    Abroad. This is a LibriVox recording, etc., etc. ...</q> That
                                way those without screens (and there are many at the screenless
                                Shuffle level, especially in schools and school libraries) can
                                quickly know where they are. <ptr target="#sayers2006"/></quote>
                        </cit>
                    </p>
                    <p>For the sake of those without immediate visual access to the list of chapters
                        or sections on a display screen, LibriVox volunteers determined together to
                        modify the order of chapter/section numbers and the introductory disclaimer.
                        New projects, from that time forward, would no longer begin immediately with
                            <quote rend="inline">This is a LibriVox recording…</quote>, but would
                        instead first note the section or chapter number of the text being recorded.
                        Volunteer coordinators and admins adopted this policy change gradually over
                        the next months, modifying instructional documentation along the way.</p>
                    <p>Only a subtle trace of this change exists in the first few seconds of the
                        finished audio files of LibaryLady’s <title rend="italic">Anne of Green
                            Gables</title>. The first 22 chapters, recorded between August 2006 and
                        March 2007, begin directly with <quote rend="inline">This is a LibriVox
                            recording,</quote> according to the older, original LibriVox convention.
                        The very next chapter gives listeners the updated, more informative
                        introduction, with <quote rend="inline">Chapter 23 of Anne of Green
                            Gables</quote> first, and <quote rend="inline">This is a LibriVox
                            recording…</quote> next. The remaining fifteen chapters of the book all
                        follow this new pattern. The audible evidence of this collaborative decision
                        about recording protocol manifests only as a sudden, easily missed change
                        between adjacent chapters. In response to a volunteer sharing their
                        listening experience, the LibriVox community accepted and shared the
                        discursive labor of negotiating this change, of shifting their established
                        recording habits, and of updating documentation across the LibriVox
                        community to represent the change in policy.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2010–2011: Adapting <title rend="italic">Anne of Green
                        Gables</title></head>
                    <p>The planning, preparation, recording, and editing of a dramatic reading
                        entails extensive work. For the dramatic reading version of <title
                            rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title>, coordinator wildemoose
                        (Arielle Lipshaw) estimated it might take a full year to complete the
                        project. The reading would need volunteers for twenty-four distinct speaking
                        roles, including Anne herself as Narrator. In reality, several more than
                        twenty-four volunteer readers professed interest in joining this project,
                        posted claims for specific roles in the project thread. Yet not all of them
                        are ultimately credited in the catalog as collaborators.</p>
                    <p>Because LibriVox maintains a volunteer-driven, loose and open structure,
                        contributors may perform come and go from the project, dedicating as much or
                        as little effort as they wish. Volunteer LibriVox coordinators do not
                        require previous audio recording experience and do not necessarily expect
                        any lasting commitment. When sections or roles in a project are claimed but
                        not completed within a reasonable time (determined by the project’s
                        coordinators), the convention at LibriVox is to <soCalled>orphan</soCalled>
                        those sections and open them up for other volunteers to take on. Orphaned
                        sections are common; all four of these collaborative <title rend="italic"
                            >Anne of Green Gables</title> project threads contain comments about or
                        other evidence of orphaned sections.</p>
                    <p>In the case of this dramatic reading, seven volunteers, most of them brand
                        new to the LibriVox forums, arrived in the project thread to claim roles in
                        the dramatic reading. Then — for reasons that now remain largely invisible
                        and unknown — these individuals never completed their planned contributions.
                        One would-be reader for the project, AmateurOzmologist (Miriam Esther
                        Goldman) did submit two chapters’ worth of Mrs. Rachel Lynde’s lines, but
                        disappeared from the thread with no public explanation before the project’s
                        end. AmateurOzmologist’s work with this text, because it was incomplete, is
                        entirely absent from and entirely unacknowledged in the finished
                        audiobook.</p>
                    <p>Volunteers like AmateurOzmologist, who come to a project and get lost from
                        it, whose un/recorded voices or other prospective efforts may ultimately not
                        make it in to the final catalog, are still a part of LibriVox. The community
                        values their willingness to volunteer even if it is only potential, put off
                        until <quote rend="inline">someday, eventually.</quote> And ideal of loose,
                        open, volunteer-powered project means that the possibility (and apparent
                        risk) of volunteers disappearing as quickly and easily as they arrive at
                        LibriVox, of course, is unavoidable. These realities — where volunteer
                        relationships and connections are tentative, easily breakable, and often
                        lost — are part of the inviting, practical modularity of LibriVox. In
                        response, the general attitude at LibriVox is one of understanding,
                        tolerance, and patience. To tolerate so readily the apparent
                            <soCalled>failure</soCalled> of seemingly earnest volunteers may seem
                        something of a burden to the volunteers who do complete their work in good
                        time. But part of LibriVox’s loose and open structure involves making space
                        for those invisible, not-yet contributions from potential members of the
                        project. Perhaps if they are too busy this time, they will come back to
                        volunteer next year, or the year after that. Overall, volunteers have
                        responded to the project’s open flexibility with an impressive number of
                        volunteer hours, the true quantity of which is only hinted at by the
                        cumulative recorded run time of the entire LibriVox catalog.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2013: A Time-Traveling Anne and the Impact of Major Catalog
                        Upgrades</head>
                    <p>When WoollyBee (Sarah Parshall) began recording what later came to be labeled
                        as <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> Version 6, she was
                        brand new to LibriVox and especially enthusiastic about recording this
                        children’s classic with which she strongly identified. The project took her
                        about six months to complete and was cataloged in July of 2013. This date
                        places WoollyBee’s solo chronologically between Version 7 (the dramatic
                        reading completed in 2010, discussed above) and Version 8 (the most recent
                        collaborative reading, completed in 2016). The reasons for the oddly
                        anachronistic tagging of both the solo recording and the dramatic reading
                        are not fully made clear in any LibriVox records I investigated, but the
                        issue is likely tied to the major catalog update that took place during the
                        summer of 2013. That August, the final stages of an in-depth, year-long
                        overhaul of the LibriVox databases, workflow tools, and infrastructure were
                        implemented <ptr target="#librivox2012a"/>
                        <ptr target="#librivox2012b"/>. Handfuls of error reports related to this
                        crossover from old system to new were posted in the LibriVox forums during
                        the first half of August 2013, including one from Woolly Bee herself
                        concerning an apparent error with her finished <title rend="italic">Anne of
                            Green Gables</title>. Hers and most other reports during this period are
                        answered with confident encouragement from administrators that the issues
                        would be fixed as soon as the new catalog system was fully functional. The
                        website and database infrastructure behind LibriVox, in combination with the
                        distributed, ad hoc volunteer community that work within that
                        infrastructure, are complex enough that quirks and inconsistencies in
                        metadata like those noted here have likely accumulated in several other
                        corners of the project.</p>
                    <p>Reflecting on this project, WoollyBee correctly cites it as the <quote
                            rend="inline">seventh version</quote> of Anne of Green Gables. She also
                        recalls the catalog updates of 2013, and their overall impact on LibriVox,
                        positively: <cit>
                            <quote rend="block">The most notable physical change that I’ve seen
                                happen to LV during the time I have been volunteering here is
                                definitely the huge update that happened maybe 3, 4 years ago. Once
                                everything was updated there was definitely a huge learning curve,
                                but I like our new system so much more. It’s so much easier to be a
                                book coordinator now… it’s just a much better system all around.
                                    <ptr target="#chesley2018a"/></quote>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p>Once more we have an instance where volunteers’ labor — that of WoollyBee and
                        the coordinators who worked on her <title rend="italic">Anne</title> solo,
                        and that of the volunteers who guided LibriVox through the upgrades and
                        redesign process — are only visible in partial traces. WoollyBee hints at
                        the work of re-learning how to coordinate LibriVox projects in the aftermath
                        of the redesign. While a handful of forum announcements and blog posts
                        communicate some of the labor involved in the update, including planned
                        server outages, status updates, and a report of hours spent <ptr
                            target="#librivox2012a"/>
                        <ptr target="#librivox2012b"/>, the full scope of individual and collective
                        efforts to accommodate the change are not made completely transparent to the
                        public.</p>
                    <p>As this case illustrates, public digital humanities projects have the
                        potential to outgrow their tentative beginnings enough to warrant drastic
                        changes in infrastructure and procedures. Whether that change emerges from
                        within or is imposed from without, it will require flexible, patient human
                        cooperation. The work of evaluating, building, and implementing new
                        technologies and the work of accommodating fellow volunteers to that new
                        technology are both important. The agility to navigate (and help others to
                        navigate) ongoing technical and infrastructural change are crucial for
                        supporting a sustainable, persistent digital humanities project. Fitzpatrick
                        (2017) offers a comforting reminder in this vein, asserting that <quote
                            rend="inline">Real sustainability, after all, isn’t just about revenue
                            generation and cost recovery. It’s about relationships, about personal
                            and institutional commitment, about the willingness to work together
                            toward long-term means of ensuring that the platforms we build today
                            will not just survive but evolve with our technologies and the people
                            who use them</quote>
                        <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2017" loc="para 3"/>. As volunteers and their many
                        tools join and contribute to the LibriVox system, the infrastructure they
                        use will also continue to evolve.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Stewarding Technology, Stewarding Community</head>
                <p>Through all of these <title rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> projects,
                    relationships among human volunteers, digital technologies, interfaces, texts,
                    recording hardware, software, and other tools intertwine and build upon each
                    other. The time and effort volunteers donate to LibriVox, whether regularly or
                    sporadically or somewhere in between, not only supports and maintains the
                    project’s infrastructure, but becomes part of that infrastructure itself,
                    working towards reinforcing (and at times contradicting) the purposes and
                    practices that bring volunteers together.</p>
                <p>In a global, digitally-distributed volunteer community, public and accessible
                    instruction is crucial for the longevity of the project, and for attracting and
                    training new participants. LibriVox’s archived technical documentation, however
                    partial, contingent, or informally distributed among the project’s members, all
                    plays a crucial role in shaping, managing, expanding, and sustaining this
                    community of diverse and sometimes transient volunteers. Volunteers, their
                    hardware and software tools, their forum posts, and their interactions all
                    contribute to the stewardship and maintenance of LibriVox as a productive
                    project and a welcoming digital community.</p>
                <p>Recognizing the importance of what they call <quote rend="inline">technology
                        stewardship,</quote> Wenger, White, and Smith (2009) define the role of
                    technology steward as one that emerges as <quote rend="inline">a natural outcome
                        of taking care of a community that’s using technology to learn
                        together</quote>
                    <ptr target="#wenger2009" loc="831"/>. They go on add that <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">… in many cases, technology stewardship is a critical
                            part of community leadership, facilitating a community’s emergence or
                            growth. It becomes a very creative practice that evolves along with the
                            community and reflects the community’s self-design — the process by
                            which a community designs itself as a vehicle for learning, which
                            includes use of technology. <ptr target="#wenger2009" loc="854"
                            /></quote>
                    </cit>As individuals learn and build themselves into the LibriVox project, they
                    take on roles as technology stewards, contingent team leaders, just-in-time
                    facilitators, teachers, or mentors. Their various and combined efforts help the
                    project to expand and continue to <quote rend="inline">design itself</quote>
                    along the way. In some cases, as we saw with the discussion about re-ordering
                    the LibriVox disclaimer, a single person’s observation about the potential needs
                    of a group can eventually scaffold a whole new set of protocols. As volunteer
                    Cori observed in a 2012 LibriVox forum discussion, <quote rend="inline"
                        >everything starts because one person thought it was a good idea. LibriVox
                        itself, and all the processes and tasks within it</quote>
                    <ptr target="#samuel2012"/>. Even if only one volunteer notices and cares that
                    something is done to serve a small subset of the community in a new or different
                    way, their influence can spread and begin to benefit larger sections of the
                    LibriVox project, its audiences, and the world.</p>
                <p>Theorizing the sometimes inscrutable decisions and actions of the many
                    participants who contribute to LibriVox is perhaps an unusual undertaking, but
                    valuable as an avenue toward appreciating the everyday digital humanities work
                    that happens as part of our increasingly digitally-mediated lives. Of the
                    possible range of motives shared among LibriVox volunteers, founder Hugh McGuire
                    writes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">Some of us are making a stand about public,
                            non-commercial space, about public domain, about the importance of
                            efforts outside the pervasive commercial framework that dominates our
                            world. But some of us are just reading because we like it. This can be
                            political if you wish, or mean nothing more than this: we read books and
                            give the audio files away for free. Both are valid, both are important.
                                <ptr target="#mcguire2005"/></quote>
                    </cit> Whether motivated by pure enjoyment, by ideology, or by a mixture of
                    both, LibriVox volunteers are engaged in a particularly open and inclusive
                    project of cultural preservation. However, despite prevailing LibriVox policies
                    that disallow censorship, bowdlerization, and abridgement, an almost invisible
                    degree of macro-censorship is inevitable within the project, driven by what
                    volunteers have so far chosen not to read. Through the results of the choices
                    they make in selecting and producing free audiobooks, volunteers at LibriVox
                    collectively influence what kinds of human culture and knowledge are being
                    collected, digitized, preserved, consumed, and circulated by global audiences.
                    This realization echoes Griffin and Hayler’s (2018) reminder that <quote
                        rend="inline">DH tools and practices reinforce, resist, shape, and encode
                        material realities which both pre-exist, and are co-produced by
                        them.</quote> The labor practices behind LibriVox’s ever-expanding audiobook
                    catalog are not neutral, no matter how much LibriVox as a collective might
                    espouse an ideal of impartiality. As is true of much volunteer work, individuals
                    and groups who are most resource-rich, whether in material/monetary terms,
                    education or expertise, or free time, are most likely to engage in and to
                    benefit from such labor <ptr target="#musick2008"/>. Similarly, as Bourg (2018)
                    points out, the risks and benefits of participating in open projects are <quote
                        rend="inline">unevenly distributed in patterns that match existing systems
                        of oppression</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bourg2018" loc="para 51"/>. No matter now democratic or equitable
                    new digital spaces and platforms may seem, we cannot merely assume that all
                    identities or perspectives are being included. Nor can we take for granted that
                    current systems and norms are adequate for supporting and serving the needs of
                    all who might wish to be a part of public digital humanities work.</p>
                <p>Understanding the perspectives and values of the volunteers who are driving these
                    processes will require further critical attention and research. Documenting the
                    full range of motives behind all LibriVox contributions has been beyond the
                    scope of this study, but efforts to do so could add depth to further discussions
                    of public digital humanities work. Future research might also attend more
                    specifically to the reception, circulation, and wider cultural effects of
                    LibriVox audiobooks as another way of accounting for the value of the labor that
                    is producing them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>LibriVox volunteers are digitizing and preserving literature and other texts in
                    audio form in ways that afford near limitless access, re-distribution, and
                    re-use. In retracing the archived conversations of LibriVox and in
                    re-articulating some of the organization’s changes over time, I’ve begun to make
                    more visible the extent of volunteers’ collaborative intellectual, social, and
                    material work. Though their efforts do not necessarily stem from scholarly
                    interest nor have the rigor that more academic digitization projects might
                    require, LibriVox volunteers are engaged in a thoroughly public and thoroughly
                    digital project, making extensive portions of human culture more widely
                    accessible to more humans. As part of this ambitious public domain project, the
                    relatively undirected work of amateurs and volunteers can make small but
                    meaningful differences in how the world’s knowledge and information is preserved
                    and passed down across media and across time. In turn, the kinds of documented
                    culture available will influence the identities and lives of those audiences:
                    the perspectives they are exposed to, the histories they may consume or to
                    contribute to, the educational opportunities they are allowed or able to access,
                    and the creative or economic or vocational decisions they might make.</p>
                <p>As we recognize public, volunteer, crowdsourcing projects like LibriVox as
                    established, yet unique, institutions of digital publishing and public digital
                    humanities work, we also are more likely to remember that all institutions were
                    once new, contingent, and shaped by the small decisions of regular humans making
                    things happen as best they could with what was around. Recognizing the
                    digitization and re-mediation work of such digital humanities projects,
                    especially in spaces outside the typical institutions of workplaces and
                    academia, is important in context of our increasingly distributed and
                    decentralized world and the economic transformations that may attend increasing
                    globalization and ongoing technological advancement. Inviting and involving more
                    people into the processes of preserving human culture will mean that more kinds
                    of culture, more perspectives on and from those cultures, and more embodied
                    experiences from across diverse cultures will also be preserved and
                    safeguarded.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adams2016" label="Adams and Thompson 2016">Adams, C. and Thompson, T.
                    L. <title rend="italic">Researching a Posthuman World: Interviews with Digital
                        Objects</title>. Palgrave: macmillan (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bilansky2015" label="Bilansky 2015">Bilansky, A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >TypeWright: An Experiment in Participatory Curation.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> 9.4 (2015). Available at <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/4/000220/000220.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/4/000220/000220.html</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boellstorff2012" label="Boellstorff, Nardi, Pearce, and Taylor, 2012"
                    >Boellstorff, T., Nardi, B., Pearce, C. and Taylor, T.L. <title rend="italic"
                        >Ethnography in Virtual Worlds: A Handbook of Method</title>. Princeton
                    University Press (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bourg2018" label="Bourg 2018">Bourg, C. <title rend="quotes">Open as
                        in Dangerous.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feral Librarian Blog</title>, (2018, Apr. 17). Available at
                        <ref
                        target="https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2018/04/17/open-as-in-dangerous/"
                        >https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2018/04/17/open-as-in-dangerous/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="causer2012" label="Causer and Wallace 2012">Causer, T. and Wallace, V.
                        <title rend="quotes">Building A Volunteer Community: Results and Findings
                        from <title rend="italic">Transcribe Bentham</title></title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> 6.2 (2012). Available at <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/6/2/000125/000125.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/6/2/000125/000125.html</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chesley2018a" label="Chesley 2018a">Chesley, A. [plaidsicle]. LibriVox
                    Community Podcast Episode #147: Then and Now. <title rend="italic">LibriVox
                        Community Podcast</title>. Duration: 33:05. (2018, Jan. 18). At <ref
                        target="https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast"
                        >https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chesley2018b" label="Chesley 2018b">Chesley, A. A brief History of
                    Crowdsourced Digital Publishing at LibriVox.org. <title rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the Annual Computers and Writing Conference, 2016-2017. Vol.
                        1</title>. WAC Clearinghouse, (2018). Available at <ref
                        target="https://wac.colostate.edu/docs/proceedings/cw2016/chesley.pdf"
                        >https://wac.colostate.edu/docs/proceedings/cw2016/chesley.pdf</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daly2012" label="Daly 2012">Daly, D. [Algy Pug]. LibriVox Community
                    Podcast Episode #121. LibriVox Community Podcast. Duration: 1:13:11. (2012, Jan.
                    15). Available at <ref
                        target="https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast"
                        >https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2017" label="Fitzpatrick 2017">Fitzpatrick, K.
                    Sustainability. <title rend="italic">Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s blog</title>, (2017,
                    Aug 1). Available at <ref target="http://kfitz.info/sustainability/"
                        >http://kfitz.info/sustainability/</ref>, accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="griffin2018" label="Griffin and Hayler 2018">Griffin, G. and Hayler,
                    M. S. <title rend="quotes">Collaboration in Digital Humanities Research —
                        Persisting Silences.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> 12:1 (2018). Available at <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000351/000351.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000351/000351.html</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howe2006" label="Howe 2006">Howe, J. <title rend="quotes">The Rise of
                        Crowdsourcing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Wired Magazine</title>. (2006, June). Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.wired.com/2006/06/crowds/"
                        >https://www.wired.com/2006/06/crowds/</ref>, accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howe2008" label="Howe 2008">Howe, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Crowdsourcing: Why the Power of the Crowd is Driving the Future of
                        Business</title>. New York: Crown Business (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hine2015" label="Hine 2015">Hine, C. <title rend="italic">Ethnography
                        for the Internet</title>. New York, NY: Bloomsbury Academic. (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="librivoxnd" label="LibriVox, n.d.">LibriVox. <title rend="quotes"
                        >About LibriVox.</title> Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/pages/about-librivox/"
                        >https://librivox.org/pages/about-librivox/</ref>, accessed Feb. 26,
                    2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="librivox2012a" label="LibriVox 2012a">LibriVox. <title rend="quotes"
                        >LibriVox Mellon Grant — Update</title> Posted on September 25, 2012
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/2012/09/25/librivox-mellon-grant-update/"
                        >https://librivox.org/2012/09/25/librivox-mellon-grant-update/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="librivox2012b" label="LibriVox 2012b">LibriVox. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><q>Rebuild LibriVox</q>(Mellon Grant Project) Update #2</title> Posted
                    on December 12, 2012. Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/2012/12/12/rebuild-librivox-mellon-grant-project-update-2/"
                        >https://librivox.org/2012/12/12/rebuild-librivox-mellon-grant-project-update-2/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lipshaw2010" label="Lipshaw 2010">Lipshaw, A. [wildemoose]. <title
                        rend="quotes">COMPLETE: Anne of Green Gables by L.M. Montgomery</title> [Msg
                    3] Posted to <ref
                        target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=544009#p544009"
                        >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=544009#p544009</ref> (2010, Dec.
                    8), accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manzo2015" label="Manzo at al. 2015">Manzo, C., Kaufman, G.,
                    Punjasthitkul, S. and Flanagan, M. <title rend="quotes"><q>By the People, For
                            the People</q>: Assessing the Value of Crowdsourced, User-Generated
                        Metadata</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> 9.1 (2015). Available at <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/1/000204/000204.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/1/000204/000204.html</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcguire2005" label="McGuire 2005">McGuire, H. [hugh]. <title
                        rend="quotes">Complete FAQ — Everything you need to know (almost).</title>
                    [Msg 1 – 2005, Nov. 13; last updated 2015, Dec 15] Message posted to <ref
                        target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=18&amp;t=219"
                        >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=18&amp;t=219</ref>, accessed
                    Feb. 26, 2019. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcguire2007" label="McGuire 2007">McGuire, H. [hugh]<title
                        rend="quotes">Conservative vs. Progressive and Openness.</title>
                    Hughmcguire.net. (2007, Feb. 19). Available at <ref
                        target="http://hughmcguire.net/2007/02/19/conservative-vs-progressive-and-openness/"
                        >http://hughmcguire.net/2007/02/19/conservative-vs-progressive-and-openness/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery1992" label="Montgomery 1992">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [Project Gutenberg ebook].
                    Produced by David Widger and Charles Keller (1992). Retrieved from <ref
                        target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/45/45-h/45-h.htm"
                        >http://www.gutenberg.org/files/45/45-h/45-h.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2006a" label="Montgomery 2006a">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook]. Available
                    at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2006b" label="Montgomery 2006b">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 2].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-2/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-2/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2007" label="Montgomery 2007">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 3].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-3/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-3/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2008" label="Montgomery 2008">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 4].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-4/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-by-lucy-maud-montgomery-4/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2009" label="Montgomery 2009">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 5].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-5-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-5-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2010" label="Montgomery 2010">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 7].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-dramatic-reading-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-dramatic-reading-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2013" label="Montgomery 2013">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 6]
                    Available at <ref
                        target="http://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-6-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                        >http://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-version-6-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montgomery2016" label="Montgomery 2016">Montgomery, L. M. <title
                        rend="italic">Anne of Green Gables</title> [LibriVox Audiobook – Version 8].
                    Available at <ref
                        target="https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-8-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/"
                        >https://librivox.org/anne-of-green-gables-8-by-lucy-maud-montgomery/</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mowatt2007" label="Mowatt 2007">Mowatt, J. [jimmowatt]. LibriVox
                    Community Podcast Episode #27. LibriVox Community Podcast. Duration: 13:40.
                    (2007, Mar 15). Available at <ref
                        target="https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast"
                        >https://wiki.librivox.org/index.php?title=Librivox_Community_Podcast</ref>,
                    accessed Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="musick2008" label="Musick and Wilson 2008">Musick, M. and Wilson, J.
                        <title rend="italic">Volunteers: A Social Profile</title>. Indiana
                    University Press, Bloomington (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="samuel2012" label="Samuel 2012">Samuel, C. <title rend="quotes">For
                        Admins: Ideas For Promoting LibriVox.</title> [Msg 9] (2012, Apr 12). Posted
                    to <ref target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=723901#p723901"
                        >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=723901#p723901</ref>, accessed
                    Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2006" label="Sayers 2006">Sayers, D. [DSayers] <title
                        rend="quotes">Getting to the point in the opening lines</title> LibriVox
                    Forums. 3 Dec. 2006. Msg posted to <ref
                        target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=24&amp;t=4410"
                        >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?f=24&amp;t=4410</ref>, accessed
                    Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shirky2010" label="Shirky 2010">Shirky, C. <title rend="italic"
                        >Cognitive Surplus: Creativity and Generosity in a Connected Age</title>.
                    Penguin Press (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spiegel2016" label="Spiegel 2016">Spiegel, M. Post in <title
                        rend="quotes">Anne of Green Gables by LM Montgomery</title> in LibriVox
                    Forums, posted 23 March 2016, 6:17 pm. Msg posted to <ref
                        target="https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=1222957#p1222957"
                        >https://forum.librivox.org/viewtopic.php?p=1222957#p1222957</ref>, accessed
                    Feb. 26, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="star1999" label="Star and Strauss 1999">Star, S. L. and Strauss, A.
                        <title rend="quotes">Layers of Silence, Arenas of Voice: The Ecology of
                        Visible and Invisible Work.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computer Supported Cooperative Work</title> 8: 9–30 (1999).
                    Kluwer Academic Publishers.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wenger2009" label="Wenger, White, and Smith 2009">Wenger, E., White,
                    N., and Smith, J. D. <title rend="italic">Digital Habitats: Stewarding
                        Technology for Communities</title>. Portland, OR: CPsquare (2009).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
