<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!-- article title in English -->Placing Graphic
                    Design at the Intersection of Information Visualization Fields</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Yvette <dhq:family>Shen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Ohio State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>shen.1049@osu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Yvette Shen is an assistant professor at the Department of Design at Ohio
                            State University. Prior to joining OSU, she worked as an assistant
                            professor at James Madison University School of Media Arts and Design,
                            and University of Utah Department of Communication. She formerly
                            practiced web, interactive, and print design for clients such as Lenox
                            Hill, HGTV, ESPN, Saucony, Abbott, Novartis, Comcast, and numerous
                            renowned art galleries in New York City. Her current research and
                            creative work is mainly focused on information design, information and
                            data visualizations.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000406</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-01-12">12 January 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="GP" when="2018-12-18">c/e begun; need author data from OJS; Figures need
                bib and captioning; author needs to be contacted about figures in wrong format (are
                they uploaded on OJS?)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The popularity of information visualization in academia and practice brings a
                    renewed emphasis on aesthetic values and visual applications to ensure its
                    appeal to a wider audience. This paper focuses on visualization aesthetics and
                    perception by making the case for using graphic design techniques and design
                    languages to understand and create more aesthetically pleasant and functionally
                    effective information design and visualization. It uses cross-disciplinary
                    reviews of background research to demonstrate the value of graphic design
                    principles and methods in the realm of visualization education. A user-centered
                    design framework and student projects are discussed by adapting graphic design
                    elements into the visualization process. It shows that the practice of
                    developing a visualization should be executed with an understanding of graphic
                    design basics in mind, and with a balanced consideration of tangible and
                    conditional design elements, as well as how these design elements fulfill the
                    purpose of the objective, context, content, audience, and the knowledge of the
                    design outcomes. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>The author imports design principles to make information visualization more
                    pleasant and effective.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Information Visualization is defined as a set of technologies that use visual
                    computing to amplify human cognition with abstract information. The purpose of
                    visualization is to communicate complex ideas with clarity, precision, and
                    efficiency to encourage objective analysis <ptr target="#card1999"/>. Early
                    research and applications of Information Visualization (infoVis) mostly
                    originated from computer science, cartography, and statistics; the teaching
                    focus was mainly for students fluent in computer systems and technology with the
                    goal of creating innovative visualization tools <ptr target="#bertin1983"/>
                    <ptr target="#cleveland1993"/>
                    <ptr target="#tufte1997"/>. In recent years, many humanities scholars, artists,
                    designers, and news media outlets have exploited innovative visualization to
                    deliver data-oriented content. These efforts made visualization more accessible
                    to the public, and created more demand for information design and infoVis
                    classes from the education system. The popularity of infoVis also brings a
                    renewed emphasis on aesthetic values and visual applications to ensure its
                    appeal to a wider audience.</p>
                <p> In a recent collaborative class focusing on data visualization projects between
                    Computational Data Visualization students and Visual Communication Design
                    students of the Ohio State University, 36.7% of students ranked the quality of
                    communication between the two disciplines as less than or equal to 3 on a scale
                    of 1 to 5 (1 being <soCalled>impossible</soCalled> and 5 being <soCalled>nice
                        and easy</soCalled>) in a post-class survey. As expressed in student
                    comments, some reasons behind the communication gap come from different
                    problem-solving processes and the overall learning goals of each discipline.
                    Some are originated from the different perspective on visual literacy education.
                    However, there are strong connections between modern graphic design and
                    computational visualization in many aspects. The shared goal of visualization
                    and graphic design practices is the desire to pursue objectivity, rationality,
                    and clarity. Visualization as taught in science and engineering disciplines is
                    considered purely analytical and intellectual, but people’s response to visual
                    images are also visceral and emotional. Images made from data, as in
                    Computational Data Visualization courses, are no exception.</p>
                <p>More and more infoVis-related projects take a synthesis approach that involves
                    multi-disciplinary teams of experts, so being able to understand each other and
                    integrate knowledge and methods from different disciplines can also facilitate
                    the collaboration process and make the connections among the various sub-fields
                    clear to students. Therefore, infoVis researchers and practitioners also need to
                    be educated about the impact of choices in design elements and styles – which
                    are usually taught in the field of art and design. </p>
                <p>This paper focuses on visualization aesthetics and perception by making the case
                    for using graphic design techniques and design languages to understand and
                    create more aesthetically pleasant and functionally effective information design
                    and visualization. Viewpoints from different academic methodologies can often
                    benefit the development of one discipline, especially a field like infoViz that
                    has its roots in a variety of areas. In order to formulate a modularity-based
                    design approach, first the infoVis design process will be introduced to
                    understand the context of <term>Visualizing</term>. Then the foundation of
                    aesthetics of both fields – infoVis and graphic design — will be discussed, as
                    well as the visual parameters included in the two fields. How graphic design
                    elements can be adapted into the visualization process will be presented through
                    a user–centered framework and student projects. In this way, researchers and
                    practitioners who come from a variety of disciplines can understand and
                    communicate to their students how graphic design is a thread that runs through
                    all aspects of infoVis. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Process of Information Visualization</head>
                <p>The process of infoVis, like all creative design processes, is an iterative
                    cyclic system. The cycle that involves defining, research, analyzing, ideating,
                    visualizing, and evaluation are iterative, but also flexible and interconnected
                        (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The stage of
                        <term>Visualizing</term> includes a constant interplay between <term>visual
                        queries</term> and <term>visual encoding</term>. In his book <title
                        rend="italic">Visual Thinking for Design</title>, Colin Ware defined
                        <term>visual queries</term> as the acts of attention involved in visual
                    thinking, which are <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ware2008">driving eye movements and tuning our
                            pattern-finding circuits</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ware2008"/>
                    </cit>. <term>Visual encoding</term> is the mapping of information to visually
                    display elements <ptr target="#muzner2015"/>. Skilled designers will visually
                    encode the data to support the visual queries, and different encoding strategies
                    will also alter the results of visual queries. <figure>
                        <head>Information Visualization Design Process</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Aesthetics of Graphic Design and InfoVis</head>
                <p>The visual encoding tools and strategies that have been heavily researched by
                    scientists and engineers are largely focused on solving functional requirements,
                    for example, how visual encoding technologies relate to multidimensional
                    databases or how they are applied to a particular programming language or
                    software <ptr target="#bostock2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#stolte2002"/>. But less attention has been paid to the aesthetics
                    or the visual appeals of the information being presented. In recent years, there
                    have been more efforts spent on visualization methods that are both visually
                    appealing as well as technically efficient. For example, popular visualization
                    tools such as Tableau and RAWGraphs (<ref target="#figure02">Figures 2 and
                        3</ref>) both adopt modern design aesthetics that support better user
                    experience and user engagement. This is one way in which the field of graphic
                    design unifies the multi-faceted infoVis discipline. <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Tableau and RAWGraphs (Figure 3) both adopt clean and crisp aesthetics
                            in the visualization tools that the software provides. Image source:
                                <ref target="https://www.tableau.com/products/server"
                                >https://www.tableau.com/products/server</ref></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure03">
                        <head>Tableau (Figure 2) and RAWGraphs both adopt clean and crisp aesthetics
                            in the visualization tools that the software provides. Image source:
                                <ref
                                target="https://rawgraphs.io/new-release/raw-graphs-updates-with-version-1-2-0/"
                                >https://rawgraphs.io/new-release/raw-graphs-updates-with-version-1-2-0/
                            </ref></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.gif"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>The modern graphic design aesthetics, shaped by the Bauhaus School (1919-1933)
                    and the International Typographic Style (1950s), imply geometric layout, orderly
                    typography, effective use of white space, and simple color composition, foster
                    universal forms, and aim to objectify representations of cultural diversity by
                    making them appear economical and perceptually transparent <ptr
                        target="#kostelnick2004"/>. Edward Tufte, who is arguably the most
                    influential theoretician in information design and visualization, also stressed
                    the importance of “minimal and efficient” design <ptr target="#cairo2013"/>.
                    Tufte advocates the functionalism of information graphics: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#tufte2004">Data graphics should draw the
                            viewer’s attention to the sense and substance of the data, not to
                            something else</quote>
                        <ptr target="#tufte2004" loc="91"/>
                    </cit>. His notion of visual aesthetics rigidly follows minimalism and
                    anti-ornamentation for clear and elegant display. As the field of infoVis has
                    experienced a burst of popularity and growth to include various scientific and
                    computation-focused disciplines in recent years, graphic design’s involvement
                    must be reemphasized in regard to visualization content, perception, and
                    aesthetics.</p>
                <p>Graphic designers’ efforts to find the perfect balance in aesthetic and
                    functional design principles are compatible with the cognition-based approach of
                    visualization scientists. In scientific fields, infoVis is considered as
                    cognitive tools in problem solving, so the focus is on visual perception, visual
                    attention, and the pattern of information processing. Similarly, the
                    effectiveness and efficiency of content delivery was advocated by modern graphic
                    designers who championed functional and universal visual language. Graphic
                    design’s visual language can be layered onto the pattern of information
                    processing to ensure visual appeal through essential visual elements such as
                    form, layout, typography, and use of color.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Visual Parameters in Science and Design</head>
                <p>Visualization researchers such as Bertin, Cleveland, Ware, and Munzner identified
                    visual parameters as the foundation to generate well-known visualization
                    techniques. Visual parameters refer to the set of visual options that are used
                    to construct design solutions that meet a specific product requirement. This
                    visual encoding process known by the visualization scientists has a deep
                    connection with the foundational design education across art and design schools
                    around the world. The visual principles and attributes that contribute to the
                    parameters are either aligned with or responding to the design ideologies rooted
                    in Gestalt psychology and the Bauhaus school. One of the Bauhaus masters Wassily
                    Kandinsky exploited the design curriculum of studying forms and understanding
                    colors using psychology and perception (Wassily Kandinsky - Wikipedia, 2018).
                    However, regardless the shared knowledge base, there still are communication
                    gaps between visualization <emph>scientists</emph> and visualization
                        <emph>designers</emph>.</p>
                <p>The visual education for scientists starts from analyzing data semantics and
                    types. Then they encode data with marks and channels. Munzner defines graphical
                    elements as marks, and visual channels are ways to control marks’ appearances
                        <ptr target="#muzner2015"/>. Design students’ education starts from learning
                    points, lines, planes, and composition tactics. In the book <title rend="italic"
                        >Exploring the Elements of Design</title>, the authors identified two groups
                    of design elements - tangible and conditional <ptr target="#evans2013"/>s. The
                    tangible elements concern physical forms; and the conditional elements are the
                    ones only exist if the tangible element is established. Visual designers’ work
                    process pays more attention to achieving the best visual quality by actively
                    constructing different visual parameters <ptr target="#cross2007"/>. The
                    comparisons of visual parameters included in Visualization (science) and Graphic
                    Design (design) are shown in Table1. The overlapping elements demonstrate the
                    similarities of visual constructions from the two approaches.</p>
                <table xml:id="table01">
                    <head>The visual parameter comparisons in science and design with shared
                        parameters italicized.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Visualization (science)</hi><lb/>(Munzner,
                            2015)</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Graphic Design (design)</hi><lb/>(Evans &amp; Thomas,
                            2013)</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Visual Marks</cell>
                        <cell>Visual Channels</cell>
                        <cell>Design Elements (tangible)</cell>
                        <cell>Design Elements (conditional)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Points</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Size</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Space</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Size</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Lines</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Color</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Line</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Color</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Areas</cell>
                        <cell>Position</cell>
                        <cell>Texture</cell>
                        <cell>Value</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Shape</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Shape</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Volume</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Tilt</cell>
                        <cell>Type</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The shared or similar visual parameters, however, may be considered for different
                    functions and purposes between science and design. For example, the line mark in
                    science visualization is commonly seen as an element that can formulate
                    quantitative value through variation in size or position such as a bar chart or
                    line graph. But from the graphic design perspective, line is an element that can
                    be used to separate or divide information as well as to show connections and
                    links. It can indicate boundary or point out directions. Different styles of
                    lines also inherit various characteristics. Thin lines suggest delicacy and
                    convey a tranquil and elegant quality; and thick lines are often associated with
                    emphasis and strength (<ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). Gesture lines
                    may also be used to represent form and movement (<ref target="#figure05">Figure
                        5</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Different types and functions of lines</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure05">
                        <head>The visual focus shifts to motion rather than the object itself by
                            adding gesture lines</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Design Elements in InfoVis Create a User-Centered Framework</head>
                <p>InfoVis is a broad and exploratory discipline that requires a galaxy of disparate
                    tactics bind together to create functional and visually-engaging solutions.
                    Therefore, infoVis designers should not only know the practical meanings of the
                    visual parameters defined in the science field, but also understand how the
                    language of visual design can improve the aesthetic and functional quality. The
                    relationships between the concepts of form, function, and content may be obvious
                    to those with design training backgrounds, but less to the science and
                    humanities community who also create infoVis frequently in their fields <ptr
                        target="#vandemoere2011"/>.</p>
                <p> In addition to aesthetic and usability concerns, the design considerations are
                    also crucial in identifying and framing the goals of the visualization. <ref
                        target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> demonstrates a modularity approach to
                    understand design elements in the context of visualization. Modern design
                    strictly follows a user-centered approach <ptr target="#norman2002"/>. All
                    stages in the visualization process entail design thinking: the choice of data
                    set and attributes, as well as the visual encoding choice to support the visual
                    queries. How the contents are chosen, how the forms are constructed, how the
                    objective of the project is portrayed to the audiences through visual
                    representations, and how the messages can ultimately influence people’s
                    knowledge, attitudes, and behavior – the existence and choice of the design
                    elements always affect and are affected by these concerns. The connection
                    between these variables forms a dialogical approach that results in a framework
                    of the semantic components (right side) to be expressed through a particular set
                    of syntactic components (left side). Modifications of one side influence the
                    outcomes of the other. Different methods of organizing and expression can create
                    different perspectives and influence how the information is perceived. Each
                    individual component has its own purpose, yet they all rely on each other to
                    function as a unit. <figure xml:id="figure06">
                        <head>A modularity approach to demonstrate how design concerns are addressed
                            in the context of visualization</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>To better understand the correlations between the two sets of modules, the next
                    section will study some student project examples that demonstrate how design
                    elements used in information visualization and information design projects help
                    to increase the quality of form and function. The examples reflect where design
                    glossaries are introduced and fed back into the visualization problem in a
                    non-design major information design and visualization course.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Case Studies</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Line and Shape</head>
                    <p>The student project shown in <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> is based
                        on the data record of Grammy award winners. In this print-based project,
                        lines are used to perform different functions. They are used to separate
                        events on a timeline; the left or right direction separates the male and
                        female artists; and the weight variations (the strength, heaviness, or
                        darkness of a line) indicate different types of artists (a thin line
                        indicates an individual artist and a thick line indicates a group or a
                        band). Changing weights pushes the lines closer and further apart, they
                        create rhythms and dynamism in the composition. The lines and their
                        intervals also create the illusions of spatial depth that helps viewers have
                        a quick grasp of the gender distributions of Grammy winners through history.
                        The line element being considered from a graphic design perspective is able
                        to bring more meanings and visual dynamics to an otherwise unimaginative
                        regular timeline approach.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure07">
                        <head><title rend="quotes">The Grammy Gap</title> information visualization
                            poster by Emma Duncliffe (New Media &amp; Communication Technology
                            major)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure08">
                        <head><title rend="quotes">Visualizing Pain</title> — using shapes to
                            represent pain in contrast to the current pain rating tools used in most
                            American hospitals (image source: <ref
                                target="https://whyy.org/segments/reassessing-the-assessment-of-pain-how-the-numeric-scale-became-so-popular-in-health-care/"
                                >https://whyy.org/segments/reassessing-the-assessment-of-pain-how-the-numeric-scale-became-so-popular-in-health-care/</ref>).
                            Pain assessment tool research study by Sana Behnam (Design Research and
                            Development)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When lines meet to form an enclosed area, it becomes a shape. Every shape, no
                        matter how abstract it appears, carries meanings. Even the three primary
                        geometric shapes — circle, square, and triangle — convey different messages
                        to the audiences. The roundness and the continuity of a circle translate
                        completion and harmony. The equal straight lines and perfect right angles
                        make a square seem stable and formal. The sharp angles and points in
                        triangle embody active and aggressive sensations. The choice of shape is
                        critical if it is to communicate the right message to the audience. <ref
                            target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref> shows a portion of a visual pain study
                        based on research conducted for a medical pain visualization assessment
                        tool. Student used abstract shapes to metaphorically represent different
                        type and the intensity of pain. In contrast to the current popular Numeric
                        Rating Scale and the Wong–Baker Faces Pain Rating Scale, different qualities
                        of shapes add more dimensions to the scale of pain measurement. The
                        connotation of symbols is also an attempt to establish better communication
                        with the patients.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Color, Type, and Space</head>
                    <p>Colors in infoVis can help distinguish different types of information, as
                        well as reinforce the connection between groups of information. Charts and
                        diagrams in information design are often associated with color-coding.
                        Color-coding is the process of attaching a specific color to a category or
                        grouping of content to make it instantly recognizable. In the interactive
                        visualization project shown in <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>,
                        different color usage strategies are applied to two similar maps. The design
                        of choropleth maps is based on the scales of value (brightness and darkness
                        of a particular hue) change so that the audience can easily perceive the
                        pattern density. Hue contrast (blue, yellow, green) are then applied to the
                        second map in order to emphasize the comparisons of the three distinct
                        groups. Graphic designers often rely on color wheels to choose effective and
                        balanced color palette for a visual composition. The value contrast shown in
                        the first map is considered as monochromatic color relationships which
                        include variations of value in one single color. The color choice on the
                        second map shows analogous color relationships which include one color and
                        its neighboring colors on a color wheel (<ref target="#figure10">Figure
                            10</ref>). Both color combinations share a common blue hue and all are
                        closely related on a color wheel. This <soCalled>designerly</soCalled> way
                        of choosing color ensures varieties of colors to fulfil different purposes,
                        yet still represents a satisfying unity that is pleasing to the eye. <figure
                            xml:id="figure09">
                            <head>Use contrast of value and contrast of hue for different content
                                and objective. <title rend="quotes">Economic Incongruity in Columbus
                                    Ohio</title> by Rui Li, Zuanxu Gong, Yi Ling, Xiao Yue,
                                Hongliang Shi, Madison Ackerman, and Emily Datsko (collaboration
                                between Computational Data Visualization students and Visual
                                Communication Design students)</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                        </figure><figure xml:id="figure10">
                            <head>Designers use color wheels to choose visually pleasant and
                                balanced color palette. Some combination strategies are time-tested
                                for their visual effectiveness.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p>Color also inherits psychological connotations that can be used to influence
                        content. Its effect on imagery – both abstract and representational – is of
                        great concern for a given communication. The individual color applied to the
                        object or subject may influence the emotional responses in the viewer. <ref
                            target="#figure11">Figure 11</ref> shows a nutrition label redesign
                        exercise that requires students to focus on using and organizing various
                        pieces of visual information. Complementary colors are used to contrast the
                        appearances and significations of the two types of nutrition ingredients.
                        Red color evokes the sense of warning to associate with “negative”
                        ingredients; while green, the color of life, is applied to healthy
                        ingredients. <figure xml:id="figure11">
                            <head>The Nutrition label redesign exercise trains students to visually
                                depict quantifiable information while paying attention to type,
                                space, and color relationships. By Sydney Ballish (Integrated
                                Systems Engineering major)</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>The attention to typography and space are the other design considerations
                        practiced in this exercise. In infoVis the essential typographic concerns
                        are legibility and readability. Legibility refers to perception. It is the
                        ability to clearly distinguish one letter from another within a font.
                        Readability refers to comprehension. It examines how lines and paragraphs of
                        text can be easily read. The spatial relationships between letters, words,
                        and interlines, the length of the text line, the x-height of a letter form
                        and the font style are all important to readability issues <ptr
                            target="#kunz2002"/>. The layers of information in the nutrition label
                        are established through different styles and weight of the type, and how
                        space is structured within or between the visual elements.</p>
                    <p>Over the years, the Gestalt Principles have become invaluable tools for
                        designers to make sure that different visual components within a design
                        composition are well connected and coherent. Originally developed in the
                        field of psychology, Gestalt Principles are a set of laws describing how
                        humans tend to see objects by grouping similar elements, recognizing
                        patterns and simplifying complex images. Some principles are directly
                        related to information organization, such as the law of proximity. It
                        indicates how elements that are close to each other are perceived to be
                        related when compared with elements that are separate from each other. It
                        allows designers to use whitespace, for example, to build perceived
                        relationships between different elements. The label exercise demands
                        students to divide the information into different parts, then practice the
                        Gestalt Principles, and use mainly conditional design elements (see <ref
                            target="#table01">Table 1</ref>) to organize content and create
                        hierarchy based on the level of importance among the content.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion and Discussion</head>
                <p>The design projects discussed in the previous section require students to collect
                    and analyze structured or unstructured data and information, and use graphic
                    design principles and techniques to ensure the aesthetic and communication
                    qualities of the visualization. The visual choices made through graphic design
                    methods are all through logical reasoning. This essay uses cross-disciplinary
                    reviews of background research to demonstrate the value of graphic design
                    principles and methods in the realm of visualization education, without which
                    there can be a perceived lack of unifying content across the various courses or
                    disciplines that make up infoVis, especially on the part of students who take
                    those courses. It shows that the practice of developing a visualization should
                    be executed with an understanding of graphic design basics in mind, and with a
                    balanced consideration of tangible and conditional design elements, as well as
                    how these design elements fulfill the purpose of the objective, context,
                    content, audience, and the knowledge of the design outcomes. </p>
                <p> Information or Data Visualization education would benefit from looking outside
                    of the traditional science domain, and adopting educational components from the
                    visual design discipline, such as those described in this paper. In addition to
                    understanding the basic design principles, tactics commonly used in graphic
                    design education that can lead to further explorations that fall outside the
                    scope of this essay may include: analyzing best practices, employing design
                    research methods, engaging in peer critiques, involving usability testing and
                    user evaluations, and further expanding the role of infoVis to the content of
                    service design and the trends of design for social good. They will also assist
                    the discussion and justification of the visualization process in
                    cross-disciplinary team practices. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bertin1983" label="Bertin 1983">Bertin, J. (1983). <title
                        rend="italic">Semiology of Graphics.</title> Redlands, California: Esri
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bostock2011" label="Bostock et al. 2011">Bostock, M., Ogievetsky, V.,
                    &amp; Heer, J. (2011). D<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> data-driven documents.
                        <title rend="italic">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer
                        graphics</title>, 17(12), 2301-2309.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cairo2013" label="Cairo 2013">Cairo, A. (2013). <title rend="italic"
                        >The Functional Art.</title> New Riders.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="card2007" label="Card 2007">Card, S. (2007). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Information Vsiualization</title>. In A. Sears, J. A. Jacko, A. Sears,
                    &amp; J. A. Jacko (Eds.), <title rend="italic">The Human-Computer Interaction
                        Handbook: Fundamentals, Evolving Technologies, and Emerging
                        Applications</title> (p. 542). Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="card1999" label="Card et al. 1999">Card, S., Mackinlay, J. D., &amp;
                    Shneiderman, B. (1999). <title rend="italic">Readings in Information
                        Visualization: Using Vision to Think.</title> San Francisco, CA: Morgan
                    Kaufmann Publishers Inc.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cleveland1993" label="Cleveland 1993">Cleveland, W. S. (1993). <title
                        rend="italic">Visualizing Data.</title> Sumit, New Jersey: Hobart
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cross2007" label="Cross 2007">Cross, N. (2007). <title rend="italic"
                        >Designerly Ways of Knowing.</title> Basel: Birkhauser.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="evans2013" label="Evans et al. 2013">Evans, P., &amp; Thomas, M. A.
                    (2013). <title rend="italic">Exploring the Elements of Design.</title> Delmar,
                    NY: Cengage Learning.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kostelnick2004" label="Kostelnick 2004">Kostelnick, C. (2004). <title
                        rend="quotes">Melting-Pot Ideology, Modernist Aesthetics, and the Emergence
                        of Graphical Conventions: The Statistical Atlases of the United States,
                        1874-1925</title>. In C. Kostelnick, <title rend="italic">Defining Visual
                        Rehtorics</title> (pp. 215-242). Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum
                    Associates.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kunz2002" label="Kunz 2002">Kunz, W. (2002). <title rend="italic"
                        >Typography: Macro-andMicroaesthetics.</title> Sulgen: Niggli.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muzner2015" label="Muzner 2015">Munzner, T. (2015). <title
                        rend="italic">Visualization Analysis &amp; Design.</title> Boca Raton:
                    Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="norman2002" label="Norman 2002">Norman, D. (2002). <title
                        rend="italic">The Design of Everyday Things.</title> New York, New York:
                    Basic Books.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="samara2007" label="Samara 2007">Samara, T. (2007). <title
                        rend="italic">Design Elements - A Graphic Style Manual.</title> Beverly, MA:
                    Rockport.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stolte2002" label="Stolte et al. 2002">Stolte, C., Tang, D., &amp;
                    Hanrahan, P. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Polaris: A system for query, analysis,
                        and visualization of multidimensional relational databases</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                        Graphics</title>, 8(1), 52-65.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tufte1997" label="Tufte 1997">Tufte, E. R. (1997). <title
                        rend="italic">Visual Explanations.</title> Cheshire, Connecticut: Graphics
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tufte2004" label="Tufte 2004">Tufte, E. R. (2004). <title
                        rend="italic">The Visual Display of Quantitative Inforation.</title>
                    Cheshire, CT: Graphics Press LLC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vandemoere2011" label="Vande Moere and Purchase 2011">Vande Moere, A.,
                    &amp; Purchase, H. (2011). <title rend="quotes">On the Role of Design in
                        Information Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">Information
                        Visualization</title>, 356-371.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ware2008" label="Ware 2008">Ware, C. (2008). <title rend="italic"
                        >Visual Thinking for Design.</title> Morgan Kaufmann Publishers.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wikipedia2018" label="Wikipedia 2018">Wikipedia Contributors. (2018,
                    May 14). <title rend="quotes">Wassily Kandinsky</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia</title> Retrieved
                    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wassily_Kandinsky#Bauhaus_(1922%E2%80%931933)</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
