<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">DH2018: A Space to Build Bridges</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Molly <dhq:family>Nebiolo</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nebiolo.m@husky.neu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Molly Nebiolo is a doctoral candidate in the world history program at
                            Northeastern University with a B.A. in history and biology from Butler
                            University. She is interested in the relationship between epistemologies
                            of health and the construction of urban space in the early modern
                            period, with a focus on the Anglo- and French- Atlantic world during the
                            seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries. She also completed the
                            graduate certificate in digital humanities offered at Northeastern and
                            has been involved in numerous digital humanities projects for the Women
                            Writers Project and the NULab for Texts, Maps and Networks. She is a
                            2018-2020 HASTAC Scholar and a 2019-2020 Digital Humanities Fellow at
                            the American Philosophical Society. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Gregory J. <dhq:family>Palermo</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>palermo.g@husky.neu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Gregory Palermo is a PhD candidate in English at Northeastern University
                            specializing in digital rhetoric and digital humanities. His research
                            uses computational methods to transform digital humanities' citation
                            landscape, studying citation as a rhetorical practice by which fields'
                            boundaries are continually redrawn. He is currently a Managing Editor of
                                <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>. He has
                            previously served on the Administrative Team of Northeastern's Civic
                            Sustainability, Diversity, and Inclusion Advisory Council in the College
                            of Social Sciences and Humanities, as a Research Associate in
                            Northeastern University Library's Digital Scholarship Group, and as a
                            Graduate Fellow of the NULab for Texts, Maps, and Networks.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000413</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>opinion</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="jhf" when="2019-04-12"/>
            <change who="GP" when="2019">Added missing citations in introduction section, added
                bio, copyedited Gregory Palermo section.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In June 2018, the Digital Humanities annual conference (DH2018) was held in the
                    Global South for the first time. This conference report offers perspectives from
                    two graduate students who attended the conference.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A report on the DH2019 conference in Mexico City</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>DH2018: A Space to Build Bridges</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> In June 2018, the Digital Humanities annual conference (DH2018) was held in the
                    Global South for the first time. The hosts of the conference, the Red de
                    Humanidades Digitales (RedHD), La Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM)
                    and El Colegio de México (Colmex), created an event that was refreshingly
                    diverse in languages and perspectives that reflected the cultural richness of
                    the conference’s location. Its theme, <q>Puentes / Bridges</q>, emphasized a
                    reexamination of ongoing trends in archival work and academic work, with the
                    hope of moving digital humanities a step toward inclusivity, accountability, and
                    decolonization. DH2018 was the first time, as well, that the international DH
                    conference featured keynote addresses delivered by two women of color working in
                    the Global South: Janet Chávez Santiago and Schuyler K. Esprit, an indigenous
                    language activist, engaged primarily beyond the academy, and a scholar of
                    Caribbean studies, respectively. Chávez Santiago’s opening keynote addressed the
                    conference’s themes by using digital humanities to bridge the gap between the
                    documentation of modern languages and indigenous languages, particularly
                    Zapotec. She noted how <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#santiago2018">being digital means being tied
                            to an ancestral world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#santiago2018"/>
                    </cit>. This strongly depicts what most of the conference’s programming aimed to
                    address when highlighting minority-centered digital projects and decolonizing
                    digital spaces over the course of its four days (please see the conference
                    program for more details). In her closing keynote, Esprit echoed these themes,
                    talking about how digital humanists can collaborate with their communities to
                    confront global narratives about climate change, and its locally-experienced
                    effects, using methods of <quote rend="inline" source="#esprit2018"
                        >technological disobedience</quote> and community-sourced narratives <ptr
                        target="#esprit2018"/>. </p>
                <p> Other journals in the humanities have published conference reviews that attempt
                    to amalgamate the work represented at meetings in those journals’ fields. <title
                        rend="italic">ESQ</title>, for example, publishes an annual <title
                        rend="quotes">The Year in Conferences</title> feature, in which 19th-century
                    scholars of American Literature and Culture who attended the year’s meetings
                    come together to relate an overview their happenings <ptr target="#ach2018"/>.
                    In the weeks leading up to the DH2018 conference, Northeastern University
                    Professors Élika Ortega and Ryan Cordell secured funding from the NULab for
                    Texts, Maps, and Networks at Northeastern University to support a similar effort
                    for Digital Humanities Quarterly. Two graduate students were funded to attend
                    DH2018, document their experiences, and write a report under Ortega and
                    Cordell’s mentorship. [Editors’ note: DHQ welcomes proposals for reports on
                    other conferences in digital humanities; please contact the editors at
                    editors@digitalhumanities.org.] </p>
                <p> Writing as the two graduate students who attended the conference, we hope to
                    reflect on the conference’s events in order to narrate and analyze notable
                    trends in the concepts and techniques that emerged. We come from the History and
                    English departments at Northeastern University and are second-year and
                    fourth-year PhD students, respectively. Having been involved with the NULab’s
                    Graduate Certificate Program in Digital Humanities and various digital projects
                    on campus, we offer different perspectives from these standpoints in the
                    University’s digital humanities community. We engage in personal reflection and
                    evaluation, as well as journalistic reporting and synthesis to determine where
                    the field seems to be headed and where it may need improvement. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Molly Nebiolo</head>
                <p> As a historian of the early modern Atlantic world, I was constantly impressed by
                    the incorporation of Latin American and non-western cultures into the conference
                    program. No other conference that I have attended thus far in my academic career
                    was structured like this. From the mixed language panels in English and Spanish,
                    to completely non-English panels, I had the experience of being challenged with
                    my knowledge of Spanish to understand and converse in what is, for me, a second
                    language. I kept reflecting on the constant inclusivity of these panels to
                    non-Spanish speakers: the encouragement to whisper to one another for
                    translation, the motivation to speak up if something needed to be repeated or
                    reworded. These moments left me thinking back to any other conference I have
                    attended and how inclusivity of multiple languages for presenting academic work
                    had never been present at the conference or presentation level for non-English
                    speakers. It is commonly assumed that English is the only language to be used at
                    an international academic conference. DH2018 directly challenged that (all
                    presenters were encouraged to use the Translation Toolkit), humbling me as
                    someone who never had to confront this truth before. </p>
                <p> In the English language panels, the themes that repeatedly appeared were those
                    of decolonization, indigeneity, and sustainability of projects. For my own work
                    both as a historian and my work for the digital humanities program at NU, I
                    gravitated towards panels on mapping and discussing the archive as a form of
                    representation, like <title rend="quotes">Maps, Networks and Data</title>,
                        <title rend="quotes">Mapas y Territorios</title>, and <title rend="quotes"
                        >Bridging Divides, Colonial Archives</title>. My reflections on these panels
                    cover only a small segment of themes that were discussed as a whole at DH2018.
                    In one of the earlier panels I attended, <title rend="quotes">Bridging Cultures
                        through Mapping Practices: Space and Power in Asia and America</title>,
                    there was constant confrontation of the idea of creating a spatial temporal
                    narrative, one that GIS tools could help define with georeferenced layers of
                    data on a location placed over areas of geographical space. The panel covered
                    mostly spatial understandings of Shanghai and Korean geographies that underlined
                    the difficulties of defining space in a digital manner. There are discrepancies
                    in what is present on a map, how things are defined, and whether or not these
                    two rhetorics are explicit with keeping the integrity of diverse places. By
                    noting the challenges and realities of creating digital maps, Cecile Armand,
                    Christian Henriot, and Sora Kim in particular created discussion with their
                    presentations, instead of solely presenting on aesthetically pleasing maps and
                    data <ptr target="#armand2018"/>. </p>
                <p> Other mapping panels, like <title rend="quotes">Mapas y Territorios</title>,
                    continued to ask this kind of question, as well. How can a digital snapshot of a
                    place or space best represent the cultural layers, struggles, and interactions
                    of boundaries and the people who made them? How important are boundaries in the
                    construction of a digital archive around mapping? How can we make the
                    understanding of boundaries more accurate to the complicated histories that they
                    hold? These inquiries ran deep into the decolonizing panels, like <title
                        rend="quotes">Bridging Divides, Colonial Archives</title>, because there was
                    this repetitive reflection on how to be more representative of non-white
                    histories, voices and stories. </p>
                <p> The panelists over the course of the conference tried to grapple with their own
                    projects to better understand how digital humanities tools (mapping tools,
                    archive creating sites, network analyses) can be harnessed to incorporate
                    decolonized voices, particularly in <title rend="quotes">Bridging Divides,
                        Colonial Archives</title> and <title rend="quotes">Social Justice, Data
                        Curation, and Latin American &amp; Caribbean Studies</title>. As someone who
                    is routinely confronting the white history of the early Americas and struggles
                    to find a comparable indigenous perspective, I was comforted that these spaces
                    were made at DH2018 to discuss these decolonizing questions. However, the sheer
                    size of the conference created many compressed panel sessions that made it
                    difficult to digest and participate fully in such discussions. Commonly with
                    four or even five presentations condensed into an hour and a half slot, many of
                    these rich presentations felt more like flash-talks and less like a fully formed
                    action plan or set of ideas to answer the questions they raised. There were so
                    many people vying for time to present and make their voices heard that I left
                    the conference full of thought-provoking questions, than real clarity on how the
                    field could build bridges to fix the problem of the colonized archive and the
                    digitization of white narrative. </p>
                <p> There were some spaces that were able to cultivate these discusses outside of
                    the presentation spaces. On the first night, there was a lively reception after
                    the keynote speech that was a space for many introductions and discussions
                    around upcoming panels, and a similar event abutted the end of the conference
                    for last minute exchange of emails, questions, and networking. However, the
                    poster session and the mid-week fiesta were the two instances where networking
                    and conversation seemed richest. Two conference rooms were sandwiched with
                    posters and presenters, which created a labyrinth-like environment for
                    participants to weave through and absorb. I found that many of the
                        posters<note>For a full list of posters, see the conference program's
                        listings of <ref
                            target="https://www.conftool.pro/dh2018/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;abstracts=show&amp;form_session=368&amp;presentations=show"
                            >session 1 posters</ref> and <ref
                            target="https://www.conftool.pro/dh2018/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;abstracts=show&amp;form_session=402&amp;presentations=show"
                            >session 2 posters</ref>.</note> focused on early-career and early-stage
                    projects that were aiming to produce databases or markup languages for
                    underrepresented cultures and languages in the digital humanities field, like
                        <title rend="quotes">Hispanic 18th Connect</title>, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Codicological Study of pre High Tang Documents from Dunhuang: An Approach
                        using Scientific Analysis Data</title>, and <title rend="quotes"
                        >Devochdelia: el Diccionario Etimolójico de las Voces Chilenas Derivadas de
                        Lenguas Indíjenas Americanas de Rodolfo Lenz en versión digital</title> (all
                    from session 1). Another major theme was the fact that most of these
                    graduate-student led presentations strongly pointed out ways they were hoping to
                    extend and sustain their projects. In a Digital History class at Northeastern
                    University led by Ben Schmidt, we ended the course grappling with this issue of
                    sustainability of an adolescent digital humanities project on the web. How this
                    situation is addressed is a part of how the field of digital humanities
                    progresses into the future. It was great to see these conversations proliferate
                    elsewhere. The fiesta was another space in which these conversations seemed to
                    expound. Situated in the plaza of the Universidad del Claustro de Sor Juana, the
                    event reverberated with the hum of conversations about the field, the torrential
                    rain of a passing storm, toasts over tequila shots, and music from the mariachi
                    band. While the conference presentations were the backbone to DH2018, it was the
                    spaces for networking and conversation, like those of the poster session,
                    keynote reception and fiesta, that fleshed out this experience for participants. </p>
                <p> There is significance in hosting the first Global South digital humanities
                    conference in Mexico City. The clashing and blending of cultures to create a
                    stratum of various ethnicities and traditions over centuries has pushed the
                    urgency of decolonizing academic, digital perspectives at the conference. The
                    various language presentations, the emphasis of getting comfortable in these
                    uncomfortable non-English spaces, and the Mexican culture that permeated the
                    conference were necessary to make this conference as successful as it was. As a
                    historian, I appreciated the integration of the commonly marginalized voices- as
                    presenters, actors in the digital projects, and with their languages being
                    digitally standardized. As a student just entering the world of digital
                    humanities, the conference left me with hope that the field is progressing
                    quickly in these aspects. There seemed to be plenty of participants,
                    particularly those early in their careers, that will hold the annual conference
                    accountable to make these themes sustainable in the future. The crowded schedule
                    of many of the panels I sat in on did result in hurried and cramped
                    presentations. In future conferences, it would be interesting to see if the
                    conference could diversify the types of panels that are held, so there could be
                    more room for discussion during the conference itself. For example, the History
                    of Science Society’s annual conference offers a selection of one-hour long
                    discussion round-tables around midday, lunchtime talks, and evening graduate
                    student-led colloquia on field-specific pedagogy in addition to poster panels,
                    classic presentations, and keynote receptions. This allowed for more
                    opportunities for presenters to speak outside of the classic presentation style,
                    and varied the schedule for many of the attendees, as well. Overall, I found
                    DH2018 to be a promising turning point for how I understood and experienced
                    digital humanities and academic conferences. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Gregory Palermo</head>
                <p> As a digital humanist working in the US-based field of writing and rhetoric, I
                    came to DH2018’s emphasis on bridging communities with certain disciplinary
                    histories in mind. My research at the time, while writing my comprehensive exams, was on the
                    rhetoric of disciplinarity: specifically, how members of fields reshape the
                        stories<note>Chávez Santiago’s keynote highlighted a Spanish-language pun
                        that portrays storytelling as a mode of <quote rend="inline">wefting</quote>
                        about a textile’s warp, alternatively translated as <quote rend="inline"
                            >plotting</quote> (7:17).</note> they tell about themselves by whom and how
                    they cite in the same space. Both digital humanities and writing studies have long
                    traditions of using digital tools and methods for research and pedagogy, while
                    attending to their processes and ethics. The two fields, however, have remained
                    largely insulated from one another, despite their resonant work and common
                    values <ptr target="#ridolfo2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#palermo2017"/>. The exclusion of writing studies until fairly
                    recently from <soCalled>big tent DH</soCalled> has inspired some hard feelings
                    in the former, along with an accompanying impulse to draw boundaries around
                    areas of research and claim these academic <soCalled>territories</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#carter2015"/>. </p>
                <p> Since DH2018 was the first international digital humanities conference to be
                    held in the Global South, the conference’s planning materials drew particular
                    critical attention to the borders dividing and constructing geopolitical territories. This frame
                    for the conference was further amplified by its location, in Mexico City, and
                    timing, just after news broke about the separation and detention of families at
                    the US/Mexico border. As local conference organizer Isabel Galina noted in her
                    opening address, now is the time to build bridges rather than walls, and our
                    field can and should apply digital methods to impact international events.
                    Conference attendees had the opportunity to intervene in the incident as part of
                    two hackathons — held by Alex Gil and Roopika Risam and generously supported,
                    with food and time, by the HASTAC community<note>See <ref
                            target="https://www.hastac.org/blogs/danicasavonick/2018/07/08/torn-apartseparados-hackathon-hastac-meet-recap"
                            >https://www.hastac.org/blogs/danicasavonick/2018/07/08/torn-apartseparados-hackathon-hastac-meet-recap</ref>.</note>
                    — that contributed to an early version of the Separados / Torn Apart
                        project.<note>See <ref
                            target="https://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/index.html"
                            >https://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/index.html</ref>.</note> The
                    project’s initial visualization of the infrastructural and financial footprints
                    of US Immigration and Customs Enforcement was the product of volunteer<note>In
                        addition to Gil and Risam, this initial team included Manan Amed, Moacir P.
                        de Sá Pereira, Sylvia A. Fernández, Merisa Martinez, and Linda Rodriguez.
                        For more information see the project site: <ref
                            target="http://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/credits.html"
                            >http://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/credits.html</ref>.</note>
                    rapid-response prototyping, work undertaken the week or so immediately
                    preceededing the conference. The project's visualizations and accompanying
                    reflections narrate this team’s numerous rhetorical and ethical decisions: choices surrounding the
                    access, curation, and reontologization of data, as well as its representation
                    for multiple audiences and purposes. </p>
                <p> While these hackathons were not a central or initially scheduled part of DH2018,
                    I begin my discussion of the conference by mentioning them because they
                    epitomize the conference’s focus on boundary-drawing and -crossing in all its
                    forms: to quote the conference web site, of borders <quote rend="inline"
                        >cultural, technological, political, and ideological</quote>.<note>See the
                        conference site at <ref target="https://dh2018.adho.org/en/acerca-de/"
                            >https://dh2018.adho.org/en/acerca-de/</ref>.</note> The coming together
                    of project's collaborators to work on a matter of emergent concern exemplifies a
                    focus on local intervention that we increasingly value. This type of
                    intervention requires literacies that draw from multiple experiences and
                    backgrounds. Building a bridge, to invoke a term used in decolonial theory, <soCalled>enunciates</soCalled> the communities being bridged, rather than
                    obscuring their difference under a totalizing tent. The choice of
                    bridge-building by the conference organizers as a metaphor also — even more
                    importantly, to my mind — calls our attention to the practical concerns of
                    that work. If there were a single defining feature of the papers given and
                    discussions happening across DH2018’s concurrent sessions, it was a focus on how
                    academics might responsibly use digital methods to redraw boundaries. </p>
                <p> A panel on <title rend="quotes">Cultural Representation</title> in digital work
                    (PS-04) grappled with the role of researchers in serving the people with whom we
                    are collaborating or whom we are studying. Presenters on their work with Somali,
                    Haitian, Filipinx, and Latinx communities called attention to the time- and
                    labor-intensive efforts to build a rapport and trust with them, in light of the
                    context-dependent, multidirectional power differentials between the academy and
                    the public. As Anelise H. Shrout put it succinctly on the conference’s Twitter
                    backchannel, a common sentiment was that digital humanists <quote rend="inline"
                        >are beholden to the communities we work with</quote>
                    <ptr target="#shrout2018"/>. A panel on <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        Decolonizations</title> convened by Allison Margaret Bigelow emphasized a
                    need for <quote rend="inline">data sovereignty</quote> in scholarship involving
                    indigenous communities, asking who on the ground controls access to data and the
                    purposes to which it is put (PS-24). In PS-04, Mahnke noted that some data
                    should simply not be digitally accessible, a reality with which digital
                    humanists should make peace despite our culture of openness <ptr
                        target="#mahnke2018"/>. It was promising to see her draw, at a digital
                    humanities conference, from rhetoric’s body of reflective scholarship on
                    community-engaged research;<note>See, e.g., <ptr target="#cushman1998"/>.</note>
                    her discussion of her work with a Filipinx community, sustaining their stories
                    in digital spaces, signals a new generation of work that bridges rhetoric with
                    DH. </p>
                <p> Other conversations reflected on how we are beholden to our communities of
                    colleagues and students. Deb Verhoeven, in her talk about using network analysis
                    techniques to locate <q>Gender Offenders</q> in Australian digital research
                    funding networks (Panel LP-13), termed a shift in digital research from mere
                        <quote rend="inline">counting</quote> to <quote rend="inline"
                        >accountability</quote>. For Verhoeven, the value of digital (and especially
                    quantitative) methods is <quote rend="inline">diagnostic</quote>: to address and
                        <emph>change</emph> the academic landscape in front of us as we describe its
                    crises of representation and access <ptr target="#verhoeven2018"/>. Brandon T.
                    Locke, in a panel on undergraduate digital pedagogy (SP-05), broadened our usual
                    understanding of access — e.g., to platforms and infrastructures — to include
                    access to critical data literacy. Locke argued that it is not enough to make
                    data available or point students to it without also teaching them about how to
                    understand and manipulate its structures. Adding to Taylor Elise Mills’ numerous
                    and lucid recommendations for supporting undergraduate research in the classroom
                        <ptr target="#mills2018"/>, Locke related his decision to give his students
                    uncleaned data, exposing them in the classroom to the <quote rend="inline">messy
                        labor</quote> we know to go into data visualization and analysis. Locke’s
                    poster on his effort to promote <quote rend="inline">Civic Data Literacy</quote>
                    with an <quote rend="inline">Endangered Data Week</quote> joined multiple
                    posters, in the conference’s two poster sessions, on related topics, such as
                    data ontologies and linked open data (Locke). Data sustainability was a topic,
                    as well, on a panel about <title rend="quotes">Project Afterlives</title> and
                        <title rend="quotes">Research Data for Pedagogical Use</title> (PS-32).
                    Presenter Megan Finn Senseney lamented the scarcity of raw data in a field with
                    so much curated data — her pedagogical solution is to <quote rend="inline"
                        >salt</quote> the data she uses with her students <ptr target="#posner2018"
                    />. </p>
                <p> Still other conversations stressed the modes by which local interventions can
                    create larger change in the academy. Danica Savonick and Lisa Tagliaferri, as
                    part of a panel on <title rend="quotes">Sustainability and Institutions</title>
                    (SP-18), used text analysis techniques to reveal patterns in the purposes for
                    higher education that universities currently articulate in their mission
                    statements <ptr target="#savonick2018"/>; their own stated purpose was to
                    provide fodder for <quote rend="inline">advancing institutional
                        change</quote>.<note>See a Twitter thread by Aaron R. Hanlon for how
                        university mission statements could be useful for tenured faculty when
                        advocating for their contingent colleagues <ptr target="#hanlon2018"
                        />.</note> In a panel addressing Institutional Infrastructures (LP-02),
                    James W. Malazita brought science and technology studies’ understanding of
                        <quote rend="inline">knowledge structures</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                        >epistemic structures</quote>, along with Michel de Certeau’s distinction
                    between <quote rend="inline">strategies</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                        >tactics</quote>
                    <ptr target="#certeau2011" loc="xix"/>, to attend to Matthew Kirschenbaum’s
                    portrayal of <quote rend="inline">digital humanities</quote> as a <quote
                        rend="inline">tactical term</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#malazita2018"/>. A panel on <title rend="quotes">Precarious
                        Labor</title> convened by Arianna Ciula (PS-22) generated discussion on how
                    we might tactically encourage and support the scholarship of those in job roles
                    supporting others’ work — roles that universities too often impel us to
                    casualize second to a narrow of production. A particularly productive panel
                    discussion on project management in digital humanities (PS-14) covered the labor
                    and turnover of projects’ largely contingent staff; Micki Kaufman led the
                    charge, there, of providing pragmatic advice for project managers (many of whom
                    are graduate students) and those who employ them. Lisa Rhody and her team’s
                    poster on the <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Research
                        Institute</title> at CUNY offered similar infrastructural support, modeling
                    an opportunity for bringing digital humanities education to one’s home campus
                        <ptr target="#rhody2018"/>. Matthew Gold et al. were as focused on getting a
                    sense of people’s ongoing needs for their publishing platform Manifold as they
                    were with presenting its current possibilities <ptr target="#gold2018"/>. Paige
                    C. Morgan reminded us, however, that unbridled openness is not always a virtue
                    within the academy either, drawing attention to the work that goes into data
                    curation and from which others benefit; she conspicuously supports scholars,
                    especially in precarious positions, who choose to keep their datasets initially
                    private while working on them, in order to avoid being digital humanities’
                    version of <soCalled>scooped</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#morgan2018"/>. </p>
                <p> Counterpoints like these surfaced an ongoing tension in digital humanities
                    around questions of openness and access: between the productive opportunities
                    that access can bring and our recognition of the differential impact of that
                    access on others. This tension is further complicated when the productive
                    opportunity is, in fact, an opportunity for bridge-building. For example, Jin
                    Gao offered to share her subtanital dataset when presenting on her team’s work
                    using analyses of citation and social networks for broadly <title rend="quotes"
                        >Visualizing the DH Community</title> (LP-20; Gao et al. 2018). Others
                    present at that panel, including Ciula, pointed out that this body of literature
                    from journals published primarily in English represented only a subset of the
                    community <ptr target="#ciula2018"/>. Panel presenter Fabio Ciotti pointed to
                    Domenico Fiormonte’s work <ptr target="#fiormonte2017"/> on the geopolitics of
                    knowledge in digital humanities, using it to critique the North
                    American-centrism of the field’s received disciplinary historiography <ptr
                        target="#ciotti2018"/>. Open data, here, could be used in our continual
                    efforts de-center English-speaking digital humanities, as long as we attend to
                    whose prerogative it is to assemble, use, and share the data. </p>
                <p> The disproportionate space, especially digital, afforded to English-speaking
                    conference attendees is one that Ernesto Priego quantified in his exploratory
                    analysis of DH2018 tweets <ptr target="#priego2018"/>.<note>Since it is
                        substantially more difficult and expensive to query the historical Twitter
                        API than collecting tweets at their moment of publication, Priego has
                        promised to publish the dataset he collected once he has anonymized
                        it.</note> Some live tweeters devoted their efforts to translating panel
                    presentations, in addition to providing the synthesis and talkback common to
                    digital humanities conferences (see Ross, et al.). This digital intervention
                    complemented the in-person <soCalled>whisper[ed]</soCalled> translation that
                    Molly Nebiolo has noted above among panel attendees. It constituted an effort to
                    somewhat temper the dominance of English in the conference’s archival
                        record,<note>One can access DH2018’s twitter backchannel by searching
                        Twitter for “#DH2018” along with the hashtag of a conference panel (e.g.,
                        #LP20).</note> especially for members of the digital humanities community
                    who could not make it physically to the conference. The ACH bolstered the
                    existing, remotely organized initiatives to facilitate conference attendance:
                    adding to ADHO’s graduate student travel bursaries so more young scholars to
                    travel to experience the conference first-hand, while offering formalized
                    mentorship programs like the Newcomer’s Dinners that pair conference
                        <soCalled>veterans</soCalled> with <soCalled>newbies</soCalled>. That said,
                    we can continue to use our digital expertises to pluralize the conference’s
                    digital spaces as well as its physical ones — spaces, like this conference
                    review genre, that I hope will provide the means for a more inclusive future for
                    the conference and the field. </p>
            </div>



        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hanlon2018" label="Hanlon 2018">Hanlon, Aaron. @AaronRHanlon. “3)
                    Bring out your university’s mission statement and US News write-up. Ask why the
                    people on the front lines of achieving those lofty ambitions are treated as
                    disposable or undeserving of benefits and salary.” Twitter, 11 Sep. 2018, 3:38
                    a.m., <ref target="https://twitter.com/AaronRHanlon/status/1039417894684319745"
                        >https://twitter.com/AaronRHanlon/status/1039417894684319745</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ach2018" label="Ach et al. 2018">Ach, Jada, et al. "The Year in
                    Conferences—2017." <title rend="italic">ESQ: A Journal of Nineteenth-Century
                        American Literature and Culture</title>, vol. 64 no. 1, 2018, pp. 133-197.
                    doi:10.1353/esq.2018.0003</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shrout2018" label="Shrout 2018">Shrout, Anelise. @AneliseHShrout.
                    “Another #DH2018 theme is the obligation of researchers to the people they
                    study/work with/are supported by. We are beholden to the communities we work
                    with. #DH2018.” Twitter, 28 Jun. 2018, 5:50 p.m., <ref
                        target="https://twitter.com/AneliseHShrout/status/1012455596359061504"
                        >https://twitter.com/AneliseHShrout/status/1012455596359061504</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ciula2018" label="Ciula 2018">Ciula, Arianna. @ariciula. “It's great
                    but let's remember that's one DH landscape pls - i.e. the one represented by
                    those selected 3 journals in English #DH2018 #LP20.” Twitter, 29 Jun. 2018, 3:47
                    p.m., <ref target="https://twitter.com/ariciula/status/1012784706109177856"
                        >https://twitter.com/ariciula/status/1012784706109177856</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="armand2018" label="Armand et al. 2018">Armand, Cecile, Henriot,
                    Christian, and Sora Kim. “Bridging Cultures Through Mapping Practices: Space and
                    Power in Asia and America.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 27 June
                    2018. Conference Presentation. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carter2015" label="Carter et al. 2015">Carter, Shannon, et al. “Beyond
                    Territorial Disputes: Toward a ‘Disciplined Interdisciplinarity’ in the Digital
                    Humanities.” <title rend="italic">Rhetoric and the Digital Humanities</title>,
                    edited by Jim Ridolfo and William Hart-Davidson, University of Chicago Press,
                    2015, pp. 33–48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="certeau2011" label="Certeau 2011">Certeau, Michel de. The Practice of
                    Everyday Life. 1984. Translated by Steven F. Rendall, 3 edition, University of
                    California Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ciotti2018" label="Ciotti2018">Ciotti, Fabio. “Dall’Informatica
                    umanistica alle Digital Humanities. Per una storia concettuale delle DH in
                    Italia.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 29 Jun. 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cushman1998" label="Cushman and Monberg 1998">Cushman, Ellen, and
                    Terese Guinsatao Monberg. “Re-Centering Authority: Social Reflexivity and
                    Re-Positioning in Composition Research.” <title rend="italic">Under
                        Construction: Working at the Intersections of Composition Theory, Research,
                        and Practice</title>, edited by Christine Farris and Chris M. Anson, Utah
                    State University Press, 1998. doi:10.2307/j.ctt46nrqf.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="esprit2018" label="Esprit 2018">Esprit, Schuyler K. “Ponencia de
                    clausura: Experimentación Digital, Ciudadanía Valiente y Futurismo Caribeño /
                    Closing Keynote: Digital Experimentation, Courageous Citizenship and Carribean
                    Futurism.” DH 2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 26 Jun. 2018. Keynote
                    Address. YouTube, ElClaustro TV, 1 Aug. 2018, <ref
                        target="https://youtu.be/K812bBfBUAI"
                    >https://youtu.be/K812bBfBUAI</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2017" label="Fiormonte 2017">Fiormonte, Domenico. “Digital
                    Humanities and the Geopolitics of Knowledge.” <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Studies/Le Champ Numérique</title>, vol. 7, no. 1, Oct. 2017. <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalstudies.org">http://www.digitalstudies.org</ref>,
                    doi:10.16995/dscn.274.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gao2018" label="Gao et al. 2018">Gao, Jin et al. “Visualising the
                    Digital Humanities Community: A Comparison Study Between Citation Network and
                    Social Network.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 29 Jun. 2018.
                    Conference Presentation. <ref
                        target="https://dh2018.adho.org/visualising-the-digital-humanities-community-a-comparison-study-between-citation-network-and-social-network/"
                        >https://dh2018.adho.org/visualising-the-digital-humanities-community-a-comparison-study-between-citation-network-and-social-network/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2018" label="Gold et al. 2018">Gold, Matthew, et al. “Manifold
                    Scholarship: Hybrid Publishing in a Print/Digital Era.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria
                    Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference Poster.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2012" label="Kirschenbaum 2012">Kirschenbaum, Matthew.
                    “Digital Humanities As/Is a Tactical Term.” <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew K. Gold, University Of
                    Minnesota Press, 2012, pp. 415–28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="locke2018a" label="Locke 2018a">Locke, Brandon T. “Critical Data
                    Literacy in the Humanities Classroom.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico
                    City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="locke2018b" label="Locke 2018b">Locke, Brandon T. “Endangered Data
                    Week: Digital Humanities and Civic Data Literacy.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria
                    Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference Poster.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita2018" label="Malazita, 2018">Malazita, James W. “Epistemic
                    Infrastructures: Digital Humanities in/as Instrumentalist Context.”DH2018.
                    Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference
                    Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mills2018" label="Mills 2018">Mills, Taylor E. “Next Generation
                    Digital humanities: A Response to the Need for Empowering Undergraduate
                    Researchers.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018.
                    Conference Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2018" label="Posner 2018">Posner, Miriam. @miriamkp. “One
                    solution: “salting” datasets so they have inconsistencies (I’ve done this too!)
                    #DH2018 #DH_PS32.” Twitter, 29 Jun. 2018, 5:57 p.m., <ref
                        target="https://twitter.com/miriamkp/status/1012817265081880578"
                        >https://twitter.com/miriamkp/status/1012817265081880578</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="morgan2018" label="Morgan 2018">Morgan, Paige. @paigecmorgan. “For
                    what it's worth, I understand people wanting to work with other folks' datasets,
                    but I also fully support people, esp. grad students &amp; other folks in
                    precarious positions, hanging on to their data for a while to work with it
                    before sharing it. #DH2018.” Twitter, 29 Jun. 2018, 3:54 p.m., <ref
                        target="https://twitter.com/paigecmorgan/status/1012786393205141504"
                        >https://twitter.com/paigecmorgan/status/1012786393205141504</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="palermo2017" label="Palermo 2017">Palermo, Gregory. “Transforming
                    Text: Four Valences of a Digital Humanities Informed Writing Analytics.” <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Writing Analytics</title>, vol. 1, Sept. 2017. <ref
                        target="https://journals.colostate.edu/analytics/article/view/135"
                        >https://journals.colostate.edu/analytics/article/view/135</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="priego2018" label="Priego 2018">Priego, Ernesto. “Tweets per user_lang
                    in a #DH2018 archive.” Everything is Connected. June 30, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://epriego.blog/2018/06/30/tweets-per-user_lang-in-a-dh018-archive/"
                        >https://epriego.blog/2018/06/30/tweets-per-user_lang-in-a-dh018-archive/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rhody2018" label="Rhody et al. 2018">Rhody, Lisa, et al. “Expanding
                    Communities of Practice: The Digital Humanities Research Institute Model.”
                    DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference
                    Poster.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ridolfo2015" label="Ridolfo and Hart-Davidson 2015">Ridolfo, Jim, and
                    William Hart-Davidson, eds. “Introduction.” <title rend="italic">Rhetoric and
                        the Digital Humanities</title>. University of Chicago Press, 2015, pp.
                    1-12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2011" label="Ross et al. 2011">Ross, Claire, et al. "Enabled
                    backchannel: Conference Twitter use by digital humanists." <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Documentation</title> 67.2 (2011): 214-237.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="santiago2018" label="Santiago 2018">Santiago, Janet Chávez. “Tramando
                    La Palabra / Weaving the World.” DH 2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 26
                    Jun. 2018. Keynote Address. YouTube, ElClaustro TV, 1 Aug. 2018, <ref
                        target="https://youtu.be/mQzyDlTB070"
                    >https://youtu.be/mQzyDlTB070</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="savonick2018" label="Savonic and Tagliaferri 2018">Savonick, Danica
                    and Lisa Tagliaferri. “The Purpose of Education: A Large-Scale Text Analysis of
                    University Mission Statements.” DH2018. Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 29
                    Jun. 2018. Conference Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="verhoeven2018" label="Verhoeven et al. 2018">Verhoeven, Deb, et al.
                    “Solving the Problem of the ‘Gender Offenders’: Using Criminal Network Analysis
                    to Optimize Openness in Male Dominated Collaborative Networks.” DH2018. Sheraton
                    Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 28 Jun. 2018. Conference Presentation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mahnke2018" label="Mahnke 2018">Mahnke, Stephanie. “The Collective in
                    the Individual: Digital Collaboration and the Filipinx Community.” DH2018.
                    Sheraton Maria Isabel, Mexico City, 27 Jun. 2018. Conference
                    Presentation.</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
