<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Computational art Explorations of Linguistic
               Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s
                  <title rend="italic">Automatype</title><ptr target="#howe201216a"/> and <title
                  rend="italic">Radical of the Vertical Heart <foreign xml:lang="zh"
                  >忄</foreign></title></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>John <dhq:family>Cayley</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5219-1537</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Brown University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>john_cayley@brown.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>John Cayley is a poet, writer, theorist, and maker of language art in networked
                     and programmable media. His poetry, translations, and adaptations were first
                     book published as Ink Bamboo in 1996. In the meantime, he has explored language
                     art in many forms including dynamic and ambient poetry, text generation,
                     transliteral morphing, aestheticized vectors of reading, and transactive
                     synthetic language. One of his more recent works is a skill, <ref
                        target="https://www.amazon.com/Digital-Language-Arts-The-Listeners/dp/B019R2YB7Y"
                        >The Listeners</ref>, for a well-known digital assistant. He now seeks to
                     compose as much for reading in aurality as in visuality, and investigates the
                     ontology of language in the context of philosophically informed practice and
                     research. Professor of Literary Arts at Brown University, Cayley co-directs a
                     graduate track in Digital and Cross-disciplinary language art. Selected essays
                     are published in <title rend="italic">Grammalepsy</title>
                     <ptr target="#cayley2018b"/>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000705</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000705/000705.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>A code-critical close reading of two related works by Daniel C. Howe. The artist's
                  <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> is an installation that visualizes and
               sonifies minimal-distance paths between English words and thus explores a possibility
               space that is relatively familiar to western readers, not only readers of English but
               also readers of any language which uses Latin letters to compose the orthographic
               word-level elements of its writing system <ptr target="#howe201216a"/>. In Radical of
               the Vertical Heart <foreign xml:lang="zh">忄</foreign> RotVH) Howe engages with
               commensurate explorations in certain possibility spaces of the Chinese writing system
               and of the language’s lexicon. Translinguistically these spaces and, as it were,
               orthographic architectures, are structured in radically different ways. A comparative
               close reading of the two works will bring us into productive discursive relationship
               not only with distinct and code-critically significant programming strategies, but
               also with under-appreciated comparative linguistic concepts having implications for
               the theory of writing systems, of text, and of language as such. Throughout,
               questions concerning the aestheticization of this kind of computational exploration
               and visualization may also be addressed. His website is <ref
                  target="http://programmatology.com">programmatology.com</ref>.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>A code-critical close reading of two works by Daniel C. Howe.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <p>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. <title
                  rend="italic">Automatype</title>, 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s
               description, <quote rend="inline">a networked installation composed of analog TV
                  monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of
                  aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association.
                  The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of
                  substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next,
                  deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases,
                  letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</quote><ptr target="#howe201216a"
               /> The algorithm running on each of the usually nine) displays in an <title
                  rend="italic">Automatype</title> installation is the same, and close reading here
               effectively focuses on this constituent of the work. <title rend="italic">Radical of
                  the Vertical Heart <foreign xml:lang="zh">忄</foreign></title>, 2019-21, the most
               recent work in what Howe considers a series, <quote rend="block">searches the Chinese
                  lexicon by repeatedly making minimal changes stroke-by-stroke) to the
                  sub-components of characters, in order to arrive at a new word. Rather than
                  evaluating letters, as in alphabetic machines, this logographic [sic] reader
                  analyses the radicals, components and strokes of characters. When the machine
                  lands on sensitive words, such as those disallowed by China’s Great Firewall or
                  those now illegal in Hong Kong), a break occurs and the machine jumps from
                  traditional [Chinese script forms] to simplified.</quote>
               <ptr target="#howe201921"/> As a critical feature of <title rend="italic"
                  >RotVH,</title> this is aligned with other work by Howe, often engaged with
               important problems and structures of our predominant digital culture – surveillance,
               security, power asymmetries, freedom of expression, etc. This essay touches on these
               matters, particularly insofar as they are addressed by algorithm, data curation, and
               data structuring, and also comparatively, insofar as they are drawn out by and
               critiqued in this work’s remarkable translinguistic and transcultural contexts. But
               for more extensive discussion of the digital politics of Howe’s work, and its
               aestheticization, the reader is referred to this other work itself.</p>
            <p>Both these works have been presented to their readers and audiences as examples of
               electronic literature, often sited in necessarily sculptural gallery
                  installation.<note> Daniel C. Howe, <title rend="italic">Automatype,</title>
                  2012-16; <title rend="italic">Radical of the Vertical Heart <foreign xml:lang="zh"
                        >忄</foreign></title>, 2019-21. Both works are quite extensively documented
                  on the artist’s website with landing pages for each as follows: <title
                     rend="italic">Automatype</title>, <ref
                     target="https://rednoise.org/daniel/automatype"
                     >https://rednoise.org/daniel/automatype</ref>; and <title rend="italic">Radical
                     of the Vertical Heart <foreign xml:lang="zh">忄</foreign></title> henceforth
                     <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>), <ref
                     target="https://rednoise.org/daniel/radicaloftheverticalheart"
                     >https://rednoise.org/daniel/radicaloftheverticalheart</ref>, both accessed
                  February 27, 2022). Live behavior of the basic, non-installation, versions of
                  these works are linked from these pages and the reader is invited to consult these
                  online. There is an entry for <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> in the
                     <title rend="italic">ELMCIP Knowledgebase</title> at <ptr
                     target="https://elmcip.net/node/4001"/>, and <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>
                  will be included in the forthcoming projected for 2022) <title rend="italic"
                     >Electronic Literature Collection 4</title>, see
                  https://collection.eliterature.org. I have provided separate bibliographic entries
                  for the code repositories for these two works, publicly available on GitHub,
                     <title rend="italic">Automatype [Code]</title>; <title rend="italic">Radical of
                     the Vertical Heart 忄[Code]</title>.</note> They are simultaneously examples of
               computational art and, as such, they are afforded the potential for re-presentation
               in other forms, particularly distinct graphic and audiovisual manifestations on
               computer monitors. The code or software of these works is at the core of what they
               are, artifactually.<note> This essay is not so much concerned with actually quoted
                  code or code <q>style.</q> The code is addressed, critically, with respect to the
                  underlying algorithms which are, for the most part, <q>paraphrased</q> from the
                  code itself, or re-expressed in what might be more accurately referred to as
                  pseudocode. Nonetheless the code repositories have not only been reviewed by the
                  author; he has also <q>cloned</q> them for examination and even potential future
                  development and collaboration. An interesting reconfiguration of the usual
                  literary or art critical relations.)</note> What the code produces as
                  <q>display</q> may be sited or made manifest in any number of 2D or 3D forms and
               spaces. This discussion, however, concerns itself, chiefly, with the code itself and
               what is presented by the code as, basically, typographic form on a 2D display, with
               some accompanying audio: letters and words in the case of <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype;</title> strokes, characters, and two-character compounds in the case
               of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>. Audio is used to signal particular
               relationships between generated forms and items in lexicons that have been derived
               from the languages of the respective works.</p>
            <p>The typographic forms generated by these works are of course referred, by those who
               engage with them, to language. At any one moment, they can often – not always – be
               read as such, as language; or rather as words <emph>in</emph>, at least, one of two
               natural languages, English on the one hand, Chinese on the other. Except that the
               situation immediately becomes more complicated. <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title> does have an English lexicon at its disposal but, as it
                  <q>explores</q> a mathematically abstracted space of Roman-letteral
                  <q>spelling,</q> quite apart from <q>spellings</q> that are non-lexical in any
               language, it will encounter and display word-like forms that may be shared by natural
               languages other than English any of those whose typography also uses Roman letters),
               or forms which are not orthographically English although they may be orthographically
               correct and readable in <emph>another</emph> language.</p>
            <p>In the case of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>, the situation is similarly
               complicated but radically different. Arbitrary or regularly abstracted rearrangements
               or substitutions of any particular character’s strokes or sub-elements will not – or
               only in extremely rare cases – produce an orthographically readable character in
               Chinese or a language other than Chinese, but any of the orthographically readable
               characters which <emph>are</emph> produced may be read, entirely differently, in any
               number of Chinese dialects or, indeed, in any number of other dialects of certain
               natural languages such as Japanese or Korean. Since Daniel Howe currently lives,
               works, and exhibits in Hong Kong, readings of <title rend="italic">RotVH,</title> for
               example, have often been anticipated in Mandarin Putonghua) and Cantonese, which are
               considered mutually unintelligible dialects of Chinese.</p>
            <p>Raising such complications at the outset of this close reading does at least two
               things. It highlights the way in which similarly motivated algorithmic processes may
               generate language-driven computational artworks with entirely different readings,
               particularly since these <q>readings,</q> quite apart from being metaphoric – that is
               critical or aesthetic – are also readings of distinct <q>written</q> linguistic
               materials which co-constitute the works. And it also reminds us of deep problems
               concerning the relationship between, on the one hand, what we call <q>text</q> or
                  <q>writing</q> or <q>typography,</q> or now also – in the context of computation –
                     <q><emph>strings</emph> of characters,</q> and, on the other, language as
               such.</p>
            <p>For text is not language unless and until is either actually read, or unless and
               until it is considered to be, potentially, readable. This is a statement from my own
               philosophy and, indeed, ontology of language. <note>Cf. <ptr target="#cayley2018b"/>;
                     <ptr target="#cayley2018a"/>; <ptr target="#cayley2020"/>. And also, <ref
                     target="https://nllf.net">https://nllf.net</ref>.</note> In the context of my
               theory I am happy to refer this statement to a species-unique human faculty of
                  language;<note> Members of this species, humans, bring language into being by
                  reading grasping, understanding) language’s material traces. These traces are
                  expressed and appreciated chiefly in aurality but also in culturally integrated
                  graphic visuality in writing; or in commensurate modes of language practice in any
                  perceptible material). The faculty that allows this to happen is necessarily
                  constitutive of language, and co-constitutive of <q>the human.</q> As such it
                  relies on the evolved and world-integrated embodiment of human animals, such that
                  the <q>differences</q> of its integral symbolic system are never abstract. They
                  are better understood as Derridean <q>differances,</q> as sayable meanings that
                  emerge as they are expressed – with the kind of ambiguity or polysemy, for
                  example, that embodied animation entails, and as neither pre-determined from a
                  finite set) nor subject to regular formulation as they are uttered and read. Thus,
                  the constitutive <q>faculty</q> of which I speak is in sharp contradistinction
                  with the predominant scientistic understanding of language, too-often based on a
                  hypothetical Chomskyean, designative, pre-engineered difference machine,
                  built-into the <q>brain</q> that runs combinatorial transformations on the
                  abstracted <q>deep structures</q> of inherently computable and
                     <q>disembodiable</q> mind/language constructs.</note> in the present context I
               ask only that those reading this essay agree that the words of <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title> and the characters of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> are
               subject to the possibility, at least, of human reading and interpretation, and that
               this does have a bearing on their appreciation as art, in particular any art of
               language that they propose. Their code, however, executes and generates typographic
               forms without regard to any human reading that may or may not be taking place. From a
               linguistic perspective, it is the various lexicons and associated data structures
               embedded in these projects’ software –pre-determined and adopted by the artist prior
               to any execution of the code – which establish relationships with human reading. The
               processes which generate their displayed linguistic forms do not.</p>
            <p>They do not, that is, unless, as readers and scholars we believe and assert, amongst
               other things, that reading and interpretation are reducible to regular, formal,
               combinatorial processes. One of the important tasks of critical code studies is to
               articulate this relationship between the code-composed programs <q>programs</q> both
               literal and figurative) insofar as they are generative of linguistic form, and the
               practices of reading that we bring to them in order to appreciate what they express
               as language or, indeed, language art. To be clear, I am not in the camp of those who
               take language to be computable reducible to computation) in any sense of this
               hypothesis that is abstracted or divorced from evolution or, indeed, history. In
               close reading these two works, I highlight the disjunctures between coded processes
               and human reading, and will even argue that these disjunctures, articulated, are
               themselves amongst the works’ most significant and affective readings. The
               disjunctures are brought into relief by the similarity of algorithmic process across
               these works, in contrast to their radically different integrations with the languages
               they engage. Both works are, I believe, easy enough to understand in terms of what
               their code is doing, while their readings are also clearly indicative of quite
               complex differences of language and culture; and also, in the case of <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title>, sociopolitics.</p>
            <p>Concluding these introductory and anticipatory remarks, it bears mentioning that this
               relation between code-generated text and human reading has the same structure,
               fundamentally, as that which obtains for the increasing predominant practices of
               Natural Language Processing that are driven by Deep Learning. Except that, when Deep
               Learning is operative, human readers’ ability to articulate and understand the coded
               processes are – is it right to say <q>literally</q>? – redacted. Deep Learning
               language models’ <q>encoding</q> of <q>representations</q> is often presented as a
                  <q>black box,</q> received as such even by willing experts. And while, in
               principle, exhaustive formal analysis may be held to be possible, what is actually
               concealed from us, as human readers and consumers sic) of the generated
               pseudo-language, is a number of unsubstantiated assumptions concerning things that we
               do not and perhaps cannot) know, scientifically or otherwise. <note> Readers may find
                  a recent <q>annual review</q> useful in this context: Ellie Pavlick, <title
                     rend="quotes">Semantic Structure in Deep Learning</title>
                  <ptr target="#pavlick2022"/>. Pavlick is not, I think, amongst those researchers
                  who are content to <q>black box</q> Deep Learning however opaque or
                  beyond-human-scale/perception the motivation of language models may appear to be;
                  and certain aspects of her problematization of the relationship between <quote
                     rend="inline">model representation</quote> and <quote rend="inline">model
                     behavior</quote> resonate with arguments in the present essay.</note> I would
               summarize this by saying that, although we speak and read, we still do not know what
               language is, nor how or why some of it may be aesthetically significant for us. As to
               this how and why, when we consider <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title>, at least we have a chance.</p>
            <p>The artist documentation pages for these works offer links to <q>Project Home
                  Pages,</q> Online Versions, and various public manifestations. The Project Home
               Page for <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> is minimal, and features an
               evaluative description extracted from a review by Brian Kim Stefans <ptr
                  target="#stefans2011"/>. The Home for <title rend="italic">R0tVH</title> however
               takes us to a page which links the two works explicitly, categorizing them both as
                  <q>Atomic Language Machines</q> ALMs), defined as <quote rend="inline">discrete
                  computational entities with the potential to change the direction, intent, or
                  magnitude of a literary vector. In general, ALMs can be defined as members of the
                  simplest class of mechanisms able to realize linguistic advantage.</quote>
               <ptr target="#howe2021"/>
               <q>Linguistic advantage</q> is one of those terms deployed in the context of
               computational linguistics to provide or explain motivation in Natural Language
               Processing, something used to test against a generated linguistic form in order to
               decide if it has, in some sense, advantageously <q>succeeded</q> or achieved a
                  <q>goal</q> which is usually interpretable by and <q>advantageous</q> to) humans.
               For both <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >RotVH</title> it is advantageous to spell out an item from the lexicons of
               English and Chinese, respectively.</p>
            <p>The <q>atomism</q> of ALMs is referred by Howe to a concept of <quote rend="inline"
                  >simplest class of mechanism</quote> and is linked with other such classes of
               mechanism which are cited as deployed, for example, in <title rend="italic">The
                  Readers Project</title>
               <ptr target="#cayleyhowe2009"/>.<note> A collaboration with the author. It is perhaps
                  worth noting that, on the ALMs page, the artist allows himself a certain poetic
                  license, with language that is a blend of technical and fanciful, somewhat
                  mythologizing, for example, the <quote rend="inline">early theoretical research
                     associated with the <title rend="quotes">Natural Language Liberation
                        Front</title><ref target="https://nllf.net"
                  >https://nllf.net</ref></quote></note> Here, I read <q>atomic</q> as indicative
               of, as it were, an <emph>elemental</emph> similarity between the class of mechanism
               driving <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and that which animates <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title>. The ALMs page quotes the following code snippet
               abstracted from the actual code driving <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>:</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>The function logographicMinEditDistance: source code and comment.</head>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of syntax-highlighted source code and comment.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p><quote rend="inline">Levenshtein distance is a string metric for measuring the
                  difference between two sequences. Informally, the Levenshtein distance between two
                  words is the minimum number of single-character edits insertions, deletions or
                  substitutions) required to change one word into the other.</quote>
               <ptr target="#wikipediacont2021"/> This metric is the measure of <q>linguistic
                  advantage</q> that underlies both <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>. When we consider <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title> – working with English words spelt out in Roman letters – this
               distance is a relatively straightforward concept to grasp. Typographic words are,
               indeed, sequences or <q>strings</q> of characters. For each word in a lexicon or its
               derivatives) we can calculate a Levenshtein distance to any other word. Having done
               so, we can start with any word we like and, having found its <q>nearest</q>
               Levenshteinian lexical neighbor, we may animate a typographic display which performs
               the minimum number of edits on our original string of characters in order to
               transform it into its neighbor. This is precisely what <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title> does, and by disallowing any <q>turning back</q> to a
               previously displayed lexical item) it effectively represents an ALM that would travel
               least-distance paths from item to item until it had visited and exhausted all the
               items of its English lexicon.<note> As such, the piece also qualifies as a work of
                  computationally animated <emph>conceptual</emph> literary art, a <q>walk through
                     the dictionary</q> not unlike Allison Parrish’s <title rend="italic"
                     >@everyword</title>, published by bot on Twitter from 2007 through 2014 and
                  documented in this printable publication: <ptr target="#parrish2015"/>. Parrish’s
                  work generates much of its significance and affect from the socially mediated
                  situation and circumstances of its publication, and thus also from the
                  transactional interventions and engagements of its readers through Twitter
                  affordances such as retweeting, liking etc.) Nonetheless, although the lexicons
                  used for <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title rend="italic"
                     >@everyword</title> were different, there is clearly a profound underlying
                     <q>sameness</q> – a shared ideality if not an identity – to the <q>texts</q> of
                  these two works. And either could have used the other’s lexicon without impugning
                  their respective concepts or motivating principles. Moreover, it is similarly the
                  case that the text’s generation by code, in <title rend="italic"
                     >@everyword</title>, has little or no bearing on its human reading, although
                  the relationship between code and reading is radically different from that which
                  we are exploring here, with respect to <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and
                     <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>. It seems that there is an opportunity,
                  which we cannot take up at present, for another interesting comparative close
                  reading with code critical implications.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another connotation of <q>atomic,</q> perhaps only latent in Howe’s ALMs webpage,
               comes into play at this point. The strings and sequences over which Levenshtein
               distances are calculated must be composed of integral, indivisible – at least for the
               purposes and processing of the algorithm – tokens, the <q>atoms</q> of the symbolic
               system of which they are expressions. The atoms of <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title>’s sequences are letters taken from a familiar, quite clearly
               delineated set, one that is widely shared over a number of linguistically integrated
               domains. In linguistic reality, the Roman letters used for English orthography are
               problematically related to what they purport to represent, the constituents of spoken
               English <q>sound-images</q> as Saussure, for one, would have it). But leaving these
               problems of reference, representation, and transcription to one side, <q>English</q>
               letters can be read straightforwardly by humans as from a finite set of integral
               elements. And although minimally semantic, they are included as lexical items in most
               dictionaries. Letters are, generally speaking, typographic atoms of reading and are
               amenable to contemporary computation as such.</p>
            <p>But what are the correspondent <q>atoms</q> of Chinese typography, of the Chinese
               writing system? Lexicons in the Chinese cultural sphere typically have characters as
               the <q>head words</q> of their articles although modern dictionaries may also use
                  <q>compounds</q> of characters, usually consisting of two characters. In modern
               Chinese these compounds correspond, linguistically, to the words of English
               dictionaries. Nonetheless, the Chinese character is, culturally speaking, the
                  <q>atom</q> of reading for the languages which use this logographic or, more
               properly, morphographic system of inscription. <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>
               works with two-character compounds. If characters were <title rend="italic"
                  >RotVH</title>’s atoms then Levenshtein distance would be calculated on the basis
               of <emph>character</emph> insertions, deletions, and substitutions. Since single
               characters are always morphemes and may often correspond with English words in modern
               Chinese while typically doing so in pre-modern Chinese) they are clearly of a
               different linguistic order as compared to Roman letters. Morpheme insertion,
               deletion, and substitution would read – if it did motivate the algorithms of <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title> – as incommensurate with the corresponding operations
               of <title rend="italic">Automatype</title>, although, in this speculative condition,
                  <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> would still exhaustively traverse a lexicon
               consisting of two-character compounds and would still sometimes display non-lexical
               items. And it would still also be able to signal and respond to any of its encounters
               with politically charged two-character terms). But it would never be non-semantic.
               Its operations would always yield readable and perhaps occasionally poetic)
               meanings.</p>
            <p>The artist recognized these circumstances and went deeper into the analysis of
               Chinese characters, coming up with a remarkable and effective compromise for his
               aesthetic purposes along, implicitly, with novel proposals for conceptualizing and
               calculating Levenshtein distances across the domain of Chinese characters. This is
               Howe’s comment on his <quote rend="inline">logographic distance</quote>
               calculation:</p>
            <p>
               <eg lang="code-general"><![CDATA[/*
 * logographic distance
 * - number of different full characters less 1 via basic Levenshtein)
 * - plus Levenshtein distance between two decompositions for each char
 * from [ ⿰ ⿱ ⿻ ⿳ ⿺ ⿸ ⿲ ⿹ ⿴ ⿵ ⿶ ⿷ ]
 * - this gives an integer distance >= 0 with 0 for identical strings)
 * - the floating point component 0 <= f < 1) is added by comparing the number
 of strokes in differing sub-parts normalized against a max-stroke count
 not used in production)
 */]]></eg>
            </p>
            <p>The distance calculation is a sum of staged Levenshtein distances. A first distance
               [1] is calculated between strings of integral characters the length of these strings
               being always equal to two in the lexical domain that is addressed by <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title>). Then [2] each of the characters in the strings being
               compared is assigned to one of twelve patterns of de)composition which are typical of
               Chinese characters. There is no generally accepted, rigorous analysis of this feature
               of characters, but sub-elements of characters are traditionally recognized and read
               into character composition and patterns of disposition for these elements falls into
               one of the twelve such that determinations are made and may even be assigned in some
               character dictionaries. Interestingly the patterns quoted above are represented by
               Unicode glyphs and thus – although these glyphs’ reference is much further divorced
               from linguistic significance, in the sense of any sound-image denotation, than that
               of alphabetic letters – their implicit deployment in Howe’s calculation resonates
               with the letters-as-tokens approach that is assumed in standard Levenshtein
               calculations over alphabetic orthographic typography. Finally, [3] calligraphic or
               sinotypographic) strokes are also recognized as finest-grained elements of
               characters. Ordered strokes are what compose the higher-level sub-elements of the
               de)composition patterns. Howe documents the possibility of using stroke-token
               sequences for each of the decomposed sub-elements and adding these to calculate a
               correspondingly finer-grained Levenshtein distance between, for example characters
               sharing the same de)composition pattern. He proposes to do this in an implicitly
               weighted manner by adding these distances as a <quote rend="inline">floating
                  point</quote> fractional) component. In practice, however, in the actual
                  <q>production</q> version of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>, Howe decided to
               ignore this component.<note> There are hints that the artist will address aspects of
                  what follows in future versions, but it should be noted that <title rend="italic"
                     >RotVH</title> does not make use of actual or potential <q>vocabularies</q> of
                  character sub-elements. This is a much-contested aspect of research on the Chinese
                  script and its abstracted analytic properties. Whereas some sets of sub-elements
                  are well-established, particularly the so-called <q>radicals</q> or
                     <q>classifiers</q> which are used in many Chinese dictionaries and are referred
                  to in the title of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>), even the standard 214
                  radicals of the canonical Kangxi dictionary have multiple forms of ordered
                  strokes, etc.) and there are problems in exhaustively assigning characters to some
                  particular <q>radical.</q> Nonetheless a finer-grain Levenshtein distance between
                  characters might be able to take account of sub-element sets, leading to, for
                  example, a Levenshtein distancing such as this: stage [1] based on strings of
                  integral characters; stage [2] assignments of the constituent characters to one of
                  the 12 de)composition patterns; stage [3] tokenized identification of constituent
                  sub-elements from a comprehensive set. Then [4, was 3 in the text] Levenshtein
                  distances between string representations of the sub-elements’ ordered constituent
                  strokes. But it is a significant graphic problem to animate, in any
                     <q>readable</q> fashion, the operations of stroke insertion, deletion, and
                  substitution that might be called for or desired.<lb/> This brings up a related
                  fact concerning the animated display of <title rend="italic">R0tVH’s</title>
                  current version. The part of its animation during which a sub-element is built up
                  is <emph>not</emph> a representation of Levenshtein edit operations. This is
                  simply an animation of the stroke-ordered process that a human calligrapher would,
                  by traditional convention, use to write the character’s sub-element. In the
                  current version of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> only the graphic removal of
                  a sub-element and its subsequent animated rendering <emph>as a whole</emph> is
                  related to Levenshtein distance, but in the current version it often represents a
                  Levenshtein-distance <q>tie</q> since the before and after characters may have the
                  same de)composition value. Otherwise, it counts as a substitution
                  operation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic"> RotVH</title> is art not science. It may well, however, engage
               more practically, empirically, and experimentally with scientific analyses or
               formulations of editing distance over the Chinese lexicon than other efforts which
               have been put forward in the context of science explicitly. The choice of next
               operation – here of insertion, deletion, or substitution – is on display to
               artistically motivated readers and viewers and will thus bring in other aesthetically
               implicated considerations apart from Levenshtein distance, the most obvious being
               based on keeping a <q>history</q> of all words or character compounds so far
               displayed, and disallowing repetitions. This principle applies to both <title
                  rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> and is
               what enables these ALMs to take their shortest possible – conceptual-art – walk
               through an entire lexicon. For <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>, Howe needs to
               establish additional pragmatic-aesthetic criteria, beyond the shared concept. <quote
                  rend="block">[O]ther criteria also affect selection from the larger pool of
                  candidates) including whether they differ on the same <q>side</q> left or right
                  character in the word) as the last few changes, so as to avoid the same character
                  remaining constant for long periods, and whether any are trigger words. In the
                  current version I ended up ignoring the floating point part of the distance
                  metric… in order to get a set of words essentially tied in distance, so that I
                  could then choose between them according to these other metrics.</quote><note>
                  Personal communication with the artist, November 30, 2021.</note> The <quote
                  rend="inline">larger pool of candidates</quote> refers to all those compounds for
               potential display which are <quote rend="inline">tied</quote> in terms of Levenshtein
               distance after stages [1] and [2] above.</p>
            <p>This is the point at which – without abandoning its inevitably computational and
               code-driven conceptual aesthetics, both also addressing the domain of Natural
               Language Processing, and both shared with <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> –
                  <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> shifts is engines of motivation in order to
               adopt a <emph>critical art</emph> aesthetic, one that is designed to inform its
               readers, creatively, concerning the sociopolitical valences of certain items in the
               Chinese lexicon. <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> contains a data file of <quote
                  rend="inline">trigger</quote> words, those compounds which are flagged by the
                  <q>Great Firewall,</q> by Chinese state surveillance of linguistic internet
               traffic, or which have been signaled as politically taboo in what is now China’s Hong
               Kong Special Administrative Region. Here is a snapshot from the JSON file
               triggers.json) to which <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> refers <ptr
                  target="#howe201921code"/>:</p>
            <eg lang="code-general"><![CDATA["滴蜡": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "滴蠟", "def": "using candles for BDSM" }, 
"滴蠟": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "滴蜡", "def": "using candles for BDSM" }, 
"汪洋": { "lang": "both", "pair": "汪洋", "def": "vast ocean, PRC ex-VP Wang Yang" }, 
"妇联": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "婦聯", "def": "women's league" }, 
"婦聯": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "妇联", "def": "women's league" }, 
"罢工": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "罷工", "def": "workers' strike" }, 
"罷工": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "罢工", "def": "workers' strike" }, 
"元朗": { "lang": "both", "pair": "元朗", "def": "Yuen Long district, Hong Kong" }, 
"陸肆": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "陆肆", "def": "ref. to Tiananmen Anniversary"}, 
"陆肆": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "陸肆", "def": "ref. to Tiananmen Anniversary"}, 
"學潮": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "学潮", "def": "student movement"}, 
"学潮": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "學潮", "def": "student movement"}, 
"八九": { "lang": "both", "def":  "1989, year of Tiananmen Sq massacre"}, 
"河殤": { "lang": "trad", "pair": "河殇", "def": "River Elegy"}, 
"河殇": { "lang": "simp", "pair": "河殤", "def": "River Elegy"},]]>
            </eg>

            <p>This is a snapshot which demonstrates the wide-ranging scope of Chinese lexical
               surveillance, flagging terms with regard to: sexual practices; <quote rend="inline"
                  >reforming</quote> politicians; gender- and class-based affiliations; the
               Tian’anmen Square massacre and its <quote rend="inline">student movement</quote>
               likely including student movements in themselves); and even a controversial
               television series. The <quote rend="inline">lang</quote> property of each
               two-character item is indicative of one of two main Chinese systems of inscription.
               Those words with the same triggering <quote rend="inline">def</quote> property may
               occur in <quote rend="inline">trad[itional]</quote> more strokes, greater complexity)
               or <quote rend="inline">simp[lified]</quote> spellings. Traditional characters are
               still widely and officially used in regions of the Chinese culture sphere – notably
               and with political significance Taiwan and Hong Kong – which are, to whatever extent,
               still <q>outside</q> the People’s Republic of China. The PRC, on the other hand, has
               instituted and adopted its own <q>reformed</q> and <q>simplified</q> character
               orthography. Some spellings – untouched by reform – belong to <quote rend="inline"
                  >both</quote> systems. There is an underlying ideality to characters or compounds)
               in either spelling. Essentially, they refer to the same <q>form-as-read</q> in the
               Chinese of their speaker-readers I would call this a <q>gram</q> of the implicit
               archi-writing) and thus they are equally <q>triggering</q> for state
               surveillance.</p>
            <p>Whereas the audiovisual behaviors of <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> – apart
               from those which represent edit operations – are confined to signaling the ALM’s
                  <q>arrival</q> at a lexical word, those of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>
               signal not only lexical arrival but also whether or not the newly displayed word is a
                  <quote rend="inline">trigger,</quote> a surveilled word. Then also, after a
               distinct sound and a flash of red, <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> is also
               triggered to switch to orthographic explorations in whatever is the other system of
               Chinese spelling, either <quote rend="inline">trad[itional]</quote> or <quote
                  rend="inline">simp[lified],</quote> depending on which of the two it was exploring
               when disrupted by a <quote rend="inline">trigger.</quote> This shift of orthographic
               systems might perhaps be interpreted as a futile attempt to <q>misspell</q> and thus
               elude surveillance, but it can never be more than a jolt to either system since the
               underlying <quote rend="inline">trigger</quote> is, as we have seen, the same word in
               any Chinese that matters to the surveillance operations of its PRC state overseers.
               Regardless of the overseers’ indifference or rather their fixation on transgression)
               or the computational indifference of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title>’s execution,
               the change of orthographic systems will, nonetheless, resonate with, and may mildly
               traumatize, Chinese readers since each system has ideological and political
               alignments and associations.<note> Cf. these interesting comments from the artist,
                     <quote rend="block">There is also the idea of an
                     externally-imposed)catastrophic?) break here… Yes, there are words in common,
                     especially as written characters, to both but one human or non-human reader) is
                     either reading in C[antonese, typically integrated with traditional characters]
                     or M[andarin, official Putonghua of the PRC and aligned with simplified
                     characters], it would seem to me, though my students sometimes try to create
                     politically-inflected mergers of the two. But historically-speaking some
                     threshold of <emph>pressure</emph> a favorite word here) may be required before
                     one willingly switches as example, the political implications of choosing to
                     speak — or not to speak — M[andarin] as a Hong Konger are quite clear). And
                     while generally the case, close relationships between the political and the
                     linguistic are perhaps more explicit/tangible in Chinese history, especially
                     regarding government policies of the last century that attempt to manage
                     language as a resource see Mullaney, etc.)</quote> Personal communication,
                  December 4, 2021) The Mullaney here is <ptr target="#mullaney2017"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The typical installation version of <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> consisted
               of a number of networked, otherwise independently operating instances of the ALM in,
               for example, a 3x3 grid, each exploring the same lexicon separately but on its own
               path from a different starting point, making minimal displayed edits, and arriving
               intermittently at actual lexical items, English words. This grid arrangement overlays
               a form suggestive of visual or pattern poetry and thus also an aesthetic, a
                  <emph>poetic</emph> that is not programmatically related not integrated by code)
               with the <emph>conceptual</emph> Natural Language Processing aesthetic of the ALM
               itself. <title rend="italic">Automatype</title>’s poetic overlay-in-installation has
               not been a significant focus of attention for this essay although it is what allowed
               Brian Kim Stefans, in his remarks on <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> to say
               that <quote rend="inline">You will spend either 10 seconds or 5 minutes staring at
                  this thing [the grid]; you will also see either a bunch of random words, or
                  occasionally, if not always, engaging samples of minimalist poetry</quote>
               <ptr target="#stefans2011"/>. </p>
            <p>Not only are <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >RotVH</title> closely related in that they share essentially the same coded,
               programmatic procedure for <q>walking through</q> a lexicon and thus essentially the
               same computational and conceptual NLP aesthetic; they are also similarly structured
               in that both have been given, by their maker, an additional, overlaid aesthetic. And
               although the code of <title rend="italic">RotVH</title> refers and reacts to its
               trigger word data, this is an additional and distinct coded operation of <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title>, dependent on an additional human-compiled data file,
               only of significance to or affective of this ALM’s readers for reasons that are
               sociopolitical rather than merely linguistic. The immediately following concluding
               remark should be part of a much larger discussion, but we might begin to take away
               something beyond the code-critical from this comparative reading by reflecting on how
               the overlaid aesthetic for a project within the domain of global English tends to
               engage with formal arrangement and poetics, whereas the closely related, subsequent
               project, addressing what is now perhaps the planet’s <q>other</q> global language,
               engages sociopolitics and critical art practices.</p>
            <p>There is at least one more important general point to make that is based on the
               descriptions and analysis that we have just undertaken, and it has transcultural
               critical resonance. From both a code critical perspective and from one attuned to
               careful, responsible humanistic readings of computational art, any writing on this
               art must remain or become more critically aware of the culture of computation and its
               history. This is an imperative within the sphere of what is the globally predominant
               regime of computation, and it has hardly been addressed, as it must be, within an
               overarching context that is <emph>trans</emph>cultural at the level of distinct
                  <q>civilizations.</q><note> The reference to <q>civilizations</q> is historical
                  and simply intended to signal the historical distinction between Eurocentric
                     <q>western</q> civilization and that of a sinocentric <q>east.</q> The artist’s
                  comments in note 15 above has already cited one of the few studies addressing
                  these transcultural issues with respect to language practice and computation. <ptr
                     target="#mullaney2017"/> Mullaney’s book explicitly presages what promises to
                  be his essential follow-up work on the history of computation in the Chinese
                  culture sphere.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We have seen that, addressing the Chinese system of inscription, an operational
               analysis of its elements must be done by way of bespoke or imported data structures
               and bespoke or imported functions – even when this is for the purposes of animating
               the same Natural Language Processing concept or operation – here, a Levenshtein
               distance-based <q>shortest walk</q> through a lexicon. By contrast, for global
               English in particular, and for <q>western</q> languages having integrated alphabetic
               systems of inscription, the data structures and functions are already more or less
               built into actually existing computational infrastructure. The historical reasons for
               this integration of computation and the alphabet are quite well known. But this is no
               reason for critical complacency, particularly when we recall that text-as-orthography
               is in no way consistent with even a linguistic-scientific analysis of language as
                  such.<note> Which has implications, please recall, for Deep Learning language
                  models and generators.</note> We call orthographic spellings <q>words,</q> but
               this is both pragmatic, living-culture convention and scientific misdirection. If
               historical and contingent computational infrastructures reinforce our misdirected
               conventions, this has implications far beyond the misapplication or bespoke
               adaptation of these infrastructures to systems of inscription for which they are
               ill-adapted. Close reading of <title rend="italic">Automatype</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">RotVH</title> allows us to encounter and explore these contemporary
               transcultural critical aporias. These two ALMs both read <q>words</q> but read them
               differently, because even the spellings of these words are culturally situated and
               involve radically different relations to linguistic structure. The ALMs nonetheless
               deploy algorithms for lexical traversal which are essentially the same. The code is
               radically different in each case, not only due to the cultural situation of the
                  <q>words,</q> but also because the code itself – and contemporary computation as
               whole – is culturally situated and adapted to particular global locations.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cayley2018a" label="Cayley 2018a"> Cayley, John. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Grammalepsy: An Introduction</title>, <title rend="italic">Electronic Book
                  Review</title>, 08-05, 2018, <ptr
                  target="http://electronicbookreview.com/essay/grammalepsy-an-introduction"/>.
               Accessed August 12, 2018. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cayley2018b" label="Cayley 2018b"> Cayley, John. <title rend="italic"
                  >Grammalepsy: Essays on Digital Language Art</title>. Electronic Literature. New
               York and London: Bloomsbury Academic, 2018, <ptr
                  target="https://doi.org/10.5040/9781501335792"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cayley2020" label="Cayley 2020"> Cayley, John. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Language That Machines Read</title>. In <title rend="italic">Attention à la Marche
                  = Mind the Gap: Penser la Littérature Électronique in a Digital Culture = Thinking
                  Electronic Literature in a Digital Culture</title>, edited by Bertrand Gervais and
               Sophie Marcotte, pp. 105-113. Montreal: Les Presses de l’Écureuil, 2020. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cayleyhowe2009" label="Cayley and Howe 2009"> Cayley, John, and Daniel C.
               Howe. <title rend="italic">The Readers Project</title>. 2009–. <ptr
                  target="http://thereadersproject.org"/>. Accessed November 28, 2021. [Also
               published/documented: <title rend="italic">Electronic Literature Collection</title>,
               vol. 3, 2016, <ptr
                  target="http://collection.eliterature.org/3/work.html?work=the-readers-project"/>.
               Accessed August 17, 2017, ELMCIP Knowledge Base <ref
                  target="https://elmcip.net/node/864">https://elmcip.net/node/864</ref>. Accessed
               August 14, 2017.] </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howe201216a" label="Howe 2012-16a"> Howe, Daniel C. <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype</title>. 2012-16. <ref target="https://rednoise.org/daniel/automatype"
                  >https://rednoise.org/daniel/automatype</ref>. Accessed November 27, 2021. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howe201216b" label="Howe 2012-16b"> Howe, Daniel C. <title rend="italic"
                  >Automatype [Code]</title>, 2012-16. <ref
                  target="https://github.com/dhowe/Automatype"
                  >https://github.com/dhowe/Automatype</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howe201921" label="Howe 2019-21a"> Howe, Daniel C. <title rend="italic"
                  >Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title>. 2019-21. <ref
                  target="https://rednoise.org/daniel/radicaloftheverticalheart"
                  >https://rednoise.org/daniel/radicaloftheverticalheart</ref>. Accessed November
               27, 2021. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howe201921code" label="Howe 2019-21b"> Howe, Daniel C. <title
                  rend="italic">Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title> [Code], 2019-21. <ref
                  target="https://github.com/dhowe/rotvh">https://github.com/dhowe/rotvh</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howe2021" label="Howe 2021">Howe, Daniel. C. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Atomic Language Machines,</title>
               <title rend="italic">rednoise.org</title>. {Avilable at: <ref
                  target="https://rednoise.org/daniel/pages/alms/index.html"
                  >https://rednoise.org/daniel/pages/alms/index.html</ref>(Accessed 28 November
               2021).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mullaney2017" label="Mullaney 2017"> Mullaney, Thomas S. <title
                  rend="italic">The Chinese Typewriter: A History</title>. Studies of the
               Weatherhead East Asian Institute, Columbia University. Cambridge: The MIT Press,
               2017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parrish2015" label="Parrish 2015"> Parrish, Allison. <title rend="italic"
                  >@everyword: The Book</title>. New York: Instar Books, 2015. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pavlick2022" label="Pavlick 2022"> Pavlick, Ellie. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Semantic Structure in Deep Learning.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Linguistics </title>8, no. 23 Review in Advance
               first posted on November 23, 2021. Changes may still occur before final publication.)
               2022): 1-25. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stefans2011" label="Stefans 2011"> Stefans, Brian Kim. <title
                  rend="quotes">Third Hand Plays: <title rend="quotes">Automatype</title> by Daniel
                  C. Howe</title>, <title rend="italic">Openspace, SFMoMA</title> September 8, 2011)
                  <ref
                  target="https://openspace.sfmoma.org/2011/09/third-hand-plays-automatype-by-daniel-c-howe/"
                  >https://openspace.sfmoma.org/2011/09/third-hand-plays-automatype-by-daniel-c-howe</ref>.
               Accessed December 4, 2021. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wikipediacont2021" label="Wikipedia contributors 2021">Wikipedia
               contributors. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Levenshtein distance,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia</title>. {Available at: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levenshtein_distance"
                  >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levenshtein_distance</ref> (Accessed 28 November
               2021).}</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
