<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Validity and Verifiability: Toward a Hybrid
                    Framework for Evaluating Digital Humanities in India</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Vinayak <dhq:family>Das Gupta
                        name</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-5623-1226</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Shiv Nadar Institution of Eminence, India</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>vinayak.dasgupta@snu.edu.in</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Vinayak Das Gupta is Associate Professor of English and Digital
                            Humanities at Shiv Nadar Institution of Eminence, India. His research
                            explores digital curation and the epistemologies of digital
                            scholarship.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000820</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2025-11-21">21 November 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#dh"/>
                    <term corresp="#globalDH"/>
                    <term corresp="#data_curation"/>
                    <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
                    <term corresp="#ethics"/>
                    <term corresp="#collaboration"/>
                    <term corresp="#cultural_criticism"/>

                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>India</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000820/000820.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article examines how evaluative infrastructures in Indian higher education —
                    such as the UGC’s Academic Performance Index (API), NAAC’s accreditation
                    rubrics, and NIRF rankings — continue to marginalise digital scholarly work by
                    equating academic value with print-based authorship and closure. Taking digital
                    curation as a diagnostic form, it traces how infrastructural, collaborative, and
                    multilingual labour remains epistemically invisible within systems designed for
                    singular outputs. Drawing on global debates in digital humanities, it situates
                    the Indian case within broader questions of legitimacy and rigour. The paper
                    proposes a hybrid evaluative framework that integrates processual,
                    collaborative, and infrastructural criteria into institutional assessment.
                    Grounded in Indian intellectual and policy contexts, it argues that recognising
                    digital scholarship is an act of epistemic accountability, redefining what
                    counts as knowledge, and who is authorised to produce it, in the contemporary
                    humanities.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Evaluative infrastructures in Indian higher education continue to marginalise
                    digital scholarly work by equating academic value with print-based authorship
                    and closure. This proposed framework imagines something better and more
                    equitable.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This article examines a structural crisis at the heart of humanities scholarship
                    in India: the persistent inability of academic institutions to recognise
                    electronic scholarly resources as legitimate forms of intellectual labour.
                    Despite the methodological rigour, conceptual innovation, and collaborative
                    infrastructure that such projects demand, they remain excluded from the
                    frameworks through which scholarly value is assigned, and academic legitimacy is
                        conferred.<note> For instance, the UGC’s Academic Performance Index (API)
                        Regulations (2018) do not list digital collections, curated platforms, or
                        infrastructure-based outputs as recognised forms of research contribution.
                        See <ptr target="#ugc_2018" loc="Appendix III, Table 1"/>.</note> Monographs
                    and journal articles continue to monopolise evaluative rubrics. In the Indian
                    context, the University Grants Commission’s<note> The University Grants
                        Commission (UGC) is the statutory body in India responsible for
                        coordinating, determining, and maintaining standards of higher education. It
                        oversees funding, accreditation, and faculty evaluation frameworks for
                        universities and colleges.</note> Academic Performance Index (API),<note>
                        The Academic Performance Indicator (API) is a points-based system introduced
                        by the University Grants Commission (UGC) in India to evaluate the
                        performance of faculty members for recruitment, promotions, and career
                        advancement. It primarily rewards peer-reviewed publications, research
                        funding, and teaching-related activities.</note> the National Assessment and
                    Accreditation Council’s (NAAC)<note> The National Assessment and Accreditation
                        Council (NAAC) is an autonomous body established by the University Grants
                        Commission (UGC) to assess and accredit higher education institutions in
                        India. Its evaluation framework emphasizes institutional infrastructure,
                        teaching quality, and outreach activities.</note> Self-Study Report
                        (SSR),<note> The Self-Study Report (SSR) is a comprehensive document
                        submitted by higher education institutions in India as part of the NAAC
                        accreditation process. It outlines institutional performance across a set of
                        criteria, including curricular aspects, research output, infrastructure, and
                        community engagement.</note> or the National Institutional Ranking
                    Framework’s (NIRF)<note> The National Institutional Ranking Framework (NIRF) is
                        an initiative by the Ministry of Education, Government of India, that ranks
                        higher education institutions based on parameters such as teaching,
                        research, graduation outcomes, outreach, and perception. It influences
                        funding, admissions, and institutional prestige.</note> ranking system
                    privileges recognisable and traditional research outputs over born-digital
                    contributions. Digital scholarly work is rendered structurally invisible, or
                    worse, misclassified as technical support, pedagogical aid, or administrative
                    extension. However, these are the constitutive frameworks that provide the core
                    mechanisms through which academic performance is audited in India. Together they
                    regulate individual promotion, institutional accreditation, and national
                    rankings, establishing the quantitative logic by which research value is
                    assigned. In a moment when knowledge is increasingly generated within digital
                    platforms, collaborative annotation, multimodal collections, and public-facing
                    infrastructures, the continued reliance on print-centric evaluative models
                    imposes a powerful form of epistemic erasure.<note> I use <term>epistemic
                            erasure</term> to name a specific institutional effect: the removal of
                        certain forms of scholarly labour from visibility at the point of audit,
                        credit, and reward. It is related to but distinct from epistemicide, which
                        denotes the destruction of knowledge traditions <ptr
                            target="#de-sousa-santos_2014"/> from epistemic violence, which marks
                        the silencing of subaltern knowers within dominant discourses <ptr
                            target="#spivak_1988"/>, and from epistemic injustice, which tracks
                        testimonial and hermeneutical wrongs done to knowers <ptr
                            target="#fricker_2007"/>. Epistemic erasure is often produced
                        administratively rather than polemically. It occurs when evaluation systems
                        recognise only authored texts and citation metrics and therefore fail to
                        read infrastructural, collaborative, multilingual, and interface-level work
                        as knowledge. In digital humanities, this erasure intersects with critiques
                        of infrastructural invisibility and care labour.</note> Projects that build
                    archives, curate metadata, design interfaces, or sustain multilingual corpora
                    are rarely seen as producing knowledge. Instead, they are evaluated through the
                    vocabulary of service: useful, but not scholarly, foundational but not credited.
                    This erasure not only obscures the labour that sustains contemporary research,
                    but it also narrows the intellectual horizon of the university itself.<note> See
                            <ptr target="#mcpherson_2012"/>. Tara McPherson argues that digital
                        infrastructure, often seen as neutral or technical, encodes epistemological
                        and ideological assumptions that shape scholarly legibility. She critiques
                        the tendency to render platform-building and codework invisible within
                        traditional academic hierarchies, suggesting that these forms of labour
                        demand recognition as deeply intellectual and political acts.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While this article focuses on the Indian academic system, these challenges are
                    global. Calls to address them have appeared consistently over the past two
                    decades, as digital humanities has grappled with the problem of how digital work
                    is recognised and credited within academic institutions. Earlier efforts to
                    define the field <ptr target="#svensson_2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#svensson_2016"/> emphasised that digital humanities was less of a
                    discipline than a landscape whose uneven global distribution mirrored existing
                    hierarchies of knowledge. Domenico Fiormonte continues in the same vein by
                    foregrounding the <quote rend="inline">geopolitical and the cultural-linguistic
                        composition of the discipline</quote>
                    <ptr target="#fiormonte_2012" loc="62"/>, arguing that infrastructural and
                    linguistic asymmetries reproduce cultural dependence even within ostensibly open
                    digital systems. Subsequent interventions by <ptr target="#fitzpatrick_2011"/>
                    and <ptr target="#drucker_2014"/> have questioned the adequacy of traditional
                    peer review and authorship models for evaluating multimodal and collaborative
                    scholarship. <ptr target="#risam_2018"/> and <ptr target="#posner_2012"/> have
                    further shown how the invisibility of labour in digital projects reflects deeper
                    inequities in the academic valuation of work. Extending this argument, <ptr
                        target="#horvath_2024"/> and <ptr target="#horvath_2025"/> shift attention
                    from infrastructures to users, showing how multilingual and non-Latin-script
                    practitioners navigate these inequities in practice, and calling for
                    institution-level reforms — in libraries, funding, and evaluation — to create
                    linguistically inclusive forms of digital scholarship. In parallel, <ptr
                        target="#dahiya_2025"/> highlight how such structural tensions manifest in
                    the Indian university system, where digital humanities pedagogy oscillates
                    between humanistic inquiry and techno-positivist training, reflecting deeper
                    curricular and institutional rigidities. While it would be possible to draw
                    formal comparisons with Euro-American institutional models, such a gesture risks
                    recentring the very inequities this paper seeks to unsettle. The point, rather,
                    is to acknowledge that India is not derivative of or exceptional to the global
                    frame, but that systemic specificities expose the limits of that frame
                    itself.</p>
                <p>This article takes digital curation as a site of examination not because it is
                    the only form of electronic scholarly labour, but because it renders visible a
                    set of structural tensions that apply more broadly across the domain of digital
                    scholarship. Curation sits at the intersection of infrastructure, authorship,
                    and interpretation; it demands methodological innovation, multilingual
                    negotiation, and public-facing design. As such, it functions as a diagnostic
                    form, foregrounding the invisibilities, exclusions, and classificatory failures
                    that attend many types of digital work within the Indian academic system.
                    Whether in annotated corpora, multimodal editions, or born-digital platforms,
                    the epistemic labour involved in making electronic resources discoverable,
                    legible, and reliable is consistent across forms. By following the labour of
                    curation across institutional rubrics, metadata infrastructures, and memory
                    projects, this paper proposes a broader reconfiguration of how academic value is
                    assigned to electronic scholarly resources in India.<note> While this article
                        focuses on digital curation as a diagnostic form of scholarly labour, it
                        recognises that the field of digital humanities in India encompasses a
                        broader range of practices — including natural language processing (NLP),
                        GIS-based spatial analysis, computational literary studies, and digital
                        pedagogy. These domains pose their own evaluative challenges and epistemic
                        tensions. However, the emphasis on curation here reflects its centrality to
                        questions of legibility, authorship, and infrastructural labour — dimensions
                        where institutional exclusions are particularly visible and where
                        recognition frameworks remain most underdeveloped.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As we examine this issue, two overlapping challenges emerge. First, at a global
                    level, existing evaluative systems have proven ill-equipped to recognise the
                    complex intellectual labour embedded in electronic resources. The interpretive
                    work of digital design, the methodological innovation of interactive platforms,
                    the collaborative ethos of open-access infrastructures, cannot be easily mapped
                    onto institutional categories structured around individual authorship and
                    citation metrics. Second, in the Indian context, these global tendencies are
                    intensified by rigid evaluative frameworks such as the UGC’s Academic
                    Performance Index (API), NAAC’s assessment rubrics, and NIRF rankings. These
                    frameworks not only privilege conventional scholarly forms, but also marginalise
                    those that operate across media, across disciplines, and across publics.</p>
                <p>While Indian digital humanities scholarship has grown steadily over the past
                    decade, much of the published work has focused on questions of pedagogy,
                    infrastructure, and method. The volume <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        in India: Learning by Doing</title>
                    <ptr target="#dodd_2024"/>, for instance, foregrounds the infrastructural
                    constraints and pedagogical experiments that have shaped digital humanities
                    projects in the Indian university system. It maps the collaborative, often
                    improvisational nature of digital research in resource-constrained environments
                    and calls for broader institutional support. My argument builds on this
                    foundational work but shifts the focus to a different, yet structurally related,
                    site of concern: the systems of evaluation through which digital scholarly
                    labour is rendered visible, or not, within the academy. If Dodd and Menon have
                    helped to define how DH is being done, this paper asks how it is being counted,
                    where it is located within institutional architectures of legitimacy, how it is
                    assessed, and what remains unintelligible within current evaluative grammars. By
                    foregrounding the absence of a coherent framework for recognising electronic
                    scholarly resources, particularly in Indian institutional contexts, this essay
                    extends the conversation from questions of capacity to those of epistemic
                    value.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Forms of Knowledge, Frames of Legitimacy</head>
                <p>Despite the rhetoric of inclusivity and reform, the Indian university remains a
                    fixed and unyielding structure, fundamentally incapable of accommodating
                    heterogeneity. As Gauri Viswanathan (2015) shows, the institutionalisation of
                    English literary study under colonial rule was never meant to foster pluralism —
                    it was a disciplinary project, designed to regulate and normalise elite subjects
                    through selective exposure to moral and aesthetic values <ptr
                        target="#viswanathan_2015"/>. The humanities in India thus emerged not as a
                    site of critical inquiry, but as a mechanism of rule, tightly bound to a canon,
                    a language, and a civility coded as universal. This legacy persists in the
                    postcolonial university, where what passes for neutrality is in fact the
                    sediment of historical exclusions. Debaditya Bhattacharya critiques the
                    disciplinary structure of the university not as a neutral or apolitical space,
                    but as a historically entrenched mechanism of enclosure. In his reading,
                    specialization and disciplinarity operate less as tools of openness than as
                    strategies of control that <quote rend="inline">seek to patrol boundaries,
                        prescribe modes of knowing, and foreclose the possibility of unauthorised
                        intellectual entry</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bhattacharya_2018" loc="5"/>. The emergence of the <soCalled>new
                        humanities</soCalled> — including digital, environmental, affective, and
                    post-humanist modes of inquiry — offers a profound opportunity to reimagine the
                    terrain of knowledge production. These fields challenge the inherited borders
                    between disciplines, as well as between the human and the non-human, the
                    material and the virtual, the textual and the embodied. As Supriya Chaudhuri
                    argues, the humanities must reckon with the <quote rend="inline">post-human
                        condition</quote>
                    <ptr target="#chaudhuri_2018" loc="22"/> in which the figure of the human is no
                    longer singular, autonomous, or self-contained, but enmeshed in networks of
                    interdependence with machines, animals, environments, and code <ptr
                        target="#chaudhuri_2018" loc="23"/>. The new humanities do not simply expand
                    the canon; they demand a transformation in how knowledge is constituted, who is
                    authorized to speak, and what forms of mediation count as legitimate. Amlan Das
                    Gupta acknowledges the university as a uniquely valuable site for the
                    development of digital humanities, especially for <quote rend="inline">sustained
                        critical reflection</quote> and the creation of <quote rend="inline">new
                        protocols of metadata</quote> and <quote rend="inline">new tools for
                        visualization and collation</quote>
                    <ptr target="#das-gupta_2018" loc="83"/>. Yet this optimistic vision exists in
                    tension with the structural conservatism of many Indian institutions, which
                    often lack the epistemic flexibility and infrastructural responsiveness required
                    to integrate these new modes of inquiry. While Das Gupta does not frame the
                    university as hostile to digital humanities, his emphasis on the need to build
                    capacities — rather than reform existing systems — suggests a quiet recognition
                    of institutional inertia. </p>
                <p>A growing body of scholarship has engaged this problem, converging around several
                    overlapping critiques. Roopika Risam has argued that digital projects emerging
                    from decolonial or community-driven imperatives are often dismissed precisely
                    because they foreground modes of knowledge production that institutional systems
                    are not built to recognise <ptr target="#risam_2018"/>. In such cases,
                    significance lies not in where a project is published, but in what it makes
                    visible, who it includes, and how it circulates. Similarly, Anne Burdick and her
                    collaborators have argued that the aesthetic, material, and infrastructural
                    choices embedded in digital scholarship are not supplementary, they are
                    constitutive. They write, <quote rend="inline">Design in dialogue with research
                        is simply a technique, but when used to pose and frame questions about
                        knowledge, design becomes an intellectual method</quote>
                    <ptr target="#burdick_2012" loc="13"/>. Usability is not an afterthought; it is
                    an argument. Nor can this labour be separated from its infrastructure. Christine
                    Borgman has made clear that digital collections must be sustained, through
                    metadata revision, interface upkeep, preservation strategies, all forms of
                    labour that rarely appear in CVs,<note> She writes, <quote rend="inline"
                            >[s]cholarship resulting in digital objects is especially risky in the
                            humanities, where printed books remain the gold standard... Given the
                            difficulties in getting credit for documentary publications in new forms
                            and forums... few fields value the publication of data as scholarly
                            products</quote>
                        <ptr target="#borgman_2007" loc=" 239"/></note> yet determine the scholarly
                    reliability of the resource itself <ptr target="#borgman_2007"/>. Matthew
                    Kirschenbaum’s notion of the <quote rend="inline">processual ontology</quote> of
                    digital humanities reinforces this view: What matters is not merely the artefact
                    but the sequence of intellectual, technical, and collaborative decisions through
                    which it is formed <ptr target="#kirschenbaum_2008"/>. As Lauren Klein and
                    Catherine D’Ignazio have argued, the care-based, collaborative, and often
                    undercompensated labour that digital scholarship demands is <quote rend="inline"
                        >a form of invisible labor</quote> that is <quote rend="inline"
                        >precarious,</quote> disproportionately undertaken by <quote rend="inline"
                        >women and people of color,</quote> and largely unacknowledged within
                    systems of academic credit <ptr target="#dignazio_2020" loc="200"/>. This labour
                    — performed by librarians, archivists, curators, and early-career scholars,
                    particularly those outside Euro-American institutions — is not supplementary but
                    fundamental to the sustainability of digital work. The failure to account for
                    this labour is a systemic reproduction of inequality. Together, these
                    interventions call not just for the inclusion of digital work within existing
                    evaluative frameworks, but for a reconsideration of how scholarly value itself
                    is assigned. The legitimacy of digital scholarship cannot rest on its
                    resemblance to traditional forms. It must be read on its own terms — as
                    iterative, hybrid, and socially embedded. Its contribution lies not only in
                    argument, but in form, infrastructure, and the conditions of its making. </p>
                <p>While global literature on digital humanities, particularly in the United States
                    and Europe, has produced a robust body of critique around scholarly legitimacy,
                    peer review, and institutional evaluation, these debates often assume the
                    existence of a mature field. In India, by contrast, digital humanities remains a
                    nascent and often project-bound formation, shaped more by infrastructural
                    improvisation than by disciplinary coherence.<note> See Padmini Ray Murray’s
                        conceputalisation of <foreign xml:lang="hi">jugaad</foreign> in Indian
                        Digital Humanities in <title rend="quotes">Making Culture: Locating the
                            Digital Humanities in India,</title>
                        <title rend="italic">Visible language</title>, 49.3, 2015. </note> As such,
                    the exclusions this paper documents cannot always be located in a formalised
                    Indian DH discourse, but in institutional behaviours, policy omissions, and the
                    lived experiences of digital scholarship. This difference reflects the deeper
                    asymmetry between where the field is written about and where it is actively
                    being built.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Curation as Scholarly Method</head>
                <p>Digital scholarly projects have increasingly come to occupy the space between
                    research, infrastructure, and public engagement. They take the form of annotated
                    corpora, multimedia archives, interactive platforms, and metadata-rich
                    collections, each demanding modes of expertise that exceed conventional
                    disciplinary boundaries. Their value lies not only in what they present but in
                    how they are structured: in their architecture, their accessibility, their
                    iterative design, and their responsiveness to multiple publics. Yet these forms
                    of labour remain institutionally ambiguous, largely because they fail to
                    resemble the scholarly genres against which academic rigour is measured. This
                    paper takes up one specific instance of digital scholarly work — curation — as a
                    site through which to explore this misrecognition. Curation, as used here,
                    refers not simply to the management or digitisation of materials, but to the
                    interpretive, infrastructural, and methodological labour involved in rendering
                    knowledge accessible, legible, and durable. Through the examination of
                    university-based curatorial projects in India, this section illustrates how
                    curation performs the core functions of scholarship, selection,
                    contextualisation, annotation, and theorisation, yet remains peripheral to
                    academic evaluation.<note> The National Institutional Ranking Framework (NIRF)
                        relies primarily on publication volume, citation indices, and research
                        funding as proxies for research quality. These metrics systematically
                        exclude non-textual, infrastructural, and collaborative digital outputs. See
                            <title rend="italic">NIRF Ranking Methodology Document</title>,
                        2023​</note> In doing so, it offers a critical account of how digital labour
                    is epistemologically central and institutionally marginal. This shift emerges
                    from the confluence of digitisation mandates, public engagement imperatives, and
                    epistemic pressures to account for what the archive omits. As institutions
                    grapple with NAAC’s emphasis on societal outreach, with the <title rend="italic"
                        >National Education Policy's</title> (NEP) call for interdisciplinarity, and
                    with the infrastructural demands of open-access research, curation becomes the
                    method through which these competing obligations are held together. But this
                    method is not neutral. It is situated within linguistic, disciplinary, and
                    technological constraints that determine what is seen, sorted, and
                    sustained.</p>
                <p>Projects like <title rend="italic">Bichitra: The Online Tagore Variorum</title>
                    at Jadavpur University<note>
                        <title rend="italic"> Bichitra</title> is a digital variorum of Rabindranath
                        Tagore’s works, hosted by Jadavpur University. It enables comparative
                        reading across multiple drafts, editions, and translations, and exemplifies
                        editorial scholarship embedded in interface design <ptr
                            target="#jadavpur-university_2013"/>.</note> foreground this convergence
                    of editorial labour and platform design <ptr target="#jadavpur-university_2013"
                    />. Built to enable comparative reading across Tagore’s drafts, revisions, and
                    publications, the project demanded not only philological rigour but
                    infrastructural creativity, interface decisions, metadata categories, encoding
                    hierarchies. The scholarly value of <title rend="italic">Bichitra</title> lies
                    not only in the corpus it curates but in the interpretive scaffolding it
                    invents. As Sukanta Chaudhuri notes, engaging meaningfully with Tagore’s corpus
                    requires more than <quote rend="inline">a simple database of images and
                        transcriptions.</quote> Because of the complexity and variability of
                    Tagore’s works, the platform must offer <quote rend="inline">conceptually
                        fundamental</quote> tools — detailed and structured enough to support
                    serious textual understanding through data mining <ptr target="#chaudhuri_2015"
                        loc="10"/>. The interface becomes the expression of its scholarship.<note>
                        For a technical overview of the platform’s design and textual collation
                        engine, see <ptr target="#chaudhuri-et_al-2015"/>
                        <title rend="quotes">Collation: Prabhed and its predecessors</title>, in
                            <title rend="italic">Bichitra: The Making of an Online Tagore
                            Variorum</title>.</note> Other platforms, like <title rend="italic"
                        >Pad.ma</title> (<title rend="italic">Public Access Digital Media
                        Archive</title>),<note>
                        <title rend="italic"> Pad.ma</title> (<title rend="italic">Public Access
                            Digital Media Archive</title>) is an online video archive built by a
                        network of scholars, activists, and artists. It allows for collaborative
                        annotation of politically sensitive audiovisual materials, often in
                        vernacular contexts <ptr target="#pad.ma_n.d."/>. </note> extend this logic
                    further. Built collaboratively by academics, artists, and software developers,
                    it curates politically sensitive video materials, many in vernacular contexts,
                    and invites users to annotate, challenge, and extend the metadata <ptr
                        target="#pad.ma_n.d."/>. Annotation, in this context, is not descriptive but
                    argumentative. The platform stages disagreement as a method of curation. As
                    Nishant Shah argues, the digital condition reconfigures authorship as a
                    networked, collaborative process shaped by platforms, protocols, and users where
                    meaning is distributed through infrastructural participation <ptr
                        target="#shah_2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#shah_2017"/>. What matters is not who composed the archive, but
                    how it remains open to competing forms of use. Platforms such as <title
                        rend="italic">Khidki Collective</title>
                    <note> See <title rend="italic">Khidki Collective’s</title> digital repository
                        at <ref target="https://www.khidkicollective.in"
                            >https://www.khidkicollective.in</ref>, especially its curated
                        roundtables and multimedia dossiers on regional memory and identity.</note>
                    and <title rend="italic">QAMRA</title>
                    <note> See <title rend="italic">QAMRA’s</title> archive at <ref
                            target="https://qamra.in">https://qamra.in</ref>, which foregrounds
                        affective visual practices and queer life worlds through annotated images
                        and oral narratives.</note> extend the epistemic commitments of digital
                    curation beyond institutional frameworks, staging archival work as an ethical,
                    affective, and infrastructural intervention. <title rend="italic">Khidki
                        Collective</title> works at the intersection of public scholarship and
                    regional memory, translating intellectual histories of the Deccan into
                    accessible multimedia forms <ptr target="#khidki-collective_n.d."/>. Through
                    roundtables, essays, lectures, and curated digital artefacts, <title
                        rend="italic">Khidki</title> renders visible the lived textures of
                    belonging, nostalgia, and spatial identity in a region often flattened by
                    national or metropolitan narratives. <title rend="italic">QAMRA</title>, by
                    contrast, builds a living archive of queer experience in India, foregrounding
                    visual cultures, personal testimony, and affective memory as central modes of
                    historical recovery <ptr target="#qamra_n.d."/>. It reclaims stories long
                    excluded from institutional memory, offering a space where gender, sexuality,
                    and image-making converge in practices of self-representation. In both projects,
                    curation is central to their intellectual positions. Through metadata,
                    interface, and community dialogue, these platforms stage arguments about
                    visibility, legitimacy, and the conditions under which knowledge becomes public.
                    Their work exemplifies a shift in scholarly authority: from the authored
                    monograph to the collaborative infrastructure, from textual finality to
                    care-based design.</p>
                <p> The misrecognition of labour in the Indian university emerges from an evaluative
                    ecosystem that continues to define scholarship through a narrow genealogy of
                    outputs that are textual, authored, bounded, and citation ready. The University
                    Grants Commission’s Academic Performance Index (API), for instance, lists
                    monographs, journal articles, and externally funded projects as primary
                    indicators of scholarly productivity. There is no category for collaborative
                    metadata architecture, no provision for the intellectual design of repositories,
                    no scoring mechanism for the creation of vernacular corpora. The university
                    knows how to read the journal article, the citation, the conference paper. It
                    does not yet know how to read the infrastructure that enables those texts to
                    circulate. As a result, digital curators are forced into a kind of rhetorical
                    double labour: building the archive and then narrating its scholarly legitimacy
                    in a vocabulary not built to accommodate.<note> This reflects widespread
                        institutional practice, as documented informally in faculty review processes
                        and workshops, including <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in India:
                            Learning by Doing</title>
                        <ptr target="#dodd_2024"/>.</note> To curate is not to prepare material for
                    future analysis, but to enact a theory of knowledge in real time. The curator
                    decides what is preserved, how it is described, what forms of access are
                    enabled, and what epistemologies are privileged. To curate is to make an
                    argument about value, legibility, and future use. When universities fail to
                    credit curatorial labour, they erase the methodological ground on which much of
                    today’s scholarship stands. To see curation as a scholarly method is to
                    recognise that form, infrastructure, and public accessibility are not peripheral
                    to knowledge, but constitutive of it. A metadata field is not neutral. A search
                    architecture encodes assumptions. A platform’s openness or opacity determines
                    who can enter and what they will find. The curated collection is itself an
                    intervention into how knowledge is structured, accessed, and authorised.<note>
                        <ptr target="#fitzpatrick_2011"/> and <ptr target="#borgman_2015"/> argue
                        that scholarly value in digital contexts resides not only in content but in
                        infrastructure, such as interface design and metadata logic. See
                        Fitzpatrick, <title rend="italic">The Humanities, Done Digitally</title>,
                        2012; Borgman, <title rend="italic">Big Data, Little Data, No Data</title>,
                        2015.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Curation, then, is not an isolated exception within the university, but a
                    paradigmatic instance of a broader transformation in the form, labour, and
                    temporality of digital scholarly projects. It exemplifies the convergence of
                    research, design, and infrastructure that now characterises much of contemporary
                    humanities work: platforms that are iterative rather than conclusive, authored
                    by teams rather than individuals, structured around access rather than closure.
                    The dilemmas faced by curators — how to render fragments legible, how to encode
                    context, how to build for users not yet imagined — are the dilemmas of digital
                    scholarship writ large. Whether in the creation of linguistic corpora,
                    multimedia editions, data visualisations, or public history portals, the same
                    questions recur: what counts as scholarly method when knowledge is mediated
                    through interface? What forms of rigour are legible to institutions built on
                    print? This examination of curation offers a lens through which we understand
                    how digital projects demand, and produce, a different conceptual grammar of
                    scholarly value. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Verification, Value, and Peer Review</head>
                <p>If digital curation is to be recognised as a legitimate mode of scholarly labour,
                    it must be supported not only through institutional policies but through the
                    rethinking of the evaluative frameworks that govern academic legitimacy. In
                    India, academic value is tethered to a limited set of outputs, peer-reviewed
                    publications, citation counts, and journal rankings, and it is formalised in
                    structures such as the UGC’s Academic Performance Index (API), NAAC’s
                    accreditation rubrics, and funding protocols issued by state research bodies.
                    These systems remain calibrated to traditional textual scholarship. </p>
                <p>To be published, in the academic sphere, is to be sanctioned by a system of
                    editorial and peer oversight whose parameters are historically shaped by
                    print-based models of authorship. Digital projects often fall outside these
                    contours. As such, they challenge the core assumptions upon which scholarly
                    publishing, and the economies it supports, are built. That challenge is
                    precisely why they remain peripheral. Their value is not unrecognised; it is
                    unaccommodated. The problem, then, is not that digital projects are
                    unrecognisable. It is that they are published outside the regimes of value that
                    govern academic credibility. </p>
                <p>A curated archive may involve developers, designers, cataloguers, historians,
                    language specialists, and user interface experts, each contributing a distinct
                    layer of knowledge. Yet institutional frameworks have no grammar to parse this
                    complexity. Who counts as <q>the author</q> of a digital edition? Is the person
                    who designed the metadata schema less of a scholar than the one who wrote the
                    funding proposal? Should the interface designer be acknowledged as a co-author,
                    or merely thanked in the acknowledgements? These questions are not semantic;
                    they determine who is cited, who is promoted, and who is credited. In the
                    absence of clear authorship conventions for multimodal, multi-contributor
                    projects, the scholarly labour embedded in digital work becomes diffused and
                    often invisibilised. </p>
                <p>In response to these conditions, global digital humanities has begun to develop
                    more nuanced models of attribution. The Contributor Roles Taxonomy
                        (CRediT),<note> The Contributor Roles Taxonomy (CRediT) defines fourteen
                        roles commonly used in academic research, including <title rend="quotes"
                            >Conceptualization,</title>
                        <title rend="quotes">Software,</title> and <title rend="quotes">Data
                            Curation,</title> allowing for transparent attribution of scholarly
                        labour. For full details on the Contributor Roles Taxonomy (CRediT), see:
                            <ref target="https://credit.niso.org/">https://credit.niso.org/</ref>
                    </note> now used by many academic journals and digital repositories, lists
                    fourteen contributor roles, from <title rend="quotes">Conceptualization</title>
                    and <title rend="quotes">Data Curation</title> to <title rend="quotes"
                        >Software</title> and <title rend="quotes">Visualization</title>, and allows
                    contributors to be recognised across multiple domains of scholarly labour <ptr
                        target="#brand_2015"/>. Yet this model has not been widely adopted in Indian
                    academic contexts. Technologists, project managers, junior researchers, and
                    curators, those whose labour makes the project legible, are rarely co-authors on
                    the papers that follow.<note> This pattern of uneven authorship credit has been
                        well documented in digital humanities scholarship. Miriam Posner has argued
                        that technologists and project managers — despite being central to project
                        design — are often excluded from authorship in favour of more conventionally
                        recognised intellectual roles (<title rend="quotes">What’s Next: The
                            Radical, Unrealized Potential of Digital Humanities</title>
                        <ptr target="#posner_2012"/>). Lauren Klein and Catherine D’Ignazio
                        similarly demonstrate how infrastructural and care-based labour is
                        disproportionately performed by women and junior scholars and frequently
                        rendered invisible in traditional credit systems (<title rend="italic">Data
                            Feminism</title>, <ptr target="#dignazio_2020"/>). In the Indian
                        context, contributors to large-scale digital projects — such as metadata
                        curators, software developers, and field researchers — rarely receive equal
                        academic credit.</note> Miriam Posner notes that DH projects, while framed
                    as collaborative, often replicate hierarchical authorship structures that
                    obscure technical labour under the guise of neutrality <ptr
                        target="#posner_2012"/>. If DH reconfigures what counts as scholarly labour,
                    then our evaluative frameworks must do the same. This paper argues that the
                    issue is not just attribution but legibility. Who gets named, and how, is not
                    merely a matter of fairness; it is a question of whether we understand
                    scholarship as a solitary act or a distributed process. If digital scholarship
                    makes it harder to locate labour in the figure of a single author, then that is
                    not a flaw, but a conceptual invitation to move beyond a model of scholarly
                    output that privileges authored closure. It is an invitation to adopt protocols
                    that reflect the collaborative, iterative, and infrastructural realities of
                    digital research. </p>
                <p>This challenge of authorship leads to a deeper institutional question: What makes
                    scholarly work verifiable? Peer review has long functioned as a marker of
                    scholarly rigour, but its institutional apparatus, characterised by disciplinary
                    gatekeeping, anonymity, and editorial discretion, has been critiqued as
                    structurally conservative and exclusionary. As Mario Biagioli argues, peer
                    review historically served less as a neutral evaluator of knowledge than as a
                    system for regulating entry into institutional credibility <ptr
                        target="#biagioli_2002"/>. This concern is amplified in digital scholarship,
                    where the epistemic labour often lies not in propositional argument but in
                    metadata design, interface architecture, and sustained infrastructural
                    maintenance, elements that evade traditional criteria for peer evaluation <ptr
                        target="#fitzpatrick_2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#borgman_2015"/>.</p>
                <p>The UGC’s API system, which governs promotions and appointments, allocates credit
                    primarily to traditional textual outputs. As the <title rend="italic">2018 UGC
                        Regulations</title> make clear, research publications only in “refereed
                    journals” and “UGC-listed journals” are considered for API scoring <ptr
                        target="#ugc_2018" loc="Table 3B"/>. Digital resources, such as metadata
                    corpora, interface designs, or collaboratively curated archives, do not appear
                    as recognisable forms of scholarly output within this matrix. NAAC’s SSR follows
                    a similar logic. Digital resources are referenced only under Criterion 4.2,
                    which notes that, “development in the field due to availability of digital mean”
                    and that “providing remote access to eresources in the library have become a
                    matter of necessity” <ptr target="#naac_2020" loc="17"/>. Neither criterion
                    treats digital collections as outputs of research or as authored contributions.
                    Even the <title rend="italic">National Education Policy (NEP) 2020</title>,
                    while foregrounding the importance of digital engagement and interdisciplinary
                    scholarship, limits its references to digitisation and technology to pedagogical
                    transformation and administrative delivery. Chapter 23 encourages the use of
                    technology platforms in higher education and proposes the creation of a
                    “National Educational Technology Forum (NETF)”,<note> The National Educational
                        Technology Forum (NETF) is a policy proposal under NEP 2020 to create an
                        autonomous body that will provide evidence-based guidance on the use of
                        technology in Indian education. As of 2025, it remains in various stages of
                        implementation.</note> yet at no point does the policy define standards for
                    evaluating digital humanities outputs or curatorial research <ptr
                        target="#moe_2020" loc="Ch. 23"/>. In the absence of a framework, the
                    university continues to recognise digital labour only when it is retrofitted to
                    textual form.</p>
                <p>This refusal is institutionalised in systems built to reduce complexity into
                    auditable units. While this is often (and perhaps justifiably) explained as a
                    defence against academic fraud, predatory journals, paper mills, and inflated
                    publication lists, such safeguards have disproportionately favoured conventional
                    publication venues and citation indices. In doing so, they obscure the work of
                    collaborative, multilingual, public-facing digital scholarship. </p>
                <p>There is little published scholarship in India that addresses how curatorial,
                    infrastructural, or multilingual digital labour is evaluated within academic
                    systems. This absence highlights the need for frameworks capable of recognising
                    non-textual, collaborative, and iterative forms of scholarly contribution. Peer
                    review, as global DH scholars have argued, need not remain adversarial or
                    text-bound; it can be collaborative, iterative, and aligned with project life
                    cycles <ptr target="#fitzpatrick_2011"/>. For India, this requires integrating
                    digital scholarship into the API, NAAC’s SSR, and funding frameworks. It demands
                    new workload models that recognise infrastructure-building, multilingual
                    metadata, and collaborative authorship as legitimate forms of knowledge
                        production.<note> While frameworks such as CRediT and the MLA’s <title
                            rend="italic">Guidelines for Evaluating Digital Scholarship</title>
                        touch upon ethical contribution, few explicitly foreground metadata or
                        affective labour as peer-reviewable scholarly components.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Toward a Hybrid Framework for Evaluating Digital Scholarship in India</head>
                <p>If the preceding sections have outlined the epistemic and institutional
                    exclusions faced by digital scholarly projects in India, this section turns
                    toward the question of what might be done. Recognition cannot remain rhetorical;
                    it must be encoded in forms that are legible to the systems that govern
                    scholarly value. The challenge is not only to validate digital scholarship, but
                    to develop evaluative models that are methodologically rigorous, contextually
                    grounded, and structurally embedded. Existing frameworks, such as those proposed
                    by the Modern Language Association (MLA) and the American Historical Association
                    (AHA) have laid important groundwork, particularly in recognising multimodal
                    forms and collaborative labour <ptr target="#mla_2024"/>
                    <ptr target="#aha_2015"/>. But these models remain shaped by infrastructures,
                    workflows, and assumptions drawn largely from Euro-American institutional
                    contexts. In India, digital scholarship unfolds through a different set of
                    conditions: linguistic pluralism, infrastructural asymmetry, project-based
                    labour, and regulatory systems that still privilege the authored monograph over
                    the curated archive, and the textual over the infrastructural. It is in this gap
                    that a hybrid evaluation model becomes necessary as a coherent system attuned to
                    the forms that digital scholarship now takes. What follows is a conceptual
                    framework for recognising scholarly labour where it currently goes
                    unacknowledged. It seeks to account for not just what a project produces, but
                    what it sustains, who it includes, and how it redefines the very conditions of
                    academic work.</p>
                <p>This model draws on existing digital humanities (DH) evaluation frameworks,
                    particularly those developed by MLA, AHA, and NEH, but extends them in key
                    directions to meet the structural, linguistic, and epistemic demands of the
                    Indian academic context. A graphical representation of this can be seen in Table
                    1. </p>
                <table>
                    <head>Four Dimensions of the Hybrid Nature of the Evaluation Model</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Dimension</cell>
                        <cell>Conventional Mode</cell>
                        <cell>Contextual Expansion in Hybrid Model</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1. Global Standards + Local Realities</cell>
                        <cell>International DH evaluation frameworks (MLA, AHA etc.)</cell>
                        <cell>Calibrated to Indian academia (UGC API, NAAC, NEP), resource
                            constraints, linguistic diversity, and cognitive justice
                            traditions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2. Theoretical + Practical Synthesis</cell>
                        <cell>Conceptual critiques of authorship, exclusion, and epistemic
                            legitimacy</cell>
                        <cell>Nine actionable principles to guide peer review, policy reform, and
                            funding evaluation</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3. Multimodal + Textual Legitimacy</cell>
                        <cell>Print-centric, authored, textual outputs as normative forms of
                            scholarly rigour</cell>
                        <cell>Recognition of metadata, platforms, paratexts, vernacular interfaces,
                            ethical design, and care-based infrastructural labour</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4. Institutional Reform + Scholarly Reimagination</cell>
                        <cell>Expanding existing frameworks to include more outputs (e.g., digital
                            articles)</cell>
                        <cell>Rethinking rigour itself: embracing collectivity, iteration,
                            infrastructure, and new epistemic forms beyond textual closure</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <p>What distinguishes this framework is its grounding in the specific epistemic,
                    infrastructural, and institutional conditions of Indian higher education. Unlike
                    existing models developed in Euro-American contexts — which often assume access
                    to stable infrastructure, established digital scholarship ecosystems, and
                    flexible evaluation mechanisms — this framework responds to the lived realities
                    of resource-constrained, multilingual, and policy-driven academic environments.
                    It does not simply adapt global standards; it rethinks what counts as scholarly
                    labour from the ground up. By drawing on Indian intellectual traditions such as
                    cognitive justice,<note> Coined by Shiv Visvanathan, cognitive justice refers to
                        the recognition and co-existence of multiple knowledge systems, including
                        those rooted in vernacular, indigenous, and subaltern traditions, often
                        marginalized by dominant academic epistemologies <ptr
                            target="#visvanathan_2009"/>.</note> and by foregrounding
                    infrastructural, affective, and collaborative work as core scholarly practices,
                    the framework offers a regionally situated yet conceptually expansive model of
                    evaluation. It is not a universal checklist but a context-sensitive structure
                    for recognising rigour, authorship, and innovation in forms long excluded from
                    academic legitimacy. In doing so, it makes a methodological and political claim:
                    that digital scholarship in the global South must be evaluated on its own terms,
                    not by retrofitting it to inherited models, but by building new ones from the
                    critical vocabularies of its own traditions. The nine principles for designing
                    an evaluation framework for digital humanities scholarship in India is listed
                    below:</p>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Multimodal and Multilingual Sensitivity</head>
                    <p>While many global DH frameworks recognise multimodality, few grapple with the
                        linguistic infrastructure of multilingual metadata, vernacular scripting,
                        and transliteration. The hybrid model insists that evaluative criteria must
                        extend beyond usability or aesthetics to include linguistic inclusivity,
                        script variation, and the epistemic labour of cross-script metadata
                        creation. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Infrastructure as Scholarly Proposition</head>
                    <p>Existing frameworks often treat infrastructure as a neutral backdrop. This
                        model rejects that separation. Drawing on Stephen Ramsay’s assertion that
                        building can be an argument, it insists that infrastructure, metadata
                        logics, interface architecture, preservation design, is itself a form of
                        scholarly thought <ptr target="#ramsay_2014"/>. When platforms shape public
                        memory, control access, or generate epistemic visibility, they must be
                        evaluated as propositional forms, not technical supports.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Ongoing and Iterative Evaluation</head>
                    <p>Following Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s call for process-aware review, this model
                        emphasises lifecycle-based evaluation <ptr target="#fitzpatrick_2011"/>.
                        Digital projects, especially in resource-constrained contexts, rarely
                        conform to a linear production timeline. They evolve through failure,
                        feedback, and community uptake. One-time peer review is insufficient.
                        Evaluation must track sustainability, uptake, and iterative responsiveness,
                        recognising that versioning and revision are not signs of instability, but
                        markers of methodological maturity.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Attribution and Distributed Authorship</head>
                    <p>Unlike traditional evaluation models that privilege sole authorship, this
                        framework recognises that digital scholarship is often collaborative and
                        layered. It foregrounds the need to document, credit, and evaluate labour
                        that is infrastructural, affective, or design-based. Building on models like
                        the CRediT taxonomy and adapted for the humanities, the framework insists
                        that project contributors, including metadata specialists, coders, interface
                        designers, and archivists, be formally named and credited. This is
                        particularly urgent in the Indian context, where the labour of project
                        fellows and contract researchers is routinely disaggregated from
                        institutional reward systems.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Embedded Institutional Reform</head>
                    <p>While global evaluative frameworks offer useful models, their institutional
                        assumptions do not always align with the Indian academic context. Here, the
                        challenge is epistemic: Universities continue to privilege abstract,
                        text-bound, and singular authorship models shaped by colonial-modern
                        legacies. A meaningful framework for evaluating digital scholarship in India
                        must draw on local intellectual traditions that interrogate how legitimacy
                        is assigned. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6. Inclusion of Affective and Ethical Labour</head>
                    <p>Projects that deal with marginalised communities, contested memory, or
                        historical trauma involve significant affective and ethical judgement:
                        decisions about anonymity, interface legibility, and representational
                        justice. This labour is often invisible but epistemically central. The
                        hybrid model proposes that ethical curation, not only what is shown, but how
                        and why, is a reviewable scholarly component, particularly when digital
                        projects work with oral histories, sensitive images, or
                        community-contributed data.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>7. Expanded Reviewer Composition</head>
                    <p>Interdisciplinary output demands interdisciplinary review. The hybrid model
                        calls for peer review bodies that include domain experts, curators,
                        designers, technologists, archivists, and community stakeholders, especially
                        in fields where institutional memory is short and where documentation
                        functions as a proxy for argument.<note> The NEH Office of Digital
                            Humanities (USA) includes software developers and metadata specialists
                            in review panels for large-scale infrastructure grants, setting a
                            valuable precedent for interdisciplinary evaluation.</note> This ensures
                        that scholarly labour is reviewed in its own idiom, not judged against
                        inapplicable textual norms.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>8. Processual Paratexts as Scholarship</head>
                    <p>Version logs, data models, controlled vocabularies, documentation protocols,
                        these are not peripheral materials. They are the argumentative scaffolding
                        of the digital project. The hybrid model insists that these be reviewed,
                        cited, and archived with the same seriousness as introductions or literature
                        reviews. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>9. Academic Infrastructure as Public Platform</head>
                    <p>Finally, the hybrid model recognises that in the Indian context, digital
                        projects often stand in for absent state archives. They are infrastructures
                        of access, repair, and public memory. Their review must reflect this dual
                        status, acknowledging that to build a corpus, translate a script, or sustain
                        an archive is to produce knowledge.</p>
                    <p>Below is a visual representation of the proposed evaluation framework:</p>
                    <table>
                        <head> Principles for Evaluating Digital Scholarship</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell>Principle</cell>
                            <cell>Core Idea</cell>
                            <cell>Implication for Evaluation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1. Multimodal and Multilingual Sensitivity</cell>
                            <cell>Recognize cross-script metadata, linguistic diversity, and
                                vernacular infrastructure</cell>
                            <cell>Value metadata creation, transliteration, and multilingual access
                                as scholarly labour</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2. Infrastructure as Scholarly Proposition</cell>
                            <cell>Platforms, metadata, and interfaces are intellectual
                                constructs</cell>
                            <cell>Treat infrastructure design as a scholarly argument, not just
                                technical support</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3. Ongoing and Iterative Evaluation</cell>
                            <cell>Digital projects evolve over time</cell>
                            <cell>Evaluate version history, community uptake, and sustainability as
                                markers of rigour</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4. Attribution and Distributed Authorship</cell>
                            <cell>Credit must reflect collaborative and layered contributions</cell>
                            <cell>Use detailed contributor taxonomies (e.g. CRediT) to acknowledge
                                design, coding, annotation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5. Embedded Institutional Reform</cell>
                            <cell>Align evaluation with India’s epistemic traditions and
                                institutional context</cell>
                            <cell>Integrate cognitive justice and vernacular legitimacy into
                                evaluative models</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>6. Inclusion of Affective and Ethical Labour</cell>
                            <cell>Ethical design and care-based decisions are central</cell>
                            <cell>Treat curatorial judgement, community sensitivity, and
                                representational choices as scholarly input</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>7. Expanded Reviewer Composition</cell>
                            <cell>Review must match interdisciplinary and infrastructural
                                complexity</cell>
                            <cell>Include designers, archivists, coders, and community stakeholders
                                in peer review panels</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8. Processual Paratexts as Scholarship</cell>
                            <cell>Documentation and scaffolding are not supplementary</cell>
                            <cell>Review version logs, data models, and metadata documentation as
                                part of the project’s scholarly output</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>9. Academic Infrastructure as Public Platform</cell>
                            <cell>Digital scholarship often fills the role of absent public
                                institutions</cell>
                            <cell>Evaluate infrastructure not just as research output, but as public
                                epistemic intervention</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>This framework is a local extension of global models — one that recognises
                        that scholarly value in India must account for its infrastructural,
                        multilingual, and political conditions. It treats value as something not
                        only argued, but enacted: in interfaces, in workflows, in care. It responds
                        to a simple proposition: that scholarship today is not just what we say, but
                        what we make possible. The <title rend="italic">National Education Policy
                            2020</title> articulates a future-oriented vision of higher education in
                        India, repeatedly invoking digital transformation, flexible learning
                        pathways, and interdisciplinarity <ptr target="#moe_2020"/>. However, its
                        engagement with digitisation remains largely pedagogical, it champions
                        online education platforms, blended classrooms, and digital literacy
                        initiatives without extending this vision into the realm of research
                        evaluation.</p>
                    <p>A hybrid evaluative framework must fill this lacuna by aligning NEP’s digital
                        ambitions with a recognition of digital scholarly labour. This means
                        acknowledging that the same infrastructures that enable online learning,
                        metadata models, interface architectures, multilingual platforms, are also
                        sites of research and innovation. A truly transformative policy cannot
                        restrict digital engagement to delivery systems; it must account for the
                        epistemic labour of building them.</p>
                    <p>To this end, the National Educational Technology Forum (NETF) and other
                        NEP-linked regulatory bodies<note> For precedent, see the NEH’s Office of
                            Digital Humanities, which provides detailed scoring guidelines for
                            platform design, sustainability, and collaborative authorship in funded
                            proposals.</note> should:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Develop formal evaluation guidelines for digital scholarship,
                            specifying criteria for metadata architecture, interface design, and
                            multilingual content as reviewable components.</item>
                        <item>Create project lifecycle templates that accommodate iterative,
                            collaborative, and versioned outputs, moving away from the linearity
                            assumed in conventional publication timelines.</item>
                        <item>Recommend adoption of attribution models (such as CRediT) for all
                            public-funded research platforms to ensure fair and visible credit
                            across roles.</item>
                        <item>Encourage the development of peer review protocols suited to digital
                            collections, platforms, and archives, possibly through interdisciplinary
                            panels that include technologists, curators, and domain scholars.</item>
                        <item>Mandate institutional reporting of digital scholarly outputs not just
                            as teaching or outreach tools but as research infrastructure under NAAC
                            and NIRF audit categories.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The NEP speaks often of <quote rend="inline">flexibility</quote> and <quote
                            rend="inline">multidisciplinarity</quote>; this framework proposes the
                        criteria that can give those terms academic substance. Without such
                        provisions, the NEP’s digital turn will remain incomplete, expanding access
                        without recalibrating recognition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion: Towards Recognition</head>
                <p>Digital collections are not peripheral to scholarship, they are among its most
                    vital contemporary forms. They materialise scholarly labour in code, metadata,
                    interface, and community practice; they carry argument not only in words but in
                    form and structure. Their marginalisation is not a matter of ambiguity, but of
                    institutional inertia, systems built for a different media ecology, struggling
                    to recognise the contours of digital epistemology. What is required is not token
                    inclusion, but structural realignment: a decisive shift in how we define rigour,
                    interpret method, and assign academic value.</p>
                <p>Though this article has taken digital curation as its focal point, the concerns
                    it raises cut across the entire digital scholarly landscape. The exclusions it
                    traces, the devaluation of infrastructure, the suspicion of collaboration, the
                    invisibilisation of process, are not exclusive to curated archives. They
                    underwrite the institutional reception of linguistic corpora, digital tools,
                    memory projects, and public-facing platforms. Curation offers a particularly
                    generative site of analysis because it embodies the epistemic tensions at the
                    heart of digital scholarship: between permanence and iteration, authorship and
                    collectivity, structure and critique.</p>
                <p>To treat curation as a method is to make a broader claim: that digital
                    scholarship requires a reimagining of what counts as knowledge, and how that
                    knowledge is recognised. It is not the form that must approximate older genres,
                    but the frameworks of evaluation that must evolve. A hybrid evaluative model,
                    grounded in iteration, multilingualism, and infrastructural care, does not
                    dilute standards; it sharpens them. It names the work that has long sustained
                    research in silence. It affirms that metadata is not mere administration, that
                    interface is not mere design, that access is not ancillary to interpretation.
                    This is not a call for parity between digital and print, it is a call to unlearn
                    the hierarchies that have governed scholarly value for too long. The question is
                    not whether digital work meets academic standards, but whether those standards
                    are capacious enough to meet the digital. </p>
                <p>At stake is nothing less than the future of the humanities. A field that cannot
                    acknowledge the infrastructural, distributed, and multimodal conditions of its
                    own present risks rendering itself irrelevant to the very publics it claims to
                    serve. To take digital collections seriously is an act of accountability: to
                    memory, to community, to the evolving forms through which knowledge is built and
                    shared. The task before us is to build the frameworks that can meet these newer
                    forms with clarity and resolve. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aha_2015" label="American Historical Association 2015">American
                    Historical Association. (2015) <title rend="italic">Guidelines for the
                        professional evaluation of digital scholarship by historians</title>.
                    Washington, DC: AHA. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.historians.org/resource/guidelines-on-the-professional-evaluation-of-digital-scholarship-by-historians/"
                        >https://www.historians.org/resource/guidelines-on-the-professional-evaluation-of-digital-scholarship-by-historians/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="biagioli_2002" label="Biagioli 2002"> Biagioli, M. (2002). <title
                        rend="quotes">From book censorship to academic peer review</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Emergences: Journal for the Study of Media &amp; Composite
                        Cultures</title>, 12(1), pp. 11–45.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bhattacharya_2018" label="Bhattacharya 2018">Bhattacharya, D. (2018)
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Notes for a future university</title>, in
                    Bhattacharya, D. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The University Unthought: Notes for
                        a Future</title>. New Delhi: Routledge India, pp. 1–18.​ </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman_2007" label="Borgman 2007">Borgman, C.L. (2007) <title
                        rend="italic">Scholarship in the digital age: Information, infrastructure,
                        and the internet</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman_2015" label="Borgman 2015">Borgman, C.L. (2015) <title
                        rend="italic">Big data, little data, no data: Scholarship in the networked
                        world</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brand_2015" label="Brand et al. 2015">Brand, A., Allen, L., Altman,
                    M., Hlava, M., and Scott, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Beyond authorship:
                        attribution, contribution, collaboration, and credit</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Learned Publishing</title>, 28 (2015): pp151–155. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1087/20150211"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1087/20150211</ref>.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick_2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012">Burdick, A., Drucker, J.,
                    Lunenfeld, P., Presner, T., and Schnapp, J. (2012) <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital_Humanities</title>.Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chaudhuri-et_al-2015" label="Chaudhuri, Bhowmik, and Bose 2015"
                    >Chaudhuri, S., Bhowmik, S., and Bose, S. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Collation:
                        Prabhed and its predecessors</title>, in Chaudhuri, S. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Bichitra: The Making of an Online Tagore Variorum</title>.
                    Cham: Springer, pp. 99–112.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chaudhuri_2015" label="Chaudhuri 2015">Chaudhuri, S. (2015) <title
                        rend="quotes">Tagore’s text,</title> in Chaudhuri, S. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Bichitra: The Making of an Online Tagore Variorum</title>.
                    Cham: Springer (2015), pp. 7–12.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chaudhuri_2018" label="Chaudhuri 2018">Chaudhuri, S. (2018) <title
                        rend="quotes">Re-defining the humanities: Place, meaning, function</title>,
                    in Miri, M. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Place of the Humanities in Our
                        Universities</title>. London: Routledge (2018), pp. 14-25.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dahiya_2025" label="Dahiya et al. 2025">Dahiya, V., Dahiya, L., Ghosh,
                    S., and Chadha, A. (2025) <title rend="quotes">D or H — What leads in DH?
                        Envisaging the digital humanities space in India</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> [advance online
                    publication]. Oxford: Oxford University Press. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqaf091"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqaf091</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="das-gupta_2018" label="Das Gupta 2018" sortKey="Dasgupta">Das Gupta,
                    A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Humanities in the Age of their Digital
                        Operability</title> in Miri, M. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Place of the
                        Humanities in Our Universities</title>. London: Routledge (2018), pp.
                    77-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dignazio_2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020" sortKey="Dignazio"
                    >D’Ignazio, C., and Klein, L.F. (2020) <title rend="italic">Data
                        feminism</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="de-sousa-santos_2014" label="de Sousa Santos 2014" sortKey="Desousa"
                    >de Sousa Santos, B. (2014) <title rend="italic">Epistemologies of the South:
                        Justice against epistemicide.</title> Boulder, CO: Paradigm
                    Publishers.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dodd_2024" label="Dodd and Menon 2024">Dodd, M., and Menon, N. (2024)
                        <title rend="italic">Practices of digital humanities in India: Learning by
                        doing</title>. London: Routledge India. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003325239"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003325239</ref>.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker_2014" label="Drucker 2014">Drucker, J. (2014) <title
                        rend="italic">Graphesis: Visual forms of knowledge production</title>.
                    Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fiormonte_2012" label="Fiormonte 2012">Fiormonte, D. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Towards a cultural critique of the digital humanities</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Historical Social Research / Historische
                        Sozialforschung</title>, 37(3), pp. 59–76. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.12759/hsr.37.2012.3.59-76"
                        >https://doi.org/10.12759/hsr.37.2012.3.59-76</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick_2011" label="Fitzpatrick 2011">Fitzpatrick, K. (2011)
                        <title rend="italic">Planned obsolescence: Publishing, technology, and the
                        future of the academy</title>. New York: NYU Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fricker_2007" label="Fricker 2007">Fricker, M. (2007) <title
                        rend="italic">Epistemic injustice: Power and the ethics of knowing.</title>
                    Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="horvath_2024" label="Horváth et al. 2024" sortKey="Horvatha">Horváth,
                    A., Wagner, C., Wrisley, D.J., Bernardi, J., Chadha, A., Garcia, D., Grallert,
                    T., Ghosh, S., Ishida, Y., Kaye, A., Meden, A., Nagasaki, K., Palmer, D.,
                    Scheithauer, H., Świetlik, M., Tharsen, J., and Wang, Y. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Multilinguality in action: Towards linguistic diversity and inclusion in
                        digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">magazén</title>, 5(2), pp.
                    179–196. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.30687/mag/2724-3923/2024/02/001"
                        >https://doi.org/10.30687/mag/2724-3923/2024/02/001</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="horvath_2025" label="Horváth et al. 2025" sortKey="Horvathb">Horváth,
                    A., Wagner, C., Wrisley, D.J., Bernardi, J., Chadha, A., Garcia, D., Grallert,
                    T., Ghosh, S., Ishida, Y., Kaye, A., Meden, A., Nagasaki, K., Palmer, D.,
                    Scheithauer, H., Świetlik, M., Tharsen, J., and Wang, Y. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Who are the users in multilingual digital humanities?</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, fqaf091.
                    Oxford: Oxford University Press (2025). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqaf091"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqaf091</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jadavpur-university_2013" label="Jadavpur University 2013">Jadavpur
                    University. (2013) <title rend="italic">Bichitra: The Online Tagore
                        Variorum</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://bichitra.jdvu.ac.in"
                        >http://bichitra.jdvu.ac.in</ref> (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khidki-collective_n.d." label="Khidki Collective n.d.">Khidki
                    Collective. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Khidki Collective</title>. Hyderabad
                    Urban Lab. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://hydlab.co.in/programmes-khidki-collective/"
                        >https://hydlab.co.in/programmes-khidki-collective/</ref> (Accessed: 14
                    April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum_2008" label="Kirschenbaum 2008">Kirschenbaum, M.G. (2008)
                        <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New media and the forensic
                        imagination</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moe_2020" label="Ministry of Education 2020">Ministry of Education.
                    (2020) <title rend="italic">National Education Policy 2020</title>. New Delhi:
                    Government of India. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.education.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/NEP_Final_English_0.pdf"
                        >https://www.education.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/NEP_Final_English_0.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mla_2024" label="Modern Language Association 2024">Modern Language
                    Association Committee on Information Technology. (2024) <title rend="italic"
                        >Guidelines for evaluating digital scholarship</title>. Modern Language
                    Association. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.mla.org/About-Us/Governance/Committees/Committee-Listings/Professional-Issues/Committee-on-Information-Technology/Guidelines-for-Evaluating-Digital-Scholarship"
                        >https://www.mla.org/About-Us/Governance/Committees/Committee-Listings/Professional-Issues/Committee-on-Information-Technology/Guidelines-for-Evaluating-Digital-Scholarship</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson_2012" label="McPherson 2012" sortKey="Mcpherson">McPherson,
                    T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Why are the digital humanities so white? or
                        Thinking the histories of race and computation</title>, in Gold, M.K. (ed.)
                        <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University
                    of Minnesota Press, pp. 139–160.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="naac_2020" label="National Assessment and Accreditation Council 2020"
                    >National Assessment and Accreditation Council. (2020) <title rend="italic"
                        >Manual for Self-Study Report (SSR) – Universities</title>. Bengaluru: NAAC.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.naac.gov.in/images/docs/Manuals/Universities-Manual-July-2020.pdf"
                        >https://www.naac.gov.in/images/docs/Manuals/Universities-Manual-July-2020.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pad.ma_n.d." label="Pad.ma n.d.">Pad.ma. (n.d.) <title rend="italic"
                        >Public Access Digital Media Archive</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://pad.ma">https://pad.ma</ref> (Accessed: 14 April
                    2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner_2012" label="Posner 2012">Posner, M. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Think talk make do: Power and the digital humanities</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, 1(2). Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="https://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-2/think-talk-make-do-power-and-the-digital-humanities-by-miriam-posner/"
                        >https://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-2/think-talk-make-do-power-and-the-digital-humanities-by-miriam-posner/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qamra_n.d." label="QAMRA Archive n.d.">QAMRA Archive. (n.d.) <title
                        rend="italic">Queer archive for memory, reflection and activism</title>.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://qamra.in">https://qamra.in</ref> (Accessed:
                    14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay_2014" label="Ramsay 2014">Ramsay, S. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">The hermeneutics of screwing around; or what you do with a
                        million books</title>, in Gold, M.K (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in
                        the Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    pp. 111–120.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_2018" label="Risam 2018">Risam, R. (2018) <title rend="italic"
                        >New digital worlds: Postcolonial Digital humanities in theory, praxis, and
                        pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shah_2010" label="Shah 2010">Shah, N. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Of
                        jesters, clowns and pranksters: YouTube and the condition of collaborative
                        authorship</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Moving Images</title>,
                    8. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://jmionline.org/article/of_jesters_clowns_and_pranksters_youtube_and_the_condition_of_collaborative"
                        >https://jmionline.org/article/of_jesters_clowns_and_pranksters_youtube_and_the_condition_of_collaborative</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shah_2017" label="Shah 2017">Shah, N. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Answers in search of questions: Deliberations on the state of the art in
                        the time of the web</title>, <title rend="italic">Schloss Post</title>.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://schloss-post.com/deliberations-on-the-state-of-the-art-in-the-time-of-the-web/"
                        >https://schloss-post.com/deliberations-on-the-state-of-the-art-in-the-time-of-the-web/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spivak_1988" label="Spivak 1988">Spivak, G.C. (1988) <title
                        rend="quotes">Can the subaltern speak?</title> in Nelson, C. and Grossberg,
                    L. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Marxism and the Interpretation of
                        Culture.</title> Urbana: University of Illinois Press, pp. 271–313.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson_2010" label="Svensson 2010">Svensson, P. (2010) <title
                        rend="quotes">The landscape of digital humanities</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 4(1). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson_2016" label="Svensson 2016">Svensson, P. (2016) <title
                        rend="italic">Big digital humanities: Imagining a meeting place for the
                        humanities and the digital.</title> Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ugc_2018" label="University Grants Commission 2018">University Grants
                    Commission. (2018) <title rend="italic">UGC regulations on minimum
                        qualifications for appointment of teachers and other academic staff in
                        universities and colleges and measures for the maintenance of standards in
                        higher education, 2018</title>. New Delhi: UGC. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.ugc.gov.in/pdfnews/4033931_UGC-Regulation_min_Qualification_Jul2018.pdf"
                        >https://www.ugc.gov.in/pdfnews/4033931_UGC-Regulation_min_Qualification_Jul2018.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="viswanathan_2015" label="Viswanathan 2015">Viswanathan, G. (2015)
                        <title rend="italic">Masks of conquest: Literary study and British rule in
                        India</title>. 25th Anniversary edn. New York: Columbia University
                    Press.​</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="visvanathan_2009" label="Visvanathan 2009">Visvanathan, S. (2009)
                        <title rend="quotes">The search for cognitive justice</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">India Seminar</title>, 597. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.india-seminar.com/2009/597/597_shiv_visvanathan.htm"
                        >https://www.india-seminar.com/2009/597/597_shiv_visvanathan.htm</ref>
                    (Accessed: 14 April 2025).​</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
