<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Politics and Ethics of Naming the Names of 
               Enslaved People in Digital Humanities Projects</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Walter <dhq:family>Hawthorne</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1637-8468</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Michigan State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>WALTERH@msu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Walter Hawthorne</name> is a professor of African, Atlantic, and Digital History at 
                    <name>Michigan State University</name>. He is director of <title rend="italic">Enslaved.org</title> 
                    and an editor of the <title rend="italic">Journal of Slavery and Data Preservation</title>. His 
                    research focuses on the history of Atlantic slavery and the Atlantic trade in enslaved people of 
                    African descent.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Richard <dhq:family>Roberts</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7191-5836</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Stanford University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rroberts@stanford.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Richard Roberts</name> is a Frances and Charles Field Professor of History Emeritus at 
                    <name>Stanford University</name>. He has published widely on the social and legal history of French 
                    <name>West Africa</name>, and he is together with <name>Rebecca Wall</name>, <name>Rachel 
                    Jean-Baptiste</name>, and <name>Babacar Fall</name> one of the co-director of the Senegal Liberations 
                    Project.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Fatoumata <dhq:family>Seck</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-1775-4953</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Stanford University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>fseck@stanford.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Fatoumata Seck</name> is Assistant Professor of French and, by courtesy, of 
                    Comparative Literature at <name>Stanford University</name>. She teaches and researches the 
                    literatures, histories, and cultures of <name>Africa</name> and the African diaspora.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Rebecca <dhq:family>Wall</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7048-8134</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Loyola Marymount University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rebecca.wall@lmu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Rebecca Wall</name> is an assistant professor of History at <name>Loyola Marymount 
                    University</name> in <name>Los Angeles</name>. She has published articles on the environmental and 
                    political history of French <name>West Africa</name> and is completing a book on the twentieth-century 
                    history <name>Senegal River</name>. She is co-director of the Senegal Liberations Project together with 
                    <name>Rachel Jean-Baptiste</name>, <name>Babacar Fall</name>, and <name>Richard Roberts</name>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000781</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#race"/>
               <term corresp="#history"/>
               <term corresp="#ethics"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000781/000781.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
           <p>This introduction provides a broad overview to the context of digital humanities projects dealing 
              with enslaved people and frames the debate over the ethics and politics of using the names of 
              enslaved people. For some descendant communities, listing the names of enslaved people 
              contributes to searches for genealogical connections; for other communities where the stigma of 
              enslaved descent still prevails, such projects may do harm. This introduction explores these 
              issues in relationship to the articles included in this special collection.
           </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>This introduction provides a broad overview to the context of digital humanities projects dealing 
              with enslaved people and frames the debate over the ethics and politics of using the names of 
              enslaved people.
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p><quote rend="inline">Say their names</quote> became one of the central chants of the Black 
               Lives Matter movement following the murders of <name>Trayvon Martin</name>, <name>George 
               Floyd</name>, and <name>Breonna Taylor</name>. Naming names has always been about 
               remembrance, connections, relationships, and identities. <quote rend="inline">The act of 
               naming is an act of power</quote>, writes <name>Katja Guenther</name>. 
               <quote rend="inline">Parents naming children, conquerors naming new lands, and 
               organizations naming themselves all involve the assertion of author and control. Names 
               allow us to communicate through the development of shared meanings</quote> 
               <ptr target="#guenther2009" loc="412"/>. Naming names has also always been seeped in power. 
               The power to name is the power to claim, which is why naming and renaming practices 
               seem central to enslaved people and their descendants.
            </p>
            <p>This collection of essays explores the politics and ethics of listing on open-source, 
               internet-based platforms the names of people of African descent who were enslaved before 
               states mandated abolition and those who were liberated by policies restricting the slave 
               trade. The authors in this special issue raise issues that resonate with 
               internet-based historical studies of other oppressed and vulnerable populations considering 
               several key questions: do historians face unique ethical considerations when 
               making named enslaved people known on publicly accessible websites? When publishing 
               historical findings about enslaved people on the internet, what are our obligations to the 
               subjects of our studies? Should historians who identify enslaved historical actors by name 
               online be concerned about the thoughts and feelings of their descendants today? Should we 
               consult with descendant communities? In brief, the authors of this collection 
               examine some of the ethical implications of studying enslaved people in the Internet Age.
            </p>
            <p>Since the early 2000s, internet platforms that name people of African descent who were 
               enslaved as the result of historical processes rooted in the rise of oceanic trade and 
               growth of capitalist economies have proliferated. <name>Gwendolyn Midlo Hall</name> 
               authored the first such study, 
               <ref target="http://www.ibiblio.org/laslave/"><title rend="italic">Afro-Louisiana History 
               and Genealogy, 1719-1820</title></ref>, which was first published online in 2001. 
               <name>Hall</name> extracted data from archival sources from colonial <name>Louisiana</name> 
               and presented her findings in a searchable dataset. Each line of the dataset 
               has information about one enslaved person, with columns arranged according to 
               characteristics such as name, location, gender, age, skills, value, and more.
            </p>
            <p><name>Hall</name>'s dataset inspired other researchers who have created or are creating a 
               great many internet-based projects that list and tell the histories of named enslaved 
               people of African descent. Most do so through datasets arranged similarly to 
               <name>Hall</name>'s. Those include 
               <ref target="https://www.kinfolkology.org/"><title rend="italic">Kinfolkology</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/"><title rend="italic">Legacies of British Slavery</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://freedomonthemove.org/"><title rend="italic">Freedom on the Move</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="http://www.marronnage.info/fr/corpus.php"><title rend="italic">Le Marronnage dans le Monde Atlantique</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://esclavage-indemnites.fr/public/"><title rend="italic">Esclavage &amp; Indemnités</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://slavery.virginia.edu/universities-studying-slavery/"><title rend="italic">Universities Studying Slavery</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://cesta.stanford.edu/research/senegal-liberations-project"><title rend="italic">The Senegal Liberation Project</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://cds.library.brown.edu/projects/sally/documents.html"><title rend="italic">Voyage of the Slave Ship Sally</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.stkittsslaves.org/"><title rend="italic">An Online Database of the Enslaved on the Sugar Plantations of Robert Cunyngham, 1729-1735</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://runaways.gla.ac.uk/"><title rend="italic">Runaway Slaves in Britain</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.slavesocieties.info/"><title rend="italic">Slave Societies Digital Archive</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://liberatedafricans.org/public/index.php"><title rend="italic">Liberated Africans</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="http://www.texasslaveryproject.org/database/form.php"><title rend="italic">Texas Slavery Project</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://freedomnarratives.org/"><title rend="italic">Freedom Narratives</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://informationwanted.org/"><title rend="italic">Last Seen: Finding Family after Slavery</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://taketheminfamilies.com/"><title rend="italic">Take Them In Families</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.evergreenplantation.org/names-of-the-enslaved"><title rend="italic">Evergreen Plantation</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.hailehomestead.org/enslaved-laborers"><title rend="italic">Historic Haile Homestead</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://thehermitage.com/"><title rend="italic">Andrew Jackson's Hermitage</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.destrehanplantation.org/history/enslaved-registry"><title rend="italic">Destrehan Plantation</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://unsilencing-slavery.org/"><title rend="italic">(Un)Silencing Slavery</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.whitehousehistory.org/spn/introduction"><title rend="italic">Slavery in the President's Neighborhood</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://virginiahistory.org/research/collections/unknown-no-longer-virginia-untold"><title rend="italic">Unknown No Longer</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://archives.novascotia.ca/africanns/"><title rend="italic">African Nova Scotians in the Age of Slavery and Abolition</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="http://slavebiographies.org/"><title rend="italic">Slave Biographies</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="http://slavery.msa.maryland.gov/"><title rend="italic">Legacies of Slavery in Maryland</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://lsc.berkeley.edu/"><title rend="italic">Louisiana Slave Conspiracies</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.monticello.org/enslaveddb/"><title rend="italic">Monticello Enslaved Community Database</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.mountvernon.org/george-washington/slavery/slavery-database"><title rend="italic">Database of Mount Vernon's Enslaved Community</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.africanregisters.org/about.html"><title rend="italic">Oceans and Continents</title></ref>; 
               <ref target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/past/database/african-origins"><title rend="italic">African Origins</title></ref>, 
               which is a part of a larger project titled <ref target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/"><title rend="italic">Slave Voyages</title></ref>; 
               and <ref target="https://enslaved.org/"><title rend="italic">Enslaved.org</title></ref> and its 
               <ref target="https://jsdp.enslaved.org/"><title rend="italic">Journal of Slavery and Data Preservation</title></ref>.
            </p>
            <p>Scholars taking their studies of named enslaved people to the internet display a 
               commitment to values long espoused by social historians. As a field of study, social 
               history emerged in the 1960s and 1970s in reaction to fields that focused on politics, 
               diplomacy, and <q>great men</q>, while ignoring the lived experiences of ordinary people. 
               Social historians embarked on studies of populations across the world. Among the histories 
               they sought to tell were those of Africans and people of African descent in diaspora. In 
               so doing, they responded to the demands of Black activists and university students, who 
               spearheaded the Civil Rights Movement, to create a more inclusive history of the 
               <name>United States</name> and the broader Atlantic world. In studies of enslaved 
               populations, social historians examined resistance to oppression, social lives, family 
               structures, cultures, labor, suffering, and resilience. They debunked myths rooted in 
               racist ideologies and showed that Black populations contributed to the creation of the 
               world we have inherited <ptr target="#stuckey1969"/> <ptr target="#zunz1985"/> 
               <ptr target="#hawthorne2018"/> <ptr target="#stanziani2023"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Since enslaved people of African descent penned precious little about their own lives, 
               social historians developed new methodologies to tell their histories. The violence of 
               enslavement ruptured Black life around the <name>Atlantic</name>. Enslavers tore Africans 
               from their natal homes, transported them far away, renamed them, and structured their 
               lives and the lives of their descendants around labor for capitalist economies. In records 
               they kept, enslavers reduced the enslaved to commodities, erasing much of their history. 
               Therefore, to understand changes in enslaved people's lives over time, social historians 
               utilize methodologies centered on the collecting oral history, analyzing language, 
               studying material culture, and quantifying data found in records recorded by 
               enslavers. In the late 1960s and 1970s, quantitative approaches to the study of enslaved 
               populations involved extracting and standardizing of data from records enslavers 
               recorded and creating large datasets. <name>Philip Curtin</name>'s seminal work, 
               <title rend="italic">The Atlantic Slave Trade: A Census</title> (1972), and <name>Robert 
               William Fogel</name> and <name>Stanley L. Engerman</name>'s <title rend="italic">Time 
               on the Cross: The Economics of American Negro Slavery</title> (1974) exemplified this 
               approach. What resulted were studies of broad populations, but beyond a 
               relatively small number of biographies of exceptional enslaved people, histories of 
               slavery did not often lend themselves to a focus on named individuals. Observing this, 
               <name>Jennifer L. Morgan</name> describes the <quote rend="inline">maddening synchronicity 
               of erasure and enumeration</quote> that has rendered enslaved individuals — especially 
               enslaved women, in <name>Morgan</name>'s account — silent and absent from the historical 
               record and from written histories. Quantitative methods, she continues, have resulted in 
               <quote rend="inline">prisons of meaning … [making] a certain kind of scholarship possible 
               while rendering another quite impossible</quote> <ptr target="#morgan2021"/> 
               <ptr target="#law2022"/> <ptr target="#miller2014"/> <ptr target="#klein2014"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Digital social historians of slavery are addressing the issue of the anonymity of enslaved 
               people in historical studies and reconceptualizing the history of slavery. As they do so, 
               they are challenged by ethical considerations that unique to publication on the 
               internet. An obvious difference between publishing findings about enslaved populations — 
               including lists of names — in print scholarship versus digital scholarship is that digital 
               scholarship, assuming it is open access, is more readily available, free to anyone with a 
               computer and internet connection. Digital projects about named enslaved people are also 
               designed to be searchable — to facilitate the identification of people quickly and easily. 
               Digital projects take history directly to the public, making information about slavery and 
               the named individuals who suffered under it widely available in the <name>United 
               States</name> and anywhere in the world. Further, digital dataset projects 
               often allow researchers to download data that they can  manipulate and analyze with 
               digital tools. And internet-based dataset projects that apply linked, open data principles 
               facilitate the rapid identification of people who appear in more than one dataset. These 
               datasets can then be combined, which enables the telling of fuller life histories 
               (for example, <ref target="https://enslaved.org/">Enslaved.org</ref>).
            </p>
            <p>Many have applauded the proliferation of websites that provide open access information 
               about named enslaved individuals. Such sites are important to African Americans undertaking 
               genealogical research; names are tangible links to a family's past, giving people who have 
               long thought that slavery erased their family history an opportunity to uncover aspects of 
               that history. For some, proven descendancy from enslaved people has been the basis for 
               claims for reparations. Further, educators seeking to diversify their lesson plans by 
               relating the history of slavery through explorations of the lives of named enslaved 
               individuals have benefitted from open-source scholarly websites. Internet sources for the 
               study of slavery can also fill a void in places in the <name>United States</name> that 
               have implemented laws banning books and pedaogy about race, racial oppression, and 
               critical race theory. Teachers in <name>Florida</name> might be hesitant to teach their 
               students about the named enslaved people who <name>James Monroe</name> sold from his 
               plantation in <name>Virginia</name> to <name>Florida</name> to pay debts in the early 
               nineteenth century, but through open-source internet-based datasets, students can explore 
               the lives of <name>Dudley</name> and <name>Eve McGuire</name>, <name>Toby</name> and 
               <name>Betsy</name>, <name>Hope Douglas</name>, and others who were uprooted by Monroe 
               <ptr target="#bon-harper_etal2022"/> <ptr target="#burnett_etal2020"/> (see also 
               <ref target="https://taketheminfamilies.com/"><title rend="italic">Take Them In 
               Families</title></ref>). Such websites tell histories that for some are empowering and 
               for others uncomfortable, in part because they raise awareness of inequalities that 
               existed in the past and might be used to show the persistence of inequalities based on 
               descent through to the present.
            </p>
            <p>By compiling data extracted from primary sources into datasets, digital historians of 
               slavery have pursued some of the methods of quantitative and statistical historians. However, 
               when sources reveal them, they have valued the recording of enslaved people's names so 
               that datasets can be used for broad studies of populations and the writing of 
               biographies and family histories. To be sure, source material usually provides only scant 
               information — shards and fragmentary data — about enslaved individuals, so we will never 
               be able to write rich, cradle-to-grave biographies about the overwhelming majority of 
               those who toiled under enslavement. But the act of naming enslaved people in internet-based 
               scholarship writes them into history; it centers them and indicates that their histories 
               are as important as the histories of elite enslavers. Naming names is a small step toward 
               countering racist narratives of Africans and their descendants as people without history. 
               It makes clear that we can know more than that generalized <q>slaves</q> suffered under 
               oppression and violence. Instead, we can know the names of the enslaved and, if other 
               information is recorded in columns beside names in datasets, get a glimpse into the lives 
               enslaved individuals forged under conditions that were not of their own choosing. Naming 
               names can humanize those who enslavers sought to dehumanize. It advances a social 
               agenda to <q>say their names</q> — to shout the names of those who have died as the result 
               of violence stemming from racism and oppression.
            </p>
            <p>That said, naming names raises thorny ethical and analytical issues. The names historians 
               list in their datasets are not often names that enslaved Africans had been given in their 
               homelands or that enslaved people of African descent in the <name>Americas</name> chose 
               for their children. As wealthy <name>Virginia</name> planter <name>Robert <q>King</q> 
               Carter</name> wrote in 1727 after purchasing enslaved Africans from a trader in the state, 
               <quote rend="inline">I name'd them here &amp; by their names we can always know what sizes 
               they are of &amp; would readily answer to them</quote>. When he handed the Africans over to 
               his overseers, he instructed that the <quote rend="inline">negros both men &amp; women… 
               always go by the names we give them</quote> <ptr target="#berlin1996" loc="251"/>. The 
               stripping of enslaved Africans of their names happened around the <name>Atlantic</name>, 
               as did the process of enslavers naming enslaved children born to women they held in 
               bondage. This raises questions about the ends that historians achieve in listing the names 
               of enslaved people in online datasets. To what extent does the naming of names that appear 
               in sources recorded by enslavers obscure as much as it clarifies? Do names tell us more 
               about enslavers' proclivities — about how they identified those they enslaved — than it 
               does about how the enslaved themselves? If we see ourselves as ethically obliged to make 
               the histories of our subjects known, are we fulfilling that obligation by listing names 
               forced upon them by those who oppressed them?
            </p>
            <p>The reality that enslavers created the archive that we as social historians of slavery 
               rely on raises other ethical considerations. Does the act of transcribing and making 
               publicly available data from an enslaver's account book, which grouped the enslaved into 
               racial categories meant to indicate inferiority based on descent, used demeaning and 
               derogatory language, and assigned monetary values to people based on age, sex, skills, 
               injuries, illnesses, and childbearing capabilities, perpetuate racism from the past into 
               the present? Could our attempts to humanize the enslaved in studies we post online reify 
               again the dehumanizing efforts of enslavers? If so, how can we read against the grain of 
               our sources, explain to our readers the historical context in which they were produced, 
               and use enslavers' records to tell new histories of the enslaved? In the Internet Age, 
               what are our obligations to the dead and especially to those who were marginalized?
            </p>
            <p>A related question is what are our obligations to the living — to descent communities, 
               many of which are marginalized today because of institutional racism that is rooted in the 
               past? Following <name>Jessica Marie Johnson</name>'s call, to what extent should historians 
               who explore the lives of named enslaved individuals on the internet 
               <quote rend="inline">infuse their work with a methodology and praxis that centers the 
               descendants of the enslaved</quote> <ptr target="#johnson2018" loc="71"/>? In some parts 
               of the world, descent communities have applauded internet-based source material that 
               facilitates research into and the teaching of Black history. And Black genealogists have 
               benefitted from access to open-source data linking them to named ancestors. But, as the 
               authors of articles in this collection show, not all descent communities welcome the 
               telling of histories that link them to slavery. Indeed, in certain places a family's 
               descent from named enslaved individuals carries today a social stigma that can cause harm 
               in the present. With this in mind, to what extent should members of descent communities 
               shape how professional historians tell — or purposely silence — the writing and 
               dissemination of history in the Digital Age? What, if anything, should historians consider 
               before making information abotu long-dead named individuals whose stories could give us 
               some new insights into the past accessible and searchable on the internet? Should historians' 
               scholarship first and foremost do no harm? Should we seek to protect the most vulnerable?
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ethics of Dealing with Vulnerable Communities in Digital Humanities Projects</head>
            <p>As <name>Kathleen Tierney writes</name>, <quote rend="inline">people are not born 
               vulnerable, they are made vulnerable… [as] different axes of inequality combine and 
               interact to [generate] systems of oppression…</quote> 
               <ptr target="#tierney2019" loc="127–128"/>. The term <name>vulnerability</name> is derived 
               from the Latin <term xml:lang="la">vulnus</term>, which means <q>wound</q> and has come to 
               refer to the condition of being susceptible to harm in a physical as well as social, 
               psychological, moral, spiritual sense <ptr target="#turner2008" loc="656"/>. Both 
               individuals and groups are vulnerable to harm, but systemic oppression is most often 
               directed against groups. Groups most subject to systemic oppression are those who are 
               defined by the dominant groups as <q>others</q> or as different. The United Nations 
               section on Fighting Racism lists those groups considered most vulnerable. People of 
               African descent, especially the descendants of the victims of the transatlantic slave 
               trade or more recent migrants face <quote rend="inline">discriminatory structures and 
               institutions, legacies of the injustices of enslavement and colonialism</quote> that result 
               in <quote rend="inline">the people of African descent being among the poorest and most 
               marginalized groups who also face alarmingly high rates of police violence, and racial 
               profiling</quote>. The UN's list of vulnerable groups includes indigenous peoples; Roma; 
               Sinti; Travelers; persons belonging to national, ethnic, religious and linguistic 
               minorities; migrants; refugees; asylum seekers; internally displaced people; people 
               living in extreme poverty; LGBTQI+ people; and women. Because of their gender, women and 
               girls face additional discrimination, making them <quote rend="inline">extra 
               vulnerable</quote> <ptr target="#un_n.d."/> <ptr target="#von-benzon_etal2018"/>. 
               Precisely because the descendants of enslaved ancestors are subject to systemic 
               oppression, those of us working with digital projects dealing with these communities need 
               to be especially engaged with the complex and often contradictory ethical issues involved. </p>
            <p>By making evidence of vulnerable communities more accessible through digital methods, our 
               work also <quote rend="inline">surfaces new moral quandaries</quote> that demand deeper 
               exploration of our moral commitments as researchers and our responsibilities to the 
               communities we study. In engaging with these new moral quandaries, <name>Nicholas 
               Proferes</name> draws a distinction between compliant and contemplative ethics. In 
               <name>Proferes</name>'s terms, compliant ethics are shorthand for compliance with the 
               Institutional Review Boards at research universities and centers that provide a 
               utilitarian baseline for the treatment and protection of human subjects in research 
               projects. The IRB ethics compliance framework is derived from broader moral and legal 
               discussions about the uses and abuses of human subjects. Compliant ethics also serve to 
               mitigate risk and liability to the institution. Ethics as contemplation, 
               <name>Proferes</name> argues, is an <quote rend="inline">ongoing practice of inwards 
               reflection about our own actions and about what is right and just</quote> to identify a 
               plurality of values in order to promote respect for persons, justice, and beneficence 
               <ptr target="#proferes2020" loc="416–418, 424"/><note><name>Rhonda Shaw</name> et al. 
               draw the distinction between <quote rend="inline">procedural ethics</quote>, which are 
               involved in seeking formal approval from relevant ethics committees, and 
               <quote rend="inline">ethics in practice</quote>, which refer to 
               <quote rend="inline">everyday, situational, and unanticipated ethical issues that occur 
               when doing research with others</quote> <ptr target="#shaw_etal2020" loc="278"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Precisely because digital humanities provide the possibility of widely sharing 
               data, they also raise a host of ethical issues that emerge from wider accessibility. 
               <name>Proferes</name> identifies three areas where ethical considerations are 
               paramount in digital humanities: data collection, data use, and data sharing. Data 
               collection involves privacy issues; data use involves interrogating the intentions of the 
               creators of the data as well as reflections on its fair use; and data sharing involves 
               reflecting on the original intent of the actors involved by means of sharing the output with 
               the impacted individuals and communities, as well as assessing whether sharing may cause 
               harm to those communities. Digital tools that promote wider sharing thus have their own 
               embedded <q>values</q>, which also need to be interrogated. <name>Proferes</name> calls 
               for an <quote rend="inline">expanded practice of moral contemplation in relationship to 
               digital humanities projects</quote> to identify and confront these embedded 
               <quote rend="inline">morally opaque practices</quote> that surround the values of sharing 
               versus the potential to harm <ptr target="#proferes2020" loc="420–426"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Particularly when dealing with vulnerable groups and communities, the potential for harm 
               must be central to ethical considerations. Vulnerability is not necessarily fixed or 
               static, but rather changes over time. We have to understand vulnerability on two levels: 
               the designation of a vulnerable group and when the individuals in the group 
               <emph>feel</emph> vulnerable. Even for individuals within vulnerable groups, their 
               experiences of vulnerability may wax or wane depending on their changing relationships to 
               inequality and power <ptr target="#shaw_etal2020" loc="279"/>. In our collection of 
               essays, <name>Kelly Duke Bryant</name> raises the special situation of unaccompanied 
               minors in colonial <name>Senegal</name>, many of whom were likely trafficked. 
               <name>Duke Bryant</name> argues persuasively that this group merits special protections 
               precisely because they were most vulnerable (see also <ptr target="#moitt2024"/>). 
               <name>Matthew Hopper</name>, in his essay, focuses on another group of vulnerable people: 
               those who were forcibly liberated from slave ships in the <name>Indian Ocean</name> by 
               European anti-slave-trade squadrons. <name>Hopper</name> argues that these liberated 
               Africans did not consent voluntarily to being liberated, although we can assume 
               that many did not fully understand that their <q>liberation</q> often meant entering into 
               long periods of indenture or apprenticeship (see also <ptr target="#anderson_etal2020"/>).
            </p>
            <p>Compliant ethics provides a one-size-fits-all tool kit for doing no harm: informed 
               consent and confidentiality. When researching living subjects, informed consent certainly 
               mitigates potential harm, and some informants feel empowered by their inclusion in 
               research projects. However, it would be naïve to assume that all subjects granting 
               informed consent do so in situations not marked by significant power imbalances 
               <ptr target="#white_etal2001"/>. The compliant ethical commitment to confidentiality thus 
               also needs to be interrogated. <name>Katja Guenther</name> argues that one of the basic 
               principles in the social sciences is protecting individuals through the use of pseudonyms, 
               which <name>Guenther</name> refers to as the <quote rend="inline">politics of 
               naming</quote>. Far from feeling protected by confidentiality, <name>Guenther</name>'s 
               research subjects, a group of vulnerable and marginalized activist women in a 
               male-dominated society, <quote rend="inline">wanted to be heard…. Yet by guaranteeing 
               their confidentiality, I was in effect denying my respondents the right to be heard; in 
               renaming them through the use of pseudonyms, I was denying them the basic right to be who 
               they are. Equally problematic, I was silencing their challenges of systems of oppression 
               and injustice</quote> <ptr target="#guenther2009" loc="411, 414"/>. In a contemplative 
               section of her essay, <name>Guenther</name> writes that her interest in protecting her 
               subjects from a range of harms that they could not possibly imagine was a 
               <quote rend="inline">patronizing concern</quote>. Guenther concludes that scholars need 
               to better recognize the complexities of the politics of naming and question the general 
               assumption that confidentiality is always the best practice 
               <ptr target="#guenther2009" loc="414, 420"/>. Similarly, <name>Shaw</name> et al. 
               underscore the risks of doing no harm: <quote rend="block">[W]e want to emphasise that 
               risk is a common feature of research engagement and that curtailing or avoiding studies 
               involving sensitive topics may prevent injury, but would also silence people's accounts 
               of their experiences…. Taking a view that vulnerability is a universal feature of the 
               human condition, we think that ethical, emotional and psychological risk is a normal part 
               of doing research with human participants, who voluntarily and openly disclose information 
               about their lives. <ptr target="#shaw_etal2020" loc="289"/></quote>
            </p>
            <p>In ideal research situations, research participants would be empowered to negotiate the 
               issue of naming or anonymity contextually. Empowering participants would also challenge 
               notions of what constitutes vulnerability and what it means to protect the vulernable. 
               <name>Niamh Moore</name> addresses the harm actually done in invoking the <q>do no 
               harm</q> principle, writing that <quote rend="inline">[f]or much of history anonymity did 
               not protect the vulnerable, but excluded women and others from authorship and ownership 
               of their own words, erasing them from the archive, even from history, and in the process 
               creating vulnerability through rending people nameless</quote> 
               <ptr target="#moore2012" loc="332"/>. Particularly in regard to the potentialities of 
               re-using data so crucial to digital humanities, <name>Moore</name> notes that one of the 
               consequences of anonymization in the presentation of primary data is an abstraction of the 
               data that have lost their situatedness or context <ptr target="#moore2012" loc="336"/>. 
               It falls to the researcher to take seriously the intentions of the actors in historical 
               primary sources and those of human subjects in ongoing research.
            </p>
            <p>The issue of naming names in vulnerable and marginal groups has significant political as 
               well as ethical ramifications. To ensure confidentiality and to disguise or change the 
               settings or context may protect vulnerable people from potential harm, but it also leaves 
               intact systems of inequality and oppression. In his research on the discrimination racial 
               minorities face in higher education, <name>Benjamin Baez</name> notes that 
               <quote rend="inline">the failure to disclose important information may have perpetuated the 
               kinds of experiences racial minorities <quote rend="inline">keep having again and 
               again</quote></quote>. <name>Baez</name> likens confidentiality to secrets; both imply 
               concealment. He writes: <quote rend="inline">[A]s with all secrets, there were negative 
               consequences. In failing to expose racism and sexism at the institution, I contributed to the 
               many ways in which the institution and their colleagues harmed the very <q>persons</q> I sought 
               to protect</quote> <ptr target="#baez2002" loc="41"/>. In his call for making research 
               socially transformative, <name>Baez</name> further argues that 
               <quote rend="inline">transformative research, if it is possible, must expose and resist 
               oppression, which is often hidden. To do so, it requires openness and risk-taking</quote> 
               <ptr target="#baez2002" loc="46"/>. By adhering to compliant ethical standards of 
               <q>doing no harm</q> — essentially by keeping secrets — researchers may actually be 
               complicit in maintaining systems of oppression, which entail their own 
               <quote rend="inline">constitutive vulnerability</quote> for vulnerable and marginal 
               groups <ptr target="#bok1989"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Doing no harm is clearly neither easy nor ethical in all situations. Several of our 
               contributors in this special issue disagree about the way forward in regard to naming the 
               names of enslaved people in <name>Senegal</name> and <name>Mali</name>. On the one hand, 
               <name>Duke Bryant</name> argues that enslaved and trafficked minors need extra protection, 
               but <name>Duke Bryant</name> also argues that scholars should be respectful of the 
               prevailing ethos in which raising issues about enslaved status or descent may cause harm. 
               In their roles as scholars of education and pedagogy in <name>Senegal</name>, 
               <name>Mamadou Yéro Baldé</name>, <name>Djibrirou Daouda Ba</name>, and <name>Ismaïla 
               Mbodji</name> seek a middle ground in designing curriculum for middle-cycle students 
               that balances the requirements of Senegalese national standards to train students in 
               critical research, historical skills, and digital literacy that focus on the country's 
               past with the <q>conservative</q> nature of Senegalese society that encourages social 
               stability.
            </p>
           <p>Encouraging social stability may, however, result in concealing social inequalities. In 
              response to calls from marginal and subaltern groups to be included in the continent's 
              history, <name>Ibrahima Thioub</name>, the recently retired rector of the 
              <name>Cheikh Anta Diop University</name> in <name>Senegal</name> and a leading Senegalese 
              historian, has called for the recognition of a new public space in <name>Senegal</name> 
              and throughout <name>Africa</name>. In particular, <name>Thioub</name> sees these emerging 
              public spaces as opportunities to <quote rend="inline">break the silence surrounding 
              slavery [in <name>Africa</name>] and put on the defensive those in power and those groups 
              who defend the status quo</quote> <ptr target="#thioub2021" loc="20"/>. In their 
              contribution to this collection, <name>Marie Rodet</name> and <name>Mamadou Séné 
              Cissé</name> explore in part how descendants of enslaved people in <name>Mali</name> have 
              been mobilizing politically to tell their history, to claim their dignity, and to assert 
              their freedom (see also <ptr target="#hahonou_etal2011"/>). <name>Roberts</name> and 
              <name>Wall</name>, in their essay in this collection, recognize the potential harm that 
              naming the names of enslaved people may have on their descendants but argue that those 
              enslaved people who actively sought their freedom in <name>Senegal</name> wanted formal 
              certificates of liberty in their names and to be inscribed in a register of liberations. 
              They conclude that naming the names of these people honors their actions and contributes 
              to a more complex interpretation of French West African history.
           </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Whose Name? Who Chooses?</head>
            <p>Enslavement and the slave trade, as we have argued, were predicated upon the violence of 
               rupture. Enslavement ruptured a person's connections to family, kin, and community and 
               almost always involved the brutal transfer of the enslaved person far from home and 
               homeland. On top of the physical violence of capture, enslavers subjected enslaved people 
               to the symbolic violence of renaming. Renaming the newly enslaved person was a central 
               part of asserting domination. Renaming also served to erase the previous identity of the 
               enslaved person. Such erasure was not always absolute, and retentions of previous 
               identities often persisted despite efforts to impose domination through naming. This was 
               certainly the case in the classic slave narrative, in which <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> 
               recounts how one of his enslavers gave him the name <name>Gustavus Vassa</name>. 
               <name>Equiano</name> listed both names — <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> and 
               <name>Gustavus Vassa</name> — as the authors of his <title rend="italic">The Interesting 
               Narrative of the Life of <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>, Or <name>Gustavus Vassa</name>, 
               the African</title>, first published in 1789. The use of both names stimulated a lively 
               debate regarding the author's birth, his identity, and the authenticity of the narrative 
               <ptr target="#carretta2005"/> <ptr target="#lovejoy2006"/>. This debate led to a 
               reassessment of the fixedness of names and identities in the Atlantic world during the 
               early modern period. Drawing from his study of <name>Domingues Alvares</name>, 
               <name>James Sweet</name> argues that <quote rend="inline">the <name>Atlantic</name> 
               represented a series of social deaths and rebirths, a repeating circuit of dislocation 
               and dismemberment, marked by an unceasing desire to reconstitute the self through family, 
               friends, and community. His was a history without end, quite literally a feedback loop of 
               subjection and social subjectivities</quote> <ptr target="#sweet2009" loc="304"/>. Far 
               from being fixed and indelible, identities and names were <quote rend="inline">overlapping, 
               shifting, and situational….</quote> <ptr target="#sweet2009" loc="298"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Naming and renaming are about power, even where the power of enslavers was incomplete. 
               In her study of enslaved people in central <name>Mali</name>, <name>Lotte Pelckmans</name> 
               notes that renaming by enslavers <quote rend="inline">consisted of the imposition of a 
               completely new, often degrading identity</quote> <ptr target="#pelckmans2017" loc="257–258"/>. 
               In the southern <name>United States</name>, enslavers regularly renamed newly enslaved 
               people, but almost always by first names only. In a study of the largest same-day slave 
               auction in <name>South Carolina</name> in mid-March 1835, the enslaved people being sold 
               included <name>Humphrey</name>, <name>Hannah</name>, <name>Celia</name>, 
               <name>Charles</name>, <name>Esther</name>, <name>Daniel</name>, <name>Dorcas</name>, 
               <name>Dye</name>, <name>London</name>, <name>Friday</name>, <name>Jacob</name>, 
               <name>Daphne</name>, <name>Cuffee</name>, <name>Carolina</name>, <name>Peggy</name>, and 
               <name>Violet</name> <ptr target="#hawes2003"/>. These names were likely only temporary 
               ones. As enslaved people were bought and sold, they were often subject to multiple 
               renamings by their enslavers as acts of power and possession. Naming and renaming were 
               thus part of the sequence of trauma that slavery imposed on people.
            </p>
            <p>But the power to name did not always reside in the enslaver. We think that it is 
               important to differentiate between who was renaming whom and under what conditions. 
               Enslavers renamed enslaved people to claim ownership and to erase the genealogy of the 
               enslaved. Enslaved people, however, were not entirely powerless in this process. Many, no 
               doubt, retained their names and their genealogies despite what enslavers did, and such 
               retentions became sites of struggle and resistance. Others used aliases, as 
               <name>Kelly Duke Bryant</name> argues in this collection. Especially for enslaved people 
               and their descendants, changing their names was central to a broad 
               <quote rend="inline">repertoire of social possibilities</quote>, according to 
               <name>Gregory Mann</name>'s analysis of names and name changing in colonial French 
               <name>West Africa</name> <ptr target="#mann2002" loc="309–312"/>. Moreover, <name>Lotte 
               Pelckmans</name> refers to enslaved people's acts of changing names in <name>Mali</name> 
               as providing <quote rend="inline">passports</quote> for social mobility 
               <ptr target="#pelckmans2017" loc="257–258"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Changing names was not without consequences, however. In many parts of the world, social 
               knowledge resides in names. Surnames or patronyms are charters for social identity that 
               link individuals to communities and communities to history. While in <name>West 
               Africa</name> many newly enslaved people kept their patronyms, which served as markers of 
               enslaved status in their enslavers' communities, children of enslaved people often 
               carried the patronym of their enslaver, whether or not he was the father of the enslaved 
               mother's children. In <name>West Africa</name>, enslaved men lacked rights of paternity, 
               enslaved female lacked <quote rend="inline">legal husbands</quote>, and children born to 
               enslaved women always belonged to their enslavers <ptr target="#pelckmans2017" loc="262"/> 
               <ptr target="#klein1989" loc="213"/> <ptr target="#mann2002"/>. Carrying the patronyms of
               their enslavers did not mean that enslaved children born in their enslavers' communities 
               were fully integrated. As <name>Martin Klein</name> writes, <quote rend="inline">[s]laves 
               are often reluctant to talk about their origins if they know them at all. This means that 
               any family the slave has is the master's family and any history is the master's 
               history</quote> <ptr target="#klein2005" loc="838"/>. Reflecting on <name>Klein</name>'s 
               argument twenty-five years later, <name>Marie Rodet</name> adds that if 
               <quote rend="inline">slaves and their descendants preferred in some instances to forget 
               their traumatic past</quote>, their efforts were incomplete because 
               <quote rend="inline">colonial and local ideologies at the time of abolition prevented 
               the stigma of slavery from disappearing</quote> <ptr target="#rodet2013" loc="28"/>. 
               Even if the descendants of enslaved ancestors may have preferred to forget their histories, 
               many still retained vivid oral histories and memories. <name>Rodet</name> challenges 
               scholars to learn how to listen better to their informants and ask better questions to 
               elicit these memories. Similarly, <name>Roberts</name> and <name>Wall</name> argue in this 
               collection that place matters in how persistent the stigma of former enslaved identity is: 
               moving away from the community of former enslavers' risks subsistence security but provides 
               for social mobility.
            </p>
            <p>As <name>James Sweet</name> argues, in a world where identities were fluid, name-changing 
               was political and personal <ptr target="#sweet2009"/>. The world of fluid identities was, 
               however, gradually narrowed through the expansion and consolidation of nation states 
               interested in the <quote rend="inline">conquest of illegibility</quote>. <name>James 
               Scott</name> and his colleagues examine this in their exploration of the use of 
               fixed names, a modern invention designed to suppress the 
               <quote rend="inline">utter fluidity of vernacular naming practices</quote> 
               <ptr target="#scott_etal2002" loc="6"/>. Emerging in the fifteenth and sixteenth 
               centuries, the use of surnames surrounded efforts to clarify grants of land and, for noble 
               families, to protect their properties. Surnames also helped to register baptisms and 
               payments of poll taxes. Precise names were essential to inheritance, especially 
               inheritance of large estates and property, and to large-scale military conscription 
               <ptr target="#forrest1989" loc="ch. 2"/> <ptr target="#scott_etal2002" loc="11, 15"/>. 
               Entering such information into written registers emerged coincidentally with the 
               consolidation of state power (see, for example, <ptr target="#scott1998"/> and 
               <ptr target="#desalle2018"/>).
            </p>
            <p>During and after the Napoleonic Wars, the British aggressively pursued treaties with 
               European powers to suppress the maritime slave trade, first in the <name>Atlantic</name> 
               and then in the <name>Indian Ocean</name>. Mixed or so-called joint commissions sat in 
               <name>Freetown</name>, <name>Luanda</name>, <name>Cape Town</name>, <name>Boa Vista</name> 
               in the <name>Cabo Verde Islands</name>, <name>Havana</name>, <name>Rio de Janeiro</name>, 
               <name>Surinam</name>, <name>Spanish Town</name>, <name>New York</name>, and <name>Saint 
               Helena</name>. Their tasks were to adjudicate the capture of slave ships, liberate 
               the enslaved people, and disperse the prize money to the captain and crew that captured 
               the slave ship  <ptr target="#bethel1966"/> <ptr target="#martinez2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#anderson_etal2020"/> <ptr target="#misevich2019"/> 
               <ptr target="#lovejoy_etal2015"/> <ptr target="#pearson2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#lovejoy_etal2020"/>. For the first time in over three centuries, registers 
               of enslaved Africans containing names as well as individual demographic information were 
               more or less systematically maintained.
            </p>
            <p>To date, the most sustained research on registers of liberation of enslaved people from 
               <name>Africa</name> have focused on those produced by these courts and commissions, which 
               operated between 1808 and 1871 and presided over nearly 600 cases 
               <ptr target="#misevich2019" loc="248"/>.<note>Because these registers are dispersed in 
               different locations and often involved producing several copies of each, research on the 
               full potential of these sources is ongoing.</note> According to <name>Henry 
               Lovejoy</name>'s compilation of evidence on liberated Africans, we can estimate that nearly 
               200,000 people were liberated by Vice-Admiralty courts and the Mixed Commissions. In 
               addition, <name>Lovejoy</name>'s network of ongoing research projects suggests that 
               scholars may have access to records regarding 700,000 liberated Africans 
               <ptr target="#la_n.d."/>. The courts and commissions kept records of individual liberated 
               Africans because most were <q>freed</q> into various forms of indenture, military 
               service, guardianship, or resettlement depending upon their gender, age, and perceived 
               health. In <name>Sierra Leone</name>, the courts and commissions liberated 99,752 Africans. 
               Nearly 72% of those liberated settled in <name>Sierra Leone</name>, and around 25% were 
               indentured or conscripted to serve elsewhere in the British empire 
               <ptr target="#anderson2020" loc="1, ch. 3"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Maintaining written registers meant creating both legibility and identity. In the 
               <name>Indian Ocean</name>, as <name>Matthew Hopper</name> describes in this collection, 
               the registers of liberated Africans were modeled on registers of indenture and served 
               equally as forms of surveillance because of the individually identifying information 
               collected for each enslaved African liberated. By collecting biometric evidence, including 
               scarification, these registers provided a useful tool in cases when liberated Africans 
               absconded from their indenture contracts. As such, the registers became, according to 
               <name>Kelly Duke Bryant</name>, points of contact between the state and individuals.
            </p>
            <p>Central to the process of creating legibility and identity, these registers included the 
               names of the enslaved people. With the exception of Muslim societies and 
               <name>Abyssinia</name>, most African societies during this period had tonal languages and 
               did not utilize writing. Thus, the very act of rendering an African's phonetic name into 
               a written form was an act of transformation. In the case of the registers of liberated 
               Africans in <name>Sierra Leone</name> and <name>Havana</name>, literate clerks, most of 
               whom were European, relied on African interpreters to help transcribe African tonal 
               names into the registers. In his study of the <name>Havana</name> registers of liberated 
               Africans, <name>Henry Lovejoy</name> argues that the names clerks entered into the 
               registers reflected the tonal structures of their own native languages, rather than those 
               of the liberated Africans <ptr target="#lovejoy2010" loc="107–135"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Central to the challenge of respecting the names but also the histories of enslaved 
               people is listening to what they tell us. In reflecting on decades of research on slavery 
               in French <name>West Africa</name>, <name>Martin Klein</name> notes that 
               <quote rend="inline">[p]erhaps the most striking conclusion from these interviews is that 
               in these societies those of slave descent do not like to recognize their slave origins even 
               where the person's origins are well-known. This contrasts to the Afro-America quest for 
               <quote rend="inline">roots</quote></quote> <ptr target="#klein1989" loc="211"/>. In 
               West African societies where slavery was based on status rather than race, the persistent 
               discrimination that those of enslaved descent faced was based on the sigma of their 
               ancestors' enslavement. With the end of slavery, enslaved people the world over struggled 
               against former enslavers for more autonomy, the means to secure and protect their 
               families, and the right to work for themselves. Where former enslavers controlled the 
               state and legal access to land and continued to shape social and political ideologies, 
               the social mobility of recently freed people was sharply constrained. Even in <name>West 
               Africa</name>, where enslavers did not control the colonial state, political ideologies and 
               fears of social upheaval helped to sustain existing social hierarchies, the social mobility 
               of the recently freed was also limited. In many cases, the stigma of enslaved status 
               persisted, sometimes for generations, becoming as <name>Benedetta Rossi</name> notes a 
               <quote rend="inline">public secret</quote> that encouraged descendants of enslaved people 
               to continue practicing subservience to descendants of former enslavers 
               <ptr target="#rossi2009" loc="10"/>. Such conservative political ideologies persist to 
               this day in many West African societies, especially in rural areas. 
               <name>Mamadou Yéro Baldé</name>, <name>Djibrirou Daouda Ba</name>, and <name>Ismaïla 
               Mbodji</name> stress this issue in their discussion about how the conservative elements 
               within Senegalese society set limits on the potential of new public-school curriculum 
               regarding the history of slavery and the slave trade in <name>Senegal</name> to address 
               issues of social inequality.
            </p>
            <p>The very nature of maintaining the public secret of a person's enslaved past has harmful 
               consequences not only to those suffering from the stigma of an enslaved past but also to 
               the host society perpetuating these secrets. In her classic study of secrets, the 
               philosopher <name>Sissela Bok</name> noted that <quote rend="inline">[l]ong-term group 
               practices of secrecy … are especially likely to breed corruption and to spread…. When 
               power is joined to secrecy, therefore, and when the practices are of long duration, the 
               danger of [the] spread [of corruption] and abuse and deterioration increases</quote> 
               <ptr target="#bok1989" loc="110"/>. Long-term secrecy is also linked to self-deception. 
               <quote rend="inline">[I]t is secrecy</quote>, <name>Bok</name> writes, 
               <quote rend="inline">that lies at the center of such self-deception…. In deceiving 
               ourselves… we keep secret from ourselves the truth we cannot face</quote> 
               <ptr target="#bok1989" loc="60"/>. The public secrets of enslaved pasts thus are complicit 
               with perpetuating inequalities and discrimination that continue to harm all of society.
            </p>
            <p>As digital social historians of slavery reconceptualize the social history of slavery by 
               charting new paths in data preservation and data sharing, they must also confront the 
               political and ethical challenges involved. Throughout the Atlantic and Indian Ocean 
               worlds, archives detailing the lives of people of color have been neglected. This is in 
               part because many such archives exist in parts of the world that struggle to fund them 
               and because nowhere have archives been immune to the institutional racism that permeates 
               the societies that created and maintain them <ptr target="#nara2021"/>. As a result of 
               underfunding and neglect, much primary source material about the lives of enslaved people 
               has been lost, and much that survives is uncatalogued and decaying. Digital social 
               historians have often preserved primary source materials by digitizing them and making 
               the images available on the internet with accompanying datasets, which can serve as a 
               finding aid to facilitate the identification of individuals listed in the documentation 
               (see especially <ptr target="#ssda_n.d."/>). The preservation and dissemination of data 
               help the community of scholars write social history today and could be foundational for 
               writing social history for generations to come.
            </p>
            <p>However, preservation efforts can be the basis for future research if and only if social 
               historians implement data stewardship plans. In other words, creating datasets with 
               information about named enslaved individuals and posting that information online 
               accomplishes the historian's goals of data preservation and access if and only if 
               websites are designed with an understanding of the questions users might ask of the data 
               and if they are properly maintained and preserved so that data is not lost and remains 
               findable. Historians can be reasonably sure that their published print scholarship will 
               be maintained in libraries for generations. But do they have commitments from 
               their institutions to maintain their digital scholarship into the future? Put another 
               way, if we have a professional obligation to preserve endangered data about the lives of 
               our subjects, are we taking steps to ensure that preservation continues after we are 
               gone? Contrary to the cliché that <q>the internet is forever</q>, in practice digital 
               resources require continual maintenance, human effort, and financial resources.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Contributions to this Special Issue</head>
            <p>In her examination of records of liberated minors in post-emancipation <name>Senegal</name>, 
               <ref target="../000772/000772.xhtml"><name>Kelly Duke Bryant</name></ref> reflects on the 
               ethical balance between accessible knowledge and avoiding transferring the colonial archive's 
               hierarchical and reductive classification systems onto the digital realm. Taking these 
               questions further, she contemplates the importance of the ethical considerations that the 
               names and aliases of the minors themselves play in the research questions under examination.
            </p>
            <p><ref target="../000780/000780.xhtml"><name>Annette Joseph-Gabriel</name></ref> examines 
               how a course centered on digital mapping, tracing the transatlantic movements of enslaved 
               individuals, surpassed traditional boundaries of retrieval. Faced with accounts of an anonymous 
               stowaway's quest for freedom, <name>Joseph-Gabriel</name> investigates the constraints of 
               historical recovery and restoration due to the challenge of archival anonymity and 
               <quote rend="inline">black geographies of flight</quote>. In reflecting on her work with her 
               students in tracing the lives of enslaved individuals in the <name>Caribbean</name> and 
               building a digital website entitled <title rend="italic">Mapping Marronage</title>, 
               <name>Joseph-Gabriel</name> proposes three analytical perspectives that not only explain her 
               digital project but help frame the broader goals of digital projects about slavery. 
               <name>Joseph-Gabriel</name> proposes that we think of these projects through the practices 
               of <q>recovery</q>, <q>hesitation</q>, and <q>unmapping</q>, concepts that she explores more 
               fully in her essay.
            </p>
            <p><ref target="../000776/000776.xhtml"><name>Matthew Hopper</name></ref> explores the ethical 
               dimensions of naming while embarking on a project that delves into the trajectory of liberated 
               enslaved people who transitioned into indentured servants in the <name>Indian Ocean</name>. 
               <name>Hopper</name> leverages an extensive dataset encompassing details like children's names, 
               parents' names, age, height, scarification, and even photographs. Given the distinctly 
               identifiable biometric quality of the data, combined with persistent stigma attached to having 
               enslaved ancestors in many parts of the <name>Indian Ocean</name>, <name>Hopper</name> considers 
               aligning the ethical responsibilities of historians with the considerations associated with 
               biometric data employed by geneticists. In doing so, he draws on an intriguing project pursued by 
               ethically minded researchers in <name>Australia</name>.
            </p>
            <p><ref target="../000768/000768.xhtml"><name>Mamadou Yéro Baldé</name>, <name>Djibrirou Daouda 
               Ba</name>, and <name>Ismaïla Mbodji</name></ref> examine pedagogical techniques for teaching 
               about <name>Senegal</name>'s slave trade in the Senegalese public school middle cycle 
               (comparable to middle school and the first two years of high school in the <name>United 
               States</name>), using digital humanities methodologies and evidence from the 
               <title rend="italic">Senegal Liberations Project</title>. Recognizing the potential 
               divisiveness of explicitly naming enslaved individuals due to societal stigma, they suggest 
               emphasizing ethics through a <quote rend="inline">patriotic perspective</quote>. This 
               pedagogical approach prioritizes interactivity and ethical considerations in historical education.
            </p>
            <p><ref target="../000778/000778.xhtml"><name>Walter Hawthorne</name></ref> examines the ethics 
               of publicly listing names in online databases, contrasting the balance that must be struck 
               between the desire of descendants of enslaved people to learn about their family heritage 
               in some regions with anxieties held elsewhere in the world about revealing enslaved ancestors. 
               Looking closely at one project, <title rend="italic">Enslaved.org</title>, <name>Hawthorne</name> 
               considers how to approach naming and anonymity and urges researchers to be attentive to the specific 
               ethical valences of their projects, particularly in terms of efforts to minimize the 
               continued commodification of enslaved individuals through digital projects. Crucial to 
               the goals of <title rend="italic">Enslaved.org</title> is to eliminate as many barriers 
               as possible to wide digital accessibility by relying on open-source software and establishing 
               sustainable practices.
            </p>
            <p><ref target="../000769/000769.xhtml"><name>Richard L. Roberts</name> and <name>Rebecca E. 
               Wall</name></ref> focus on an ongoing research initiative, the <title rend="italic">Senegal 
               Liberations Project</title>. <name>Roberts</name> and <name>Wall</name> discuss how different 
               descendant communities might have vastly different preferences regarding the anonymization 
               or naming of their enslaved ancestors and how living close to former enslavers impacts this 
               preference. They argue that ethical considerations, while very real, should not deter 
               research, but the preferences of the original enslaved or freed person should be paramount 
               if they are discoverable. For the registers of liberation that they work with, 
               <name>Roberts</name> and <name>Wall</name> conclude that because the enslaved people 
               identified in the registers actively sought their freedom by presenting themselves before 
               French colonial officials and receiving certificates of liberty in their names, they 
               wanted themselves so recognized. To complicate matters, however, many enslaved people 
               sought their liberation together with minor children, who could not give their consent.
            </p>
            <p>In their reflections on a different kind of digital public history project — a 
               web-based oral history project — <ref target="../000773/000773.xhtml"><name>Marie 
               Rodet</name> and <name>Mamadou Séné Cissé</name></ref> explore the ethics and politics of 
               collecting and making public the histories of enslaved people in western <name>Mali</name> 
               who have and continue to struggle against the discrimination and stigma of enslaved descent. 
               Describing their project as a <quote rend="inline">co-production</quote> involving both 
               well-funded researchers and struggling farmers, <name>Rodet</name> and <name>Cissé</name> 
               discuss how they sought to  overcome the asymmetrical relationships in the project, which 
               were made sharper by the digital divide separating the north from the south. Despite the 
               challenges posed by COVID, <name>Rodet</name> and <name>Cissé</name> conclude that their 
               collaboration with the villagers of <name>Bouillagui</name> advances the goals of 
               participatory history-making and the power of digital tools to achieve those goals.
            </p>
            <p>Public-facing digital humanities projects dealing with enslaved people are rich with 
               potentialities for revising the past and restoring human dignity to those who have been 
               reduced to commodities or mere entries in aggregate data. But there are profound ethical, 
               political, and analytical risks to such projects. Digital humanities projects dealing with 
               vulnerable groups must be mindful that they have a duty to do no harm and that conforming to 
               compliant ethics may further anonymize individuals who want to reclaim their histories. The 
               contributors to this special issue do not agree on the best practices for naming 
               the names of enslaved people in all digital slavery projects, but we all agree that project 
               designers must clearly state their ethical practices. We hope that this collection of papers 
               will help all practitioners of digital humanities articulate and address the ethical and 
               political issues inherent in our projects.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Acknowledgements</head>
           <p>The editors gratefully acknowledge the support from <name>Stanford University</name>'s Changing 
              Human Experience project, which provided the means to host the virtual international workshop out 
              of which most of these papers were initially presented. The Changing Human Experience project is 
              designed to promote the public humanities. We also wish to thank the anonymous reviewers for 
              their many helpful suggestions for all the articles in this special edition and <name>Cailin 
              Roles</name> for the most excellent work of transforming our often inchoate writing into clearer 
              prose and the management of the many tasks to go into this collection.
           </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anderson2020" label="Anderson 2020">Anderson, R.P. (2020) <title rend="italic">Abolition in Sierra 
             Leone: Re-Building lives and identities in nineteenth-century West Africa</title>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge 
             University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anderson_etal2020" label="Anderson and Lovejoy 2020">Anderson, R.P. and Lovejoy, H.B. (2020) (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Liberated Africans and the abolition of the slave trade, 1807-1896</title>. Rochester, 
             NY: Rochester University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berlin1996" label="Berlin 1996">Berlin, I. (1996) <title rend="quotes">From Creole to African: 
             Atlantic Creoles and the origins of African-American society in mainland North America</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 53(2), pp. 251-288.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bethel1966" label="Bethel 1966">Bethel, L. (1966) <title rend="quotes">The mixed commissions for the 
             suppression of the transatlantic slave trade in the nineteenth century</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal 
             of African History</title>, 7(1), pp. 79-93.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bon-harper_etal2022" label="Bon-Harper and Stetz 2022">Bon-Harper, S. and Stetz, N. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Enslaved lives documented in the slaveholding of James Monroe, Virginia planter and political 
             figure, 1774-1836</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Slavery and Data Preservation</title>, 3(3), pp. 4-9.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="baez2002" label="Baez 2002">Baez, B. (2002) <title rend="quotes">Confidentiality in qualitative research: 
             Reflections on secrets, power and agency</title>, <title rend="italic">Qualitative Research</title>, 2(1), pp. 35-58.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bok1989" label="Bok 1989">Bok, S. (1989) <title rend="italic">Secrets: On the ethics of concealment and 
             revelation</title>. New York: Vintage.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnett_etal2020" label="Burnett and Violette 2020">Burnett, M.R.W. and Violette, M.H. (2020) 
             <title rend="quotes">Take them in families: The enslaved people of Casa Bianca Plantation, Florida</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of Slavery and Data Preservation</title>, 1(2), pp. 15-21.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnett_etal_n.d." label="Burnett and Violette n.d.">Burnett, M.R.W. and Violette, M.H. (n.d.) 
             <title rend="italic">Take them in families</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://taketheminfamilies.com/">https://taketheminfamilies.com/</ref> (Accessed 9 September 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="carretta2005" label="Carretta 2005">Carretta, V. (2005) <title rend="italic">Equiano, the African: Biography 
             of a self-made man</title>. New York: Penguin.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="curtin1972" label="Curtin 1972">Curtin, P.D. (1972) <title rend="italic">The Atlantic slave trade: A 
             census</title>. Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="desalle2018" label="Desalle 2018">Desalle, P. (2018) <title rend="italic">A history of archival practice</title>. 
             Translated by Margaret Procter. London: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fogel_etal1974" label="Fogel and Engerman 1974">Fogel, R.W. and Engerman, S.L. (1974) <title rend="italic">Time 
             on the cross: The economics of American negro slavery</title>. New York: Norton.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="forrest1989" label="Forrest 1989">Forrest, A. (1989) <title rend="italic">Conscripts and deserters: The army 
             and French society during the revolution and empire</title>. New York: Oxford University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="guenther2009" label="Guenther 2009">Guenther, K.M. (2009) <title rend="quotes">The politics of names: 
             Rethinking the methodological and ethical significance of naming people, organizations, and places</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Qualitative Research</title>, 9(4), pp. 411-421.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hahonou_etal2011" label="Hahonou and Pelckmans 2011">Hahonou, E. and Pelckmans, L. (2011) 
             <title rend="quotes">West African antislavery movements: Citizenship struggles and the legacies of slavery</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Stichproben: Wiener Zeitschrift für kritische Afrikastudien</title>, 20, pp. 141-162.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hall2001" label="Hall 2001">Hall, G.M. (2001) <title rend="italic">Afro-Louisiana history and genealogy, 
             1719-1820</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.ibiblio.org/laslave/">https://www.ibiblio.org/laslave/</ref> (Accessed: 9 September 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawes2003" label="Hawes 2003">Hawes, J.B. (2003) <title rend="quotes">How a grad student uncovered the 
             largest known slave auction in the U.S.</title>, <title rend="italic">Propublica</title>, 16 June. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-grad-student-discovered-largest-us-slave-auction">https://www.propublica.org/article/how-grad-student-discovered-largest-us-slave-auction</ref> 
             (Accessed: 4 August 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawthorne_etal_n.d." label="Hawthorne, Williams, and Rehberger n.d.">Hawthorne, W., Williams, D., and 
             Rehberger, D. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Enslaved: Peoples of the Historical Slave Trade</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://enslaved.org/">https://enslaved.org/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawthorne2018" label="Hawthorne 2018">Hawthorne, W. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The idea of the Atlantic 
             world from an Africanist perspective</title>, in Worger, W.H., Ambler, C., and Achebe, N. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Companion to African history</title>. Hoboken, NJ: Wiley Blackwell, pp. 353-366.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="henrik2020" label="Henrik 2020">Henrik, C. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Vulnerability and vulnerable 
             groups from an intersectionality perspective</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Disaster Risk 
             Reduction</title>, 50, pp. 1-8.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, J.M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Markup bodies: Black [life] 
             studies and slavery [death] studies at the digital crossroads</title>, <hi rend="italic">Social Text</hi>, 36(4), pp. 
             57-79.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein1989" label="Klein 1989">Klein, M.A. (1989) <title rend="quotes">Studying the history of those who would 
             rather forget: Oral history and the experience of slavery</title>, <title rend="italic">History in Africa</title>, 16, pp. 
             209-217.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein2005" label="Klein 2005">Klein, M.A. (2005) <title rend="quotes">The concept of honour and the persistence 
             of servility in the western Sudan</title>, <title rend="italic">Cahiers d'Études Africaines</title>, 3-4, pp. 831-851.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein2014" label="Klein 2014">Klein, M.A. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Understanding the slave experience in 
             West Africa</title>, in Lindsay, L.A. and Sweet, J.W. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Biography and the Black Atlantic</title>. 
             Philadelphia, PA: University of Pennsylvania Press, pp. 48-65.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="law2022" label="Law 2022">Law, R. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Individualising the Atlantic slave trade: The 
             biography of Mahommah Gardo Baquaqua of Djougou (1854)</title>, <title rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Historical 
             Society</title>, 12, pp. 113-140.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="la_n.d." label="Liberated Africans n.d.">Liberated Africans (n.d.) Available at: 
             <ref target="https://liberatedafricans.org/about/essays.php?id=1">https://liberatedafricans.org/about/essays.php?id=1</ref> 
             (Accessed: 12 September 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy2010" label="Lovejoy 2010">Lovejoy, H. (2010) <title rend="quotes">The registers of liberated Africans of 
             the Havana Slave Trade Commission: Transcription methodology and statistical analysis</title>, <title rend="italic">African 
             Economic History</title>, 38, pp. 107-135.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy_etal2020" label="Lovejoy and Anderson 2020">Lovejoy, H. and Anderson, R. (eds) (2020) 
             <title rend="italic">Abolition in Sierra Leone: Re-building lives and identities in nineteenth century West Africa</title>. 
             Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy2006" label="Lovejoy 2006">Lovejoy, P. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Autobiography and memory: Gustavus 
             Vassa, alias Olaudah Equiano, the African</title>, <title rend="italic">Slavery and Abolition</title>, 27(3), pp. 316-347.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy_etal2015" label="Lovejoy and Schwarz 2015">Lovejoy, P.E. and Schwarz, S. (eds.) (2015) 
             <title rend="italic">Slavery, abolition and the transition to colonialism in Sierra Leone</title>. Trenton, NJ: Africa 
             World Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mann2002" label="Mann 2002">Mann, G. (2002) <title rend="quotes">What's in an alias? Family names, individual 
             histories, and historical method in the Western Sudan</title>, <title rend="italic">History in Africa</title>, 29, pp. 309-320.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="martinez2012" label="Martinez 2012">Martinez, J. (2012) <title rend="italic">The slave trade and the origins 
             of international human rights law</title>. New York: Oxford University.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="miller2014" label="Miller 2014">Miller, J.C. (2014) <title rend="quotes">A historical appreciation of the 
             biographical turn</title>, in Lindsay, L.A. and Sweet, J.W. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Biography and the Black Atlantic</title>. 
             Philadelphia, PA: University of Pennsylvania Press, pp. 19-47.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="misevich2019" label="Misevich 2019">Misevich, P. (2019) <title rend="italic">Abolition and the transformation of 
             Atlantic commerce in southern Sierra Leone, 1790s to 1860s</title>. Trenton, NJ: Africa World Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moitt2024" label="Moitt 2024">Moitt, B. (2024) <title rend="italic">Child slavery and guardianship in colonial 
             Senegal</title>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moore2012" label="Moore 2012">Moore, N. (2012) <title rend="quotes">The politics and ethics of naming: Questioning 
             anonymisation in (archival) research</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Social Research Methodology</title>, 
             15(4), pp. 331-340.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="morgan2021" label="Morgan 2021">Morgan, J.L. (2021) <title rend="italic">Reckoning with slavery: Gender, kinship, 
             and capitalism in the early Black Atlantic</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nara2021" label="NARA 2021">National Archives and Records Administration (2021) <title rend="italic">The archivist's 
             task force on racism report to the archivist</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.archives.gov/files/news/archivists-task-force-on-racism-report.pdf">https://www.archives.gov/files/news/archivists-task-force-on-racism-report.pdf</ref> 
             (Accesse: 24 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pearson2012" label="Pearson 2012">Pearson, A. (2012) <title rend="italic">Distant freedom: St. Helena and the 
             abolition of the slave trade, 1840-1872</title>. Liverpool, UK: Liverpool University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pelckmans2017" label="Pelckmans 2017">Pelckmans, L. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Surnames as passports to social 
             mobility? Renaming practices of Fulbe slave descendants in central Mali</title>, in Bellagamba, A., Greene, S., and Klein, M. 
             (eds.) <title rend="italic">African slaves, African masters: Politics, memories, social life</title>. Trenton, NJ: Africa 
             World Press, pp. 255-286.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="proferes2020" label="Proferes 2020">Proferes, N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">What ethics can offer the digital 
             humanities and what the digital humanities can offer ethics</title>, in Shuster, K. and Dunn, S. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Handbook of digital humanities research methods</title>. New York: Routledge, pp. 416-426.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2013" label="Rodet 2013">Rodet, M. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Listening to the history of those who 
             don't forget</title>, <title rend="italic">History in Africa</title>, 40(2013), pp. s27-s29.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rossi2009" label="Rossi 2009">Rossi, B. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Rethinking slavery in West 
             Africa</title>, in Rossi, B. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Reconfiguring slavery: West African trajectories</title>. 
             Liverpool, UK: Liverpool University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="scott1998" label="Scott 1998">Scott, J.C. (1998) <title rend="italic">Seeing like a state: How certain schemes 
             to improve the human condition have failed</title>. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="scott_etal2002" label="Scott, Tehranian, and Mathias 2002">Scott, J.C., Tehranian, J., and Mathias, J. (2002) 
             <title rend="quotes">The production of legal identities proper to states: The case of the permanent family surnames</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Comparative Studies in Society and History</title>, 44(1), pp. 4-44.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="shaw_etal2020" label="Shaw et al. 2020">Shaw, R.M. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Ethics and positionality 
             in qualitative research with vulnerable and marginal groups</title>, <title rend="italic">Qualitative Research</title>, 20(3), 
             pp. 277-293.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ssda_n.d." label="Slave Societies Digital Archive n.d."><title rend="italic">Slave Societies Digital Archive</title> 
             (n.d.) Available at: <ref target="https://slavesocieties.org/about">https://slavesocieties.org/about</ref> (Accessed: 9 
             September 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="stanziani2023" label="Stanziani 2023">Stanziani, A. (2023) <title rend="italic">Tensions of social history: Sources, 
             data, actors and models in global perspective</title>. London: Bloomsbury Academic.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="stuckey1969" label="Stuckey 1969">Stuckey, S. (1969) <title rend="quotes">Relationships between Africans and 
             Afro-Americans</title>, <title rend="italic">Africa Today</title>, 16, pp. 4-9.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sweet2009" label="Sweet 2009">Sweet, J.H. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Mistaken identities? Olaudah Equiano, 
             Domingos Álvares, and the methodological challenges of studying the African diaspora</title>, <title rend="italic">American 
             Historical Review</title>, 114(2), pp. 279-306.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thioub2021" label="Thioub 2021">Thioub, I. (2021) <title rend="quotes">L'esclavage en Afrique: briser le silence 
             sur une question tabou</title>, in Klein, M.A. <title rend="italic">Esclavage et pouvoir colonial en Afrique Occidentale 
             Française</title>. Paris: Karthala, pp. 11-21.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tierney2019" label="Tierney 2019">Tierney, K. (2019) <title rend="italic">Disasters: A sociological approach</title>. 
             London: Polity.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="turner2008" label="Turner 2008">Turner, B.S. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Vulnerability</title>, in Darity, W.A., Jr. 
             (ed.) <title rend="italic">International encyclopedia of the social sciences</title> 2nd ed, vol. 8. Detroit, MI: Macmillan 
             Reference, pp. 656-657.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="un_n.d." label="UN n.d.">The United Nations (n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Vulnerable groups: Who are they?</title> 
             Available at: <ref target="https://www.un.org/en/fight-racism/vulnerable-groups">https://www.un.org/en/fight-racism/vulnerable-groups</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="von-benzon_etal2018" label="von Benzon and van Blerk 2018">von Benzon, N. and van Blerk, L. (eds.) (2018) 
             <title rend="italic">Geographical research with <quote rend="inline">vulnerable groups</quote>: Re-examining methodological 
             and ethical processes</title>. New York: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="white_etal2001" label="White, Miescher, and Cohen 2001">White, L., Miescher, S., and Cohen, D.W. (eds.) (2001) 
             <title rend="italic">African words, African voices: Critical practices in oral history</title>. Bloomington, IN: Indiana 
             University Press. </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zunz1985" label="Zunz 1985">Zunz, O. (ed.) (1985) <title rend="italic">Reliving the past: The worlds of social 
             history</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
