<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Stretched Skulls: Anamorphic Games and the <term>memento mortem
                  mortis</term>
            </title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Stephanie <dhq:family>Boluk</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Vassar College</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>stboluk@vassar.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Stephanie Boluk is a recent graduate from the Department of English at the
                     University of Florida and is now completing a postdoctoral fellowship in the
                     Media Studies program at Vassar College. For more information please visit <ref target="http://stephanieboluk.com">http://stephanieboluk.com</ref>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Patrick <dhq:family>LeMieux</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Duke University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>patrick.lemieux@duke.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Patrick LeMieux is an artist and Ph.D. student in the Department of Art, Art
                     History, and Visual Studies at Duke University. He has exhibited artwork in the
                     Tampa Museum of Art, FSU Museum of Fine Arts, the Samuel P. Harn Museum of Art,
                     and his latest artwork, <title rend="italic">Open House</title>, was featured
                     at SIGGRAPH 2011. For more information please visit <ref target="http://patrick-lemieux.com">http://patrick-lemieux.com</ref>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication: -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000122</idno>
            <idno type="volume">006</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2012-11-01">1 November 2012</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2012-07-30" who="MCC">Encoded article</change>
         <change when="2012-11-01" who="JHF">Updated based on author changes</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>From Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> to Robert
               Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, anamorphic artworks explore the
               tension between mathematical models of vision and an embodied experience of space.
               After reviewing the ways in which anamorphosis has been deployed as a philosophical
               tool for investigating digital media in terms of human phenomenology, specifically
               through the criticism of Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, this paper analyzes how
               contemporary videogames like Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series,
                  <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> by Julian Oliver, and Mark ten Bosch’s
               forthcoming <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> technically, aesthetically, and
               conceptually explore anamorphic techniques. While <title rend="italic">The
                  Ambassadors</title> is famous for its anamorphically skewed skull, a classic
                  <foreign>memento mori</foreign>, we propose that the anamorphic effects of
               videogames can be more accurately described as a <term>memento mortem mortis</term>:
               not reminders of human mortality, but of a nonhuman the death of death. By
               foregrounding the impossibility of ever fully resolving the human experience of
               computational space, the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> in these <q>anamorphic
                  games</q> gestures toward experiential domains altogether indifferent to human
               phenomenology to create allegories of the beyond.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Anamorphic games: allegories of the beyond</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <div>
               <head>The Myth of Mimesis</head>
               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>
                     <title rend="italic">The Origin of Painting: Dibutades Tracing the Portrait of
                        a Shepherd</title> (1785), by Jean-Baptiste Regnault.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>In <title rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</title> (c. AD 77-79), Pliny the Elder
                  recounts two myths of mimesis. In one, the daughter of the Corinthian sculptor
                  Butades, saddened by the imminent departure of her lover, traces the outline of
                  his shadow as it is cast on a wall (<ref target="#figure01">see Figure 1</ref>)
                     <ptr target="#pliny"/>. Inspired by this image, Butades presses clay over the
                  drawing to sculpt a relief portrait based on the silhouette. This myth, which
                  binds drawing and sculpting, does not celebrate the originality or expressivity of
                  the artist’s hand but instead focuses on the possibility of an indexical
                  relationship between light, sight, and representation: an ancient camera activated
                  by the hand of Butades’ daughter. Elsewhere in his <title rend="italic">Naturalis
                     Historia</title>, Pliny recites another well-known myth featuring the painters
                  Zeuxis and Parrhasius who compete to determine the most talented artist <ptr target="#pliny"/>. In the story, Zeuxis paints grapes that look so natural
                  birds fly down to peck at them, but Parrhasius wins the competition by painting
                  curtains that deceive even Zeuxis who attempts to draw them aside to reveal his
                  competitor’s artwork. Like the crows clamoring for figurative fruit, Zeuxis had
                  been tricked by Parrhasius’ <foreign>trompe l’oeil</foreign>. The desire for
                  mimetic representation has fueled the invention of perspectival technologies from
                  Butades’ lovelorn daughter tracing shadows on a wall to Renaissance-era drawing
                  machines tracing light through panes of glass to contemporary ray tracing, an
                  algorithm for rendering photorealistic computer graphics (see Figure 2). What
                  unites these mathematical methods of simulating light is their obligatory and
                  often unexamined process of reducing the human body to a cycloptic camera lens, an
                  abstract optic perfectly positioned to decode perspectival data.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>
                     <title rend="italic">Man Drawing a Lute</title> (1525) by Albrecht Dürer and a
                     typical example of ray tracing</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>But imagine if the sun had begun to set on Butades’ daughter, transforming her
                  lover’s silhouette into a monstrous grotesque? Or if Zeuxis had approached
                  Parrhasius’ painted curtains from an oblique angle, disrupting the two-dimensional
                  illusion of depth? What if Albrecht Dürer’s glass <q>veil</q> had been bumped
                  askew or the algorithms responsible for rendering computer-generated imagery were
                  not calibrated properly? Do these subtle shifts in view or vantage point radically
                  alter the human perception of perspectival images or is optical distortion
                  actually a precondition for mimetic representation? Pliny’s myths of mimesis
                  remain myths because they continue to express the desire for a technological
                  correlate to human sight — a technology capable of rendering a painted, projected,
                  or backlit screen into a transparent, immaterial, or immediate window.<note>In Jay
                     David Bolter and Richard Grusin’s <title rend="italic">Remediation</title>
                     (1999), the concept of <q>immediacy</q> is treated as a powerful fantasy bound
                     in a complex relationship with <q>hypermediacy.</q> Immediacy is the desire for
                     a completely transparent mode of communication through an interface that
                     renders itself invisible to the user while hypermediacy draws attention to the
                     multiple and interconnected layers of mediation at work in an object. As Bolter
                     and Grusin write, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bolter1999">[o]ur culture wants both to multiply its
                        media and to erase all traces of mediation: ideally, it wants to erase its
                        media in the very act of multiplying them</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bolter1999" loc="5"/></cit>. This paradoxical <q>double logic</q> has
                     dominated popular imagination throughout the history of Western art and
                     continues to inform the development of image-making technologies from painting,
                     photography, and film to computer graphics, interface design, and virtual
                     reality. The desire for immediacy is expressed by the privileging of linear
                     perspective which Bolter and Grusin argue <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bolter1999">is still
                        regarded as having some claim to being natural...Meanwhile computer graphics
                        experts, computer users, and the vast audiences for popular film and
                        television continue to assume that unmediated presentation is the ultimate
                        goal of visual representation and to believe that technological progress
                        toward that goal is being made. When interactivity is combined with
                        automaticity and the five-hundred-year-old perspective method, the result is
                        one account of mediation that millions of viewers today find
                        compelling</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bolter1999" loc="30"/></cit>.</note> The fantasy of immediacy
                  stubbornly ignores both the material support of an image and the embodied response
                  of a viewer, reinforcing the notion of a lossless transmission between an abstract
                  set of Cartesian coordinates and an equally abstract Cartesian mind. In contrast,
                  this essay treats anamorphosis as the rule governing vision rather than the
                  exception to <q>normal</q> sight. We argue that there is no central,
                  authoritative, or natural way of seeing despite the way optical technologies
                  simulate the effects of light on the human eye. Even after the centuries-long
                  construction of the modern viewing subject, the most naturalistic representational
                  technologies still suppress a strange supplement. Whether one is examining early
                  painting or traversing the polygonal environments of a virtual world, an
                  anamorphic remainder looms in the interstices between technics, optics, and human
                  perception.</p>
               <p>The possibilities and problems of perspectival rendering have been inherited by
                  the computer graphics industry, a field of research whose design goals and
                  business models are deeply wedded to the history of mimetic technologies. Despite
                  the fact that there are only a finite number of unique polygons, pixels, and
                  processes perceptible to the human eye, the videogame industry, for example,
                  continues to invest in higher and higher visual fidelity. As graphics guru and
                  co-founder of id Software John Carmack noted at the 2011 Electronic Entertainment
                  Expo (E3), rendering technologies are <quote rend="inline" source="#mccormick2011">converging at the
                     limits of our biological systems</quote>
                  <ptr target="#mccormick2011"/>. With graphics approaching the threshold of human
                  perception, an increasing number of computer games are beginning to experiment
                  with alternative spatial, temporal, and optical regimes indigenous to digital
                  environments. Much like the restrained naturalism of Renaissance perspectival
                  rendering led to a more self-conscious and reflexive Mannerist period of visual
                  art, so have the nascent discourses surrounding computer generated imagery and
                  videogaming begun to internalize and amplify the codes of perspective to produce
                  what we call <q>anamorphic games.</q> Anamorphic games overtly dramatize the
                  relationship between sight and simulation, vision and virtual reality and begin to
                  rethink what it means to play with perspective.</p>
               <p>This paper begins with a review of how anamorphosis has been treated as a
                  philosophical tool for exploring the relationship between phenomenology and
                  technology. From Hans Holbein the Younger’s <title rend="italic">The
                     Ambassadors</title> (1533) to Robert Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title> (2001), anamorphic artworks mediate the tension between
                  mathematical models of vision that reduce sight to a single, abstract locus and
                  more fully embodied modes of perception. This tension is made patent in the 3D
                  modeling and real-time graphic processing of computers. Extending the arguments of
                  media theorists Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, we analyze how anamorphosis
                  functions in contemporary videogames. Games like Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series (2008-10), <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>
                  (2007) by Julian Oliver, and Mark ten Bosch’s <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> (forthcoming) feature anamorphic techniques that mark the
                  dissonant registers of time and space produced between human biology and digital
                  media. By perturbing vision in order to problematize the relation between body and
                  code, anamorphic games produce what we call the memento mortem mortis: a reminder
                  of the limits of human phenomenology and a tacit acknowledgment of the desire to
                  think the unthinkable and play in the spaces that exceed the boundaries of
                  perception.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <term>Memento Mortem Mortis</term>
               </head>
               <p>Anamorphosis is a perspectival rendering technique popularized during the
                  Renaissance that results in a strangely stretched, but geometrically viable image.
                  When attempting to <q>decode</q> the distortions applied to a given anamorphic
                  artwork, an onlooker must either assume an oblique viewing angle in relation to a
                  foreshortened image or reflect a catoptrically warped image through a
                  corresponding conic or cylindrical mirror. In 1927, Erwin Panofsky famously
                  characterized traditional perspective as a <quote rend="inline" source="#panofsky1996">symbolic
                     form</quote> loaded with the Western ontology of the stable, fixed, and unified
                  Cartesian subject <ptr target="#panofsky1996"/>. Anamorphosis, on the other hand,
                  is regarded as a marginal visual technique, a <foreign>trompe l’oeil</foreign>
                  that operates according to a different cultural logic, covertly applying pressure
                  to the universality of classical perspective and all its ideological assumptions.
                  But imagine if these assumptions were somehow reversed. Does not perspectival
                  rendering, despite its cultural ubiquity and long history of perceptual
                  conditioning, also require decoding? Is it even possible to see a perfect,
                  perspectival image without minor distortions of eye, angle, and atmosphere
                  intervening? Though ease of rendering and conventions of human sight privilege
                  this particular, historically contingent instance of mimesis, what if every
                  perspectival image is actually anamorphic? What if anamorphosis was not only
                  considered a means of encoding secrets in images, but was itself the secret that
                  lies at the heart of all images?</p>
               <p>Traditionally, perspectival rendering assumes that the position of the viewer is
                  directly in front of and oriented toward the <q>picture plane,</q> a geometric
                  field that typically coincides with the material surface of an image. Conflating
                  the picture plane with the angle and dimension of a canvas, for example, allows
                  geometric projections representing light vectors to intersect with an unambiguous,
                  material support (i.e., the surface of a canvas). This conflation of mathematics
                  and materiality removes the need for difficult, higher level modeling and
                  simplifies the rendering process considerably. The geometry of anamorphic images,
                  however, requires nonstandard viewing angles by intentionally foreshortening the
                  picture plane and decoupling it from the physical geometry of the painting, panel,
                  page, or screen. As an experimental and unconventional technique that produces
                  coded, mannered, and seemingly non-natural imagery, anamorphosis is often regarded
                  as a curiosity, an occasional virtuosic supplement to the catalogue of classical
                  perspective throughout the history of art. But if one acknowledges the fact that
                  any historical coincidence of the imaginary picture plane and the material surface
                  of a painting is merely one particular case within a much larger field of
                  possibility, anamorphosis can be re-thought as the rule, rather than the exception
                  to perspectival image-making.</p>
               <p>From the covers of book jackets to the commercials on television to first-person
                  videogames, contemporary visual culture is dominated by perspectival modes of
                  representation. It is easy to forget that mimetic images, no matter how
                  naturalistic, require a cognitive leap in order to <q>resolve</q> the relationship
                  between a mathematical system of rendering and embodied vision. By explicitly
                  denying the <q>correct</q> viewing position in front of a canvas, anamorphosis
                  forecloses the possibility of ever resolving the human gaze to the geometric
                  parameters of an image. Anamorphic technique foregrounds the biological complexity
                  of binocular vision, the angle of approach, height of the viewer, surface
                  deformations in a medium, and even the atmosphere through which light passes.
                  These anamorphic conditions undergird human perception and demonstrate that
                  classical perspective — what has been culturally coded as natural — remains a
                  constructed, mathematical method of simulating light rather than a practical model
                  of sight. Despite the popular desire for transparent, immediate experiences of
                  media, traditional perspective is impossible to fully realize for viewer and
                  painter alike. Whether standing in front of a painting or grasping a controller,
                  embodied vision is not properly perspectival but <emph>actually anamorphic</emph>,
                  constantly modulated by haptic encounters with the material environment.</p>
               <p>The quintessential example of anamorphosis is Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, a large and meticulously rendered oil painting
                  featuring a strange, anamorphic <q>smear</q> across the bottom of the otherwise
                  typical portrait of two sixteenth-century European diplomats (<ref target="#figure03">see Figure 3</ref>). The men stand costumed and well lit in
                  a carefully proportioned, perspectival space, each with an elbow resting on the
                  foreshortened table. The painting displays a menagerie of symbolic details
                  denoting worldly opulence including fine clothing and foreign textiles, a lute
                  with a book of open sheet music, two globes, and various instruments for
                  navigation and cartography: instruments of rationalism that will help provide the
                     <q>correct</q> perspective for mapping the New World. Yet, if the viewer
                  examines the painting from an unorthodox position below and to the right of the
                  standard viewing angle, the smear congeals into a grinning skull: a subliminal
                     <foreign>memento mori</foreign> hidden in plain sight.<note>It has been
                     suggested that the <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> was originally
                     hung at the top of a staircase and that glimpses of the skull could be caught
                     upon approaching the painting from the bottom left. Turning around upon
                     descending the staircase would also reveal a concealed skull.</note>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> and a detail of
                     the <q>resolved</q> anamorphic skull.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>While the inclusion of subtle reminders of mortality like skulls, time pieces,
                  wilting flowers, or rotting fruit were common among portraits and still lifes
                  produced in medieval and Renaissance Europe, Holbein’s <foreign>memento
                     mori</foreign> is particularly unsettling given its uncanny manifestation
                  through the technique of anamorphic foreshortening.<note>Jacques Lacan writes in
                     the <title rend="italic">Four Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis</title>
                     (1973) that the anamorphic distortion gives access to <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#lacan1998">a
                        dimension that has nothing to do with vision as such — something symbolic of
                        the function of the lack</quote>
                     <ptr target="#lacan1998" loc="88"/></cit>. Read psychoanalytically, Holbein’s
                     anamorphic skull is a <q>trap for the gaze</q> into which the subject
                     disappears. Lacan ultimately concludes his chapter not by distinguishing
                     anamorphosis from traditional perspective, but by arguing that it demonstrates
                     what is implicit in all image production (and by extension the concept of a
                     stable Cartesian subject): <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#lacan1998">In any picture, it is precisely
                        in seeking the gaze in each of its points that you will see it
                        disappear</quote>
                     <ptr target="#lacan1998" loc="89"/></cit>.</note> The anamorphic skull is powerful
                  not because it looks like a skull, but precisely because it does <emph>not</emph>
                  look like a skull. Consider the possibility that this <q>not-skull</q> might
                  reveal nothing to the viewer but paint. A sixteenth century audience, for example,
                  might have missed the skull entirely, only subliminally apprehending a
                  death’s-head upon one last, over-the-shoulder glance from the bottom of a
                  stairwell or threshold of an exit. Though it has the potential to trick the eye,
                  this smear of abject materiality exists within its own ontological (and more
                  specifically mathematical) register and casts an anamorphic doubt back into the
                  previously-perspectival world of the two diplomats. Working with the established
                  cultural tradition of the <foreign>memento mori</foreign>, the artist summons
                  notions of death’s alterity as a metaphor for the ultimate strangeness of both the
                  materiality of paint and the mathematics of perspective. This fleeting glimpse of
                  a death’s head reminds the viewer not of their eventual expiration, but of the
                  (perhaps more unsettling) fact that there exist objects and affects that exceed
                  not only perspectival rendering but human experience all together. The anamorphic
                  skull suggests a world of nonhuman technics that not only lies beyond the
                  limitations of the human body, but is also completely disinterested in the affairs
                  of man and the vagaries of life and death.</p>
               <p>In this respect, it may be more accurate to use the term <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term> than <foreign>memento mori.</foreign> The <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term> transforms the human-centered <q>remembrance of death</q> into
                  the nonhuman <q>remembrance of the death of death</q> — the realization that one
                  day even death will die and despite the impossibility of ever experiencing a world
                  devoid of life, the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> invites the viewer to
                  speculate on the radically attenuated phenomenology and starkly materialist
                  conditions of such a world. Where the <foreign>memento mori</foreign> mobilizes
                  representations of death to challenge human vanity, the <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term> extends this critique beyond morbid anthropocentrisms by
                  summoning not the representations of human death, but the nonhuman processes of
                  technical objects. The result is not the humbling acknowledgement of some
                  thanatological equalizer between all human life, but a call toward philosophical
                  speculation. In this way, the painterly materiality of the anamorphic skull
                  exposes a notion of cosmic indifference that is vaster, more alien, and more
                  terrifying than the anthropocentric concerns of life and death represented through
                  a <foreign>memento mori</foreign>. Throughout the history of painting, the skull,
                  like other depictions of human detritus, has been used to signal human mortality.
                  By stretching these skeletal remains across a separate, foreshortened picture
                  plane that refuses to cohere with the geometry of the painted scene, the
                     <foreign>memento mori</foreign> opens up the yawning abyss of the <term>memento
                     mortem mortis</term>.</p>
               <p>This paper proposes anamorphosis — and those technologies that directly frame
                  their nonhuman components in relation to human phenomenology — as one example of a
                     <term>memento mortem mortis</term>. In anamorphic images, the subject and
                  object never completely resolve for one another, and there remains an
                  incommensurable gap as reflected in Holbein’s painting. In this sense, the human
                  and the skull can never see eye to eye, and <title rend="italic">The
                     Ambassadors</title> functions as an allegory for de-anthropomorphized
                  materiality in the idiom of early-modern painting. Hubert Damisch has argued that
                  mathematical perspective was the dominant mode of image-making in the twentieth
                  century (far more than in previous eras prior to the development of mechanical
                  forms of image inscription such as photography, film, and video <ptr target="#damisch1995" loc="28"/>). Yet these chemical, mechanical, and digital
                  forms of perspectival rendering can still each be regarded as different cases of
                  anamorphosis. All images are anamorphic in so far as they apply the rules of
                  perspectival projection to an ontologically arbitrary and anthropocentric picture
                  plane. The coincidence of the picture plane and material surface of the image is
                  popular because of the convenience of calculating only one projection, rather than
                  the multiple abstractions necessary for anamorphic rendering. Despite the fact
                  that all paintings could be considered anamorphic under this definition, only
                  some, like <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, form a <term>memento
                     mortem mortis</term> by explicitly questioning the necessary relation between
                  the human body, an image’s material support, and the abstract geometries of the
                  perspectival picture plane.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part 1: Anamorphosis and Media Theory</head>
            <div>
               <head>Ergodic Resolution</head>
               <p>For theorists such as Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, anamorphosis functions as a
                  paradigm for understanding digital media. Whereas Aarseth appropriates
                  anamorphosis to examine what he calls <q>ergodic literature</q> and operates from
                  the common assumption that anamorphic images necessarily posit a privileged
                  perspective from which to faithfully reconstruct an image, Hansen embraces
                  anamorphic technique as a model for those aspects of digital media that fail to
                  visually resolve and produce bodily discomfort because of the formal incongruity
                  between inhabitable, haptic space and digital media. We will begin by
                  problematizing Aarseth’s theory of ergodic literature through a close reading of
                     <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, a <q>digital born</q> sculpture by Robert
                  Lazzarini in the tradition of <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>. <title rend="italic">Skulls</title> is featured in Hansen’s writing on the <q>digital
                     any-space-whatever,</q> a term he uses to describe the embodied, proprioceptive
                  sensation produced in response to the disjunct ontological registers of digital
                  media. The affective apprehension of the digital any-space-whatever parallels the
                  speculative gesture of the <term>memento mortem mortis</term>. After gaining an
                  understanding of the anamorphic qualities of digital media, this essay turns
                  toward three anamorphic videogames in order to explore the phenomenological and
                  technological character of human (and nonhuman) play.</p>
               <p>Espen Aarseth’s <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic
                     Literature</title> is a highly influential work of media criticism and an early
                  entry into the nascent field of game studies. Taking examples from print, computer
                  games, hypertext fiction, and electronic literature, Aarseth builds a working
                  theory of <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">ergodic literature,</quote> his term for literary
                  works whose completion requires <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">nontrivial effort</quote> on
                  the part of the reader <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="1–2"/>. By nontrivial
                  effort, Aarseth means the kinetic as well as intellectual labor performed by a
                  reader or player that specifically influences the outcome of a given text or game.
                  Ergodic literature is distinct from most standard forms of writing because it
                  requires meaningful effort above and beyond, for example, turning pages or
                  flipping to the end of a book to read the final chapter. If we consider Aarseth’s
                  model in relation to Holbein’s skull, a viewer’s self-conscious act of bending low
                  to the ground in order to match the oblique angle of anamorphic distortion meets
                  the requirements of ergodic, nontrivial labor. The active engagement required in
                  any attempt to decode or decrypt anamorphic images is what leads Aarseth to make
                  an analogy between early modern techniques of anamorphosis and certain forms of
                  interactive media.</p>
               <p>In the concluding chapter of <title rend="italic">Cybertext</title>, Aarseth
                  defines anamorphosis as a <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">solvable enigma</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="181"/></cit>. For Aarseth, the key quality of
                  anamorphosis is the moment of revelation produced when the distortion of the
                  warped image is resolved through the viewer’s effort to locate the vantage point
                  from which classical perspective is restored. The passage from what he terms
                     <q>aporia</q> to <q>epiphany</q> characterizes anamorphic painting with ergodic
                  literature <ptr target="#aarseth1997"/>. With this in mind, Aarseth interprets the
                  text-based games and interactive fiction of the late seventies and early eighties
                  such as Will Crowther and Don Woods’ <title rend="italic">Colossal Cave
                     Adventure</title> (1975–76) and Infocom's <title rend="italic">Zork</title>
                  trilogy (1980–84) as models of an anamorphic textuality in which the player must
                  work in order for the mystery to be revealed.</p>
               <p>But not all ergodic texts provide puzzles with seemingly concrete answers and
                  Aarseth invents a second category he terms <q>metamorphosis</q> in which mastery
                  and resolution are refused (e.g., Michael Joyce’s <title rend="italic">Afternoon:
                     A Story </title>[1987]). We argue, however, that there is no need for a second
                  category in which to reroute those texts which appear to not have singular
                  interpretations, linear causality, or solvable enigmas waiting at the ready. As
                  suggested in the previous section on the <term>memento mortem mortis</term>,
                  rather than reifying a specific subject position in front of a painting, image, or
                  artifact, the concept of anamorphosis radically critiques all subject positions as
                  tenuous and fraught. Even if there is a viewing angle in which an image becomes
                  more legible, there remains no one <q>correct</q> angle and any resolution the
                  viewer might feel should be met with some skepticism. The anamorphic skull in
                     <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> (1553) is not a <foreign>memento
                     mori</foreign> in the sense that it reminds the viewer of her mortality as she
                  catches a glimpse of the skull through the corner of her eye, but is actually a
                     <term>memento mortem mortis</term> because it calls into question the very
                  concept of a fixed subject and resolved object. Rather than simply serving as a
                  reminder of some distant, future bereft of human life, the <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term> demonstrates that experience itself is already composed from
                  nonhuman assemblages imbricated within a vast network of relations never entirely
                  legible to conscious experience.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Digital Any-Space-Whatever</head>
               <p>In <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media</title> (2004), it is the
                  failure of anamorphic images to be easily assimilated by the human body that Mark
                  Hansen finds relevant to digital forms. Robert Lazzarini’s sculptural installation
                     <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, exhibited at the Whitney Museum of
                  American Art’s 2000 show <title rend="italic">BitStreams</title>, serves as
                  Hansen’s central case study on the issue (<ref target="#figure04">see Figure
                     4</ref>). Like Holbein and other artists using anamorphic techniques,
                  Lazzarini’s artwork engages with the limits of human perception, systems of
                  perspectival projection, and the tension produced between these two orders.
                  Instead of projecting smears of paint across picture planes, Lazzarini builds
                  smeared sculptures that stretch in three-dimensions and challenge the viewer to
                  reconcile vision and proprioception. Where anamorphic images are rendered onto a
                  foreshortened picture plane, Lazzarini’s sculptural process involves applying
                  two-dimensional perspectival effects directly to the geometry of three-dimensional
                  haptic objects.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>A photograph of Robert Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Lazzarini’s digital development process begins by laser scanning a household
                  object, instrument, or weapon to generate an editable polygonal mesh. The points,
                  lines, and planes of these abstract geometries are then mathematically bent,
                  warped, shifted, and distorted before being rapid prototyped. The 3D prototypes
                  serve as templates for sculpting the now-deformed objects, often from the same
                  materials that constitute the original object (e.g., the stretched <title rend="italic">skulls</title> is carved by hand from bone resin). Though this
                  process remains relatively consistent throughout his catalogue of sculptures,
                  Lazzarini's subject matter is selected specifically to enhance the cognitive
                  dissonance created between the physical materiality of his anamorphic sculptures
                  and their perceptual effects <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="199"/>. Ranging from
                  skulls to violins, hammers, teacups, telephones, telephone booths, chairs, knives,
                  revolvers, and brass knuckles, these handheld objects and weapons share one thing
                  in common aside from their anamorphic effects: an ergonomic reference to the human
                  body. It is only through this remarkable conflict between optic and haptic that
                  Lazzarini’s sculptures become tools from another digital dimension, hammers with
                  ungraspable handles.<note>In <title rend="italic">Tool-Being: Heidegger and the
                        Metaphysics of Objects</title>, Graham Harman re-imagines Martin Heidegger's
                     philosophy of objects and the distinction between <q>readiness-to-hand</q> and
                        <q>presence-at-hand.</q> The concept of <q>readiness-to-hand</q> is
                     generally used to refer to the way in which objects are not seen in themselves,
                     but only in terms of their relationship and utility to humans. Thus, the cup is
                     not understood as an object in itself, but defined instead based on its ability
                     to hold liquid. When a cup breaks and becomes <q>presence-at-hand,</q> an
                     encounter with the pure presence of the cup as a being in itself can then
                     occur. The ontology of objects is defined in terms of and against their
                     relevance human users. Harman resists the reduction of objects to human
                     phenomenology and proposes that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#harman2002">the famous tool-analysis
                        holds good for all entities, no matter how useful or useless they might be.
                        Beings themselves are caught up in a continual exchange between
                        presence-at-hand and readiness-to-hand</quote>
                     <ptr target="#harman2002" loc="4"/></cit>. According to Harman, Heidegger’s thinking
                     implicitly contains a far more radical ontology of objects than has been
                     previously assumed. He builds an <q>object-oriented ontology</q> around the
                     idea that objects have a kind of secret life in which they <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#harman2002">withdraw from human view into a dark subterranean reality that never
                        becomes present to practical action any more than it does to theoretical
                        awareness</quote>
                     <ptr target="#harman2002" loc="1"/></cit>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Among this selection of digitally disfigured tools, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> stands apart. These sculptures do not share the same status as
                  the broken, Heideggerian hammer that reveals its nonhuman character only when it
                  ceases to function for a human operator’s intended use. Instead, <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, like <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>
                  before it, conceals a <term>memento mortem mortis</term> that frames nonhuman
                  fields of experience within the register of human utility. The horizon of
                  unthinkability represented in skulls serves as a means to philosophical inquiry.
                  The unthinkable itself becomes a technology — an important (and fully operational)
                  philosophical tool for speculation. The optical instability of Lazzarini’s
                  sculptures draws attention to this speculative horizon as a means of re-inscribing
                  it within the sphere of human perception. Thus, there is a certain irony to the
                  fact that skulls maintains a kind of functionality despite its anamorphic
                  distortions. The fact that viewers cannot fix their gaze on a stable optical
                  regime only intensifies the skulls’ role as a <term>memento mortem mortis</term>.
                  Technically, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> does what it is
                     <emph>supposed</emph> to do — it enables philosophical, aesthetic, and
                  contemplative work.</p>
               <p>Mark Hansen identifies <title rend="italic">skulls</title> as an emblematic object
                  that expresses the embodied as well as the profoundly alienating condition of
                  digital media in <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media</title>.
                  Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title> shifts focus away from the
                  ergonomic, hand-held common objects to the forms of the body itself. Looming in
                  life-scale and carved in bone (yet digitally modeled), <title rend="italic">skulls</title> renders one of the most visually recognizable parts of human
                  anatomy strange and uncanny and is the means through which Hansen describes the
                  incommensurable ontology of a computer. In a chapter titled <title rend="quotes">The Affective Topology of New Media,</title> Hansen argues that Lazzarini’s
                  adaptation of the anamorphic skull from Holbein’s <title rend="italic">Ambassadors</title> is <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">exemplary of digital media
                     art</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. Lazzarini’s sculptures exist physically
                  within three-dimensional space and yet, no matter what angle the distorted objects
                  are viewed from, they fail to visually resolve in a satisfying way. Their hollow
                  eyes refuse to stare back. If an observer closed her eyes and held Lazzarini’s
                  stretched skulls, the contours might resolve to the haptic touch, but as Hansen
                  writes, <title rend="italic">skulls</title>
                  <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">
                     <q>makes sense</q> visually — only within the weird logic and topology of the
                     computer</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. Lazzarini offers an optical distortion
                  designed to disrupt, rather than pacify, the senses. The sculptures, according to
                  Hansen, produce a bodily experience of what he terms the <q>digital
                     any-space-whatever</q> (digital ASW), a proprioceptive sense akin to nausea,
                  vertigo, or ilinx as the body fails to orient itself <ptr target="#caillois2001" loc="12"/>. Hansen writes that in the face of <title rend="italic">skulls</title>
                  <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">you feel the space around you begin to ripple, to bubble, to
                     infold…and you notice an odd tensing in your gut, as if your viscera were
                     itself trying to adjust to this warped space</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="198–9"/></cit>.</p>
               <p>Hansen’s term for this unsettling bodily awareness, the digital ASW, is based on
                  Gilles Deleuze’s cinematic <q>any-space-whatever</q> (ASW) discussed in <title rend="italic">Cinema 1: The Movement-Image</title>
                  <ptr target="#deleuze1986" loc="109"/>. The cinematic ASW is an attempt to
                  describe the empty, dislocated spaces of post-war cinema and distinguish them from
                  the Hollywood logic of pre-war film. What is highlighted in both Deleuze’s and
                  Hansen’s version of the ASW is not the visual perception of this space, but the
                  effects produced on the body. The key difference between the digital ASW and
                  Deleuze’s theory is that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">because it must be forged out of
                     contact with a radically inhuman realm, the digital ASW lacks an originary
                     contact with the space of human activity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="204"/></cit>. As such, the digital ASW emerges within the
                  body when the viewer comes in contact with the nonhuman logic and incommensurable
                  perspectives of computational space. According to Hansen, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">[w]hat <title rend="italic">skulls</title> affords is, consequently, not a
                     direct apprehension of an alien space that <emph>is</emph> digital, but a
                     bodily apprehension of just how radically alien the formal field of the
                     computer is</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="205"/></cit> (emphasis in original). In this sense the
                     <term>memento mortem mortis</term> and the digital ASW go hand in hand. In an
                  artwork like <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, which is as psychologically
                  unsettling as it is proprioceptively disruptive, experiential strangeness quickly
                  transforms into existential thinking when confronted not with mortal remains, but
                  with the irresolvable remainder of the <term>memento mortem mortis</term>. Though
                  Hansen’s concept begins as an embodied, affective apprehension, the digital ASW
                  gestates within the same inclement ontological spaces conceptualized by the
                     <term>memento mortem mortis</term>.</p>
               <p>Following Hansen’s argument, videogames, like all digital media, are built upon
                  formal fields only interpretable by computers. The rapid speed of bits being
                  flipped, the immense scale and mind-numbing repetition of data processing, and
                  even the mechanical flow of electrons can never be visually represented to human
                  experience. Instead, the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> relies on the
                  incongruity between computational and biological forms of space and time that
                  manifest as an embodied and affective response in the human (i.e., Hansen’s
                  digital ASW) to allegorize these invisible processes. Most game designers,
                  however, attempt to mitigate these processes. While a work like <title rend="italic">skulls</title> emphasizes the failure of the viewer to grasp
                  these forever skewed and uncanny objects, most mainstream videogames do not
                  generally make a practice of cultivating sensory discomfort.<note>
                     <p>While a novice player may find the side-scrolling environments of a game
                        like <title rend="italic">Super Mario Bros.</title> (1985) uncanny and
                        baffling, the goal of Shigeru Miyamoto and Nintendo’s developers has always
                        been to create worlds in which the spatial and temporal mechanics can be
                        quickly apprehended and then taken for granted in order to engage in other,
                        more digestible operations. For example, two-dimensional spatializations
                        such as moving left to right (as one might read English or advance forward
                        in the first quadrant of a Cartesian grid) or climbing from bottom to top
                        were exploited by and reinforced in early arcade games and influenced
                        Nintendo’s original titles. However, in <title rend="italic">The Legend Of
                           Zelda</title> (1986), it is only custom and visual literacy that prevents
                        a player from thinking that the player’s avatar, Link, is not floating
                        through a 2D space, a gravityless version of <title rend="italic">Super
                           Mario Bros</title>. In <title rend="italic">Legend of Zelda</title>,
                        rather than assuming the perspective of a side-scrolling cross section, the
                        horizontal and vertical axes correspond to the cardinal directions of an
                        orthographic, bird’s-eye view map. Link’s movement is multi-directional, a
                        significant feat at the time allowing him to walk North, South, East, and
                        West rather than forward, backward, up, and down. While there is nothing
                           <term>necessarily</term> intuitive or natural about this spatial mapping,
                        the game was designed to mitigate the strangeness of navigating this
                        artificial world rather than draw attention to its eccentricities.</p>
                     <p>In <title rend="italic">The Legend of Zelda</title> (1986), there are two
                        in-game locations that explicitly defy Cartesian cartography: the Lost Woods
                        and the Lost Hills. When traveling through these single-screen mazes, Link
                        finds himself endlessly looping, temporarily arrested by a classic gaming
                        trope. Like <title rend="italic">Asteroids</title> (1979) and <title rend="italic">Pacman</title> (1980), if the player’s avatar crosses the
                        edge of the screen, it appears immediately on the opposite side as if
                        teleported instantly from one side of the level to the other. This looping
                        effect is initially counterintuitive because of the morphology of the flat,
                        two-dimensional screen but becomes more and more comfortable as player’s
                        adjust their spatial expectations to the particularities of each game-space.
                        The mazes in <title rend="italic">The Legend of Zelda</title> are relatively
                        straightforward to program. A series of conditional <q>if</q> statements
                        dictate which sequence of directions lead Link out of each repeating
                        landscape. Yet, the mathematical certainty and programmatic simplicity of
                        the Lost Woods and Lost Hills generates complex and sometimes paradoxical
                        topologies. Were a player to attempt to map the twists and turns traversed
                        while rambling through the woods or hills, she would find the geometry of
                        each maze does not cohere with the map of Hyrule. In this case, procedural
                        and haptic logics defining the game-space do not render coherent visual
                        schema. Whether the player realizes it or not, each looping space maps not
                        to the flattened grid on which the rest of Hyrule is mapped, but instead to
                        the topology of a three-dimensional torus.</p>
                  </note> The games we examine in this essay intentionally play within the dissonant
                  registers produced between biological and computational systems. They produce
                  ludic metaphors of the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> to model an engagement
                  with the concept of an unthinkable computational wilderness. Yet, despite their
                  experimentation with alternative haptic and visual regimes, even these games
                  resist pushing the implications of their design to its limits. Rather than forcing
                  the player to stare an inassimilable digital landscape in the face, they offer a
                  fantasy of mastery through the successful completion of goal-oriented tasks and
                  suggest that the body can be acclimated to their eccentric spaces. Flight
                  simulators were developed to combat airsickness, and it is with a similar logic
                  that <q>anamorphic games</q> invite players to test-drive the digital ASW, to make
                  it safe and naturalize the body to the <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">incredible
                     strangeness,</quote>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">odd tensing[s],</quote> and <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">weird
                     sensation[s]</quote> of the <term>memento mortem mortis</term>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="198–9"/>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part 2: Anamorphic Games</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction to Anamorphic Games</head>
               <p>Although thousands of years have passed since Butades’ sculpted silhouette and
                  Zeuxis’ painted grapes, the desire for mimesis remains one of the guiding
                  principles of the videogame industry. W.J.T. Mitchell’s <title rend="italic">Reconfigured Eye: Visual Truth in the Post-Photographic Era</title> (2001),
                  for example, opens with Pliny’s <q>birth of painting</q> and draws a genealogical
                  line from early optical experiments such as Dürer’s glass <q>veil</q> to
                  contemporary digital imaging technologies like ray tracing. Mainstream videogame
                  development participates in this logic, constantly propelled forward by fantasies
                  of <q>realistic,</q> immersive imagery and dematerialized interfaces. As Robert F.
                  Nideffer pithily summarizes: <quote rend="block" source="#nideffer2007">Improved lighting, increasingly
                     accurate physics models, and more believable artificial intelligence (AI) are
                     seen as the next frontier for game engines by many in the industry. For anyone
                     who attends meetings like the Game Developers Conference (GDC), the Electronic
                     Entertainment Expo (E3), or SIGGRAPH, it quickly becomes apparent that these
                     concerns are voiced almost exclusively from the desire to enhance the game
                     world's realism. <ptr target="#nideffer2007" loc="215–16"/>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Realism, in this case, refers to the ability to accurately represent mimetic
                  details like high-resolution, photographic textures and believable camera and
                  character animation. In addition to privileging graphic spectacle, the videogame
                  industry relies on Hollywood’s narrative conventions, which frequently take
                  precedence over aesthetic experimentation and the development of novel game
                  mechanics. Thus it is not realism or naturalism, but, more precisely, a
                     <emph>filmic</emph> realism that defines the aesthetic and narrative
                  sensibilities of many recent commercial games.<note>The emergence and celebration
                     of the <q>cut-scene</q> in the late nineties is perhaps the most egregious way
                     in which games have attempted to translate filmic storytelling into videogame
                     narratives. A survey of the most anticipated games shown at this year’s E3
                     confirms that Nideffer’s observations remain relevant as mainstream games are
                     dominated by Hollywood-style visual and narrative logic. The showpieces are
                     comprised of games like <title rend="italic">Mass Effect 3</title> (2012),
                        <title rend="italic">Modern Warfare 3</title> (2011), <title rend="italic">Battlefield 3</title> (2011), <title rend="italic">Uncharted 3</title>
                     (2011), and <title rend="italic">Far Cry 3</title> (2012), which tempt players
                     with the promise of the richest and most filmically immersive graphics on the
                     market. The ubiquity of the series, as seen in the overwhelming number of game
                     franchises, further demonstrates the conservative conditions under which
                     mainstream games operate. There is generally less stigma attached to videogame
                     sequels when compared to other media as both programmers and gamers alike seem
                     to have a higher tolerance for seriality and repetition. The computational
                     processes driving most games (and software at large) can be easily expanded,
                     modified, and resold — there is always a substantial amount of exchange and
                     appropriation in games at the level of code. Moreover, a game’s narrative is
                     frequently regarded as peripheral to enjoyment of the software compared with
                     modifications of gameplay. As a result, commercial studios are more reluctant
                     to take million-dollar risks on untested intellectual property than simply
                     revise an already-vetted formula when there is less pressure from the market to
                     do so.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Amidst the production of <title rend="italic">Final Fantasy XIV</title>s and the
                  annual <title rend="italic">Madden NFL</title>, however, a transformation has
                  begun to occur. The increased power of home computers, availability of open-source
                  game engines, and prevalence of digital distribution services has catalyzed the
                  development of smaller-scale projects like maphacks and modified engines, social
                  and networked games, augmented and alternate realities, and mobile and web
                  applications. The diffusion of the modes of production, the accessibility of
                  design technologies, number of digital distribution platforms, and the formation
                  of a broader audience has permitted experimental game designers to challenge the
                  representational hegemony of traditional genres to develop alternative forms of
                  artgames, antigames, countergames, overgames, notgames, and metagames.</p>
               <p>The <q>anamorphic games</q> discussed in this essay manipulate time, space, and
                  physics in ways that not only draw attention to the formal logics of the computer,
                  but also attempt to highlight a player’s embodied interaction with graphic
                  technologies. The human body is affectively tuned to negotiate physics and the
                  flow of time and space. Whether deftly crouching to avoid a low overhang or
                  unconsciously sidestepping some four-dimensional form, proprioceptive capacity is
                  largely reflexive. But what happens to these embodied actions when encountering a
                  hybridized space, a mixture of the actual and the virtual that contrasts embodied
                  space-time by deploying anamorphic algorithms? What if a body were required to
                  negotiate two- and three-dimensional spaces simultaneously as with Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> software? Can muscles remember the
                  extra-dimensional abstractions overlaying Julian Oliver’s <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>? And is it possible to render four-dimensional sight as Mark
                  ten Bosch’s <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> claims? The games mentioned
                  here offer the player simulations of a poetic physics, or what Bill Seaman has
                  termed <q>e-phany physics</q> or <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#seaman2000">the code-based authoring of
                     an artificial physics which is consistent within the virtual space, yet does
                     not adhere to the laws of actual physics</quote>
                  <ptr target="#seaman2000" loc="41"/></cit>. So what happens to the body when those
                  internalized dynamics are re-written within poetic simulations? The following
                  videogames create interfaces to allegorize a space beyond the limits of human
                  perception and attempt to hubristically resolve the gulf between technological
                  abstraction and phenomenological action.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>: Anamorphic Architecture and Shadow
                  Play</head>
               <p>When the first generation of home videogame consoles supporting 3D graphic
                  processing was introduced in the mid-nineties, the development of 2D, sprite-based
                  games was temporarily arrested.<note>This generation included notable systems like
                     the Sega Saturn (1994), the Sony PlayStation (1994), and the Nintendo 64 (1996)
                     which ran at least 32-bit graphic processors in order to render the real-time
                     polygonal meshes that make up the perspectival spaces of 3D games.</note> In
                  the flush of fascination with these strange polygonal spaces, the efforts of
                  software engineers and game designers alike were redirected from painting with
                  pixels to domesticating and naturalizing 3D environments for mainstream
                     consumption.<note>Nintendo’s transition from 2D to 3D games demonstrates the
                     challenges of adjusting to these new spaces. Remembering the difficult launch
                     of <title rend="italic">Super Mario 64</title> (1996), a release title for the
                     Nintendo 64, Shigeru Miyamato remarked in a conversation with Nintendo’s CEO
                     Satoru Iwata that the reason why 3D action games were unpopular was because of
                     how common it was for <quote rend="inline" source="#iwata2011">people to get motion
                        sickness</quote> and that it was <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#iwata2011">easy to get lost in
                        the playing field</quote>
                     <ptr target="#iwata2011"/></cit>. Hansen likens the feeling of the digital ASW to
                     motion sickness and, in the case of videogames, this is precisely the medical
                     condition a significant number of uninitiated players experienced upon first
                     exposure to 3D graphics. Despite dramatic advancements in graphic processing
                     technologies and the growth of audiences desiring to play in 3D virtual worlds,
                     the difficulty of acclimatizing players to these spaces remains. Even today,
                     particularly amongst Japanese consumers, Nintendo's 2D titles consistently
                     out-sell its 3D counterparts. Both <title rend="italic">Super Mario
                        Galaxy</title> (2007) and <title rend="italic">New Super Mario Bros.</title>
                     (2006), for example, were released around the same time and both were
                     critically acclaimed; yet the side-scrolling platforming game sold two and a
                     half times more copies than <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title> was one of the first games
                     to incorporate eccentric gravity and spherical levels into its design. In his
                     interview with Miyamoto, Iwata comments, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#iwata2011">[A]t the time, I
                        did not fully understand its benefits. I knew right away that visually
                           [<title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title>] would look great. But
                        its true value was beyond what could be seen with the eyes, it was something
                        that I hadn’t realized</quote>
                     <ptr target="#iwata2011"/></cit>. Both Miyamoto's remark on motion sickness and
                     Iwata’s observation on the way in which the effects of spherical space
                     transcend visuality indicate an awareness of how the body functions while
                     playing these games. The visual is only a small part in a much more
                     comprehensive bodily engagement with digital space.</note> In recent years,
                  there has been a renaissance of 2D platforming games. The flatness of the screen
                  and depiction of 2D space is no longer a technological constraint, but a creative
                  tool, a game design element that can be placed in conjunction with 3D spaces to
                  create metagames which use graphics processing and computer rendering as their
                  main technological platforms and design constraints. One series of games that
                  structures its gameplay around the perspectival play of both two- and
                  three-dimensional spaces is Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echo</title> franchise
                  which includes <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> (2008), <title rend="italic">Echoshift</title> (2009), and <title rend="italic">Echochrome
                     II</title> (2010).</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> is produced by Sony's Japan Studio and
                  Game Yarouze for the PlayStation Portable (PSP) and PlayStation 3 (PS3). In the
                  game, the player is presented with a minimal, immaculately white space featuring a
                  centralized, floating object composed of stairs, walkways, ramps, and ramparts
                  reminiscent of M.C. Escher's impossible spaces and paradoxical architectures (<ref target="#figure05">see Figure 5</ref>). By twisting the joystick, <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s hovering levels begin to rotate and, unlike
                  a hand-drawn optical illusion, actually reconstitute their perspectival conditions
                  in real time. All the while, a solitary figure wanders back and forth, footsteps
                  clacking in empty space. The lone resident of these <soCalled>endless
                     walkways</soCalled> (the rough translation of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s Japanese title, <title rend="italic">Mugen Kairō</title>)
                  is a textureless mannequin who autonomously strolls up and down the crisply
                  contoured, isometric expanses. Both the oblique reference to Escher's artwork and
                  the mannequin (an object traditionally used for rendering perspectival figures)
                  are fitting considering that the game’s main mechanic involves rotating anamorphic
                  architectures in ways that paradoxically play with the dichotomy between screen
                  and space.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>Images of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>'s mannequin and level
                     design.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>In <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, there are five main rules governing
                  the mannequin's movements: <quote rend="block" source="#sony2008">(1) When two separate pathways
                     appear to be touching, they are. (2) If one pathway appears to be above
                     another, it is. (3) When the gap between two pathways is blocked from view and
                     the pathways appear to be connected, they are. (4) When a hole is blocked from
                     view, it does not exist. (5) When the mannequin jumps, it will land on whatever
                     appears beneath it. <ptr target="#sony2008"/>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>These five laws of perspective define the relationship between two- and three-
                  dimensions within the game-space.<note>In the world of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, the three-dimensional architecture reinforces the logic
                     of the two-dimensional screen like Nintendo's 2007 release of <title rend="italic">Super Paper Mario</title> (2007) for the Nintendo Wii, Kuju
                     Entertainment's Zoë Mode development studio's 2007 release of <title rend="italic">Crush</title> (2007) for the PSP, Polytron Corporation’s
                     premier XBLA title, <title rend="italic">Fez</title> (2012), and DigiPen
                     Institute of Technology's eagerly awaited student game, <title rend="italic">Perspective</title> (forthcoming).</note>[9] By inverting the order of
                  perspectival rendering, the pictorial logic of the screen is given precedence over
                  the mimetic representation of space. What you see is literally what you get.</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> recalls Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The
                     Ambassadors</title> in the way it mixes traditional perspective with anamorphic
                  effects. By placing both two- and three-dimensional space in conversation with
                  each other, the game conflates the dual logic of flat <q>screen</q> and deep
                     <q>window,</q> two metaphors Anne Friedberg contrasts in <title rend="italic">The Virtual Window: From Alberti to Microsoft</title> (2006). Friedberg argues
                  that although perspective has been the historically dominant form of visuality,
                  computers have dramatically transformed how space is culturally perceived and
                  organized. She examines the graphic user interface of computer desktops and the
                  way they are composed of multiple, overlapping windows, conflicting light sources,
                  and purely abstract drop shadows. Although Leon Battista Alberti famously
                  described classical perspective as a <q>window</q> onto another world, Friedberg
                  demonstrates how computer software companies have appropriated similar rhetoric
                  for describing the non-perspectival, non-linear incongruities and contradictions
                  of computer operating systems. In this sense, Microsoft Windows has become a
                  window as the artificial tropes and interface metaphors of these operating systems
                  have been naturalized as yet another form of realism.<note>Terry Harpold also
                     makes this observation in <title rend="italic">Ex-foliations: Reading Machines
                        and the Upgrade Path</title> (2009) when he examines the default desktop
                     wallpaper of Windows XP known as the <title rend="quotes">Bliss Screen,</title>
                     a vista composed of rolling grass and blue sky. Noting the uncanny connection
                     between this pastoral imagery and Freud’s description of an alpine meadow in
                     his 1899 essay <title rend="quotes">Screen Memories,</title> Harpold analyzes
                     the advertising surrounding the release of the OS. One television commercial
                     sets Madonna’s <title rend="quotes">Ray of Light</title> against images of
                     euphoric Microsoft users <q>diving</q> through the screen in order to soar
                     through (indistinguishable) physical and virtual spaces to the amazement of
                     those looking on who have yet to test the GUI for themselves. The rhetoric of
                     unmediated immersion and of a deep perspective, which the advertisement deploys
                     in order to present the computer screen as a perspectival <q>window,</q>
                     renders invisible the complex and contradictory non-linear visual organization
                     that truly comprises the Windows GUI <ptr target="#harpold2009" loc="238–41"/>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> stands out as a particularly intriguing
                  example of alternative spatial organization because it knowingly plays with the
                  tension between pictorial and sculptural space. As the player rotates the central
                  object in three-dimensions, real-time graphic processes render an illusion of
                  depth with the screen or monitor serving as virtual window. Near and far, broad
                  and deep, <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s rotating spaces appear to
                  behave rationally, like a revolving showroom car or a piece of electronics on a
                  turntable. But when the motion stops, the collisions and connections of the
                  Escher-esque architecture are ultimately determined according to the logic of the
                  suspended two-dimensional image. The <q>window</q> into another realm flattens
                  into an opaque screen.<note>
                     <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> also illustrates the tension
                     between material surface and illusionistic depth. Applying the rhetoric of
                     window and screen that Friedberg articulates, one can imagine viewing the two
                     ambassadors as an act of looking through a virtual window. This fantasy is
                     disrupted, however, through the presence of the smeared skull. The skull does
                     not exist within the three-dimensional space of the painting, but instead
                     appears as an object that is literally not of that world, or, as Hansen writes,
                     an <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">envoy from elsewhere</quote>
                     <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. The fact that Holbein’s skull does not
                     inhabit the same virtual plane is reinforced by the fact that its shadows are
                     not cast from the same light source. It is as if an imaginary pane of glass
                     covers this <q>window</q> and the skull has been smeared over its transparent
                     surface. There is a figure/ground oscillation as the painting moves between
                     drawing attention to itself as a window as well as a screen. This hypermediated
                     effect of <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, in which multiple
                     lighting sources create layered windows into heterogeneous visual orders is
                     also at work in <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Adjusting <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s perspective not only
                  transforms the player’s view, but the structure of the architecture itself. The
                  spatial dimensions and composition of the object do not remain fixed in an
                  absolute space. Instead, the in-game architecture is reconstituted depending on
                  the angle from which it is viewed. Yet, in the tradition of Espen Aarseth’s
                  concept of ergodic literature, this is perspectival rendering structured within
                  the idiom of anamorphic play and operating according to fixed points of
                  resolution. If the player rotates the architecture correctly, or, more precisely,
                  manipulates the in-game camera, the puzzle will be solved and the secret revealed.
                  Discovering the solution to these levels, cracking their spatial code, promotes a
                  reductive model of anamorphosis — one that equates embodied vision with an
                  absolute, mathematical result produced by a virtual camera. In this sense, <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> differs from a work like <title rend="italic">skulls</title> in which there is no chance of ever decoding the painterly
                  smear into perspectival representation. The game’s ludic logic acts as an
                  interface through which the player finds herself able to assume a naïve position
                  of control and mastery of those perspectives that would otherwise be hopelessly
                  irresolvable. Through <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s eccentric camera,
                  the human eye is simulated as a one-dimensional point in space, perfect for
                  projecting and reflecting ray-traced light.</p>
               <p>While <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> creates a world built around the
                  intersections of two- and three-dimensional space, its sequel, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, adds the play of light and shadow to its
                  predecessor’s uniquely hybrid perspective of multi-dimensional objects. Once
                  again, what you see is what you get. The mannequin’s silhouette, referred to as
                     <q>the cast,</q> must traverse visual puzzles through the player’s anamorphic
                  manipulations of light. In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, the cast
                  does not walk along the physical objects, but along the shadowy, two-dimensional
                  projections that fall in the wake of floating blocks, stairs, and steps (<ref target="#figure06">see Figure 6</ref>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure06">
                  <head>An <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> advertisement featuring
                     interactive illumination.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Like its predecessor, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> was developed by
                  Sony’s Japan Studio and made for PS3, but it requires the PlayStation Move, a
                  motion-sensing hand controller spatially tracked by the PS Eye, Sony’s
                  interactive, infrared camera.<note>The Sony Move is part of the latest generation
                     of controllers for mainstream consoles and competes with other motion-control
                     sensors such as the Wii Remote and the hands-free Kinect for the Xbox 360. The
                     Kinect is a human interface device that is able to track real-time 3D video
                     using a grid of infrared laser beams. It reads the physical gestures and voice
                     commands of the player. These technologies call attention to the player’s body,
                     situating them much more explicitly in a spatial relationship to the games
                     being played. Unlike <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> and <title rend="italic">skulls</title> that unsettle the human body through the
                     tension produced between the virtual and the physical, these controllers
                     attempt to suture the two realities together in a way that appears seamless and
                     intuitive.</note> The Move controller is topped by a glowing sphere that
                  flickers and changes colors when the wand is active, emitting infrared light for
                  the PS Eye. This motion-tracking technology inverts the relationship between
                  controller and camera popularized by the Nintendo Wii, which emits two infrared
                  points of light from a stationary bar set near the screen and tracked by a camera
                  within the Wii Remote (<ref target="#figure07">see Figure 7</ref>). In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, this light-tracking technology is used to
                  position the in-game light source which, when cast on the floating objects,
                  produces virtual shadows in real time based on the player’s bodily gestures. These
                  motions translate into the screen's perspectival space surprisingly well as the
                  player shines the Move controller on their television like a digitized flashlight.
                  Rays are traced from the tip of the wand at the precise angle of incidence — rays
                  which pierce the screen to connect out-of-game light sources to in-game objects
                  and architectures.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure07">
                  <head>A comparison of Sony’s PlayStation Move and Nintendo’s Wii Remote.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>The shadows produced by the Move evoke the flickering lamp flame from Pliny’s
                  account of Butades’ daughter, but rather than assume a visual symmetry between
                  silhouette and object (the way in which this myth has been traditionally depicted
                  in various paintings), the game reveals the dissonance and distortions that
                  prevail in the world of shadows.<note>Continuing this minor tradition of <q>shadow
                        play</q> alongside <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, the more
                     experimental offerings from the independent developers producing <title rend="italic">Closure</title> (2012) and <title rend="italic">Unfinished
                        Swan</title> (2012) focus on shadows as their main game mechanic. In the
                     Flash-turning-console game <title rend="italic">Closure</title>, a puzzle
                     platformer which follows <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s
                     what-you-see-is-what-you-get logic, designers Jon Schubbe and Tyler Glaiel
                     program onscreen objects that physically persist only if illuminated. In the
                     procedural architecture of <title rend="italic">Closure</title> blackness
                        <emph>is</emph> nothingness — any unlit object simply ceases to exist
                     allowing the childlike player-character to tiptoe through dimly lit walls and
                     tumble through shadows cast on the floor. Recalling the aesthetic of Edward
                     Gorey’s <title rend="italic">Gashlycrumb Tinies</title> (1963) and, like <title rend="italic">Limbo</title> (2010), following lone children through
                     Purgatory, Schubbe and Glaiel present a child’s-eye view of a world turned
                     black and white, a world in which anamorphic light and shadow distort physical
                     reality. Like the reader of <title rend="italic">Gashlycrumb Tinies</title>,
                     the player uncovers the many ways in which she can plunge into nothingness.
                     Lying at the opposite end of the color spectrum, <title rend="italic">The
                        Unfinished Swan</title> is an experimental prototype developed by Giant
                     Sparrow. The game is a first-person shooter set in a field of blinding
                     whiteness. Luckily, the player wields a kind of paint or shadow gun used to
                     differentiate the otherwise invisible geometry of each level as one progresses.
                     In both <title rend="italic">Closure</title> and <title rend="italic">Unfinished Swan</title>, 3D space and the architecture therein do not exist
                     without some form of anamorphic shading.</note> In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, the player can adjust the light source in order to form
                  a kind of anamorphic shadow play. If a player positions the controller at a
                  particular angle, in the same way a viewer might position her body in relation to
                     <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, the game will reveal hidden,
                  albeit banal, images (e.g., a smiling face, a snake, etc) simultaneously
                  converting previously insurmountable obstacles into more conventional 2D platforms
                  for the player-controlled <q>cast</q> to hop, skip, and jump across (<ref target="#figure08">see Figure 8</ref>). Just as Butades used the shadow traced
                  by his daughter to cast a relief portrait, <title rend="italic">Echochome
                     II</title> conflates silhouette and sculpture to model not earthen effigies but
                  polygonal pathways. These digital-born projections not only operate according to
                  the pictorial logic of two-dimensional shadow play, but are assigned an autonomous
                  physics and materiality distinct from the original objects. The glowing orb
                  simulates a cycloptic eyeball, projecting unique perspectives as the player learns
                  how to alter the angle of the light source in order to play along with the fantasy
                  of mastery over distorted, anamorphic images.</p>
               <p>Both <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> and <title rend="italic">Echochrome
                     II</title> produce spatial effects that are unique to the logic of the
                  computer, but they depart from the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> by
                  generating puzzles as a <q>solvable enigmas.</q> Both games encourage the player
                  to participate in a fantasy of mastery by simulating of anamorphic effects within
                  a deterministic game-space. Whereas anamorphic painting requires a player’s body
                  to physically adjust in relation to the object, these videogames produce
                  anamorphic encounters through in-game camera rotation. <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> doesn’t actually require a bodily perception of space, but
                  uses perspectival rendering in a way that mimics anamorphosis. Similarly, <title rend="italic">Echochrome 2</title> simulates a perspectival <q>eye</q> as a
                  single point in space through using Sony’s Move. In this sense, players only see
                  the shadow play of <title rend="italic">Echochrome 2</title> second hand. Rather
                  than activating perspective through vision, they render the gaze of a cycloptic
                  eye, adjusting the Move controller in order to project perspectival imagery onto
                  the screen. Though the <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> games require
                  haptic input, the mathematical transformations depicted in each polygonal space do
                  not engage an expanded field of affective, bodily experience and instead work to
                  reinforce the hegemony of vision through a user-friendly design. The visual
                  distortions are framed in such a way that any sense of a radical encounter with
                  the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> is as repressed as it is with
                  conventionally perspectival renderings.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure08">
                  <head>Anamorphic shadows in <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>: A Multi-Dimensional Memory Palace</head>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> is designed to function with (and
                  market) a specific commercial remote: Sony’s PlayStation Move. The most recent
                  generation of console controllers, inspired by the success of Nintendo’s
                  unconventional Wii Remote, challenged the joystick-button and mouse-keyboard input
                  combinations that have served as the industry standard in human-computer interface
                  design. New hardware like the Wiimote, Move, and Microsoft’s Kinect are beginning
                  to expand players’ attention beyond their two thumbs by incorporating motion
                  tracking and gesture recognition. Despite explicitly reframing input in terms of
                  the body, these technologies fall under the category of <q>natural user
                     interfaces</q> or NUIs that rhetorically reinforce a conventional understanding
                  of immersivity and interaction in which the body is rendered invisible and vision
                  is transformed into a mathematical abstraction. Amidst this technological turn
                  toward the natural, independent artist Julian Oliver has designed a game and
                  control scheme that does not take standard forms of interaction for granted.</p>
               <p>In 2007, Oliver created <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>, an interactive
                  installation exhibited in museums and galleries as well as on home computers (<ref target="#figure09">see Figure 9</ref>). <title rend="italic">LevelHead</title>
                  combines color-coded and patterned cubes with custom, open-source software and a
                  webcam to motion track and replace the six unique <q>quick response</q> or QR
                  codes of each cube with three-dimensional, interactive architecture. The result is
                  a large, real-time video projection that displays the player's hands interfacing
                  with the virtualized cubes, each facet filled with internal geometries. The cubes
                  serve as both screens and joysticks, and, as with <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> and <title rend="italic">Echochrome II,</title> the
                  player's physical gestures and positioning change the perspectival viewport to
                  propel a small, white, humanoid silhouette through a six-sided interior space.
                  This unassuming avatar, like the minimally-designed <q>cast</q> featured in the
                     <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series, follows the path of least
                  resistance based on the angle at which a user holds each cube. By tilting the
                  cube-controllers, the player indirectly steers the small silhouette that behaves
                  like an automaton or dummy, a lost soul wandering aimlessly through shifting
                  architecture. The cubes work in sequence, each containing six three-dimensional
                  rooms overlaid within the same physical space for a total of eighteen rooms. By
                  tracking objects and actions instead of interfacing with standardized controller
                  input and by projecting the results back on that which is being sampled, Oliver’s
                  augmented reality game extends the perspectival space of the screen to the
                  physical environment and vice versa.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure09">
                  <head>Installation of <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> with
                     cube-controllers, camera, and projection.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">LevelHead</title> presents the inside of the cube as if it
                  were a shadowbox, but when the player adjusts any QR-encoded face captured by the
                  camera, an entirely different space appears. The challenge of <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> is to imagine six simultaneous rooms within the geometry of
                  the box in hand. This difficulty, as Oliver has written, is complicated when one
                  must remember the spatial organization of six discrete geometries despite the fact
                  that they are not simultaneously present or interconnected in a way that is
                  physically possible. The logic of the cube’s architecture, therefore, must be
                  constructed out of a different set of haptic cues, engaging with the wrist and
                  hand rather than the screen and eye:</p>
               <p>The tangible interface aspect becomes integral to the function of recall...[A]s
                  the cube is turned by the hands in search of correctly adjoining rooms
                  muscle-memory is engaged and, as such, aids the memory as a felt memory of
                  patterns of turns: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#oliver2009">that room is two turns to the left when
                     this room is upside down</quote><ptr target="#oliver2009"/></cit>.</p>
               <p>Although Oliver offers a walkthrough on YouTube, he notes that the game is <quote rend="inline" source="#oliver2009">very difficult</quote> and, given the two-minute time limit to
                  finish each puzzle, it is doubtful many have fully toured what he calls <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#oliver2009">the apartment</quote>
                  <ptr target="#oliver2009"/></cit>. Thus, for the vast majority of players, engagement
                  with <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> comes closer to producing an
                  experience of Hansen’s digital ASW and engaging the <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term> than <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>. The cube-controller
                  each player holds inevitably transforms into a kind of virtual skull, a reminder
                  of an anamorphic discrepancy between eye-hand coordination and camera-computer
                  calculation.</p>
               <p>When grasping the <q>level heads,</q> hands and wrists quickly organize each cube
                  into a coherent program that does not necessarily comply with what the eyes see.
                  As Oliver points out, the body grounds the player’s frame of reference, yet she
                  grapples with a space removed from standard forms of orientation. There is a
                  palpable disconnect between what the player feels holding the solid cube and what
                  she sees projected. The incommensurability between haptic and optical feedback
                  recalls <title rend="italic">skulls</title>. Were a viewer to close her eyes and
                  place her hands on the sculptures, the digital-born objects would resolve to the
                  touch, yet the visual distortions throw off the viewer’s equilibrium to produce
                  the feeling of a digital ASW. <title rend="italic">LevelHead</title> makes a game
                  out of negotiating haptic orientation with a visual and cognitive disorientation
                  and dramatizes what Andy Clark and David J. Chalmers characterize as <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#clark1998">the externalization of thought</quote>
                  <ptr target="#clark1998" loc="8"/></cit>.</p>
               <p>In <title rend="quotes">The Extended Mind,</title> Clark and Chalmers cite a 1994
                  study by David Kirsh and Paul Maglio in which participants were asked to play the
                  game <title rend="italic">Tetris</title> (1985). Data was collected in three ways:
                  (1) the unobtrusive sampling of real-time keystroke data as advanced,
                  intermediate, and novice gamers played <title rend="italic">Tetris</title>, (2)
                  tachistoscopic tests of the same subjects performing mental rotation tasks related
                  to <title rend="italic">Tetris</title>, and (3) an <quote rend="inline" source="#kirsh1994">expert
                     system</quote> called <title rend="italic">Robotetris</title> built as a
                  machine control for the experiment <ptr target="#kirsh1994" loc="518"/>. After
                  comparing the results of these three groups, Kirsh and Maglio discovered that when
                  enabled by environmental as well as bodily support, the human operators were far
                  more efficient. Using a controller, participants performed the operation in 300
                  milliseconds (200 milliseconds to press a button, then 100 milliseconds for the
                  screen to refresh) while it took around 1000 milliseconds for the same result to
                  be achieved mentally (measured with standard tachistoscopic tests). For Clark and
                  Chalmers, this study empirically demonstrates how cognition exceeds not only the
                  mind, but the hand as well — consciousness co-developing in concert with body and
                  environment.</p>
               <p>While Kirsh and Maglio explain how prosthetic technology transforms cognition
                  using the example of <title rend="italic">Tetris</title>, the videogame itself was
                  designed with a model of vision independent of haptic engagement. For most
                  videogames, the screen is treated as invisible or transparent and gamers assume
                  the pixels and polygons are accurate representations of the game-space.
                  Conversely, the ability to recall space in <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>
                  is overtly dependent on both the body and a series of external apparatuses
                  precisely due to the fact that the architecture produced in the game <title rend="italic">cannot</title> be visualized accurately in three-dimensional
                  space. As Oliver emphasizes in an artist statement, the muscle memory of the hand
                  is indispensable for successful navigation of the game’s paradoxes. While seasoned
                  players of almost any videogame are acutely aware of the operation and
                  indispensability of muscle memory, most game design still relies on a model of
                  autonomous visual memory (i.e., observing a visual space enables the player to
                  form an abstract mental model). This is one of the unique aspects of <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> which does not take hand, body, or
                  cube-controller for granted or treat them as merely instruments for executing
                  orders. Oliver’s game is built around the assumption that all the interactions
                  within this cybernetic system are a necessary pre-condition for comprehending and
                  traversing the environment.</p>
               <p>The <title rend="italic">Tetris</title> study erodes the Cartesian model of
                  mind-body dualism, demonstrating a distributed model of cognition that puts
                  pressure on the question of where the body stops and the rest of the world begins.
                  Ironically, this example of situated cognition is constructed around a cognitive
                  aporia. The incommensurable gulf between the processes of a computer and the
                  embodied engagement of the human is also necessary for the cybernetic system to
                  function: the hyphen in human-computer interaction signifying this chasm. Thus,
                  Oliver’s <q>level heads</q> tilt and twist into versions of the smeared skull,
                  challenging the player to peer into an irresolvable and paradoxical architecture.
                  Clutching this existential object, a clear <term>memento mortem mortis</term>, the
                  player glimpses into a space beyond human thought, beyond the debates of <q>to be
                     or not to be</q> into a dimension where these questions are rendered
                  insignificant.</p>
               <p>Beyond the simulated cameras and on-screen architecture of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> extends anamorphic
                  distortion to the embodied space of the human viewer. By creating a mathematical
                  projection in which six interconnected rooms co-exist within the same
                  three-dimensional space, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> inverts the
                  standard notion of projection and plays with a kind of fourth-dimensional logic.
                  In the virtual space of the screen, these three-dimensional rooms exist within the
                  same cube, overlapping each other. Although only one room is visible, the player
                  can imagine the cube functioning like a tesseract or hypercube. The player must
                  imagine six three-dimensional cubes contained within the cube she holds in her
                  hand, although only one set of three-dimensional coordinates is observable at any
                  time. These rooms simulate a fourth-dimensional space. This conceptual abstraction
                  functions as a rhetorical device that stands in for the player’s encounter with
                  the alien and inaccessible ontology of the everyday technological objects with
                  which we surround ourselves. Anamorphosis becomes a means to aestheticize this
                  encounter with what Ian Bogost has called the <quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2012">alien
                     phenomenology</quote> of the computer (a concept we discuss further below) <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>: A Garden of Many Forking Dimensions</head>
               <p>While <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>’s disorienting architecture implies a
                  fourth-dimensional space and marshals the <term>memento mortem mortis</term> to
                  allegorize this potential, Marc ten Bosch’s <title rend="italic">Miegakure: A
                     Garden in Four Dimensions</title> (in development) directly incorporates
                  four-dimensional theory into its game design philosophy. Both <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> and <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> experiment with
                  perspectival systems in which the laws of two- and three-dimensional perspective
                  overlap with each other. <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>, on the other
                  hand, adds one more spatial register in order to attempt to create a
                  four-dimensional puzzle platformer (<ref target="#figure10">see Figure 10</ref>).
                  Although visualizing the fourth dimension stretches the very limits of human
                  perception, it is relatively simple to represent mathematically. It is a space
                  where the abstractions of math and physics discourse freely and the human body may
                  be able to affectively register interdimensional shifts subconciously, but
                  perspectival vision is more or less left in the dark. For this reason, the fourth
                  dimension has been a curiosity for artists wishing to critique the ocularcentrism
                  of classical perspective and Cartesian space. In her work on fourth-dimensional
                  theories of twentieth-century art, Linda Dalrymple Henderson writes that <quote rend="inline" source="#henderson1984">the fourth dimension was a concern common to artists in nearly
                     every major modern movement</quote> because it <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#henderson1984">encouraged
                     artists to depart from visual reality and to reject completely the one-point
                     perspective system that for centuries had portrayed the world as
                     three-dimensional</quote>
                  <ptr target="#henderson1984" loc="205"/></cit>. Though many visual artists throughout
                  the twentieth century have dabbled in four-dimensional theory, from multi-point
                  and non-perspectival Cubist renderings to Surrealist explorations of scientific
                  theories like the non-Euclidian spatial geometries of Henri Poincaré, ten Bosch
                  takes his inspiration from Edwin Abbot Abbot’s <title rend="italic">Flatland: A
                     Romance of Many Dimensions</title> (1884), a nineteenth-century novel narrating
                  a square’s journey through one-, two-, three-, and eventually four-dimensional
                  space.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure10">
                  <head>Screenshots from Mark ten Bosch’s forthcoming <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>
                  </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Faced with the paradox of representing the non-representable, ten Bosch’s strategy
                  is to create a game-space in which each three-dimensional coordinate contains not
                  three, but four points of information. As written on his website, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#tenbosch2011">at the press of a button one of the dimensions is exchanged with
                     the fourth dimension, allowing for four-dimensional movement</quote>
                  <ptr target="#tenbosch2011"/></cit>. Thus, a block situated within a three-dimensional
                  grid will appear to magically <q>smear</q> across the screen by substituting a
                  given coordinate for a hidden fourth point in another space. Mathematically, one
                  can make n-dimensional objects by simply adding more and more coordinates
                  alongside the traditional designations for width, height, and depth. What exists
                  as a computational abstraction cannot be visually modeled on the two-dimensional
                  screen but the process of substituting alternate sets of data symbolizes the
                  traversal between four spatial dimensions.</p>
               <p>Marc ten Bosch does not treat this relationship between gameplay and
                  fourth-dimensional physics merely as a form of symbolic substitution. He
                  hubristically proposes that <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> grants access
                  to the fourth dimension, allowing players to <quote rend="inline" source="#tenbosch2011">experience it
                     first-hand, using trial and error, as opposed to being told about it</quote>
                  and promotes a fantasy of mastery, colonization, and control over four-dimensional
                  space <ptr target="#tenbosch2011"/>. Despite his ambitious claims, the deeper
                  significance that will ultimately be gained from the game is not a
                     <q>first-hand</q> knowledge of the fourth dimension, but its computational
                  processes. And it is in this respect that <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>’s
                  fantasy of traversing the fourth dimension becomes a metaphor for traversing the
                  microtemporal repetitions and vast spatial scale of informatic systems. The
                  gameplay of <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> recalls Hansen’s claim about
                  the way in which the anamorphic space of <title rend="italic">skulls</title>
                  stands in for the <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2006">weird logic and topology of the
                     computer</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>.</p>
               <p> In <title rend="italic">Gaming: Essays on Algorithmic Culture</title> (2006),
                  Alexander Galloway persuasively argues that videogames are <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2006">allegories of control</quote>; they are cultural objects which rhetorically
                  present themselves as sources of interactivity and agency, yet in doing so conceal
                  the <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2006">protocological network of continuous informatic
                     control</quote> under which individuals now live <ptr target="#galloway2006" loc="106"/>. Computer games ultimately subsume the player within a strict
                  system of rules that allegorize contemporary informatic culture at large. One
                  might further add that videogames function not only as allegories of control, but
                  as allegories of the beyond. And this is the logic of the <term>memento mortem
                     mortis</term>. By presenting a set of computational processes as rules for
                  organizing play, videogames invite players to discover the limits and affordances
                  of a given game-space and along the way produce reminders of the death of death.
                  To play a game is to test a nonhuman system, to uncover (and be uncovered by) the
                  codes that will produce both experiential dissonances like the digital ASW while
                  opening fields for philosophical speculations. In this way, play is co-developed
                  through a mutual enterprise of <q>becoming computational.</q> In <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>, the fourth-dimensional exercises depicted in
                  the game’s diegesis and its computational dynamics are interlinked. In this way,
                     <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> establishes a tidy homology between the
                  fourth spatial dimension and the internal workings of a computer by placing them
                  within the same experiential register: at the limits of human perception. By
                  attempting to colonize computational space through the insertion of a human
                  agency, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> adopts the ambitious premise that
                  the formal topology of computational space can be manipulated, controlled, and
                  conquered absolutely (when, as Galloway observes, videogames in fact excel at
                  accomplishing the opposite) <ptr target="#galloway2006" loc="106"/>. Ten Bosch’s
                  game delights in the telic fantasy of extending the human agency into spaces and
                  places where it does not belong.</p>
               <p>The gap between what is possible to represent in mathematics and what is sensible
                  within human phenomenology is the inspiration for Quentin Meillassoux’s concept of
                     <q>the great outdoors</q> in <title rend="italic">After Finitude</title>
                  (2008). Rather than thinking of the great outdoors in the tradition of Caspar
                  David Friedrich and those works of art which situate the human subject amongst the
                  overwhelming sublimity of nature, Meillassoux uses the expression to refer to a
                  universe that persists beyond the horizon of human correlation writing <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#meillassoux2008">[t]his is the enigma which we must confront: mathematics' ability
                     to discourse about the great outdoors; to discourse about a past where both
                     humanity and life are absent</quote>
                  <ptr target="#meillassoux2008" loc="26"/></cit>. <quote rend="inline" source="#tenbosch2011">Miegakure,</quote>
                  ten Bosch clarifies, is Japanese for <quote rend="inline" source="#tenbosch2011">hide and reveal</quote>
                  and refers to a specific gardening technique used in Japan <ptr target="#tenbosch2011"/>. The game is set within a Japanese Zen garden, evoking
                  a space of contemplation and relaxation as the player ponders mathematical
                  abstractions and inter-dimensional ontologies. Like Mark Z. Danielewski’s <title rend="italic">House of Leaves</title>, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>’s
                  four-dimensional gardening techniques conjure a space that is paradoxically larger
                  on the <q>inside</q> than the outside. The objects in the garden interweave with
                  one another and expand through multiple dimensions. The gardening metaphor is
                  particularly apt because a garden not only represents a space of contemplation,
                  but one of control and the domestication of nature. Ten Bosch's game can be read
                  as an attempt to domesticate a computational wilderness, to seize the great
                  outdoors, and till the land such that it falls back under the purview of human
                  experience and agency. By creating a morphology between anamorphic techniques and
                  the great outdoors, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> pushes anamorphic games
                  into the next speculative dimension by procedurally rendering an allegory of the
                  beyond.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <div>
               <head>Alien Phenomenology and the Entelechy of the Weird</head>
               <p>The fascination with a computational wilderness, the great outdoors of digital
                  space, is what games scholar and designer Ian Bogost has developed into a
                  philosophy he calls <term>alien phenomenology.</term> Synthesizing the recent
                  proliferation of ideas falling under the category of Speculative Realism, and
                  specifically engaging with Graham Harman’s version of Object-Oriented Ontology,
                  Bogost’s <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title> (2012) embraces the
                  alien nature of quotidian material objects. He passionately describes how the
                  material world of objects and things has been de-privileged in the face of the
                     <foreign>sturm und drang</foreign> of human drama. According to Bogost: <quote rend="block" source="#bogost2012">If we take seriously [Graham Harman’s] idea that all objects
                     recede interminably into themselves, then human perception becomes just one
                     among many ways that objects might relate. To put things at the center of a new
                     metaphysics also requires us to admit that they do not exist just for us <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>.</quote>
               </p>
               <p>These concealed and re-distributed relations underwrite Bogost’s construction of
                  an alien phenomenology. He declares that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2012">[t]he true alien
                     recedes interminably. It is not hidden in the darkness of the outer cosmos nor
                     in the deep sea shelf, but in plain sight, everywhere, in everything</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit>. This insight opens the question of how the behavior
                  of humans is transformed as a result of this reconfigured relation to objects. The
                  answer Bogost offers is <emph>wonder</emph>: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2012">[d]espite all
                     the science fictional claims to the contrary, the alien is different. One does
                     not ask the alien, <q>Do you come in peace?</q> but rather, <q>What am I to
                        you?</q> The posture one takes before the alien is that of curiosity, of
                     wonder</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit>. Bogost attempts to reinscribe a sense of respect for
                  the mysteries of quotidian objects — for the alien that does not arrive from a
                  galaxy far, far away but is part of our everyday lives. The <quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2012">alien is everywhere</quote> and perhaps this is most deeply felt when
                  attending to what peers back from the remote space of a computer <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>.</p>
               <p>Bogost’s response to this call of the wild is to practice wonder, but this is by
                  no means the only answer philosophers have posited. On the other hand, is not
                  horror the obverse of wonder? Horror comes closer to the feeling Hansen describes
                  as the digital ASW and what Eugene Thacker articulates in his recent book, <title rend="italic">After Life</title> (2010). In <title rend="italic">After
                     Life</title>, Thacker explores the philosophical concept of life and living.
                  Also informed by the recent explosion of speculative philosophies which redirect
                  philosophical inquiry away from the human towards <quote rend="inline" source="#thacker2010">a politics
                     of life in terms of the nonhuman or the unhuman,</quote> Thacker turns to the
                  fantasy writing of H.P. Lovecraft to find creative models for thinking that which
                  exists beyond thought <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="5"/>. Lovecraft, he argues,
                     <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#thacker2010">presents the possibility of a logic of life, though an
                     inaccessible logic, one that is absolutely inaccessible to the human, the
                     natural, the earthly, an <q>entelechy of the weird</q>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="23"/></cit>. What Thacker identifies as <q>weird</q> in
                  Lovecraft’s writing, is the same speculation at work in the anamorphic gameplay of
                  videogames that attempt to test or allegorize the limits of human experience.
                  While Lovecraft attempts to name the unnamable, these games convey the sense of
                     <emph>playing the unplayable</emph>. As Thacker writes, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#thacker2010">the weird is the discovery of an unhuman limit to thought, that is
                     nevertheless foundational for thought. The life that is weird is the life
                     according to the logic of an inaccessible rift, a life <q>out of space and
                        time,</q> and life of <q>extra-dimensional biologies</q>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="23"/></cit>.</p>
               <p>Whether using terms like <q>weird,</q>
                  <q>eccentric,</q>
                  <q>alien,</q> or <q>anamorphic,</q> these ideas attempt to resituate the place of
                  the human within a more complex cosmology of objects (Levi Bryant’s term for this
                  is <quote rend="inline" source="#bryant2010">flat ontology</quote> and Bogost revises this slightly
                  with his theory of <quote rend="inline" source="#bogost2012">tiny ontologies</quote>) <ptr target="#bryant2010"/>
                  <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>. The strange spaces navigated in videogames like
                     <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, <title rend="italic">levelHead,</title> and <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> allegorize the
                  incomprehensibility of a computer; they create expressive systems that point to
                  the profoundly alien nature of the technological objects that are such an integral
                  and often ignored aspect of contemporary culture. Yet, despite the ubiquity and
                  embeddedness of computers within the economic, social, and even biological strata
                  of everyday life (at least on one side of the digital divide), the games examined
                  here perform the friction produced as a result of the irreconcilable alterity that
                  defines technological objects. As a way of assuaging the anxiety of discovering
                  one lives on an alien planet, games like <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>,<title rend="italic"> levelHead</title>, and <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> present defamiliarized spaces and propose that
                  the abyss that separates humanity from the mysterious black box of technology is,
                  in fact, navigable. In these games, the computer is not so much a Lovecraftian
                  monster, but a kind of riddle or enigma, troubling but potentially solvable. The
                  fundamental paradox of these <q>anamorphic games</q> is that they ultimately
                  subsume alternate worlds into a playable world. They present imagery and gameplay
                  referencing the <q>great outdoors</q> but packaged specifically for the human
                  player. Their controls fit into the palms of human hands and their screens cast
                  wavelengths of light within the spectrum of human vision. In this respect, and
                  based on the fundamentals of game design, the videogames presented in this essay
                  actively resist what could be called a kind of speculative gaming. The
                     <term>memento mortem mortis</term> is still only a reminder that tentatively
                  motions toward a nonhuman heart at the center of all material media. Like
                  Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> and Lazarrini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, these anamorphic games deploy a <term>memento
                     mortem mortis</term> to create metaphors for a computational wilderness,
                  reminding their users of both their experiential limitations and the limitations
                  of technological understanding.</p>
               <p>If one were tasked to develop a game completely indifferent to an end user, what
                  would this speculative game look like? Would it participate in a mutual withdrawal
                  of both player and game, or would it place both game and player at incommensurable
                  odds with one another? In much the same way the anamorphic lens can be said to
                  neither reflect nor refract light, but rather trap the gaze, the speculative game
                  would serve as a black hole. Speculative games cannot have a user, they cannot be
                  used or even be thought by the player. The software discussed in this paper
                  challenges the viewer, not to perceive the imperceptible or conquer otherworldly
                  domains, but to simply begin speculating on the possibilities of such dimensions
                  of existence. The result is that these are not so much speculative games, as they
                  are games of speculation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Aarseth 1997" xml:id="aarseth1997" key="aarseth1997">Aarseth, Espen. <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature.</title> Baltimore,
               MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bogost 2012" xml:id="bogost2012" key="bogost2012"> Bogost, Ian. <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of
               Minnesota Press, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bolter 1999" xml:id="bolter1999" key="bolter1999">Bolter, J. David and
               Richard Grusin. <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New Media</title>.
               Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bryant 2010" xml:id="bryant2010" key="bryant2010">Bryant, Levi. <title rend="quotes">Flat Ontology</title>
               <title rend="italic">Larval Subjects</title>. 24 Feb 2010. Accessed 10 July 2012.
                  <ref target="http://larvalsubjects.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/flat-ontology-2/">http://larvalsubjects.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/flat-ontology-2/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Caillois 2001" xml:id="caillois2001" key="caillois2001">Caillois, Roger.
                  <title rend="italic">Man, Play, and Games</title>. Trans. Meyer Barash. Chicago:
               University of Illinois Press, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Clark 1998" xml:id="clark1998" key="clark1998">Clark, Andy and David J.
               Chalmers. <title rend="quotes">The Extended Mind.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Analysis</title> 58, (1998) 7–19.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Damisch 1995" xml:id="damisch1995" key="damisch1995">Damisch, Hubert.
                  <title rend="italic">The Origin of Perspective</title>. Trans. John Goodman.
               Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Deleuze 1986" xml:id="deleuze1986" key="deleuze1986">Deleuze, Gilles.
                  <title rend="italic">Cinema 1: The Movement-Image</title>. Trans. Hugh Tomlinson
               and Barbara Habberjam. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1986.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Friedberg 2005" xml:id="friedberg2006" key="friedberg2006">Friedberg, Anne.
                  <title rend="italic">The Virtual Window: From Alberti to Microsoft</title>.
               Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Galloway 2006" xml:id="galloway2006" key="galloway2006a">Galloway,
               Alexander. <title rend="italic">Gaming: Essays on Algorithmic Culture</title>.
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hansen 2006" xml:id="hansen2006" key="hansen2006a">Hansen, Mark B. N.
                  <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT
               Press, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Harman 2002" xml:id="harman2002" key="harman2002">Harman, Graham. <title rend="italic">Tool-Being: Heidegger and the Metaphysics of Objects</title>.
               Chicago, IL: Open Court, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Harpold 2009" xml:id="harpold2009" key="harpold2009">Harpold, Terry. <title rend="italic">Ex-foliations: Reading Machines and the Upgrade Path.</title>
               Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Henderson 1984" xml:id="henderson1984" key="henderson1984">Henderson, Linda
               Dalrymple. <title rend="quotes">The Fourth Dimension and Non-Euclidean Geometry in
                  Modern Art: Conclusion.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Leonardo</title> 17.3, (1984) 205-210.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Iwata 2011" xml:id="iwata2011" key="iwata2011">Iwata, Satoru. <title rend="quotes">Iwata Asks: <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy.</title> Vol. 4:
                  Shigeru Miyamoto.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wii.com</title>, 2011. Accessed 10 July 2012. <ref target="http://us.wii.com/soft_smg.jsp">http://us.wii.com/soft_smg.jsp</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirsh 1994" xml:id="kirsh1994" key="kirsh1994">Kirsh, David and Paul
               Maglio. <title rend="quotes">On Distinguishing Epistemic from Pragmatic
                  Action.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cognitive Science</title> 18.4, 1994. 513-549.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Lacan 1998" xml:id="lacan1998" key="lacan1998">Lacan, Jacques. <title rend="italic">The Four Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis: The Seminar of
                  Jacques Lacan Book IV</title>. Ed. Jacques-Alain Miller. Trans. Alan Sheridan. New
               York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl label="McCormick 2011" xml:id="mccormick2011" key="mccormick2011">McCormick, Rich.
                  <title rend="quotes">E3 2011: Our John Carmack Video Interview Covers <title rend="italic">Rage</title>, the PC, and Gamma Corrected Anti-Aliasing.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PC Gamer</title>. 8 June 2011. Accessed 10 July 2012. <ref target="http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/06/08/e3-2011-our-john-carmack-interview-covers-rage-the-pc-and-gamma-corrected-anti-aliasing/">http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/06/08/e3-2011-our-john-carmack-interview-covers-rage-the-pc-and-gamma-corrected-anti-aliasing/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Meillassoux 2008" xml:id="meillassoux2008" key="meillassoux2008">Meillassoux, Quentin. <title rend="italic">After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity
                  of Contingency</title>. New York: Continuum, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mitchell 1994b" xml:id="mitchell1994b" key="mitchell1994b">Mitchell,
                  W.J.T. <title rend="italic">Reconfigured Eye: Visual Truth in the
                  Post-Photographic Era.</title> Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nideffer 2007" xml:id="nideffer2007" key="nideffer2007">Nideffer, Robert.
                  <title rend="quotes">Game Engines as Embedded Systems.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Database Aesthetics: Art in the Age of Information
                  Overflow</title>, ed. Victoria Vesna, 211–242. Minneapolis, MN: University of
               Minnesota Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Oliver 2009" xml:id="oliver2009" key="oliver2009">Oliver, Julian. <title rend="quotes">levelHead.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Selectparks.net</title>. 2009. Accessed 10 July 2012. <ref target="http://selectparks.net/~julian/levelhead/">http://selectparks.net/~julian/levelhead/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Pliny, Bk 35, Ch 43" xml:id="pliny" key="pliny">Pliny, the Elder. <title rend="italic">The Natural History</title>. eds. John Bostock, Henry T. Riley, and
               Karl Friedrich Theodor Mayhoff. Somerville, MA.: Perseus Digital Library. Accessed 10
               July 2012. <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Plin.+Nat.+toc.">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Plin.+Nat.+toc.</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Panofsky 1996" xml:id="panofsky1996" key="panofsky1996">Panofsky, Erwin.
                  <title rend="italic">Perspective as Symbolic Form</title>. Trans. Christopher S.
               Wood. Cambridge, Mass.: Zone Books (MIT Press), 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Seaman 2000" xml:id="seaman2000" key="seaman2000">Seaman, Bill. <title rend="quotes">Motioning Toward the Emergent Definition of E-phany Physics.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Art, Technology, Consciousness Mind@large</title>, ed. Roy
               Ascott. Bristol, UK; Portland, OR: Intellect Ltd., 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sony 2008" xml:id="sony2008" key="sony2008">Sony Computer Entertainment
               Inc. <title rend="italic">Echochrome Official Trailer</title>. Accessed 10 July
               2012.</bibl>
            <bibl label="ten Bosch 2011" xml:id="tenbosch2011" key="tenbosch2011">ten Bosch, Marc.
                  <title rend="quotes">Miegakure: A Puzzle-Platformer in Four Dimensions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Marctenbosch.com</title>. 2011. Accessed 23 July 2011. <ref target="http://marctenbosch.com/miegakure/">http://marctenbosch.com/miegakure/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Thacker 2010" xml:id="thacker2010" key="thacker2010">Thacker, Eugene.
                  <title rend="italic">After Life</title>. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press,
               2010.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>