<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Stretched Skulls: Anamorphic Games and the <foreign xml:lang="la">Memento Mortem Mortis</foreign></title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Stephanie <dhq:family>Boluk</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Vassar College</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>stboluk@vassar.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>Stephanie Boluk is a recent graduate from the Department of English at the University of Florida and is now completing a postdoctoral fellowship in the Media Studies program at Vassar College. For more information please visit <ref target="http://stephanieboluk.com">http://stephanieboluk.com</ref></p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
<dhq:authorInfo><dhq:author_name>Patrick <dhq:family>LeMieux</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
    <dhq:affiliation>Duke University</dhq:affiliation><email>patrick.lemieux@duke.edu</email> <dhq:bio>
       <p>Patrick LeMieux is an artist and Ph.D. student in the Department of Art, Art History, and Visual Studies at Duke University. He has exhibited artwork in the Tampa Museum of Art, FSU Museum of Fine Arts, the Samuel P. Harn Museum of Art, and his latest artwork, Open House, was featured at SIGGRAPH 2011. For more information please visit <ref target="http://patrick-lemieux.com">http://patrick-lemieux.com</ref></p>
   </dhq:bio>
</dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
              <idno type="DHQarticle-id">  <!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --> </idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change>encoded by Michelle. June 2012.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>From Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> to Robert Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, anamorphic artworks explore the tension between mathematical models of vision and more fully embodied models of subjectivity. After reviewing the ways in which anamorphosis has been deployed as a philosophical tool for examining this relationship between technology and phenomenology, specifically via the criticism of Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, this paper analyzes how contemporary videogames like Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> by Julian Oliver, and Mark ten Bosch’s forthcoming <title rend="italic">Miegakure </title>technically, aesthetically, and conceptually explore anamorphic techniques. Historically, anamorphosis has been deployed as a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign>, but we propose that games which frame anamorphosis as a metaphor for technology can be more accurately described as <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign>: reminders of a space beyond the death of death. Anamorphic games gesture towards fields of experience altogether indifferent to the human and foreground the radical alterity of computational logics to create allegories of the beyond. The result is that these are not so much speculative games, as they are games of speculation.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <!-- Use <div> only if there is more than one section -->
          
                <div>
                    <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Myth of Mimesis</head>
                        <figure xml:id="figure01"><head><title rend="italic">The Origin of Painting: Dibutades Tracing the Portrait of a Shepherd</title> (1785), by Jean-Baptiste Regnault.</head></figure>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</title> (c. AD 77-79), Pliny the Elder recounts two myths of mimetic representation. In one, the daughter of the Corinthian sculptor Butades, saddened by the imminent departure of her lover, traces the outline of his shadow as it is cast on a wall (see Figure 1) <ptr target="#pliny" loc="Bk 35, ch 43"/>. Inspired by this image, Butades presses clay over the drawing to sculpt a relief portrait based on the silhouette. This myth, which binds drawing and sculpting, does not celebrate the originality or expressivity of the artist’s hand but instead focuses on the possibility of an indexical relationship between light, sight, and representation: an ancient camera activated by the hand of Butades’ daughter. Elsewhere in his <title rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</title>, Pliny recites another well-known myth: the story of Zeuxis and Parrhasius who compete to determine the best painter <ptr target="#pliny" loc="Bk 35, ch 32"/>. Zeuxis paints grapes that look so natural, birds fly down to peck at them, but Parrhasius bests Zeuxis by painting curtains that deceive the other painter so completely that Zeuxis asks to draw the curtains aside to reveal the artwork he believes they conceal.</p>
                        <p>The desire for mimetic representation and the development of image-making technologies have progressed from the ancient legend of Butades’ lovelorn daughter tracing shadows to Renaissance-era techniques of tracing light through panes of glass to contemporary ray tracing, a technique for rendering computer graphics (see Figure 2). Deeply wedded to historical theories of light, what joins these separate methods is their focus on the human body as a cycloptic camera lens, an abstract optic perfectly positioned to decode perspectival data.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure02"><head><title rend="italic">Man Drawing a Lute</title> (1525) by Albrecht Dürer and a typical example of ray tracing.</head></figure>
                        <p>But what if the sun had begun to set on Butades’ daughter, transforming her lover’s silhouette into a monstrous grotesque? Or if Zeuxis had approached Parrhasius’ painted curtains from an oblique angle, disrupting the two-dimensional illusion of depth? If Albrecht Dürer’s glass <soCalled>veil</soCalled> had been bumped askew or the algorithms responsible for rendering 3D space were not calibrated properly, would the difference be noticeable or is optical distortion a precondition for mimetic representation? Once the rules of naturalism have been established, it is inevitable that artists, architects, and illustrators alike will seek to break or re-write the codes of perspectival rendering. This potential for experimentation applies as much to the anamorphic techniques employed by early painters as it does to the strange, polygonal environments traversed in virtual worlds. Many recent developments in graphical realism are converging around the computer graphics industry whose design goals and business models largely conform to the possibilities and problems of mimetic technologies. Much like the restrained naturalism of Renaissance perspectival rendering led to a more self-conscious and reflexive Mannerist period of visual art, so have the nascent discourses surrounding computer generated imagery (CGI) and videogaming begun to internalize and amplify their codes and logics. As John Carmack recently noted at the 2011 Electronic Entertainment Expo (E3), computer graphics are <cit><quote rend="inline">converging at the limits of our biological systems</quote> <ptr target="#mccormick2011"/></cit>. The videogame industry is evolving asymptotically toward higher and higher graphic fidelity, and there are only a finite number of unique polygons and pixels perceptible to the human eye. With graphical realism approaching the threshold of human perception, there are an increasing number of computer games experimenting with alternative spatial and optical regimes indigenous to digital environments.</p>
                        <p>This paper begins with a review of how anamorphosis has been deployed as a philosophical tool for exploring the relationship between human phenomenology and technology. Anamorphosis is a perspectival rendering technique that produces warped but geometrically viable images. From Hans Holbein the Younger’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> to Robert Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, anamorphic artworks explore the tension between mathematical models of vision (that reduce sight to a single, abstract locus) and more dispersed models of subjective vision which account for both the human body and its relation to an environment. This tension is made explicit in the 3D modeling and real-time graphic processing of computers. Extending the arguments of media theorists Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, we analyze how anamorphosis functions in contemporary videogames. Games like Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> by Julian Oliver, and Mark ten Bosch’s forthcoming <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> employ anamorphosis as a metaphor for technology, marking dissonant registers of time and space produced between computational processes and the human body. By attempting to represent the alterity of computational logics, these <soCalled>anamorphic games</soCalled> remind the player of the limits of human phenomenology and create gameplay from the desire to think the unthinkable and to play in spaces that exceed the boundaries of human perception.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Memento Mortem Mortis</head>
                        <p>Anamorphosis is a perspectival rendering technique popularized during the Renaissance which results in a strangely stretched, but geometrically viable image requiring a human viewer to assume an oblique viewing angle in order to uncover its encrypted images. While Erwin Panofsky famously claimed in 1927 that traditional perspective operated as a <quote rend="inline">symbolic form,</quote> loaded with the Western ontology of the stable, fixed, and unified Cartesian subject, anamorphosis has remained a marginal visual technique, a <foreign xml:lang="fr">trompe l’oeil</foreign> that operates according to a different cultural logic, stealthily putting pressure on the universality of classical perspective and all the attendant ideological assumptions surrounding this symbolic form <ptr target="#panofsky1996"/>. More recently, the concept of anamorphosis has appeared in the writing of media theorists such as Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen. In these texts, anamorphosis is treated as a tool for examining the discontinuities between biological and computational registers via the discussion of re-embodied vision.</p>
                        <p>Traditionally, the techniques of geometrical projection employed in perspectival rendering assume the position of the viewer as directly in front of and oriented toward the <soCalled>picture plane,</soCalled> an imaginary field that typically coincides with the material surface of an image. Conflating this picture plane with the geometry of canvas allows the simulated light vectors of a given geometric projection to intersect with a material plane rather than a purely virtual surface. This conflation removes the need for difficult, higher level modeling and simplifies the rendering process considerably. The geometry of an anamorphic image, however, produces nonstandard viewing angles by foreshortening this picture plane and decoupling it from the physical geometry of the canvas, screen, or parchment. An experimental and unconventional technique which produces coded, mannered, and seemingly non-natural imagery, anamorphosis is often regarded as a curiosity, an occasional virtuosic supplement to the catalogue of classical perspective throughout the history of art. But if one acknowledges the fact that any historical coincidence of the imaginary picture plane and the material surface of a painting is merely one particular case within a much larger field of possibility, anamorphosis can be re-thought as the rule, rather than the exception to perspectival image making. In a sense, <emph>every image is already anamorphic</emph> though ease of rendering and conventions of human sight privilege one particular, historically contingent instance of anamorphosis: perspective.</p>
                        <p>Though anamorphic images explicitly reinforce the relationship between vision and embodiment through the construction of perspectival spaces that appear to resolve only at nonstandard vantage points and viewing angles (compelling the subject to configure her body to the painting’s unusual constraints), there is a more profound critique of Cartesian subjectivity at work in this optical technique. Anamorphosis foregrounds the impossibility of a perfectly resolved image (including those constructed according to the rules of classical perspective) given the biological complexity of binocular vision, angle of approach, height of the subject, and surface deformations of the media. These anamorphic biases demonstrate that what has been culturally defined as classical perspective remains an essentially arbitrary method of rendering light through mathematical abstractions that are impossible to realize on the parts of both viewer and painter. Whether standing in front of a painting or grasping a controller, embodied vision is made anamorphic through haptic encounters with the material environment.</p>
                        <p>The quintessential example of anamorphosis is Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, a large and meticulously rendered oil painting featuring a strange, anamorphic <soCalled>smear</soCalled> across the bottom of the otherwise typical portrait of two sixteenth-century European diplomats (see Figure 3). The men stand costumed and well-lit in a carefully proportioned, perspectival space, each with an elbow resting on the foreshortened table. The painting displays a menagerie of symbolic details denoting worldly opulence including fine clothing and foreign textiles, a lute with a book of open sheet music, two globes, and various instruments for navigation and cartography: instruments of rationalism that will provide the <soCalled>correct</soCalled> perspective for mapping the New World. Yet, if the viewer examines the painting from an unorthodox position below and to the right of the standard viewing angle, the smear congeals into a grinning skull: a subliminal <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori </foreign> hidden in plain sight.<note>It has been suggested that the portrait was originally hung at the top of a staircase and that glimpses of the skull could be caught upon approaching the painting from the bottom left. Turning around upon descending the staircase would also reveal a concealed skull.</note></p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure03"><head>Hans Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> and a detail of the <soCalled>resolved</soCalled> anamorphic skull.</head></figure>
                        <p>While the inclusion of subtle reminders of mortality like skulls, time pieces, wilting flowers, or rotting fruit were common among portraits and still lifes produced in medieval and Renaissance Europe, Holbein’s <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign> is particularly unsettling given its uncanny manifestation through the technique of anamorphic foreshortening. As Jacques Lacan writes in the <title rend="italic">Four Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis</title>, the anamorphic distortion gives access to <cit><quote rend="inline">a dimension that has nothing to do with vision as such - something symbolic of the function of the lack</quote> <ptr target="#lacan1998" loc="88"/></cit>. Read psychoanalytically, Holbein’s anamorphic skull is a <quote rend="inline">trap for the gaze</quote> into which the subject disappears. Lacan ultimately concludes his chapter not by distinguishing anamorphosis from traditional perspective, but by arguing that it demonstrates what is implicit in all image production (and by extension the concept of a stable Cartesian subject): <cit><quote rend="inline">In any picture, it is precisely in seeking the gaze in each of its points that you will see it disappear </quote> <ptr loc="89" target="#lacan1998"/></cit>.</p>
                        <p>Lacan’s reading of the painting acknowledges the idea that Holbein’s anamorphic skull is powerful not because it looks like a skull, but precisely because it <emph>doesn’t </emph>look like a skull. It is a <emph>not-skull</emph> - a <emph>not-skull</emph> revealing nothing to the viewer but paint. Though it has the potential to trick the eye, this smear of abject materiality bears no formal resemblance to human anatomy and exists within its own ontological register. Holbein’s choice of the skull as representational content further supports this idea. Working with the established cultural tradition of the <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign>, the artist summons notions of death’s alterity as a metaphor for the ultimate strangeness of paint. The fleeting glimpse of a death’s head, reminds the viewer not of their eventual expiration, but - perhaps an even more unsettling reminder - of the fact that there exist inaccessible objects in the world that exceed human legibility. The anamorphic skull suggests a world that not only lies beyond the limitations of the human body, but one that is also completely disinterested in the affairs of man and the vagaries of life and death. </p>
                        <p>In this respect, it may be more accurate to use the term <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis </foreign>than <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori.</foreign> The <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign> transforms the human-centred <soCalled>remembrance of death</soCalled> into the <soCalled>remembrance of the death of death</soCalled>: the realization that one day even death will die. The painterly materiality of the anamorphic skull ultimately exposes a notion of cosmic indifference that is vaster, more alien, and more terrifying than even the anthropocentric concerns of life and death represented through a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign>. The stretched skull, like other depictions of human detritus, has been used to signal human mortality. But by rendering it on a separate, foreshortened picture plane that refuses to cohere with the geometry of the painted scene, this <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign> opens upon the yawning abyss of the <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem.</foreign>
                        </p>
                        <p>This paper reads anamorphosis as a form of <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign>. In anamorphic images, the subject and object never completely resolve for one another, and there remains an incommensurable gap as reflected in Holbein’s painting. In this sense, the human and the skull can never see eye to eye, and <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors </title>functions as an allegory for deanthropomorphized materiality in the idiom of early-modern painting. Hubert Damisch has argued that mathematical perspective has been the dominant mode of image-making in the twentieth century (far more than previous eras prior to the development of mechanical forms of image inscription such as photography, film, and video <ptr target="#damisch1995" loc="28"/>). Yet this traditional perspective can still be regarded as just a special case of anamorphosis: projected from one point on an infinite spectrum adapted to generalized angles and eyelines of the human body. All paintings are anamorphic in so far as they apply the rules of perspectival projection to an arbitrary, anthropocentric picture plane. The coincidence of the picture plane and material surface of the image is popular because of the convenience of calculating only one projection, rather than the multiple abstractions necessary in anamorphosis. Developing alongside this technology, the culture of perspective reinforces the status until it appears natural to the human viewer despite the fact that perspectival rendering still requires those same mathematical systems of geometric projection used to construct any anamorphic image. Thus, all paintings could be considered anamorphic, but only some, like <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, form a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign> to explicitly question the necessary relation between the human body, an image’s material support, and the virtual geometries of the perspectival picture plane.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>PART 1: ANAMORPHOSIS AND MEDIA THEORY</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Ergodic Resolution</head>
                        <p>For media theorists like Espen Aarseth and Mark Hansen, anamorphosis functions as a useful model for framing their theories of digital media. Aarseth and Hansen adopt two contrasting approaches. Whereas Aarseth uses anamorphosis to speak about what he calls <soCalled>ergodic literature</soCalled> and operates from the assumption that anamorphic objects include a <soCalled>correct</soCalled> location or perspective from which to view an image, Hansen uses anamorphosis as a model for describing those aspects of digital media that fail to resolve and which produce a bodily tension based on the formal incongruity between inhabitable space and computational space.</p>
                        <p>Espen Aarseth’s <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title> <ptr target="#aarseth1997"/>is a highly influential work of media criticism and an early entry into the nascent field of game studies. Using a variety of examples taken from print, computer games, hypertext, and electronic literature, Aarseth builds a working theory of <soCalled>ergodic literature,</soCalled> his term for literary works whose completion requires <quote rend="inline">nontrivial effort</quote> on the part of the reader <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="1-2"/>. By nontrivial effort, Aarseth means the kinetic as well as intellectual effort performed by a reader or player that specifically functions to influence the outcome of a given text or game (this is distinct, for example, from flipping to the end of a book to read the final pages). If we consider Aarseth’s model in relation to Holbein’s skull, bending low to the ground in an effort to match the oblique angle of anamorphic distortion is similar to Aarseth’s notion of ergodic, nontrivial labor. This effort required of a viewer of anamorphic images is what leads Aarseth to make an analogy between early modern techniques of anamorphosis and certain forms of interactive media.</p>
                        <p>In the concluding chapter of <title rend="italic">Cybertext</title>, Aarseth suggests that anamorphosis is a <cit><quote rend="inline">solvable enigma</quote> <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="181"/></cit>. For Aarseth, the key quality of anamorphosis is the moment of revelation produced when the distortion of the warped image is suddenly resolved through the viewer’s effort of locating the vantage point from which the rational order of classical perspective is restored. It is this passage from what he terms <quote rend="inline">aporia</quote> to <quote rend="inline">epiphany</quote> by which he conflates anamorphic painting with ergodic literature <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="181"/>. For Aarseth, the text-based games and interactive fiction of the late seventies and early eighties such as Will Crowther and Don Woods’ <title rend="italic">Colossal Cave Adventure</title> (1975–76) and Infocom's <title rend="italic">Zork</title> trilogy (1980–84) are models of an anamorphic textuality in which the player must work in order for the mystery to be revealed. </p>
                        <p>But not all ergodic texts provide puzzles with seemingly concrete answers and Aarseth invents a second category he terms <quote rend="inline">metamorphosis</quote> in which mastery and resolution are refused (e.g. Michael Joyce’s <title rend="italic">Afternoon: A Story </title>[1987]). This article proposes, however, that there is no need for a second category in which to reroute those texts which do not have singular interpretations, linear causality, or solvable enigmas. As argued in the previous section, rather than reifying a specific subject position in front of a painting, image, or artifact, the anamorphic technique radically critiques all subject positions as tenuous and fraught. Even if there is a viewing angle in which an image becomes discernible, this angle is no more <soCalled>correct</soCalled> than any other and any resolution the viewer might feel is automatically suspect. The anamorphic skull in <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> (1553) is not a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign> in the sense that it reminds the viewer of her mortality as she catches a glimpse of the skull through the corner of her eye, but because it calls into question the very concept of a fixed subject and resolved object. The logic of the stretched skull, the <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign>, suggests that the subject herself is distributed, deferred, and derealized in the same way the anamorphic image smears across the canvas.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Strange Skulls</head>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media </title> <ptr target="#hansen2006"/> Mark Hansen also relates anamorphosis to contemporary digital media practice. For Hansen, however, it is the failure of anamorphic images to be easily digested by the human body which he finds relevant to digital forms. Hansen uses Robert Lazzarini’s sculptural installation <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, exhibited at the Whitney Museum of American Art’s 2000 show <title rend="italic">BitStreams</title>, as his central case study in order to explain the relationship between digital media and anamorphosis (see Figure 4). Like Hans Holbein and other Renaissance painters who practiced anamorphic techniques, Robert Lazzarini’s artwork engages with the limits of human perception, systems of perspectival projection, and the essential tension produced between these two orders. Instead of projecting smears of paint across picture planes, a purely visual puzzle, Lazzarini builds smeared sculptures which stretch in three-dimensions and challenge the viewer to reconcile vision and proprioception. Where anamorphosis renders perspectival imagery onto a foreshortened picture plane, Lazzarini’s sculptural process involves applying perspectival effects directly to the geometry of a set of haptic objects.</p>
                        <p>Figure 4. A photograph of one of Robert Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title>.</p>
                        <p>A critical component of Lazzarini’s practice is his choice of what to sculpt. Though the artist’s thoroughly digitized development process - starting by 3D laser-scanning each object to produce editable polygonal models then bending, warping, shifting, and deforming each file before finally crafting each rapidly prototyped outcome from authentic materials - remains relatively consistent throughout his catalogue of sculptures, each is selected to produce cognitive tension between the physical materiality of the sculpture and a particular perceptual effect <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="199"/>. The subject matter and materials of Lazzarini’s process change from skulls to violins, hammers, teacups, telephones (and telephone booths), chairs, knives, revolvers, and brass knuckles. These household objects and weapons share one thing in common aside from Lazzarini’s anamorphic effects: an ergonomic reference to the human body. It is only through this remarkable tension between optic and haptic that Lazzarini’s sculptures become tools from another digital dimension, hammers with ungraspable handles.</p>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">Tool-Being: Heidegger and the Metaphysics of Objects</title> <ptr target="#harman2002"/>, Graham Harman re-imagines Martin Heidegger’s philosophy of objects, examining the commonly received understanding of Heidegger’s concept of <quote rend="inline">present-at-hand</quote> and <quote rend="inline">ready-to-hand objects.</quote> Harman proposes that implicit in Heidegger’s thinking is a far more radical ontology of objects themselves than has been traditionally assumed and builds his <quote rend="inline">object-oriented ontology</quote> around the idea that objects have a kind of secret life in which they <cit><quote rend="inline">withdraw from human view into a dark subterranean reality that never becomes present to practical action any more than it does to theoretical awareness</quote> <ptr target="#harman2002" loc="1"/></cit>. With Lazzarini’s sculptures, the viewer experiences the chasm between herself and the inaccessible tool-being of objects. Anamorphosis functions as a metaphor for a speculative ontology as Lazzarini sculpts objects that literally appear to recede from our vision. These objects gesture towards a world beyond life and death (and even undeath).</p>
                        <p>Yet amongst this myriad of digitally disfigured tools, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> stands apart. The sculpture does not have the same status as a hammer that cannot be held or wielded. There is a certain irony to the fact that <title rend="italic">skulls</title> maintains a kind of functionality: the fact that viewers cannot fix their gaze on a stable optical regime only intensifies the skulls’ role as a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign>. Technically, it does what it is supposed to do: it enables the (philosophical and contemplative) work such objects are typically designed to generate. Harman writes that there is <quote rend="inline">an absolute gulf between the things and any interaction we might have with them</quote> which exists with respect to all objects. The optical instability of Lazzarini’s sculptures draws attention to this fact, yet it still reinscribes the centrality of human perception. This is perhaps why Mark Hansen chose <title rend="italic">skulls</title> as emblematic of the profoundly alienating condition of the digital in <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media</title>. Lazzarini’s skulls shift focus away from the ergonomic, hand-held common objects to the forms of the body itself. Looming in life-scale, carved in bone, yet digitally modeled, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> renders one of the most visually recognizable parts of human anatomy strange and uncanny. What provided a fleeting glimpse into the Real for Lacan, is used by Hansen to demonstrate the incommensurable ontology of a computer.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Digital Any-Space-Whatever</head>
                        <p>In a chapter titled <title rend="quotes">The Affective Topology of New Media,</title> Hansen argues that Lazzarini’s adaptation of the anamorphic skull from Holbein’s <title rend="italic">Ambassadors</title> is <cit><quote rend="inline">exemplary of digital media art</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. Lazzarini’s sculptures exist physically within three-dimensional space and yet, no matter what angle the distorted objects are viewed from, they fail to visually resolve in a satisfying way. Their hollow eyes refuse to stare back. Viewers of these uncanny objects inhabit a space completely at odds with the skulls which remain inaccessible and inassimilable to standard optical perspective. If one could close her eyes and hold Lazzarini’s stretched skulls, the contours might resolve to the haptic touch, but as Hansen writes, <title rend="italic">skulls </title> <cit><quote rend="inline"><soCalled>makes sense</soCalled> visually - only within the weird logic and topology of the computer</quote> <ptr loc="202" target="#hansen2006"/></cit>. In this sense, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> picks up where <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> left off, signaling the existence of a nonhuman realm external to embodied perception and simultaneously challenging the ocularcentrism of the Cartesian subject by reinforcing a mutual, albeit dissonant, relation between eye and touch.</p>
                        <p>Holbein’s use of anamorphosis re-directs attention away from mathematical models of vision by emphasizing the contingency of sight on a viewer’s specific bodily relation to an image (and when conceived as a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign>, the radical contingency of life in general). Similarly, <title rend="italic">skulls</title> challenges notions of frictionless immersivity and the desire for intuitive, natural, or, as Apple advertises, <soCalled>magic</soCalled> interfaces that attempt to render human-computer interaction invisible. In spite of this history of user-friendly interface design, Lazzarini offers an optical distortion designed to disrupt, rather than pacify, the senses. Instead of appealing to the fantasy of immersion, anamorphic technologies delight in the fact that perspective can never be fully realized to the embodied viewer. Lazzarini’s sculptures, according to Hansen, produce a bodily experience of what he terms the <quote rend="inline">digital any-space-whatever</quote> (digital ASW), a proprioceptive experience akin to nausea or vertigo as the body fails to orient itself. Hansen writes that in the face of <title rend="italic">skulls</title> <cit><quote rend="inline">you feel the space around you begin to ripple, to bubble, to infold…and you notice an odd tensing in your gut, as if your viscera were itself trying to adjust to this warped space</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="198-9"/></cit>. This physical response recalls Slavoj Žižek’s description of the Lacanian Real as <cit><quote rend="inline">the pulsing of the pre-symbolic substance in all its abhorrent vitality</quote> <ptr target="#zizek1999" loc="19"/></cit>.</p>
                        <p>Hansen’s term for this unsettling bodily awareness, the digital ASW, is based on Gilles Deleuze’s cinematic <quote rend="inline">any-space-whatever</quote> (ASW) discussed in <title rend="italic">Cinema 1</title> <ptr target="#deleuze1986" loc="109"/>. Deleuze’s cinematic ASW was an attempt to describe the empty, dislocated spaces of post-war cinema and distinguish them from the Hollywood logic of pre-war film. What is foregrounded, in both Deleuze’s and Hansen’s version of the ASW, is not the visual perception of this space, but the effects produced on the body. The key difference between the digital ASW and Deleuze’s theory is that <cit><quote rend="inline">because it must be forged out of contact with a radically inhuman realm, the digital ASW lacks an originary contact with the space of human activity</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="204"/></cit>. As such, the digital ASW emerges within the body when the viewer comes in contact with the impossible physics and unconventional perspectives of computational space. Hansen argues that <cit><quote rend="inline">[w]hat <title rend="italic">skulls</title> affords is, consequently, not a direct apprehension of an alien space that <emph>is</emph> digital, but a bodily apprehension of just how radically alien the formal field of the computer is</quote> <ptr loc="205" target="#hansen2006"/></cit>. In a famous scene from <title rend="italic">The Matrix</title> (1999), a character named Cypher comments <quote rend="inline">I don't even see the code. All I see is blonde, brunette, red-head</quote> (a feat which simultaneously exceeds human optical processing power and posits an indexical relationship between code and representation). The desire to see through the code is conflated with a voyeuristic pleasure in women's bodies. By contrast, Lazzarini’s art substitutes <foreign xml:lang="grc">eros</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">thanatos</foreign> in a process that forecloses any fetishized fantasy of access. A viewer’s encounter with his computational space produces only a heightened sense of the bodily alterity and unreadability of digital landscapes.</p>
                        <p>Following Hansen’s argument, videogames, like all digital media, are built upon formal fields only interpretable by computers. Effectively barring the human agent from ever achieving full access, the incongruity of computational and biological forms of space and time produces an embodied and affective response in the human: Hansen’s digital ASW. This is a response, however, that most game designers attempt to mitigate. While a work like <title rend="italic">skulls</title> emphasizes the failure of the viewer to grasp these forever skewed and uncanny objects, videogames do not generally make a practice of cultivating sensory discomfort as such a game is unlikely to gain a large audience or be commercially viable. While a novice player may find the side-scrolling environments of a game like <title rend="italic">Super Mario Bros.</title> (1985) uncanny and baffling, the goal of Shigeru Miyamoto and Nintendo’s developers has always been to create worlds in which the spatial and temporal mechanics can be quickly apprehended and then taken for granted in order to engage in other, more digestible operations.</p>
                        <p>For example, two-dimensional spatializations such as moving left to right (as one might read English or advance forward in the first quadrant of a Cartesian grid) or climbing from the bottom of the screen toward the top were exploited by and reinforced in early arcade games and influenced Nintendo’s original titles. However, in <title rend="italic">The Legend Of Zelda</title> (1986), it is only custom and visual literacy that prevents a player from thinking that the player’s avatar, Link, is not floating through a 2D space, a gravityless version of <title rend="italic">Super Mario Bros.</title> In <title rend="italic">Legend of Zelda</title>, rather than assuming the perspective of a side-scrolling cross section, the horizontal and vertical axes correspond to the cardinal directions of an orthographic, bird’s-eye view map. Link’s movement is multi-directional, a significant feat at the time allowing him to walk North, South, East, and West rather than forward, backward, up, and down. While there is nothing <emph>necessarily</emph> intuitive or natural about this spatial mapping, the game was designed to mitigate the strangeness of navigating this artificial world rather than draw attention to its eccentricities.</p>
                        <p>Not all games follow this policy, and there are some exceptions to this rule. Even in <title rend="italic">The Legend of Zelda</title>, there are two in-game locations that explicitly defy Cartesian cartography: the Lost Woods and the Lost Hills. When traveling through these single-screen mazes, Link finds himself endlessly looping, temporarily arrested by a classic gaming trope. Like <title rend="italic">Asteroids</title> (1979) and <title rend="italic">Pacman</title> (1980), if the player’s avatar crosses the edge of the screen, it appears immediately on the opposite side as if teleported instantly from one side of the level to the other. This looping effect is initially counterintuitive but becomes more and more naturalized as player’s adjust their spatial expectations to the particularities of each game-space. </p>
                        <p>The logic of each maze in <title rend="italic">The Legend of Zelda</title> is relatively straightforward to program. A series of <soCalled>if</soCalled> statements dictate which sequence of directions lead Link out of each repeating landscape. Yet, the mathematical certainty and programmatic simplicity of the Lost Woods and Lost Hills generates visually complex topologies. Were a player to attempt to map the twists and turns Link traverses while rambling through the woods or hills, she would find the geometry of each maze would not cohere with the map of Hyrule. In this case, procedural and haptic logics do not render coherent visual schema. Whether the player realizes it or not, each looping space maps not to the flattened grid on which the rest of Hyrule is designed, but instead to the topology of a 3D torus (see Figure 5.) Recalling Hansen’s reading of <title rend="italic">skulls</title>, it is possible for experienced players intuit the topology of the torus, but visualizing this space proves far more difficult.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure04"><head>Screenshots of the Lost Woods and Lost Hills from <title rend="italic">The Legend of Zelda</title>, with visualizations of each location in the form of a torus.</head></figure>
                        <p>The games we will examine in this essay intentionally play within the dissonant registers produced between biological and computational systems. Their use of anamorphic techniques does not abandon the player to some raw, naked digital landscape (such an encounter, like an encounter with the Lacanian Real, would be impossible), but instead produces gameplay-metaphors that model an engagement with the concept of an unthinkable computational wildernesses. Moreover, they offer a fantasy of mastery through the successful completion of goal-oriented tasks and suggest that the body can be acclimated to these eccentric spaces. Flight simulators were developed to combat air sickness, and it is with a similar logic that <quote rend="inline">anamorphic games</quote> invite players to test drive the digital ASW, to make it safe and naturalize the body to the <cit><quote rend="inline">incredible strangeness…odd tensing[s]…weird sensation[s]</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="198-9"/></cit> of a computer’s alien topography.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>PART 2: ANAMORPHIC GAMES</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Introduction to Anamorphic Games</head>
                        <p>Although thousands of years have passed, the guiding principles of the gaming industry are not radically different from those which produced the lover’s silhouette or Zeuxis’ painted grapes. W.J.T. Mitchell’s <title rend="italic">Reconfigured Eye: Visual Truth in the Post-Photographic Era</title> <ptr target="#mitchell2001"/>, for example, opens with Pliny’s birth of painting and draws a genealogical line from early optical experiments to contemporary digital imaging techniques. This path from Dürer’s glass perspectival grids to digital ray tracing is one to which the development of computer games has stubbornly stuck, largely propelled by the desire for realistic, immersive experiences. As Robert F. Nideffer pithily summarizes:
                        <cit><quote rend="block">Improved lighting, increasingly accurate physics models, and more believable artificial intelligence (AI) are seen as the next frontier for game engines by many in the industry. For anyone who attends meetings like the Game Developers Conference (GDC), the Electronic Entertainment Expo (E3), or SIGGRAPH, it quickly becomes apparent that these concerns are voiced almost exclusively from the desire to enhance the game world's realism.</quote> <ptr target="#nideffer2007" loc="215-16"/></cit></p>
                        <p>Realism, in this case, refers to the ability to accurately represent mimetic detail as well as simulate a lived experience. Added to this privileging of graphic spectacle is an adherence to Hollywood’s narrative conventions, which frequently take precedence over aesthetic experimentation and the development of novel game mechanics. Thus, it is not realism or naturalism, but more specifically it is a <emph>filmic</emph> realism that defines the aesthetics of many recent commercial games. The emergence and celebration of the <soCalled>cut-scene</soCalled> in the late nineties is perhaps the most egregious way in which games have attempted to translate filmic storytelling into videogame narratives. A survey of the most anticipated games shown at this year’s E3 confirms that Nideffer’s observations continue to be applicable as mainstream games are dominated by Hollywood-style visual and narrative logic. The showpieces are comprised of games like <title rend="italic">Mass Effect 3,</title> 
                            <title rend="italic">Modern Warfare 3</title>, <title rend="italic">Battlefield 3</title>, <title rend="italic">Uncharted 3,</title> and <title rend="italic">Far Cry 3</title>, which tempt players with the promise of the richest and most filmically immersive graphics on the market. The ubiquity of the series, as seen in the overwhelming number of game franchises, further demonstrates the conservative conditions under which mainstream games operate. There is generally less stigma attached to videogame sequels when compared to other media as both programmers and gamers alike seem to have a higher tolerance for seriality. The computational processes driving most games (and software at large) can be easily expanded, modified, and resold – there is always a substantial amount of exchange and appropriation in games at the level of code.  Moreover, a game’s narrative is frequently regarded as peripheral to enjoyment of the software compared with modifications of gameplay. As a result, commercial studios are more reluctant to take million-dollar risks on untested intellectual property than simply revise an already-vetted formula when there is less pressure from the market to do so.</p>
                        <p>Amidst the production of <title rend="italic">Final Fantasy XIV</title> and the annual <title rend="italic">Madden NFL</title>, however, a transformation has occurred. The increased power of home computers and the availability of open source game engines and network toolsets have re-catalyzed the development of smaller-scale projects through user-generated content and modding, networked webgames, augmented and alternate reality game design, and mobile apps. The diffusion of the modes of production, the accessibility of design technologies, and the formation of a broader audience have inspired the development of experimental games that challenge more traditional genres. Now it is not uncommon to see games that frame themselves as meta-games, art games, countergames, antigames, overgames, endgames, and notgames.</p>
                        <p>The games discussed in this essay have been selected because they manipulate time, space, and physics in ways that draw attention not only to the formal logics of the computer, but also to how they situate and re-embody the player’s interaction with the game. The human body is tuned to intuitively negotiate the physics of time and space: crouching to avoid a low overhang or deftly catching balance after slipping on unstable terrain. But what happens to this proprioceptive capacity when encountering a hybridized space, a mixture of the actual and the virtual which contrasts embodied space-time with anamorphic algorithms? What if a body were required to negotiate two- and three-dimensional spaces simultaneously as with Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> software? Can muscles remember the extra-dimensional abstractions overlaying Julian Oliver’s <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>? And is it possible to simulate a fourth dimension as Mark ten Bosch’s <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> claims? These games offer the player simulations of a poetic physics, or what Bill Seaman has termed <quote rend="inline">e-phany physics,</quote> namely <cit><quote rend="inline">the code-based authoring of an artificial physics which is consistent within the virtual space, yet does not adhere to the laws of actual physics</quote> <ptr target="#seaman2000" loc="41"/></cit>. So what happens to the body when those laws of physics internalized since birth are re-written within these poetic simulations? The following videogames create interfaces to allegorize a space beyond the limits of human perception. Louis Althusser famously defined ideology as <quote rend="inline">imaginary resolutions to real contradictions</quote> and these games attempt to resolve, hubristically, that <quote rend="inline">absolute gulf</quote> that Hansen posits between digital space and human experience.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Echochrome: Depth Perception, Optical Architecture</head>
                        <p>When the first generation of home videogame consoles supporting 3D graphic processing was introduced in the mid-nineties, the development of 2D, sprite-based game development was temporarily arrested. <note>This generation included notable systems like the Sega Saturn (1994), the Sony PlayStation (1994), and the Nintendo 64 (1996) which ran at least 32-bit graphic processors in order to render real time polygonal meshes which made up the perspectival spaces of 3D games.</note> In the flush of fascination with these strange new polygonal spaces, the efforts of game designers were redirected from painting with pixels towards domesticating and naturalizing 3D environments for mainstream consumption (compared to earlier videogames, 3D games had a higher barrier to entry).</p>
                        <p>Nintendo’s transition from 2D to 3D games demonstrates the challenges of adjusting to these new spaces. Remembering the difficult launch of <title rend="italic">Super Mario 64</title> (1996), a release title for the Nintendo 64, Shigeru Miyamato remarked in a conversation with Nintendo’s CEO Satoru Iwata that <cit><quote rend="inline">[t]he reason that people felt distant to 3D action games was because those games were easy for some people to get motion sickness” and that it was “easy to get lost in the playing field</quote> <ptr target="#iwata2011"/></cit>. Hansen likens the feeling of the digital ASW to motion sickness and, in the case of videogames, this is precisely the medical condition a large number of uninitiated players experienced upon first exposure to 3D graphics. Despite the dramatic advancements that have been made in graphic processing technologies and audiences for such games have expanded, the difficulty of acclimatizing players to these spaces still remains. Even today, particularly amongst Japanese consumers, Nintendo's 2D titles consistently out-sell its 3D counterparts. Both <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title> (2007) and <title rend="italic">New Super Mario Bros.</title> (2006), for example, were released around the same time and both were critically acclaimed; yet the side-scrolling platforming game sold two and a half times more copies than <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title>. <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title> was one of the first games to incorporate eccentric gravity and spherical levels into its design. In his interview with Miyamoto, Iwata comments, <cit><quote rend="inline">[A]t the time, I did not fully understand its benefits. I knew right away that visually [<title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy</title>] would look great. But its true value was beyond what could be seen with the eyes, it was something that I hadn’t realized</quote> <ptr target="#iwata2011"/></cit>. Both Miyamoto's remark on motion sickness and Iwata’s observation on the way in which the effects of spherical space transcend optical effects indicate an awareness of how the body functions while playing these games. The visual is only a small part in a much more comprehensive bodily engagement with digital space.</p>
                        <p>In recent years, there has been a renaissance of 2D platforming games. The flatness of screen and 2D space is no longer a technological constraint, but a design decision which can be placed in conjunction with 3D spaces. One series of games which structures its gameplay around the intersection of two- and three-dimensional space and perspectival play is Sony’s <title rend="italic">Echo</title> series consisting of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II,</title> and <title rend="italic">Echoshift</title>.</p>
                        <p>The first title, <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, is produced by Sony's Japan Studio and Game Yarouze for the PlayStation Portable (PSP) and PlayStation 3 (PS3). In <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> the player is presented with a minimal, immaculately white space featuring one central object: a strange set of stairs, walkways, ramps, and ramparts reminiscent of M.C. Escher's impossible spaces and paradoxical architectures (see Figure 6). By twisting the joystick, this hovering level begins to rotate and, unlike a hand-drawn optical illusion, actually reconstitutes its perspectival paradoxes in real time. All the while, one solitary figure wanders back and forth, clacking footsteps resonating in empty space. The lone resident of these <soCalled>endless walkways</soCalled> is a textureless wooden mannequin who automatically strolls up and down the crisply contoured, isometric spaces inspired by M.C. Escher. Both the reference to Escher's artwork and the autonomous wooden mannequin, an object traditionally used for rendering perspectival figures, are fitting considering that the game’s main mechanic involves the player morphing strange spaces in ways that paradoxically play with the dichotomy between the representations of 3D rotations and the flat screen on which it is rendered.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure05"><head>Images of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s mannequin and level design.</head></figure>
                        <p>There are five main rules to the pictorial logic governing the mannequin's movements through geometric space. These five perspectival laws, as presented in the official trailer, are:
                        <cit><quote rend="block">(1) When two separate pathways appear to be touching, they are. (2) If one pathway appears to be above another, it is. (3) When the gap between two pathways is blocked from view and the pathways appear to be connected, they are. (4) When a hole is blocked from view, it does not exist. (5) When the mannequin jumps, it will land on whatever appears beneath it</quote> <ptr target="#sony2008"/></cit>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s five rules all relate to the appearance of space as rendered to a flat image. Much like Nintendo's 2007 release of <title rend="italic">Super Paper Mario</title> for the Nintendo Wii, Kuju Entertainment's Zoë Mode development studio's 2007 release of <title rend="italic">Crush</title> for the PSP, and Polytron Corporation’s perennially forthcoming premier title, <title rend="italic">Fez</title>, for XBLA, in the world of <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, the three-dimensional architecture reflects and corroborates that which appears on the two-dimensional screen. In <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, it is the pictorial logic of the screen that is given precedence over the mimetic representation of space. What you see is literally what you get.</p>
                        <p>Along with games such as <title rend="italic">Super Paper Mario</title>, <title rend="italic">Crush</title>, and <title rend="italic">Fez</title>, <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> recalls Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors </title>in the way it mixes traditional perspective with anamorphic effects. By self-consciously placing both two- and three-dimensional space in conversation with each other, the game conflates the dual logic of flat <soCalled>screen</soCalled> and deep <soCalled>window,</soCalled> two metaphors Anne Friedberg compares and contrasts in <title rend="italic">The Virtual Window: From Alberti to Microsoft</title> <ptr target="#friedberg2006"/>. Friedberg argues that although perspective has historically been the culturally dominant form of visuality, computers have dramatically transformed how space is perceived and organized. She examines the graphic user interface of a computer desktop and the way it is composed of multiple, overlapping windows, conflicting light sources, and purely abstract drop shadows. Despite the fact that the <soCalled>window,</soCalled> which operating systems like Microsoft Windows provide, is overlooking a non-linear, non-perspectival vista, contemporary culture has adapted to this mode of spatial organization to the point that it appears as a continuous, uninterrupted space. Despite its mathematical artifice, Leon Battista Alberti famously described classical perspective as a <soCalled>window</soCalled> onto another world, and Friedberg demonstrates how computer software companies have appropriated similar rhetoric in order to naturalize what is a constructed, artificial space composed of many perspectival contradictions and incongruities. <note>Terry Harpold also makes this observation in <title rend="italic">Ex-foliations: Reading Machines and the Upgrade Path</title> <ptr target="#harpold2009"/> when he examines the <soCalled>Bliss Screen</soCalled> of Windows XP, which included the default wallpaper of rolling grass and blue sky. Noting the uncanny connection between this pastoral imagery and Freud’s description of an alpine meadow in his 1899 essay <title rend="quotes">Screen Memories,</title> Harpold analyzes the advertising surrounding the release of the OS. One television commercial sets Madonna’s <title rend="quotes">Ray of Light</title> against images of euphoric Microsoft users <soCalled>diving</soCalled> through the screen in order to soar through (indistinguishable) physical and virtual spaces to the amazement of those looking on who have yet to test the GUI for themselves. The rhetoric of unmediated immersion and of a deep perspective, which the advertisement deploys in order to present the computer screen as a perspectival <soCalled>window,</soCalled> renders invisible the complex and contradictory non-linear visual organization that truly comprises the Windows GUI <ptr target="#harpold2009" loc="238-41"/>.</note></p>
<p>
                            <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> stands out as a particularly intriguing example of an alternative spatial organization because it knowingly plays with the tension between pictorial and three-dimensional space. <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> insists that the player confront the contradictions of digital space rather than render them invisible or subordinate to the goals of user-friendliness or functionality. It is in this respect that <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> places itself in the same genealogical family as <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors.</title> 
                            <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, in fact, similarly illustrates the tension between material surface and illusionistic depth. Within the rhetoric of window and screen that Friedberg explores, one can imagine oneself looking through a virtual window onto the scene of two ambassadors standing beside each other. This fantasy is disrupted, however, through the presence of the smeared skull. The skull does not exist within the three-dimensional space of the painting, but instead appears as an object that is literally not of that world, or, as Hansen writes, an <cit><quote rend="inline">envoy from elsewhere</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. The fact that Holbein’s skull does not inhabit the same virtual plane is demonstrated by the fact that its shadows are not cast from the same light source. It is as if an imaginary pane of glass covers this <soCalled>window</soCalled> and the skull has been smeared over its transparent surface. There is a figure/ground oscillation as the painting moves between drawing attention to itself as a window as well as a screen. This hypermediated effect in which multiple lighting sources create layered windows into heterogeneous visual orders is the same visual logic at work in <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>.</p>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>, as the player rotates the central object in three-dimensions, the real-time graphic processes render the illusion of depth, the screen or monitor serving as virtual window. Near and far, broad and deep, at first <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s architecture appears to behave rationally, like a revolving showroom car or a piece of electronics on a turntable. However, when the collisions and connections of the Escher-esque architecture are ultimately determined according to the logic of the suspended two-dimensional image, the <soCalled>window</soCalled> into another realm flattens into an opaque screen.</p>
                        <p>Adjusting <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s perspective does not only transform the player’s view, but the structure of the architecture itself. The spatial dimensions and the composition of the object do not remain fixed in an absolute space. The architecture is reconstituted depending on the angle from which it is viewed. Much like <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> the game suggests that if the player positions herself correctly in front of the screen, the secret of solving the puzzle will be revealed. Discovering the solution to these levels, cracking their spatial code, is not unlike the idea that there exists a single viewing point from which <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> must be viewed in order to see the skull. This is also what separates <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> (and even <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> to some extent) from a work like <title rend="italic">skulls</title>. The puzzle logic acts as an interface through which the player finds herself able to assume a naïve position of control and mastery of those perspectives that should otherwise be hopelessly unresolvable. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Echochrome II: Hand Puppets and Shadow Play</head>
                        <p>
                            <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> creates a world built around the intersections of pictorial and three-dimensional space. <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s sequel, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, once again plays with these rules, but, in addition to its predecessor’s uniquely hybrid perspective of both two- and three-dimensional objects, the sequel incorporates the play of light and shadow. Once again, what you see is what you get. The mannequin’s silhouette, referred to as <quote rend="inline">the cast,</quote> must traverse visual puzzles via the player’s anamorphic manipulations of light. In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, the cast does not walk along the physical objects, but along the shadowy, two-dimensional projected surfaces that fall in the wake of floating blocks, stairs, and steps (see Figure 7).</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure06"><head>An <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> advertisement featuring interactive illumination.</head></figure>
                        <p>Like its predecessor, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II </title>is developed by Sony’s Japan Studio and made for PS3 but requires the PlayStation Move, a motion sensing hand controller spatially tracked by the PS Eye, Sony’s interactive infrared camera. <note>The Sony Move is part of the latest generation of controllers for mainstream consoles and competes with other motion-control sensors such as the Wii Remote and the hands-free Kinect in which the Xbox 360 reads the physical gestures and voice commands of the player. These technologies call attention to the player’s body, situating them much more explicitly in a spatial relationship to the games being played. Unlike <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title> and <title rend="italic">skulls</title> which shock the human body by highlighting the tension between the virtual and the physical, these controllers attempt to suture the two realities together in a way that appears natural or intuitive.</note> The Move controller is topped by a glowing sphere that flickers and changes colors when the wand is active, emitting infrared light for the PS Eye (see Figure 8). This motion tracking technology inverts the relationship between controller and camera pioneered by the Nintendo Wii, which emits two infrared points of light from a stationary bar set near the screen and received by a camera within the Wii Remote (see Figure 8). In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, this light-tracking technology is used to literally position the in-game light source which, when cast on the floating objects, produces virtual shadows in real time based on the player’s bodily gestures. These motions translate into the computational space surprisingly well as the player shines the Move controller on her television screen like a digitized flashlight. Rays are traced from the tip of the wand at the precise angle of incidence, rays which pierce multiple realities to simulate light sources for in-game objects and architectures.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure07"><head>A comparison of Sony’s PlayStation Move and Nintendo’s Wii Remote.</head></figure>
                        <p>While videogames like Hideo Kojima’s <title rend="italic">Metal Gear Solid</title> series (1998–present) revolutionized stealth mechanics by extending the physicality of in-game characters to include their footsteps, blood trails, ambient sounds, odor, and, of course, shadows, other games like Fumito Ueda’s <title rend="italic">Ico</title> (2001) pits the player against impressionistic shadow beasts, dwelling in the dark corners of high citadels and deep dungeons. Shadows have long been generated in videogames to both establish <foreign xml:lang="fr">mise-en-scène</foreign> and shape the mood of virtual settings, enhancing graphic realism and general legibility through the addition of naturalistic details. Recently, however, a number of games have re-cast the shadow, moving it from the background to become either an overarching aesthetic style or core game mechanic. Within the last year, for example, Playdead’s <title rend="italic">Limbo</title> (2010) and Hudson’s <title rend="italic">Lost in Shadow</title> (2011) exploit shadowy imagery to represent the wandering souls of lost children. In <title rend="italic">Limbo</title> and <title rend="italic">Lost in Shadow</title>, flat, boyish avatars traverse perverted silhouettes of everyday life in search of their missing bodies (see Figure 9). They are shades caught in monotone netherworlds. The visual rhetoric employed by these two games is reminiscent of fairytales featuring magic mirrors, crystal balls, and wishing wells – cautionary tales of reflection, refraction, and other tricks of light.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure08"><head>Screenshots comparing the shadowy avatars in both <title rend="italic">Limbo</title> and <title rend="italic">Lost in Shadow</title>.</head></figure>
                        <p>Continuing this minor tradition of <soCalled>shadow play,</soCalled> the more experimental offerings from the independent developers producing <title rend="italic">Closure</title> (forthcoming) and <title rend="italic">Unfinished Swan</title> (forthcoming) focus on shadows as their main game mechanic. In the Flash-turning-console game <title rend="italic">Closure</title>, a puzzle platformer which follows <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>’s what-you-see-is-what-you-get logic, designers Jon Schubbe and Tyler Glaiel program onscreen objects that physically persist only if illuminated. In the procedural architecture of <title rend="italic">Closure</title> blackness <emph>is</emph> nothingness – any unlit object simply ceases to exist allowing the childlike player-character to tiptoe through dimly lit walls and tumble through shadows cast on the floor. <title rend="italic">Closure</title> recalls the aesthetic of Edward Gorey’s <title rend="italic">Gashlycrumb Tinies</title> (1963), a gruesome alphabet book which poetically describes how a group of children met their untimely deaths (e.g. <quote rend="inline">N is for Neville who died of ennui</quote>) and, like <title rend="italic">Limbo</title>, follows lone children through Purgatory (see Figure 10). Following the conventions of the other two games, Schubbe and Glaiel present a child’s-eye view of a world turned black and white, a world in which anamorphic light and shadow distort physical reality. Like the reader of <title rend="italic">Gashlycrumb Tinies,</title> the player uncovers the many ways in which she can plunge into nothingness.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure09"><head>A comparison of the Gashlycrumb aesthetic and indie game <title rend="italic">Closure</title>.</head></figure>
                        <p>Lying at the opposite end of the color spectrum, <title rend="italic">The Unfinished Swan</title> is an experimental prototype developed by Giant Sparrow. The game is a first-person shooter set in a field of blinding whiteness. Luckily, the player wields a kind of paint or shadow gun used to differentiate the otherwise invisible geometry of each level as one progresses (see Figure 11). In both <title rend="italic">Closure </title>and <title rend="italic">The Unfinished Swan</title>, 3D space and the architecture therein does not exist without some form of anamorphic shading.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure10"><head>Early screenshot from the forthcoming <title rend="italic">Unfinished Swan</title>.</head></figure>
                        <p>The philosophy of these games hinges on the popular idea that light forms an index of a fixed material reality, and the play of shadows on an uneven surface reveals the deeply anamorphic properties of light. Truth is never resolved and always distorted. Like the possibility of Butades’ daughter revealing the wicked or grotesque, <soCalled>shadowy</soCalled> side of her lover by miscasting his image in the fading light, the digital shadows of <title rend="italic">Limbo</title>, <title rend="italic">Lost in Shadow</title>, and even <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> engage time-tested cultural myths as a way of thinking about the computer in general. If Mark Hansen’s digital ASW is activated by the friction between biological and technical systems, then the anamorphic shadow play depicted in these popular games should function to remind the user of the ubiquity of deception. These shadowy reminders are not simply a new generation of <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign> - though, in the case of <title rend="italic">Limbo, Lost in Shadow</title>, and <title rend="italic">Closure</title>, depictions of Purgatory certainly conjure the spectre of death. No, these games are more related to Hans Holbein’s stretched skull, a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mori</foreign> shot through with the logics of technological alterity. Because computerized shadow play of this sort aestheticizes the uncomfortable feelings of the digital ASW through morbid imagery of death, it reminds the viewer not of her mortality, but of the limits of human experience in general: a <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign>. This digital <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign> carves out a space not for death, but the death of death - a reminder that beyond consciousness there exist fields of experience altogether indifferent to the human.</p>
                        <p>Though it lacks the pallor of the previously discussed titles, <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> is also ranked among these games which make the maneuvering of shadows a core game mechanic. The shadows produced by the Move recall the flickering lamp flame in Pliny’s story of Butades, but rather than assume a visual symmetry between silhouette and object (the way in which this myth has been almost universally depicted in various paintings), the game reveals the dissonance and distortions that prevail in the world of shadows. In <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>, the player can adjust the light source in order to form a kind of anamorphic shadow art. Similar to Holbein’s skull, if a viewer positioned the light source at a particular angle, the game will reveal hidden, albeit banal, images (e.g. a smiley face or snake, etc.) (see Figure 12). Just as Butades took the silhouette traced by his daughter to cast a sculpture, the shadows of <title rend="italic">Echochome II</title> serve as a conflation of silhouette and sculpture. These digital-born shadow puppets operate according to the pictorial logic of two-dimensional shadow play, but also have the geometrical space of a three-dimensional model. The shadow that is <soCalled>cast</soCalled> by the player’s control of the <soCalled>flashlight</soCalled> is not modeled with clay, but with polygons and assigned an autonomous physics and <soCalled>materiality</soCalled> from the original object. The <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series invites the player to haptically engage with this de-realized space and to not take their physical position with respect to the screen for granted. The glowing orb substitutes for the player’s eyeball, as the player learns how to alter the angle of the light source in order to achieve a mastery (albeit naïve) over distorted, anamorphic images.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure11"><head>Anamorphic shadows in <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title>.</head></figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>levelHead: A Multi-Dimensional Memory Palace</head>
                        <p>
                            <title rend="italic">Echochrome II</title> is designed to function with (and market) a specific commercial remote: Sony’s PlayStation Move. The most recent generation of console controllers, inspired by the success of Nintendo’s unconventional Wii Remote, has challenged the joystick-button and mouse-keyboard input combinations previously taken for granted as the industry standard. Though the advertising surrounding these products, fueled by the naïve desire for heightened immersivity, boasts the most streamlined and transparent forms of interactivity, this certainly does not mean players are freed from constraints. Even Microsoft’s Kinect, a <soCalled>hands free</soCalled> human interface device which is able to track real-time 3D video using a grid of infrared laser beams, reinforces the schism between screen and embodied space as it is less responsive and more opaque in terms of how gestures are translated to onscreen commands. The irony at the heart of these aspirations towards increased immersivity is articulated in Mark Hansen’s theory of the digital ASW, which claims that biological entities are always somewhat sensitive to the disruptive phenomenal effects of computational systems. Because artworks like Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title> are designed around the bodily tension one experiences in the face of digital media, they offer a stern critique of the very possibility of immersion. Subscribing to this design ideology, independent artist Julian Oliver has designed both a game and controller which do not take standard forms of interaction for granted. </p>
                        <p>In 2007, Oliver created <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>, an interactive video installation to be displayed in museums and galleries or on home computers via open source software (see Figure 13). The installation combines color-coded and patterned cubes with the custom software which, via a small webcam, tracks and replaces the six unique facets of each cube with three-dimensional, interactive architecture appearing to fill the space inside the cube given the angle of view. The result is a large real-time video projection that displays the player's hands interfacing with the virtualized cubes. The cubes serve as controllers, and, like <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> and especially <title rend="italic">Echochrome II, </title>the player's physical gestures and positioning change the virtual viewpoint and guide a small, white, humanoid silhouette through a six-sided interior architecture. This unassuming avatar, like the minimally-designed <soCalled>cast</soCalled> featured in the <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title> series, simply follows the path of least resistance based on the angle at which a user holds each cube. By tilting each cube, the player indirectly guides the avatar instead of interacting directly as is more common in games. Not coincidentally, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>’s avatar is figured as an automaton or dummy, a lost soul wandering aimlessly through shifting architecture. The cubes work in sequence, each containing six unique rooms overlaid inside the same internal space for a total of eighteen rooms. By tracking objects and actions instead of interfacing with standardized controller input and projecting the results back on that which is being sampled, Oliver’s game extends the virtual space of the screen to the physical environment.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure12"><head>Screenshots of <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>’s interior architecture.</head></figure>
                        <p>
                            <title rend="italic">LevelHead</title> presents the inside of the cube as if it were a shadowbox, but when the player adjusts the side of the cube facing the camera, an entirely different architectural space appears. Difficulty and tension arise from the fact that the player must imagine six simultaneous spaces within the singular geometry of the box twisting in her hand. Each two-dimensional surface becomes a window to a different three-dimensional space. The challenge of this game, as Oliver has written, lies in having to remember the spatial organization of the rooms despite the fact that they are not simultaneously present to the viewer or interconnected in a way that is physically possible. The logic of the cube’s architecture, therefore, must be constructed out of a different set of haptic cues, engaging with the wrist and hand:</p>
                        <p>The tangible interface aspect becomes integral to the function of recall also: as the cube is turned by the hands in search of correctly adjoining rooms muscle-memory is engaged and, as such, aids the memory as a felt memory of patterns of turns: <cit><quote rend="inline">that room is two turns to the left when this room is upside down</quote> <ptr target="#oliver2009"/></cit>.</p>
                        <p>Although Oliver offers a walkthrough available on Youtube, he notes that the game is <quote rend="inline">very difficult</quote> and, given the two-minute time limit to finish each puzzle, it is doubtful many have fully toured what Oliver calls <cit><quote rend="inline">the apartment</quote> <ptr target="#oliver2009"/></cit>. Thus, for the vast majority of players, engagement with <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> produces a response similar to Hansen’s description of <title rend="italic">skulls</title>.</p>
                        <p>When holding the <soCalled>level heads,</soCalled> hands and wrists quickly organize each cube into a coherent program which does not comply with what the eyes see. As Oliver points out, the body grounds the player’s frame of reference, yet she is placed in a space removed from standard forms of orientation, and there is a disconnect between what the player feels holding the solid cube and what she sees projected. The incommensurability between haptic and optical feedback recalls <title rend="italic">skulls</title>. Were a viewer to close her eyes and place her hands on the skulls, the objects would still resolve to the touch, yet the visual anamorphic distortions throw off the viewer’s equilibrium to produce what Hansen describes as the feeling of a digital ASW. <title rend="italic">LevelHead</title> makes a game out of negotiating haptic orientation with a visual and cognitive disorientation.</p>
                        <p>This process is a good example of what Andy Clark and David J. Chalmers described as the externalization of thought. The expression <soCalled>the left hand doesn’t know what the right hand is doing</soCalled> is a common saying, but when it comes to gaming, neurological experiments have discovered that the expression should more accurately be that the conscious mind does not know what the hands are doing. Clark and Chalmers cite a 1994 study by David Kirsh and Paul Maglio in which participants were asked to play the game <title rend="italic">Tetris</title>, using a controller to rotate the shape to ascertain the ideal slot into which the block should be placed <ptr target="#clark1998" loc="8"/>. A second test group was asked to visualize the same action without an interface, haptic or otherwise. What they discovered was that, enabled by environmental as well as bodily support, the brain was able to process the information far more efficiently. Using a controller, participants were able to perform the operation in 300 milliseconds (200 milliseconds to press a button, then 100 milliseconds for the screen to refresh) while it took around 1000 milliseconds for the same result to be achieved mentally. These findings suggest that cognition exceeds not only the mind, but the hand as well, consciousness co-developing in concert with body and environment. </p>
                        <p>Games like <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> dramatize the externalization of thought, compelling the player to not only rethink the way in which she processes space, but also her haptic engagement with this alternative visual regime. Recalling the findings of Kirsh and Maglio’s <title rend="italic">Tetris</title> study, Oliver’s game is constructed with an awareness of how vision is dependent on the rest of the body and external apparatuses. As he emphasizes in an artist statement, the muscle memory of the hand is indispensable for successful navigation of the game’s paradoxical space. While seasoned players are acutely aware of the operation of muscle memory, the design of most games still relies on a model of autonomous visual memory (i.e. observing a space enables us to orient and then move within it). This is one of the unique aspects of <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> which does not take hand, body, or cube-controller for granted or treat them mainly as instruments for executing orders. Oliver’s game is built around the assumption that all the interactions within this cybernetic system are a necessary pre-condition for comprehending and traversing the environment.</p>
                        <p>	The <title rend="italic">Tetris</title> study erodes the Cartesian model of mind/body dualism, demonstrating a distributed model of cognition that puts pressure on the question of where the body stops and the rest of the world begins. What is also notable about this example of situated cognition is the fact that it is based around a cognitive aporia. The incommensurable gulf between the processes of a computer and the embodied engagement of the human is also a precondition for the cybernetic system to function: the hyphen in human-computer interaction signifying this chasm. If the left hand does not know what the right is doing, the corollary to this is that it cannot know what the machine does either. Thus Oliver’s <soCalled>level heads</soCalled> tilt and twist into versions of the smeared skull, challenging the player to peer into an irresolvable and paradoxical architecture. Clutching this existential object, another <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign>, the player glimpses into a space beyond human thought, beyond the anxious debates of “to be or not to be” into a dimension where these questions are rendered insignificant and objects historically designed to expose and critique human <foreign xml:lang="la">vanitas</foreign> are themselves turned into displays of anthropocentric vanity and narcissism.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Miegakure: A Garden of Many Forking Dimensions</head>
                        <p>By creating an imaginary space in which six interconnected rooms co-exist within the same three-dimensional space, the game inverts the standard notion of projection and plays with a kind of fourth-dimensional logic. In the physical world, the projection of a three-dimensional object will produce a two-dimensional image. By contrast, <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> produces a reverse-projection as the flat surface of the side of the cube is converted into a three-dimensional virtual world. <note>Recently smartphones have begun to develop augmented reality software and applications more widely which project a three-dimensional image over a two-dimensional screen. Much like <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>, physical and virtual worlds overlap within a hybrid space. The Nintendo 3DS, a portable game console which features a glasses-free 3D screen, has also released augmented reality games in which a player positions the camera of the console over machine-readable images. The player sees three-dimensional objects placed over the video of her surroundings, which are also subject to manipulation and distortions rendered in real-time.</note> In the virtual space of the screen, these three-dimensional rooms exist within the same cube, overlapping each other. Although only one room is seen at a time, the player can imagine the cube functioning like a tesseract or hypercube. The player must imagine six three-dimensional cubes contained within the cube she holds in her hand, although only one set of three-dimensional coordinates is observable at any time. These rooms simulate a fourth-dimensional space. This conceptual abstraction functions as a rhetorical device which stands in for a player’s actual encounter with the alien and inaccessible ontology of the everyday technological objects with which we surround ourselves. Anamorphosis becomes a means to aestheticize this encounter with what Ian Bogost has called the <quote rend="inline">alien phenomenology</quote> of the computer, which we will discuss further below.</p>
                        <p>While <title rend="italic">levelHead</title>’s disorienting architecture has an implied fourth dimensional physics, there are games being developed such as Marc ten Bosch’s <title rend="italic">Miegakure: A Garden in Four Dimensions</title> which directly incorporate fourth dimensional theory into their platforming game design. Whereas the <title rend="italic">Echochrome </title>series and <title rend="italic">levelHead</title> experiment by creating a spatial regime in which the laws of two- and three-dimensional perspective overlap with each other, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> adds another dimension to create a puzzle platform game that thinks in four dimensions (see Figure 14). While the fourth dimension is impossible for the human mind to visualize, it can be easily represented mathematically. The expanse between what is possible to represent in mathematics and what can be humanly imagined, is the reason why Quentin Meillassoux coins the expression <soCalled>the great outdoors</soCalled> in <title rend="italic">After Finitude</title>. Rather than thinking of the great outdoors in terms of a Caspar David Friedrich painting, which situates a human subject amongst the overwhelming sublimity of nature, Meillassoux uses the expression to refer to a universe that persists beyond the boundaries of human knowability: <cit><quote rend="inline">[t]his is the enigma which we must confront: mathematics' ability to discourse about the great outdoors; to discourse about a past where both humanity and life are absent</quote> <ptr target="#meillassoux2008" loc="26"/></cit>.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure13"><head>Screenshots from Mark ten Bosch’s forthcoming <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title></head>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The fourth dimension is one such space where the abstractions of math and physics, but not humans, may venture. Thus, faced with the paradox of representing the non-representable, ten Bosch’s strategy is to create a computational space in which each three-dimensional coordinate contains not three, but four points of information representing four possible dimensions in space and, as ten Bosch writes on his website, <cit><quote rend="inline">at the press of a button one of the dimensions is exchanged with the fourth dimension, allowing for four-dimensional movement</quote> <ptr target="#tenbosch2011"/></cit>. Thus, a block situated within a three-dimensional grid will appear to magically smear by removing one coordinate and substituting it for the hidden fourth coordinate. Mathematically, one can make n-dimensional objects simply by adding more coordinates alongside the traditional designations for width, height, and depth. What exists as a computational abstraction cannot be visually modeled on the two-dimensional screen, yet the process of substitution simulates the traversal between alternate sets of data representing dimensions. The caveat to both <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> and Lazzarini’s <title rend="italic">skulls</title> is that the player never engages directly with an extra-dimensional space. These works do not provide, as Lacan suggested of anamorphic imagery, a glimpse into the Real, but rather continue to signify and speculate on the impossibility of doing so.</p>
                        <p>This, however, is not what ten Bosch argues, somewhat hubristically proposing that games grant access to the fourth dimension, allowing players to <cit><quote rend="inline">experience it first-hand, using trial and error, as opposed to being told about it</quote> <ptr target="#tenbosch2011"/></cit>. <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> extends the fantasy of being able to colonize and control fourth-dimensional space. But the deeper significance that will ultimately be gained from the game is not a “first-hand” knowledge of the fourth dimension, but the computational processes, what Ian Bogost terms the “procedural rhetoric” of the game [Bogost 2007, 28–29]. And it is in this respect that <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> uses the fantasy of traversing the inaccessible fourth dimension as a metaphor for traversing the equally inaccessible computational processes of a computer. The gameplay of <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> recalls Hansen’s claim about <title rend="italic">skulls</title> and the way in which the anamorphic space stands in for the <cit><quote rend="inline">weird logic and topology of the computer</quote> <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="202"/></cit>. <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> and other games that experiment with eccentric spatial and temporal regimes suggest that the inside of a computer is as strange and mysterious as the fourth dimension and that both exceed human capacities of comprehension. </p>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">Gaming: Essays on Algorithmic Culture </title> <ptr target="#galloway2006"/>, Alexander Galloway has persuasively argued that videogames are <quote rend="inline">allegories of control</quote>; they are cultural objects which rhetorically present themselves as the source of freedom, yet in doing so they conceal the <quote rend="inline">protocological network of continuous informatic control</quote> under which individuals now live <ptr target="#galloway2006" loc="106"/>. Computer games ultimately subsume the player within a strict system of rules that allegorize contemporary informatic culture at large. One might further add that videogames function not only as allegories of control, but <quote rend="inline">allegories of the beyond.</quote> By presenting a set of computational processes as rules for organizing play, videogames invite players to learn the limits and affordances of a game-space. To play a game is to test the system, to uncover (and be uncovered by) the codes that will allow for successful execution of in-game commands. In this way, play is co-developed through a mutual enterprise of <quote rend="inline">becoming computational.</quote> <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title>’s attempt to visualize the fourth spatial dimension is particularly apt because the fourth set of coordinates the game actually visualizes engage with the same problematic: the limit of human perception. By attempting to colonize computational space through the insertion of a human subjectivity, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> adopts the ambitious premise that the formal topology of computational space can be manipulated, controlled, and conquered (when, as Galloway observes, videogames in fact excel at accomplishing the opposite). Ten Bosch’s game simulates the insertion of human agency into a place in which it does not belong.</p>
                        <p>
                            <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> uses a fourth set of 3D coordinates as a metaphor and simulation of fourth dimensional space. This does not allow the player access to actual fourth dimensional physics, yet the parallel between computational and fourth-dimensional space is apt as both engage with the same problematic: the limit of human perception. By attempting to colonize computational space through the insertion of a human subjectivity, <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> adopts the ambitious premise that the formal topology of the computer can be manipulated, controlled, and conquered (when, as Galloway observes, videogames in fact excel at accomplishing the opposite). Ten Bosch’s game simulates the insertion of human agency into a place that it does not belong.
                        </p>
                        <p><soCalled>Miegakure</soCalled>, ten Bosch clarifies, is Japanese for <soCalled>hide and reveal</soCalled> and refers to a specific gardening technique used in Japan. The game is set within a Japanese Zen garden, evoking a space of contemplation and relaxation as the player ponders mathematical abstractions and inter-dimensional ontologies. Like Mark Z. Danielewski’s <title rend="italic">House of Leaves</title>, the gardening technique conjures a space which is paradoxically larger on the <soCalled>inside</soCalled> than the outside. The objects in the garden interweave with one another and expand through multiple dimensions. The gardening metaphor is particularly apt because a garden not only represents a space of contemplation, but one of control and the domestication of nature. Ten Bosch's game similarly represents an attempt to domesticate a computational wilderness, to seize the <soCalled>great outdoors,</soCalled> and till the land such that it falls back under the purview of human authority.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>CONCLUSION</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Alien Phenomenology and the Entelechy of the Weird</head>
                        <p>The fascination with a computational wilderness, the great outdoors of digital space, is what game scholar Ian Bogost has developed into a philosophy he calls <quote rend="inline">alien phenomenology.</quote>  Synthesizing the recent proliferation of ideas falling under the category of Speculative Realism, and specifically engaging with Graham Harman’s version of Object-Oriented Ontology (OOO), Bogost’s <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/> embraces the alien nature of quotidian material objects. He passionately describes how the material world of objects and things – he revels in play around the term <soCalled>stuff</soCalled> – has been de-privileged in the face of the <foreign xml:lang="de">Sturm und Drang</foreign> of human drama. According to Bogost:
                        <cit><quote rend="block">If we take seriously [Graham Harman’s] idea that all objects recede interminably into themselves, then human perception becomes just one among many ways that objects might relate. To put things at the center of a new metaphysics also requires us to admit that they do not exist just for us.</quote> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit></p>
                        <p>These concealed and re-distributed relations underwrite Bogost’s construction of an alien phenomenology. He declares that <cit><quote rend="inline">[t]he true alien recedes interminably. It is not hidden in the darkness of the outer cosmos nor in the deep sea shelf, but in plain sight, everywhere, in everything</quote> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit>. This opens the question of how the behavior of humans is transformed as a result of this reconfigured relation to objects. The answer Bogost offers is <emph>wonder</emph>: <cit><quote rend="inline">[d]espite all the science fictional claims to the contrary, the alien is different. One does not ask the alien, <quote rend="inline">Do you come in peace?</quote> but rather, <quote rend="inline">What am I to you?</quote> The posture one takes before the alien is that of curiosity, of wonder</quote> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit>. Bogost attempts to reinscribe a sense of respect for the mysteries of quotidian objects – for the alien that does not arrive from a galaxy far, far away but is part of our everyday lives. Alien phenomenology goes <cit><quote rend="inline">where everyone has gone before, but where few have bothered to linger</quote> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/></cit>. The <quote rend="inline">alien is everywhere</quote> and perhaps this is most deeply felt when attending to what peers back from the remote space of a computer <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>.</p>
                        <p>Bogost’s response to this call of the wild is to practice wonder, but this is by no means the only answer philosophers have posited. After all, is not horror the obverse of wonder? Fittingly, at the conclusion of his book, Bogost turns to a discussion of zombies and leverages a common critique: that the living dead only naïvely objectify humans. In fact, the horror of the zombie lies precisely in their all-too-human status and does not offer an escape from the correlationist’s lockbox. As Bogost argues throughout <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title>, the <soCalled>posthuman</soCalled> is frequently not <soCalled>posthuman enough,</soCalled> and the zombie perhaps best typifies this problem <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>. </p>
                        <p>Rather than the hot-blooded horror inspired by zombie narratives, there is a terror to be found in a truly post-apocalyptic temporality. The greatest horror is not to be found on this cusp where there is still hope for humanity’s futurity, but in the cold world of cosmological time. As Stephanie Boluk and Wylie Lenz write, <cit><quote rend="inline">[t]he zombie remains intractably wedded to the logic as well as temporality of the living human. From this perspective we see the biocentric biases implicit in the posthuman zombie…The zombie again and again returns to this time just before the death of death, where – or when – the end of humanity functions as a vanishing point toward which the zombie shambles but never reaches</quote> <ptr target="#boluk2011" loc="XX"/></cit>. The horror of a glacial temporality in which human subjectivity recedes in the face of a universe that is indifferent to human and zombie struggle alike (if such a distinction even exists) can also be produced by the fundamentally alien spaces of objects: of computers and coffee cups, which exist on ontological planes forever out of reach. This comes closer to what Hansen describes as the digital ASW – complete with the gurgling, spluttering, and lurching of bodies attempting to negotiate strange computational environments – but also enacts the kind of horror Eugene Thacker accounts for in his recent book, <title rend="italic">After Life</title> <ptr target="#thacker2010"/>.</p>
                        <p>In <title rend="italic">After Life</title>, Thacker explores the philosophical concept of life and living. Informed, like Bogost, by the recent explosion of speculative philosophies which redirect philosophical inquiry away from the human towards <quote rend="inline">a politics of life in terms of the nonhuman or the unhuman,</quote> Thacker turns to the fantasy writing of H.P. Lovecraft to find creative models for thinking that which exists beyond thought <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="5"/>. Lovecraft, he argues, <cit><quote rend="inline">presents the possibility of a logic of life, though an inaccessible logic, one that is absolutely inaccessible to the human, the natural, the earthly, an <quote rend="inline">entelechy of the weird</quote></quote> <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="23"/></cit>. What Thacker identifies as <soCalled>weird</soCalled> in Lovecraft’s writing, is the same speculation at work in the anamorphic gameplay of videogames which attempt to test or allegorize the limits of human experience. While Lovecraft attempts to name the unnameable, these games convey the sense of <emph>playing the unplayable</emph>. As Thacker writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">the weird is the discovery of an unhuman limit to thought, that is nevertheless foundational for thought. The life that is weird is the life according to the logic of an inaccessible rift, a life <quote rend="inline">out of space and time,</quote> and life of <quote rend="inline">extra-dimensional biologies</quote></quote> <ptr target="#thacker2010" loc="23"/></cit>.</p>
                        <p>Whether using terms like <soCalled>weird,</soCalled> <soCalled>eccentric,</soCalled> <soCalled>alien,</soCalled> or <soCalled>anamorphic,</soCalled> these ideas attempt to re-situate the place of the human within a more complex cosmology of objects (Levi Bryant’s term for this is <quote rend="inline">flat ontology</quote> and Bogost revises slightly with his theory of <quote rend="inline">tiny ontologies</quote>) <ptr target="#bryant2010"/> <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>. The strange spaces navigated in videogames like <title rend="italic">Echochrome I</title> and <title rend="italic">II</title>, <title rend="italic">levelHead,</title> and <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> allegorize the incomprehensibility of a computer; they create expressive systems, which point to the profoundly alien nature of the technological objects that are such an integral and often ignored aspect of contemporary culture. Yet, despite the ubiquity and embeddedness of computers within the economic, social, and even biological strata of every day life (at least on one side of the digital divide), the games examined here dramatize the friction produced as a result of the irreconcilable alterity that defines technological objects. As a way of assuaging the anxiety of discovering one lives on an alien planet, games like <title rend="italic">Echochrome</title>,<title rend="italic"> levelHead</title>, and <title rend="italic">Miegakure</title> present defamiliarized spaces and propose that the uncrossable schism that separates humanity from the mysterious black box of technology is, in fact, crossable. In these games, the computer is not so much a Lovecraftian monster, but a kind of riddle or enigma, troubling but potentially solvable. The fundamental paradox of these <soCalled>anamorphic games</soCalled> is that they ultimately subsume alternate worlds into a playable world. They present imagery and gameplay referencing the <soCalled>great outdoors</soCalled> but packaged specifically for the human player. Their controls fit into the palms of human hands and their screens cast wavelengths of light within the spectrum of human vision. In this respect, the games presented in this essay do not explicitly achieve what could be called a kind of speculative gaming, but only tentatively make motions toward the <foreign xml:lang="la">memento mortem mortis</foreign> at the heart of all media. Like Holbein’s <title rend="italic">The Ambassadors</title>, <soCalled>anamorphic games</soCalled> deploy contemporary rhetoric to create metaphors for a computational wilderness, reminding their users of both their experiential limitations and the limitations of technological understanding.</p>
                        <p>If one were tasked to develop a game completely indifferent to an end user, what would this speculative game look like? Would this type of game participate in a mutual withdrawal of both player and game, or would it instead place both game and player in an incommensurable tension with one another? In much the same way the anamorphic lens can be said to neither reflect nor refract light, but rather trap the gaze, the speculative game would serve as a black hole. Speculative games cannot have a user, they cannot be used or even be thought by the player. The software discussed in this paper challenges the viewer, not to perceive the imperceptible or conquer otherworldly domains, but to simply speculate on the possibilities of such dimensions of existence. The result is that these are not so much speculative games, as they are games of speculation.</p>
                        <!-- Orphaned note:
                        <p>[6] In fact, Vannevar Bush’s “As We May Think” (1945), commonly regarded as a foundational text that led to the eventual development and emergence of the Internet and personal computing (amongst other predictions), literally argues that the entire future of the world is at stake in developing better computational and information-processing strategies. He argues that humans must depend on technologies like the Memex (what is essentially an early model for hypertext) for their continued survival. This view was motivated by Bush’s own participation in the creation of the Manhattan Project. Bush non-coincidentally published “As We May Think” in <title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title> two weeks prior to the dropping of the bombs in Japan and then again, two weeks after, in <title rend="italic">Life </title>magazine. His message of hope for humanity’s future bookends this dark moment which, although it effectively ended WWII, inaugurated the world’s entry into the Atomic Age in which the possibility of global annihilation was now a lived reality. For Bush, and subsequently many others, the survival of humanity literally depended on our ability to non-linearly manage vast, complex, and constantly in flux, information systems. For more information on the relationship between Bush’s essay and his participation in nuclear weaponry, see Harpold [Harpold 2009, 209].</p> -->
                    </div>        
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
           <listBibl>
                <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. --> 
                <bibl xml:id="surname2009" label="Surname 2009"/>
               
                <bibl xml:id="aarseth1997" label="Aarseth 1997">Aarseth, Espen. <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature. </title>Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1997. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bogost2012" label="Bogost forthcoming 2012">Bogost, Ian. <title rend="italic">Alien Phenomenology</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, forthcoming 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bogost2007" label="Bogost 2007">Bogost, Ian. <title rend="italic">Persuasive Games: The Expressive Power of Videogames</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boluk2011" label="Boluk 2011">Boluk, Stephanie and Wylie Lenz (eds). <title rend="italic">Generation Zombie: Essays on the Living Dead in Modern Culture</title>. Jefferson, NC: McFarland, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bryant 2010" xml:id="bryant2010">Bryant, Levi. <title rend="quotes">Flat Ontology</title> <title rend="italic">Larval Subjects</title>. 24 Feb 2010. Accessed 23 July 2010. <ref target="http://larvalsubjects.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/flat-ontology-2/">http://larvalsubjects.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/flat-ontology-2/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark1998" label="Clark 1998">Clark, Andy and David J. Chalmers. <title rend="quotes">The Extended Mind.</title> <title rend="italic">Analysis</title> 58, (1998) 7–19.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Damisch 1995" xml:id="damisch1995">Damisch, Hubert. <title rend="italic">The Origin of Perspective</title>. Trans. John Goodman. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="friedberg2006" label="Friedberg 2006">Friedberg, Anne. <title rend="italic">The Virtual Window: From Alberti to Microsoft</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Galloway 2006" xml:id="galloway2006">Galloway, Alexander. <title rend="italic">Gaming: Essays on Algorithmic Culture</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2006. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hansen2006" label="Hansen 2006">Hansen, Mark B. N. <title rend="italic">New Philosophy for New Media</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Harman 2002" xml:id="harman2002">Harman, Graham. <title rend="italic">Tool-Being: Heidegger and the Metaphysics of Objects</title>. Chicago, IL: Open Court, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harpold2009" label="Harpold 2009">Harpold, Terry. <title rend="italic">Ex-foliations: Reading Machines and the Upgrade Path. </title>Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Iwata 2011" xml:id="iwata2011">Iwata, Satoru. <title rend="quotes">Iwata Asks: <title rend="italic">Super Mario Galaxy.</title> Vol. 4: Shigeru Miyamoto.</title> <title rend="italic">Wii.com</title>, 2011. Accessed 23 July 2011. <ref target="http://us.wii.com/soft_smg.jsp">http://us.wii.com/soft_smg.jsp</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lacan1998" label="Lacan 1998">Lacan, Jacques. <title rend="italic">The Four Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis: The Seminar of Jacques Lacan Book IV</title>. Ed. Jacques-Alain Miller. Trans. Alan Sheridan. New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl label="McCormick 2011" xml:id="mccormick2011">McCormick, Rich. <title rend="quotes">E3 2011: Our John Carmack Video Interview Covers <title rend="italic">Rage</title>, the PC, and Gamma Corrected Anti-Aliasing.</title> <title rend="italic">PC Gamer</title>. <ref target="http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/06/08/e3-2011-our-john-carmack-interview-covers-rage-the-pc-and-gamma-corrected-anti-aliasing/">http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/06/08/e3-2011-our-john-carmack-interview-covers-rage-the-pc-and-gamma-corrected-anti-aliasing/&gt;</ref>8 June 2011. Accessed 23 July 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="meillassoux2008" label="Meillassoux 2008">Meillassoux, Quentin. <title rend="italic">After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity of Contingency</title>. New York: Continuum, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nideffer 2007" xml:id="nideffer2007">Nideffer, Robert. <title rend="quotes">Game Engines as Embedded Systems.</title> <title rend="italic">Database Aesthetics: Art in the Age of Information Overflow</title>, ed. Victoria Vesna, 211–242. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oliver2009" label="Oliver 2009">Oliver, Julian. <title rend="quotes">levelHead.</title> <title rend="italic">Selectparks.net</title>. 2009. <ref target="http://selectparks.net/~julian/levelhead/">http://selectparks.net/~julian/levelhead/</ref>Accessed 23 July 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Panofsky 1996" xml:id="panofsky1996">Panofsky, Erwin. <title rend="italic">Perspective as Symbolic Form</title>. Trans. Christopher S. Wood. Cambridge, Mass.: Zone Books (MIT Press), 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Pliny" xml:id="pliny">Pliny. <title rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</title> c. AD 77-79.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="seaman2000" label="Seaman 2000">Seaman, Bill. <title rend="quotes">Motioning Toward the Emergent Definition of E-phany Physics.</title> <title rend="italic">Art, Technology, Consciousness Mind@large</title>, ed. Roy Ascott. Bristol, UK; Portland, OR: Intellect Ltd., 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Sony 2008" xml:id="sony2008">Sony Computer Entertainment Inc. <title rend="italic">Echochrome Official Trailer</title>. <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GybxIwfU4rI">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GybxIwfU4rI</ref>Accessed 23 July 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tenbosch2011" label="ten Bosch 2011">ten Bosch, Marc. <title rend="quotes">Miegakure: A Puzzle-Platformer in Four Dimensions.</title> <title rend="italic">Marctenbosch.com</title>. 2011. Accessed 23 July 2011. <ref target="http://marctenbosch.com/miegakure/">http://marctenbosch.com/miegakure/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Thacker 2010" xml:id="thacker2010">Thacker, Eugene. <title rend="italic">After Life</title>. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zizek1999" label="Žižek 1999">Žižek, Slavoj.
                <title rend="italic">The Žižek Reader</title> Eds. Elizabeth Wright and Edmond Wright. Malden, Mass.: Blackwell Publishers, 1999.</bibl></listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>