<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The case of the golden background, a virtual
               restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau
               Master (c. 1425)</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Liselore <dhq:family>Tissen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 using an idno element-->
               <dhq:affiliation> Leiden University and Delft University of
                  Technology</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>l.n.m.tissen@hum.leidenuniv.nl </email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sanne <dhq:family>Frequin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 using an idno element-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Utrecht University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>s.frequin@uu.nl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Ruben <dhq:family>Wiersma</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 using an idno element-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Delft University of Technology</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>R.t.Wiersma@tudelft.nl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000663</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->1</idno>
            <date when="2023-02-03">3 February 2023</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000663/000663.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Cleaning and provisional restoration treatments on <title rend="italic">The
                  Crucifixion</title> (1425) revealed that the visible azurite layer obscures an
               originally golden background. This leads to the question of whether or not the
               azurite should be removed as it is not original, or should be kept as part of the
               panel’s history. To overcome this dilemma, this paper presents a methodological
               solution of approaching this problem by combining the knowledge of art historians,
               restorers and by integrating modern 3D technologies before, during, and after the
               restoration. By creating a modifiable digital model, a virtual restoration can
               potentially attribute to analyzing and visualizing optical changes due to restoration
               treatments. Additionally, multiple 3D-printed facsimiles physicalize these
               adaptations. A facsimile’s value is demonstrated by analyzing the diversity of
               meanings an artwork can have in terms of authenticity whilst respecting the artwork's
               material and social integrity. The 3D prints be decisive in the restoration of the
               panel.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This paper presents a methodological solution of approaching the problem of restoring
               the medieval <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title> of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)
               by combining the knowledge of art historians, restorers and by integrating modern 3D
               technologies before, during, and after the restoration.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. </head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">The Crucifixion</title> of the Master of the Lamentation of
               Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an
               early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with
               Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in
               golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.
               The painter has added a layer of plaster on the panel in order to create depth in
               this panel. In this layer, the space between the tendrils was cut away thus leaving
               the figures, the cross, and the tendrils in a slightly higher relief that it
               currently has with the now visible dark blue colored background.</p>
            <p>The painting was in a bad condition and has stayed in the museum depot for decades.
               Its paint was obscured with dirt and yellowed varnish. Furthermore, it contained many
               discolorations, darkened retouches, and overpaints. When it was taken out of the
               depot for the <title rend="italic">Body Language </title> exhibition (2020) of the
               museum the work was cleaned and a provisional restoration was carried out by restorer
               Caroline van der Elst <ptr target="#museumcatharijneconvent2020"/>.<note>The authors
                  would like to thank Dr. Micha Leeflang, Caroline van der Eyck and Carlos Bayod for
                  their valuable input in this research project.</note> During this process, an
               interesting discovery was made. The currently visible blue background of the panel
               originally was golden: golden shining tendrils were placed on a gold field (the gold
               field was done in <q><foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign></q>, small scales, applied with a gouge) (Figure
               2.). The blue azurite layer that remains visible today is old. It probably dates from
               the late sixteenth or early seventeenth century, yet it was not the original
               intention of the Lindau master.</p>
            <p>This leads to an important dilemma in the restoration of the painting. Should the
               blue layer be removed as it is not part of the original work? This would mean a large
               and irreversible intervention in the painting, which opposes the ethics of
               conservation practice. To prevent this, the dark blue layer can also be maintained.
               It was applied not long after the creation of the work and it is therefore part of
               the life story of the painting. The owner of the work decided to have it painted
               over, perhaps because of a change of taste or perhaps a bad condition of the golden
                  <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>.<note> The question why the painting was overpainted is part of the
                  ongoing conservation process. </note> To remove it, is to remove this layer of
               meaning, or to put it differently, to remove this important life event of the
               painting. Yet, by preserving the blue layer, it is not possible to experience the
               earliest version of the painting.</p>
            <p>Traditionally, the golden background of medieval panel paintings is connected to the
               divine space. Wölfgang Schöne aptly called it <quote rend="inline">the echo of
                  Paradise</quote> (Schöne, 1954). Another vein of scholars led by Ernst Gombrich
               has stressed the importance of the materiality, or, in his words: the <quote
                  rend="inline">thingness</quote> of gold <ptr target="#gombrich1932"/>. The use of
               gold turned the average object into a precious material thing. Gold was a costly
               material, connected with other worlds via trading routes <ptr target="#dunlop2009"/>.
               The material could be manipulated – using techniques like punch work or the
               <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign> that was used in the <title rend="italic">Lindau Crucifixion</title> –
               in ways that wouldn’t be possible using tempera. One could argue that panel paintings
               with a golden background, manipulated to play with the light, are objects that linger
               between a representation of Paradise and physical reality. As David Young King puts
               it, the gold ground connects the material and the immaterial, the worldly and
               otherworldly <ptr target="#kim2019"/>. The current version of the Lindau painting,
               with the blue obscuring the <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>, does not do justice to this pivotal role of
               the painting as the ambassador between the worldly and the divine both in materiality
               as in its symbolic meaning.</p>
            <p>This report will not deliver the final answer to this complex question. However, we
               aim to propose a methodological solution that potentially can serve both sides of
               this discussion: a virtual restoration of the painting using a 3D scan and a 3D print
               of this restoration or the original work. In this project, for the first time, the
               virtual restoration of the work is presented as an argument that plays a role in the
               conservation process. Here we would like to share the steps we have taken so far and
               look into the future of this project.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau, <title rend="italic">The
                     Crucifixion</title>, ca. 1425. Tempera on panel, 125 × 89 cm, Museum
                  Catharijneconvent – Courtesy of Museum Catharijneconvent</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
               <figDesc>Color photograph of the Lindau Master's <title rend="italic"
                     >Crucifixion</title> in its unrestored state, with blue background</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Digital photo reconstruction where the azurite layer was removed and a golden
                  background was added – Ruben Wiersma</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
               <figDesc>The Lindau Master's Crucifixion as it might have appeared when first made,
                  with golden background</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Capturing the current state of <title rend="italic">The Crucifixion</title>
            </head>
            <p>The basis for the digital restoration of the Lindau Crucifixion was a 3D scan of the
               panel. To record the current state of the panel in terms of color and topography, the
               Lucida 3D Scanner was used <ptr target="#factumfoundation2021c"/>. This scanner was
               developed thanks to the collaboration between artist Manuel Franquelo and a team of
               professionals of different backgrounds (e.g. artists, architects, engineers, and
               software developers) from the Factum Foundation, a Spanish foundation specialized in
               digital recording of cultural heritage and in creating three dimensional facsimiles
               of recorded objects.<note> Since 2011, the Factum Foundation has been using this
                  scanner to record the surface topography of 200+ paintings and cultural heritage
                  objects with low relief surfaces all over the world (e.g. the tombs of the Valley
                  of the Kings in Luxor and Michelangelo’s Epifania at the British Museum) <ptr
                     target="#factumfoundation2021e"/>.</note> The Lucida 3D Scanner is a
               close-range triangulation laser recording system. It provides a non-invasive method
               that documents the surface texture data of the artwork. The scanner projects a
               mechanically moving strip of red light onto the panel’s surface. The relief and
               curvature of the panel’s surface distort the light as it moves from left to right,
               completing scanning sections of about 48 x 48 cm. These deformations of the laser are
               captured by two cameras that are positioned 45° to the panel’s surface <hi
                  rend="italic">normal</hi>. These cameras take black and white videos of the
               laser’s trail, which are then processed as relief information into a grayscale depth
               map, using a geometric information system (GIS) and shaded render formats.</p>
            <p>The combination of laser scanning and black and white video results in the capture of
               the panel’s topography at a high resolution (up to 100μm).<note> Factum Foundation,
                  2021. <hi rend="italic">Lucida 3D scanner,</hi>
                  <ref target="https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1478/lucida-3d-scanner"
                     >https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1478/lucida-3d-scanner</ref>. Accessed
                  09 September 2021.</note> Furthermore, the scanner makes it possible to capture
               and unveil the topography of the panel without getting distorted and misled by its
               color or other material information. By relying upon the combination of laser and
               video information and the specific algorithms that were developed to interpret the
               video information, it becomes possible to scan highly reflective and glossy surfaces,
               such as the golden elements of the panel. This would not be possible when using a
               technology that solely relies on high-definition photography, such as photogrammetry
               or systems casting a fringe pattern. Furthermore, scanning the topography this way,
               it is easier to actually obtain more detailed data in deeper areas of the painting.
               With photographic methods relying on light sources, this information cannot be
               captured, meaning that the data of some of the depths relies on calculations rather
               than actual measurements.</p>
            <p>A downside of this technology, in contrast to photographic methods, is the fact that
               the color information of the panel had to be recorded separately. This was done by
               using panoramic photography in combination with a two-direction lighting system. In
               contrast to <quote rend="inline">regular</quote> parallel photography where each
               image is taken with its own view point, the panoramic method uses a single point from
               which the whole surface is recorded in smaller sections, arranged as a mosaic of rows
               and columns <ptr target="#factumfoundation2021d"/>. This makes recording fast
               (approximately one hour per 4 square meters, resulting in a file with a resolution of
               around 600 dpi) and efficient. Reflections are avoided by creating neutral lighting
               by using two strobe lights and the colors are balanced with the help of an X-rite
               color checker among other control methods. The separate color photographs (tiles) are
               automatically aligned and stitched into one full color map with PTGui. We store the
               geometry of the panel as a heightmap. This representation fits the surface of the
               panel, is lightweight, and allows users to process the data with image processing
               software, such as Photoshop. This way, the geometry and shading derived from the
               geometry can be blended with the color map.</p>
            <p>The color information was combined with the heightmap that was recorded by the Lucida
               Scanner into the final 3D model. The Lucida's capacity of working with 3D information
               as grayscale depth map images, avoids the need of working with cloud points or
               polygon meshes. Combining color information with a 3D scan is much more efficient
               using a GIS map and the final model can be edited easily, making this a user-friendly
               method of 3D scanning (Figures. 3,4,5.).</p>
            <p>Additionally, the digital model will be supplemented with data resulting from other
               types of material research that will be carried out during the conservation process
               of the painting (e.g. X-ray, ultraviolet, infra-red analyses) <ptr
                  target="#factumfoundation2021a"/>. <figure>
                  <head>Color photograph – Made by Factum Foundation</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Detail of the Lindau Master's <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title>
                     featuring an angel, with blue background. Depth of plaster bas-relief is not
                     shown.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>3D shaded heightmap – Made by Factum Foundation</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Detail of the Lindau Master's <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title>
                     featuring an angel, in greyscale and showing plaster bas-relief.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Color and height combined Color photograph – Made by Factum
                     Foundation</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Detail of the Lindau Master's <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title>
                     featuring an angel, with color and bas-relief.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Processing the virtual reproduction</head>
            <p>The 3D model of the painting was the basis of the virtual restoration of the work to
               its earlier state with the golden background. Not only the appearance (now blue,
               originally gold leaf) had to be restored, also the geometry (<foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>) had to be
               adapted. The blue over paint has filled the <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>s lacunae, and made them less
               deep than they originally were. </p>
            <p>We created a virtual copy of the painting that could be rendered in real-time. The
               low-frequency geometry, such as the large-scale curvature of the panel, was mapped to
               a planar mesh with 16x16 quads. High frequency details were applied to the mesh with
               normal mapping, yielding a convincing virtual object suited for real-time
               applications <ptr target="#blinn1978"/>.</p>
            <p>The panel was rendered using Blender’s Eevee renderer for real-time rendering and
               Cycles for offline, ray-traced rendering.<note> Blender Community. 2018. <title
                     rend="italic">Blender – a 3D modeling and rendering package</title>. Stichting
                  Blender Foundation, Amsterdam. (Retrieved from <ref
                     target="http://www.blender.org">http://www.blender.org</ref> 20 March
                  2022)</note> It can be transported to other programs and into VR and AR
               applications using a universal scene description file <ptr target="#elkouraetal2019"
               />. The appearance of the materials in the painting were modeled with a GGX-based
               principled BSDF, which allows the user to set material properties such as base color,
               metallicness, and roughness <ptr target="#walteretal2007"/>.</p>
            <p>To virtually restore the object, we assigned both the appearance and geometry masked
               regions. Mask A is the set of all points that were originally painted with gold leaf
               and mask B ⊂ A only contains the regions with <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>. These masks were created
               by selecting all pixels with a color within a certain distance to the color of a
               representative pixel in the <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign> region and corrected manually.</p>
            <p>The appearance for mask A was adjusted by setting the base color to an ochre yellow
               blended with imperfections modeled with Perlin noise <ptr target="#perlin2002"/>. The
               metallic property was set to 1 and roughness property to 0.6. All other regions were
               given the base color from the Factum scans, metallic property of 0 and roughness set
               to 0.4. The appearance was validated by the restorer of the painting Caroline van der
               Elst.</p>
            <p>The geometry in mask B was adjusted to approximate a reconstruction of the
               <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign> pattern. We opted for a simple intervention: scaling and offsetting the
               geometry, which is equivalent to increasing the contrast of the height map. This
               approximates the removal of a layer of paint. In future work, we aim to virtually
               recreate the <foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign> pattern using geometry processing techniques and to
               investigate the use of the virtual model to situate the piece in its original
               setting.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The 3D printed facsimile</head>
            <p>Based on the previous explanation, it can be stated that 3D scanning the panel’s
               materials will contribute to documenting highly detailed information about the
               artwork. Moreover, it digitalizes the panel in such a way that we can modify,
               manipulate and alter it to our own liking without having to alter the original work.
               This way, it becomes possible to visualize potential outcomes of future conservation
               treatments. In our case, we were able to reconstruct the original appearance of the
               painting, with the golden background.</p>
            <p>Subsequently, this data can be translated into 3D printable data, which makes it
               possible to create an exact reproduction of the panel in various stages. In this
               research two versions will be made: one <q>as-is</q> with the blue background and one
               with the appearance (gold) and the geometry (<foreign xml:lang="de">tremolierung</foreign>) texture restored. The
               first phase of the creation of an exact 3D replica, is making an elevated print (a
               technique developed by Canon Production Printing, Venlo).<note> 3D printing (or
                  additive manufacturing (AM) is a technique that uses digital computer information
                  to rapidly create a physical three-dimensional object. This digital design can
                  either be acquired by scanning an existing object or by constructing a shape from
                  scratch. The physicalization of the digital model can be done using various
                  methods, but this process is either additive (printing layers upon layers of
                  photosensitive filament) or subtractive (by gradually removing materials until the
                  desired design has been achieved). </note> This technology uses computer data –
               the grayscale depth map – which is translated into a printable format. This digital
               information is combined with a 3D printing technique called material jetting, which
               involves hardening a material of choice (in our case polymer) by exposing it to
               ultraviolet (UV) light. This way, the panel’s relief can be created by printing layer
               upon layer of plastic until the right height is reached. Elevated printing thus
               allows for a highly detailed reproduction of textures.</p>
            <p>The second phase is the application of color. The polymer that is used in this
               process has a light gray color. To reconstruct the polychromy of the painting, it is
               possible to print the last layer in color. Additionally, layers of transparent ink
               can be added to achieve some glossiness on the surface. Although the developments in
               improving the quality of these 3D color prints are promising, there still are some
               limitations to overcome. One major issue is the quality of color. As this technology
               uses inkjet printing and the curing of photopolymers, the colors achieved are not
               complex and as a result of the heating process, the color can look grainy.
               Furthermore, the material is very stiff, which results in an artificial <q>feel</q>
               of the reproduction.</p>
            <p>The aim of this project is an exact 3D replica of the painting in its current, and in
               its restored state. The current quality of the inkjet printing does not yet meet our
               demands for this project.<note>Although currently, 3D printing is not yet up to par
                  with the requirements of art historians and restorers working with these
                  reproductions, the developments of the technology are promising. Thanks to the
                  work of Clemens Weijkamp, it will be a matter of time before the creation of high
                  quality reproductions of artworks with mixed materials are possible without any
                  manual labor.</note> To overcome these issues our partner Factum Foundation has
               found a solution. The elevated printing is used to create the topography of the
               painting. This is done by using the uncolored elevated print as a positive to create
               a mold. This mold is then used as a negative, for another positive that consists of a
               silicon solution, a more flexible material. This monochrome silicon <q>print</q> is a
               basis on which a separately printed two dimensional high quality color image of the
               artwork is attached. Lastly, to make the material appearance more convincing,
               paramount features of the artwork’s material appearance (e.g. glossiness, varnish)
               are added manually. In the case of the Lindau <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title>, the background of the two
               facsimiles will be gilded manually.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The meaning of material</head>
            <p>The creation of exact reproductions using elevated printing generates the opportunity
               of visualizing and physicalizing the potential effects of decisions made and
               treatments done during the restoration process. It allows us to think about the way
               this 3D print could provide a solution to the important dilemma in the restoration of
               the painting and whether or not the blue layer be removed as it is not part of the
               original work. Could the 3D print help in understanding and discussing the
               complexities of this discussion within the field of art restoration. Additional
               questions that automatically come to mind are: What this type of reproduction means
               to the original panel? In what way does this second physical manifestation of the
               panel (in its current blue and its earlier golden state) contribute to the
               understanding of the original artwork? How does 3D printing a panel affect the value
               of the original? Could the 3D print potentially have its own value at some point?</p>
            <p>The authenticity of art and the role of facsimiles – which are everything but
               original, and are often considered as anti-authentic – has been a heated topic of
               debate ever since German sociologist Walter Benjamin <ptr target="#benjamin1936"/>
               described how reproduction (in his case photography) changes artworks’ historic value
               – in Benjamin's words: <quote rend="inline">aura</quote> – into one of exhibition
               value <ptr target="#benjamin1936"/>. It has lost its artistic relevance and
               connections to the past. Contemporary Western society has been highly fixated on the
                  <q>magical</q> encounter with the physical original artwork. Nowadays, art
               reproductions are omnipresent (e.g. on mobile devices and posters). The discussion
               that Benjamin started has gained momentum and still continues to grow (<ptr
                  target="#jones2010"/>; <ptr target="#latour_lowe2011"/>; <ptr target="#tissen2020"
               />; <ptr target="#tissen_malik_vermeeren2021"/>; <ptr
                  target="#digiuseppantoniodifranco_galeazzi_vassallo_2018"/>). There has been an
               increase in theorists specifically examining the moral and ethical implications of
               art reproduction. A reason for this might be the rapid development of advanced
               reproduction technologies such as 3D printing. In today’s world of <q>fake news</q>,
               not knowing what to believe and where to find the truth when information is at our
               disposal at any time and any place, the material qualities of original artworks,
               carefully guarded in the museum seem to be the one of the only sources that can
               validate an artwork — the survivor of the passage of time — as genuine. Consequently,
               in conservation practice this has resulted in the prevalent goal to keep and conserve
               as much of the artworks' material features as possible in their current state — thus
               including <term>patina</term>, cracks, losses and other material traces of time — for
               generations to come. This means that any form of treatment should be done in favor of
               its original materials and implies that treatment should be reversible, in the case
               that better conservation methods are discovered and can be applied.</p>
            <p>With this information in mind, how can a 3D print, a visually indistinguishable copy
               yet one without the material features of the artwork itself, mean something to the
               original artwork? In the case of the Lindau <title rend="italic">Crucifixion</title>,
               it is precisely the materiality of the artwork that poses the dilemma. As previously
               described, the biggest issue we are currently facing during the restoration of the
               panel is the decision regarding the appearance of its background. During a seminar
                  <title rend="italic">The digital reconstruction of the crucifixion of the Lindau
                  master (ca. 1425)</title> (held on the 9th of June 2021 at Museum
            	Catharijneconvent (Utrecht)) we presented this dilemma to a group of professionals from
               different backgrounds (curators, restorers, (technical) art historians, and art
               scholars) and the online participants <ptr target="#tissen2021"/>.</p>
            <p>3D scanning the panel’s materials and the possibility to 3D print exact reproductions
               generate the opportunity of visualizing and physicalizing the potential effects of
               decisions made and treatments done during the restoration process in two ways.
               Firstly, by using the 3D print, the blue background can be documented and
               physicalized before it would be lost, due to an irreversible restoration of the
               painting’s background to the earlier version. Secondly, when the decision would be
               made to maintain the blue azurite layer, the 3D print could be used to show a
               reconstruction of the painting to the primary version without the azurite blue layer
               that is currently covering the golden background. We asked the participants whether
               or not the azurite blue should be removed and what role a 3D print of the panel could
               function as a solution for this issue. Here, when proposing these options, in the
               discussion it soon became evident that the panel’s value cannot be solely attributed
               to its material qualities. In this report we would like to reflect on two arguments
               considering the <q>authenticity</q> of the 3D print that came up during the
               discussion.</p>
            <p>The first important aspect of authenticity mentioned was the intention of the artist,
               which is oftentimes a highly valued quality <ptr target="#martens2010"/>. In the case
               of the panel, the Master of Lindau himself initially decided to fully gild the
               panel’s background. When this intention is considered of utmost importance, this
               would imply that the 3D print with the reconstruction of this <q>original</q>
               background with the gold leaf in itself could be considered more valuable than the
               panel in its current state, with the blue. The latter does not visually simulate what
               the Master would have intended, and thus one could argue that the 3D printed
               reconstruction of the golden background is closer to the artist's original intentions
               than the panel in its current state, thus more significant in terms of
               authenticity.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, another participant mentioned, what should be remembered when looking at
               original artworks (or at their facsimiles), is that the artwork’s current state is
               just a snapshot of a single moment in time. Artworks have their own lifecycle which
               spans over decades if not centuries, not only in their material composition but also
               in their function, communal and social value. Their conceptual value is not set in
               stone, it changes over time. This way, an artwork knows many <q>faces</q> or
                  <q>identities</q>. With the help of conservation methods, it can be decided to
               freeze the panel’s material appearance. But this does not do justice to the lifecycle
               of the artwork. An example of how reconstructions can help to demonstrate this
               lifecycle is the recently revealed reconstruction of missing parts of Rembrandt van
               Rijn’s <title rend="italic">The Night Watch</title> at the Rijksmuseum (Amsterdam)
                  <ptr target="#rijksmuseum2021"/>. For centuries the public has looked at a
               mutilated version of this painting. In the case of the Night Watch, the
               reconstruction has revealed an earlier, lost identity of the art work.</p>
            <p>Both arguments show that reproductions of artworks and especially the high-quality 3D
               printed facsimiles can contribute to visualizing and physicalizing the elements that
               contribute to the diversity of identities one artwork can have. The authenticity of
                  <title rend="italic">The Crucifixion</title> is not static and solely based on the
               original panel’s unique materials alone. In contrast, the discussions during the
               symposium showed that the panel’s authenticity is considered diverse, it changes over
               time and it can be attributed to many different elements (e.g. the intention of the
               artist and changes in materiality). Reproductions of artworks and especially the
               high-quality 3D printed facsimiles can contribute to visualizing and physicalizing
               the elements that contribute to the diversity of values, <q>authenticities</q>, and
               identities one artwork can have, such as its artistic and conceptual value to name a
               few <ptr target="#latour_lowe2011"/>. As the original artwork can only represent one
               specific moment in time due to its unique material, 3D printed reproductions can be
               used in addition to the original artwork to express its life cycle and multiplicity
               of values.</p>
            <p>The question that arises in this case and which we hope to solve using the 3D prints,
               is which version will be considered to be more genuine or <q>authentic</q>: would
               this be to present the painting in its current state, conserving its materials the
               way it looks today and by considering the blue layer as a part of its history? Or to
               irreversibly remove the azurite layer, but coming closer to the way the Master would
               have wanted the panel to look and in a way more similar to the way the artwork was
               experienced during the Middle Ages? This relates to the question if the availability
               of a high quality facsimile of one over these versions will play a role in the
               conservation process? How will the restoration committee weigh the availability of
               both versions in their decision on what conservation treatment will be applied to the
               panel?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>Within this research, we want to use a 3D facsimile to see whether visualizing a past
               state of an artwork can help to get a better understanding of the material changes an
               artwork goes through, which might aid the final restoration of the original. Although
               it is a high-quality reproduction based on detailed 3D data and extensive material
               research opting to be as scientifically close to the original painting as possible,
               it is important to realize that a facsimile will and can never be identical to a
               previous state of the artwork. For this reason, it is essential to pinpoint where the
               differences lie. First and foremost, a synthetic 3D print is different in terms of
               materials and could therefore never provide an exact and accurate model of the panel
               in a previous state. </p>
            <p>Furthermore, although the way the facsimile looks is partly based on accurate
               measurements, it will always be a <q>best guess</q>. However, the same can be said in
               the case of the actual restoration of the original for the interpretation of the past
               is always subjective and place and time dependent <ptr target="#stols-witlox2021"/>.
               Consequently, both the 3D prints as well as the original represent the object in a
               specific moment in time: one 3D print will show the artwork before the restoration;
               one 3D print will show a reconstructed version of what we think the artwork must have
               looked like in 1425; the painting itself will show a restored version of the panel.
               Although the facsimiles make it possible to visualize multiple stages of the
               artwork’s lifecycle, it simultaneously <q>freezes</q> them in time. Subsequently, all
               three <q>time-freezes</q> will impact the way the artwork will be perceived and
               interpreted for the years to come. For this reason, similarly to the actual
               restoration, the way the 3D reconstructed version looks must be carefully discussed.
               For instance, one could question that if the background would be reconstructed to a
                  <q>pristine</q> state, should the figurines and the tendrils be reconstructed as
               well? Or since the figurines and the tendrils are weathered, to what extend should
               the golden background be adjusted? Simultaneously, the same kinds of questions can be
               asked in terms of storytelling and explaining the context in which this artwork was
               made. Do we know how the artwork was used and how it was displayed?</p>
            <p>Yet, we want to emphasize that although the 3D print might not be exactly accurate to
               the original’s current or past state, it meets the inquiry central to this research
               project <ptr target="#fors_principe_sibum2016"/>. Furthermore, we believe that using
               reproduction and visual reconstructions could be greatly beneficial to get a better
               and more life-like idea of how the artist and his contemporaries must have
               experienced the artwork. This way, not only researchers and conservators can
               understand the inquiries central to the conservation of art, but also the public can
               get an insight in the difficulties of restoring this panel.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Future works</head>
            <p>Currently, after recording the panel’s colors and topography, we are aiming to
               continue this research by processing the data. By researching the artwork’s materials
               (e.g. using dendrological research, IRR, MA-XRF scanning), damages, art historical
               past, and by relying on the knowledge of the restorer, we will analyze the digital
               model on its accuracy. This way, we can combine the digital data gathered by Factum
               Foundation with the knowledge of the professionals involved in the conservation to
               come to a digital model which most accurately presents the current and past state of
               the panel. We aim to explore how we can combine different modalities to learn more
               about the materials and stratigraphy of the panel. This could be used to study the
               effect of changes in material composition.</p>
            <p>Consequently, multiple printed facsimiles of the artwork will be made to see the
               physical effects of digital changes made to the materials. Two 3D prints will be made
               by Factum Foundation in collaboration with the restorer of the painting, Caroline van
               der Elst. She will be involved with the digital restoration and will check the
               facsimiles to make the final material appearance correspond to what the panel
               originally must have looked like. Additionally, in collaboration with Canon
               Production Printing, we will try to create a third 3D printed facsimile without the
               post-printed craftsmanship (the retouchings of the restorer). This way, we aim to
               analyze both the digital model as well as the 3D printing technology’s ability to
               correctly reconstruct the material appearance of the panel. The 3D prints will be
               useful in communicating the dilemma to a larger audience (of both professionals and
               non-professionals) and will help in making the multifaceted authenticity of the
               artwork more clear during a potential exhibition about this project. Additionally,
               perception research done during this event and using the 3D prints will provide
               insight into the perception of the artwork and the potential effects of removing the
               background.</p>
            <p>The two accurate 3D prints of Factum Foundation of both versions of the painting also
               allow the investigation of the perception of the artwork. An eye tracking experiment
               will be conducted to analyze the viewing experience of the visitor, regarding the two
               versions of the artwork. The eye tracking research will be combined with the think
               aloud-method, in which raw eye-tracking data is supported with qualitative data based
               on the conversations of the participants. We will focus on the effect of the light
               source (stable / unstable) on the perception of both versions of the painting. A
               hypothetical difference in perception is the appearance of the blood of Christ in the
               painting. Using an unstable light source (e.g. flickering candle-light), the contrast
               between the shine of the full golden background and the matte red tempera used for
               the blood could mean a better visibility and thus a stronger symbolic presence, in
               comparison to the current blue background. The perception research using the 3D
               prints will provide insight in the perception of the artwork and the potential
               effects of removing the background. This, together with the high quality of the
               reproductions, will be highly important for the final restoration of <title
                  rend="italic">The Crucifixion</title>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            
            <p>This project is done in collaboration with Museum Catharijneconvent, Delft University
               of Technology, Leiden University, Utrecht University, and The Factum Foundation.</p>
            <p>The authors would like to extend their sincere thanks to Carlos Bayod of the Factum
               Foundation for reviewing the technical information; Micha Leeflang as the
               representative of Museum Catharijneconvent; Caroline van der Elst for restoring this
               artwork; Clemens Weijkamp of Canon Production Printing for the elevated printing;
               Stichting Rembrandt, Leiden University Centre for the Arts in Society and LDE –
               Centre for Cultural Heritage and Development, The Netherlands Institute for
               Conservation+Art+Science+ for making this project possible.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin1936" label="Benjamin 1936">Benjamin, W. (1936) <title
                  rend="italic">The work of art in the age of mechanical reproduction</title> (J. A.
               Underwood, Trans. 2007). Penguin Books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blendercommunity2018" label="Blender Community 2018">Blender Community
               (2018) <title rend="italic">Blender – a 3D modelling and rendering package</title>.
               Stichting Blender Foundation, Amsterdam. (Retrieved from <ref
                  target="http://www.blender.org">http://www.blender.org</ref> 20 March 2022) </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blinn1978" label="Blinn 1978">Blinn, J.F. (1978) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Simulation of wrinkled surfaces</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  5th annual conference on Computer graphics and interactive techniques</title>,
               286–292</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen1998" label="Cohen 1998">Cohen, J.D. (1998) <title rend="italic"
                  >Appearance-preserving simplification of polygonal models</title>. PhD thesis,
               (Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="digiuseppantoniodifranco_galeazzi_vassallo_2018"
               label="Di Giuseppantonio Di Franco, Galeazzi, and Vassallo 2018">Di Giuseppantonio Di
               Franco, P., Galeazzi, F., and Vassallo, V., eds. (2018) <title rend="italic"
                  >Authenticity and cultural heritage in the age of 3D digital
               reproductions</title>. McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research, University
               Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunlop2009" label="Dunlop 2009">Dunlop, A. (2009) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Materials, Origins and the Nature of Early Italian Painting</title>, in <title
                  rend="italic">Crossing Cultures: Conflict, Migration and Convergence</title>, ed.
               Jaynie Anderson (Carlton, 2009): 472–76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elkouraetal2019" label="Elkoura et al. 2019">Elkoura, G., Grassia, S.,
               Boonyatera, S., Mohr, A., Jeremias-Vila, P., and Kuruc, M. (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">A deep dive into universal scene description and hydra</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">ACM SIGGRAPH 2019 Courses, </title>1–48.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="factumfoundation2021a" label="Factum Foundation 2021a">Factum Foundation.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">High resolution image viewer of the Crucifixion</title>,
                  <ref
                  target="https://www.highres.factum-arte.org/Utrecht_Crucifixion_Panel/shared/viewer.html"
                  >https://www.highres.factum-arte.org/Utrecht_Crucifixion_Panel/shared/viewer.html</ref>
               [accessed 09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="factumfoundation2021b" label="Factum Foundation 2021b">Factum Foundation.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">High resolution image viewers</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.factumfoundation.org/high-resolution-multi-layered-viewers"
                  >https://www.factumfoundation.org/high-resolution-multi-layered-viewers</ref>
               [accessed 09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="factumfoundation2021c" label="Factum Foundation 2021c">Factum Foundation.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">Lucida 3D scanner</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1478/lucida-3d-scanner"
                  >https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1478/lucida-3d-scanner</ref> [accessed 09
               September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="factumfoundation2021d" label="Factum Foundation 2021d">Factum Foundation.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">Panoramic Composite Photography</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1343/panoramic-composite-photography"
                  >https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1343/panoramic-composite-photography</ref>
               [accessed 09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="factumfoundation2021e" label="Factum Foundation 2021e">Factum Foundation.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">Recording with the Lucida 3D scanner</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1552/recording-with-the-lucida-3d-scanner"
                  >https://www.factumfoundation.org/pag_fa/1552/recording-with-the-lucida-3d-scanner</ref>
               [accessed 09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gombrich1932" label="Gombrich 1932">Gombrich, E. (1932/33) <title
                  rend="quotes">Dinghaftigkeit</title>, <title rend="quotes">Review of Josef
                  Bodonyi, Entstehung und Bedeutung des Goldgrundes in der Spätantiken
                  Bildkomposition (1932/33),</title>
               <title rend="italic">Kritische Berichte zur Kunstgeschichtlichen Literatur</title> 5,
               65–7. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17863/CAM.27029"
                  >https://doi.org/10.17863/CAM.27029</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fors_principe_sibum2016" label="Fors, Principe, and Sibum 2016">Fors, H.,
               Principe L.M., and Sibum, H.O. (2016) <title rend="quotes">From the Library to the
                  Laboratory and Back Again: Experiment as a Tool for Historians of Science</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Ambix</title>, 63:2, 85–97, <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00026980.2016.1213009"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/00026980.2016.1213009</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jones2010" label="Jones 2010">Jones, S. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Negotiating Authentic Objects and Authentic Selves: Beyond the Deconstruction of
                  Authenticity</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Material Culture</title>,
               vol. 15(2), 181–203. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1359183510364074"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1177/1359183510364074</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kim2019" label="Kim 2019">Kim, D.Y. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Points on
                  a Field: Gentile da Fabriano and Gold Ground</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal
                  of Early Modern History</title> 23, vol. 2(3), 191–226.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour_lowe2011" label="Latour and Lowe 2011">Latour, B., and Lowe, A.
               (2011) <title rend="quotes">The Migration of the Aura, or How to Explore the Original
                  through Its Facsimiles</title>, <title rend="italic">Switching Codes: Thinking
                  Through Digital Technology in the Humanities and the Arts</title>. Eds: Thomas
               Bartscherer, Roderick Coover. (Chicago: Chicago UP): 275–298. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="martens2010" label="Martens 2010">Martens, M.P.J. (2010) <title
                  rend="quotes">Leave it or take it away: ethical considerations on the removal of
                  overpaintings</title>, <title rend="italic">CeROArt</title> [Online], <ref
                  target="doi.10.4000/ceroart.4765">doi.10.4000/ceroart.4765</ref> [accessed 06
               September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="museumcatharijneconvent2020" label="Museum Catharijneconvent 2020">Museum
               Catharijneconvent (2020–2021) <title rend="italic">Body Language</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.catharijneconvent.nl/tentoonstellingen/body-language/"
                  >https://www.catharijneconvent.nl/tentoonstellingen/body-language/</ref> [accessed
               09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perlin2002" label="Perlin 2002">Perlin, K. (2002) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Improving noise</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 29th annual
                  conference on Computer graphics and interactive techniques</title>. 681–82.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rijksmuseum2021" label="Rijksmuseum 2021">Rijksmuseum (2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Nachtwacht Missende Stukken</title>, <ref
                  target="https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/nl/stories/operatie-nachtwacht/story/nachtwacht-de-missende-stukken"
                  >https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/nl/stories/operatie-nachtwacht/story/nachtwacht-de-missende-stukken</ref>
               [accessed 09 September 2021]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stols-witlox2021" label="Stols-Witlox 2021">Stols-Witlox, M. (2021) <title
                  rend="quotes">Imperfect Copies. Reconstructions in Conservation Research and
                  Practice</title>, <title rend="italic">Reconstruction, Replication and
                  Re-enactment in the Humanities and Social Sciences</title> (Amsterdam: University
               of Amsterdam Press): 30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tissen2020" label="Tissen 2020">Tissen, L.N.M. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Authenticity vs 3D reproduction: Never the twain shall meet?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Arts in Society. Academic Rhapsodies, </title>(Leiden: Leiden
               University Press), 21–40. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tissen2021" label="Tissen 2021">Tissen, L. (2021) <title rend="quotes">The
                  digital reconstruction of the crucifixion of the Lindau master (ca. 1425)</title>,
               Museum Catharijneconvent, Utrecht. 9 June. <ref
                  target="https://www.globalheritage.nl/news/the-digital-reconstruction-of-the-crucifixion-of-the-lindau-master-ca-1425"
                  >https://www.globalheritage.nl/news/the-digital-reconstruction-of-the-crucifixion-of-the-lindau-master-ca-1425</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tissen_malik_vermeeren2021" label="Malik, Tissen, and Vermeeren 2021"
            	>Malik, U.S., Tissen, L.N.M., and Vermeeren, A.P.O.S. (2021) <title rend="quotes">3D
                  Reproductions of Cultural Heritage Artefacts: Evaluation of Significance and
                  Experience</title>, <title rend="italic">Studies in Digital Heritage</title> vol.
               4:1.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="walteretal2007" label="Walter et al. 2007">Walter, B., Marschner, S.R.,
               Li, H., and Torrance, K.E. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Microfacet Models for
                  Refraction through Rough Surfaces</title>, <title rend="italic">Rendering
                  Techniques 2007: Eurographics Symposium on Rendering: Grenoble, France, June
                  25–27, 2007 </title>. 195–206.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
