<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets
               to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Todd <dhq:family>Presner</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>UCLA</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>presner@ucla.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Todd Presner is Chair of UCLA’s Digital Humanities Program and Ross Professor
                     of Germanic Languages and Comparative Literature. Since 2018, he is Associate
                     Dean of Digital Innovation in the Division of Humanities and Adviser to the
                     Vice Chancellor of Research for Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences
                     research.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Lizhou <dhq:family>Fan</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Michigan</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lizhouf@umich.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000623</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <language ident="de"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Indexing Agency in Testimonies</item>
                  <item>Digital Humanities</item>
                  <item>Holocaust Studies</item>
                  <item>Information Extraction</item>
                  <item>Semantic Triplets</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The following article presents a digital humanities exploration of indexing and
               analyzing expressions of agency in Holocaust testimonies. Using a set of text
               analysis methods to identify, classify, and visualize “semantic triplets,” we show
               how attention to agency complements and extends conventional approaches to indexing.
               Our examples come from two corpora of Holocaust oral histories: the first were
               conducted in Displaced Persons camps in 1946 by an interviewer named David Boder; the
               second were conducted by the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive in the
               1990s. We focus on two salient testimonies from each corpus in order to describe the
               methodology and what the analysis of agency can contribute to the writing of
               “microhistories” of the Holocaust. Building on semantic web analyses, the methods
               provide a groundwork for the development of a graph database to search testimonies by
               agency and thereby provide historical insights about what people report they did and
               what was done to them.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</p>
         <p>
            <ref target="mailto:lizhouf@umich.edu">lizhouf@umich.edu</ref>, <ref
               target="mailto:presner@ucla.edu">presner@ucla.edu</ref>
         </p>
         <div>
            <head>Abstract</head>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.gjdgxs">
            <head>1 Introduction</head>
            <p>Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding
               the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history
               interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the
               rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath.
               The “era of the witness,” as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence
               of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff
               Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation
               Visual History Archive (Wieviorka 2006). Altogether, these archives have recorded
               well over one-hundred thousand hours of testimony and preserved hundreds of thousands
               of individual stories.</p>
            <p>Because of the sheer size of these collections, indexing systems are critically
               important for accessing their content. As such, all of these collections can be
               searched effectively by names, dates, events, places, organizations, and various
               subject headings. This is because “noun-based ontologies” form the taxonomic
               structure of most indexing systems and finding aids. Attuned to the objective realm
               of what was said, these ontologies help make the general content of an oral history
               discoverable and accessible to researchers and the broader community of listeners.
               When users enter keywords into a textbox, search and retrieval works because the
               content is consistently and thoroughly described by a standardized, controlled
               vocabulary (Presner 2016).</p>
            <p>Not surprisingly, this is also the approach of most entity-recognition software
               packages, such as OpenNLP (The Apache Software Foundation 2017) and SpaCy (Explosion
               AI 2020), which are very successful at identifying things said, such as proper names,
               organizations, geographic locations, historical events, dates, units of time,
               quantities, and other numerical units, such as percentages and times of day. But one
               of the fundamental limits is the focus on extracting isolated elements (primarily
               nouns) rather than larger narrative units that describe what people did and what was
               done to them. The purpose of this paper is to ask: In what ways can oral histories be
               mined computationally to index how survivors narrate behaviors, actions, reactions,
               assessments, and modes of self-orientation and personal agency? This is vitally
               important in Holocaust testimonies since agency is often described within networks of
               violence and coercion. This paper explores a method for extracting, characterizing,
               and interlinking “semantic triplets” to index and analyze vectors of action and
               agency, rather than just discrete topics, themes, or isolated nouns. In so doing, we
               complement conventional indexing to gain a richer, nuanced understanding of the
               events, agents, and actions described in a testimony.</p>
            <p>A semantic triplet is a grammatical unit consisting of <hi rend="italic"
                  >Subjects</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Relations</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                  >Objects</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>s are units consisting of nouns,
               primarily people, pronouns, and proper names, as well as direct modifiers of the
               subject. <hi rend="italic">Relation</hi>s are verb units including one or more verbs,
               related prepositions, and modifiers like adverbs. <hi rend="italic">Object</hi>s,
               both direct and indirect, have a broader range of parts-of-speech and include regular
               noun units, adjectives, adverbs, and more. For example, “I removed the yellow
                  patch”<note> Removing the “yellow patch” refers to removing the yellow star that
                  Jews were forced to wear on their outer garments to identify themselves publicly.
               </note> is a semantic triplet expressed as active speech (something the subject did),
               while “I was shipped to Auschwitz” is a semantic triplet expressed as passive speech
               (something done by an unspecified agent to the subject). By linking semantic triplets
               with descriptive, keyword metadata, we hope to show how new patterns of agency and
               previously unrecognized “microhistories” (Zalc and Bruttmann 2016) can be highlighted
               and discovered within oral histories. Rather than considering our method as a
               reduction or simplification of the text into discrete units of data, we argue that
               semantic triplets form a paratext that highlights the richness of the testimonial
               narrative by adding to existing metadata and methods of indexing.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.30j0zll">
            <head>2 Indexing Approaches in Two Corpora of Holocaust Testimonies</head>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.1fob9te">
               <head>2.1 Corpus #1: David Boder’s 1946 Interviews with Displaced Survivors </head>
               <p>The psychologist and linguist David Boder has a unique place in the history of
                  Holocaust testimony collection because he was the first person to record the
                  voices of displaced survivors in their own words after the end of World War
                     II.<note> Both before and after the time that Boder completed his audio
                     recordings, various Historical Commissions throughout Germany, Poland, Hungary,
                     and Eastern Europe also collected personal stories, primarily through written
                     questionnaires and interviews (Jockusch 2012).</note> In the summer and early
                  fall of 1946, he conducted over a hundred interviews with Jewish survivors and
                  other displaced people in nine different languages (mostly in German and Yiddish,
                  but also in English, Russian, Polish, French, Lithuanian, Latvian, and Spanish),
                  using a relatively new technology called a wire recorder.<note> The best biography
                     of Boder and the significance of his recordings is <hi rend="italic">The Wonder
                        of their Voices: The 1946 Holocaust Interviews of David Boder</hi> (Rosen
                     2010).</note> He carried out his interviews in Displaced Persons (DP) camps and
                  other safe houses in France, Switzerland, Italy, and Germany, mostly with Jewish
                  survivors of concentration camps and slave labor camps, as well as with a smaller
                  group of non-Jewish refugees consisting of Mennonites and other Christians who had
                  fled Soviet territories. The interviews range in length from about 15 minutes to
                  over four hours, with most about one-hour in duration. He asked over 16,000
                  questions to his subjects in an attempt to understand the historical events of the
                  Holocaust and learn about his interviewee’s personal story of loss and
                     survival.<note> Boder and his interviewees do not use the term “Holocaust,” as
                     this term did not come into common usage until the 1950s to describe the Nazi
                     genocide of the Jews. He does, however, refer to and attempt to explicate “the
                     concentration camp phenomenon” (xiv) in the preface to his book of interviews,
                        <hi rend="italic">I Did Not Interview the Dead </hi>(1949). He says that the
                     “displaced” and “uprooted” people were “dislocated by a world catastrophe”
                     (xviii), perhaps referencing the Hebrew word <hi rend="italic">Shoah </hi>or
                     the Yiddish word <hi rend="italic">Churban</hi>, both of which were used by his
                     interviewees to describe the destruction of the Jewish communities of
                     Europe.</note> Today, Boder’s interviews are available online, as audio files
                  in their original languages as well as in English translation, through the
                  Illinois Institute of Technology’s “Voices of the Holocaust” project.<note> Copies
                     of the original wire spools were sent to the Library of Congress, which,
                     decades later, procured the technical means to undertake the media transfer of
                     the wire-recorded audio to tape. Later, they were digitized by the Illinois
                     Institute of Technology (IIT) and made available as WAV files through the
                     Aviary platform. The interviews can be accessed on the Voices of the Holocaust
                     website: <ref target="https://voices.library.iit.edu/david_boder"
                        >https://voices.library.iit.edu/david_boder</ref>. The English translations,
                     annotations, and indexing were done by Boder for the testimonies in his book,
                        <hi rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies of Displaced People </hi>(Boder
                     1950-56).</note>
               </p>
               <p>After the interviews were recorded, Boder spent nearly ten years preparing a
                  3,194-page anthology of the survivor reports, which he called <hi rend="italic"
                     >Topical Autobiographies of Displaced People</hi>.<note> Boder’s full indices
                     are found at the end of <hi rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies of Displaced
                        People</hi> (Boder 1950-56), 3,105-3,159.</note> It consisted of typewritten
                  translations, which he marked-up and indexed, of 70 of the testimonies. He
                  developed the first indices for characterizing the experiences of Holocaust
                  survivors, including a “subjects and situations” index with more than 300 entries,
                  a “geographic and ethnic” index with over 400 entries, a “persons and
                  organizations” index with close to 300 entries, and a “trauma inventory”
                  enumerating 46 types of trauma and violence experienced by survivors. His
                  “subjects and situations” index represented the first controlled vocabulary for
                  indexing Holocaust testimonies and included shared experiences like deportations,
                  selections, mistreatment, and killings as well as personal experiences such as
                  food deprivation, thirst, and screaming.</p>
               <p>Our analysis below will focus on two of these testimonies: The first is an
                  interview he conducted on September 26, 1946, with a 34-year-old, Polish-Jewish
                  woman named Anna Kovitzka (given the pseudonym “Anna Kaletska” by Boder). Kovitzka
                  lost most of her family, including her young baby, who she had given to a
                  Christian Polish woman in the hopes that the child would be able to survive. The
                  Polish woman was later denounced by a neighbor, and the child was killed. The
                  hour-long interview, spoken in Yiddish, covers about eight years of her life and
                  moves between her birthplace of Kielce, escaping the Grodno ghetto, being deported
                  to Auschwitz, and, finally, at the end of the war, being driven back into Germany,
                  and ending up after the war in Wiesbaden, where she is interviewed. The second
                  interview is with a German-Jewish survivor named Jürgen Bassfreund, who was also
                  deported to Auschwitz, where he worked in a forced labor factory. Conducted in
                  Munich on September 20, 1946, Bassfreund describes the rise of Hitler in Germany,
                  the deportation and death of his mother, and the horrific conditions he endured
                  while being transferred between multiple concentration camps. We chose this
                  particular interview because Bassfreund – who later changed his name to Jack Bass
                  – was re-interviewed by the USC Shoah Foundation in 1997, in his home in
                  Alabama.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.3znysh7">
               <head>2.2 Corpus #2: The USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive</head>
               <p>Containing about 55,000 audiovisual testimonies, the Shoah Foundation’s Visual
                  History Archive (VHA) is the largest digital archive of Holocaust and genocide
                  testimonies in the world. The videos range in length from several minutes to more
                  than ten hours, although most are between one and three hours in duration.
                  Indexers trained by the Foundation tagged the videos with keywords by linking
                  one-minute segments of video to one or more search terms in its 60,000+ word,
                  hierarchical thesaurus. In addition, transcripts are currently being created for
                  many of the testimonies in their original languages as well as in English
                     translation.<note> The Shoah Foundation generously provided our team with 983
                     English-language transcripts prepared by ProQuest and an additional set of 900
                     German language testimonies prepared by the Freie University in Berlin. While
                     this article describes only the analyses conducted with English-language
                     transcripts, the methods are being developed for German, too.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Using a tool called a “Video Indexing Application,” the majority of the
                  testimonies were automatically separated into discrete, one-minute segments, and
                  an indexer was prompted to assign a keyword from the thesaurus to the segment
                  (although not every segment had to have an indexing keyword). The VHA derived its
                  indexing protocols from the National Information Standards Organization’s Z39.19
                  standard for the construction, format, and management of monolingual controlled
                  vocabularies. While useful for identifying topics, people, places, and events for
                  general searching, the index tends to obscure individual actions and agency, not
                  to mention aspects of performative delivery, subjective experiences, and
                  expressions of questioning, doubt, and possibility (Presner 2016). Even though the
                  aim of the index is objectivity, it is important to underscore that a human
                  listener decided what to index and what not to index; a human listener decided
                  what indexing term to use and what indexing term not to use; and a human listener
                  decided if a given narrative segment should be described by a keyword or not. What
                  is missing in the indexing system’s “philosophy of pursued objectivity” (USC Shoah
                  Foundation 2006) are the specific semantic expressions used by survivors to
                  describe actions, give evaluative assessments, provide orientation, and tell about
                  other types of agency and activities, including subjective experiences and
                  everyday behaviors, reactions, and acts of resistance.</p>
               <p>In addition to the Jürgen Bassfreund/Jack Bass re-interview, our analysis will
                  focus on the testimony of Erika Jacoby. Jacoby, a Hungarian Jew deported to
                  Auschwitz with her family in the Summer of 1944, survived the camp with her
                  mother. Her family was among the hundreds of thousands of Hungarian Jews deported
                  to Auschwitz at the height of the mass murder operations at Auschwitz. She was
                  separated from her grandparents and other members of her family at the ramp of
                  Auschwitz-Birkenau and never saw them again. She was able to stay together with
                  her mother, and both were selected for forced labor at Auschwitz. Her testimony
                  was recorded in her home in Los Angeles in 1994. Like the testimony of Bass, the
                  interview follows the structure of a chronological life-story, beginning with
                  childhood, experiences during the War and Holocaust, liberation, and eventual
                  immigration to the United States.</p>
               <p>The four testimonies discussed in this article are intended to provide a
                  proof-of-concept for a method to identify and index expressions of agency. Our
                  hope is that the methods can be used to complement conventional, subject-based
                  indexing and open new possibilities for cross-corpora analysis. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.2et92p0">
            <head>3 Methodology</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Figure 1: Processing and Categorizing Triplets </hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the highest level, the aim of our research method is the transformation of a
               Holocaust archives relational database (keywords linked to testimony segments) into a
               Holocaust triplets graph database (networks of semantic triplets derived from the
               testimonial transcripts). As shown in Figure 1, we use both interview transcripts and
               their metadata, while our main contribution, as discussed in this article, is the
               identification, extraction, and categorization of semantic triplets from the
               transcripts. Our process can be summarized as follows: First, we identify and extract
               triplets algorithmically from the cleaned transcripts; then, we use text mining
               methods to assign categories and cluster the triplets; finally, the results are
               manually reviewed (human check, correction, and curation). After that, they can be
               stored, along with the original metadata, in a Tableau dashboard or eventually a
               graph database for querying, indexing, and visualization. We will introduce these
               core methods below.</p>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.tyjcwt">
               <head>3.1 Semantic Triplets Extraction</head>
               <p>Triplestore and RDF store are databases optimized for storing and retrieving
                  semantic triplets (Rusher 2006; Peter 2001). In general, triplets take the form of
                  subject-predicate-object expressions and can be searched through network relations
                  between entities. Digital humanities scholars have used semantic web methods, such
                  as linked data, to facilitate interoperable research structures to analyze social
                  or cultural datasets (Hyvönen 2020) as well as to model scholarly processes in the
                  humanities by exploring the productive tension between formally structured,
                  semantic data and humanities scholarship (Bradley and Pasin 2017). Inspired by
                  both the database design of Triplestore and RDF store and their humanistic
                  applications, we have developed our own process of extracting semantic triplets
                  from spoken testimonies. Our approach is best situated in the field of information
                  extraction for domain specific documents (in our case, Holocaust and genocide
                  testimonies), while the methods and ideas are replicable in other domains such as
                  oral histories more broadly, autobiographies, and personal narratives. </p>
               <p>Traditionally, researchers proceed by creating open information extractors using
                  token related patterns (Yates et al. 2007; Fader, Soderland, and Etzioni 2011) or
                  dependency parsing related features (Wu and Weld 2010; Mausam et al. 2012). With
                  the advancement of machine learning technologies, we now see a trend of switching
                  the research focus from extracting informative and broad coverage semantic
                  triplets to producing canonical triplets which are linguistically coherent
                  (Angeli, Johnson Premkumar, and Manning 2015). This trend of research tends to
                  focus on improving the extractors’ accuracy, and, to date, there are few
                  applications that use semantic triplets to analyze spoken, personal narratives,
                  which resist formalized structures. Our semantic triplets extraction method is an
                  automated, rule-based process to aid close reading and focuses on extracting
                  expressions of agency and statements that speak to memories of individual and
                  collective actions. </p>
               <p>This triplet extraction method leverages a combination of chunk parsing, also
                  known as partial parsing, and domain specific dictionaries. It focuses on the
                  lower-level chunks of nouns and/or adjectives (NAP) and verbs, which are groups of
                  connected but non-recursive tokens with different levels in syntactic structures
                  of sentences.<note> For simplicity and consistency, we still use the name <hi
                        rend="italic">Noun Chunk</hi> to represent the extended version, i.e. nouns
                     and/or adjectives (NAP).</note> The basic linguistic representation of the
                  chunks’ rules with regular expression are converted from the NP and VP expressions
                  of Abney (1996)’s rules as</p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">N</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">P</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">?</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">*</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">N</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">*</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">N</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">|</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">?</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">*</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>and</p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">V</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">P</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mo>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>V</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mo>-</mo>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">|</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>V</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mo>-</mo>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>g</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>where <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mi>
                  </mml:math> means determiner, <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                  </mml:math> means adjectives, <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">N</mi>
                  </mml:math> means Nouns, <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>V</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mo>-</mo>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                  </mml:math> means the variation of a verb depending on its tense, <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mi>
                  </mml:math> means auxiliary, and <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>V</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mo>-</mo>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>g</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                  </mml:math> means the present participle of a verb. Using the natural language
                  processing tools in SpaCy, we further extend these rules for chunks using the
                  built-in Noun Chunk function and a customized Matcher of verb chunks.<note> Our
                     work is built on the pretrained SpaCy model “en_core_web_lg,” which is an
                     English pipeline with components including part of speech tagger, dependency
                     parser, and lemmatizer.</note> Our extension includes more parts of speech as
                  the possible components around core nouns, verbs, and adjectives, and we link the
                  chunks together to check if we fully process the sentences.<note> Our method is
                     inspired by the built-in SpaCy function of noun chunk extraction, as described
                     in its python source code <ref
                        target="https://github.com/explosion/spaCy/blob/master/spacy/lang/en/syntax_iterators.py"
                        >syntax_iterators.py</ref>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For example, Figure 2 shows a parsing tree with the different parts of a triplet.
                  In the sentence “I was clinging to the window,” we detect the active agency of
                  window clinging with “I” as the subject noun chunk and “the window” as the object
                  noun chunk. In this case, the verb chunk includes the verb, an auxiliary verb, and
                  a preposition. Using this extraction method, in our four example testimonies, we
                  are able to extract more than 3,000 triplets. Some sentences may contain multiple
                  triplets, such as this sentence: “I went with her down to the door, and there I
                  stood across the street, hidden in the gate, and I saw how my child was lying on
                  the snow.” In this example, four triplets were extracted: “I went with her,” “I
                  stood across the street,” “I hidden in the gate,” and “my child was lying on the
                  snow.” </p>
               <p>
                  <lb/>
                  <hi rend="italic">Figure 2: A Parsing Tree with Lexical Chunks that Form a
                     Triplet</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When parsing longer sentences, we always include, in a separate column for each
                  triplet, what we call “context terms.” We define the context terms to be all the
                  related lexical chunks other than those included in the extracted triplet. In the
                  first triplet above (“I went with her”), the contextual chunks are the following
                  words: the door, the street, the gate, my child, the snow. The context is
                  especially important when we want to understand an action embedded in a complex
                  sentence or create network diagrams from the triplets.<note> As discussed in
                     section 5, we have also developed a fuller, chunk-based extraction method that
                     enables us to capture longer object phrases with higher accuracy. </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.3dy6vkm">
               <head>3.2 Characterization: Action, Orientation, and Evaluation (AEO) Categories with
                  Subcategories</head>
               <p>One of our methods for characterizing semantic triplets is derived from Labov and
                  Waletzky’s (1997) social-linguistic model of narratives, where clauses are
                  characterized by temporal organization (the order in which the subject narrates
                  events and actions in the story), evaluative description (personal assessments
                  made by the narrator), and contextual orientation (usually information provided by
                  the narrator that helps orient the listener). Statements of evaluation provide
                  judgment about a person or situation, while statements of orientation provide
                  contextual or relational information. Various scholars have developed tools or
                  solved related problems using the Labov model: For example, Swanson et al. (2014)
                  created a part of speech (POS) based algorithm for clause type detection and
                  labelling based on this model; and Saldias and Roy (2020) used this model to train
                  a classifier to analyze and compare spoken personal narratives. Although these
                  applications to characterizing narratives focus on the clause level, the Labov
                  model is also applicable to our research because triplets are derived from clauses
                  and need to retain semantic information.</p>
               <p>Not unlike the use of text mining to study literary “styles” (Jockers and
                  Underwood 2015), we use our text mining methods to classify triplets by similar
                  types of speech in order to discover relationships between different types of
                  expressions of agency in oral histories. We divide descriptions of agency into
                  four sub-categories: active, passive, coercive, and speculative speech. Active and
                  passive speech are, respectively, actions done by the subject of the triplet and
                  actions done by others to the subject; coercive speech may have an active
                  structure but a passive meaning since it represents something the subject was
                  forced to do (sometimes without mentioning the person or group responsible for the
                  coercion); and, lastly, speculative speech, often expressed through modal verbs,
                  represents an uncertain or imaginary action, or a statement of possibility,
                  desire, ability, or futurity. While these categories are not perfect or
                  definitive, they help to identify the general kinds of speech describing actions.
                  We summarize and provide examples for the two-level AEO characterization system in
                  Table 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Table 1: Two-level AEO Characterization System with
                     Examples</hi>
               </p>
               <table>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Categories</cell>
                     <cell>Examples</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Agency</cell>
                     <cell>Active</cell>
                     <cell>I removed the yellow patch.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Passive</cell>
                     <cell>I was shipped to Auschwitz.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Coercive</cell>
                     <cell>My father had to leave his home.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Speculative</cell>
                     <cell>They could consummate the terrible deed.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Evaluation</cell>
                     <cell>I am not ashamed.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Orientation</cell>
                     <cell>I remembered a Christian woman.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The Triplets AEO Algorithm implements the above process as a basic
                  characterization system. In SpaCy, the algorithm takes tokens consisting of the
                  Relation Verb Chunks, <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">R</mi>
                  </mml:math>, and Object Noun Chunks, <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">O</mi>
                  </mml:math>. For each token in both <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">R</mi>
                  </mml:math> and <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">O</mi>
                  </mml:math>, there is retrievable syntactic information including (but not limited
                  to) a part of speech (POS) tag, a dependency tag, and the lemma form of the word.
                  We then put together this lexicon- and rule-based mechanism as shown in Appendix
                  I, Algorithm 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.1t3h5sf">
               <head>3.3 Characterization: Perpetrators, Victims, and Others (PVO) Categories</head>
               <p>The tripartite approach to characterizing victims, perpetrators, and bystanders
                  has been around for decades in Holocaust historiography (Hilberg 1992). While not
                  absolute or unproblematic, we strive to disambiguate subjects and objects in
                  triplets when they are identified as people or groups. To do so, we first used the
                  Entity Recognition pre-trained models in SpaCy to determine the category of a NOUN
                  (people, organizations, geographic locations, and so forth). We, then, manually
                  classified the detectable entities, where possible, into victim and perpetrator
                  groups. For example, the phrases “the German Army,” “the SS,” or “the Gestapo” are
                  detected as organizations and marked as Perpetrator, whereas the interviewee (“I”
                  and “we”) as well as familial units (parents, grandparents, sister, brother, and
                  so forth) are marked as Victim. Pronouns, however, were not disambiguated. This
                  classification method will always be incomplete, as many subjects and objects do
                  not unequivocally belong to the victim or perpetrator group. The “gray zone”
                  contains bystanders, aid-providers, “implicated subjects,” and people who moved
                  across categories and do not easily fit the binary (Rothberg 2019; Luft 2015).
                  These and other such subjects and objects are also extracted but not categorized,
                  as they demand human scrutiny of context and, indeed, prompt further questions and
                  future research about the range of agents in an oral history. For the ones that
                  are certain, we created lists of victim and perpetrator lemmas, which provided the
                  base forms of the entity words in the triplets.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.4d34og8">
            <head>4 Results and Applications</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Figure 3: Distribution of AEO Categories in Four Testimonies</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Figure 3, we show statistical summaries of the triplets in each of the four
               testimonies. The triplets were algorithmically generated from the transcripts,
               assigned categories by speech type, and evaluated for accuracy. The size of each pie
               chart is scaled to the number of triplets extracted for each testimony. Boder’s
               interviews are shorter than the Shoah Foundation interviews (and, of course, end in
               1946, rather than the 1990s). Due to the large number of triplets, we needed to
               develop ways to categorize and cluster the results. This entailed categorizing the
               triplets into six types of speech, assigning Victim and Perpetrator identities to
               certain subjects and objects, and experimenting with using a Wordnet-based
               characterization of the objects to cluster them by lemma and categories.<note> The
                  process of assigning “victim” and “perpetrator” identities is very incomplete due
                  to the need to disambiguate pronouns (“they,” “he,” “she”) as well as account for
                  proper names. </note> For our initial version of the triplet extraction process,
               6.5% of the triplets were manually corrected due to incorrect or incomplete subjects,
               verb relations, or objects. In addition, about 14% were manually removed from the
               original output because the triplet did not make sense grammatically or was
               misidentified as a triplet. The challenges and shortcomings of the triplet extraction
               process are discussed in section 5.2. To better analyze the triplets and their
               characterization, we created an interactive Triplets Dashboard, shown in Figure 4,
               which brings together the corrected triplets output, an object lemmas bubble plot,
               and multiple other filters.<note> This is <ref
                     target="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/lizhou/viz/Tableau_triplets_sheet_V3/TripletsDashboard"
                     >the interactive triplets dashboard</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>As a finding aid, the dashboard helps us query and sort the triplets by interview,
               subject, object, speech type, and more. In the dashboard, a search for semantic
               triplets can be initiated on any term, category, or type of speech both within a
               given testimony or across a group of testimonies. In the screenshot, we see the
               triplets around Bassfreund’s description of his deportation from Berlin to his
               selection for forced labor in Auschwitz. They evidence a wide-range of speech acts,
               including active speech about other people’s agency (“they gave us six slices” and
               “they placed a can”), passive speech (“we were put on trains” and “we were driven out
               of the cars”), coercive speech (“we had to sign affidavits” and “we have to leave
               Germany”), speculative speech (“I shall never forget those screams”), evaluation (“it
               was uncomfortable” and “the screams were terrible”), and orientation (“I have
               forgotten something” and “the people had a premonition”). Looking further at the
               contextual information for the coerced action of being forced to sign affidavits, for
               example, we see the following terms: “our disloyalty,” “Germany,” “account,” and
               “hostility.” The original sentence can be seen on the far right of the triplet
               output, as translated by Boder: “Before being sent away we had to sign affidavits
               that we have to leave Germany on account of our disloyalty and hostility to
                  Germany.”<note> The German original also shows both passive and coerced speech:
                  “Bevor wir abtransportiert wurden, mussten wir unterschreiben, dass wir wegen
                  staatspolitischer und feindlicher Umtriebe Deutschland verlassen müssen.”
                  (Bassfreund) </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Figure 4: Semantic Triplets Dashboard in Tableau (version 1.0)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic"> Selection from Boder’s interview with Jürgen Bassfreund</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another way triplets can be used is to identify instances of different types of
               speech within a testimony. For example, leading up to and following his description
               of being deported to Auschwitz, we can visualize all the passive and coercive
               statements made by Bassfreund in which “I” or “we” is the subject. As shown in Figure
               5, there are over 50 such instances of passive and coercive speech described in this
               section of his interview with Boder (about ten type-written pages). Bassfreund
               emphasizes, with precise language, what was done to him and the Jewish community by
               the Nazis (we were surrounded, taken, moved, driven out, loaded on, led to, rubbed
               with, shoved into, sent into, transferred to) as well as what was specifically done
               to him (I was forcibly taken, assigned, sent, transferred).<note> Examples in the
                  original German, which all follow the semantic pattern of passive speech in the
                  English translations, include: “Plötzlich waren wir umringt von der Leibstandarte,
                  und wurden dann mit Füßen getreten und in Autos verladen”; “Und dann kamen wieder
                  Autos und wieder wurden wir von der Leibstandarte zu einem ganz entlegenen Bahnhof
                  in Berlin gebracht und wurden dort einwagoniert”; “wir wurden aus diesen Wagons
                  herausgetrieben;” “wir wurden mit Petroleum eingerieben.” (Bassfreund) </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Figure 5: Selection of Bassfreund’s Passive and Coercive Speech
                  (Boder interview), with “we” and “I” as subject, respectively</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can now show our approach to semantic triplets extends and deepens topical
               indexing by pairing the triplets with the human-created indexing terms. As developed
               by both Boder and the Shoah Foundation, we see a significant continuity in terms of
               topics and themes (places, time periods, people, conditions, and events) used to
               index the testimonies. For instance, on pages 292-293 of Bassfreund’s testimony in
                  <hi rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies</hi>, Boder indexed the testimony with
               the following terms: bathing, clothing, hair cutting and shaving, professional
               criminals, confiscations, punishments, and tattoos. Similarly, in segment 25 of Bass’
               testimony, we see the following indexing terms from the Shoah Foundation: Auschwitz I
               (Poland: Concentration Camp), camp forced labor, camp latrines, camp living
               conditions, camp selections, Poland 1941 (June 21) - 1945 (May 7), prisoner hair
               cutting forced labor, transfer from Auschwitz III-Monowitz (Poland: Concentration
               Camp), and transfer to Auschwitz I (Poland: Concentration Camp). While these topics
               certainly give us guidance for finding the overarching places, dates, conditions in
               captivity, movement, and forced labor, the indexing is not at the level of sentences
               or clauses and, therefore, we do not really know what Bassfreund/Bass did or what was
               done to him. As we see in Figure 6, we produce a corresponding network of just a few
               of the triplets derived from these specific parts of his testimonies. The
               interrelated set of triplets provide information about un-indexed subjects and agents
               (both victims and perpetrators), un-indexed actions (written on, picked up by, worked
               in, filled, sent), and un-indexed objects (the formation, their stomach, a truck, the
               crematories, human hair, mattresses, packages, and a mountain). Altogether, they
               point us toward ways of using the extracted semantic triplets to read, mark-up, and
               index testimonies by including microhistorical accounts of actions by both victims
               and perpetrators. </p>
            <p>(a) Bassfreund (interviewed by Boder) (b) Bass (interviewed by the Shoah
               Foundation)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Figure 6: Selected Examples of Triplets related to Indexing
                  Categories in Two Testimonies</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next section, we discuss some of the applications of the triplets to
               identifying acts of resistance, detecting unindexed stories, and analyzing larger
               semantic networks.</p>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.2s8eyo1">
               <head>4.1 Microhistorical Acts of Resistance</head>
               <p>While large-scale acts of resistance (such as the Warsaw Ghetto uprising or the
                  Sonderkommando rebellion in Auschwitz) are rightly known and celebrated, there has
                  been comparatively less appreciation of the range of everyday, seemingly ordinary
                  acts of resistance by individuals. One historian who is working at the vanguard of
                  this reappraisal of Jewish agency is Wolf Gruner, who has delved into numerous
                  police and municipal archives in Germany to uncover the wide-range of acts of
                  defiance, opposition, and protest by Jews living in Nazi Germany (Gruner 2011;
                  2016b). In his studies of “microhistories,” he has unearthed thousands of examples
                  of Jews mounting both formal and informal protest, ranging from the filing of
                  petitions and government complaints to outright acts of defiance, such as sitting
                  on benches marked “Aryan only” or refusing to use the forced middle name of
                  “Israel” or “Sara,” to physical and armed resistance against Nazi officials
                  (Gruner 2016a). For our purposes here, we are interested in using our
                  computational method of identifying networks of semantic triplets to find
                  underappreciated or largely unknown acts of everyday resistance within Holocaust
                  testimonial narratives. Our argument is that triplets point to a wide-range of
                  small-scale actions that would otherwise go unremarked, since they do not,
                  generally speaking, rise to the level of what might be indexed as “acts of
                  resistance.” Oftentimes, these actions are not even considered to be “indexable
                  content,” and thus they are extremely difficult to locate.</p>
               <div xml:id="bookmark=id.17dp8vu">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">4.1.1 Example 1: Anna Kovitzka</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Interviewed by Boder in 1946, Anna Kovitzka’s story is particularly poignant,
                     as she describes the violent separation and loss of her family and, in
                     particular, her efforts to save her baby girl who was born in the Grodno
                     ghetto. With her husband, she managed to escape the ghetto in the hopes of
                     finding someone to care for her child. Shortly after giving up the child to a
                     Christian woman who promised to protect her, Kovitzka was deported to
                     Auschwitz. The child, unfortunately, did not survive as the Christian woman was
                     denounced for trying to protect a Jewish baby. Examining the indexing terms
                     used by Boder to mark-up her testimony, we see a wide-range of themes and
                     topics, including: geographic locations (Wiesbaden, Kielce, Grodno, Slonim,
                     Lvov, and Auschwitz), living conditions and objects (epidemics, starvation,
                     thirst, illness, sleeping accommodations, and clothing), people (children,
                     Gestapo, Prisoners-of-War, family, and Gypsies), and events (looting,
                     childbirth, burials, flight, killings, escapes, work, bathing, rebellion, and
                     appells or roll calls in camps). The last group of events certainly raises
                     questions about actions, but without further analysis, we cannot know who was
                     looting, escaping, working, rebelling, or even giving birth to a child.
                     Moreover, without delving into the testimony, we cannot uncover specific
                     vectors of agency (such as who did what, how did they do it, and to whom).</p>
                  <p>By examining the semantic triplets around the topical indexing term “escapes,”
                     we can illuminate the specific agency described by Kovitzka in this part of her
                     testimony (Table 2). The triplets indicate the actions of Kovitzka and her
                     husband to escape the ghetto in order to save their child: “went over” the
                     wires, “set up a chair,” “raised” the wire, “went out” on the street, “removed”
                     the yellow patch, and, finally, “went down” the street. In each case, we see
                     active speech describing a set of actions that occurred in the context of
                     escaping the ghetto, even after she reports that sixteen Jews were killed at
                     the gate in a first attempt to escape. While this section of the text is
                     indexed by Boder as “escapes,” “curfew,” “fences,” and “yellow star,” the
                     actual acts of escaping the ghetto through the wires, removing the yellow Star
                     of David, and going down the street represent acts of resistance and agency
                     that can be successfully detected and added to the index through computational
                     text analysis attuned to semantic triplets.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Table 2: Anna Kovitzka Triplets (around “escapes”)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Subjects</cell>
                        <cell>Relations</cell>
                        <cell>Objects</cell>
                        <cell>Context and Coreference</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Sixteen Jews</cell>
                        <cell>fell at</cell>
                        <cell>the gate</cell>
                        <cell>first attempt</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>went over</cell>
                        <cell>the wires</cell>
                        <cell>second attempt, my man, me, the child, her</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>my man</cell>
                        <cell>handed</cell>
                        <cell>the child</cell>
                        <cell>I, the wires, the second attempt, me, I, her</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>My man</cell>
                        <cell>set up</cell>
                        <cell>a chair</cell>
                        <cell>me</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>He</cell>
                        <cell>raised</cell>
                        <cell>one wire</cell>
                        <cell>Coreference: He = my man</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>He</cell>
                        <cell>handed</cell>
                        <cell>the child</cell>
                        <cell>me, Coreference: He = my man</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>went out in</cell>
                        <cell>the street</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>removed</cell>
                        <cell>the yellow patch</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>went down</cell>
                        <cell>the street</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="bookmark=id.3rdcrjn">
                  <head>Using the dashboard to search on the object “child” in Kovitzka’s testimony
                     reveals a number of triplets that show her attempts to save her child and,
                     ultimately, the child’s fate: “I must save my child,” “My man handed the
                     child,” “she has taken my child,” “she had picked up the child,” “I don’t have
                     my child,” “she kept the child,” “she loved the child,” “my child was lying on
                     the snow,” and “they buried the child.” The tragedy of Kovitzka’s loss of her
                     child forms the traumatic core of her testimony and, yet, there is barely any
                     indication of this from the indexing terms. The creation of a semantic network
                     around the term “child” would help us locate and appreciate these critical
                     actions and thus begin to index the testimony attuned to expressions of agency
                     (Figure 7).</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Figure 7: Building a semantic network from triplets related
                        to the term “child” in Anna Kovitzka’s testimony</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">4.1.2 Example 2: Erika Jacoby</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>After being deported to Auschwitz and separated from her grandparents on the
                     arrival ramp, Jacoby and her mother are selected for the slave labor camp.
                     Their heads are shaven; they are deloused for lice; and they are given meager
                     clothes. Most of Jacoby’s testimony, then, focuses on everyday life in
                     Auschwitz, including forced labor, sleeping conditions, food rations, violence,
                     and abuse. While the associated triplets bear witness to her struggle for
                     survival, our indexing of agency in Jacoby’s testimony also included the
                     following groups of triplets. As shown in Table 3, after one passive
                     construction, we see five successive, active constructions and one triplet
                     characterized as “orientation” (considered as information to the
                     interviewer).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Table 3: Erika Jacoby Triplets (401 to 407)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Subjects</cell>
                        <cell>Relations</cell>
                        <cell>Objects</cell>
                        <cell>AEO Category</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>We</cell>
                        <cell>were</cell>
                        <cell>taken to a bath</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Passive Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>were going by</cell>
                        <cell>a German officer’s area</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Active Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>saw</cell>
                        <cell>a swimming pool</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Active Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>jumped out of</cell>
                        <cell>the line</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Active Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>dove into</cell>
                        <cell>the swimming pool</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Active Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>swam across</cell>
                        <cell>the pool</cell>
                        <cell>Agency (Active Speech)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>They</cell>
                        <cell>didn’t shoot</cell>
                        <cell>me</cell>
                        <cell>Orientation</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>This utterly astonishing action is not marked up or identified in any way
                     through the Shoah Foundation’s topical indexing. In fact, there is no word
                     search that will find this part of her testimony. Jacoby relays the story in
                     just a dozen sentences, comprising about 50 seconds of her two-hour testimony.
                     And yet it is a stunning act of defiance, risk, and agency. </p>
                  <p>Here is the portion of the testimony with a little bit of context to set up the
                     scene and reflect on its meaning:</p>
                  <p>“We stayed six weeks in Auschwitz. We had many, many interesting events that
                     happened to us in Auschwitz. I just want to tell you one that was very
                     important. And I don’t think I have time to describe Auschwitz. And I’m sure
                     that it’s well known. But we were– one, one day, we were taken to a bath. We
                     were taken to a bath about once a week or once every other week. And as we were
                     marching, we were go– we were going by a German officer’s area. And I saw a
                     swimming pool. And I jumped out of the line, and I dove into the swimming pool.
                     And I swam across the pool, and I got back. And they didn’t shoot me, and I
                     survived. But of course, my mother almost died. I mean, it was such an irr–
                     irresponsible act from my part. But I was young, and I, I needed to be alive.
                     And I did that.” (Jacoby, 51:40-52:30).</p>
                  <p>Indeed, there were two “pools” on the grounds of Auschwitz: one for prisoners
                     and one for SS officers, near blocks 7 and 8. They were built as reservoirs to
                     store water rather than be used for recreational swimming. Today, a sign
                     clarifies the remains of the structure: “Fire brigade reservoir built in the
                     form of a swimming pool, probably in early 1944.” When Jacoby arrived in
                     Auschwitz in the summer of 1944, the pool would have been complete. The Shoah
                     Foundation manually tagged these segments of Jacoby’s testimony with the
                     following keywords: “camp intake procedures,” “camp prisoner marking,” “camp
                     family interactions,” “loved ones’ contacts,” “prisoner external contact,” and
                     a single person tag, her mother, Malvina Salamonovits. Judging by these tags,
                     one might expect her discussion to focus on procedural elements of the camp,
                     perhaps coupled with how she and her mother survived together. There is nothing
                     in the indexing that would indicate jumping out line, diving into the pool, and
                     swimming across. While we can certainly read or hear Jacoby talking about this
                     experience if we happened to land on this part of her testimony, it remains <hi
                        rend="italic">an unindexed action</hi>, which otherwise submerges a
                     significant act of resistance and agency. Through the computational extraction
                     of triplets, we can index, hone in on, and appreciate this defiant act.</p>
                  <p>After Auschwitz is liberated by the Soviet army, Jacoby relays that she and her
                     mother left the camp in search of food and safety from sexual assaults by
                     Russian soldiers. Over the next three and a half minutes (1:18-1:21), she
                     describes a set of actions that helped her and her mother survive. She also
                     tells of acts of revenge and anger committed by her 16-year-old self. Two of
                     the three segments are tagged by the Shoah Foundation as “food acquisition” and
                     “looting” (the third is not tagged at all). These topical terms convey little
                     about the agency involved and the kinds of actions that a listener may want to
                     search for and find in her testimony. In Table 4, we reproduce the full set of
                     23 semantic triplets that our methodology identified over these three minutes.
                     All forms of agency are included as well as all subjects and objects. The “we”
                     subject refers to Erika and her mother.</p>
                  <p>While “food acquisition” and “looting” are indexing terms that signal the
                     overall set of content, these terms tell us nothing specific about what Erika
                     and her mother did in the days after liberation; they tell us nothing about the
                     vectors of agency and reasons for their actions; and they tell us none of the
                     details of the actions conveyed in her testimony. And perhaps more pointedly,
                     the indexing terms tend to obscure more than they reveal: Far from abstract
                     topics, “food acquisition” involved the specific act of stealing and eating a
                     pig (a non-kosher act of desperation for survival), while “looting” was
                     connected to Jacoby’s immediate post-War actions, which reflect personal anger,
                     acts of revenge, and the longing for a “normal life.” The objects she takes
                     from a home are symbols of family life, domesticity, and normalcy: a white
                     tablecloth, an apron, and a little silver cup. Her act of “looting” is to take
                     these everyday, material objects from somebody’s home, the first possessions
                     that she acquires after liberation from Auschwitz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Table 4: Erika Jacoby Triplets (1:18-1:21)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Subjects</cell>
                        <cell>Relations</cell>
                        <cell>Objects</cell>
                        <cell>Segments</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>got out of</cell>
                        <cell>the camp</cell>
                        <cell>1:18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>went into</cell>
                        <cell>town</cell>
                        <cell>1:18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>looked for</cell>
                        <cell>a house</cell>
                        <cell>1:18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>found</cell>
                        <cell>a very beautiful home</cell>
                        <cell>1:18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>occupied</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>couldn’t lock</cell>
                        <cell>the door</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>barricade</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>they</cell>
                        <cell>broke into</cell>
                        <cell>the stores</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>shoved</cell>
                        <cell>a lot</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>had</cell>
                        <cell>a canvas bag</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>passed by</cell>
                        <cell>a butcher store</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>took off</cell>
                        <cell>half a pig</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>carried</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>my mother</cell>
                        <cell>saw</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>she</cell>
                        <cell>cooked</cell>
                        <cell>the pig</cell>
                        <cell>1:19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>ate</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>we</cell>
                        <cell>got</cell>
                        <cell>sick</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>was trying to find</cell>
                        <cell>a way</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>We</cell>
                        <cell>stayed in</cell>
                        <cell>this town</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>want to mention to</cell>
                        <cell>you</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>didn’t bring</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>have</cell>
                        <cell>a memento</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>broke into</cell>
                        <cell>a house</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>had</cell>
                        <cell>so much anger</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>expressed</cell>
                        <cell>that anger</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>went into</cell>
                        <cell>that house</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>broke</cell>
                        <cell>the piano</cell>
                        <cell>1:20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>many people</cell>
                        <cell>went into</cell>
                        <cell>homes</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>did not want</cell>
                        <cell>anything</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>took from</cell>
                        <cell>the house</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>took</cell>
                        <cell>a white tablecloth</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>took</cell>
                        <cell>an apron</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>took</cell>
                        <cell>a little silver cup</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>had</cell>
                        <cell>the initials</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>kept</cell>
                        <cell>it</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>longed to establish</cell>
                        <cell>a normal life</cell>
                        <cell>1:21</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.lnxbz9">
            <head>5 Discussion, Limitations, and New Work</head>
            <p>Although our process of extracting and characterizing triplets creates new paratexts
               that enhance our interpretation and ability to index testimonies by descriptions of
               agency, there are a number of limitations and shortcomings. The major issue is that
               “semantic triplets” – strictly speaking as subjects, verb relations, and objects –
               can oversimplify narrative expressivity when truncated, extracted, or
               decontextualized. Below, we will identify and discuss a number of limitations as well
               as discuss how our newer, “meticulous” triplet extraction process (version 2.0)
               addresses some of those problems. </p>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=kix.pepef34z77cd">
               <head>5.1 Considering Coreferences: Pronoun Disambiguation and Entity Linking</head>
               <p>As is evident in many of the triplets, pronouns often exist in subjects and
                  objects, and they are sometimes ambiguous. For example, there are multiple
                  references to “he,” “she,” “they,” or “them” where the pronoun could refer to a
                  perpetrator in one line but a victim in the following. Thus, a coreferencing
                  solution for the triplets needs to disambiguate pronouns or, at the very least,
                  link triplets together such that the coreference can be clearly identified. We
                  experimented with using NeuralCoref, a coreference resolution python package which
                  annotates and resolves coreference clusters using a neural network (Hugging Face
                  2019). However, this pre-trained language model is based on out-of-domain text
                  data, and it is only effective about half the time, which is not precise enough
                  for our needs. </p>
               <p>Thus, we are working on creating our own model of coreferencing for use in
                  Holocaust and genocide testimonies. This close-domain model was initially trained
                  by annotating testimonies using BRAT, a web-based annotation tool that allows
                  customized labels for entities and coreferences (Stenetorp 2012). Inspired by the
                  annotation process of entities and coreferences in an English literature dataset,
                  we will use a customized set of entity types, including named people, groups,
                  communities, as well as other regular named-entities like organizations and
                  geo-political entities (Bamman 2019). Our hope is that the training model, derived
                  from a diverse set of annotated Holocaust testimonies, will help us disambiguate
                  pronouns throughout a corpus. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=kix.6bb2i1dd5ezm">
               <head>5.2 Revisiting the Chunk Method: A More “Meticulous” Triplet Extraction Process </head>
               <p>Our chunk-based triplets extraction method is certainly not flawless. One
                  challenge is that important expressions that are not triplets are simply not found
                  (for instance, “we were separated”). Another challenge is how to capture fuller
                  object phrases and distinguish direct and indirect objects. In this version, we
                  capture both, and usually the direct object is part of the triplet and the
                  indirect object is part of the contextual information; in the more “meticulous”
                  version, we capture fuller object phrases by extracting from the “context” as much
                  as possible. Although the objects tend to be longer, they are more complete and
                  integrate the contextual elements within the object phrase itself. This newer
                  version results in both more triplets being extracted and higher accuracy.<note>
                     The details of the “meticulous” version, including the rules and sample data,
                     are available in the Github repository: <ref
                        target="https://github.com/lizhouf/semantic_triplets"
                        >https://github.com/lizhouf/semantic_triplets</ref>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>An ongoing challenge, however, concerns certain sentences with dependent,
                  relative, or conditional clauses, which are not always captured completely or may
                  be broken apart in the course of the chunk method. This problem can be seen with
                  “if, then” statements or ones that begin with a form of negation. For example,
                  this sentence spoken by Bassfreund, is turned into three triplets: “And it was
                  already night and the SS opened the doors and said if we throw out the dead bodies
                  we shall get some food.” Getting food from the SS is dependent upon the victims
                  being forced to throw out dead bodies from the train. Although the triplets are
                  captured individually, maintaining the specific contingency of the actions and
                  understanding the reasons for them requires human review and interpretation.</p>
               <p>While network analysis may give rise to new narrative orderings that allow us to
                  see relationships across a testimony or corpus, we also preserve the narrative
                  sequence of the triplets in our extraction process since the context for a triplet
                  certainly matters both within an individual sentence and between sentences. For
                  instance, when Bass says: “Well, you could tell. These guys were very rough and
                  very bad. They used to beat you up, and scream, and holler, and push you. And hit
                  you with a– a rubber– piece of rubber there. It looked like a rubber hose.” Our
                  triplet extraction method maintains the contiguity between the description of the
                  men (former criminals who the Nazis put in place as supervisors in camps) so that
                  the last triplet (“it looked like a rubber hose”) continues to make sense within
                  this context. Sequential groupings are one way to maintain narrative continuity. </p>
               <p>Another basic challenge that we face is extracting triplets from fragmented,
                  vernacular speech, which the process often has trouble parsing. Survivors
                  sometimes switch from first-person narration to second or third-person; sometimes
                  the sentences contain incomplete thoughts, repetitions, or stuttering; sometimes
                  the transcribed sentence lacks regular punctuation; and sometimes survivors quote
                  the speech of others directly or indirectly. The triplet extraction process has no
                  way of telling if a triplet refers to the quoted or attributed speech of someone
                  else. For example, Anna Kovitzka says: “Once my man said: ‘I can’t make peace with
                  them. Our child must be saved even if we two shall die.’” While two triplets are
                  extracted (“I can’t make peace with them” and “our child must be saved”), the
                  triplets are not attributed to her husband because the phrase “once my man said”
                  is not part of either triplet. </p>
               <p>To take another example: In his interview with Boder, Bassfreund says: “We were
                  rubbed with kerosene” with respect to the delousing process in Auschwitz. That
                  triplet is easily found; however, in his later interview with the Shoah
                  Foundation, he says: “And then they did some – used some kind of delousing agent,
                  they poured all over us.” No triplets were found in the first version of our
                  process, as the sentence is spoken with breaks that less clearly connect the
                  subject (“they”) to the verbs and objects. To address this, our “meticulous”
                  version of triplet extraction is based on a set of finer-defined, semantic rules
                  to extract noun and verb chunks. To make chunks include more contextual
                  information and complete grammatical structures, we add a layer in between the
                  sentence and chunk levels, which we call the “segment level,” for chunk-boundary
                  decision making, as shown in Figure 8. Even though the sentence is not
                  grammatically correct, the new extraction method is able to find the triplets in
                  this sentence, while the previous approach was not. And although some objects and
                  object phrases become longer than expected, we can now extract a more complete
                  context for the objects of a triplet. We are also experimenting with categorizing
                  object phrases based on semantic features like word lemmas, WordNet synsets, and
                  dependency parsing, which will create more filters for large scale triplets
                  retrieval.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Figure 8: Example of the Three-level Chunk-based Triplets
                     Extraction Method</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=kix.o1ayauhedcf3">
               <head>5.3 Other Improvements and Potential Applications</head>
               <p>Based on the indexing and analysis of agency in the four example testimonies
                  discussed here, we have applied our “meticulous” method to over a thousand
                  Holocaust testimonies. The output creates a new paratext of triplets for each
                  interview that provides a set of additional metadata that can be queried, indexed,
                  and overlaid on existing metadata. The triplets are intended to function as
                  finding aids to supplement the original text by providing a new set of metadata
                  attuned to articulations of agency. One of the promising directions is to query
                  “shared experiences” (such as reports of and responses to discrimination) across a
                  corpus using the semantic triplets. What, for example, did hundreds of different
                  witnesses say about their memories of discrimination during the 1930s and early
                  40s and how did they describe their individual reactions? How many other people
                  remember removing the yellow star from their clothes and what did they say they
                  did next? </p>
               <p>Going forward, we hope to create a better finding aid and scaled-up visualization
                  tool, perhaps through an indexing dashboard supported by a triplets database.
                  Researchers can then query and visualize through the same interface to find
                  semantic triplets and generate associated networks. This interactive dashboard
                  could combine the flexibility of curation in the Triplets Dashboard in Tableau
                  with a Neo4j Network Visualization Dashboard. At the same time, we are continuing
                  to explore how searching for “agency” within a narrative can complement standard
                  thematic and topical searches through network clustering and category clustering
                  of triplets. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.44sinio">
            <head>6. Conclusion</head>
            <p>Semantic triplets are a text immanent way to computationally identify and index
               descriptions of agency within oral histories. While conventional indexing is
               important for finding overarching themes and topics, it relies on the creation of a
               secondary scaffolding for searching within the testimonies, almost always attuned to
               named entities, topics, and general themes. Indexing semantic triplets, on the other
               hand, is primarily an algorithmic approach to identify specific expressions of agency
               and their lexical context from transcripts. As such, we are able to link and analyze
               multiple vectors of action and attune our reading and listening to networks of
               agents, relations, objects, and contexts. Our approach always relies on and is
               derived from the interviewee’s spoken (and transcribed) language. In this regard, it
               is a kind of “algorithmic close reading” built on a paratext derived from the
               original transcript. Although “distant reading” remains a powerful approach for
               statistically summarizing the content of a corpus, digital humanities scholars have
               also warned against the seduction of “delegating observation” and “delegating
               interpretation” to machines (Underwood 2019, 157-158). In many ways, semantic
               triplets use some of the algorithmic tools of distant reading (large-scale text
               analysis attuned to patterns, classifications, and clusters) to enable humans to
               undertake close readings and perform interpretative queries. It is up to us to figure
               out the meaning or significance of any description of agency in the context of an
               oral history or corpus.</p>
            <p>In this sense, our approach is also quite different from current machine learning
               methods for information extraction systems. Although seemingly unpopular these days
               from a natural language processing perspective, a fully rule-based and easily
               interpretable system works well for our purposes of triplets extraction and analysis.
               We can describe the algorithms we use based on conditional statements and clear rules
               for additional human curation and correction. Computational indexing of agency shifts
               the scale of analysis to individual mentions of agency and interconnected actions,
               helping us read and listen to testimonies in ways that deepen our understanding of
               what people report they did and what was done to them. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookmark=id.2jxsxqh">
            <head>7. Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>The research presented here owes a significant debt of gratitude to the USC Shoah
               Foundation, particularly Stephen Smith, Samuel Gustman, Martha Stroud, Claudia
               Wiedeman, and Crispin Brooks. All of the analyses presented in this paper were
               performed at UCLA under the direction of Todd Presner. The co-authors, Lizhou Fan and
               Todd Presner, are grateful to UCLA team members Anna Bonazzi, Rachel Deblinger, Kyle
               Rosen, Michelle Lee, and Wanxin Xie. We also thank Anne Knowles, David Shepard,
               Anthony Caldwell, Wolf Gruner, and Zoe Borovsky for their generous support and
               feedback over the years.</p>
            <p>
               <pb/>
            </p>
            <p>Works Cited</p>
            <p>Abney, Steven. 1996. “Partial Parsing via Finite-State Cascades.” <hi rend="italic"
                  >Nat. Lang. Eng.</hi> 2 (4): 337–344.
               https://doi.org/10.1017/S1351324997001599.</p>
            <p>Angeli, Gabor, Melvin Jose Johnson Premkumar, and Christopher D. Manning. 2015.
               “Leveraging Linguistic Structure For Open Domain Information Extraction.” In <hi
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 53rd Annual Meeting of the Association for
                  Computational Linguistics and the 7th International Joint Conference on Natural
                  Language Processing (Volume 1: Long Papers)</hi>, 344–354. Beijing, China:
               Association for Computational Linguistics. <ref
                  target="https://aclanthology.org/P15-1034"
               >https://aclanthology.org/P15-1034</ref>.</p>
            <p>Bamman, David, Olivia Lewke, and Anya Mansoor. 2019. “An annotated dataset of
               coreference in English literature.” arXiv preprint arXiv:1912.01140.</p>
            <p>Bass, Jack. Interview 30765. <hi rend="italic">Visual History Archive</hi>, USC Shoah
               Foundation, 1997. Accessed November 1, 2020. </p>
            <p>Bassfreund, Jürgen. Interview with David Boder (September 20, 1946). <hi
                  rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies of Displaced People</hi>. 276-318. Also
               available on: <hi rend="italic">Voices of the Holocaust</hi>, Illinois Institute of
               Technology. <ref target="https://voices.library.iit.edu/interview/bassfreundJ"
                  >https://voices.library.iit.edu/interview/bassfreundJ</ref>. Accessed November 1,
               2020. </p>
            <p>Boder, David. 1949. <hi rend="italic">I Did Not Interview the Dead</hi>. University
               of Illinois Press. </p>
            <p>Boder, David. 1950-56. <hi rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies of Displaced
                  People</hi>. UCLA Special Collections, Young Research Library. Unpublished
               manuscript. Boxes 9-11.</p>
            <p>Bradley, John, and Michele Pasin. 2017. “Fitting Personal Interpretation with the
               Semantic Web: Lessons Learned from Pliny.” <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</hi> 11 (1).</p>
            <p>Explosion AI. 2020. “Industrial-Strength Natural Language Processing.” 2020.
               https://spacy.io/.</p>
            <p>Fader, Anthony, Stephen Soderland, and Oren Etzioni. 2011. “Identifying Relations for
               Open Information Extraction.” In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2011 Conference
                  on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</hi>, 1535–1545. Edinburgh,
               Scotland, UK.: Association for Computational Linguistics.
               https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/D11-1142.</p>
            <p>Gruner, Wolf. 2011. “‘The Germans Should Expel the Foreigner Hitler’: Open Protest
               and Other Forms of Jewish Defiance in Nazi Germany.” Edited by David Silberklang. <hi
                  rend="italic">Yad Vashem Studies</hi> 39 (2): 13–53.</p>
            <p>— — — . 2016a. “Defiance and Protest. A Comparative Micro-Historical Re-Evaluation of
               Individual Jewish Responses towards Nazi Persecution.” Edited by Claire Zalc and Tal
               Bruttmann. <hi rend="italic">Microhistories of the Holocaust</hi>, 209–26.</p>
            <p>— — — . 2016b. “Defiance and Protest: Forgotten Acts of Individual Jewish
               Resistance.”
               https://www.cornell.edu/video/wolf-gruner-jewish-defiance-protest-nazi-germany.</p>
            <p>Hilberg, Raul. 1992. <hi rend="italic">Perpetrators, Victims, Bystanders: The Jewish
                  Catastrophe, 1933-1945</hi>. Aaron Asher Books New York.</p>
            <p>Hugging Face. 2019. “NeuralCoref 4.0: Coreference Resolution in SpaCy with Neural
               Networks.” 2019. https://github.com/huggingface/neuralcoref.</p>
            <p>Hyvönen, Eero. 2020. “Using the Semantic Web in Digital Humanities: Shift from Data
               Publishing to Data-Analysis and Serendipitous Knowledge Discovery.” <hi rend="italic"
                  >Semantic Web</hi>,11(1): 187-193.</p>
            <p>Jacoby, Erika. Interview 8. Segments, 52-53, 78-82. <hi rend="italic">Visual History
                  Archive</hi>, USC Shoah Foundation, 1994. Accessed November 1, 2020. </p>
            <p>Jockers, Matthew L., and Ted Underwood. 2015. “Text-Mining the Humanities.” <hi
                  rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</hi>, Edited by <ref
                  target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/action/doSearch?ContribAuthorRaw=Schreibman%2C+Susan"
                  >Susan Schreibman</ref>, <ref
                  target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/action/doSearch?ContribAuthorRaw=Siemens%2C+Ray"
                  >Ray Siemens</ref>, and <ref
                  target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/action/doSearch?ContribAuthorRaw=Unsworth%2C+John"
                  >John Unsworth</ref>. John Wiley and Sons. 291–306.</p>
            <p>Jockusch, Laura. 2012. <hi rend="italic">Collect and Record! Jewish Holocaust
                  Documentation in Early Postwar Europe</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p>
            <p>Kovitzka (Kaletska), Anna. Interview with David Boder (September 26, 1946). <hi
                  rend="italic">Topical Autobiographies of Displaced People</hi>. 244-275. Also
               available on: <hi rend="italic">Voices of the Holocaust</hi>, Illinois Institute of
               Technology. <ref target="https://voices.library.iit.edu/interview/kaletskaA"
                  >https://voices.library.iit.edu/interview/kaletskaA</ref>. Accessed November 1,
               2020. </p>
            <p>Labov, William, and Joshua Waletzky. 1997. “Narrative Analysis: Oral Versions of
               Personal Experience.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Narrative &amp; Life History</hi>
               7 (1–4): 3–38.</p>
            <p>Luft, Aliza. 2015. “Toward a Dynamic Theory of Action at the Micro Level of Genocide: </p>
            <p>Killing, Desistance, and Saving in 1994 Rwanda.” Sociological Theory 33.2:
               148–72.</p>
            <p>Mausam, Michael Schmitz, Stephen Soderland, Robert Bart, and Oren Etzioni. 2012.
               “Open Language Learning for Information Extraction.” In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings
                  of the 2012 Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing
                  and Computational Natural Language Learning</hi>, 523–534. Jeju Island, Korea:
               Association for Computational Linguistics.
               https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/D12-1048.</p>
            <p>Peter, Dingley Andrew. 2001. Data replication system and method. US6304882B1, issued
               October 16, 2001.
               https://worldwide.espacenet.com/patent/search/family/009930067/publication/US2003145022A1?q=US2003145022.</p>
            <p>Presner, Todd. 2016. “The Ethics of the Algorithm: Close and Distant Listening to the
               Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive.” In <hi rend="italic">Probing the Ethics of
                  Holocaust Culture</hi>, edited by Claudio Fogu, Wulf Kansteiner, and Todd Presner,
               175–202. Harvard University Press.</p>
            <p>Rosen, Alan. 2010. <hi rend="italic">The Wonder of Their Voices: The 1946 Holocaust
                  Interviews of David Boder</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p>
            <p>Rothberg, Michael. 2019. <hi rend="italic">The Implicated Subject: Beyond Victims and
                  Perpetrators</hi>. Stanford University Press.</p>
            <p>Rusher, Jack. 2006. “Triple Store.” 2006.
               https://www.w3.org/2001/sw/Europe/events/20031113-storage/positions/rusher.html.</p>
            <p>Saldias, Belen, and Deb Roy. 2020. “Exploring Aspects of Similarity between Spoken
               Personal Narratives by Disentangling Them into Narrative Clause Types.” In <hi
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the First Joint Workshop on Narrative Understanding,
                  Storylines, and Events</hi>, 78–86. Online: Association for Computational
               Linguistics. https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.nuse-1.10.</p>
            <p>Stenetorp, Pontus, Sampo Pyysalo, Goran Topić, Tomoko Ohta, Sophia Ananiadou, and
               Jun’ichi Tsujii. "BRAT: a web-based tool for NLP-assisted text annotation." In
               Proceedings of the Demonstrations at the 13th Conference of the European Chapter of
               the Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 102-107. 2012.</p>
            <p>Swanson, Reid, Elahe Rahimtoroghi, Thomas Corcoran, and Marilyn Walker. 2014.
               “Identifying Narrative Clause Types in Personal Stories.” In <hi rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the 15th Annual Meeting of the Special Interest Group on Discourse
                  and Dialogue (SIGDIAL)</hi>, 171–180. Philadelphia, PA, U.S.A.: Association for
               Computational Linguistics. https://doi.org/10.3115/v1/W14-4323.</p>
            <p>The Apache Software Foundation. 2017. “Welcome to Apache OpenNLP.” 2017.
               http://opennlp.apache.org/.</p>
            <p>Underwood, T. 2019. <hi rend="italic">Distant Horizons: Digital Evidence and Literary
                  Change</hi>. University of Chicago Press. </p>
            <p>USC Shoah Foundation. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Indexing Guidelines</hi>. <ref
                  target="https://sfi.usc.edu/sites/default/files/docfiles/Indexing_Guidelines_0.pdf"
                  >https://sfi.usc.edu/sites/default/files/docfiles/Indexing_Guidelines_0.pdf</ref>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Voices of the Holocaust</hi>. Illinois Institute of Technology,
               Paul V. Galvin Library. <ref target="https://voices.library.iit.edu/"
                  >https://voices.library.iit.edu/</ref>. </p>
            <p>Wieviorka, Annette. 2006. <hi rend="italic">The Era of the Witness</hi>. Translated
               by Jared Stark. Cornell University Press.</p>
            <p>Wu, Fei, and Daniel S. Weld. 2010. “Open Information Extraction Using Wikipedia.” In
                  <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for
                  Computational Linguistics</hi>, 118–127. Uppsala, Sweden: Association for
               Computational Linguistics. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P10-1013.</p>
            <p>Yates, Alexander, Michele Banko, Matthew Broadhead, Michael Cafarella, Oren Etzioni,
               and Stephen Soderland. 2007. “TextRunner: Open Information Extraction on the Web.” In
                  <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Human Language Technologies: The Annual
                  Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational
                  Linguistics (NAACL-HLT)</hi>, 25–26. Rochester, New York, USA: Association for
               Computational Linguistics. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/N07-4013.</p>
            <p>Zalc, Claire, and Tal Bruttmann, eds. 2016. <hi rend="italic">Microhistories of the
                  Holocaust</hi>. Berghahn Books.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <pb/>Appendix</head>
            <div xml:id="bookmark=id.3j2qqm3">
               <head>Triplets AEO Algorithm, as an Example of High Interpretability</head>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl/>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
