<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Naming Names of Enslaved People in the Senegal Liberations Project</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Richard <dhq:family>Roberts</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7191-5836</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Stanford University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rroberts@stanford.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Richard Roberts</name> is a Frances and Charles Field Professor of History Emeritus at <name>Stanford 
                    University</name>. He has published widely on the social and legal history of French West <name>Africa</name>, 
                    and he is together with <name>Rebecca Wall</name>, <name>Rachel Jean-Baptiste</name>, and <name>Babacar Fall</name> 
                    one of the co-director of the Senegal Liberations Project.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Rebecca <dhq:family>Wall</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7048-8134</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Loyola Marymount University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rebecca.wall@lmu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Rebecca Wall</name> is an assistant professor of History at <name>Loyola Marymount University</name> in 
                     <name>Los Angeles</name>. She has published articles on the environmental and political history of French West 
                     <name>Africa</name> and is completing a book on the twentieth-century history <name>Senegal River</name>. 
                     She is co-director of the Senegal Liberations Project together with <name>Rachel Jean-Baptiste</name>, 
                     <name>Babacar Fall</name>, and <name>Richard Roberts</name>.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000769</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#ethics"/>
               <term corresp="#dh"/>
               <term corresp="#social_justice"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>slavery</item>
                  <item>liberation</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000769/000769.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Enslavement is linked to enduring and systemic inequalities, hierarchies, and to the erasures of enslaved people's 
               historiesl, including their names. Such erasures meant and continue to mean different things to different populations 
               of formerly enslaved people. Descendants of enslaved people, especially in the diaspora, turned to well-established 
               means of genealogical research and new forms of DNA research to trace their ancestors. However, in West 
               <name>Africa</name> and in other parts of the world where obvious racialized markers do not automatically hint at an 
               enslaved ancestor, many former enslaved people <quote rend="inline">would rather forget</quote> their enslaved past or 
               that of their ancestors, precisely because descent from enslaved ancestry remains stigmatized. Ethical considerations 
               of conducting digital historical research on slavery and emancipation have been hotly discussed for a number of years, 
               and given the public-facing character of many of these digital projects, the stakes of naming versus anonymity are high. 
               This article suggests a way forward for those people recorded in the Registers of Liberation in colonial 
               <name>Senegal</name>.
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Given the prevailing stigma and potential violence against people of slave descent in West <name>Africa</name>, 
               what are scholars' ethical and political responsibilities in using the names of enslaved people who actively sought 
               their liberation at the hands of French colonial officials during the second half of the nineteenth century in public 
               facing digital humanities projects?
            </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Digital humanities projects have great potential to promote social justice and address inequities. Indeed, a key element of the digital humanities' ability to further social justice is its often public-facing character. Making information visible to a broad audience, typically via web-based projects, is a major factor in rendering untold or under-told stories visible and inspiring people beyond academic confines to seek a more just future. This is particularly true for projects which deal with historical injustices and the experiences of marginalized, silenced, and subjugated groups, such as enslaved or formerly enslaved individuals. A number of recent projects fit this paradigm, with initiatives focusing on the experiences of enslaved people throughout the world and during different historical eras leading the way in terms of availability, richness of data, and research output. The first and most significant digital project on enslavement is the Slave Voyages Database (Borucki et al.). Other major projects include Liberated Africans (Chadha and Lovejoy, H.),“Fugitives from Slavery in Jamaica” (Wood and Smith 2021), “Slave Societies Digital Archive” (Landers et al.), and “Freedom on the Move” (Baptist). The Peoples of the Historical Slave Trade Website (Rehberger et al.) is an ongoing initiative to consolidate the numerous and expanding projects on this topic. </p>
            <p>At the same time, the visibility of digital humanities projects poses ethical challenges. All researchers bear ethical responsibility toward their subjects, whether formalized through institutional frameworks like Institutional Review Board (IRB) protocols or as an often-unstated backdrop or rarely articulated to their research methods and production. The stakes are arguably higher for projects that are published online, and thus readily available to a global audience, because ethical missteps or inattention to the possible harms to research subjects have the potential to reverberate across the web and deep into effected communities. Consequently, digital humanities scholars have in recent years articulated ethical frameworks to guide research and publication, including data presentation and visualization (Saagsma 2023; Thykstrup 2022; Profess 2021; Hepworth and Church 2018). However, in some cases clear-cut best practices prove elusive. This is especially true for projects that discuss controversial topics or center historically marginalized communities, such as enslaved or formerly enslaved people, the subject of the Senegal Liberations Project.</p>
            <p>Slavery and enslavement always involved physical and social violence. It contributed to enduring and systemic inequalities, hierarchies, and the erasure of enslaved people's histories including their names. Such erasures meant, and continue to mean, different things to different populations of formerly enslaved people and their descendants. In many contexts, the violence of enslavement and various mechanisms of renaming rendered formerly enslaved people without history. The particular histories of enslavement hold ramifications for how descendants of enslaved people view this issue because the end of slavery did not end these forms of inequality and discrimination. In the Americas, the racialization of status persisted after emancipation resulting in new forms of struggle and resistance. Descendants of formerly enslaved people especially in the diaspora turned to well-established means of genealogical research and new forms of DNA research to trace their ancestors. For this group, recovering their “names” and their origins are important as the trauma of the Middle Passage occluded their heritage. However, in West Africa and in other parts of the world where obvious racialized markers do not automatically hint at an enslaved ancestor, many former enslaved “would rather forget” their enslaved past or that of their ancestors precisely because descent from enslaved ancestry remains stigmatized.</p>
            <p>Such questions of naming and anonymity extend to contemporary research. Ethical considerations of conducting digital historical research on slavery and emancipation have been hotly discussed for a number of years (Odumosu 2020; Dalgeish 2011; Martina 2014). Given the public-facing character of many of these digital projects, the stakes of naming versus anonymity are high. While digital projects on enslavement can promote public engagement with historical injustices, scholarly research, and pedagogical innovations, they also risk re-dehumanizing enslaved individuals and their ancestors. Jessica Johnson challenges us to introduce social justice and ethics into digital enslaved studies in ways that “mark their humanity” through efforts to provide a “window into the everyday lives of Africans, who remained faceless, anonymous, disembodied. (Johnson 2018). Using digital research to reclaim the humanity of enslaved individuals through tracing their origins and identities has emerged as an important frontier in this work. However, issues of naming versus anonymity for people descended from enslaved populations within Africa merit further consideration given the different attitudes toward enslaved ancestry, raising significant issues regarding the ethics of naming the names of enslaved people. This article suggests a way forward for those people recorded in the Registers of Liberation in colonial Senegal, the topic of the Senegal Liberations Project.</p>
            <p>We approach our project as a case study to address how we arrived at a determination about a question with major ethical ramifications: whether or not to include the names of enslaved individuals who obtained liberation on a publicly available website. Although this may seem like a simple question, reaching a decision about what to do required discussions between scholars and stakeholders in Senegal, Europe, and North America, as well as reflections on our responsibility to both the people whose lives are recorded in historical sources and their descendants. We also drew on ethical guidelines that similar research initiatives have developed (“Statement of Ethics,” <hi rend="italic">Enslaved: Peoples of the Historical Slave Trade</hi>; Agostinho 2019; Johnson 2018). After much debate, reflections, and further research in these sources, we ultimately decided to include names on the SLP website. How we arrived at this decision requires discussion of the history of enslavement in West Africa and a deep dive into our sources. Our case study of the ethics of naming versus anonymity will hopefully be of use not only to other scholars of enslavement and liberation, but more broadly digital humanities researchers working on public-facing projects utilizing ethnically complex sources.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The Registers of Liberation in Colonial Senegal and the Senegal Liberations Project</head>
            <p>These were the political and ethical concerns we had when we began the process of mining the French colonial registers of liberation in Senegal from 1857 to 1903, which recorded the enslaved Africans who sought their liberation by presenting themselves before French colonial officials. France had decreed the abolition of slavery throughout its empire on 27 April 1848. Article 7 of that decree stated that “The principle that the soil of France frees the slave who touches it is applied in colonies and possessions of the Republic” (French Republic 1848). In 1848, the enslaved people in the two tiny towns that constituted the French colony of Senegal (Gorée and Saint-Louis) were freed, but not all left their owners who were mostly African and <hi rend="italic">métis </hi>inhabitants of these towns (Guèye 1965; Klein 1998;  Getz 2004;  Westland 2022). Enslaved people from neighboring African communities and polities began streaming into these colonial towns seeking their liberation. Due to commercial and political considerations that threatened the viability of the colony, Governor Faidherbe in 1855 decreed that the 1848 abolition applied only to French citizens, not subjects of the French empire, and that enslaved people fleeing to French territory from friendly African polities were to be considered vagabonds and expelled. Fugitive enslaved peoples from African polities fighting against the French would be welcomed subject to a waiting period and subject to a redemption fee. Many of those entering the process were enslaved minors, who were subsequently entrusted to named adults for whom the minors continued to work until they turned 18 (Moitt 2024). To keep track of the process, Faidherbe introduced the registers of liberation in 1857 (Faidherbe 1857). </p>
            <p>At the outset, the liberations were recorded in handwritten ledgers consisting of nine columns: a number in order of liberation, the date, the name of the person making the declaration to the colonial official (often the enslaved person or their owner, who was seeking the redemption fee), the name of the enslaved period and his or her place of origin, his or her age, the destination where the liberated individual would live, names of the individual with whom the liberated individual would live, and signatures of the declarant. In 1875, the ledgers changed and so did the flow of enslaved people seeking liberation. Political conflicts within and between African polities contributed to the increase in enslaved people leaving their owners. This process accelerated further after 1883. Pre-printed forms began to be used and the content of the columns changed. Eight columns now included the number in order of liberation, date of liberation, the profession of the declarant (who was now mostly the colonial official), the name and place of birth of the liberated individual, his or her age, the names of the liberated person's father and mother if known, the name and profession of the guardian to whom the liberated individual was conferred if that individual was an unaccompanied minor, and the signature of the declarant. By 1883, the French colonial officials abolished all restrictions on offering liberation and those seeking liberation were offered freedom certificates the same day they applied (Renault 1972, p. 37). Most of the enslaved people seeking liberation from this period forward were those fleeing their owners from elsewhere in Senegal. </p>
            <p>Overall, the registers consist of twenty handwritten ledgers from 1857-1903 and record around 28,421 cases of enslaved people in colonial Senegal seeking to obtain from French officials legal documentation of their liberation. The registers are held in the National Archives of Senegal. With permission of the archives, Stanford University acquired a microfilm of the registers, which sat unused until 2018, when we launched the Senegal Liberations Project. Again, with permission from the National Archives of Senegal, we digitized the microfilm images in order to be able to enhance them for research. We also returned a copy of the digital images to the archives in Senegal, which serves as a form of data preservation since the original registers are deteriorating. </p>
            <figure>
              <head></head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png" style="width: 800px"/>
            </figure>
            <p>That same year we began entering the liberation data into Excel sheets reflecting the information in the pre-printed columns in which most of the liberations were recorded with the goal of building a public facing website in order to make available this fascinating source to a wider audience in Senegal and throughout the world. </p>
            <p>At the beginning of our data entry, we were concerned about the enduring stigma of enslaved descent in Senegal and whether to include the names of the enslaved people seeking their liberation because having enslaved ancestors continues to carry social stigma in West Africa, and many whose ancestors were enslaved prefer to keep this past hidden. We consulted with Senegalese colleagues and scholars, who were mostly urban-based and who were less concerned with this issue than we were. Nonetheless, we proceeded with data entry without naming the names of the liberated individuals moving from the most recent records backwards in part because the ledgers were in better shape and because the handwriting was more legible. Our initial goal was to identify quantitative trends in the evidence of liberation, which resulted in a preliminary analysis of 10,000 cases of liberation from 1895-1904 (Goodwin et al. 2021). Our initial results demonstrated significant agency on the part of the enslaved people who most often strategically fled their owners during the slow period of the agricultural cycle in order to arrive at their liberation destination in time to begin planting crops for their own subsistence. A central task of digital humanities is to visualize data in order to make intelligible trends and patterns to a wider audience. Even though these quantitative trends demonstrated human agency, they still did not capture the individual lived experiences of the enslaved as they sought their liberation and thus did not fully capture the challenge laid out by Jessica Johnson and others to better “mark their humanity.”  This realization brought us to the following reflections on the politics and ethics of naming names in public facing digital humanities projects. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Places: To Stay or To Leave</head>
            <p>There is no easy answer to the simple question: to name or not to name? Answering this in an ethical and responsible way requires careful consideration of the historical specificity of enslavement and liberation in Senegal and the wider region of French West Africa. The end of slavery always takes place in places. These places were almost always deeply saturated by power asymmetries and social hierarchies as well as resistance to them. Even in decentralized societies where hierarchies were thinly structured, power emanating from more centralized polities nearby shaped status and slavery within those societies. The end of slavery did not mean the end of these power asymmetries or hierarchies; they may have shifted slightly to adapt to the changed circumstances, but absent radical ruptures, they persisted and imposed significant limits on the meanings of the end of slavey to the formerly enslaved (Miers and Roberts 1988; Lovejoy and Hogendorn 1993; Klein 1998). The FulBe of central Mali use the metaphor of the rope to indicate how in post-slavery societies persistent cultures of hierarchy, the stigma of slave descent, and poverty limited the social mobility of formerly enslaved people who remained bound to the former masters. To be bound to a former master is also to remain within a network of reciprocity and subsistence security. To remain within the rope requires the retention of the stigma of the enslaved descent and to be known as such. “To cut the rope” in contrast is to separate from the place where the former masters' power persists, to risk subsistence security, and embrace precarity, at least temporarily or until a new set of ropes were established (Pelckmans 2011, p. 6-32; Bellagamba 2009, p. 69).<note>1 The “rope of slavery” has also become a metaphor for colonial and postcolonial elite oppression in the People's Progressive Party in the Gambia (Bellagamba 2009, p. 69)</note>1  </p>
            <p>Most population centers in Senegal, Mali, and Mauritania in the middle to end of the nineteenth century were relatively small. The majority of people lived in villages and hamlets; urban-like agglomerations that served as central places or seats of political or religious authority were few and most had a seasonal quality during which they swelled a bit during the dry season and shrunk again during the rainy season when most people turned to farming or led their herds to green pastures. French colonial outposts like Saint Louis developed urban attributes fueled by an expansion in commerce requiring a built infrastructure and a labor force of both skilled and unskilled workers many of whom were enslaved (Klein 1998, pp. 21-25; Searing 1993, ch 3). During the second half of the nineteenth century, colonial urban spaces expanded in number and scale. Still, most people lived in villages where social stratification consisted largely of endogamous social categories: free people who could be poor or wealthy; casted groups of those who controlled skills such as ironwork, praise singing, and leatherwork; and enslaved people who consisted of the newly enslaved and those born into the house. In the West African savannah, ethnic groups often identified themselves by economic and cultural boundaries, although there was movement across these ethnic boundaries. The second half of the nineteenth century also witnessed the rise of several warrior states and militant Islamic revival movements that fueled the expansion of enslavement and the supply of new slaves (Klein 1989, pp. 209-17; Roberts 1987). The influx of newly enslaved people into villages and emerging urban spaces certainly contributed to sharpening power asymmetries and cultures of hierarchy, which in turn may have led to hardening boundaries surrounding social stratification. Militant Islamic revival contributed to social stratification by dividing communities into believers and non-believers and into those who were legally considered Muslims and those considered only partially so. </p>
            <p>The influx of significant numbers of newly enslaved into many West African societies during this period likely sharpened social stratification through endogamy — the rules and practices surrounding who can marry whom.  “Endogamic marriage,” Alice Bellagamba reminds us, “ensures that moral, social, and material resources will circulate among people who are already related in one way or another” (Bellagamba 2020, pp. 159-60). Endogamy also contributed to the owners' ideology of “purity of blood” that according to Ibrahima Thioub contributed to the persistence of the stigma of inferiority among slaves and their descendants in societies where owners and enslaved shared the same “chromaticity (Thioub 2015).” While owners had powers of sexual access over their enslaved women, marriages were restricted between free and enslaved. Concubinage was widely practiced among Muslims allowing owners to manumit their female concubines upon the birth of a child if the owner chose to recognize his child. Such endogamy persists to this day in villages and town, which contributes to the enduring stigma of enslaved descent (Bellagamba 2020; Pelckmans 2011). As Paul Irwin notes for the villages surrounding Liptako, a primarily FulBe historical region that contains modern day eastern Burkina Faso, southwest Niger, and southeastern Mali, “a social calculus based on kinship requires people to know their genealogies” and “genealogies are so inextricably bound up with notions of personal identity that no one neglects them entirely” (Irwin 1981, p. 43, p. 20). The very nature of enslavement involves the rupture of genealogical continuities, which renders them “truncated. (Rodet 2010). A truncated genealogy is thus a legacy of enslavement. </p>
            <p>In many ways, slave descent even long past the end of slavery remains central to social standing and expected behavior in communities where everyone knows everybody. Slave descent is as Michael Taussig notes a “public secret” which is simultaneously “revealing and concealing (Taussig 1999, p. 16).” As such, a public secret entails “knowing and not knowing” predicated around the power and the obligation to keep the secret (Taussig 1999, p. 2; Rossi 2009, p. 10). Anthony Appiah describes his encounter with such a public secret.</p>
            <p>Once, when I was a child, I asked my father, in a room full of people, how we were related to a woman whom I knew and liked, who lived in one of the family houses. I thought of her, in fact, as one of my “aunts.”  My father brushed the question angrily aside. Only later, when we were alone, did he say that one should never inquire after people's ancestry in public. She was, as it turned out, the descendant of a family slave. Everybody in the family knew this, and that meant that she was of lower status than the rest of us. As children, we were required to be courteous to all adults, even those of lower status. But that didn't mean they weren't inferior (Appiah 2007, p. 253). </p>
            <p>For those of us who study slavery and its legacies in Africa, the core questions are as Martin Klein poses it: why, given the persistence of inferior social status, do former slaves remain and why do they continue to accept even minimal obligations of deference and subjugation (Klein 2006, p. 279)? And second, what are our obligations to the public secret of an individual's slave descent? Such questions are relevant throughout West Africa.</p>
            <p>The enslaved people seeking their freedom in the Senegal Liberations Project have specificity rooted in the sources' provenance in France's nascent West African Empire. Although the French had abolished slavery in its territories in 1848, French antislavery policy was largely subordinated to political expediency during the conquest phase. By 1898, the French had pursued conquest aggressively and while small-scale enslavement and the slave trade persisted, largescale enslavement had ended with the military victory over the warriors states led by Amadu Tal, Samori Ture, and BaBemba. During the conquest phase, the French had not only tolerated slavery but returned runaway slaves to owners in polities that remained allied to them. In 1903, the French decreed a new colonial legal system which did not recognize the legal category of the slave and thus owners could not turn to the colonial state to enforce their rights over their enslaved people. In effect, it “delegalized” slavery without abolishing it (Rossi 2024, p. 2, fn 2). In 1905, following the expansion of the slave exodus, the French decreed the prohibition of new enslavement. These two decrees effectively ended the legal status of slavery. But it did not end slavery or its legacies (Klein 1998; Roberts 2005, ch 4; Lawrance and Roberts 2012).</p>
            <p>Klein has argued that around one million enslaved people in French West Africa left their masters in an exodus that started around 1896 and accelerated after 1905 (Klein 1998). Klein also estimates that those who left their masters constituted only around one-third of the total number of enslaved people in this region. Not all of the remaining two-third (or two million enslaved people) remained with their owners; we do know that some not insignificant number separated from their former owners and formed new communities, sometimes nearby (Roberts 1988; Rodet 2015; Rodet 2019). But clearly a significant number of enslaved people remained with their former owners.  </p>
            <p>Examining these general statistics regarding the proportion of enslaved people who remained with their former masters, Igor Kopytoff argued that those who left were the most marginalized of the enslaved population, the least integrated into their owners communities and cultures, and most likely the more recently acquired. African slavery, in Kopytoff's view, was a system that was predicated on the progressive integration of enslaved people to the point where the enslaved would no longer be recognizable as such. In the Kopytoff system, enslaved people were eager for integration and belonging in their owners' societies even at the expense of some residual discrimination. Kopytoff's view of the end of slavery was one of a stark dichotomy between belonging and separation with no space for resistance and renegotiation (Kopytoff 1988). While Kopytoff may have minimized the options available to enslaved people, we have come to appreciate more fully the risks involved in leaving even an exploitative relationship which offers some promise of subsistence security for an uncertain future. </p>
            <p>The promise of subsistence security does not quite resolve the problem of how to explain why some who have left returned to their former owners' communities sometimes periodically and sometimes after decades away and after having secured significant alternative subsistence security. Lotte Pelckmans describes the case of Maman Abidjan, a descendant of an enslaved person, who left the village of Dalla and spent nearly four decades in the capital city of the Cote d'Ivoire, where she changed her identity to be part of a casted group, achieved a relative degree of security, and built a social network. Why then did she return to Dalla and why did she accept the subtle but persistent reminders of her subordinate status (Pelckmans 2011, p. 122, p. 155)?  </p>
            <p>Anthropologists have long been intrigued by the pattern of remittances and regular return visits to their natal villages by young male labor migrants. Claude Meillassoux has argued that lineage and household elders who remained in their home villages exerted significant control over matrimonial goods and the pool of brides thus effectively controlling marriage eligibility. Without access to matrimonial goods, young men could not properly marry and thus could not become elders within the ideological context still enforced by the elders. To access elderhood and thus gain access to established modes of subsistence security through remittances from their own sons, young men had little choice but to remit their earnings to elders in order to gain access to the material benefits of elderhood (Meillassoux 1981). Building on Meillassoux's materialist argument, Charles Piot explores why long-term migrants in southern Togo periodically returned to their natal villages in the north bringing money, consumer goods, and building materials even though many of these migrants had settled in the south, built their own networks, and established families there. Piot discovered that these long-term migrants were drawn back home to participate in annual rituals precisely because such participation provided them with means to renew their belongingness to their natal communities and provided their children with a sense of historical continuities (Piot 1999). But as James Ferguson reminds us, even those long-term migrants who settled in cities and mines and found security in stabilized work and pensions, could find themselves confronting insecurity during financial and political crises. By investing in their home villages, these modern workers retained a measure of subsistence security and cultural belonging (Ferguson 1999). Leaving with the intention of returning or leaving and periodically returning served to maintain connections, status, and belongingness.</p>
            <p>Leaving without the intention of returning involved ruptures. Leaving put subsistence security at risk, sometimes for an indefinite period. Despite this, enslaved people did leave. Those who remembered their natal homes were inclined to leave; those whose lives grated against discrimination and diminished personhood of enslaved status, and those who wanted to establish households that they could control may also have left. Some left in groups and others individually. Some left spontaneously while others planned their departures to coincide with the agricultural calendar, seeking to minimize subsistence insecurity by departing just after the harvest was in and before the new planting season began in the expectation of arriving at a new place in time to resume farming (Goodwin et al. 2021, figure 7). Making their way home or finding a new place to live almost always involved negotiating with chiefs and kin for access to land and entering into new forms of dependency. Enslaved people who left most likely calculated these costs and benefits and saw that moving was in their interests. Marie Rodet describes the challenges facing a group of enslaved people who left en masse from their owners only to find themselves struggling against hostility from neighboring villages and drought before they were able to establish new villages (Rodet 2018). </p>
            <p>We know relatively little about the planning that went into leaving, but certainly knowledge of political and economic conditions circulated among enslaved populations. This may have helped in deciding the direction of departure. Tapping into whatever kind of networks existed may also have helped enslaved people navigate their departures. Knowledge of destinations and knowledge of potential hosts in those destinations contributed to decisions to leave and facilitated integration into the new places. In the expanding peanut zone of Senegambia, hosts welcomed migrants and enslaved people and entered them into forms of dependency involving exchanges of labor or shares of the harvest in exchange for access to land and subsistence security. This was the well-established patterns of the stranger farmer or navetanne system in the peanut zone (Klein 1998, ch 12; Swindell 2006;  Moitt 1989). Formerly enslaved people may have found themselves in new dependency relationships that resembled slavery. Some may also have suffered from status discrimination (Bellagamba 2009; Bellagamba 2020). In other regions, formerly enslaved people could take new names, new identities, and eventually merge with the “free” peasant communities in which they were living (Klein 1998, ch 12-14). </p>
            <p>Enslaved people could also join the proliferating number of Islamic communities that welcomed newcomers regardless of their status. Some of the communities promised access to land, subsistence, and learning while others promised an emancipatory environment in which goods were shared and bridewealth prohibited. This stood in stark contrast to the mosques of their owners where enslaved people and their descendants were unwelcome (Hanretta 2009; Pelckmans 2011; O'Brian 1975; Babou 2007; Searing 2002). </p>
            <p>Hosts played important roles in migration to urban centers and other places where navigating the often-challenging housing and labor markets required significant help. Locating an urban host often meant tapping into existing diasporic networks that linked urban centers with rural villages. As Pelckmans described for migrants to Bamako, many of these hosts reproduced the cultural hierarchies from the rural villages preventing migrants from easily escaping established forms of dependency and discrimination (Pelckmans 2011). </p>
            <p>Nonetheless, leaving provided formerly enslaved people with the possibility of getting “lost” (Pelckmans 2011, p. 249). Getting lost meant complete rupture with their former dependencies and the opportunities to establish new identities and new networks. Social costs of such ruptures were considerable, but moving to new areas, founding new villages or settling into new urban neighborhoods provided the opportunity to invent new identities even if they may have been fictitious. New identities often involved new names. In such cases, taking on a new name was not a dehumanizing erasure, but part of their claims of fuller social acceptance. The Registers of Liberation provide an important prequel to the better documented slaves' exodus of 1905 by documenting the ebbs and flows of enslaved people actively seeking their liberty in the fifty years prior to the exodus. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Whose Name?</head>
            <p>The meanings of naming and renaming vary from place to place and from context to context. Naming and renaming also reflect the violence and power asymmetries inherent in enslavement and slavery. The American historian Drew Gilpin Faust describes the multiple meanings embedded in ledgers kept by owners of slaves. </p>
            <p>But sometimes handwritten documents tell stories that their creators neither intended nor understood. James Henry Hammond maintained a ledge in which he kept scrawled records of the births and deaths of the enslaved population on his South Carolina plantation. Because he included the names of newborns' parents and often some additional commentary, it was possible for me to reconstruct family ties among generations of people forbidden to keep their own written history. At one point, Hammond purchased an 8-year-old boy named Sam Jones to work in the house, changing his name to “Wesley” in the process. Nearly three decades later, Hammond recorded the birth of a son to Wesley –a child to whom Wesley had given the name “Sam Jones.”  As he recorded the baby's birth, Hammond was in all likelihood unaware of Sam/Wesley's act of memory and resistance (Gilpin Faust 2022, p. 76). </p>
            <p>Equiano recounts how one of his owners gave him the name Gustavus Vassa. Equiano used both names –Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa- as the author of his <hi rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, Or Gustavus Vassa, The African</hi>, first published in 1789. The use of both names stimulated a lively debate regarding the author's birth, his identity, and the authenticity of the narrative (Carretta 2005; Lovejoy, P. 2006). This debate led to a reassessment of the fixedness of names and identities in the Atlantic world during the early modern period. Drawing from his study of Domingues Alvares, James Sweet argues that “the Atlantic represented a series of social deaths and rebirths, a repeating circuit of dislocation and dismemberment, marked by an unceasing desire to reconstitute the self through family, friends, and community. His was a history without end, quite literally a feedback loop of subjection and social subjectivities”(Sweet 2009, p. 304). Far from being fixed and indelible, identities and names were “overlapping, shifting, and situational….” (Sweet 2009, p. 298).</p>
            <p>Enslaved people who remained in Africa but were moved from where they were enslaved to where they were settled suffered similar social deaths and rebirths as their counterparts in the Atlantic world. Enslavement in any form was violent; it ruptured connections with kin and community. And it also ruptured genealogy. In the absence of robust research on naming practices in African societies, most of the evidence we have is drawn from the colonial period or ethnographic research in the recent past shaped by all the distortions those sources produce. On top of the physical violence of capture, owners subjected their newly acquired slaves to the symbolic violence of renaming. Pelckmans notes that renaming the newly enslaved was a central part of asserting domination; it was part of their efforts to “erase the previous identity of their slaves…. The renaming of captured people consisted of the imposition of a completely new, often degrading identity…. Slave names were thus often a source of shame in contrast to the names of the freeborn, which invoked a freeborn status and honorable condition” (Pelckmans 2017, pp. 257-58). Gregory Mann suggests that newly acquired slaves did not lose their patronyms (<hi rend="italic">jamuw</hi>), which represents “an all-important identity marker” that is linked to genealogical history and myth. In contrast, enslaved people born into their owner's community (<hi rend="italic">wolosow</hi>) were often given the patronym of their owner, which signified “integration” into the owner's household (Mann 2002, p. 308-12). Different naming practices for enslaved people certainly prevailed throughout Africa, but both Pelckmans and Mann recognize the power of the owner to name or rename their enslaved people. Both also recognize the power of owners to name the children of enslaved people. According to Pelckmans, enslaved women lacked a “legal husband” and therefore could not give the patronym of the father to her children (Pelckmans 2011, p. 262; Klein 1989, p. 213). </p>
            <p>Mann's larger argument, however, focused on the discrepancies between local practices of naming and renaming and the introduction of colonial bureaucracies in which registers of names for taxation and military recruitment assumed greater permanence of names. As Mann argues, changes in family names were “extremely common under colonial rule, particularly among soldiers” precisely because so many military recruits were drawn from the former enslaved population that remained near their former owners. Former owners and village chiefs were complicit in this process whereby former slaves assumed the patronym of their former owner and thus substituted for their former owner's sons in the recruitment process. Former slaves also drew from a wider array of patronyms. Mann refers to this practice as assuming “names of convenience” (Mann 2002, p. 39). </p>
            <p>Maintaining registers of names for taxation and recruitment was central to the instruments of governmentality, which formed a core component of making legible to the state local populations. As James Scott and his colleagues argue, “In the case of colonial rule, when the conquerors speak an entirely different language, the unintelligibility of the vernacular landscape is a nearly insurmountable obstacle to effective rule. Renaming much of the landscape therefore is an essential step of imperial rule…. Like place names, permanent surnames help to chart the human topography of any region” (Scott et al. 2002, pp. 6-7). However, the process of inventing surnames and rendering them legible and indelible by including them in official ledgers was messy. The process relied on literate clerks few of whom were trained in the variety of indigenous and local languages and on pressures of time to process individuals into these ledgers expeditiously. </p>
            <p>Two aspects of this messy process merged when recording evidence of enslaved people in the Registers of Liberation. First, clerks who did not necessarily know or understand local languages transcribed what they heard into names that they could more easily recognize (Clark 2015). Clerks may have drawn upon a limited pool of surnames that may have had some tonal kinship with the name presented by the individual supplicant. Oscar Moráguez captures well some of these issues in his discussion of the African origins of slaves imported into Cuba. “Planters, lawyers, colonial authorities, and notaries generated lists and descriptions of slaves –for parish records, property records of individual estates, marriages, baptisms, runaway notices, bills of slave slaves, and the like — many of which identified African-born slaves by geographic or linguistic criteria or by imputed nationality. The people who compiled these lists recognized cultural variants, but they did not know much about Africa itself….”  Instead, these clerks “automatically labeled” individuals as belonging to groups just because of where in Africa they embarked on slave ships (Moróguez 2008, pp. 176-77;  Miesevich 2008, p. 156).<note>2 Philip Misevich argues that the names recorded in the ledgers of the liberated slaves in Havana were reliable. “Prior to their liberation, the Africans were asked to provide information about themselves that was recorded by colonial officials in ledger books. Each page of these books was divided into seven columns and each ‘recaptive' was given one line on the page. The details recorded by the officials included a unique identity number, name, sex (man, woman, girl, or boy), age, height, and a description of any distinctive body markings. In the case of the Sierra Leone and Havana courts, where the large majority of vessels were tried, an additional column for ‘Country of Origin' was included, although the Sierra Leone officials eventually discontinued this practice. In addition, the registers clearly indicate that this information was provided through an African translator who was previously freed by the courts, and who came from the same region as the slaves on board the vessel under adjudication, thus partially mitigating the normally severe linguistic barriers that existed between European officials and African captives. To my knowledge, the registers represent the earliest extant list of indigenous African names.”</note>2 In his study of the Havana registers of Liberated Africans, Henry Lovejoy argues that most African languages were phonetic and what names clerks entered into the registers reflected the tonal structures of their own native languages (Lovejoy, H. 2010).</p>
            <p>The second aspect builds on the established practices of enslaved people to rename themselves or be renamed. Taking the opportunity of redefining oneself at the moment of being recorded in ledgers, enslaved and formerly enslaved people could present themselves as having whatever surname they wished. As Pelckmans notes, “Slaves and their descendants have been most concerned to change their surnames,” which then become “tickets to social mobility” (Pelckmans 2017, p. 267, p. 277). Thus, the initiative of the enslaved to rename themselves in order to potentially disguise their enslaved origins and the often-sloppy practices of actually recording names in official ledgers means that we do not really know if the names being recorded were “authentic” or invented. This process thus resulted in what Scott refers to paradoxically as “rampant name pluralism” (Scott et al. 2002, p. 29). How do places and practices of naming and renaming, as well as the “authenticity” of recorded names, influence whether we should include names of enslaved people in our research?</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Naming Names and the Paths to Freedom</head>
            <p>The ethical and political dimensions regarding naming the names of enslaved people are also shaped by the means through which they achieved their liberation. We can identify four broad paths to freedom: 1) owners offered manumission to individual enslaved people; 2) states mandated abolition through a decree that formally ended enslavement;  3) naval squadrons and subsequently international courts liberated enslaved people on ships, imposing treaties that prohibited the slave trade and placed enslaved people apprenticeships for some length of time;  and 4) enslaved people sought their own freedom through self-purchase, through the courts, or by fleeing to spaces where they could not be found by their enslavers or where slavery was outlawed.  Each of these paths have implications for the status of formerly enslaved people and on the wider political, cultural, and social environment in which the paths took place. These different pathways to freedom also have implications for our discussion about the ethical and political issues regarding whether to name the freed people or not. As we argue, those enslaved people in the Senegal Liberations project actively sought their own freedom, which involved securing a certificate of liberty in their name from French colonial officials. Their agency in this regard is essential to how we resolved the ethical and political concerns for this project.</p>
            <p>Manumission was an individual act by owners that freed one or several enslaved people. Owners manumitted slaves for a variety of reasons, but manumission always reinforced the power of owners over their enslaved people precisely because owners chose this option. Manumission carried with it a sense of benevolence that also served the owner's interests. The promise of manumission may have encouraged enslaved people to remain with their owners rather than run away or rebel;  this promise of manumission may have eased the trauma of sexual violence against enslaved females in the expectation that they could be freed if they gave birth to their owner's child;  manumitting an old enslaved person may have been couched in terms of benevolence, but it also limited the owner's responsibilities to the freed person as that person's capacity to work diminished. Unless they moved away manumitted people likely retained some dependency vis-à-vis their former owners. </p>
            <p>The abolition of slavery was a result of a state decree and most often the result of a long and contested struggle to end slavery. Although always a state decree, the mechanisms of abolition and the conditions established differed considerably. British abolition in its crown colonies involved a mandated period of apprenticeship as a transition from slavery to freedom, although individual owners and enslaved people could negotiate shorter periods. In other regions of the British empire, abolition involved a state decree, but often framed to provide an even longer gradual end to slavery. Enslaved people were not freed, but those born after a certain date were no longer considered enslaved, and new enslavement was prohibited. The meanings of freedom, however, were constrained in some parts of the empire by the coinciding British policy of importing indentured laborers (Northrup 1995: Connolly 2024). Except for minors, French abolition of 1848 did not mandate a period of apprenticeship but applied abolition only to physical spaces considered French soil, leaving considerable latitude to colonial governors to define these borders (Klein 1998; Getz 2004; Duke Bryant 2019; Moitt 2024). In those colonial regions considered protectorates, French abolition was indirect: in French West Africa, the French abolished the legal category of slave (“delegalization”), thus preventing owners from using colonial courts to control their enslaved people in 1903 and in 1905 prohibited new enslavement. In Portuguese Africa, a royal decree in 1854 declared Portugal's intention to emancipate slaves in its empire, although gradually. The first stage required owners to register their slaves and failure to do so rendered them into <hi rend="italic">libertos</hi> (free person), who still had to work for their owners. Additional decrees over the next twenty years changed the legal status of enslaved people and libertos, but as Daniel Domingues and Edward Alpers argue, “that for most individuals … there was apparently little difference between what they had experienced as slaves” (da Silva and Alpers 2021, p. 389; Cooper, Holt, and Scott 2000). </p>
            <p>As part of the broader global (but largely British) effort to end the slave trade, European nations after the Napoleonic Wars entered treaties allowing the search and seizure of ships carrying enslaved people. Already in 1808, the British had established a Royal Navy West Africa Squadron to patrol the coast in order to put teeth into the 1807 Parliamentary Act to Abolish the Slave Trade. Seized slave ships were directed to the courts of the Vice Admiralty and later to Mixed Commission Courts, which adjudicated the case. If the evidence proved prohibited activities, the ship was seized and sold, and the enslaved people liberated. Many of the liberated Africans found themselves in apprenticeship conditions for varying periods of time (Martinez 2012; Bethell 1966; Pearson 2016; Chadha and Lovejoy, H.; Anderson 2020). By far the largest and best analyzed of these registers was kept at Freetown, Sierra Leone. The Freetown register of liberated Africans contains selected details from 81,745 Africans landed in Freetown from 1808 to 1863 (Anderson 2020;  Miesevich 2019). It is important to remember that through their actions on the seas and in courts, Europeans liberated the enslaved Africans referred to as Liberated Africans. </p>
            <p>Through the fourth path, enslaved people sought their own freedom through self-purchase, through the courts, or by fleeing to spaces where slavery was outlawed.  Free or freed people falsely enslaved had recourse to courts if they knew how to access these courts and had the evidence necessary to prove their status (Candido 2016). Some societies provided enslaved people with the options to liberate themselves through self-purchase, usually for a sum equivalent to the cost of a young, productive enslaved person. In 1880s Cuba, a gradual end of slavery was decreed and enslaved people found themselves in the slave-like condition of <hi rend="italic">patrocinada, </hi>which like British apprenticeship gradually ended and placed the relationship under the scrutiny of a new institution controlled largely by owners and wealthy businessmen,  Even though the 1880 law set the date for the formal end of enslavement, Rebecca Scott writes that “the unusual effort made my <hi rend="italic">patrocinados</hi> to achieve their freedom through indemnification of services suggests that the act of self-purchase has a particular importance for the man or woman who could achieve it” (Scott, R. 2000, pp. 153-54). The slow death for slavery in Northern Nigeria rested in part on enlarging the pathway for self-redemption, by outlawing new enslavement, and by declaring free all children born to enslaved mothers freed as of 1 March 1901 (Lovejoy and Hogendorn 1993). Even in post-slavery societies, where slavery is no longer a legally recognized institution, some formerly enslaved people chose to redeem themselves because this act imparted a new level of respectability. Elisabeth McMahon reminds us that in in Islamic societies, former enslaved people “had the possibility for social mobility, but their ability to attain respectability likewise left them vulnerable ….”  Former slaves on Pemba, an island off the East African coast, invested in <hi rend="italic">heshima, </hi>which was an expansive term referred to respectability and honor, but it did so within the established idiom of the standards of pious behavior and deportment established by the Arab elite (McMahon 2013, pp. 6-7). Ann McDougall recounts how an elderly former enslaved person in Senegal denigrated “colonial freedom” under which all he needed to do was to request a certificate of liberty from a colonial official. Instead, he insisted on buying his freedom from his owner because this act would “wipe away all his sins, past and present.”  McDougall argues that it was not the price of self-redemption that made the former slave free, but that only the pilgrimage would truly set him free. And only legally free people could make the hajj (McDougall 2007, pp. 174-75). Self-purchase was thus a step towards becoming free and respectable. In her ethnographic research in central Mali, Lotte Pelckmans also found that former enslaved people continued to negotiate their self-purchase from their former owners even though they were legally free because they wanted both the respectability from this act and because this act allowed them to make the pilgrimage (Pelckmans 2011, ch 5). </p>
            <p>Enslaved people who wanted to leave their owners had many different options; the most common was simply to leave. Risks abounded for those who sought to leave their owners. The owners could try to hunt them down and force their return; owners could confiscate children and goods that the enslaved people possessed; and those who left faced real dangers of hunger. We have bits and pieces of records of those who left particularly after 1899 and especially after 1905 (Klein 1998; Roberts 2005; Rodet 2010).</p>
            <p>The enslaved people in the Senegal Liberation Registers actively sought what French colonial officials offered them: certificates of liberty. The enslaved people in the wider Senegal-Mali-Mauritanian region who walked to French colonial officials thus shared with those who engaged with self-purchase an intention to end their enslavement. Whether through self-purchase or walking towards French colonial officials, these individuals engaged in purposeful actions with specific goals to have their new status recognized within their communities, by their former owners, and/or by governmental officials. These enslaved people wanted their names and their new status inscribed in certificates of liberty and in the Registers of Slave Liberation. They wanted or at least they accepted that to signify their new status, they needed to do so publicly. Their decision to seek their liberation meant that they needed and wanted public recognition of their new status.</p>
            <p>Enslaved people seeking their liberation from French colonial officials sometimes used names strategically. On 13 December 1897, Fatou Sane aged 25 presented herself and her three children before the French colonial officer at Louga, Senegal. Fatou Sane indicated that she was born in Kajoor to Sallé Niang and Penda Diop. Fatou's surname –Sane- was neither her father's nor mother's, which suggests that her surname may have been her owner's. Fatou Sane traveled to Louga with her three children: Seinabou Badiou, aged 6, N'Doube Gaye, aged 8, and Mamdou Badiou, aged 2. All three children were born in the village of N'Dawa in Kajoor. What is most intriguing about this request for liberation is that Fatou Sane did not indicate the name or names of the father of her children. Fatou is recorded as the mother of all three children. And all three children were remanded into her custody upon their registration as liberated slaves. It could be that Fatou did not know the names of her children's father or fathers. Or Fatou consciously avoided naming the names of her children's father or fathers because she did not want their father or fathers to reclaim them. What we can take from this single entry is a hint that enslaved people seeking their liberation from French colonial officials through the Senegal Liberation Registers used names –their own and their children's — consciously and with intentionality.</p>
            <figure>
              <head></head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png" style="width: 800px"/>
            </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ethical Guidelines and Politics of Naming the Names of Enslaved People</head>
            <p>Robust and clearly articulated ethical guidelines are critical for scholars engaged in research involving enslaved people or their descendants and taking place under conditions of inequality. This is because the wrenching experiences of enslavement, rupture from natal homes and families, and experiencing the social violence on being renamed often several times were characteristics of slavery, and thoughtless research practices can easily reproduce the erasures and violence of enslavement. Enslaved people the world over struggled against these processes of deracination and erasure and built anew kinship and communities (Mintz and Price 1992; Hawthorne 2010). However, such experiences meant different things to different populations of formerly enslaved people. For example, Fredrick Miller did not realize that when he purchased a “handsome house” not far from where he was born in Gretna, Virginia, in 2020 that he was also buying a historic plantation among whose former enslaved residents were his own ancestors. Miller and members of his family used the purchase of Sharswood to conduct genealogical research only to discover that the 1860 census did not list the enslaved by name, only by age and gender. Only by digging deeper into the Virginia Slave Births Index did the Miller family find direct links to an enslaved boy named Samuel born in 1864. At the time when Samuel was born the plantation was owned by Charles Edwin Miller and Nathaniel Crenshaw Miller, who gave their surnames to baby Samuel. Only now, the Miller family “is reclaiming its past” (Heim 2022). Through various mechanisms of renaming, formerly enslaved people were “rendered without history.”  Descendants of former enslaved people especially in the diaspora turned to well-established means of genealogical research to trace their ancestors, while others have gravitated to newer methods of DNA research to find out their ancestral origins (Sweet 2022). For this group, recovering their “names” and their origins are important and humanizing.  For other descendants of enslaved ancestors in other parts of the world, recovering the names of their enslaved ancestors may not be welcomed especially when they chose to live close to their former owners (Klein 1998; El Hamel 2013; Becker 2021). Although a “public secret” of an enslaved past may be widely known, as Alice Bellagamba's elderly Gambian informants argue, “not all should be said” (Bellagamba 2012, pp. 39-40). So how do historians working with evidence of the enslaved past navigate these ethical and political cross currents?</p>
            <p>We have identified three different but overlapping ethical and legal frameworks to help us think about how to proceed with whether to name the former enslaved people in our historical record. The first is drawn from ethical guidelines embedded in the rules governing research on human subjects in US federal grants. Universities and research institutes receiving federal funds must establish Institutional Review Boards charged with assessing research using human subjects. Drawing on the ethical standards of human subjects research, we need to be concerned with 1) do no harm; 2) informed consent; and 3) preferences for anonymity. To do no harm is directly correlated with to do good or to provide beneficence. What does this mean in the case of naming names?  Where the stigma of slave descent persists, then naming names may do harm. On the other hand, where the stigma of slave descent persists, opening up public conversations through public history and teaching modules about enslavement, slavery, and cultural hierarchies may well undermine such stigma and promote greater equality in society (see Baldé, Ba, Mbodje and Duke Bryant in this collection). In Senegal and Mali, high school curriculum deal with the export slave trade but do not engage robustly with slavery and the slave trade in Africa and thus with the legacies of slavery (see Ba, Baldé, and Mbodje in this collection). The principle of informed consent is predicated upon providing human subjects with sufficient knowledge and understanding of our projects for them to make considered and informed decisions regarding whether they want to participate or not. It is based also on the principle of agentive participation. We cannot, however, ask this question of our subjects recorded in the registers of slave liberations because they are long dead. But we could, following Ana Lucia Araujo, ask permission of the descendants of the liberated slaves if we could locate them (Araujo 2021; Johnson 2018, p. 71). However, given the incomplete nature of colonial registers and censuses in the middle and late nineteenth century and the paucity of civil registers of births and deaths in Africa even to this day, such a task may be impossible. </p>
            <p>Secondly, since the Registers of Slave Liberations are official French colonial documents that name names, the regulations closest to these documents may be those governing access to court cases. The Senegalese National Archives generally follow the regulations governing access to documents held by the French National Archives. The regulations that come closest to the “legal” character of the registers of liberation are “documents relating to cases before the courts, subject to the special provisions relating to judgements and the execution of court decisions,” which remain closed to the public for 75 years following the most recent document in the file or 25 years following the death of the individual concerned in the case. In the case of a minor, the files remain closed for 100 years following the most recent document or 25 years after the death of the person concerned. The registers of slave liberation may also fall under the provision of civil status birth and marriage registers, which are communicable “from the time they are closed (Republic of France 2021). None of these regulations would prohibit access to the Registers of Slave Liberations and naming the names of the enslaved people recorded since the last liberation was recorded in 1903.</p>
            <p>The third framework for the ethical use of personal information comes from the US Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 better known as HIPAA. HIPAA privacy rule was designed to protect individuals' medical records and individually identifiable health information. While HIPAA is not directly germane to the issue of naming names, it may be helpful by broadening out the guidance on protection of individually identifiable information, which would then include basic demographic information contained in the registers. In particular, HIPAA privacy extends 50 years beyond the death of the individual, demonstrating a realization that divulging private information can remain harmful even after death. HIPAA actually takes into consider the privacy interests of the surviving relatives “with the needs for archivists, biographers, historians, and others to access old or ancient records on deceased individuals for historical purposes.”  Thus, even during the 50-year protection period, the personal representative of the decedent has the authority to lift these restrictions (U.S. Department of Health and Human Services 2013).. HIPAA's consideration of relatives is logical in a medical context, as many diseases have genetic components, and it is unlike many other privacy frameworks in this regard. Even though the SLP does not incorporate medical information, therefore, HIPAA's framework for long term protection of anonymity offers an important lesson for other kinds of information that impact relatives and descendants, including the enslaved status of ancestors. This makes it helpful for our project.</p>
            <p>From a purely legal or regulatory perspective, these three ethical frameworks do not prohibit the release of personal information regarding those people who sought their liberation in Senegal from 1857 to 1903. Nonetheless, the ethical issues of naming names remains and the ethical considerations of publishing the names of liberated Africans bears special charge for the historical and sociological reasons enumerated earlier in this article. From an anthropological perspective and dealing with living informants, Lotte Pelckmans reflects on these issues especially regarding those who changed their names.</p>
            <p>Finally, there is an ethical dimension that impedes in-depth research and presentation of the data on these issues. Ethically, it is difficult to ask informants discussing name changers to get in touch with those described, since this would be considered a kind of betrayal…. [W]riting and publishing about this group is an ethical dilemma for me and other researchers. As a researcher, I do not want to violate their right to remain invisible (Pelckmans 2017, p. 277).</p>
            <p>While some descendants of enslaved people would prefer to remain forgotten, others struggle against persistent discrimination and the enduring silence regarding the history of enslavement in Senegal and West Africa more generally through political movements and legal suits (Rodet 2013, p. 27-29; Bales 2007; Hahonou and Pelckmans 2011; Pelckmans 2020). </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="agostinho2019" label="Agostino 2019">Agostinho, D. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Archival encounters: 
             Rethinking access and care in digital colonial archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 
             19, pp. 141-165. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-019-09312-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-019-09312-0</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anderson2020" label="Anderson 2020">Anderson, R. (2020) <title rend="italic">Abolition in Sierra Leone: 
             Re-building lives and identities in nineteenth-century West Africa</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="appiah2007" label="Appiah 2007">Appiah, K.A. (2007) <title rend="quotes">What's wrong with slavery?</title>, 
             in Appiah, K.A. and Bunzl, M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Buying freedom: The ethics and economics of slave 
                redemption</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, pp. 249-258.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="araujo2021" label="Araujo 2021">Araujo, A.L. (2021) <title rend="italic">Slavery in the age of memory: 
             Engaging the past</title>. London: Bloomsbury Academic.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="babou2007" label="Babou 2007">Babou, C. (2007) <title rend="italic">Fighting the greater Jihad: Amadu 
             Bamba and the founding of the Muridiyya of Senegal, 1853-1913</title>. Athens, OH: Ohio University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bales2007" label="Bales 2007">Bales, K. (2007) <title rend="italic">Ending slavery: How we free 
             today's slaves</title>. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="baptist_n.d." label="Baptist n.d.">Baptist, E. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Freedom on the move</title>. 
             Available at: <ref target="https://freedomonthemove.org/">https://freedomonthemove.org/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="becker2021" label="Becker 2021">Becker, F. (2021) <title rend="quotes"><quote rend="inline">Looking for 
             life</quote>: Traces of slavery in the structures and social lives of southern Swahili towns</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of African Diaspora Archaeology and Heritage</title>, 10(1-2), pp. 87-109. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/21619441.2020.1804691">https://doi.org/10.1080/21619441.2020.1804691</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bellagamba2009" label="Bellagamba 2009">Bellagamba, A. (2009) <title rend="quotes">After abolition: 
             Metaphors of slavery in the political history of the Gambia</title>, in Rossi, B. (ed.) 
             <title rend="italic">Reconfiguring slavery: West African trajectories</title>. Liverpool, UK: Liverpool University 
             Press, pp. 63-84.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bellagamba2012" label="Bellagamba 2012">Bellagamba, A. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Reasons for silence: 
             Tracing the legacy of internal slavery and the slave trade in contemporary Gambia</title>, in Araujo, A.L. (ed.) 
             <title rend="italic">Politics of memory: Making slavery visible in the public space</title>. London: Routledge, pp. 
             35-53.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bellagamba2020" label="Bellagamba 2020">Bellagamba, A. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Marriage is the arena: 
             <quote rend="inline">Inside</quote> stories of genealogical purity and slave ancestry from southern Senegal (Kolda 
             region)</title>, <title rend="italic">Anthropologia</title>, 7(1), pp. 141-64. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.14672/ada20201628141-164">http://doi.org/10.14672/ada20201628141-164</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bethell1966" label="Bethell 1966">Bethell, L. (1966) <title rend="quotes">The mixed commissions for the 
             suppression of the transatlantic slave trade in the nineteenth century</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal of 
             African History</title>, 7(1), pp. 79-93. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0021853700006095">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0021853700006095</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="borucki_etal_n.d." label="Borucki et al. n.d.">Borucki, A. et al. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Slave 
             voyages</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/">https://www.slavevoyages.org/</ref> 
             (accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="candido2016" label="Candido 2016">Candido, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">African freedom suits and 
             Portuguese vassal status: Legal Mechanisms for Fighting Enslavement in Benguela, Angola, 1800-1830</title>, in 
             Peabody, S. and Grinberg, K. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Free Soil in the Atlantic World</title>. London: Routledge, 
             pp. 117-29.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="carretta2005" label="Carretta 2005">Carretta, V. (2005) <title rend="italic">Equiano, the African: 
             Biography of a self-made man</title>. New York: Penguin.   
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chadha_etal_n.d." label="Chadha and Lovejoy n.d.">Chadha, K. and Lovejoy, H. (n.d.) 
             <title rend="italic">Libeated Africans</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.liberatedafricans.org/">https://www.liberatedafricans.org/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="clark2015" label="Clark 2015">Clark, L. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Ellis Island isn't to blame 
             for your family's name change</title>, <title rend="italic">Smithsonian Magazine</title>, 8 January. Available 
             at: <ref target="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/ellis-island-isnt-blame-your-familys-name-change-180953832/">https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/ellis-island-isnt-blame-your-familys-name-change-180953832/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 27 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="connolly2024" label="Connolly 2024">Connolly, J. (2024) <title rend="italic">Worthy of freedom: Indenture 
             and free labor in the era of emancipation</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cooper_etal2000" label="Cooper, Holt, and Scott 2000">Cooper, F., Holt, T.C, and Scott, R. (2000) 
             <title rend="italic">Beyond slavery: Explorations of race, labor, and citizenship in postemancipation 
             societies</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dasilva_etal2021" label="da Silva and Alpers 2021">da Silva, D.B.D. and Alpers, E. (2021) 
             <title rend="quotes">Abolition and the registration of slaves and libertos in Portuguese Mozambique, 1856-76</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of African History</title>, 62(3), pp. 377-93.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dalgeish2011" label="Dalgeish 2011">Dalgeish, P. (2011) <title rend="quotes">The thorniest area: 
             Making collections accessible online which respecting individual and community sensitivities</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Archives and Manuscripts</title>, 39(1), pp. 67-84. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://publications.archivists.org.au/index.php/asa/article/view/10121">https://publications.archivists.org.au/index.php/asa/article/view/10121</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dukebryant2019" label="Duke Bryant 2021">Duke Bryant, K. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Changing childhood: 
             <quote rend="inline">Liberated minors</quote>, guardianship, and the colonial state in Senegal, 1895-1911</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of African History</title>, 60(2), pp. 209-228.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="elhamel2013" label="El Hamel 2013">El Hamel, C. (2013) <title rend="italic">Black Morocco: A history of 
             slavery, race, and Islam</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="faidherbe1857" label="Faidherbe 1857">Faidherbe, L. (1857) <title rend="quotes">Arrête relatif aux captifs 
             rachetés et amenés à Saint-Louis pour être libérés</title>, <title rend="italic">Archives Nationales République du 
             Sénégal</title>, 5 December, K 11.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ferguson1999" label="Ferguson 1999">Ferguson, J. (1999) <title rend="italic">Expectations of modernity: 
             Myths and meanings of urban life on the Zambia Copperbelt</title>. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fr1848" label="French Republic 1848">French Republic (1848) <title rend="italic">Constitution de la 
             République Française</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k202941g">https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k202941g</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="getz2004" label="Getz 2004">Getz, T. (2004) <title rend="italic">Slavery and reform in West Africa: Toward 
             emancipation in nineteenth-century Senegal and the Gold Coast</title>. Athens, OH: Ohio University Press.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="glipenfaust2022" label="Glipen Faust 2022">Glipen Faust, D. (2022) <title rend="italic">Gen Z never learned 
             to read cursive: How will they interpret the past?</title>, <title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title>, October. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2022/10/gen-z-handwriting-teaching-cursive-history/671246/">https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2022/10/gen-z-handwriting-teaching-cursive-history/671246/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 25 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goodwin_etal2021" label="Goodwin et al. 2021">Goodwin, J. et al. (2021) <title rend="italic">The 
             registers of slave liberation in colonial Senegal: Preliminary analysis of the evidence from 1894-1903</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Esclavages &amp; Post-esclavages/Slaveries &amp; Post-Slaveries</title>, 5. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/slaveries.5495">https://doi.org/10.4000/slaveries.5495</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gueye1965" label="Guèye 1965">Guèye, M. (1965) <title rend="quotes">A fin de l'esclavage à Saint-Louis 
             et à Gorée en 1848</title>, <title rend="italic">Bulletin de L'IFAN</title>, 27(3-4), pp. 637-656.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hahonou_etal2011" label="Hahonou and Pelckmans 2011">Hahonou, E. and Pelckmans, L. (2011) 
             <title rend="quotes">West African antislavery movements: Citizenship struggles and the legacies of slavery</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Stichproben: Wiener Zeitschrift fur kritische Afrikastudien</title>, 20, pp. 141-162.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hanretta2009" label="Hanretta 2009">Hanretta, S. (2009) <title rend="italic">Islam and social change 
             in French West Africa: History of an emancipatory community</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawthorne2010" label="Hawthorne 2010">Hawthorne, W. (2010) <title rend="italic">From Africa to Brazil: 
             Culture, identity, and an Atlantic slave trade, 1600-1830</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heim2022a" label="Heim 2022a">Heim, J. (2022a) <title rend="quotes">An Old Virginia plantation, a new 
             owner and a family legacy unveiled</title>, <title rend="italic">The Washington Post</title>, 22 January. Available 
             at: 
             <ref target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/history/2022/01/22/virginia-plantation-slavery-owners-history/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/history/2022/01/22/virginia-plantation-slavery-owners-history/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 27 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heim2022b" label="Heim 2022b">Heim, J. (2022b) <title rend="italic">Reclaiming history: Inside the 
             60 Minutes story as it unfolded in real time</title>. 15 May. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xaQkl1xd6uI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xaQkl1xd6uI</ref> 
             (Accessed: 27 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hepworth_etal2018" label="Hepworth and Church 2018">Hepworth, K. and Church, C. (2018) 
             <title rend="quotes">Racism in the machine: Visualization ethics in digital humanities projects</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12(4). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="irwin1981" label="Irwin 1981">Irwin, P. (1981) <title rend="italic">Liptako speaks: History from oral 
             traditions in Africa</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, J.M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Markup bodies: Black [life] 
             studies and slavery [death] studies at the digital crossroads</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>, 
             36(4), pp. 57-79.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein1989" label="Klein 1989">Klein, M. (1989) <title rend="quotes">Studying the history of those who 
             would rather forget: Oral history and the experience of slavery</title>, <title rend="italic">History in 
             Africa</title>, 16, pp. 209-217.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein1998" label="Klein 1998">Klein, M. (1998) <title rend="italic">Slavery and colonial rule in French 
             West Africa</title>. New York: Cambridge University Press.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="klein2006" label="Klein 2006">Klein, M. (2006) <title rend="quotes">After slavery in French West Africa: 
             The problem of the invisible slave</title>, in Kleijwegt, M. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Faces of freedom: The 
             manumission and emancipation of slaves in Old World and New World slavery</title>. Leidon, UK: Brill, pp. 265-285.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kopytoff1988" label="Kopytoff 1988">Kopytoff, I. (1988) <title rend="quotes">The cultural context of African 
             abolition</title>, in Miers, S. and Roberts, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic">The end of slavery</title>. Madison, WI: 
             University of Wisconsin Press, pp. 485-503.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="landers_etal_n.d." label="Landers et al. n.d.">Landers, J. et al. <title rend="italic">Slave 
             societies digital archive</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.slavesocieties.org/">https://www.slavesocieties.org/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lawrance_etal2012" label="Lawrance and Roberts 2012">Lawrance, B. and Roberts, R. (eds.) (2012) 
             <title rend="italic">Trafficking in slavery's wake: Law and the experience of women and children in Africa</title>. 
             Athens, OH: Ohio University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy_h2010" label="Lovejoy 2010">Lovejoy, H. (2010) <title rend="quotes">The registers of liberated 
             Africans of the Havana Slave Trade Commission: Transcription methodology and statistical analysis</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">African Economic History</title>, 38(1), pp. 107-135.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy_p2006" label="Lovejoy 2006">Lovejoy, P. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Autobiography and memory: 
             Gustavus Vassa, alias Olaudah Equiano, the African</title>, <title rend="italic">Slavery and Abolition</title>, 
             27(3), pp. 316-347. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01440390601014302">https://doi.org/10.1080/01440390601014302</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy_etal1993" label="Lovejoy and Hogendorn 1993">Lovejoy, P. and Hogendorn, J. (1993) 
             <title rend="italic">Slow death for slavery: The course of abolition in northern Nigeria, 1897-1936</title>. 
             Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mann2002" label="Mann 2002">Mann, G. (2002) <title rend="quotes">What is in an alias? Family names, 
             individual histories, and historical method in the western Sudan</title>, <title rend="italic">History in 
             Africa</title>, 29, pp. 309-320.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="martina2014" label="Martina 2014">Martina, E. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Open sourcing the colonial 
             archive — A digital montage of the history of Fernando Pó and the Bight of Biafra</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">History in Africa</title>, 42, pp. 387-415. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="martinez2012" label="Martinez 2012">Martinez, J. (2012) <title rend="italic">The slave trade and the 
             origins of international human rights law</title>. New York: Oxford University Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcdougall2007" label="McDougaall 2007">McDougall, E.A. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Dilemmas in the 
             practice of Rachat in French west Africa</title>, in Appiah, K. and Bunzl, M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Buying 
             freedom: The ethics and economics of slave redemption</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, pp. 158-178.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcmahon2013" label="McMahon 2013">McMahon, E. (2013) <title rend="italic">Slavery and emancipation in 
             Islamic east Africa: From honor to respectability</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="meillassoux1981" label="Meillassoux 1981">Meillassoux, C. (1981) <title rend="italic">Meals, maidens, and 
             money: Capitalism and the domestic economy</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="miesevich2008" label="Miesevich 2008">Miesevich, P. (2008) <title rend="quotes">The origins of slaves 
             leaving the upper Guinea coast in the nineteenth century</title>, in Eltis, D. and Richardson, D. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Extending the frontiers: Essays on the new transatlantic slave trade database</title>. 
             New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, pp. 155-175.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="miers_etal1988" label="Miers and Roberts 1988">Miers, S. and Roberts, R. (eds.) (1988) 
             <title rend="italic">The end of slavery in Africa</title>. Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="miesevich2019" label="Miesevich 2019">Miesevich, P. (2019) <title rend="italic">Abolition and the 
             transformation of Atlantic commerce in southern Sierra Leone, 1790s to 1860s</title>. Trenton, NJ: 
             Africa World Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mintz_etal1992" label="Mintz and Price 1992">Mintz, S. and Price, R. (1992) <title rend="italic">The 
             birth of African-American culture: An anthropological perspective</title>. Boston, MA: Beacon Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moitt1989" label="Moitt 1989">Moitt, B. (1989) <title rend="quotes">Slavery and emancipation in Senegal's 
             peanut zone: The nineteenth and twentieth centuries</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of African 
             Historical Studies</title>, 22(1), pp. 27-50.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moitt2024" label="Moitt 2024">Moitt, B. (2024) <title rend="italic">Child slavery and guardianship in 
             colonial Senegal</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moroguez2008" label="Moróguez 2008">Moróguez, O.G. (2008) <title rend="quotes">The African origins of 
             slaves arriving in Cuba, 1789-1865</title>, in Eltis, D. and Richardson, D. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Extending the 
             frontiers: Essays on the new transatlantic slave trade database</title>. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 
             pp. 176-201.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="northrup1995" label="Northrup 1995">Northrup, D. (1995) <title rend="italic">Indentured labor in the age 
             of imperialism, 1834-1922</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.   
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="obrian1975" label="O'Brian 1975">O'Brian, D.B.C. (1975) <title rend="italic">Saints and 
             politicians: Essays in the organization of a Senegalese peasant society</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University 
             Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="odumosu2020" label="Odumosu 2020">Odumosu, T. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The crying child: On colonial 
             archives, digitization, and the ethics of care in the cultural commons</title>, <title rend="italic">Current 
             Anthropology</title>, 51(S22), pp. S289-S302. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pearson2016" label="Pearson 2016">Pearson, A. (2016) <title rend="italic">Distant freedom: St Helena 
             and the abolition of the slave trade, 1840-1872</title>. Liverpool, UK: Liverpool University Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pelckmans2011" label="Pelckmans 2011">Pelckmans, L. (2011) <title rend="italic">Traveling hierarchies: 
             Roads in and out of slave status in a central Malian Fulbe network</title>. PhD thesis. Leiden University.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pelckmans2017" label="Pelckmans 2017">Pelckmans, L. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Surnames as passports 
             to social mobility? Renaming practices of Fulbe slave descendants in central Mali</title>, in Bellagamba, A., 
             Greene, S., and Klein, M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">African slaves, African masters: Politics, memories, social 
             life</title>. Trenton, NJ: Africa World Press, pp. 255-286.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pelckmans2020" label="Pelckmans 2020">Pelckmans, L. (2020) <title rend="italic">Breaking the silence? 
             The ongoing legacies of internal African slavery in Mali</title>. Bonn Center for Dependency and Slavery Studies. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://amis.ku.dk/research/protracted-rural-displacements/Dependent_Aug2020_Lotte_Pelckmans.pdf">https://amis.ku.dk/research/protracted-rural-displacements/Dependent_Aug2020_Lotte_Pelckmans.pdf</ref> 
             (Accessed: 27 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="piot1999" label="Piot 1999">Piot, C. (1999) <title rend="italic">Remotely global: Village modernity 
             in West Africa</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="prilea2019" label="Prilea 2019">Prilea, F. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Birth registrations is less than 
             50% in many African countries</title>, <title rend="italic">World Bank Blogs</title>, 26 July. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://blogs.worldbank.org/opendata/birth-registration-less-50-many-african-countries">https://blogs.worldbank.org/opendata/birth-registration-less-50-many-african-countries</ref> 
             (Accessed: 7 June 2023). 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="profess2021" label="Profess 2021">Profess, N. (2021) <title rend="quotes">What ethics can offer the 
             digital humanities and what the digital humanities can offer ethics</title>, in Schuster, K. and Dunn, S. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Routledge international handbook of research methods in digital humanities</title>. 
             Abingdon, UK: Routledge, pp. 416-427.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rehberger_etal_n.d." label="Rehberger et al. n.d.">Rehberger, D. et al. (n.d.) 
             <title rend="quotes">Statement of ethics</title>, <title rend="italic">Enslaved: Peoples of the historical slave 
             trade</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://enslaved.org/statementofEthics/">https://enslaved.org/statementofEthics/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 26 July 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="renault1972" label="Renault 1972">Renault, F. (1972) <title rend="italic">L'Abolition de L'Esclavage 
             au Sénégal: L'Attitude de L'Administration Françaie, 1848-1905</title>. Paris: Société Française d’Histoire 
             d'Outre-Mer.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="republic1848" label="Republic of France 1848">Republic of France (1848) 
             <title rend="italic">Constitution</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://esclavages.cnrs.fr/wp1/constitution-de-la-republique-francaise/">https://esclavages.cnrs.fr/wp1/constitution-de-la-republique-francaise/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 29 May 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="republic2021" label="Republic of France 2021">Republic of France (2021) <title rend="italic">Code du 
             Patrimony: Chapitre 3: Régime de Communication</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/codes/article_lc/LEGIARTI000037269071">https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/codes/article_lc/LEGIARTI000037269071</ref> 
             (Accessed 26 July 2024). 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="roberts1987" label="Roberts 1987">Roberts, R. (1987) <title rend="italic">Warriors, slaves, and merchants: 
             The state and the economy in the Middle Niger Valley, 1700-1914</title>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.  
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="roberts1988" label="Roberts 1988">Roberts, R. (1988) <title rend="quotes">The end of slavery in the French 
             Soudan, 1905-1914</title>, in Miers, S. and Roberts, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic">The end of slavery in 
             Africa</title>. Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press, pp. 282-307.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="roberts2005" label="Roberts 2005">Roberts, R. (2005) <title rend="italic">Litigants and households: 
             African disputes and colonial courts in the French Soudan, 1895-1912</title>. Portsmouth, NH: Heinemann. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2010" label="Rodet 2010">Rodet, M. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Mémoires de l'esclavage dans la région 
             de Kayes, histoire d'une disparition</title>, <title rend="italic">Cahiers d’Études Africaines</title>, 197, pp. 
             263-291.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2015" label="Rodet 2015">Rodet, M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Escaping slavery and building 
             diasporic communities in French Soudan and Senegal, ca 1880-1940</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal 
             of African Studies</title>, 48(2), pp. 363-386.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2019" label="Rodet 2019">Rodet, M. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Reconfiguration des liens sociaux 
             dans les <quote rend="inline">villages rebelles</quote> (Soudan Francais), 1890-1940</title>, in Rogers, D. and 
             Lesueur, B. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Libres àpres les abolitions? Statuts et idetnités au Amériques et en 
             Afrique</title>. Paris: Karhtala, pp. 163-180.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rossi2009" label="Rossi 2009">Rossi, B. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Rethinking slavery in 
             West Africa</title>, in Rossi, B. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Reconfiguring slavery: West African trajectories</title>. 
             Liverpool, UK: Liverpool University Press, pp. 1-25.  
          </bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="rossi2024" label="Rossi 2024"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="saagsma2023" label="Saagsma 2023"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="scott_etal2002" label="Scott et al. 2002"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="searing1993" label="Searing 1993"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="searing2002" label="Searing 2002"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="sweet2009" label="Sweet 2009"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="sweet2022" label="Sweet 2022"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="swindell2006" label="Swindell 2006"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="taussig1999" label="Taussig 1999"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="thioub2012" label="Thioub 2012"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="thykstrup2022" label="Thykstrup 2022"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="usdh2013" label="U.S. Department of Health and Human Services 2013"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="westland2022" label="Westland 2022"></bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="wood_etal2021" label="Wood and Smith 2021"></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
