<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">New Media in the Academy: Labor and the Production of Knowledge in
               Scholarly Multimedia</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Helen J. <dhq:family>Burgess</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Maryland Baltimore County</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>burgess@umbc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Helen J. Burgess is an Assistant Professor of English at the University of
                     Maryland Baltimore County. She has published in both digital and print formats,
                     including most recently <title rend="italic">Biofutures: Owning Body Parts and
                        Information</title>, a DVD-Rom coauthored with Rob Mitchell and Phillip
                     Thurtle. She is currently working with Jeanne Hamming on a multimedia project
                     entitled <title rend="quotes">Highways of the Mind: Imagining the Superhighway
                        from the World's Fair to the World Wide Web.</title>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Jeanne <dhq:family>Hamming</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Centenary College of Louisiana</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jhamming@centenary.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jeanne Hamming is an Associate Professor of English at Centenary College of
                     Louisiana, where she also teaches courses in new media communication and
                     digital culture. Her research on the intersections of ecology, gender, and
                     media technologies has appeared in national and international publications. She
                     is currently working with Helen Burgess on a multimedia project entitled <title rend="quotes">Highways of the Mind: Imagining the Superhighway from the
                        World's Fair to the World Wide Web.</title>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000102</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2011-06-27">27 June 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2011-03-10" who="Alyssa">encoded</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Despite a general interest in exploring the possibilities of multimedia and web-based
               research, the humanities profession has been slow to accept digital scholarship as a
               valid form of intellectual endeavor. Questions about labor, peer-review, and
               co-authorship often arise in academic departments’ attempts to evaluate digital
               research in the tenure and promotion process. In this essay, we argue that these
               tensions stem from a general misunderstanding of the kinds of
                  <soCalled>work</soCalled> that goes into producing scholarship in multimedia form.
               Multimedia work, we suggest, places scholars in an extended network that combines
               minds, bodies, machines, and institutional practices, and lays bare the fiction that
               scholars are disembodied intellectuals who labor only with the mind. We argue that
               while traditional ideas of what <soCalled>counts</soCalled> as scholarship continue
               to privilege content over form, intellectual labor over physical labor, and print
               over digital media, new media’s functional (and in some cases even biological)
               difference from old media contributes to a double erasure, for scholars working in
               multimedia, of both their intellectual contributions and their material labor.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Working with digital media in the academy forces us to think about how our scholarly
               practices are material and embodied.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>New Media in the Academy: Labor and the Production of Knowledge in Scholarly
            Multimedia</head>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#mitchell2003">I construct, and I am constructed, in a mutually recursive
                     process that continually engages my fluid, permeable boundaries and my
                     endlessly ramifying networks. I am a spatially extended cyborg.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#mitchell2003" loc="39"/>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#tuana2001">Knowledge arises from the flesh — that intertwining of my body
                     and the world, and my interactions with others.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="236" target="#tuana2001"/>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Digital scholarship is not new. By the time the World Wide Web appeared on the
               screens of professors and students at academic institutions in the mid-1990s, a
               profound transformation was well under way. Digital preservation, spearheaded by the
               Text Encoding Initiative and other similar efforts to apply computing power to
               literary analysis and preservation, had become a well established, if somewhat
               marginalized, field of study. For literary critics interested in computing, text had
               morphed into hypertext. Still others recognized that multimedia, as a practice, was a
               promising new frontier; as a result, media studies quickly became new media studies.
               In many ways, the institution adapted: new journals, such as the <title rend="italic">Electronic Book Review</title>, emerged as open-access e-journals. Print
               journals, such as <title rend="italic">Genders</title>, followed suit and were reborn
               in cyberspace. Brave, forward-looking deans, provosts, and grant-giving agencies like
               the National Endowment for the Humanities and the National Science Foundation threw
               money at multimedia and web-based projects that promised to revolutionize the way
               that scholarly knowledge is presented and circulated.</p>
            <p>This institutional interest in exploring the possibilities for digital scholarship,
               after an initial flurry of activity followed by something of a hiatus, seems to be
               gaining impetus again. We have recently seen the establishment of new granting
               initiatives (such as the NEH’s Digital Humanities Start-Up Grants and the ACLS
               Digital Innovation Fellowship Program) as well as a general <soCalled>buzz</soCalled>
               about digital scholarship epitomized by recent articles in the <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title> and elsewhere, culminating in a standing
               room only panels on digital humanities at the MLA conferences of 2009 and 2010, and
               the awarding of the MLA’s 2009 first book prize to <title rend="italic">Mechanisms</title>
               <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2008"/>, a seminal book on new media forensics. Innovative
               work, such as that sponsored by the Maryland Institute for Technology in the
               Humanities (MITH), MediaCommons, and the journal <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>, is gaining ground among a growing cohort of digital scholars.
               Despite these promising developments over the last decade, however, academia itself
               has been slow to respond to the changing face of scholarly practice when it comes to
               issues of promotion and tenure, peer-review, funding, and faculty development, and
               more broadly in recognizing the emerging importance of scholarly multimedia. In this
               respect, academia seems to suffer from its own version of technological obsolescence,
               seeing the emergence of scholarly multimedia as challenging the primacy of
               traditional humanities scholarship.</p>
            <p>This article considers the historically important role that new media have played in
               configuring not just articulations of humanist subjectivity in general (a now
               well-trodden field in literary and cultural studies), but also the humanist
                  <emph>scholarly</emph> subject. By placing the institutional tensions between
               traditional scholarly practice and new media within larger theoretical and
               disciplinary contexts, we can demonstrate how new media challenges the ways in which
               the traditional humanities scholar has been imagined as having a secure and stable
               position within institutionalized hierarchies of knowledge production. Furthermore,
               we can consider how scholarly multimedia threatens the very coherence of humanities
               scholarship by insisting on the re-embodiment of scholarly activity. In this respect,
               we hope to bring critiques of techno-scientific epistemologies coming out of new
               media and science studies to bear on humanities scholarship in order to follow
               through on Donna Haraway’s call for interventions into all forms of knowledge
               production: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#haraway2004">Knowledge-making technologies, including crafting subject
                     positions and ways of inhabiting such positions, must be made relentlessly
                     visible and open to critical intervention</quote>
                  <ptr target="#haraway2004" loc="236"/>
               </cit>. Our analysis will reveal the ways in which the production of scholarly
               multimedia has been hampered by two key obstacles: traditionalist definitions of
               humanities scholarship that still overwhelmingly determine the evaluation of digital
               works, and a narrow understanding of what the <soCalled>materiality</soCalled> of new
               media can actually come to mean. We hope to address both of these issues by
               foregrounding some of the material and intellectual potentialities revealed by
               scholarly multimedia.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Scholarly Multimedia: Defining an Emerging Genre</head>
            <p>Scholarly multimedia in the humanities has, historically, gone by many names: digital
               humanities, humanities computing, and more recently new media scholarship. Each of
               these names points to the technological aspects of this new mode of scholarship, and
               thus acknowledges the vital importance of medium to scholarly activity. In literary
               studies, media scholarship has for the most part diverged into two basic fields of
               study. On the one hand, we have traditional text-based readings of innovative
               literary forms, usually referred to as <term>new media studies</term>. N. Katherine
               Halyes, among others, has pioneered this important field.<note>
                  <ptr target="#hayles1999a"/>, <ptr target="#hayles1999b"/>, <ptr target="#hayles2005"/>
               </note> On the other hand, we have digital reimaginings of or interventions into
               preexisting text manuscripts, such as the William Blake Archive and Emily Dickinson
               Electronic Archives. These works are usually gathered under the title of
                  <term>digital humanities</term> or <term>humanities computing</term>. This
               division between analysis of new media and digital archiving has been accompanied by
               an equally notable split in tenure and promotion evaluation, wherein scholarship
                  <emph>about</emph> new media, in the form of single-author monographs,
                  <soCalled>counts,</soCalled> while multimedia projects themselves, no matter how
               transformative, are viewed (if the scholar is lucky) as akin to producing a somewhat
               gimmicky scholarly edition — i.e. the <soCalled>work</soCalled> is primarily viewed
               as reformatting rather than as <soCalled>original</soCalled> scholarship. The
               important work of digital preservation of existing texts, itself a crucial field, is
               more likely to be considered the province of library science than that of Literature
               and the Humanities.</p>
            <p>Spearheaded by the Electronic Literature Organization, scholars in the digital
               humanities are now starting to explore some of the technical and rhetorical problems
               of approaching and preserving <soCalled>born digital</soCalled> creative works —
               interactive Flash poems, hypertext novels, and the like — which never existed in
               print. But what about <soCalled>born digital</soCalled>
               <emph>scholarship</emph> — scholarship that never had a print analog? Very few
               theorists have attended to this category, being mostly concerned with digital
               creative works as their object of analysis, rather than digitally rendered scholarly
               works. Thus the work of new media researchers in the humanities tends to get lumped
               into a single category rather than, as Cheryl Ball distinguishes, into the very
               distinct categories of scholarship rendered <emph>in</emph> new media and scholarship
                  <emph>about</emph> new media <ptr target="#ball2004" loc="404"/>. Institutionally,
               this distinction is crucial for upcoming scholars, since much of the contention
               centers around <term>originality</term> of content: if the multimedia format of the
               work is absolutely essential to (and constitutive of) the argument it presents, where
               should it count — as a work of scholarship as fundamentally complex as a written
               monograph, or as a reworking of an existing argument (a <term>porting</term>, if you
               like — a term we borrow from software development practices)? Thus it is important to
               distinguish, as we do here, between the term <term>scholarly multimedia</term> and
               other terms frequently used in considerations of the role of new media in academic
               contexts. By scholarly multimedia we specifically mean critical scholarly works —
               interpretive and argumentative, as opposed to creative or archival — that are
               produced, and in some cases performed, in multimedia form. These works represent a
               new rhetorical genre of scholarship that is at once both discursive and embodied, and
               that differs from multimedia art or hypertext fiction (as artistic and literary
               genres) and from multimedia as interactive storage spaces for archival materials or
               critical resources.</p>
            <p>The messy contention over how to define scholarly multimedia is symptomatic of the
               very old argument, played out continually in the academy, over a perceived split
               between form and content. Content is the essence of analysis, while form is merely
               the <soCalled>matter</soCalled> out of which it is made. But materiality matters —
               has always mattered — in the meaning-constitution of analysis. Digital machines, in
               all their undeniable physicality, confront us as a transformational tool in the same
               way that the printing press does. In this way, we see, from the earliest writings
               about the role of computers in humanities scholarship, an awareness of materiality.
               In the fields commonly known as <title rend="quotes">history of the book</title> or
                  <title rend="quotes">print culture,</title> critics have devoted considerable
               attention to the materiality and visual spatiality of the scholarly artifact – the
               illuminated manuscript, the Concrete poem, the hypertext novel, etc. In the analysis
               of the many forms new media take, <ptr target="#drucker2002"/>, <ptr target="#hockey2000"/>, and <ptr target="#mcgann2004"/> serve as excellent
               examples, as does N. Katherine Hayles in her call for <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2002">media-specific analysis</quote> and later <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2002">New
                  Materialism,</quote> a mode of literary criticism that takes seriously the
               material instantiation of the text as integral to critical interpretation (<ptr target="#hayles2002" loc="29"/>; <ptr loc="142" target="#hayles2005"/>). Critics
               have also attended to the body of the reader as an important locus of materiality,
               arguing, as Mark Hansen does, that readers engaged with new media experience the
               text/artifact in an embodied, post-representationalist way; that is to say, new media
               produces in the user/reader <soCalled>affects</soCalled> that cannot be separated
               from material embodiment <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="223"/>. But the importance of
               the material conditions of multimedia <emph>production</emph>, i.e. the embodied and
               materially-mediated work of the digital author has remained drastically
               under-theorized.</p>
            <p>Our goal here is to extend the discourse of new media criticism by addressing
               specifically the materiality of scholarly production, both in print and multimedia
               form. That is, we hope to attend not only to the bodies of the text and the
               user/reader, but also to the bodies of the authors/engineers and to the material
               aspects of scholarly activity itself. Crucially, we want to focus on the material and
               embodied aspects of multimedia production, rather than simply the rhetorical
               arrangements or rearrangements of information that are so often considered the
               primary labor of multimedia authoring. In this mode, it is important to distinguish
               between material labor and embodied labor.</p>
            <p>For us, <term>material labor</term> is a broad term encompassing both physical
               movement and the kinds of <soCalled>material</soCalled> actions necessary to provide
               an infrastructure for digital media. On an immediate level, these actions can be
               thought of as a nodal network of bodies and machines in which machines <emph>combine
                  with</emph> humans to perform tasks: the manipulation of software packages, the
               shooting and compression of video, the recording and recasting of audio. In addition,
               we have the even wider infrastructural support necessary for producing such media
               objects: the institutional search for grants, the subvention of copyright clearances,
               the securing of financial support for and mentoring of graduate students, and
               technical assistance provided by, variously, presses, contract programmers,
               videographers, and animators.</p>
            <p>By <term>embodied labor</term>, more narrowly, we mean the physical actions (often
               disciplined by machinic interactions) that go into interacting with machines — the
               focusing of the eye on the screen, the repetitive hand movement, the response of the
               ear to input, and the performative bodily movements when interacting with machines as
               physical objects. This distinction will be crucial when we come later in the article
               to a discussion of the most radical forms of scholarly multimedia currently being
               conducted in the academy — performative scholarship.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Purification and the Problem of Material Rhetorics</head>
            <p>A host of binary oppositions emerges when we reflect on the unusual space scholarly
               multimedia occupies within the academy, particularly within the humanities: content
               versus form, information versus materiality, multimedia versus print, collaboration
               versus single-authorship, nodal or networked <soCalled>writing</soCalled> versus
               linear academic prose, word versus image, and so on. These binaries are often cited
               as arguments for the line we draw between print and new media as well as between
               intellectual labor (often seen as pure information) and bodily labor (often rendered
               transparent) in the process of producing scholarly works. But such binaries are by no
               means sustainable, and lead to a proliferation of hybrids, in the Latourian sense, as
               the labor practices of academics who work in multimedia have become more and more
               visible as embodied material practices.</p>
            <p>In Bruno Latour’s articulation of the modern constitution, he offers
                  <term>purification</term> as a term to describe the institutional practice of
               vigorously separating the domain of the social from the domain of nature. But this
               practice of purification is met with resistance as there continue to arise objects
               (and by extension practices) that refuse to be easily contained within one or the
               other of these purified domains. Modernity attempts to subsume such unrulqy <quote rend="inline" source="#latour1993">quasi-objects</quote> or hybrids by characterizing them as <quote rend="inline" source="#latour1993">a mixture of two pure forms,</quote> so that rather than tearing at
               the fabric of modernity’s stable ontology, they reinforce the purified domains of the
               material and the social that constitute modernity <ptr loc="78" target="#latour1993"/>. The consequence of this dual process of purification and mediation (Latour also
               calls this mixing of domains <soCalled>translation</soCalled>) is a
               frustration with modern philosophy’s incapacity to account for the proliferation of
               hybrids other than by resorting to a pernicious relativism at the expense of more
               nuanced accounts of the relationship between materiality and cultural productions.
               Within the academy we see these processes of purification and mediation at work,
               producing and maintaining the distinction between intellectual labor and material
               labor, both of which are essential to multimedia production.</p>
            <p>The distinction between intellectual and material labor is pervasive throughout
               scholarly criticism and evaluation of media forms. But usually these oppositions
               amount to a debate over genre in terms of <emph>rhetorical</emph> construction,
               rather than its material conditions. In addition, any discussion of scholarly
               activities in multimedia format are usually elided in favor of literary texts, which
               can be safely analyzed using traditional tools of critical analysis. Thus early
               criticism of hypertext, for example, focuses on its rhetorical difference as a
               reading and writing practice. However, critics of this early celebration of hypertext
               generally point out the ways that print conventions have <emph>always</emph> been
               associative, non-linear, and intertextual, citing footnoting and indexing as examples
               of the always already hypertextual nature of print. Richard Grusin, for one,
               demonstrates how ascribing revolutionary qualities to electronic writing is
               tantamount to a technological fallacy whereby we ascribe agency to technology itself
               rather than attending to the ways in which writing is always produced in particular
               historical, social, and technological contexts. In this way, he asserts, rather
               paradoxically, that electronic authorship is the same as print authorship only
               different: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#grusin1996">To then imagine that current technologies of (and like)
                     writing are destabilized by pointing out that they have histories is only to
                     suggest that since things used to be different, they could be again</quote>
                  <ptr target="#grusin1996" loc="52"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>Some attempts have been made to reintroduce the material world into new media texts.
               In a reexamination of literary <soCalled>cybertexts,</soCalled> for example, <ptr target="#aarseth1997"/> attempts to reconcile the <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">new/old</quote> contradiction pervasive in media criticism. Aarseth’s project, he
               claims, is to create a space within literary theory that can account for new media
               technologies. At the same time, however, Aarseth dismisses new media technologies as
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">not important in themselves</quote> in order to favor a
               reader/user-centered approach to cybertext that disregards media-specific rhetorics
               and aesthetics, both of which, implies Aarseth, are superficial: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">The ideological forces surrounding new technology produce a
                     rhetoric of novelty, differentiation, and freedom that works to obscure the
                     more profound structural kinships between superficially heterogeneous
                     media</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="14"/>
               </cit>. By focusing on the role of the reader in the construction of meaning,
               regardless of the medium in which meaning is delivered, and by redefining writing
               itself as a <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">material machine</quote> (and therefore only
               superficially different from new media) Aarseth dismisses arguments for cybertexts’
               newness as being premised on extraneous distinctions <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="18–24"/>. In this way, Aarseth levels the field between digital and
               non-digital literary objects and redefines <term>cybertext</term>, not in material or
               technological terms, but as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">a <emph>perspective</emph> on all forms of textuality</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="18"/>
               </cit>. This view fails, however, to account for actual material and technical
               differences between media, as well as the material-social differences (i.e. in the
               skills and knowledges required to produce such works) that necessitate a more nuanced
               account of new media as facilitating new rhetorical modes.</p>
            <p>More recent criticism has begun to grapple with the idea of media writing as a
               practice that is embedded in <emph>both</emph> rhetorical and material networks of
               machine and institution. Mary Hocks and Michelle Kendrick consider the <soCalled>modern constitution</soCalled> in terms of the purifying impulses that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hocks2003">dichotomize our experiences with visual and verbal
                     communication systems</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hocks2003" loc="3"/>
               </cit>. The binary that emerges within the humanities between word and image points
               to a larger constitutional dichotomy between old modes of scholarly practice and new
               modes. This dichotomy, often described in critical discourse as a contest among
                  media<note>In <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New Media</title>,
                  Jay David Bolter and Richard Grusin have framed the contest among media forms in
                  terms of what they call <q>remediation,</q> which describes
                  the ways media <q>compete</q> with one another for cultural
                  significance. Bolter and Grusin are among many critics — N. Katherine Hayles, Mark
                  Hansen, Friedrich Kittler, Jerome McGann — concerned with what they regard as a
                  rivalry between new media and old media (comprising what Hayles has called the
                     <q>new media ecology</q>). One form that this competition
                  has taken among humanities scholars is what Hocks and Kendrick describe as the
                     <q>new battleground between word and image,</q> where
                  word stands in for the old and image stands in for the new. Hocks and Kendrick
                  point out, however, that word and image, like old and new media, have always
                  operated dialogically, rather than dichotomously, in a <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#hocks2003">dynamic interplay</quote>
                     <ptr loc="1" target="#hocks2003"/>
                  </cit>. Within the academy this supposed rivalry must also be seen as a convenient
                  narrative that sutures over two underlying anxieties: anxiety of obsolescence
                  among critics who perceive themselves as working in <soCalled>old
                     media,</soCalled> and on a more fundamental level, anxiety regarding the status
                  of the human (and humanism, and the humanities) in relation to technology.</note>,
               produces two contradictory purification narratives, the first being overstated claims
               of new media’s radical newness and the second being claims of its radical sameness.
               Early enthusiasts of hypertext, Michelle Kendrick points out, have claimed that
               electronic writing, by embedding technologically associative structures in a
               non-linear way, function more like the natural human brain than the artificial medium
               of print. In this way, hypertext enthusiasts have claimed that new media <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kendrick2001">truly reveals the subject, for it enacts the patterns of
                     cognition in the human mind[…]</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kendrick2001" loc="233"/>
               </cit>. Such claims, Kendrick writes, rely on the notion that the subject of writing
               in print culture has been rendered obsolete by the emergence of new media <ptr target="#kendrick2001" loc="233"/>.</p>
            <p>This ongoing debate about new media’s functional (and in some cases even biological)
               difference from old media contributes to a double erasure, for scholars working in
               multimedia, of both their intellectual contributions and their material labor. If
               multimedia is regarded as no different from other scholarly forms, the complex labor
               practices and new knowledges required to produce scholarly works of multimedia, such
               as interface design, coding, video production, hardware support, institutional
               interactions and so on, may be devalued to the extent that they are seen more as
               service (akin to maintaining a department’s computer lab or website) or not seen as
               meaningful scholarly activity at all. This leads to the reduction of scholarly
               multimedia to the status of <soCalled>unacademic,</soCalled> suggesting that it is
               somehow less intellectually significant than <soCalled>equivalent</soCalled> works
               produced in print because the differences between media are
                  <soCalled>superficial.</soCalled> Here we find ourselves in a bind similar to the
                  <q>old/new</q> argument. On the one hand, if we claim that
               digital scholarship is old scholarship translated to a new format, we elide the ways
               in which multimedia fundamentally changes scholarly argument; on the other hand, if
               we regard multimedia as radically other to scholarly production (i.e.
                  <soCalled>new</soCalled>), the intellectual and rhetorical expertise of multimedia
               authors/engineers may also be discredited insofar as they are working in a medium not
               recognized within the institution as scholarly enough. Furthermore, as a consequence
               of casting academic labor practices in these ways, the material practices of
                  <emph>all</emph> scholarship are erased, as traditional scholarship is purified as
               a solely intellectual act. Narratives of purification that dictate which scholarly
               practices count as intellectually significant and which don’t foreclose the
               possibility of accounting for multimedia as a viable scholarly activity and limit our
               understanding of how scholarly activity more generally is socially and
               technologically constructed.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Old Media and New Media: The Problem of (Scholarly) Humanism</head>
            <p>The emergence within the academy of scholarly multimedia as a new rhetorical genre is
               certainly not the first time that technological change has prompted anxious
               reconsiderations of humanism. Rather, it exists as one localized example of an
               ongoing concern about the status of the human in relation to technology. In <title rend="italic">Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</title>, Friedrich A. Kittler argues
               that media threaten, indeed have always threatened, to render the liberal humanist
               (and by extension, we would argue, the humanist scholar) obsolete <ptr target="#kittler1999"/>. According to Kittler, prior to the invention of devices
               such as the phonograph that could record sound waves, writing was imagined as the
               only means to transmit the voice of the author. In this respect, the voice of the
               author, as it was imagined by readers, functioned as a kind of <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kittler1999">fictitious elevated phallus born from the alphabet</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kittler1999" loc="70"/>
               </cit>. With early recording devices, the modern engineer was able to capture the
               waves of human vocalizations and could thus reproduce this <q>fictitious phallus</q> technologically, calling into question the purity of
               the phallic voice. Kittler elaborates on this in his discussion of Rilke in which
               Rilke describes phonographic emanations as <q>primal
                  sounds.</q> In other words, phonographic recordings, which seem to capture the
               human voice <q>as it really is,</q> offered the illusion of
               primacy (immediacy) and in this way appear to outperform the written word: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#kittler1999">With the demise of writing’s storage monopoly comes to an end
                     a love that was not only one of literature’s many possible subjects but also
                     its very own media technology: since 1800 perfectly alphabetized female readers
                     have been able to endow letters with a beloved voice. But tracing primal sounds
                     has, as Rilke put it, nothing to do with <q>the presence of
                        mind and grace of love</q>.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="70" target="#kittler1999"/>
               </cit> In this passage, we see a crucial split between mind and body take shape: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kittler1999">machines have taken over the function of the central nervous
                     system</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kittler1999" loc="51"/>
               </cit>. Machines are primal and embodied and therefore threaten the subject of
               writing. Suddenly, with the emerging importance of the machine engineer, there is the
               capacity for writing without a subject-author, and so the role of the subject-author
               is no longer entirely stable. One important consequence of machines taking over the
               function of the central nervous system is that, for the first time, memory
               suqpersedes <q>spirit</q> as the imminent characteristic of
               subjectivity, yet memory is no longer solely the domain of the mind or brain. It can
               also be scratched on surfaces. Memory has now been externalized by media
               technologies. The consequence of this externalization of memory, Kittler argues
               rather dramatically, is that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kittler1999">Media render Man[…]superfluous[…]The fictional elevated
                     phallus shrivels up[…]the engineer has finally beaten the author</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kittler1999" loc="78"/>
               </cit>. As Kittler’s historical analysis reveals, this perceived contest between
               media technologies (captured here through the figure of the engineer) and the liberal
               humanist subject-as-author (presumed here to be male or at least to possess the
               phallus) is ongoing. More interestingly, we see this contest structured around yet
               another series of dichotomous relations: author versus engineer, soul versus memory,
               writing versus recording, humanities (e.g. the poetry of Rilke) versus science and
               technology (e.g. phonographic recordings), and ultimately, mind versus
                  body.<note>Willard McCarty, in <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing</title>,
                  looks to engineering as occupying the mid-point between science and humanities
                  insofar as engineering leads to the <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2005">genesis of new
                     knowledge,</quote> yet not through scientific experimentation (although it does
                  depend on an interaction with scientific knowledge) nor through a philosophical
                  detachment from materiality <ptr loc="51" target="#mccarty2005"/>. The new media
                  practitioner, as engineer, facilitates the emergence of new knowledge by
                  interacting with the material world.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In <title rend="quotes">The Condition of Virtuality</title>
               <ptr target="#hayles1999a"/> and <title rend="italic">How We Became Posthuman</title>
               <ptr target="#hayles1999b"/>, N. Katherine Hayles’ offers a similar narrative of the
               emergence of the tension between mind and body, which she casts as a tension between
               virtuality and materiality. As a result of post-World War II scientific discoveries
               (namely, DNA and genetic code) we (meaning Westerners) have experienced a paradigm
               shift in the ways we imaginCe the <soCalled>self.</soCalled> Whereas prior to these
               discoveries we imagined the material body and the <soCalled>self.</soCalled> as a
               unified, self-identical whole (this is what Hayles calls humanism), in the post-DNA
               age the body is re-imagined as a container or husk for the self, which is itself
               re-imagined as an informational pattern produced by and through genetic code. Hence,
               writes Hayles, we see the emergence of a posthuman dialectic — information versus
               materiality — where the former trumps the latter as the root cause of the (illusion
               of the) liberal humanist subject. <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles1999b">A defining characteristic of
                  the present cultural moment,</quote> Hayles writes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles1999b">is the belief that information can circulate unchanged among
                     different material substrates</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hayles1999b" loc="1"/>
               </cit>. The body, in such a posthuman arrangement, becomes the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles1999b">original prosthesis</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hayles1999b" loc="1"/>
               </cit>. This ongoing tension between materiality and informatics contributes to our
               understanding of how we in the academy think about multimedia in relation to other,
               more <soCalled>legitimized</soCalled> modes of scholarly practice. For one, the
               materiality of multimedia scholarship is constantly under erasure insofar as we
               imagine that the heart of any scholarly work (the intellectual part) is purely
                  <soCalled>informational,</soCalled> as if, like Athena, it springs forth from the
               scholar’s mind and takes up residency inside the book or article or machine. Hayles,
               drawing on Richard Doyle, calls it an <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles1999b">impossible
                  inversion,</quote> where the informational pattern or code is imagined as actually
               producing the thing on which the pattern nonetheless depends <ptr target="#hayles1999b" loc="293"/>.</p>
            <p>In the case of humanities scholarship and the methods by which we evaluate and
               validate research practices, Hayles’ <soCalled>impossible
                  inversion</soCalled> surfaces as a practice of purification wherein the embodied or
               material aspects of scholarly work are rendered secondary to (rather than
               constitutive of) scholarly argument. We imagine that the intellectual content of
               scholarship pre-exists its material enactment. Deborah Lines Andersen, in her
               introduction to <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Tenure, Promotion,
                  and Review Process</title>, reiterates this view: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#andersen2004">The critical issue in academe is what one does with what one
                     has. It is the act of creation that defines the digital scholar. Tools such as
                     computers and software programs are critical to this creation, but they are
                     only the means to this end.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="3" target="#andersen2004"/>
               </cit> While <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship</title> is a valuable and
               ground-breaking discussion of the institutional problems faced by those working in
               multimedia, Andersen’s attempt to define digital scholarship as independent from the
               medium in which it is produced tends to undermine her argument for the value of
               digital work. We should be mindful, then, of Hayles’ criticism of similar virtualist
               accounts that disregard the material substrates upon which informational patterns
               depend. Perhaps understandably, given its computational origins, Andersen sees
               digital scholarship as better suited to natural or social sciences where research
               tends to be presented graphically (for example, in the form of maps or charts) or
               quantitatively. She does her best to argue for the application of these existing
               strengths to a wider range of cultural materials. <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#andersen2004">Arts, languages, literature, philosophy, and religion have not
                     naturally embraced digital scholarship in the ways exhibited by scientists and
                     social scientists. There are a variety of very good reasons for this
                     resistance. Foremost among these reasons is the type of material humanists
                     study. Diaries, plays, music scores, novels, paintings, religious works, and
                     philosophical treatises, to name a few, do not lend themselves to
                     quantification.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="9" target="#andersen2004"/>
               </cit> Along with arts, languages, literature, philosophy, and religion, we might add
               film studies, visual culture, cultural studies, science studies, and new media, all
               of which lend themselves quite well to scholarly analyses using multimedia precisely
               because they are not constrained by the purely textual.</p>
            <p>More to the point, this view fails to account for versions of scholarly multimedia,
               particularly within the humanities, that do <emph>more</emph> than facilitate textual
               or rhetorical analyses of print literature or art objects through the use of a
               computer. In part, Andersen’s restrictive view of digital scholarship within the
               humanities stems from an historically narrow understanding of the diversity of
               humanities research as fundamentally ancillary to the text, rather than
               transformative. Certainly Andersen is not alone in her assumptions about the meaning
               of digital scholarship within the humanities, nor is such an argument without value
               for the crucial scholarship of digital annotation, translation and preservation.
               Again, <ptr target="#hockey2000"/>, <ptr target="#drucker2002"/>, and <ptr target="#mcgann2004"/> are among those who imagine media technologies as useful to
               humanities scholars insofar as they facilitate the capturing, cataloging, and
               indexing of <soCalled>electronic texts,</soCalled> and rightly so <ptr target="#hockey2000" loc="1"/>. And while we recognize the crucial value in this
               practical application of technology, we resist the argument that electronic archival
               work offers a totalizing view of the possibilities offered by digital humanities.
               Such a limiting perspective reveals precisely the sort of virtualism that, as Hayles
               points out, relies on the unusual notion that information can exist independently of
               its medium: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#hayles1999a">The illusion that information is separate from materiality
                     leads not only to a dangerous split between information and meaning but also to
                     a flattening of the space of theoretical inquiry. If we accept that the
                     materiality of the world is immaterial to our concerns, we are likely to miss
                     the very complexities that theory at its best tries to excavate and
                     understand.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="30" target="#hayles1999a"/>
               </cit> This passage from Hayles bolsters her claim that literature
                  <emph>itself</emph> is undergoing a revolution as a result of digital technologies
               and that, as literary critics, we must confront these changes by incorporating an
               awareness of a text’s materiality into our analyses. We would extend this argument to
               suggest that the very practices of literary and cultural analysis are undergoing a
               parallel revolution and that we must also confront these changes and embrace the full
               potential of multimedia as a rich, complex scholarly medium. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>How Scholarly Media Restructure Intellectual Work</head>
            <p>All of these discussions, from the early hypertextual emphasis on the newness of
               multimedia, through critiques of this newness in favor of a continuation of existing
               textual practices through to, finally, the important recognition of the material
               embeddedness of media that must accompany any evaluation of what it means to be a
               digital humanist, present a trajectory of media criticism that moves us closer and
               closer to a recognition of the crucial <term>materiality</term> of digital rhetorics.
               From this trajectory, we can begin to formulate a true manifesto for digital
               scholarship. If we are to argue for the value of multimedia work in the academic
               milieu, we must confront the physicality of rhetorical practices themselves. On the
               most physical level: what can we make, given the material constraints of the machines
               we work with? And on the rhetorical level: what can we argue (or not argue) given the
               structures we're given to work with (software packages, database design) which are
               themselves constrained by issues of memory storage, drive and processing speed? But
               most importantly: why and how does the academy seek to constantly devalue the work we
               do as multimedia scholars by casting it as instrumental practices of rhetorical and
               material labor, rather than the intellectual practices of analysis and criticism –
               and what can we do about this perception?</p>
            <p>Addressing these important issues requires, first, that we break open our
               understanding of what scholarly multimedia is and can become. Andersen’s primary
               example of digital humanities scholarship consists of digitizing Jane Austen’s work
               in its entirety in order to perform database queries of main characters. As Andersen
               points out, this is hardly an appropriate or efficient scholarly use of computing
               technology. But then again, computer assisted textual analysis, while valuable, is
               not the only role computing plays within the humanities, and such a view ignores
               recent (and not so recent) forays into argument-driven scholarly multimedia, notably
               a number of academic presses who have experimented with publishing original works of
               scholarship in laserdisc, CD-ROM, and DVD-Rom format.<note>Notably, Keller Easterling
                  and Rick Prelinger’s <title rend="italic">Call it Home: The House That Private
                     Enterprise Built</title>
                  <ptr target="#easterling1992"/>, from the pioneering Voyager series of laserdiscs
                  and CD-ROMs produced in the late 80s and early 90s; Greg VanHoosier-Carey and
                  Ellen Strain’s grant-supported <title rend="italic">Griffith in Context: A
                     Multimedia Exploration of D. W. Griffith’s The Birth of a Nation</title>
                  <ptr target="#strain2004"/>, distributed by Norton; and the University of
                  Pennsylvania Press’s <title rend="italic">Mariner10</title> DVD-rom series working
                  at the boundaries of science and the humanities, which includes such titles as
                     <title rend="italic">Red Planet: Scientific and Cultural Encounters with
                     Mars</title>
                  <ptr target="#markley2001"/>, <title rend="italic">Medicine and Humanistic
                     Understanding</title>
                  <ptr target="#vannatta2005"/>, and <title rend="italic">Biofutures: Owning Body
                     Parts and Information</title>
                  <ptr target="#mitchell2008"/>. Eastgate Press, long the preeminent home for
                  literary hypertexts, has also extended its primary mandate to publish electronic
                  fiction, and has embraced scholarly work such as Roderick Coover’s <title rend="italic">Cultures in Webs</title>
                  <ptr target="#coover2002"/>.</note> In terms of rhetorical strategies, the
               significance of these works is their contribution to humanities knowledge where the
               contribution itself exists as medium-dependent and cannot simply be reduced to acts
               of digital archiving or remediations of a pre-existing scholarly book. On a more
               basic level, the materiality of these works — both in terms of production and
               delivery in tangible format — leads us to consider the immense technical labor
               involved in producing scholarly multimedia.</p>
            <p>It is important to note that one of the chief characteristics of the above titles is
               that they are <soCalled>published</soCalled> in tangible form — CD-ROM, DVD-ROM or
               laserdisc — and thus at least benefit from the fetishization so readily apparent in
               the academy of the print document as a physical form. More recent works in multimedia
               (mostly web-based works) confound even this basic understanding of what constitutes a
                  <soCalled>text.</soCalled> Roderick Coover’s <title rend="italic">Voyage Into the
                  Unknown</title>
               <ptr target="#coover2008"/>, an <soCalled>interactive documentary</soCalled>
               about John Wesley Powell’s journey down the Colorado River in 1869, consists of
               tagged maps, first-and third-person narratives and analyses, and invites readers to
               integrate all these modes into thesir own <soCalled>journey.</soCalled> Additionally,
               we must account for the many non-<soCalled>publishable</soCalled> but infrastructural
               multimedia projects proliferating in the community: the development of authoring
               software such as if:Book’s SOPHIE and Juan B. Gutierrez’ <title rend="italic">Literatronic</title>; the CommentPress project supported by MediaCommons; and the
               open peer-review model pioneered by Noah Wardrip-Fruin for his book <title rend="italic">Expressive Processing</title>
               <ptr target="#wardrip2009"/>. Evaluating these works as scholarly activity has proven
               difficult in an academy so wedded to the physical artifact as indicative of
                  <soCalled>real</soCalled> scholarship.</p>
            <p>Finally, digital scholarship can take on radical, literally physical forms. To take
               as one case in point, consider Marcel O’Gorman’s <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title>
               <ptr target="#ogorman2005"/>. Described as <q>Critique,
                  Performance, Installation, Education,</q> this unruly hybrid of art
               performance, argument and exposition is by far one of the most provocative examples
               to date of a re-embodiment of humanities scholarship. While running on a treadmill
               that generates a multimedia display, O’Gorman critiques our culture’s increasing
               denial of the body and our increasingly sedentary lifestyles. He delivers a smart,
               theoretically informed presentation about the relationships between technology,
               death, violence, mobility, consumerism, corporeality, disability, and even
               nationality and national borders. The entire performance lasts about one hour.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>Marcel O'Gorman performing <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title>, 2005.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of O'Gorman's onstage performance.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>How might such a performance be classified as a work of scholarship? It isn’t
                  <soCalled>publishable</soCalled> in any traditional sense, though the ideas are
               sophisticated enough in that respect. Most troubling, to the academy, is the fact
               that it would be impossible to disentangle the content of <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title> from its delivery medium — its dynamic presentation. It is
               certainly more than a conference presentation. And while O’Gorman is an artist among
               other things, <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title> isn’t easily classified as an
               art installation. For one, unlike other somewhat famous <soCalled>body
                  artists</soCalled> like Stelarc, <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title> is not
               just about manipulating the body in visually provocative or sensual ways. While
               running, O’Gorman delivers a thesis-driven academic argument. He cites Nietzsche,
               Kittler, Virilio, Haraway, Ernest Becker, among other scholars. In all aspects,
                  <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title> represents a new frontier in reimagining
               humanities scholarship. It also foregrounds the roles of both multimedia and physical
               bodies in the practice of humanities scholarship where the stakes of that scholarship
               are no less than (bodily) death and (intellectual) obsolescence.</p>
            <p>Jay David Bolter has suggested that theoretically informed multimedia performances
               such as O’Gorman’s <title rend="italic">Dreadmill</title> are often the products of
               new media artists and thus are only tangentially related to the academy <ptr target="#bolter2000" loc="24"/>. He points this out in order to argue that a key
               dichotomy that takes shape within the academy is that of theory versus practice
               (which, of course, is another deployment of the mind/body dichotomy). While this
               divide between theory and practice may have been clearly in place in the past,
               performative scholarship such as O’Gorman’s threatens the integrity of precisely such
               a divide. O’Gorman’s status as an academic as well as new media artist is well
               established; he has been a tenured Associate Professor of English at the University
               of Detroit Mercy; he is now in the Department of English at the University of
               Waterloo, where he also directs the <ref target="http://criticalmedia.uwaterloo.ca">Critical Media Lab</ref>. In other words, as both a multimedia performance artist
               and scholar, O’Gorman embodies a new kind of academic professional — a cyborg scholar
               — who answers Bolter’s call, that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bolter2000">media theory engage with the practice of digital
                     media</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bolter2000" loc="25"/>
               </cit>. O’Gorman demonstrates the kind of hybrid scholarship possible in our current
               digital age, in which the tools available to humanities scholars extend far beyond
               the textual to include the material, the technical, and the rhetorical (not to be
               confused with the textual). Gregory VanHoosier-Carey and Ellen Strain, practitioners
               of scholarly multimedia themselves, frame these new potentialities offered by new
               media in terms of interface design which they site as an often invisible locus of
               rhetoric praxis. Interface design, they argue, creates <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#strain2003">architected meaning, an arena within which the demonstration
                     of humanities methodologies can take on a dynamic form</quote>
                  <ptr loc="259" target="#strain2003"/>
               </cit>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <soCalled>Selling</soCalled> New Media: the Problem of Genre and Tenure</head>
            <p>Confusion within the institution over how to categorize and evaluate scholarly
               multimedia often amounts to a tension between <quote rend="inline" source="#andersen2004">the application of
                  digital scholarship</quote>
               <emph>to</emph> research, to quote Andersen, as opposed to doing digital scholarship
               as research <ptr target="#andersen2004" loc="11"/>. This tension seems symptomatic of
               a larger problem within the institution to reckon with the emergence of new media,
               particularly at the level of promotion and tenure where the traditional model of
               humanities scholarship as intellectual labor dominates. According to this traditional
               model, a scholarly publication in an online journal, even if the writing itself was
               performed on a word processor, <soCalled>counts</soCalled> as digital scholarship
               primarily because it can be easily be measured according to traditional print
               standards: is the journal peer-reviewed? Does the journal have a reputation of being
               intellectually rigorous? While such online publications, which have significant merit
               in their own right, are in the practical sense digital, they don’t necessarily depart
               significantly from print-based journals. Nonetheless, e-journal articles are often
               devalued for the simple reason that they do not appear in print form.<note>An
                  important example of an online journal that resists being easily reduced to a
                  digital equivalent of a print journal is <title rend="italic">Electronic Book
                     Review</title>, edited by Joseph Tabbi, which departs from the traditional
                  linear layout of a journal by relying instead on <soCalled>threads,</soCalled>
                  each of which has its own editor. In this way, <title rend="italic">EBR</title> is
                  able to expand out in multiple directions simultaneously and the content of a
                  particular topic is not confined to a single issue.</note> By relying on this
               older and, frankly, obsolete model for defining and evaluating scholarship, we
               continue to privilege content over form, intellectual labor over physical labor, and
               print over digital media.</p>
            <p>Scholars working in multimedia have been forced to reckon with this problem and must
               continue to engage with fundamentally conservative analogies to argue for the
               scholarly merit of the project. The first project in Penn Press’ <title rend="italic">Mariner10</title> series, <title rend="italic">Red Planet</title>
               <ptr target="#markley2001"/>, led by Robert Markley (at some professional risk) had
               to be <soCalled>pitched</soCalled> to presses, granting agencies, and fellow
               colleagues as a multimedia version of a scholarly book. The argument necessary to
               secure publication and scholarly credibility even took the form of equating the
               storage capacity of a DVD-ROM to the thickness of a book: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#burgess2003">This storage capacity means that a DVD-ROM can hold several
                     hours of high-resolution video, the equivalent of a book ninety feet
                     thick…</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burgess2003" loc="67–68"/>
               </cit>. While describing the project in terms of such an equivalence seemed a
               necessary step at the time to gain entrance into the humanities scholarly canon in a
               way that would <soCalled>matter,</soCalled> especially for collaborators who were
               untenured or still in graduate school, such a decision would also force the project’s
               authors to reconsider the implications of such a choice in terms of the politics of
               remediation. Were the authors really challenging the conventions of humanities
               scholarship by producing such a work of multimedia, or were they hampered by old
               standards for what counts as legitimate scholarship? Were they, by claiming to
               remediate the scholarly book, limiting the potential of what we were already
               recognizing as a new and valuable rhetorical genre? The answer to this last question
               is certainly yes, and points to <title rend="italic">Red Planet</title> as a
               first-generation (and conservative, given what can be done with the form) work of
               scholarly multimedia. Nonetheless, much was gained by working through the
               institutional and rhetorical challenges that multimedia practitioners face in
               articulating the significance of their scholarly activities.</p>
            <p>As we have suggested, scholarly multimedia has often been situated outside of the
               traditional model of scholarly activity insofar as its practitioners participate in a
               host of activities rarely recognized as <soCalled>intellectually
                  significant.</soCalled> Coding, shooting and editing digital video, interface and
               information design, data-basing, troubleshooting, debugging: these activities often
               fall outside the purview of traditional notions of humanities scholarship. In a
               supreme irony, it is only after the project has itself become the object of critical
               inquiry, for instance in a scholarly print article reflecting on the visual rhetorics
               of multimedia design, do these activities come into view. Two examples of such
               post-production publications include, as we have previously mentioned, <title rend="quotes">The Dialogics of New Media: Video, Visualization, and Narrative in
                  Red Planet: Scientific and Cultural Encounters with <title rend="italic">Mars</title>
               </title>
               <ptr target="#burgess2003"/>, as well as <title rend="quotes">Eloquent Interfaces:
                  Humanities-Based Analysis in the Age of Hypermedia</title>
               <ptr target="#strain2003"/>. In both articles, which appear in <title rend="italic">Eloquent Images: Writing Visually in New Media</title>
               <ptr target="#hocks2003"/>, authors reflect critically on their collaborative
               multimedia projects; thus the articles bear two crucial markers. First, they offer a
               kind of testimonial of the work accomplished in the multimedia project itself,
               explaining some of the works’ features, and some of the authors’ technical choices;
               Second, the articles argue for the importance of the combined intellectual and
               material labor practices that went into the multimedia projects. These
               characteristics of early articles about the practice of scholarly multimedia suggest
               rather strongly that multimedia is a rich medium in which to work. However, these
               articles also demonstrate that, at the time of their publication, it still seemed
               necessary to argue aggressively for the merits of multimedia as a new scholarly
               genre, suggesting that multimedia remained, and continues to remain, outside of
               accepted definitions of what counts as legitimate scholarship. This perception of the
               need to defend the significant and unique contributions of multimedia has been of
               particular concern for scholars who have embraced multimedia production as their
               primary research activity despite obvious professional challenges and risks. More
               importantly, the emergence of scholarly multimedia points to a fundamental conflict
               between traditional views of the humanities scholar and the new digital scholar who
               threatens to reveal the former’s purchase on reality.</p>
            <p>One way to trace the origins of the traditionalist view is to situate evaluations of
               humanities research in terms of its perceived difference from natural or social
               sciences research. Multimedia, because it relies overtly on digital technologies, has
               been historically situated in an intermediary position between these two disciplines.
               The definition of digital scholarship offered by the traditional model depends on
               seeing scientific research as quantitative and graphical and humanities research as
               textual and/or rhetorical. Even when humanities scholarship does make use of visual
               or graphical content, for instance in art history, the graphical nature of the
               scholarship is commonly viewed as the subject of the investigation (akin to
               scientific data) rather than a rhetorical or research tool (akin to a graphical
               representation of the data). Scholarly multimedia, on the other hand, relies heavily
               on graphical interfaces, navigational schemas, and visual layout as well as text as
               essential rhetorical tools for the construction of arguments and the production of
               meaning. In this way, multimedia occupies a liminal space between or even beyond
               science and humanities as a new mode of scholarship and is, as a consequence,
               battered by traditional definitions of what constitutes <term>research</term> within
               the humanities. Is research found in the production stage or embodied within the
               final new media object? Is it the rhetorical analysis one produces as part of the
               multimedia work, or the analysis one writes about the production process, or the
               rhetorical analysis one writes about the new media object? Ironically, because new
               media work has been so hampered by accepted models of humanities scholarship that
               privilege content over form and intellectual labor over technical labor, the
               temptation exists to see print-articles or books about multimedia as more valid than
               the multimedia work itself. In fact, a host of well-known
                  <soCalled>multimedia</soCalled> scholars have themselves never actually practiced
               multimedia. This is by no means to suggest that scholarship <emph>about</emph>
               multimedia is not valid or important or that all critics of multimedia must,
               themselves, become practitioners (in the same way that we would not expect literary
               critics to also become poets or novelists). Rather, we should take care not to
               confuse storage medium (book versus multimedia) with rhetorical genre (book versus
               multimedia) lest we fall into the trap of technological determinism, or worse,
               technophobia, when evaluating the merits of a scholarly work.</p>
            <p>One way to draw ourselves out of this bind is to pay attention to the key overlap
               between representationalism (what humanities scholars are assumed to do) and
               performativity (what bodies and machines are assumed to do) in the context of the
               technologies we work with in producing multimedia. In <title rend="italic">Embodying
                  Technesis</title>, and later in <title rend="italic">Bodies in Code</title>, Mark
               Hansen calls for a deeper understanding of the role embodiment plays in producing
               reality (<ptr target="#hansen2000"/>, <ptr target="#hansen2006"/>). At the same time,
               he argues, we must develop a more robust, materialist account of the ontological role
               of technology. Technological change, he states, is so foundational to human
               experience that it has taken on an <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2000">extracultural, extrasocial dimension</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hansen2000" loc="3"/>
               </cit>. This transformation invites us to reconsider technology in terms of its
               resistance to <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2000">explicit cultural thematization</quote> or <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2000">representational capture</quote> so that we can come to understand
               technology as an agent of <quote rend="inline" source="#hansen2000">material complexification</quote> that
               does not rely solely on cognition or human intervention for its evolution (<ptr target="#hansen2000" loc="56"/>, <ptr target="#hansen2006" loc="19"/>).</p>
            <p>Hansen’s argument in both books, that we must move beyond a representationalist
               understanding of humankind’s relationship to technology by focusing on embodiment,
               suggests that we should also rethink our own identity as scholars and intellectuals,
               in particular the ways in which our scholarly activities are bound up at a very deep
               level with the technologies we use to practice our craft. We believe scholarly
               multimedia offers a promising answer to Hansen’s call insofar as it can truly perform
               at the nexus of what Hayles calls our posthuman <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2005">mindbodies</quote>
                  <ptr loc="7" target="#hayles2005"/>
               </cit>. Technology does not merely assist us as representationalist scholars. Rather,
               it transforms us into embodied agents.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Performing Scholarship: A Radical (Technological) Act</head>
            <p>In complicating the traditional academic model of disembodied intellectual activity,
               scholarly multimedia tends toward what Andrew Pickering calls the <quote rend="inline" source="#pickering1995">performative idiom,</quote> a model that foregrounds the material
               agencies (both human and nonhuman) that emerge as essential to the scholarly
               production of knowledge <ptr loc="7" target="#pickering1995"/>. Scholarly multimedia
               stands as an unruly and undisciplined body of work that challenges humanities
               scholars’ claims about what we <soCalled>do</soCalled> precisely because it changes
               what we do at the material level, revealing that what has been overvalued all along
               is the immaterial, intellectual act that has often been conceived of as existing
               independently from social, institutional, and material contexts. In this respect,
               scholarly multimedia makes visible what Marcel O’Gorman calls the <term>material
                  remainder</term>, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#ogorman2006">the repressed technological element of humanities
                     scholarship</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ogorman2006" loc="6"/>
               </cit>. This material remainder includes the material-technical labor practices of
               multimedia scholars as well as the material contexts and constraints of the scholarly
               production of knowledge in general.</p>
            <p>By making these aspects of scholarly practice visible, multimedia reveals the
               repressed other, the material monster if you will, of scholarly production and
               invites scholars working in this genre to take seriously O’Gorman’s recommendation
               that we engage with the materiality of our own knowledge-productions: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#ogorman2006">If the remainder is hidden or repressed, monstrous
                        <soCalled>other</soCalled> of the conventional academic discourse, then
                     those who seek to change that conventional discourse might engage in a science
                     of <term>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">anagnorisis</foreign>
                     </term>; that is, a science of invention and knowledge-production that depends
                     on a face-to-face encounter with the monster.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="4" target="#ogorman2006"/>
               </cit> In part, this engagement can be achieved by making visible the strategies that
               scholars employ to construct arguments that are valued for their capacity to produce
               closure and containment, and to construct a scholarly subject-of-writing as a
               hyper-rational, often-disembodied subject, a subject described by Bruno Latour in
                  <title rend="italic">Pandora’s Hope</title> as a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#latour1999">mind-in-a-vat</quote>
                  <ptr target="#latour1999" loc="12"/>
               </cit>. The denial of the material remainder of writing is too horrible to
               contemplate for long: Latour’s formulation of a giant brain floating in a vat of
               fluid attached by wires to a CPU, or worse, a typewriter, or, still worse, pen and
               paper. A single pattern, a single brain, a single author alone in a small dark room,
               immersed in the gray matter of others who came before. This is the image cultivated
               by the notion of an <soCalled>immaterial</soCalled> disembodied humanities scholar
               resistant to rediscovering the materiality of his or her own activities.</p>
            <p>In <title rend="quotes">Interactive Technology and the Remediation of the Subject of
                  Writing,</title> Michelle Kendrick writes that early critical discourse about the
               revolutionary nature of hypertext centered on its supposed ability to better reflect
               the way we think — in nonlinear, networked associations. Such claims, she argues,
               depend on a dubious double logic: that through its intensification of media
               technologies, hypertext erases mediation. <quote rend="inline" source="#kendrick2001">This double
                  logic,</quote> Kendrick continues, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#kendrick2001">promises metaphysical transcendence, while paradoxically
                     grounding such transcendence in technology’s materiality and
                     specificity</quote>
                  <ptr loc="233" target="#kendrick2001"/>
               </cit>. Kendrick’s crucial insight, that all subjects-of-writing are produced by and
               through material-technological interventions, invites us to reconsider traditional
               print-based scholarship in order to uncover this double-logic. Her critique reveals
               the incoherence of the subject-of-writing that is covered over by media-specific
               strategies such as dense, esoteric, often impersonal academic prose, complex citation
               practices, as well as the conventions of single-authorship. Such strategies continue
               to set the standards by which we define and judge ourselves as scholars, and this
               evaluation is extended through the peer-review process as well as through the
               promotion and tenure process. Multimedia threatens to undermine the establishment of
               these standards, not because, as early hypertext enthusiasts claimed, it disperses
               the writing subject over vast networks or because it liberates the reader from the
               tyranny of the disembodied, single author. Rather, scholarly multimedia threatens to
               re-embody the heretofore disembodied intellectual by embracing a more performative
               mode or, to borrow from feminist philosopher of science Nancy Tuana, an
                  <emph>interactionist</emph> mode of scholarly practice that emphasizes the <quote rend="inline" source="#tuana2001">emergent interplay</quote> between <quote rend="inline" source="#tuana2001">human
                  materiality and the materiality of the more than human</quote>
               <ptr target="#tuana2001" loc="221–223"/>. The multimedia scholar, by taking seriously
               the materiality of knowledge production, embodies an intellectual identity that is
               dispersed over material, rhetorical, and technical networks — a crucial
               transformation that must be acknowledged when assessing <soCalled>what
                  counts</soCalled> as scholarly activity in the academy.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Aarseth 1997" xml:id="aarseth1997" key="aarseth1997">Aarseth, E. <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>. Johns Hopkins
               University Press, Baltimore (1997).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andersen2004" label="Andersen 2004" key="andersen2004">Andersen, D. L.
                  <title rend="quotes">Introduction,</title> in D. L. Andersen (ed), <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Tenure, Promotion, and Review
                  Process</title>. ME Sharpe, London and New York (2004): 3-24.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Ball 2004" xml:id="ball2004" key="ball2004">Ball, C. E. <title rend="quotes">Show, not tell: The value of new media scholarship.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Computers and Composition</title>, 21 (2004): 403-425.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bolter2000" label="Bolter &amp; Grusin 2000" key="bolter2000">Bolter, J.
               D., and Grusin, R. <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New Media</title>.
               MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Burgess et al. 2003" xml:id="burgess2003" key="burgess2003">Burgess, H. J.,
               Hamming, J., and Markley, R. <title rend="quotes">The Dialogics of New Media: Video,
                  Visualization, and Narrative in Red Planet: Scientific and Cultural Encounters
                  with Mars,</title> in M. E. Hocks and M. R. Kendrick (eds), <title rend="italic">Eloquent Images: Word and Image in the Age of New Media</title>. Cambridge,
               Massachusetts: MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2003): 61-85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coover2002" label="Coover 2002" key="coover2002">Coover, R. <title rend="italic">Cultures in Webs: Working in Hypermedia with the Documentary
                  Image</title>. CD-ROM. Eastgate Systems Inc, Watertown (2002).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Coover 2008" xml:id="coover2008" key="coover2008">Coover, R. <title rend="italic">Unknown Territories: Voyage Into the Unknown</title>. <ref target="http://www.unknownterritories.org">http://www.unknownterritories.org</ref>
               (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2002" label="Drucker 2002" key="drucker2002b">Drucker, J. <title rend="quotes">Theory as Praxis: The Poetics of Electronic Textuality
                  (review),</title>
               <title rend="italic">Modernism/Modernity</title> 9:4 (2002): 683-691.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Easterling &amp; Prelinger 1992" xml:id="easterling1992" key="easterling1992">Easterling, K. and Prelinger, R. <title rend="italic">Call It
                  Home: The House that Private Enterprise Built</title>. Laserdisc. The Voyager
               Company (1992).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grusin1996" label="Grusin 1996" key="grusin1996">Grusin, R. <title rend="quotes">What is an Electronic Author? Theory and the Technological
                  Fallacy,</title> in R. Markley (ed), <title rend="italic">Virtual Realities and
                  Its Discontents</title>. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore (1996):
               39-53.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gutierrez" xml:id="gutierrez" key="gutierrez">Gutierrez, J. B. <title rend="italic">Literatronic: Adaptive Digital Narrative</title>. Software/Authoring
               System. Available at <ref target="http://www.literatronic.com/src/initium.aspx">http://www.literatronic.com/src/initium.aspx</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hansen2000" label="Hansen 2000" key="hansen2000">Hansen, M. B. N. <title rend="italic">Embodying Technesis: Technology Beyond Writing</title>. University
               of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hansen 2006" xml:id="hansen2006" key="hansen2006a">Hansen, M. B. N.
                  <title rend="italic">Bodies in Code: Interfaces with Digital Media</title>.
               Routledge, New York (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="haraway2004" label="Haraway 2004" key="haraway2004b">Haraway, D. J.
                  <title rend="quotes">Modest_Witness@Second_Millennium.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Haraway Reader</title>. Routledge, New York (2004):
               223-250.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hayles 1999a" xml:id="hayles1999a" key="hayles1999a">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="quotes">The Condition of Virtuality,</title> in P. Lunenfeld (ed), <title rend="italic">The Digital Dialectic: New Essays on New Media</title>. Cambridge,
               Massachusetts: MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2000): 68-94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles1999b" label="Hayles 1999b" key="hayles1999">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature,
                  and Informatics</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, Chicago
               (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hayles 2002" xml:id="hayles2002" key="hayles2002">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">Writing Machines</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2005" label="Hayles 2005" key="hayles2005">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">My Mother Was a Computer: Digital Subjects and Literary
                  Texts</title>. University of Chicago Press, Chicago (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hockey 2000" xml:id="hockey2000" key="hockey2000">Hockey, S. <title rend="italic">Electronic Texts in the Humanities</title>. Oxford University Press,
               Oxford (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hocks2003" label="Hocks &amp; Kendrick 2003" key="hocks2003">Hocks, Mary
               E., and Michelle R. Kendrick. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Eloquent
                  Images.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Eloquent Images: Word and Image in the Age of New Media</title>.
               Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press, 2003. 1-16.</bibl>
            <bibl label="if:Book" xml:id="ifbook" key="ifbook">Institute for the Future of the Book
               (if:Book). SOPHIE. Software/Authoring System. Available at <ref target="http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/tags/sophie/">http://www.futureofthebook.org/blog/archives/tags/sophie/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kendrick2001" label="Kendrick 2001" key="kendrick2001">Kendrick, M. R.
                  <title rend="quotes">Interactive Technology and the Remediation of the Subject of
                  Writing.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Configurations</title> 9.2 (2001): 231-251.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2008" xml:id="kirschenbaum2008" key="kirschenbaum2008">Kirschenbaum, Matthew G. <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New Media and the Forensic
                  Imagination</title>. The MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kittler1999" label="Kittler 1999" key="kittler1999">Kittler, F. A. <title rend="italic">Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</title>. G. Winthrop-Young and M. Wutz
               (trans). Stanford University Press, Stanford (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Latour 1993" xml:id="latour1993" key="latour1993">Latour, B. <title rend="italic">We Have Never Been Modern</title>. C. Porter (trans). Harvard
               University Press, Cambridge MA (1993).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour1999" label="Latour 1999" key="latour1999">Latour, B. <title rend="italic">Pandora’s Hope: Essays on the Reality of Science Studies</title>.
               Harvard University Press, Cambridge MA (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl label="McCarty 2005" xml:id="mccarty2005" key="mccarty2005">McCarty, W. <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, New York
               (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2004" label="McGann 2004" key="mcgann2004b">McGann, J. <title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide Web</title>.
               Palgrave Macmillan (2004).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Markley et al. 2001" xml:id="markley2001" key="markley2001">Markley, R.,
               Higgs, H., Kendrick, M. and Burgess, H. J. <title rend="italic">Red Planet:
                  Scientific and Cultural Encounters with Mars</title>. DVD-ROM. University of
               Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell2008" label="Mitchell et al. 2008" key="mitchell2008">Mitchell,
               R., Burgess, H. J. and Thurtle. P. <title rend="italic">Biofutures: Owning Body Parts
                  and Information</title>. DVD-ROM. University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia
               (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mitchell 2003" xml:id="mitchell2003" key="mitchell2003b">Mitchell, W. J.
                  <title rend="italic">M++: The Cyborg Self and the Networked City</title>. MIT
               Press, Cambridge MA (2003).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ogorman2005" label="O’Gorman 2005" key="ogorman2005">O’Gorman, M. <title rend="italic">DREADMILL</title>. Digital Performance, 2004-5, several locations.
                  <ref target="http://www.dreadmill.net">http://www.dreadmill.net</ref>
               (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl label="O’Gorman 2006" xml:id="ogorman2006" key="ogorman2006">O’Gorman, M. <title rend="italic">E-Crit: Digital Media, Critical Theory, and the Humanities</title>.
               University of Toronto Press, Toronto (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pickering1995" label="Pickering 1995" key="pickering1995">Pickering, A.
                  <title rend="italic">The Mangle of Practice: Time, Agency, and Science</title>.
               University of Chicago Press, Chicago (1995).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Strain &amp; VanHoosier-Carey 2003" xml:id="strain2003" key="strain2003">Strain, E, and VanHoosier-Carey, G. <title rend="quotes">Eloquent Interfaces:
                  Humanities-Based Analysis in the Age of Hypermedia,</title> in M. Hocks and M.
               Kendrick (eds), <title rend="italic">Eloquent Images: Word and Image in the Age of
                  New Media</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2003): 257-281.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="strain2004" label="Strain &amp; VanHoosier-Carey 2004" key="strain2004">Strain, E, and VanHoosier-Carey, G. <title rend="italic">Griffith In Context: A
                  Multimedia Exploration of D. W. Griffith’s The Birth of a Nation</title>. 2
               CD-ROMs. W.W. Norton Company, New York (2004).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tuana 2001" xml:id="tuana2001" key="tuana2001">Tuana, N. <title rend="quotes">Material Locations : An Interactionist Alternative to Realism/Social
                  Constuctivism,</title> in N. Tuana and S. Morgen (eds), <title rend="italic">Engendering Rationalities</title>. SUNY Press, Albany (2001): 221-243.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vannatta2005" label="Vannatta et al. 2005" key="vannatta2005">Vannatta,
               J., Schleifer, R. and Crow, S. <title rend="italic">Medicine and Humanistic
                  Understanding: The Significance of Narrative in Medical Practices</title>.
               DVD-ROM. University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl label="Wardrip-Fruin 2009" xml:id="wardrip2009" key="wardrip2009b">Wardrip-Fruin, N. <title rend="italic">Expressive Processing</title>. MIT Press,
               Cambridge MA (2009). Ongoing peer review available at <ref target="http://grandtextauto.org/2008/01/22/expressive-processing-an-experiment-in-blog-based-peer-review/#0">http://grandtextauto.org/2008/01/22/expressive-processing-an-experiment-in-blog-based-peer-review/#0</ref>.</bibl>

         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>