<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">History Harvesting: A Case Study in Documenting Local History<!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Kimberly <dhq:family>Woodring</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3347-2912<!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of History, East Tennessee State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>woodringk@etsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>KIM WOODRING, MA, MLIS, is an Adjunct Professor of History at East 
                        Tennessee State University. Her research interests include romanization in Roman Britain, 
                        burial and funerary practices in Roman Britain, Digital History/Humanities, and Archival 
                        Studies. She teaches history courses at the undergraduate and graduate level, as well as 
                        teaches for the Division of Cross-Disciplinary Studies and the Archival Studies Graduate 
                        Certificate program.</p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Julie <dhq:family>Fox-Horton</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6091-9786<!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Cross-Disciplinary Studies, East Tennessee State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>foxhorton@etsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>JULIE FOX-HORTON, PhD, is Assistant Professor in the Division of Cross-Disciplinary 
                        Studies at East Tennessee State University. Her research interests include inquisition studies 
                        in late medieval and early modern Venice at the intersection of witchcraft trials and archives 
                        of authority. She teaches interdisciplinary studies at the undergraduate and graduate level, as 
                        well as coordinates and teaches in the Archival Studies Graduate Certificate program.</p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000674<!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --></idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
<!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>History Harvest, Digital History, Digital Project Management, Community Archiving, Regional History</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>History Harvest, digital history, digital project management, community archiving, regional history</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000674/000674.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>As a case study for the practice and application of digital history in a mid-size 
                    university history department, this paper analyzes two History Harvest events 
                    undertaken in a split-level digital history course. By examining the results of 
                    two local History Harvests, specifically through participation of the greater 
                    community, outside the university, and the preservation and digitization of the 
                    local historical items, we discuss the impact history harvests can have on a 
                    community, as well as history students. The primary goal of both History 
                    Harvests outlined in this paper was to work with the local community 
                    surrounding the university to preserve pieces of local history. This article 
                    provides guidelines for conducting a History Harvest including suggestions for 
                    community outreach, local university involvement with the greater community, and
                    digitizing issues that might occur while conducting the Harvest.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
            <head></head>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    
                    <p>As a component of regional education, a central mission of regional universities
                        is to connect with the greater community surrounding the institution. As a potential 
                        member of the future workforce of a community, it is likewise important to provide 
                        opportunities for students to engage with people outside the university in meaningful 
                        and impactful ways to facilitate the creation of enduring relationships. Community 
                        engaged learning is a useful method for introducing and fostering these connections 
                        between students and the greater community. One way to accomplish this 
                        student-community engagement is to involve the community in the production of their 
                        own history through the organization of a History Harvest event. In a History 
                        Harvest, members of the local community are invited to bring their artifacts and 
                        family histories together in one place for the purpose of creating a historical 
                        collection. Usually organized around a particular theme, Harvest materials are 
                        typically arranged to create a digital repository documenting the community history 
                        based on the theme.</p> 
                    
                    <p>This paper explores two History Harvest events hosted by the Department of History 
                            at East Tennessee State University (ETSU) <ptr target="#etsu2022b"/>, a mid-size regional university located 
                        in northeast Tennessee that has been serving communities throughout Western North 
                        Carolina, Southwest Virginia, and East Tennessee for over a century <ptr target="#etsu2022b"/>.
                        Approaching this topic through the lens of digital history and 
                        community archiving, this paper offers a case study for engaging undergraduate and 
                        graduate students in the practice of digital history and community outreach while
                        offering the local community the opportunity to participate in the creation of 
                        their history using History Harvest events. The final goals for the History Harvest 
                        projects are to share the results with the local community by creating a digital 
                        repository which will allow the community as well as scholars to make use of 
                        materials collected through the harvests. Some of the items mentioned in this 
                        study are also scheduled to be on display in the museum at East Tennessee State 
                        University. The long-term goal of this paper is that this case study will provide 
                        helpful guidelines to others wishing to involve their community and local 
                        universities in preserving their own history and reveal issues that might occur 
                        while conducting a Harvest.</p> 
                </div>
                        <div>
                       <head> Defining a History Harvest</head>
                        
                    <p>The History Harvest movement began in 2010 to serve as an open-access, 
                        community-based project. The movement was created by William Thomas and Patrick 
                        Jones in the Department of History at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. The 
                        goal of a History Harvest, according to its founders, is to <quote rend="inline">create a new model 
                        of undergraduate learning in the humanities that is team-oriented, student-led, 
                        community-based and integrated through digital technologies</quote> and to <quote rend="inline">democratize 
                        history by creating public conversation about the materials of history and their 
                        meaning, as well as through the creation of an online public archive, which makes 
                        available new material — the artifacts of everyday life — for historical study</quote> <ptr target="#thomasjones2013"/>.
                        As such, a History Harvest can serve as a way for 
                        undergraduate and graduate history students to put the practice of history into 
                        action, as well as connect with the greater community. From a pedagogical 
                        standpoint, a History Harvest, according to their webpage, can serve as
                        <cit><quote rend="block">an innovative new authentic learning initiative. The collaborative, 
                        team-oriented, student-centered and community-based project seeks to 
                        create a popular movement to democratize and open American history by 
                        utilizing digital technologies to share the experiences and artifacts 
                        of everyday people and local historical institutions.</quote> <ptr target="#unl2022"/></cit> </p>
                        
                        <p>The <q>Harvest</q> means just that. The concept is that a team of public historians go 
                        out into the community and invite members of that community to bring artifacts they
                        wish to share with the greater community. Community members are also invited to share
                        their knowledge and experience with the artifacts that they wish to have shared onto
                        the open-source website where the digital archive of the community collection will 
                        in turn serve as an open source for the purpose of public education. Although the 
                        movement began in the Great Plains region, the goal of the creators of the History 
                        Harvest movement is that the movement would spread across the US, allowing for a 
                        national digital archive <ptr target="#unl2022"/>. The digital collections 
                        contained on the History Harvest Project website serve as a repository for educators 
                        to use in their classrooms as well as a community archive containing the collective 
                        memories of local people.</p>
                        </div>
        
             <div>
                        <head>Community Archiving</head>
                        
                       <p> Defining a community can be a daunting task. The variables are many and membership
                        often crosses the traditional markers such as ethnicity, race, gender, religion,
                       and geography, to include social justice issues. Community, for the purpose of this
                        case study, is defined by geographic location and includes life-long residents and
                        local business owners within Johnson City, as well as those living nearby in the 
                        Appalachian Highland region. Conducting a History Harvest allows for the introduction
                        of new members into an existent community, in this instance, university students 
                        who may be living in the area just for the duration of their studies, planning to 
                        remain within the area after graduation, or are already life-long members of the 
                        community. As Richard Cox <ptr target="#cox2009"/> writes, <quote rend="inline">Community is seen by many to be an 
                        asset; to not belong to a community is a problem, a detriment to living out life 
                        to its fullest. The point here is that being part of some sort of community is 
                        deemed to be a normal part of humanity, and it is seen as an essential objective 
                        if one seems disconnected from a community.</quote> Whether the members of the community 
                        are temporary or life-long, connection and investment in the community are the 
                        essential factors, no matter the duration of membership.</p>
                    
                        <p>The term community archive, likewise, is difficult to discern and is often used 
                        interchangeably with terms like <quote rend="inline">local history group, oral history project, 
                        community history project, and community memory project</quote> <ptr target="#flinn2007"/>. Other 
                        scholars, when defining community archives emphasize, <quote rend="inline">the community or group’s 
                        own self-definition and self-identification by locality, ethnicity, faith, 
                        sexuality, occupation, ideology, shared interest or any combination of the above</quote> <ptr target="#flinnstevens2009"/>.
                        Community archives are deliberate and careful in 
                        their placement and role within an area or region and even their presence within a
                        community suggests their social importance. For archival activists like Michelle 
                        Caswell, Marika Cifor, and Mario H. Ramirez <ptr target="#caswellciforramirez2016"/>, community archives formed 
                        as <quote rend="block">alternatives to mainstream repositories through which communities can make 
                        collective decisions about what is of enduring value to them, shape collective 
                        memory of their own pasts, and control the means through which stories of their 
                        past are constructed.</quote> Jeanette Bastian <ptr target="#bastian2003"/> claims, the archives of a 
                        community are often a mirror of that society and are therefore <quote rend="inline">evidence of the 
                        actions and transactions of the individuals within the community but also define 
                        the public consciousness of the community itself.</quote></p>
                    
                        <p>As a primary component of the two History Harvests discussed in this paper, the 
                        goal was to connect history students to the greater Johnson City community 
                        through the process of digital history and community archiving to promote enduring
                        connections while documenting the history of the area. The Harvest purpose here 
                        is closely related to Rebecka Sheffield’s <ptr target="#sheffield2017"/> point that, <quote rend="inline">Community 
                        archives grow out of the desire to collect documentary heritage that reflects our 
                        common identities, experiences, and interests.</quote> As such, students gain a valuable 
                        learning experience which offers them knowledge about the practical aspects of 
                        conducting public history, history of the region, the value of history to the 
                        greater community, and the importance of members of the community giving voice to 
                        its own history.</p>
                        </div>
             
             
             <div>
                        <head>Purpose of History Harvest</head>
                        
                        <p>The main purpose of a History Harvest is to preserve local historical items for future 
                        generations. The second purpose includes community outreach and community-based 
                        education. Thirdly, History Harvests can support and implement education initiatives 
                        for students and educators at all levels of learning. Finally, a History Harvest 
                        can help a local community connect to the larger American historical experience 
                        and explore those connections through the sharing of memory and preservation of 
                        history. Ultimately, a History Harvest allows individuals to create and preserve 
                        their community history. Faye Sayer <ptr target="#sayer2019"/>, defines community history as <quote rend="inline">the
                        engagement of a community, usually geographically determined, with their local 
                        history.</quote> History Harvests encourage communities to participate in the sharing of 
                        not only individual history but also the combination of the individual and the 
                        local community history to form a more complete historical record.</p>
                        </div>
             
             
                 <div>
                     <head>The History Harvest Project Scope</head>
                        
                       <p>The History Harvest projects discussed here centered on two different themes, but 
                        with the same goal in mind. The overall purpose and scope of the Harvests was to 
                        get students and the local community involved in collecting and preserving local 
                        history. The first History Harvest, held in Spring 2017, was a component of an 
                        Instructional Development Grant awarded to members of the History department at 
                        East Tennessee State University. This Instructional Development Grant is a grant 
                        is meant to promote and support innovative teaching projects. The History Harvest 
                        project in Spring 2017 consisted of two components, a Digital History Course, and 
                        a History Harvest. The Digital History course, which ran in the Fall semester of 
                        2016, offered a hands-on approach to history meant to introduce students to the 
                        use of digital tools and sources for the purpose of conducting original historical 
                        research, analyzing and interpreting findings, and communicating results.</p> 
                        
                        <p>The theme of the Spring 2017 Harvest was <q>Preserving Southern Appalachia’s Tobacco
                        Heritage.</q> The students from the Fall 2016 Digital history course were invited 
                        back to volunteer at the History Harvest by providing the skills and knowledge 
                        they learned about collection and digitization of historical items and documents. 
                        The second History Harvest in Spring 2019 was part of a larger project in collaboration 
                        with the city of Johnson City and East Tennessee State University to commemorate 
                        Johnson City’s Sesquicentennial celebration of the founding of the city <ptr target="#jcpl2022"/>. 
                        The Spring 2019 Harvest’s theme was <q>Johnson City: Preserving Our Heritage.</q></p>
                    
                       <p>The items collected from the 2017 and 2019 History Harvests consisted of documents,
                        artifacts, pictures, and oral histories. After participants signed a consent form,
                        the items were scanned or photographed then returned to the contributors with a 
                        digital copy of each item. Some items were donated to the Reece Museum <ptr target="#etsu2022d"/> 
                        and the Archives of Appalachia <ptr target="#etsu2022a"/>, 
                        located on the campus of East Tennessee State University. The oral histories were 
                        recorded by a History Department faculty member, who followed up with the 
                        contributors to finalize the oral histories and submit them to the Archives of 
                        Appalachia for long-term preservation.</p>  </div>
                        
               <div> 
                        <head>Harvesting and Preserving History in Practice</head>
                        
                        <p>A portion of the grant for the 2017 Harvest provided necessary equipment for the digital 
                        preservation of items brought to the History Harvest including a Canon digital camera 
                        complete with extra lenses, tripod, and storage case. The other items include two 
                        external hard drives to store the digital material and a bundle of USB drives used
                        to store contributors' contributions digitally. Each contributor received a USB 
                        drive containing a digital image of the items they brought to the Harvest. The 
                        2017 Harvest was held in the document room of the Sherrod Library at East Tennessee 
                        State University, which offered wide tables where items could be adequately examined,
                        photographed, and cataloged <ptr target="#etsu2022c"/>. The room was set 
                        up to handle approximately 3 to 4 contributors at one time, which helped with wait 
                        time as well as flow to the other stations. The stations consisted of sign in, intake,
                        photography, scanning, and oral history intake. The forms, including consent and 
                        deed of gift, were provided for the contributors as they moved through the stations. 
                        The director of both History Harvests invited students, faculty and volunteers to 
                        a training session which included training on the scanners, cameras, and other equipment 
                        needed to provide the digital preservation of items brought to the harvests. The 
                        labor for the 2017 harvest was provided by the undergraduate and graduate students
                        that had taken the Digital History course during the previous semester as well as 
                        volunteers and faculty from the history department.</p> 
                    
                        <p>The 2019 Harvest workload was supported by graduate students, faculty, and library 
                         staff. The 2019 Harvest was held at the Johnson City Public library. The library 
                         provided a location for the Harvest as well as archivists to help evaluate and 
                         scan the items brought to the event. The library also provided two flatbed scanners 
                         and laptops for the harvest. The organization and set up of the 2019 Harvest were 
                         similar to the 2017 Harvest except for an extra station designated for the Reece 
                         Museum at East Tennessee State University. The museum director was present to 
                         evaluate the items that contributors requested to be donated.</p>
                        
                        <figure>
                            <head><q>Pride in Tobacco</q> 45 vinyl record collected in 2017 Harvest. Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc>Vinyl record.</figDesc>
                        </figure>      
                    
                    <figure>
                        <head>Framed Tobacco knife and braided tobacco collected at
                            2017 History Harvest.
                            Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring.
                        </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"></graphic>
                        <figDesc>A braided tobacco leaf with a tobacoo knife.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    
                    <figure>
                        <head>Cigarette Pack Display collected at 
                            2017 History Harvest. Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>Cigarette and cigar packing labels in frame.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    
                    <figure>
                        <head>John Sevier Hotel Register Box collected at
                            2019 History Harvest. Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc> Wooden file box with one draw open to show files.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    
                    <figure>
                        <head>John Sevier Hotel Keys collected at
                            2019 History Harvest. Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"></graphic>
                        <figDesc>Three keys displayed.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    
                    <figure>
                        <head>Railroad retirement watch collected
                            at 2019 History Harvest. Picture taken by Rebecca Woodring.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>Gold pocket watch with train shaped charm.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    
               </div>
             
             <div>
                        <head>Challenges/Recommendations</head>
                        
                        <p>The 2017 History Harvest was supported by an instructional development grant through 
                        East Tennessee State University, which allowed for purchasing of equipment that was 
                        not readily available at the institution. Although the institution provided most of 
                        the needs for the Harvest other challenges arose during the process including issues 
                        dealing with the logistics, greater community, technical and operational issues. The 
                        largest issue for this Harvest was the timing of contributors arriving at the staging 
                        area. The contributors were scheduled for morning or afternoon appointments but on the
                        day of the Harvest, most of the contributors arrived in the morning session, even though 
                        they had confirmed an afternoon time slot with the director. The result of this issue 
                        was the contributors had to wait in line at the sign-in and intake stations and therefore
                        put more strain on the workflow at the other stations. This problem could have been avoided 
                        if some face-to-face appointments, including confirmation of arrival time, were made 
                        with the contributors prior to the start of the Harvest.</p>
                    
                        <p>The 2019 History Harvest did not have the scheduling issues of the previous Harvest, 
                        but did experience issues related to production and workflow stemming from lack of 
                        proper equipment. The public library was the venue for this Harvest as well as providing
                        most equipment needed to scan and digitize the items brought in by contributors. The 
                        library provided two flatbed scanners to use for the digitization of documents. Unfortunately, 
                        the equipment was not up to date enough nor quick enough to offer efficient workflow.
                        This issue, as with the first Harvest, caused a backup of intake and processing stations,
                        which led to the contributors waiting to get their items scanned and examined. Most of 
                        these issues could be resolved if the Harvests were done more traditionally. Most History 
                        Harvests do not digitize the items contributors bring to the harvest at the time of 
                        collection. The items are dropped off/collected, or donated, (donation can sometimes 
                        be a requirement) then the digitization process takes place later in a more controlled 
                        environment. The advantage this Harvest had that the 2017 Harvest did not have was 
                        the availability of two professional archivists from the public library to help scan 
                        and evaluate the items brought in by the contributors. The addition of the archivist 
                        freed up the director to manage other issues if they arose during the Harvest.</p>
                        
             </div>
             
               <div>
                   <head>Discussion</head>
                        
                        <p>The implications of collecting and preserving local history have been presented, but 
                        it is also imperative to discuss the goals of the project that pertain to transferable 
                        skills, student and community collaboration, as well as community outreach. Students 
                        enrolled in the digital history course learned transferable skills like scanning 
                        materials, uploading/saving files, preservation techniques, organizational and technical 
                        skills. The students that came back and volunteered to work at the first Harvest 
                        gained experience with community outreach and collaboration with local businesses
                        in the community. They also were able to apply the technical skills they learned 
                        in the digital history course while learning organizational skills pertaining to 
                        public history and archival studies. The Harvests themselves brought together people 
                        of the local community, which extended to neighboring states. The first Harvest 
                        contributors came from neighboring states of Tennessee to share their experiences
                        of growing and selling tobacco, like Western North Carolina and Southwest Virginia. 
                        This allowed the contributors to interact with new people and some they had not 
                        seen in years because they were brought together by their love of tobacco.</p>
                    
                        <p>The goal of the second Harvest was to bring together the local community 
                        surrounding the university to collect items pertaining to the city’s 150th 
                        anniversary. Community outreach was the most important skill learned from 
                        this Harvest. The contributors were residents of the city, and some had a 
                        connection with the university. But the connection between the contributors 
                        was not seen in this Harvest like it was for the first Harvest. The contributors 
                        brought mostly family related items that in some way connected to the city. 
                        But other relationships were formed between the community and the university, 
                        as well as between university departments. Through the outreach process of the 
                        Harvest, businesses in the community contacted the director of the Harvest to 
                        see if the university would be interested in not only digitizing the material 
                        they had, but also wanted to form a collection in the university’s archive. 
                        The university archive, Archives of Appalachia, acquired a large collection 
                        of photos from the local electric company that had been taking pictures of 
                        sites they had worked on since the early 1900s. Internal university departments 
                        also forged new cooperative relationships. The history department reconnected 
                        with the archives and the museum on campus to work together on the second Harvest 
                        which resulted in more collaboration and new exciting ways the departments could 
                        create other collaborative events.</p>
                    
                        <p>It is the hope of everyone involved in these projects that harvests and the 
                        engagement of students with the Digital History course can continue with help 
                        of the university and the local community. Future plans for the material 
                        collected in the 2017 and 2019 include displays in the Reece Museum, located 
                        on the East Tennessee State University campus, as well as a possible traveling 
                        exhibit. There are also plans to create an online exhibit so students can have 
                        access to the materials as examples for future collections plus allow the local 
                        community to enjoy the collections. Making the Harvest materials readily 
                        available to the public as an open-source platform is also a primary tenant 
                        of the conducting a History Harvest we wish to honor. The cases presented in 
                        this discussion were a unique experience in collecting and preserving local 
                        history. Although both cases had their own successes and complications, they 
                        both provided a connection between the university and the local community that 
                        will continue to grow into the future and hopefully be a shining example of 
                        community outreach and collaboration. 
                        </p>
               </div>
                    
              <div>          
                  <head>Conclusion</head>
                        
                        <p>Conducting a History Harvest combines elements of community archiving and the 
                        practice of digital history, creating a powerful dialog for future generations 
                        to build upon. As a component of pedagogy and best practices, the relationship
                        generated between university students and members of the greater community 
                        facilitate community engagement and community-based learning experiences. 
                        In addition, the type of community-based learning a History Harvest creates 
                        gives students the opportunity to practice history. Since students at the 
                        Harvest are responsible for gathering memorabilia and hearing stories from 
                        members of the community as they share their heirlooms, the sharing of 
                        authority, according to Fien Danniau <ptr target="#danniau2013"/>, allows discourse between 
                        historians and <quote rend="inline">the experiences and interpretations of the public.</quote> The 
                        practice of digital history, when intertwined with tenets of community 
                        archiving offers <quote rend="inline">ways for communities to make shared, autonomous decisions 
                        about what holds enduring values, shape collective memory of their own pasts 
                        and control the means through which stories about their past are constructed</quote> <ptr target="#caswelletal2017"/>. </p>    
              </div>
        </body>
        
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etsu2022a" label="ETSU 2022a"> East Tennessee State University (2022).
                    <title rend="quotes">Archives of Appalachia.</title>
                    <ref target="https://www.etsu.edu/cas/cass/archives/">https://www.etsu.edu/cas/cass/archives/</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="bastian2003" label="Bastian 2003">Bastian, Jeannette Allis (2003). <title rend="italic">Owning Memory: How a Caribbean Community Lost its Archives
                    and Found its History</title> Westport, CT: Libraries Unlimited.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="caswellciforramirez2016" label="Caswell, Cifor, and Ramirez 2016">
                    Caswell, M., Cifor, M. and Ramirez, M. (2016). <title rend="quotes"><q>To 
                        Suddenly Discover Yourself Existing</q>: Uncovering the Impact of Community 
                        Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title>
                    79, no.1 (Spring/Summer): 56-81.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="caswelletal2017" label="Caswell et al., 2017">
                    Caswell, M., Migoni, A., Geraci, N., Cifor, M. (2017). <title rend="quotes">
                        <q>To Be Able to Imagine Otherwise</q>: Community Archives and the
                        Importance of Representation.</title> <title rend="italic">Archives and Records
                       </title> 28, no. 1: 5-26.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="cox2009" label="Cox 2009"> Cox, Richard J. (2009)<title rend="quotes">
                   The Archivist and Community</title> In <title rend="italic">Community Archives: 
                        The Shaping of Memory,</title> edited by Jeannette A. Bastian and Ben Alexander,
                    251-262. London: Facet Publishing.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="danniau2013" label="Danniau 2013">Danniau, Fien (2013). 
                    <title rend="quotes">Public History in a Digital Context: Back to 
                        the Future or Back to Basics?</title> <title rend="italic">Low 
                            Countries Historical Review</title> 128, no. 4: 118-144.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="etsu2022b" label="ETSU 2022b"> East Tennessee State University (2022).
                    <title rend="quotes">Department of History.</title> 
                    <ref target="https://www.etsu.edu/cas/history/">https://www.etsu.edu/cas/history/</ref>
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="flinn2007" label="Flinn 2007">Flinn, Andrew (2007). <title rend="quotes">Community
                    Histories, Community Archives: Some Opportunities and Challenges.</title> <title rend="italic">
                    Journal of the Society of Archivists</title> 28, no. 2:151-176.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="flinnstevens2009" label="Flinn and Stevens 2009"> Flinn, A., and Stevens, M. (2009).
                    <title rend="quotes"><q>It is noh mistri, wi mekin histri.</q> Telling our Own Story: 
                        Independent and Community Archives in the UK, Challenging and Subverting the 
                        Mainstream.</title> In <title rend="italic">Community Archives: The Shaping of Memory,</title>
                    edited by Jeannette A. Bastian and Ben Alexander, 3- 27. London: Facet Publishing.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="jcpl2022" label="JCPL 2022"> Johnson City Public Library (2022). <title rend="quotes">Johnson City Public Library-
                    Home.</title> <ref target="https://www.jcpl.org/">https://www.jcpl.org/</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="kaplan2000" label="Kaplan 2000"> Kaplan, Elizabeth (2000). <title rend="quotes">
                    We Are What We Collect, We Collect What We Are: Archives and the Construction of Identity.</title> 
                    <title rend="italic">The American Archivist</title> 63, no 1: 126-151.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="etsu2022c" label="ETSU 2022c"> East Tennessee State University (2022). <title rend="quotes">
                    Libraries Home: Sherrod Library.</title> <ref target="https://libraries.etsu.edu/home">
                        https://libraries.etsu.edu/home</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="etsu2022d" label="ETSU 2022d"> East Tennessee State University (2022). <title rend="quotes">Reece Museum.</title>
                    <ref target="https://www.etsu.edu/cas/cass/reece/">https://www.etsu.edu/cas/cass/reece/</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="sayer2019" label="Sayer 2019">Sayer, Faye (2019). <title rend="italic">Public History: A Practical Guide.</title> London: Bloomsbury Academic.</bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="sheffield2017" label="Sheffield 2017">Sheffield, Rebecka (2017). <title rend="quotes">Community Archives.</title> In <title rend="italic">Currents in Archival Thinking,</title>
                    2nd ed. edited by Heather MacNeil and Terry Eastwood, 351-376. California: ABC-CLIO, LLC.</bibl>
       
                <bibl xml:id="unl2022" label="UNL 2022"> University of Nebraska-Lincoln, (2022). <title rend="quotes"> <q>The History Harvest.</q></title>
                    <ref target=" https://historyharvest.unl.edu/about"> https://historyharvest.unl.edu/about</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="thomasjones2013" label="Thomas and Jones 2013">Thomas, G., and Jones, P. (2013). <title rend="quotes">The History 
                    Harvest: An Experiment in Democratizing the Past Through Experiential Learning.</title> <title rend="italic">International 
                        Conference on e- Learning</title> (IADIS). Prague, Czech Republic.</bibl>
              
            </listBibl>
           
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
