<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">From close listening to distant listening: Developing
          tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio </title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Iben <dhq:family>Have</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Aarhus University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>ibenhave@cc.au.dk</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Iben Have is associate professor in Media Studies, School of Communication and
              Culture, Aarhus University, Denmark. She holds a PhD from Musicology and has
              specialized in research of sound and media in different constellations across the
              fields of reception-, text-, and institutional analysis. She is co-founder and editor
              in chief of the open access journal <title rend="italic">SoundEffects</title> and has
              been managing the digital radio archive and infrastructure <ref
                target="https://www.larm.fm/">LARM.fm</ref>.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Kenneth <dhq:family>Enevoldsen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Aarhus University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>kenneth.enevoldsen@cas.au.dk</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>PhD student at the Center for Humanities Computing Aarhus, at Aarhus University. His
              current research is on multimodal representation learning with a primary focus on how
              to meaningfully combine data sources from disparate domains into meaningful
              representations. He is especially interested in applied machine learning in the
              humanities and arts.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000522</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>Digitization has changed flow music radio. Competition from music streaming services like
          Spotify and iTunes has to a large extend outperformed traditional playlist radio, and the
          global dissemination of software generated playlists in public service radio stations in
          the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host. But digitization has also
          changed the way we can do research in radio. In Denmark digitization of almost all radio
          programming back to 1989, have made it possible to actually listen to the archive to
          investigate how radio content has changed historically. This article investigates the
          research question: <emph>How has the distribution of music and talk on the Danish
            Broadcasting Corporation’s radio channel P3 developed 1989-2019</emph> by comparing a
          qualitative case study with a new large-scale study. Methodologically this shift from a
          close listening to a few programs to large-scale distant listening to more than 65,000
          hours of radio enables us to discuss and critically compare the methods, results,
          strengths and shortcomings of the two analysis. Previous studies have demonstrated that
          Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) trained for image recognition of spectograms of the
          audio outperforms alternative approaches, such as Support Vector Machines (SVMs). The
          large-scale study presented shows that the CNN-based approach generalizes well, even
          without fine-tuning, to speech and music classification in Danish radio, with an overall
          accuracy of 98%.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>This article investigates the research question: <emph>How has the distribution of music
            and talk on the Danish Broadcasting Corporation’s radio channel P3 developed
            1989-2019</emph> by comparing a qualitative case study with a new large-scale study.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1: Introduction</head>
        <p>In the collective research project, <emph>A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark</emph>
          financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers
          investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music
          radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the
          flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like
          Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of
          software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded
          the passionate music radio host <ptr target="#have2018"/>
          <ptr target="#krogh2018"/>
          <ptr target="#wallevik2018"/> (see also <ptr target="#dubber2014"/>). As opposed to music
          radio, talk radio is experiencing an increasing popularity in synergy with on-demand
          podcast formats. And while music radio channels are bleeding listeners, these years
          national governments and public debates around the world discuss whether music radio
          should still be viewed as a public service and receive public funding <ptr
            target="#michelsen2018b"/>.</p>
        <p>As a part of the Danish research project, Have investigated the hypothesis that there has
          been a development from recorded music being the most important content to an increasing
          emphasis on spoken words (chattering hosts, news etc.) on Danish public service music
          radio. This hypothesis was tested, discussed, and to some extent also confirmed, in a
          qualitative study of five case studies of the most popular Danish morning music show on
          the radio channel P3 in the period 1989-2016 <ptr target="#have2018"/>. P3 is a public
          service music radio channel broadcasted nationwide in Denmark and the equivalent of, for
          example, the Swedish P3, the Norwegian P3 and the British BBC Radio 1. In this article we
          investigate this hypothesis from a quantitative perspective, by extending the data from
          five case studies to 65,000 hours of music radio at P3.</p>
        <p>Digitization is not only changing radio but it is also paving the way for new areas of
          radio research. Radio archives are being digitized all over the world as a part of a
          preservation policy regarding cultural heritage and some of these archives allow access
          for researchers. Even if archive politics are becoming more user-friendly, there is still
          a need for developing tools for engaging with the overwhelming amounts of material in the
          audio archives <ptr target="#michelsen2018b" loc="9"/>. Access to digital archives has
          changed radio studies and media studies in general. First, by making it possible to
          actually listen deeply to the archive and investigate how radio content and expression
          have changed historically and thereby also enabling corrections and rewriting of existing
          radio history <ptr target="#michelsen2018a"/>. Humanities scholars are skilled and have
          many tools at hand in doing deep hermeneutic and aesthetic content analysis. But the
          existing digital archives and improvement of metadata also opens open up new possibilities
          of large-scale analysis and enables us to listen both closely and at distance to the
          archive.</p>
        <p>The terms close and distant listening are inspired by Franco Moretti's concept of distant
          reading <ptr target="#moretti2013"/>; in this article these terms will refer to two
          different methodological approaches to audio analysis. By close listening we understand a
          human sensorial listening, manual registering, and hermeneutic interpretation of audio
          material. The strength of this method is the possibility to dive deeply and detailed into
          the data, which require a limited amount of material, which in this context means a few
          selected radio programs. Distant listening, on the other hand, refer to a methodology
          where computational models are developed to do the <soCalled>listening</soCalled> for you,
          so to speak, because the amount of data is too big for human sensorial processing. The
          strength is here the width in listening to a huge amount of radio programs in the archive
          focusing on simple categories such as music and speech.</p>
        <p>In sound studies the term <soCalled>deep listening</soCalled> has previously been used to
          describe a concentrated and contemplative listening mode <ptr target="#bull2003"/> and
          Charles Bernstein has used the term in relation to poetry analysis (1998). Tanya Clement
          has introduced the term distant listening, as we use it here, as a methodological term in
          digital humanities to describe large-scale machine-processing of audio data <ptr
            target="#clement2012"/>
          <ptr target="#clement2016"/>
          <ptr target="#clement2013"/>
          <ptr target="#mustazza2018"/>. Large-scale analysis of audio data is still quite rare in
          Digital Humanities compared to textual and visual analysis. Most of the existing audio
          analysis deal with recordings of text associated with the field of literary studies. In
          Musicology the field of Music Information Retrieval (MIR) has been growing the last few
          years as a part of the broader field of Audio Content Analysis (ACA)<note>See for instance
            the activities at International Society for Music Information Retrieval (<ref
              target="https://ismir.net/">https://ismir.net/</ref>), including the journal
            Transactions of the International Society for Music Information Retrieval (<ref
              target="https://transactions.ismir.net/"
            >https://transactions.ismir.net/</ref>).</note>, but in Media Studies large-scale audio
          analysis are still rare.</p>
        <p>The present study's point of departure is the Danish digital radio archive and digital
          infrastructure <ref target="https://www.larm.fm">LARM.fm</ref>, which gives access to
          almost two million digitized Danish radio programs. No tool has yet been developed for
          large-scale analysis of the archive, and one of the ambitions behind the project presented
          in this article is to demonstrate a way to do just that. Thus, the aim of the article is
          twofold: 1) To describe the methodological process and challenges for developing a model
          for large-scale Speech-Music discrimination analysis on audio data to answer the research
          question <emph>How has the distribution of music and talk on the Danish Broadcasting
            Corporation's radio channel P3 developed (1989-2019)</emph>? 2) To discuss and
          critically compare the methods, results, strengths and shortcomings of the qualitative
          case study and the large-scale analysis, respectively.</p>
        <p>In the following we will first present the LARM.fm archive that serves as the basis for
          both studies. After that we shortly present the analogue hand-held case study first
          presented in the article <title rend="quotes">A Lost Link between Music and Hosts: The
            Development of a Morning Music-Radio Show</title>
          <ptr target="#have2018"/> — we will call it <emph>the case study</emph> in this article.
          Hereafter we present the new big data study — <emph>the large-scale study</emph> — in
          relation to methodological processes and challenges and analytical results. In the section
          that follows we discuss and compare the two studies and the strengths and weaknesses of
            <emph>close listening</emph> and <emph>distant listening</emph> methodologies, and the
          article ends with a short conclusion.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>2: LARM.fm a digital archive and infrastructure</head>
        <p>LARM.fm was originally developed by the research project LARM Audio Research Archive
          (2010-2014), which was a collaboration between 10 research and cultural institutions
          funded by the Danish Ministry of Higher Education and Science. Since 2015 LARM.fm has
          formed part of the national project DIGHUMLAB, www.dighumlab.org. The infrastructure was
          then recreated on the present HTML5 platform, and the platform was expanded to also
          include TV <ptr target="#have2016" loc="2"/>.</p>
        <p>Since 1987 Denmark have had legal deposit of all broadcast material to the Royal Danish
          Library which is included in the Danish Media Collection. From 2005 onwards, this material
          has been exclusively born-digital and almost all analogue programs from 1989 to 2005 have
          been digitized. Due to legal protection the Media Collection is only available to the
          public through on site computers at the libraries. However, an agreement between The
          Danish Agency for Culture and the copyright holders allows university faculty and students
          to stream, but not to download, the material through the library's platform Mediestream or
          LARM.fm.</p>
        <p>As opposed to Mediestream LARM.fm also contains older material from the archives of the
          Danish Broadcasting Corporation (Danmark's Radio or DR in the following), dating back to
          1925, when the national radio was launched in Denmark. The old material is incomplete and
          consists mostly of text documents, as many programs were not saved, and others (still)
          have not been digitized <ptr target="#have2016" loc="3"/>. Besides access, LARM.fm also
          provides various search tools and opportunities for organizing, annotating and sharing
          material.</p>
        <p>The amount of available material grows proportionally as new Danish radio and TV programs
          are broadcasted in Danish media. In November 2019 the collection consisted of more than
          three million radio and TV programs and more than 200,000 OCR-scanned PDF files .</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure01">
          <head>A segment of the interface of LARM.fm (November 2019) with searching tools and list
            of content at the left and a list of the files at the right side.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>As shown in <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref> (left column) the material is arranged
          according to type: TV programs, Radio programs, Radio news reports, Radio news
          manuscripts, Program guides, Radio news guides. Radio- and TV programs are available for
          streaming the other types of material consist of PDF files containing OCR-scanned
          documents — some handwritten and others typed or printed.</p>
        <p>The oldest radio program in the archive is from 22 May 1931 and lasts just over five
          minutes. As illustrated in <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2b</ref> there are 10 or fewer
          programs from the first five years and between 35 and 61 programs from the remaining years
          in the 1930s.<note>For a more thorough description of LARM.fm we refer to Have and Nielsen
            2016.</note></p>
        <figure xml:id="figure02">
          <head>Overview of the collection of radio programs available for streaming in the LARM.fm
            archive, by November 9 2019, divided by decades and number of files shown in the black
            areas. Notice the relatively low number of the 2000s compared to the 1990s, reflecting a
            lack of files in this period. Bottom: the result of clicking at the 1930s showing the
            distribution of years. And the drill down process can continue to months and
            days.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>LARM.fm has expanded Danish radio research towards deep and detailed content analysis of
          first-hand sources, which has been requested not only in Danish radio research but
          internationally within media studies, where radio studies used to be characterized by
          institutional and media systemic analysis <ptr target="#michelsen2018b"/>. Research access
          to archives and digital tools such as LARM.fm makes it possible to do deeply and broadly
          contextualized synchronic analysis because it enables us to study what was broadcasted
          simultaneously, before and after a given event or a specific program. However, archives
          especially call for historical diachronic analysis of longer time-spans and affords unique
          possibilities for coupling qualitative and quantitative methods and analysis. The
          following is an example of such a study combining an already existing qualitative study
            <ptr target="#have2018"/>, with a large-scale study presented for the first time in this
          article. The combination of human close listening to the LARM.fm-archive and distant
          machine listening to the very same archive also prepare the ground for discussions of
          methodological strengths and challenges in Digital Humanities.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>3: The case study</head>
        <p>The close listening case study of the development of the share of music and speech
          focuses on the most popular music radio program <emph>Go' Morgen P3</emph> (Good Morning
          P3) broadcasted on the national radio channel P3. The channel has existed on the frequency
          modulation band (FM) since 1963 and <emph>Go' Morgen P3</emph> was launched in November
          1989 playing music from 6 to 9 a.m. on weekdays. Except from a shifting variety of hosts
          and host constellations the program appears rather stable during the decades.</p>
        <p>The aim of the case study was to test the hypothesis that from 1989 to 2016 <emph>Go'
            Morgen P3</emph> developed from having recorded music as the most important content of
          the programs (qualitatively as well as quantitatively) to have increasingly emphasis on
          speech and entertaining hosts. In Have (<ref target="#have2018">2018</ref>) this
          hypothesis was discussed in the light of the introduction of computerized playlists and
          rotation systems in Danish public service radio in the 1990s, as well as the increasing
          competitive situation, involving commercial and digital radio stations and, not least,
          digital music streaming services. In this article we will only present selected results
          and methods from the case study relevant to the large-scale study.</p>
        <p>We listened closely to five selected <emph>Go' Morgen P3</emph> programs broadcast
          between 6 and 9 a.m. on Wednesdays close to 1 November covering a period of 25 years.
          First, the programs were roughly annotated by Have using the categories music, speech,
          other to get a first impression of the results. The category 'speech' includes only speech
          of the hosts and interviewees, while the category 'other' covers news, sport, weather
          forecasts, jingles, channel advertisements etc. Then the counting was independently
          validated and fine-tuned by student assistants.<note>The registrations for the case study
            was done by the help of student assistant Caroline Skov. The registrations of the same
            programs for the large-scale study was done by the help of student assistant Martha
            Jepsen.</note> Choosing the same weekday at the same time of the year renders yearly
          comparisons more valid and Wednesdays around 1 November are not influenced by bank or
          festive holidays. The aim was to ensure that the five programs were evenly distributed
          throughout the time span, but due to few accessible programs from the first years of the
          millennium in the LARM.fm archive it ended up with five programs from 1992, 1998, 2006,
          2011 and 2016 respectively <ptr target="#have2018"/>.</p>
        <p>To ensure that the program from 1992 was representative for the early 1990s and not
          affected by the institutional restructuring and formatting of radio channels in DR that
          year, registrations from the previous years were included for comparison: 31 October, 1990
          and 30 October, 1991. As shown in <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>, the distribution
          between the categories was rather even, which confirmed that 1992 was not different from
          the previous two years. Unfortunately, the program from 2006 appeared to be unusual
          because it has technical problems in the studio, which gave rise to the use of some
          unplanned <soCalled>rescue music</soCalled> during the first 15 minutes, and therefore the
          music takes up more time than expected. However, that was discovered so late in the
          process that we kept it in the case study.</p>
        <p>The registrations of the content of the five/seven programs point to some stable as well
          as evolving elements during the period. The basic format remained fairly stable over the
          years, but there were significant changes in the content of <emph>Go' Morgen P3</emph> and
          the relations between music and hosts. During the 25 years there was a change from one
          host's talking filling out the gaps between the musical tracks to music as something
          filling out the gaps between a group of 3-4 hosts. However, as shown in <ref
            target="#table02">Table 2</ref> there were only a slight decrease of recorded music but
          in general more host speak during the years. The analysis showed that the amount of speech
          has increased, but not so much to the detriment of music (as expected) as to
            <soCalled>other</soCalled>
          <ptr target="#have2018"/>.</p>
        <p>However, a close listening to the programs revealed that the emphasis on music
            <emph>in</emph> the talk has gradually been disappearing. The time spent on introducing
          the music decreases radically and the link between the music and the hosts has
          correspondingly weakened during the past 25 years, finally disappearing from the program
          in 2016. The five/seven examples illustrate that in the early 1990s there was a strong
          connection between the music and the host, who chose the music and to some extent scripted
          speech of him- or herself. And almost everything said between the tracks was about the
          music. After the introduction of playlists in the 1990s, this link was terminated, and the
          presentation is minimized in 2011 from <title rend="quotes">Chris Brown, <emph>With
              You</emph></title> to a total disappearance in 2016.</p>
        <p>Some elements of content are identical in all five programs namely the recorded music,
          the time announcements and channel/program adverts, but new, entertaining elements that
          are not related to music (satire, quizzes, and everyday news and actuality) are gradually
          introduced. This development together with the hosts' ignorance towards the music is
          pushing the music further into the background.</p>
        <table xml:id="table01">
          <head>Go' Morgen P3 programs in minutes divided between content categories.</head>
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Date/Category</cell>
            <cell>4 Nov. 1992</cell>
            <cell>28 Oct. 1998</cell>
            <cell>25 Oct. 2006</cell>
            <cell>2 Nov. 2011</cell>
            <cell>2 Nov. 2016</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Speak</cell>
            <cell>10.28 minutes</cell>
            <cell>26.48</cell>
            <cell>46.3</cell>
            <cell>55.52</cell>
            <cell>51.5</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Music</cell>
            <cell>116.52</cell>
            <cell>92.5</cell>
            <cell>100.32</cell>
            <cell>91.45</cell>
            <cell>101.95</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Other</cell>
            <cell>42.22</cell>
            <cell>51.07</cell>
            <cell>28.63</cell>
            <cell>26.15</cell>
            <cell>22.5</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <figure xml:id="figure03">
          <head>Same as Table 1, but here visualized in percentages and including 1990 and
            1991.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>On the basis of the findings from the case study, it was concluded that <emph>Go' Morgen
            P3</emph> evolved from being a radio program with a strong focus on music or at least
          with music as the most important content, to a program focusing on light, entertaining
          news and chatter of the hosts. This changed the status of the program from being a clear
          music-radio format where the recorded music is clearly significant and essential to being
          a more blurred soft-news format, where music takes many different roles, not only as
          musical pieces but also as underscore music and jingles important to the flow of the
          program. These observations enabled by a close listening to the programs combined with
          knowledge of Danish media politics and institutional changes in DR are of relevance for
          the large-scale analyses presented in the following section. Instead of relying on a
          small, curated and hand-annotated sample, this study utilizes thousands of radio programs
          to test the qualitative observations on data from LARM.fm. The study represents the first
          large-scale audio analysis in the Danish Media Collection.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>4: The large-scale study</head>
        <p>In this study we take the existing study further by zooming out and letting a computer do
          the <soCalled>listening</soCalled> and <soCalled>counting</soCalled> — not on five/seven
          case studies but on a sample of the whole morning programming of P3 1989-2019 including
          the Go' Morgen P3 schedule.<note>The computational part of the project is supported by
            DeIC's National Cultural Heritage Cluster and Royal Danish Library providing
            HPC-facilities, and developed together with Center for Humanities Computing
            Aarhus.</note> The study has been guided by the following research questions: How has
          the distribution of music and talk developed 1989-2019? How much music and how much
          speech? (classification). How long are the sequences with speech/music?</p>
        <p>The corpus for analysis is all radio programs broadcasted at P3 1989-2019 between 6 a.m.
          and 12 a.m. and available as audio files in the Danish Media Collection and accessible
          through LARM.fm. The data in the corpus is divided in two corpora, resulting from
          different digitization processes: 1) Digitized radio files 1989-2005. 20,660 programs from
          1989-01-01 to 2005-06-30 and 2) Born digital radio files 2005-2019. 24,456 programs from
          2005-07-20 11:05:00 to 2019-05-28 14:03:00.<note>The timespan of the material from
            2005-2019 shows that it will take four years, one month and fourteen days to listen to
            it all.</note> Since the material is copyright-protected, we made a processing agreement
          with the Royal Danish Library which allowed us to retrieve digital copies of the
          audio-files from the Media Collection needed for the project.</p>
        <p>First, we repeated the manual coding of the five programs from the case study — this time
          through the open source multi-track audio editor and recorder Audacity — to be able to
          test the performance of a large-scale analysis. Doing the coding on the same material
          twice enhanced the reliability and as you can see by comparing <ref target="#figure04"
            >Figure 4</ref> with <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> the diagrams are quite
          consistent from 2006-2016. However, the comparison also revealed some errors, since there
          is a discrepancy in 1992 and 1998. So, we went back to LARM.fm to deep-listen to the
          programs and found some external program segments with more speech than usual in Go'
          Morgen P3 were included in the data. Those smaller inconsistencies further add to the need
          for quantitative analysis in cohort with a qualitative approach.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure04">
          <head>Result of coding in Audacity. Percentage of music and speech at the y-axis and years
            at the x-axis. The blue overlap <soCalled>Speech and Music</soCalled> counts as
            speech.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In the next step we utilize the trained model by Papakostas and Giannakopoulos
            (2018)<note>The model along with code is available at Papakostas' <ref
              target="https://github.com/MikeMpapa/CNNs-Speech-Music-Discrimination">Github</ref>.
          </note> for Speech-Music discrimination, in which it is shown that a convolutional neural
          network (CNN) image-based classification on spectrograms obtain state-of-the-art
          performance. This model was trained by applying transfer-learning from a CNN trained on
          subset of the Imagenet <ptr target="#deng2009"/>. In this approach each audio file is
          broken into overlapping mid-term segments of 2.4 seconds with a step of 1 second. A
          spectrogram is then derived for each segment after which the CNN trained by Papakostas and
          Giannakopoulos (<ref target="#papakostas2018">2018</ref>) is used to discriminate between
          speech and music. Followingly, a median filter was used to smooth the signal. This could
          e.g. remove 1-second segments of speech in music, which is naturally very
            unlikely.<note>Notably if the CNN was retrained to predict other classes, this might
            result in short segments such as jingles being smoothed out, which would be
            undesirable.</note> During testing, this image classification approach yield accuracy of
          approximately 93-98% on 11 hours of radio stream <ptr target="#papakostas2018"/>, while
          state-of-the-art audio-based classifiers obtain a performance of approximately 85-94%. For
          more on how the model was trained, its performance and audio to spectrogram preprocess we
          encourage the interested reader to examine the original study by Papakostas and
          Giannakopoulos (<ref target="#papakostas2018">2018</ref>).</p>
        <p>As seen in <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref> and <ref target="#figure05">Figure
            5</ref> these performance levels generalize well to Danish when comparing it with our
          coded dataset. For a comparison with an audio-based classifier we used the support vector
          machine (SVM) by Giannakopoulos (<ref target="#giannakopoulos2015">2015</ref>).</p>
        <table xml:id="table02">
          <head>Performance using only the Speech and Music categories. Positive class is set as
            speech for reference.</head>
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Audio-based Classifier (SVM)</hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Image-based Classifier (CNN)</hi></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Accuracy (95% CI)</cell>
            <cell>0.92 (0.920, 0.925)</cell>
            <cell>0.98 (0.979, 0.982)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Balanced Accuracy</cell>
            <cell>0.94</cell>
            <cell>0.98</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Sensitivity</cell>
            <cell>0.98</cell>
            <cell>0.99</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Specificity</cell>
            <cell>0.90</cell>
            <cell>0.97</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Pos Pred Value</cell>
            <cell>0.80</cell>
            <cell>0.94</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Neg Pred Value</cell>
            <cell>0.99</cell>
            <cell>0.99</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>No Information Rate</cell>
            <cell>0.70</cell>
            <cell>0.70</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <figure xml:id="figure05">
          <head>ROC Curve showing the performance of the CNN when evaluated on the coded corpus. The
            area under the curve (AUC) is 0.99. The ROC curve shows the relation between the
            sensitivity and specificity. Sensitivity, also called true positive rate, is the
            proportion of speech segments correctly classified as speech, while specificity, also
            called the true negative rate, is the proportion of music segments corrected classified
            as music. The diagonal indicates a model which would guess at chance level. Note that it
            is always possible to get a specificity or sensitivity of 1, by always guessing one of
            the two categories.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>These performance levels include only pure categories of speech and music, which does not
          represent the music radio programs, especially not after 2006 (see <ref target="#figure04"
            >Figure 4</ref>) in which it is seen that the proportion of the mixed category speech
          and music is increased. Including <soCalled>Speech and music</soCalled> in the
            <soCalled>speech</soCalled> category and <soCalled>jingles</soCalled> in the
            <soCalled>music</soCalled> category, we see that the CNN obtains an accuracy of 0.96
          (95% CI: 0.954, 957). Note that this includes categories which are unpredictable by the
          CNN, such as noise and silence. Therefore, this is the likely performance which we will
          see over all categories, given the assumption that jingles are music and <soCalled>speech
            and music</soCalled> is speech.</p>
        <p>This level of performance allows for large-scale analysis of the relationship between
          speech and music and while our approach focuses on speech and music classification in
          radio, it can be generalized to other audio media and audio recordings such as podcasts,
          audiobooks and music performances. It is also possible to alternate predictors and, for
          instance, include gender and mood and allow for multiple outcomes, such as speech, music
          and jingles.</p>
        <p>The results of the analysis are shown in the following four Figures, which will be
          further discussed in the following section.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure06">
          <head>Shows proportion of speech over time as predicted by the model. Shaded area is
            uncertainty in 95% confidence interval. The data is smoothed using Kolmogorov-Zurbenko
            filter with a window size of 4 for easier interpretation.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> we measured the changes in the proportion of
          speech during the thirty years and notice significant changes around 1992 and 2001 and
          again in 2005. We also see an upward trend from 2016-2019.</p>
        <p>Apart from the Music-Speech discrimination we also have an interest in how the length of
          the sequences with speech/music might change during the years. This interest came from the
          findings in the case study showing that the length of a musical track has been
          standardized, especially after the introduction of playlists, rotates systems and musical
          clock-schemes <ptr target="#russo2013"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure07">
          <head>Average length in seconds over time as predicted by the model. Shaded area is
            uncertainty in 95% confidence interval. The data is smoothed using Kolmogorov-Zurbenko
            filter with a window size of 6 for easier interpretation. Note that if a section is
            interrupted, e.g. if a radio host interrupt a segment of music, with a segment of
            speech, this will result in the music segment being cut in half. Interpret the results
            accordingly.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Because we in <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> present the mean length in seconds,
          the distribution is rather a Poisson distribution for speech and for music — a
          distribution which resembles a bimodal Poisson distribution (see <ref target="#figure08"
            >Figure 8</ref> and <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>). Note the increase in the
          average length of music in 1992 and the decline in music and speech length from 2011,
          which seems to indicate that there are shorter segments of both speech and music and
          consequently they must have switched more often. Additionally, we observe a rise in
          average speech length from 1992 until 1999.</p>
        <p>To elaborate the findings from <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> we grouped the
          numbers in seven-years-periods to make comparison of these segments in relation to speech
          and music, separately.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure08">
          <head>Proportion of music section length over time as predicted by the model. It can be
            seen that segments of music are typically short (less than 30 seconds) or approximately
            200 seconds. Note the increase in segments of music around 200 seconds after
            1995.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref> and <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref> we
          pay attention to the first peak of very short segments of 10-20 seconds and the second
          peak around the 200 seconds - especially significant in relation to music.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>5: Discussion and comparison with qualitative study</head>
        <p>The study has analyzed some general tendencies in the development of the morning
          programming 6-12 a.m. at P3 1989-2019 by measuring the proportional distribution of music
          and speech and by measuring the length of music and speech segment respectively. When we
          look at the most visually striking changes in Figures 6 - 9, some years across the
          analysis seems note-worthy: 1992, 2001, 2005 and 2016.</p>
        <p>Some important institutional and media political changes must be taken into account to
          explain the development. The official end of the monopoly in Danish radio came in 1983
          when local radio stations were allowed for the first time; however, with regard to
          nationwide channels DR's monopoly was not fully broken until 2003. That means that P3 has
          been in an increasing competitive condition during the thirty years, which is further
          intensified by the competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes from
          the latter half of the 2000s.</p>
        <p>To meet the competition from the local and commercial music radio channels, P3's profile
          was strengthened with the formatting of DR's four radio channels in 1992 (P1, P2, P3 and
            <emph>Danmarkskanalen</emph> (from 1997: P4). Together with a more market-oriented
          strategy, a controversial playlist tool for music control was introduced and slowly
          implemented together with rotation systems during the 1990s, meaning that the music
          presenter no longer chooses the music for the program. This systematization and a
          standardization of the lengths of musical tracks might explain the increase in the average
          length of music in 1992 supported by the increase in segments of music around 200 seconds
          after 1995 in <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>.</p>
        <p>If we look at <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>, we see significant changes around
          1992 and 2001 and again in 2005. This generally confirms the case study in relation to the
          tendency of less speech in the early 1990s before the restructuring and formatting of DR's
          radio channels in 1992, and a growth peaking around 2011 and hereafter a decreasing
          tendency towards 2016. What is new in the large-scale study is, that we here see an upward
          trend in the proportion of speech from 2016 to 2019 reflecting a corresponding decrease in
          musical content.</p>
        <p>The rise in the proportional amount of speech from 2005 to 2011 in Figure 6 can be
          explained by the increasing number of hosts in the studio (Figure 10). More hosts entail
          more talking. Have (<ref target="#have2018">2018</ref>) found that there were many
          different hosts in the early years but only one host in the studio at a time (1989-2000),
          after which there was a relatively stable group of hosts of three to four who were all
          co-present in the studio (2005-2015). In the intervening years there was a short period
          with one or two hosts in the studio (2001-2004) <ptr target="#have2018" loc="132f"
          />.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure09">
          <head>Overview of the development of the changing host constellations in DR's morning
            music-radio show Go' Morgen P3 <emph>1989-2015.</emph>
            <ptr target="#have2018" loc="133"/>.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The changes in 2005 might also be explained by a change in file format in the dataset.
          That year The Danish State Media Collection's procedure changed from digitizing the
          incoming material from the Danish media providers, to receiving it as born-digital as
          described above. While this change is positive, it leads to analysis on individual
          programs rather than the entire morning section. This leads to files which predominantly
          is music or speech hereby leading to increased uncertainty. To normalize across corpora
          each file was further split into segments of approximately 1,000 seconds leading less
          effect of outliers, however a noticeable difference still remains between the corpuses. As
          seen in <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref> and <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>,
          hardly any sections of music or speech is above 1,000 seconds. But we must still take an
          increase in uncertainty after 2005 into account.</p>
        <p>In <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> we see an increase in the average length of
          music from 1992 and a decline in music and speech length from 2011, which seems to
          indicate that there are shorter segment of both speech and music in the early years which
          might to some extend be explained by the practice of the host overlapping with the music
          and consequently music and speech are switching more often. The shift in 2011 might be
          explained by a general use of jingles and segments like quizzes and DR's own commercials.
          However, that does not correspond with <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref> showing a
          more stable category of <title rend="quotes">Other</title> between 2011 and 2016. The rise
          in average speech length from 1992 until 1999 can be explained by the fact that DR in
          relation to the reorganization in 1992 introduced more entertaining and chatty news
          communication as a part of Go' Morgen P3, which occupy half of the morning programs during
          the thirty years. In general, P3 after 1992 turned from being a purer music channel
          towards a more entertaining and communicative channel.</p>
        <p>In <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref> and <ref target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref> we
          pay attention to the first peak of very short segments of 10-20 seconds, which again can
          be explained by the overlapping host talk in the early years, and the second peak around
          the 200 seconds — especially significant in relation to music. This observation is
          interesting because it confirms a standardization in the lengths of musical tracks played
          in the radio after the restructuring in 1992. It is an example of what Have (<ref
            target="#have2018">2018</ref>) calls a <emph>radiotization</emph> of music, which means
          that the logic of radio dictate parts of the creative processes of the musicians. In other
          words: If you want to be played in the radio, you must compose tracks close to 3 minutes
          and 20 seconds to fit into the flow of the musical clock structure. The clock format is
          based on the structure of an hour divided in segments of speech and music (see e.g. <ptr
            target="#hendy2000"/>, 94ff for an introduction to the so-called clock format <ptr
            target="#michelsen2018a" loc="192f"/>
          <ptr target="#russo2013"/>). The structure of well over 3 minutes per segment has proven
          to be the best to maintain the listeners on the channel — a perfect balance between
          recognizability and renewal. As the playlists in the case study show, the variation in the
          music became narrower after the introduction of the playlist tool, and as shown in <ref
            target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref> the length of the individual sections of music have
          become more stable during the years confirming a more controlled and computer-calculated
          playlist and structure.</p>
        <p>Apart from the specific results of the changes in the Danish radio channel P3, this
          article also has an interest in the methodological discussions of deep and distant
          listening. The opportunity to move back and forth between the existing case study and the
          large-scale study — you might call it a meso scale listening approach — has made the
          analysis not just more solid in relation to the existing findings but also in relation to
          filling the gaps of each method. Risks of cherry picking in relation to the qualitative
          case study have been dismissed, and <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> added a more
          nuanced perspective to the case study by showing a quite variable amount of speech during
          the years. However, with an upward trend from 2016-2019, which is the period not included
          in the case-study. So, the large-scale study also gave rise to new questions, such as, why
          do we see an increasing amount of speech from 2016 and onwards? An explanation could be
          the increasing competitive situation, both from commercial digital music radio stations
          and digital music streaming services. In this competitive field of musical content DR and
          P3 turn towards one of their core competences as a public service institution, to offer
          professional journalistic content presented by well-known young personas in an
          entertaining way. That strategy turns P3 even more away from being the music channel it
          once was towards an entertaining and communicative radio channel.</p>
        <p>Many of the eye-catching changes in Figures 6-9 can be explained from institutional
          changes in DR, but the significant change in 2005 cannot. That gave rise to questioning
          not the classifier but the data, which changed format in 2005. This is valuable knowledge
          not only in this study but in future large-scale studies of the LARM.fm archive. Working
          with the LARM.fm archive as reverse-engineering Humanists has given insights in some of
          the challenges of large-scale archive analysis calling for critical attention to
          significant oscillation, which is not always anchored in the actual changes in the content
          of the data but in the formats providing this content.</p>
        <p>A main aim of this study in total has been to analyze whether there has been a
          development from recorded music being the most important content to an increasing emphasis
          on spoken words. The close listening approach enabled a study of how the music was
          presented by the hosts in the program and confirmed the qualitatively change from a host
          filling out the gaps between the musical tracks by talking about the music in the early
          1990s to music as something filling out the gaps between a group of hosts, who do not
          relate to the music at all. However, the large-scale study enabled us to correct or at
          least nuance the findings further by demonstrating that the general amount of speech has
          actually not increased but is varying during the 30 years period, as shown in <ref
            target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>. From the large-scale study we learned that the
          diachronic changes in the share of music and speech are less significant than initially
          expected. This points to the fact that picking single case studies (even if sampled
          deliberately) can lead to doubtful conclusion if not reflected on a background of the full
          radio programming. At this point our study clearly shows strengths and weaknesses of the
          two approached and why it generates more valid answers to combine them.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>6: Conclusion: Combining close to distant listening</head>
        <p>This study has compared a case study of five Danish music radio programs (1990-2016) to a
          large-scale study of the whole morning programming (6 to 12 a.m) of the music channel P3
          1989-2019. Both studies are anchored in the data from Danish digital archive and
          infrastructure LARM.fm, which is offering new paths for radio and media studies by
          affording deep listening studies as well as large-scale distant listening studies. The
          study is the first to present a large-scale analysis of the huge amount of data from the
          Danish radio archive. Inspired by Papakostas and Giannakopoulos we applied a convolutional
          neural network (CNN) image-based classification on spectrograms, which was obtaining
          state-of-the-art performance. For a comparison with an audio-based classifier we used the
          support vector machine (SVM) by Giannakopoulos (<ref target="#giannakopoulos2015"
            >2015</ref>). As demonstrated in <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref> and <ref
            target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> the classifier tools developed from Papakostas and
          Giannakopoulos performed with high accuracy and the performance levels generalized well to
          Danish. This is useful insight to bring into future studies of automated speech
          recognition in Digital Humanities: For instance, how the analytical results found in a
          small amount of data can successfully be generalized to a large amount of data, and how
          models of speech-music discrimination can successfully be transferred across languages
          (Danish and English in this case). We also expect that the model developed in this article
          can be trained in relation to other tasks such as gender detection or regional accent
          detection.</p>
        <p>The findings in the study confirms that the political and institutional changes in Danish
          music radio leave their imprint in the content of the programs. For instance, when we
          register more standardized formats and segments after the restructuring in 1992. But the
          most eye-catching protrusion of <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> in 2005 must be
          explained by a change of format caused by a shift from digitized to born digital files in
          the archive. Thereby the study also contributes with an example of how it is important to
          include reflections on the constitution and possible changes in the data when doing
          large-scale analysis.</p>
        <p>In general, we can conclude that the combination of a close listening and a distant
          listening approach has given us a more saturated picture of the development of the morning
          music radio programming at P3 from 1989 to 2019. The combination both enables us to give
          more valid answers to how the distribution of music and talk has changed during the period
          but it also brings forward some strengths and shortcomings of the qualitative case study
          and the large-scale analysis, respectively. Finally, we hope that this study can
          contribute to encouraging Digital Humanities scholars to include more audio content
          analysis in relation to the field of Media Studies.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="barber2016" label="Barber 2016">Barber, J. F. (2016). <title rend="quotes"
            >Sound and Digital Humanities: reflecting on a DHSI course</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10(1).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bernstein1998" label="Bernstein 1998">Bernstein, C. (ed.) (1998). <title
            rend="italic">Close Listening: Poetry and the Performed Word</title>. Oxford: Oxford
          University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="birdsall2019" label="Birdsall and Tkaczyk 2019">Birdsall, C. and Tkaczyk, V.
          (2019). <title rend="quotes">Listening to the Archive: Sound data in the Humanities and
            Sciences</title>
          <title rend="italic">Technology and Culture</title>, 60(2), John Hopkins University
          Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bull2003" label="Bull and Back 2003">Bull, M. and Back, L. (ed.) (2003).
            <title rend="italic">The Auditory Culture Reader</title>. Oxford, New York: Berg.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="clement2013" label="Clement et al. 2013">Clement, T. et al. (2013). <title
            rend="quotes">Distant Listening to Gertrude Stein's <q>Melanctha</q>: Using Similarity
            Analysis in a Discovery Paradigm to Analyze Prosody and Author Influence</title>
          <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 28(4), 582-602.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="clement2012" label="Clement 2012">Clement, T. (2012). <title rend="quotes"
            >Distant Listening: On Data Visualisations and Noise in the Digital Humanities</title>
          <title rend="italic">Text Tools for the Arts</title>, special issue of <title
            rend="italic">Digital Studies</title> / <title rend="italic">Le champ numérique</title>,
          3(2), 2012.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="clement2016" label="Clement 2016">Clement, T. (2016). <title rend="quotes"
            >Towards a Rationale of Audio-Text</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly,</title> 10(2).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dubber2014" label="Dubber 2014">Dubber, A. (2014). <title rend="italic">Radio
            in the digital age</title>. Cambridge: Polity.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="giannakopoulos2015" label="Giannakopoulos 2015">Giannakopoulos, T. (2015).
          pyAudioAnalysis: An Open-Source Python Library for Audio Signal Analysis. <title
            rend="italic">PloS One</title>, 10(12), e0144610.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="have2018" label="Have 2018">Have, I. (2018). <title rend="quotes">A Lost Link
            Between Music and Hosts: The Development of a Morning Music Radio Programme</title> In
          Michelsen, M., Krogh, M, Have, I. and Nielsen S. K. (ed.), <title rend="italic">Tunes for
            All: Music on Danish Radio</title>, Aarhus: Aarhus University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="have2016" label="Have and Nielsen 2016">Have, I. and Nielsen, J. (2016),
            <title rend="italic">User Manual for LARM.fm. A Digital Radio and TV Research
            Infrastructure for Researchers, Teachers and Students</title>, Aarhus: DIGHUMLAB.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hendy2000" label="Hendy 2000">Hendy, D. (2000). <title rend="italic">Radio in
            the global age</title>. Cambridge, Oxford, Boston, New York: Polity.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="jia2014" label="Jia et al. 2014">Jia, Y., Shelhamer, E., Donahue, J., Karayev,
          S., Long, J., Girshick, R., … Darrell, T. (2014). <title rend="quotes"
            >Caffe.</title><title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM International Conference on
            Multimedia - MM '14</title>, 675-678.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="deng2009" label="Deng et al. 2009">Deng, J., Dong, W., Socher, R., Li, L. J.,
          Li, K., &amp; Fei-Fei, L. (2009, June). Imagenet: A large-scale hierarchical image
          database, <title rend="italic">2009 IEEE conference on computer vision and pattern
            recognition</title> (pp. 248-255). Ieee.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="krogh2018" label="Krogh 2018">Krogh, M. (2018). <title rend="quotes"
            >Non/Linear Radio Genre, Format and Rationalisation in DR Programming</title> In
          Michelsen, M., Krogh, M, Have, I. and Nielsen S. K. (ed.) (2018). <title rend="italic"
            >Tunes for All: Music in Danish Radio.</title> Aarhus: Aarhus University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="michelsen" label="Michelsen et al. 2018">Michelsen, M., Krogh, M, Nielsen S. K
          and Have, I. (ed.) (2018). <title rend="italic">Music Radio: Building Communities,
            Mediating Genres</title>. New York: Bloomsbury.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="michelsen2018a" label="Michelsen et al. 2018a">Michelsen, M., Have, I.,
          Lindelof, A. Sivertsen, H. S. and Larsen, C. R. (ed.) (2018a). <title rend="italic">Stil
            nu ind …: Danmarks Radio og Musikken</title>. Aarhus: Aarhus University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="michelsen2018b" label="Michelsen et al. 2018b">Michelsen, M., Krogh, M, Have,
          I. and Nielsen S. K. (ed.) (2018). <title rend="italic">Tunes for All: Music in Danish
            Radio</title>. Aarhus: Aarhus University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, Franco (2013). <title rend="italic"
            >Distant Reading</title>. Verso.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mustazza2018" label="Mustazza 2018">Mustazza Chris (2018). <title
            rend="quotes">Machine aided close listening, Machine-aided close listening: Prosthetic
            synaesthesia and the 3D phonotext</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 12(3).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="papakostas2018" label="Papakostas and Giannakopoulos 2018">Papakostas, M. and
          Giannakopoulos, T. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Speech-Music Discrimination Using Deep
            Visual Feature Extractors</title>
          <title rend="italic">Expert Systems with Applications</title> 114, 334-344.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="russo2013" label="Russo 2013">Russo, A. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Tick Tock
            goes the Musical Clock</title> In Loviglio and Hilmen (ed.) <title rend="italic">Radio's
            New Wave</title>. New York: Taylor and Francis.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="r2013" label="R 2013">R Core Team (2013). <title rend="italic">R: A Language
            and Environment for Statistical Computing</title>. R Foundation for Statistical
          Computing, Vienna. <ref target="http://www.R-project.org/"
          >http://www.R-project.org/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="wallevik2018" label="Wallevik 2018">Wallevik, Katrine (2018). <title
            rend="quotes">To Go with the Flow and to Produce It</title> In Michelsen, M., Krogh, M,
          Have, I. and Nielsen S. K. (ed.) (2018). <title rend="italic">Tunes for All: Music in
            Danish Radio.</title> Aarhus: Aarhus University Press.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->
</TEI>
