<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in
          DH</title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Taylor <dhq:family>Arnold</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Richmond</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>tarnold2@richmond.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Taylor Arnold is Associate Professor at the University of Richmond.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Stefania <dhq:family>Scagliola</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Université du Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>stefania.scagliola@uni.lu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Stefania is a Research Associate at the Luxembourg Centre for Contemporary and
              Digital History (C2DH).</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Lauren <dhq:family>Tilton</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Richmond</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>ltilton@richmond.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Lauren Tilton is Assistant Professor of Digital Humanities at the University of
              Richmond. She directs the Distant Viewing Lab.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Jasmijn <dhq:family>Van Gorp</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Utrecht University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>J.vanGorp@uu.nl</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Jasmijn Van Gorp is Assistant Professor of Audiovisual Data and Digital Culture at
              Utrecht University.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000541</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2021-03-09" who="Taylor Arnold">Final edits</change>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>Our special issue explores audio and visual (AV) data as form, method, and practice in
          the digital humanities. Spurred by recent advances in computing alongside disciplinary
          expansions of what counts as evidence, audio and visual ways of knowing are enjoying a
          more prominent place in the field. Whether the creation, analysis, and sharing of
          audiovisual data or audiovisual ways of communicating scholarly knowledge, scholars are
          building compelling avenues of inquiry that are changing how we know, what we know, and
          why we know in the digital humanities (DH). These epistemological shifts not only
          challenge existing methodological and theoretical pathways within the field of audiovisual
          studies, but most importantly defy existing knowledge hierarchies within the entire field
          of DH.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>This is the introduction to the special issue on AudioVisual data in DH.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
      	<figure xml:id="figure01">
          <head>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <head>Towards AV DH</head>
        <p>Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new
          routes for the field <ptr target="#mcpherson2009"/>
          <ptr target="#manovich2002"/>. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have
          found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position
          in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of
          academic journals <ptr target="#svensson2009"/>
          <ptr target="#sula2019"/>.<note>For data about the focus on text analysis and increased presence of AV, see
              <ptr target="#weingart2017"/> as well as Weingart's <ref
              target="http://scottbot.net/tag/dhconf/">blog posts</ref> about the ADHO conference.
            For a list of analysis and data about DH conferences and journals from DH scholars, also
            see Weingart's list on his <ref target="http://scottbot.net/dh-quantified/"
            >blog</ref></note>
          Replicating the larger structures of higher education,
          racialized and gendered beliefs about what counts as "rigorous" scholarship that
          marginalize fields such as cultural studies and visual culture studies also permeate DH
          and further explain why text (analysis) has enjoyed a privileged position along with their
          related academic fields <ptr target="#losh2018"/>.<note>For example, efforts to frame
            computational text analysis as more rigorous and hard in part based on claims to the use
            of scientific methods has asserted problematic hierarchies of knowledge production in
            the field. It is not a coincidence that the field has been slow to acknowledge and
            engage with the work of humanities fields that have been feminized and racialized.
            Scholars from these fields have long proven how ways of knowing - such as affective,
            aural, embodied, and performative, and visual - may actually be the only way to recover
            the pasts that constitute (and often haunt) our present and through which we can imagine
            new futures. The work of scholars such as Kim Gallon <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>, Safija
            U. Noble <ptr target="#noble2019"/>, Amanda Phillips <ptr target="#bailey2016"/>,
            Roopika Risam <ptr target="#risam2019"/>, and Puthiya Purayil Sneha <ptr
              target="#sneha2016"/> to center BlackDH, postcolonial DH, and #transformDH has made
            important space to think about other forms of knowledge.</note> However, exciting
          developments are continuing to support and amplify the work of AV data in DH.</p>
        <p>One of those developments is shifts in technology. The ability for computers to create,
          "read", and store AV data followed by advances in areas such as machine learning have
          augmented computational image and sound analysis. Pioneering approaches such as
          cinemetrics that once relied on hand coding and text-based annotations can now be
          automated. Within DH, this has led to new theories and methods such as cultural analytics,
          distant listening, and distant viewing <ptr target="#manovich2020"/>
          <ptr target="#clement2013"/>
          <ptr target="#arnold2019"/>. These developments have led scholars such as Melvin Wevers
          and Thomas Smits <ptr target="#wevers2020"/> to argue that DH is seeing a "visual, digital
          turn". Meanwhile, Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller and Whitney Trettien <ptr
            target="#lingold2018"/>, in the edited volume <emph>Digital Sounds Studies</emph>,
          demonstrate how pairing digital tools with "interpretive practices that always attend to
          the human" forges new paths for sound studies and DH.</p>
        <p>Another critical development is digital access to AV materials. As DH scholars
          increasingly think of their sources as data, they have benefited from large-scale
          digitization of audiovisual collections.<note>The transformation is quite impressive if we
            look back to Miriam's Posner's article on the term "humanities data" <ptr
              target="#posner2015"/>. Posner notes that this is an unusual term for humanities
            scholars. Fast forward five year and it is increasingly common to hear materials such as
            books, films, and photo called data.</note> At the forefront over the last three decades
          have been governmental and GLAM (gallery, libraries, archives, museums) institutions
          around the world to digitize collections, whose initiatives have often been spurred by
          deteriorating physical collections.<note>We give some examples of digitization initiatives
            from around the globe for further reading. A number of initiatives across Asia and the
            Pacific are mentioned in a report about digitization of Indian cultural heritage at the
              <emph>Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Art</emph>
            <ptr target="#bakhsi2016"/>, a centre which itself has digitized a considerable
            proportion of its heritage resources, and made them available through its website. Other
            initiatives mentioned in the report are a.o. <ptr target="#zhizhong2009"/>, <ptr
              target="#manaf2007"/>, and <ptr target="#urgola2014"/>. When considering Africa, a
            special issue on the impact of digitization and new media on various African societies
            in the <emph>Journal of Eastern African Studies</emph> sheds light on how in this part
            of the world the digital transformation primarily manifests itself by the uptake of
            social media <ptr target="#srinivasan2018"/>. Classical ancient works are digitized in
            Egypt, at the remake of the ancient Library of Alexandria, the <emph>Bibliotheca
              Alexandrina</emph> that can be found in present day Alexandria. In a report published
            by the Unesco on digital culture in Spanish speaking countries <ptr target="#kulesz2017"
            />, the core initiatives are investments in infrastructure to decrease the digital
            divide within the countries. In the US, the Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines
            Initiative FADGI established guidelines for digitization in 2007, enabling standardized
            digitization of cultural heritage collections by archives, museums and libraries. For
            more information about the EU's work, see <ptr target="#de2007"/>.
            Given the important calls for a postcolonial DH, it is worth noting
            that ideas of nation and nation building are inextricably linked to many of these
            initiatives. Such work can be a colonial project as well as a form of resistance and
            decolonization. What gets digitized and by whom is a complicated, and often fraught,
            process, see <ptr target="#moseley2008"/>
            <ptr target="#collins2015"/>
            <ptr target="#zaagsma2019"/>.</note> With millions of items digitized, platforms were
          funded by cultural, government, and scientific organisations for providing access to
          audiovisual heritage collections alongside the emergence of platforms by for-profit
          multinational corporations, all of which enabled the circulation of digitized and
          digital-born materials online.<note>For example, an early European initiative was Video
            Active, the predecessor of EUscreen and EUscreenXL, currently consisting of 31
            organisations from 22 European countries who have come together to increase access to
            their materials. Together with the increased availability of digitized materials, the
            launch of user-generated content platforms such as YouTube in 2005 and SoundCloud in
            2007 enabled the circulation of digitized and digital-born materials online.</note>
          While issues such as copyright and funding still loom large, DH scholars have greatly
          benefited from the significant investment in digitization over the last 30 years.</p>
        <p>Finally, we turn to institutional developments.<note>We find Jessica Marie Johnson's
            naming "the digital humanities in its most structural form as articulated by global
            academic institutions" as "DHDH" to be a helpful configuration <ptr
              target="#johnson2018"/></note> Along with conferences specifically dedicated to DH and
          media [e.g. <ref target="https://transformationsconference.net">Transformations
            Conference</ref>], new journals have developed such as the <emph>International Journal
            of Digital Art History</emph> and <emph>Journal of Cultural Analytics</emph> featuring
          scholarship at the intersection of AV research and DH.<note>Indeed, parallel to this
            evolution, media studies and other humanities journals started to pay attention to
            multimedia data as a new presentation form, often in an open access format, such as <ref
              target="http://vectors.usc.edu">Vectors</ref>. In history, sound studies musicology we
            notice similar initiatives such as the <emph>International Journal of Digital
            Art</emph>.</note> In order to further amplify AV work in DH, colleagues worked to
          develop a Special Interest Group (SIG) within the Alliance of Digital Humanities
          Organizations (ADHO). The AudioVisual in DH (AVinDH) SIG was proposed after a successful
          workshop on how to integrate the Audiovisual in the Digital Humanities in Lausanne at
          DH2014, and formalized a year later at DH2015 in Melbourne. One result of the SIG's work
          is this special issue.<note>To read more about the founding, please see our
          	<ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000542/000542.html">interview</ref>
          	with
            the SIG's founders. Notably, in 2016, a SIG for Digital Humanities and Videographic
            Criticism was founded within the Society for Cinema and Media Studies, the largest
            association for film and television scholars in the world.</note>
        </p>
        <p>New pathways are bringing about exciting opportunities in DH as exemplified by the
          articles in this issue. They model how AV research can be the subject of analysis (e.g.
          film) or result of analysis (e.g. podcast). They highlight less visible humanities
          disciplines in the DH, model the importance of interdisciplinary collaboration across
          institutional structures, demonstrate how cutting edge scholarship comes from a plethora
          of positions, and offer new questions that the field is only beginning to grapple with.
          The contributors' model paths for constructing entry points, building bridges, or adding
          intersections for engaging with audiovisual in the digital humanities. Amplifying the work
          of scholars with a range of disciplinary, institutional, and political commitments, the
          special issue constructs a more capacious configuration of DH.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributions</head>
        <p>The special issue is organized into five sections. The first focuses on annotation of AV
          material as method and theory. The second explores analyzing (meta)data, which often
          includes annotation, to build and analyze AV corpora. The third focuses on creative and
          liberatory ways to remix AV (meta)data as a way to innovate pedagogically and
          methodologically while furthering discipline specific interventions. The fourth dives
          further into computational methods, particularly machine learning, in turn demonstrating
          how DH is reconfiguring these methods and ways of knowing to answer humanities questions.
          The special issue ends with a focus on how AV forms such as podcasts and film can also be
          the form of scholarly knowledge in the field, highlighting how form and argument can be
          mutually constituted.</p>
        <p>Next, we turn to the contributions that comprise each section. The first explores
          annotation as a powerful way to add context and analyze AV data. A particularly prominent
          area of such work has been in film studies. Therefore, the first three articles offer a
          snapshot of different approaches and tools for film annotation.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000515/000515.html">Cooper, Nascimento and Francis</ref>
          present their KinoLab and discuss the opportunities and challenges of Omeka for
          narrative film language analysis, including the challenges related to copyrights. They
          argue for a universally accepted data model for film analysis. We then turn to a new
          annotation platform called <emph>Mediate</emph> built by a team at the University of
          Rochester.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000507/000507.html">Burges et al.</ref>
          discuss how they use the annotation tool in the classroom in
          three different disciplines - film and media studies, music history, and linguistics - and
          introduce the concept of "audiovisualities" as a theoretical frame for understanding
          remediation through annotation. Next,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000524/000524.html">Williams and Bell</ref>
          discuss how the Media Ecology
          Project is conceived as a virtuous cycle and incubator working to increase access and
          discovery of moving images, with a particular focus on tools such as the Semantic
          Annotation Tool. Zooming out,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000512/000512.html">Clement and Fisher</ref>
          theorize a new approach to annotation.
          They bring together sound and literary studies to introduce the concept of "audiation" as
          a framework for audiated annotations that increase access and discovery.</p>
        <p>The next section focuses on how (meta)data can open up analytical possibilities. Using
          metadata to reunite AV materials,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000509/000509.html">Sapienza et al.</ref>
          describe the process of reuniting radio
          and text files virtually that belong together but ended up at different institutions.
          After discussing why audiovisual collections in general are heavily under described, they
          describe how virtual reunification and integrated access was realized through the use of
          linked data, minimal computing, and synced transcripts. Next,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000519/000519.html">Hoyt et al.</ref>
          discuss the
          analytical possibilities afforded by metadata. Focused on podcasting, they discuss three
          different methods for studying RSS feeds and podcast metadata, and point at the
          specificities of methods for born-digital media vis-à-vis digitized media.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000523/000523.html">Carrivé et al.</ref>
          then focus on the first development phase of their ANTRACT project for the
          transdisciplinary content analysis of 1262 newsreels containing more than 20,000 French
          news reports. They discuss how they dealt with the project's main technological challenge
          to process data and build tools to familiarize historians with the automated research of
          large audiovisual corpora in order to then use the data to pursue inquiry about Les
          Actualités Françaises news reports. Finally,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000504/000504.html">Gienapp et al.</ref>
          show what can be done when
          data is brought together from different sources to analyze music collaboration. They
          demonstrate how network analysis can reveal the contours of collaboration among
          musicians.</p>
        <p>In the third section, the authors creatively (re)mix AV data with a focus on audio data.
          Using audio data,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000516/000516.html">Tyechia and Carrera</ref>
          demonstrate how centering Afrofuturism in DH
          pedagogy through mixtapes can not only realize the goals of an undergraduate composition
          course but realize a liberatory DH praxis.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000505/000505.html">Bonnett et al.</ref>
          combine data art, landscape art
          and augmented reality in their DataScapes Project. Departing from the premise that data
          can be translated into visual and sonic forms, they use protein data and texts from the
          bible, turn them into sequences, and translate these into visualisations and compositions.
          Kramer then asks what if we listened to images. Building off of previous work on "image
          sonification", he argues that transforming the visual into audio opens up new ways of
          seeing and hearing the past. Next,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000522/000522.html">Have and Enevoldsen</ref>
          demonstrate how toggling from close to distant
          listening offers insights about the longue durée of Danish radio content by scrutinizing
          what is audible with the human ear and searching for patterns using AI. Next, we turn to
          work that makes field specific interventions.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000513/000513.html">Martin</ref>
          constructs a new path for listening
          to gentrification in Washington DC by combining ethnography, passive acoustic recording,
          and computational sound studies. The work also demonstrates how centering Black DH offers
          new ways to understand the relationship between embodied and computational audio analysis
          in DH, in turn forging new liberatory possibilities for the field.</p>
        <p>The next section continues with the application and reconfiguration of computational
          techniques, particularly machine learning, to conduct data analysis on large collections
          of AV data. Looking at a large collection of artwork showcasing musical instruments,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000517/000517.html">Sabatelli et al.</ref>
          introduce the usage of computer vision techniques to automatically locate
          musical instruments in images. They investigate the algorithmic properties of their
          analysis and show how it leads to innovative scholarship in music iconography. A paper by
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000520/000520.html">Lupker and Turkel</ref>
          illustrates the potential of investigating novel intersections between
          research in the humanities by using musical theory to guide the training and usage of
          machine-learning algorithms applied to a large corpus of digitized music. A born-digital
          collection of K-pop dance videos hosted on YouTube is analyzed using state-of-the-art
          computer vision techniques in a paper by
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000506/000506.html">Broadwell and Tangherlini</ref>.
          Their article develops
          a typography for describing and analyzing poses and choreography to facilitate the
          data-driven analysis of time-based media.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000511/000511.html">Oyallon-Koloski et al.</ref>
          present a
          different approach to the study of movement in space by showing how motion capture
          technology can be used within film, dance, and movement studies. As with the Lupker and
          Turkel article, Oyallon-Koloski et al.
          illustrate the novel integration of theoretical
          frames from the humanities – in their case, Laban Movement Analysis and Bartenieff
          Fundamentals and Movement Studies – and the usage of computational techniques. In another
          take on the detection of bodies moving in space,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000510/000510.html">Fragkiadakis et al.</ref>
          introduce an automatic system and taxonomy for tagging and describing digital videos of
          sign-language usage. Together, these articles illustrate the potential for work in AV DH
          to infuse machine learning with analytical commitments from the humanities.</p>
        <p>Finally, we turn to articles that use DH to push the boundaries of form for scholarly
          knowledge. In order to demonstrate how the podcast format expands our definitions of text,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000527/000527.html">Edwards and Hershkowitz</ref>
          reveal how podcasts can realize intersectional feminist approaches
          to DH. Along with demonstrating and discussing the creation of the Books Aren't Dead (BAD)
          podcast in the article, they discuss the process in a podcast for this special issue.
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000514/000514.html">Kim</ref>
          then explores how motion caption and virtual reality can be used to record and visualize
          movement histories as a form of cultural heritage preservation. Through these forms, one
          can then use visual storytelling, she argues, to demonstrate how movement, dance, and
          ritual cannot be separated from a person's personal narration of the experience. Finally,
          <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/1/000521/000521.html">Mittel's</ref>
          contribution showcases twenty audiovisual deformations of the classic musical
          "Singin in the Rain" in still image, GIF, and video formats. The essay considers both what
          each new deformation reveals about the film and the way we engage with the by algorithmic
          practices derived object as a product of the "deformed humanities."</p>
        <p>The invitation of the authors in this special issue to think about the relationship
          between form and argument is one we also embraced. The publication needs, some of which
          weren't possible, of our special issue pushed the boundaries of the form and format of DHQ
          as a journal that is catered for linear reading of articles as written texts in XML. As a
          result, the articles in this special issue include 5 sound files, 52 embedded videos, and
          176 gifs and images. These AV components are key elements of the authors' argumentation.
          The special issue attempts to more closely mirror how scholars of AV materials in DH
          actually produce and create scholarship. In this context we take as a guide other
          pioneering initiatives in this field such as <ref target="https://scalar.me/anvc/about/"
            >Scalar</ref>, <ref target="https://viewjournal.eu/">VIEW journal</ref>, <ref
            target="https://vimeo.com/groups/audiovisualcy/">Audiovisualcy</ref>, and <ref
            target="http://mediacommons.org/intransition/">[in]transition</ref> that question the
          relation between the affordances of a publication platform and the interactivity and
          multimodality of scholarship that increasingly embraces creative modes of production. We
          hope that these incremental steps within DHQ can forge exciting new possibilities for the
          field.</p>
        <p>Finally, our decision to partner together to co-edit was driven by features of AV work in
          DH. First, our own areas of expertise – statistics and digital images, history and audio,
          american studies and photography, and media studies, television &amp; film – reflect a
          range of audio and visual scholarship that animates DH. Second, the inclusion of a
          colleague housed in a Math &amp; Computer Science department, Tayor Arnold, demonstrates
          how digital humanities scholarship often requires working with and giving proper credit to
          experts trained in computational fields. Third, we wanted to build collaborations across
          geopolitical boundaries and languages that might help us think critically and beyond the
          particular configurations of DH that shape our local, regional, or national context. We
          recognize that our positionalities as White able-bodied scholars living in the global west
          and north also brings limits. As a part of our efforts, we paid special attention to
          circulating the CFP beyond our immediate DH circles with particular attention to reaching
          beyond the US and Western Europe. However, there is still more work to do. Yet, we do hope
          that the issue in aggregate reveals how thinking across disciplinary, cultural, and
          spatial boundaries enables a more capacious configuration of the field than currently
          articulated.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>As we look toward the future, we are enthused about the possibilities and realistic about
          the challenges. Along with the work featured in this special issue, areas such as 3D,
          AR/VR, and game studies are forging exciting paths. As disciplines (albeit slowly) adopt
          more capacious guidelines for what counts, forms of scholarship such as films, multimodal
          digital projects, podcasts, and software are receiving well overdue credit. Because of the
          teamwork and expertise often required to access and work with AV data, this area of DH
          also pushes us to work across ossified divisions such as the "Humanities" and "Sciences",
          "faculty" and "staff", and "university" and "cultural institution" in ways that can help
          us realize a more collaborative, equitable, and generous configuration of the
            field.<note>For more about this, see <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>, <ptr
              target="#griffin2018"/>, and <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2019"/>.</note>
        </p>
        <p>At the same time, challenges remain. There are major obstacles to working with AV. For
          example, digitized images have significantly larger file sizes than textual data making
          them hard to transfer and process even in light of recent technological advances <ptr
            target="#simoncelli1997"/>. This makes computational analysis of large collections of
          digitized visual materials difficult for institutions that do not have access to extensive
          computational resources. Audiovisual materials are also often subject to varying degrees
          of copyright and access restrictions, dictated often by large multimedia producers <ptr
            target="#menell2002"/>. This makes it relatively difficult to work with certain
          collections, such as television news programs and feature films, and risks limiting the
          kinds of work with which digital humanists can work. Even when we do have access, the
          scale of AV data is growing rapidly, particularly given the rise of born digital AV
          content, and with this comes implications for how and who is positioned to analyze these
          materials. Existing audiovisual archives are heavily skewed towards European- and
          U.S.-centric collections. As we work through these challenges and opportunities, we need
          to continue to listen and engage with the cautions and critiques about computation and
          algorithms from scholars such as dana boyd and Kate Crawford <ptr target="#boyd2012"/>,
          Ruha Benjamin <ptr target="#benjamin2019"/>, Jessica Marie Johnson <ptr
            target="#johnson2018"/>, Catherine d'Ignazio and Lauren Klein <ptr target="#d2020"/>,
          and Safiya U. Noble <ptr target="#noble2018"/>.</p>
        <p>Finally, we want to thank the contributors, reviewers, and DHQ, specifically Managing
          Editor Cassandra Cloutier, for their work. Even under what were once "normal" conditions,
          writing an essay for publication is demanding. The challenges quickly mounted as authors
          revised amidst a global pandemic that disrupted everyone's daily lives and affected
          communities unequally due to structural inequalities. As authors and our colleagues at DHQ
          tried to balance caregiving, jobs, and their own health, among other duties, they still
          carved out time to make this issue possible. This is quite an achievement, and for which
          we are grateful. Finally, we want to leave with an invitation. We encourage readers
          interested in continuing to further engage with AVinDH to <ref
            target="https://avindhsig.wordpress.com/">join the SIG</ref>. We look forward to all
          that lies ahead.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="arnold2019" label="Arnold and Tilton 2019">Arnold, T. and Tilton, L. <title
            rend="quotes">Distant Viewing: Analysing large visual corpora</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34, 1 (2019): pp.
          i3-i16.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bakhsi2016" label="Bakhsi 2016">Bakhshi, S. I. <title rend="quotes"
            >Digitization and Digital Preservation of Cultural Heritage in India with Special
            Reference to IGNCA, New Delhi</title>
          <title rend="italic">Asian Journal of Information Science and Technology,</title> 6, 2,
          (2016).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bailey2016" label="Bailey et al. 2016">Cong-Huyen, A., Lothian, A., &amp;
          Philips, A. <title rend="quotes">Reflections on a Movement: #TransformDH, Growing
            Up</title> In M. Gold and L. Klein (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
            Humanities 2016</title> (pp. 71-80), Minneapolis, London: University of Minnesota Press
          (2016).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="benjamin2019" label="Benjamin 2019">Benjamin, R. <title rend="italic">Race
            After Technology.</title> Cambridge: Polity Press (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="boyd2012" label="boyd and Crawford 2012">boyd, d. and Crawford, K. <title
            rend="quotes">Critical questions for big data</title>
          <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp; Society</title>, 15, 5 (2012): pp.
          662-67.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="clement2013" label="Clement 2013">Clement, T. <title rend="quotes">Distant
            listening or playing visualisations pleasantly with the eyes and ears</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numérique</title>, 3, 2 (2013).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="collins2015" label="Collins 2015">Collins, J. <title rend="quotes"
            >Doing-it-together: Public history-making and activist archiving in online popular music
            community archives</title> In S. Baker (ed.) <title rend="italic">Preserving Popular
            Music Heritage: Do-it-Yourself, Do-it-Together</title> (pp. 77-90). Abington: Taylor and
          Francis (2015).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="de2007" label="de Jong and Wintermans 2007">de Jong, A., and Wintermans, V.
            <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title> In Y. de Lusenet and V. Wintermans (eds.)
            <title rend="italic">Selected papers of the international conference organized by
            Netherlands National Commission for UNESCO, November 4, 2005, The Hague, The
            Netherlands,</title> (2007).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="d2020" label="d'Ignazio and Klein 2020">D'Ignazio, C. and Klein, L. <title
            rend="italic">Data Feminism</title>, Cambridge MA: MIT Press (2020).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2019" label="Fitzpatrick 2019">Fitzpatrick, K. <title rend="italic"
            >Generous Thinking: A Radical Approach to Saving the University</title>, Baltimore: John
          Hopkins University Press (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. <title rend="quotes">Making a Case
            for the Black Digital Humanities</title> In M. Gold and L. Klein (Eds.), <title
            rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title> (pp. 42-49). Minneapolis,
          London: University of Minnesota Press (2016).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="griffin2018" label="Griffin and Hayler 2018">Griffin, G. and Hayler, M. S.
            <title rend="quotes">Collaboration in Digital Humanities Research - Persisting
            Silences</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12, 1: pp. 1-33.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, J.M. <title rend="quotes">Markup
            Bodies: Black [Life] Studies and Slavery [Death] Studies at the Digital
            Crossroads.</title>
          <title rend="italic">Social Text,</title> 36,4,137: pp. 57–79 (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kulesz2017" label="Kulesz 2017">Kulesz, O. <title rend="italic">Culture in the
            digital environment: assessing impact in Latin America and Spain</title> Paris: Unesco
          (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lingold2018" label="Lingold et al. 2018">Lingold, M. C., Mueller, D. and
          Trettien, W. (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies. Durham</title>, London:
          Duke University Press (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="losh2018" label="Losh and Wernimont 2018">Losh, E., and Wernimont, J. (Eds.)
            <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional Feminism and the Digital
            Humanities</title>, Minneapolis, London: University of Minnesota Press (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="manaf2007" label="Manaf 2007">Manaf, Z.A., <title rend="quotes">The state of
            digitization initiatives by cultural institutions in Malaysia: an exploratory
            survey</title>
          <title rend="italic">Library Review</title>, 56, 1: pp. 45-60 (2007)</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="manovich2002" label="Manovich 2002">Manovich, L. <title rend="italic">The
            Language of New Media</title>, Cambridge MA: MIT Press (2002).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="manovich2020" label="Manovich 2020">Manovich, L. <title rend="italic">Cultural
            Analytics</title>, Cambridge MA: MIT Press (2020).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2009" label="McPherson 2009">McPherson, T. <title rend="quotes"
            >Introduction: Media Studies and the Digital Humanities</title><title rend="italic"
            >Cinema Journal</title> 48, 2: pp. 119-123 (2009).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="menell2002" label="Menell 2002">Menell, P. S. <title rend="quotes">Envisioning
            Copyright Law's Digital Future</title>
          <title rend="italic">NYL Sch. L. Rev</title>., 46: pp. 63-199 (2002).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="moseley2008" label="Moseley and Wheatley 2008">Moseley, R., and Wheatley, H.
            <title rend="quotes">Is Archiving a Feminist Issue? Historical Research and the Past,
            Present, and Future of Television Studies</title>
          <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal,</title>
          <title rend="italic">47</title>, 3): pp. 152-158 (2008).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="noble2018" label="Noble 2018">Noble S. U. <title rend="quotes">Algorithms of
            Oppression. How Search Engines Reinforce Racism</title> New York: NYU Press
          (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="noble2019" label="Noble 2019">Noble, S. U. <title rend="quotes">Toward a
            Critical Black Digital Humanities</title> In M. Gold and L. Klein (Eds.), <title
            rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2019</title> (pp. 27-35), Minneapolis,
          London: University of Minnesota Press, http://doi:10.5749/j.ctvg251hk.5.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="posner2015" label="Posner 2015">Posner, M. <title rend="quotes">Humanities
            Data: A Necessary Contradiction</title> June 25 (2015)
          http://miriamposner.com/blog/humanities-data-a-necessary-contradiction/.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="risam2019" label="Risam 2019">Risam, R. <title rend="italic">New Digital
            Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy</title>,
          Evanston, Illinois: Northwestern University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="simoncelli1997" label="Simoncelli 1997">Simoncelli, E. P. <title rend="quotes"
            >Statistical models for images: Compression, restoration and synthesis</title>
          <title rend="italic">Conference Record of the Thirty-First Asilomar Conference on Signals,
            Systems and Computers,</title> 1: pp. 673-678 (1997).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="spiro2012" label="Spiro 2012">Spiro, L. <title rend="quotes">'This Is Why We
            Fight': Defining the Values of the Digital Humanities</title> In M. K. Gold (Ed.),
            <title rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities</title> (online). Minnesota:
          University of Minnesota Press (2012), <ref
            target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13"
            >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="srinivasan2018" label="Srinivasan et al. 2018">Srinivasan, S., Diepeveen, S.
          and Karekwaivanane, G. <title rend="quotes">Rethinking publics in Africa in a digital
            age</title>
          <title rend="italic">Journal of Eastern African Studies</title>, 13, 1 (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sneha2016" label="Sneha 2016">Sneha, P.P. <title rend="italic">Mapping Digital
            Humanities in India,</title> Banglore: The Center for Internet and Society. December 30
          (2016).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sula2019" label="Sula 2019">Sula, S.A. and Hill, H.V. <title rend="quotes">The
            early history of digital humanities: An analysis of Computers and the Humanities
            (1966–2004) and Literary and Linguistic Computing (1986–2004)</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34, 1: pp. i190–i206
          (2019), <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqz072"
            >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqz072</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="svensson2009" label="Svensson 2009">Svensson P. <title rend="quotes"
            >Humanities computing as digital humanities</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3, 3 (2009).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="urgola2014" label="Urgola 2014">Urgola, S. <title rend="quotes">Archiving
            Egypt's revolution: 'the university on the square project', documenting January 25, 2011
            and beyond</title>
          <title rend="italic">IFLA Journal</title>, 40, 1: pp. 12-16 (2014).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="weingart2017" label="Weingart and Eichmann-Kalwara 2017">Weingart, S. B. and
          Eichmann-Kalwara, N. <title rend="quotes">What's Under the Big Tent?: A Study of ADHO
            Conference Abstracts</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/le Champ Numérique</title>, <title rend="italic"
            >7</title>,1, 6 (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="wevers2020" label="Wevers and Smits 2020">Wevers, M. and Smits, T. <title
            rend="quotes">The visual digital turn: Using neural networks to study historical
            images</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 35, 1: pp. 194–207
          (2020).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="zaagsma2019" label="Zaagsma 2019">Zaagsma, G. <title rend="quotes">Digital
            History and the Politics of Digitization</title> Utrecht: ADHO DH conference Utrecht
          (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="zhizhong2009" label="Zhizhong 2009">Zhizhong, L. <title rend="italic">Zhongguo
            guojia tushuguan guanshi</title>. Beijing Shi: NLC Press (2009).</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
