<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections
               on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sarah-Mai <dhq:family>Dang</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Institute of Media Studies, Philipps-Universität Marburg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>sarah-mai.dang@uni-marburg.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sarah-Mai Dang is a Postdoctoral Researcher at Philipps-Universität Marburg’s Institute of Media Studies. She received a PhD in Film Studies from Freie Universität Berlin and published her dissertation on aesthetic experience and chick flicks as a hybrid self-publishing project on her website <ref target="https://oabooks.de">oabooks.de</ref>. Her current research and teaching focus on digital film historiography, data visualization, open science, feminist theory, and media aesthetics. She is the project leader of the international DFG research network <title rend="italic">New Directions in Film Historiography</title> (2019–2022). ORCID: <ref target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1960-247X">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1960-247X</ref></p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000528</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <date when="2020-12-20">20 December 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>digital database</item>
                  <item>film history</item>
                  <item>feminist theory</item>
                  <item>early cinema</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-11-10" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Due to the increasing production of digital artifacts, data-driven approaches are
               gaining more and more importance in the humanities. In order to understand how they
               affect film and media studies, this article reflects on databases in the context of
               feminist film historiography. Focusing on the collaborative <title rend="italic"
                  >Women Film Pioneers Project</title> (WFPP) (<ref
                  target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/">https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/</ref>),
               it considers the methodological matters when presenting and accessing research
               results online. One of the biggest challenges for film and media historians today is
               not only to retrieve and preserve historic sources but also to make both historical
               records and research outcomes accessible, while taking into account the
                  <q>unknowability</q> of history. How can we identify and include the many blind
               spots when trying to reconstruct the past? In this article, it is made the case that
               due to their openness and variable use, digital databases, such as the <title
                  rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>, seem to be perfectly suited to
               respond to this challenge.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Discusses the role of feminist film historiography in constructing film databases</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as
               a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both
               collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering
               and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt
               observes in his book about the history of databases <ptr target="#burkhardt2015"
                  loc="117"/>. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but
               they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating
               information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others
                  <ptr target="#burkhardt2015" loc="117"/>. Databases serve to store, organize,
               search, query and retrieve information. As it is explained in the UCLA Digital
               Humanities coursebook, <quote rend="inline">[d]atabases come in many forms,
                  relational, object-oriented, and so on. Databases can be described by their
                  contents, their function, their structure, their appearance, or other
                  characteristics</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker2014" loc="29"/>. Similarly, English studies scholar Stephen
               Ramsay points out the various aspects of how we can approach databases. According to
               him, <quote rend="inline">the inclusion of certain data (and the attendant exclusion
                  of others), the mapping of relationships among entities, the often collaborative
                  nature of dataset creation, and the eventual visualization of information
                  patterns, all imply a hermeneutics and a set of possible methodologies that are
                  themselves worthy objects for study and reflection</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay2004" loc="177"/>.</p>
            <p>In order to understand how digital technologies affect the production of knowledge in
               the context of film history, this article discusses the role of digital databases. In
               doing so, it focuses on the <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>
                  (<hi rend="italic">WFPP</hi>).<note><ref target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/"
                     >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/</ref></note> The WFPP is a collaborative
               website which aggregates digital research and provides archival and bibliographical
               information on women workers in film industries. Considering the current debates in
               feminist historiography, one of the biggest challenges for film and media historians
               concerns the appropriate acknowledgement of the many blind spots – the
                  <q>unknowability</q> of history – while making historical records and research
               results accessible, discoverable and comprehensible. In this article, it is made the
               case that due to their openness and variable use, digital databases, such as the
                  <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>, seem to be perfectly
               suited to respond to this challenge.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Databases and film and media history</head>
            <p>In the field of film and media history, digital databases are often described with
               respect to the potential opportunities of enhancing research by making sources
               visible that have been hitherto overlooked. One media studies project which is
               especially interesting in this context is the online platform <title rend="italic"
                  >Media History Digital Library</title> (MHDL),<note><ref
                     target="http://mediahistoryproject.org/"
                  >http://mediahistoryproject.org/</ref></note> founded by archivist and historian
               David Pierce and led by media studies scholar Eric Hoyt. The freely accessible
               database, searchable by means of the platform Lantern, features digitized books and
               magazines on film, broadcasting, and recorded sound that are no longer protected by
               copyright or that have been licensed to share.<note>The Media Digital History Library
                  collaborates with the Internet Archive, the Prelinger Archive, MoMA, Margaret
                  Herrick Library, Library of Congress among other institutional partners.</note>
               The collections can be used in many ways. For instance, by comparing aggregated data
               of the MHDL to the
               JSTOR-Service <title rend="italic">Data for Research</title> (DFR),<note><ref target="http://dfr.jstor.org/"
                  >http://dfr.jstor.org</ref></note> we can see that canonical film magazines like
                  <title rend="italic">Variety</title> or <title rend="italic">Photoplay</title> are
               relatively often quoted in contrast to other publications which were also quite
               popular at those times <ptr target="#hoyt2014"/>. This finding raises the specific
               question what has made <title rend="italic">Variety</title> so popular among scholars
               and sparks a discussion about more general issues such as citation politics, bias and
               other reasons for neglection and marginalization.</p>
            <p>Digital databases which store data at a large scale can enable film and media
               historians to ask new questions or to ask questions differently. They allow for
               observing trends in a broader context and perhaps discover new conjunctions between
               sources. For example, with the help of <title rend="italic">Project
                     Arclight</title>,<note><ref target="http://projectarclight.org/"
                     >http://projectarclight.org/</ref></note> a collaborative data mining and
               visualization tool initiated by Hoyt and cultural and media studies scholar Charles
               Acland, we can measure word frequencies in historic trade papers and fan
               magazines included in the MHDL.
               It allows us to explore developments in film and media history over a longer period
               of time. At the same time, the project facilitates direct access to a particular
               issue we might want to study more closely by providing links to the content in the
                  <title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title>.<note><ref
                     target="https://archive.org/">https://archive.org/</ref></note> Thus, the
               application allows us to zoom in and out while retaining the entities’ integrity and
               historical context.</p>
            <p>Databases can also help us to validate, refute or differentiate hypothesis. The
               online platform <title rend="italic">Early Cinema History Online</title>
                     (ECHO),<note><ref target="http://echo.commarts.wisc.edu/"
                     >http://echo.commarts.wisc.edu/</ref></note> for instance, provides further
               evidence that at the beginning of the 20th century, a relatively large number of
               women in the US-American film industry had worked as scriptwriters <ptr
                  target="#long2016" loc="158–9"/>. In order to come to this conclusion or rather to
               affirm existing research, media historian Derek Long, who created this filmographic
               database, compared the <title rend="italic">American Film-Index</title> credits of
               35,000 films which appeared in the US from 1908 to 1920 to the female names gathered
               in the <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>.</p>
            <p>Digital databases can foster new perspectives and insights. However, while they can
               enhance research by making historic developments visible on a meta level, they seem
               unsuited for showing ambiguities, contingencies and contradictions inherent to film
               history. A subjective, personal approach to the past including speculation and
               imagination – methods central to feminist historians who strongly oppose the concept
               of objective history – seems to be rather impossible. There is also the risk of
               favoring an institutionalized meta history to individual micro stories, as historian
               Kathryn M. Hunter stresses in her reflections on evidence and silence with regard to
               digitization <ptr target="#hunter2017"/>. In the context of empirical research,
               questions around the issues of visibility, absence, and evidence arise with regard to
               the <quote rend="inline">discursive power of records and archives,</quote> where,
               according to Hunter, <quote rend="inline">non-mention was not simply invisibility but
                  erasure</quote>
               <ptr target="#hunter2017" loc="203"/>. In view of that notion, how can we document
               individual contributions in history in the absence of historical documents? Are
               databases able to account for what may not be known and why it remains unknown?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The <q>unknowability</q> of history</head>
            <p>It is a truism that the more we come to know about a particular subject, the more we
               realize how much we do <emph>not</emph> know. When it comes to history, this
               awareness has become a key issue of feminist debate: How can we identify and include
               blind spots when trying to reconstruct the past? In what way can we narrate ellipsis
               and absences while avoiding the pitfall of implicitly promising to grasp the
                  <q>whole</q> story once enough information will be gathered? How is it possible to
               explore unchartered territory when faced with the lack of historical objects?</p>
            <p>The discursive formation of knowledge has been a central concern of feminism ever
               since. In the field of film history, the question of how to reconstruct the past
               while taking into account the contingent and transformative nature of history has
               become equally important for scholars (e.g., <ref target="#gledhill2015a">Gledhill
                  and Knight 2015a</ref>) and filmmakers (e.g., <ref target="#dang2020b">Dang and
                  Akkermann 2020</ref>). In her book about women in the silent film industries,
                  <title>Pink-Slipped</title>, film historian Jane Gaines quotes famous novelist
               Gertrude Stein wondering about how historians <quote rend="inline">can write so
                  knowingly about what they cannot have known</quote> (Stein 1993 [1935], quoted in
                  <ref target="#gaines2018" loc="1">Gaines 2018, p. 1</ref>). Being aware of the
               imaginary and often intimate relationship between the researcher and their subject
                  <ptr target="#dallasta2015"/>, Gaines asks, following Stein: <quote rend="inline"
                  >Is there any other way to <q>say</q> without claiming to know?</quote>
               <ptr target="#gaines2018" loc="1"/>. She prompts the fundamental question of how we
               can narrate past events if we did not happen to be <quote rend="inline"
                  >there.</quote> Nowadays, film history, <quote rend="inline">as both practice and
                  product,</quote> can hardly be grasped as a grand, coherent and evolutionary
               narrative but rather as an aggregation of local <quote rend="inline">micro histories</quote> based on fragmentary,
               sometimes contradictory knowledge <ptr target="#sobchack2000" loc="8–9"/>. Yet, how
               are we able to <q>do</q> history with respect to the <quote rend="inline">precarious
                  relations</quote> between the present moment and the historical past, the very
               past that we proceed to make <ptr target="#gaines2018" loc="3"/>? In short, how can
               we grasp the <quote rend="inline">historical conditions of
                  <q>unknowability</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#gaines2018" loc="3"/>?</p>
            <p>Until only some time ago, it used to be common knowledge in film studies that women
               played only a minor part in the early years of filmmaking. <q>Women’s work</q> was
               dismissed as menial labor, if at all accounted for, notwithstanding the skills of
               generations of women which have been essential to the film industry <ptr
                  target="#hill2016"/>. Still today, as pointed out by film and media studies
               scholars Shelly Stamp, Yvonne Tasker and Gaines at past <title rend="italic">Doing
                  Women’s Film and Television History Conference</title> (DWFTHC) in Lancaster in
               2018, women’s contributions continue to be marginalized in footnotes or text boxes.
               At the same time, for about three decades now, more and more scholars have begun to
               explore the achievements of innumerous women in early cinema – not only as actresses
               before the camera, but also behind the scenes, as cutters, scriptwriters, producers,
               hand-colorers, operators, and directors among other indispensable occupations (e.g.
                  <ref target="#bean2002">Bean and Negra 2002</ref>). From their research we have
               learned that women have had a surprisingly significant impact on film production all
               over the world from the very beginning of film history. Women have worked and
               collaborated globally, not merely in North America and Europe but also in Latin
               America, Asia, and the Middle East <ptr target="#gaines2009" loc="926–7"/>. These
               unexpected findings have led historians to challenge historiography fundamentally. Concepts such as <q>authorship,</q>
               <q>agency,</q>
               <q>director,</q>
               <q>narration,</q>
               <q>canon,</q>
               <q>national cinema,</q>
               <q>evidence</q> and <q>facts</q> are thereby critically scrutinized. As books such as
                  <title rend="italic">Reclaiming the Archive: Feminism and Film History</title>
               <ptr target="#callahan2010"/> and other recent monographs, anthologies and articles
               show, history and theory are no longer regarded as binary oppositions. Methodological
               and epistemological questions have become essential for feminist film and media
               historians. Telling a story differently rather than telling a different story has
               become a primary goal in the field of feminist film historiography. With the
               increasing digitization of objects, research outcomes and scholarly media practices,
               the interest in digital data is growing as well – data that <quote rend="inline">can
                  be transformed, analyzed, and acted upon computationally</quote>
               <ptr target="#schoch2013"/>.<note>For a broader discussion of what <q>data</q> means
                  in the humanities, see, for example, the reflections of Digital Humanities scholar
                  Christof Schöch on <quote rend="inline">smart data</quote> and <quote
                     rend="inline">big data</quote>
                  <ptr target="#schoch2013"/>. For a film and media studies perspective, see, for
                  example, <ref target="#dang2020a">Dang 2020</ref>.</note> In view of this fact, the
               question of how to make the multifaceted influence of women visible while accounting
               for the <q>unknowability</q> is gaining particular importance, since digital data
               adds another methodological and epistemological layer of complexity to the
               relationship between the researchers and their subject <ptr target="#schoch2013"
               />.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Women Film Pioneers Project</head>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title> (WFPP) is probably one
               of the most well-known online platforms in the field of women in film
                  history.<note>Another example worth mentioning due to its popularity is the
                  Women’s Film &amp; Television History Network UK/Ireland (<ref
                     target="https://womensfilmandtelevisionhistory.wordpress.com/"
                     >https://womensfilmandtelevisionhistory.wordpress.com/</ref>). Another project,
                  which features digital resources is <title rend="italic">SP-ARK</title> (<ref
                     target="http://www.sp-ark.org/">http://www.sp-ark.org/</ref>). <title
                     rend="italic">SP-ARK</title> is the online archive of Sally Potter. It provides
                  a selection of multi-media material related to her films (e.g. annotated scripts,
                  costume designs, and production schedules), just to mention a few.</note>
               Originally planned in the 1990s to be a multi-volume book set, it was launched in
               September 2013 by film theorists Gaines, Radha Vatsal, and Monica Dall’Asta as a freely accessible
               collaborative digital resource. Its goal is to challenge the established <q>great male
                  pioneers of cinema</q> by documenting the high influence of women who pursued a
               variety of professions in the silent film industries. The website serves as a
               database of women film pioneers worldwide. As of December 2018, it contains 276
               career profiles (including images and sometimes film clips) written by scholars,
               curators, and archivists. The platform facilitates access to Internet sources and
               aggregates archival and bibliographical information on women workers as well as
               references for further historical research both online and offline. It features also
               a couple of overview essays.<note>After I finished the manuscript, the WFPP has been
                  subject to a relaunch. The homepage has been slightly rearranged, and – perhaps
                  the most interesting aspect – a <title rend="quotes">Projections</title> section
                  for various forms of reflection has been added. However, no fundamental changes
                  have been made. All my observations in this article relate to an earlier version
                  of the website (status as of November 2018), but I believe most issues raised also
                  apply to the present website.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Though lots of historical records got irretrievably lost, the project seeks to
               foreground that <quote rend="inline">[w]hat we assume never existed is what we
                  invariably find</quote>
               <ptr target="#gaines2020"/>. As discussed by several feminist film historians, due to
               the focus on the representation of women in film during the 1970s and 1980s, for a
               long time it had been difficult to imagine that women had a huge impact on early
               cinema at a wide range of capacities <ptr target="#dang2018"/>. In order to shift the
               attention towards what has been unimaginable, the WFPP points to the variety of
               sources which document women’s work. Instead of focusing on the lack of material, it
               emphasizes the abundance of material assumed to be non-existent. This approach
               reminds us that, as film studies scholars Christine Gledhill and Julia Knight have
               emphasized, <q>facts</q> do not tell themselves <ptr target="#gledhill2015b" loc="3"
               />. Their existence depends on the questions we ask and on narrative conventions, on
               preservation politics, archival practices and, as I would like to emphasize,
               aesthetics of access – the various ways in which resources are presented and
               perceived by the users.</p>
            <p>Media scholar Lev Manovich, whose reflections on the relation between database and
               narration has had a high impact in media and cultural studies, suggests to look at a
               database from the user’s experience in a more general sense. Unlike in information
               science, where a database is largely known as the organization of data and
               information, he defines the database as a cultural form of expression that
               fundamentally shapes our perception of the world in the computer age <ptr
                  target="#manovich1999" loc="81"/>. Contrary to the narrative which follows a
               cause-and-effect trajectory, according to Manovich, the database is open-ended and
               does not represent a certain order. A database represents a potentially growing
               collection of diverse elements such as texts, videos, images, and hyperlinks, which
               can be accessed in various ways: via viewing, navigating and searching <ptr
                  target="#manovich1999" loc="82"/>. Thus, a database offers a great deal of
               potential ways of meaning-making.</p>
            <p>On the basis of these distinctions, Manovich imagines a combat between database and
               narrative, whereby each as a form of expression claims an <quote rend="inline"
                  >exclusive right to make meaning out of the world</quote>
               <ptr target="#manovich1999" loc="85"/>. Interestingly, even though Manovich
               foregrounds the different ontologies, purposes and histories of database and
               narrative, when reflecting on cinema, the clear-cut distinction between database and
               narrative begins to dissolve. His analysis of Peter Greenaway’s and Dziga Vertov’s
               films reveal that his concern is narration – produced by databases. Praising the
               specific editing style of the legendary film <title rend="italic">Man with a Movie
                  Camera</title> (1929), Manovich ennobles Vertov to be a major <quote rend="inline"
                  >database filmmaker</quote>
               <ptr target="#manovich1999" loc="95"/>. It is remarkably though that in fact, it was
               Vertov’s wife, Elizaveta Svilova, who did all the editing, as Manovich mentions on
               the site. This is only one of many cases where the historiographical narrative of
               film editing effaces women’s work <ptr target="#pearlman2018"/>.</p>
            <p>Regardless of Manovich’s inconsistent and rather metaphorical use of the database and
               his problematic perception of cinema as a primarily linear medium (as opposed to
               time-based and spatial), his approach can be fruitfully used for exploring the <title
                  rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>. Following Manovich’s
               observations on the database logic with regard to cinema, a database does not
               necessarily represent an opposing model to narrative but can rather be viewed as a
               horizon of possibilities for narration in context of digital media technologies <ptr
                  target="#burkhardt2015" loc="141"/>. Considering the open-endedness and variable
               use of databases, the WFPP seems to be perfectly suited to facilitate the
               reconstruction of the past while taking into account the contingencies and
               contradictions of history. But how exactly does it shape our understanding of the
               women film pioneers’ influence? What kind of usage does it foster? Which questions
               does the website evoke and which unexpected answers can we find? To what extent does
               it facilitate narration?</p>
            <p>As Manovich, in this article, I focus on digital database as a venue of
               representation and on the possible engagement of the user. Important as it is, I will
               leave aside the question of what lies beneath the interface, hence the technical
               aspects of the software which translates the invisible data into perceivable media
               constellations <ptr target="#burkhardt2015" loc="144"/>. While Burkhardt rightly
               emphasizes that databases provide no unconditional openness but are dependent on the
               underlying management system <ptr target="#burkhardt2015" loc="145"/>, I think that
               in addition to a technically informed analysis of programs and algorithms we also
               need to pay attention to the ‘content’ as well as its digital representation and the
               users’ media practices.</p>
            <p>The type of data that is collected and the way in which it is presented, effects the
               potential use of it. Data can be objective but not neutral, databases can serve for
               research, arguments and interpretation. Organizing data by different categories and
               metadata, we interpret by ascribing specific meaning to discrete elements which can
               then serve to support an argument. One could also argue that the creation of data is
               always already an interpretation because we try to make sense out of the world. And
                  <quote rend="inline">interpretation invokes narrative to achieve dramatic impact
                  and significance,</quote> N. Katherine Hayles contends in her article on narrative
               and database as <quote rend="inline">natural symbionts</quote>
               <ptr target="#hayles2007" loc="1605"/>. In this sense, the interpretation – and
               imagination – of relations revealed by database queries are already a form of
        x       meaning-making as part of a narrative <ptr target="#hayles2007" loc="1607"/>.
               Following this line of argument, it can reasonably be concluded that a database
               implies three levels of interpretation/narrative: 1) when producing data, 2) when
               categorizing data, 3) when organizing and/or linking data. That said, <quote
                  rend="inline">databases are powerful rhetorical instruments that often pass
                  themselves off as value-neutral observations or records of events, information, or
                  things in the world</quote>
               <ptr target="#drucker2014" loc="31"/>.</p>
            <p>Although digital databases appear to hold complete collections and promise definite
               knowledge, they are in constant transformation. Yet, in doing so, they do not only grow, as
               Manovich and others have emphasized, but they can also shrink. Entries can be
               deleted, accidentally or on purpose, tables be removed, or links be broken. Databases
               require coherent data and continuous adjustment. By explaining the meaning of
               relational database model for humanities, however, Ramsay emphasizes the intellectual
               value also of inadequacies and inconsistencies. While, for example, the <quote
                  rend="inline">terms we use to describe books in a bookstore (authors, works,
                  publishers) and the relationships among them (published by, created by, published
                  in) posses an apparent stability for which the relational model is ideally
                  suited,</quote> the <quote rend="inline">most exciting database work in humanities
                  computing necessarily launches upon less certain territory.</quote> He thereby
               thinks of uncertain relations expressed by a database, such as <q>influenced by,</q>
               <q>resembles,</q>
               <q>is derived from.</q>
               <quote rend="inline">If the database allows one to home in on a fact or a
                  relationship quickly,</quote> Ramsay notes, <quote rend="inline">it likewise
                  enables the serendipitous connection to come forth.</quote> In this sense,
               databases hold out <quote rend="inline">not merely of an increased ability to store
                  and retrieve information about a particular domain but of a critical and
                  methodological self-awareness</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay2004" loc="178"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot of the WFPP homepage (<ref target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/"
                     >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/</ref>), taken January 2019 (for illustrative
                  purposes, the website’s format has been adjusted for this article).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The WFPP’s homepage offers numerous but limited ways of accessing information (see
               Figure 1). On top, it features four main pathways which lead to the overview essays,
               the pioneers’ career profiles, a list of resources, and the <q>about</q> section. Below, a
               box presents a list of links which refer to the women’s various occupations
               (producers, directors, co-directors, scenario writers, scenario editors, camera
               operators, title writers, editors, costume designers, exhibitors, and actresses). It
               stresses that women did not only work as actresses. Furthermore, there is one
               selected video embedded (for as of November 2018, a trailer on the recent restoration
               of <title rend="italic">Shoes</title> (1916) by the leading female Hollywood
               director-screenwriter Lois Weber). In addition, the homepage highlights one pioneer
               (for as of November 2018, Brazilian director Cleo de Verberena). Besides these
               features, the homepage includes a news section, a newsletter subscription box, and a
               search field. It also provides information on how to contribute to the project, where
               to find further resources, and how to cite the website. The footer links to the WFPP
               social media presentation on Twitter and Facebook. The color scheme of the website
               encompasses shades of gray and purple. Though the featured video is placed in the
               center, the homepage does not really prioritize one element to another. Since there
               is no obvious pre-selection made by the editors, the user has to make their own
               choice about which path of inquiry to follow.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot of the WFPP subpage <q>pioneers</q> (<ref
                     target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/pioneers/"
                     >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/pioneers/</ref>), taken January 2019.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The <q>occupation</q> section (accessible at the upper right) references the wide
               range of women’s contribution in the silent-era, whereas the subpage <q>pioneers</q>
               demonstrates the abundance of women workers (see Figure 2). The collection is ordered
               alphabetically by default but can also be sorted by geography or occupation. Each
               selection can be viewed both in a tiled format (and thus in a more spacial
               arrangement) or as a list. Remarkably, the underlying management system does not
               distinguish between more or less popular pioneers. All the women appear
               simultaneously at once. Due to their diverse activities in different countries, the
               women appear repeatedly in multiple lists. For example, Lotte Reiniger (1899-1981) –
               who has, according to the website’s profile, <quote rend="inline">made over sixty
                  films, of which eleven are considered lost and fifty to have survived</quote>
               <ptr target="#guerin2016"/> – is listed as animator, assistant director, co-director,
               director, film actress, illustrator, screenwriter, and in the category of special
               effects. Apparently, she worked in Canada, Germany, Italy, and England. The
               relatively extensive entry on her work includes screenshots of her silhouette films,
               images of her activities, and YouTube clips. Moreover, it features a selected
               bibliography and a large filmography (including her unfinished work) as well as a
               list of additional sources. A <q>credit report</q> at the bottom of the entry
               describes the context of research for the profile and elaborates on the creation of
               the archival filmography.</p>
            <p>What is interesting with regard to the relational database management system is how
               the website presents other pioneers related to Lotte Reiniger by occupation or
               geography. Below the entry follows a couple of lengthy lists of other women who
               worked as assistant directors, co-directors, directors etc. and also in Canada,
               Germany, Italy, and/or England. All sections (profile, bibliography, filmography, and
               relations) can be accessed directly via the sidebar and do not have to be read from
               top to bottom. Due to the great amount of data and the way it is presented, the
               website enables us to follow our own path of inquiry scanning for items of interest.
               The hypertext structure fosters a non-linear reading of the entries which makes it
               possible to discover unexpected conjunctures between women, occupations and places.
               Thus the database interface facilitates searching for detailed information on women
               pioneers as well as making serendipitous discoveries. In this regard, Ramsay is right
               in noting that databases are <quote rend="inline">not so much pre-interpretative
                  mechanisms as para-interpretative formations</quote>
               <ptr target="#ramsay2004" loc="178"/>.</p>
            <p>In the case of the WFPP, the data is structured on a very basic level, which allows
               for a large number of potential findings. This complies with the editors’ goal to
               primarily foreground the high incidence of transnational women workers in early
               cinema without predetermining how to make sense of these facts. One might even argue
               that the contingent and transformative nature of history is reflected in the
               arrangement of data and also in each career profile. Different to encyclopedic
               entries which appear to provide all basic information needed, the profiles reflect
               upon the very conditions of historiography. The authors explain which historical
               sources have probably gotten lost and, above all, highlight the wealth of surviving
               material which has, however, not been retrieved yet, let alone examined.</p>
            <p>The website invites users to undertake further research on each woman film pioneer.
               It lists 623 pioneers who have been <q>unhistoricized</q> to this point, followed by
               a number of occupations which were held by women but have remained generally
               unacknowledged (such as cashier, interpreter, supervisor) <ptr target="#gaines2013b"
               />. Potentially, everyone can contribute to the database. In doing so, authors must
               follow detailed instructions. Several guidelines and checklists serve to ensure that
               the entries comply with the website’s standards, for example with regard to writing
               style, citation format, historiographic resources. Each entry has to be consistent in
               order to provide a collection of highest possible data quality. Valuable knowledge
               requires reliable data about data sources. This is also important for sharing
               research with students and colleagues and other people interested. The bigger a
               collection becomes, the more pitfalls occur, for example misspellings, disparate
               attributions, or incoherent metadata. From our own personal experience we know how
               easily digital data can get lost by unsystematic filing or naming, or how it can be
               even erased unintentionally, sometimes with no chance of restoration. The discussion
               about the messiness of data, and what might be gained and what be lost when
               implementing standards, exceeds this article’s framework but is more relevant than
               ever regarding the rapid growth of digital data infrastructures.</p>
            <p>Like archives, databases do not store complete collections. They are neither
               universal nor neutral. Instead, databases reflect personal habits, institutional
               conventions, intellectual frameworks and hence discursive power structures. The
               meaning and the structure of a database is inherently connected to the results
               produced by categorizing and filtering the data contained in it and the nature of its
               visualizing interface <ptr target="#mcgann2007" loc="1588"/>. Thus, while we <quote
                  rend="inline">celebrate the branching, rooting, rhizomic, proliferating quality of
                  database</quote> we need to also question the choices that have gone into the
               making of databases <ptr target="#freedman2007" loc="1597"/> and their front end
               design. On the one hand, the increasing amount of data available in the Internet
               enables us to gather information and make meaning out of the world on our own. On the
               other hand, we become more dependent on guidance, classification and ordering due to
               the ways in which searches and databases are constructed for us <ptr
                  target="#freedman2007" loc="1597"/>. For this reason, it is important to
               critically scrutinize the specific implications of database logics, hence digital
               representation politics.</p>
            <p>In contrast to most databases, the WFPP foregrounds the transformative nature of
               knowledge production. It highlights gaps and absences while at the same time
               stressing the abundance of existing yet unexplored material on women’s contribution
               to cinema. Analyzing the WFPP website and its rich collection it becomes clear again
               what has been pointed out by a number of feminist film historians, the
               marginalization of women is the result of a variety of factors, which are, however,
               closely intertwined: the dismissal of women’s work as menial labor, insufficient
               documentation, lack of evidence in addition to lack of imagination due to narrative,
               aesthetic, and theoretical conventions. <q>Raw data</q> cannot serve as an argument
               but as a valuable starting point for further, context-based analysis. Providing all
               possible sources along with each entry, as in the case of the WFPP career profiles,
               it is possible for users to get an idea of what data was left out of a particular
               narrative – or even in history more general. Ideally, in doing so, users can retrace
               how <q>facts</q> have been produced and perhaps transformed.</p>
            <p>In view of these remarks, the WFPP offers the opportunity to counter a meta history
               and instead foster the acknowledgment of women’s contribution to film history by
               telling individual stories. At the same time, the website demonstrates the broad and
               multifaceted field of the pioneers’ transnational activities. As English studies
               scholar Ed Folsom notes in his article <title rend="quotes">Database as Genre: The
                  Epic Transformation of Archives,</title> which has provoked a vigorous debate
               among scholars, <quote rend="inline">[d]atabase might initially seem to denigrate
                  detail and demand abstract averaging and universalizing, but in fact the structure
                  of database <emph>is</emph> detail; it is built of particulars</quote>
               <ptr target="#folsom2007" loc="1574"/>. With this important observation in mind, in
               order to discover significant details we need to be open for new patterns and
               insights. Tools are, as English studies scholar Meredith L. McGill rightly points out
               in her response to Folsom’s article, <quote rend="inline">limited by financial and
                  physical constraints as well as by the imagination of their creators and
                  users</quote>
               <ptr target="#mcgill2007" loc="1595"/>. Other than in a cause-and-effect narrative,
               there is less control of meaning-making in a database. It leaves more space for
               unpredictability. Against this backdrop, databases can be said to offer a fascinating
               possibility of knowing and experiencing history in an intellectually stimulating way.
               However, we must take advantage of this opportunity and tell stories differently by
               using our imagination.</p>
            <p>While the WFPP provides a large amount of information on women in early cinema, its
               ultimate goal is to stimulate further research on women in film history both online
               and offline by examining original sources in archival collections. Online databases
               might help disseminating information beyond institutions and transform the control
               over the circulation of knowledge, as English studies scholar Peter Stallybrass
               enthusiastically proclaims <ptr target="#stallybrass2007" loc="1576, 1581"/>. Through
               the careful curation of an extensive range of information on resources, such as film
               print collections, academic papers, video sources, film festivals, cultural
               organizations, the WFPP website provides an extremely helpful scholarly venue. The
               aggregated references show that the immediate access to material and information
               online is a myth. The search for historical sources and evidence used to be a costly,
               tedious work – and it still is (e.g. <ref target="#leigh2015">Leigh
                  [2015]</ref>; <ref target="#mckernon2015">McKernan [2015]</ref>). But with the
               help of digital databases, we can open up historiographical research and share
               information and resources and thereby ease archival workflows and scholarly
               activities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>There is no doubt that digital technologies can help facilitate easier access to
               historical source material and research output. Provided that access to a computer
               and to the Internet is given, knowledge can be disseminated and shared with
               relatively little effort and at relatively low costs. Nevertheless, we need to keep
               in mind that inclusion always implies exclusion – both in terms of users and content.
               Foregrounding certain aspects of the past by selectively digitizing and presenting
               some information, we inevitably omit other sources and potential discoveries. As we
               know, archiving means not only preservation and memory but also forgetfulness and
               amnesia. Deciding on what will be represented means also deciding on what will
                  <emph>not</emph> be represented – and therefore <emph>not</emph> be remembered.
               This becomes even more significant in light of digitizing artifacts <ptr
                  target="#zaagsma2013" loc="20"/> and the investment of financial and human
               resources needed for preservation projects <ptr target="#heftberger2014" loc="57"/>
               but also when considering digital infrastructures such as searchable databases.</p>
            <p>On the one hand, one could argue, while shifting our research more and more online,
               the risk of letting offline sources be consigned to oblivion is increasing. Because
               of the plethora of resources which are immediately available to us on the Internet,
               we tend to use what is accessible from our desktops. Due to the growing digitization
               of artifacts some scholars fear that funding organizations might cut their financial
               support for expensive research trips to archives <ptr target="#zaagsma2013"
                  loc="21–3"/>. On the other hand, online platforms provide a profound insight into
               which archives exist in the first place. Databases like the <title rend="italic"
                  >Women Film Pioneer Project</title> can be an incitement to the use of analogue as
               well as digital collections. Furthermore, if someone does not live close to a
               library, a museum, or other knowledge-management venues and/or is not affiliated with
               an institution and/or lacks financial means, barrier-free online access to records
               and studies, without technical, financial, or legal restrictions, is critical for
               both academic and non-academic research <ptr target="#pampel2014" loc="214–5"/>.</p>
            <p>Since databases, such as the WFPP, often rely on collaborative contributions, they
               challenge the persistent concept of authorship, understood as a genius solitary
               achievement. In doing so, they make us reflect on the reputation economy in academia
               and the regime of intellectual property <ptr target="#stallybrass2007" loc="1583"/>.
               Furthermore, databases represent work in process, they are never as <q>finished</q>
               as books. As a dynamic and subjective site of representation they strengthen the
               argument that there is no such thing as <q>final facts.</q></p>
            <p>The WFPP editors invite contributions from various authors (which will be
               peer-reviewed) and allow for <quote rend="inline">a great deal of variation
                  and creativity in terms of the topics and themes</quote> while at the same time
               offering suggestions <ptr target="#gaines2013c"/>. In terms of creation and content,
               the editors work towards an inclusive and diverse film historiography, whereas the
               potential usage of the website is limited in some aspects such as language and
               design. The site is entirely in English and therefore can only be accessed by a
               certain group of users. Multilingual entries would help both to expand the project’s
               outreach and bring in many more, various perspectives. Unlike current web design
               trends which promote the use of animations, large images, a short introduction video,
               serif-less fonts, bold typography and other characteristics, the WFPP website stands
               out with its rather simple web design. The aggregation of data, information, and
               knowledge has been clearly the focus of the project so far. In my view, however,
               engaging the user in an enjoyable manner would very much help to make history
               accessible while indicating blind spots. While aesthetics is a matter of taste, a
               stronger focus on user experience can enhance the engagement with a database
               tremendously. The platform convincingly illustrates that a great deal of women
               pioneers had played a significant role in the silent-era. Nevertheless, additional
               features and data visualization techniques, for example GIS (geographic information
               systems), could help highlighting the many interactions and entangled paths of women
               in history. The curatorial work which has been put into the project is of great value
               to feminist film history. The WFPP provides an extensive collection of high quality
               data to further explore the digital representation of research and data visualization
               – and much potential for creative experiments toward the unknown. Let us make use of
               it. It is time for redistributing the narrative wealth, as proclaimed at DWFTHC in
               Lancaster: for telling many more stories, and first and foremost, telling stories
               differently. History is not only about the <quote rend="inline">power of the
                  records</quote>
               <ptr target="#hunter2017" loc="203"/> but also of aesthetics and access.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>I thank the two anonymous reviewers for carefully reading the manuscript, and for
               insightful comments and suggestions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="acland2016" label="Acland and Hoyt 2016">Acland, C. R. and Hoyt. E. (eds)
                  <title rend="italic">The Arclight Guidebook to Media History and the Digital
                  Humanities</title>. REFRAME Books, Sussex (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bean2002" label="Bean and Negra 2002">Bean, J. M. and Negra, D. (eds)
                  <title rend="italic">A Feminist Reader in Early Cinema</title>. Duke University
               Press, Durham (2002).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burkhardt2015" label="Burkhardt 2015">Burkhardt, M. <title rend="italic"
                  >Digitale Datenbanken, Eine Medientheorie im Zeitalter von Big Data</title>.
               transcript Verlag, Berlin, Boston (2015), doi: 10.14361/9783839430286.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="callahan2010" label="Callahan 2010">Callahan, V. (ed) <title rend="italic"
                  >Reclaiming the Archive: Feminism and Film History</title>. Contemporary
               Approaches to Film and Television Series. Wayne State University Press, Detroit
               (2010).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dallasta2015" label="Dall’Asta and Gaines 2015">Dall’Asta, M. and Gaines,
               J. M. <title rend="quotes">Prologue. Constellations. Past Meets Present in Feminist
                  Film History.</title> In Christine Gledhill and Julia Knight (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Doing Women’s Film History: Reframing Cinemas, Past and
                  Future</title>, Urbana (2015), pp. 28-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dang2018" label="Dang 2018">Dang, S.-M. <title rend="quotes">Digital
               Tools &amp; Big Data: Zu gegenwärtigen Herausforderungen für die Film- und
               Medienwissenschaft am Beispiel der feministischen
               Filmgeschichtsschreibung,</title>
               <title rend="italic">MEDIENwissenschaft: Rezensionen | Reviews</title>, 2-3 (2019):
               142, doi: 10.17192/ep2018.2-3.7836.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dang2020a" label="Dang 2019a">Dang, S.-M. <title rend="quotes"
               >Forschungsdatenmanagement in der Filmwissenschaft: Daten, Praktiken  und Erkenntnisprozesse.</title>In: Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski (eds): <title rend="quotes">Praktiken des Digitalen</title>, <title rend="italic">Montage AV</title>, 29.1, (2020): 120-140.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dang2020b" label="Dang and Akkermann 2020">Dang, S.-M. and Akkermann, M.
               <title rend="quotes">Inszenierte Abwesenheit – eine Frage der Perspektive?
                  Intersektionalität im Film am Beispiel von <title rend="italic">Watermelon
                     Woman</title>.</title> In A. Charton, B. Dornbuch, and K. Knaus (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Marginalisierungen – Ermächtigungen. Intersektionalität und
                        Medialität im gegenwärtigen Musikbetrieb</title>, Hildesheim, Zürich, New York
               (2019), pp. 119-137.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2014" label="Drucker et al. 2014">Drucker, J., Kim, D., Salehian,
               I., and Bushong, A. <title rend="quotes">Data and Databases. Critical and Practical
                  Issues.</title> In J. Drucker, D. Kim, I. Salehian, and A. Bushong (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Introduction to Digital Humanities. Concepts, Methods, and Tutorials
                  for Students and Instructors</title>, Los Angeles (2012), pp. 28-34, <ref
                  target="http://dh101.humanities.ucla.edu/?page_id=93"
                  >http://dh101.humanities.ucla.edu/?page_id=93</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folsom2007" label="Folsom 2007">Folsom, E. <title rend="quotes">Database
                  as Genre: The Epic Transformation of Archives,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1571-1579.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freedman2007" label="Freedman 2007">Freedman, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Whitman, Database, Information Culture,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1596-1602.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2009" label="Gaines 2009">Gaines, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Filmgeschichte als Kritik feministischer Filmtheorie,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Das Argument</title>, 51.6 (2009): 926-934.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2018" label="Gaines 2018">Gaines, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Pink-slipped: What Happened to the Women in the Silent Film Industries?</title>
               University of Illinois Press, Urbana (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2013a" label="Gaines et al. 2013a">Gaines, J., Vatsal, R., and
               Dall’Asta, M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>. Center
               for Digital Research and Scholarship. Columbia University Libraries, New York (2013),
                  <ref target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/"
                  >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2013b" label="Gaines et al. 2013b">Gaines, J., Vatsal, R., and
               Dall’Asta, M. <title rend="quotes">Unhistoricized Women Film Pioneers.</title> In J.
               Gaines, R. Vatsal, and M. Dall’Asta (eds), <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers
                  Project</title>. Center for Digital Research and Scholarship, New York (2013),
                  <ref
                  target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/resources/appendix-f-unhistoricized-women-film-pioneers/"
                  >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/resources/appendix-f-unhistoricized-women-film-pioneers/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2013c" label="Gaines et al. 2013c">Gaines, J., Vatsal, R., and
               Dall’Asta, M. <title rend="quotes">Call for Contributors for Overview Essays.</title>
               In J. Gaines, R. Vatsal, and M. Dall’Asta (eds), <title rend="italic">Women Film
                  Pioneers Project</title>. Center for Digital Research and Scholarship, New York
               (2013), <ref target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/call-for-contributors/"
                  >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/call-for-contributors/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaines2020" label="Gaines 2020">Gaines, J., Vatsal, R., and Dall’Asta, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">About the Project.</title> In J. Gaines, R. Vatsal, and M.
               Dall’Asta (eds), <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>. Center for
               Digital Research and Scholarship, New York (2013), <ref
                  target="https://wfpp.columbia.edu/about/"
               >https://wfpp.columbia.edu/about/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gladhill2015a" label="Gledhill and Knight 2015a">Gledhill, C. and Knight,
               J. (eds) <title rend="italic">Doing Women’s Film History. Reframing Cinemas, Past and
                  Future</title>. Women and film history international. University of Illinois
               Press, Urbana (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gledhill2015b" label="Gledhill and Knight 2015b">Gledhill, C. and Knight,
               J. <title rend="quotes">Introduction.</title> In C. Gledhill and J. Knight (eds),
                  <title rend="italic">Doing Women’s Film History. Reframing Cinemas, Past and
                  Future</title>, Urbana (2015), pp. 1-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guerin2016" label="Guerin and Mebold 2016">Guerin, F. and Mebold, A.
                  <title rend="quotes">Lotte Reiniger.</title> In J. Gaines, R. Vatsal, and M.
               Dall’Asta (eds), <title rend="italic">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>. Center for
               Digital Research and Scholarship<hi rend="italic">,</hi> New York (2016), <ref
                  target="https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/pioneer/lotte-reiniger/#citation"
                  >https://wfpp.cdrs.columbia.edu/pioneer/lotte-reiniger/#citation</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2007" label="Hayles 2007">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Narrative and Database: Natural Symbionts,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1603-1608.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2014" label="Heftberger 2014">Heftberger, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Film archives and digital humanities – an impossible match? New job
                  descriptions and the challenges of the digital era,</title>
               <title rend="italic">MedieKultur: Journal of media and communication
               research</title>, 30.57 (2014): 135-153, doi:
               10.7146/mediekultur.v30i57.16487.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hill2016" label="Hill 2016">Hill, E. <title rend="italic">Never Done: A
                  History of Women’s Work in Media Production</title>. Rutgers University Press, New
               Brunswick (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoyt2014" label="Hoyt 2014">Hoyt, E. <title rend="quotes">Lenses for
                  Lantern: Data Mining, Visualization, and Excavating Film History’s Neglected
                  Sources,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Film History</title>, 26.2 (2014): 146-169.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hunter2017" label="Hunter 2017">Hunter, K. M. <title rend="quotes">Silence
                  in Noisy Archives: Reflections on Judith Allen’s <title rend="quotes">Evidence and
                     Silence – Feminism and the Limits of History</title> (1986) in the Era of Mass
                  Digitisation,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Australian Feminist Studies</title>, 32.91-92 (2017): 202-12,
               doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/08164649.2017.1357009"
                  >10.1080/08164649.2017.1357009</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leigh2015" label="Leigh 2015">Leigh, M. <title rend="quotes">Reading
                  between the Lines. History and the Studio Owner‘s Wife.</title> In C. Gledhill and
               J. Knight (eds), <title rend="italic">Doing Women’s Film History. Reframing Cinemas,
                  Past and Future</title>, Urbana (2015), pp. 42-52.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="long2016" label="Long 2016">Long, D. <title rend="quotes">Excavating Film
                  History with Metadata Analysis: Building and Searching the ECHO Early Cinema
                  Credits Database.</title> In C. R. Acland and E. Hoyt (eds), <title rend="italic"
                  >The Arclight Guidebook to Media History and the Digital Humanities</title>,
               Sussex (2016), pp. 145-164.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich1999" label="Manovich 1999">Manovich, L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Database as Symbolic Form,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Convergence</title>, 5.2 (1999): 80-99.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2007" label="McGann 2007">McGann, J. <title rend="quotes">Database,
                  Interface, and Archival Fever,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1588.92.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgill2007" label="McGill 2007">McGill, M. L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Remediating Whitman,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1592-96.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckernan2015" label="McKernan 2015">McKernan, L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Searching for Mary Murillo.</title> In C. Gledhill and J. Knight (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Doing Women’s Film History. Reframing Cinemas, Past and
                  Future</title>, Urbana (2015), pp. 78-92.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pampel2014" label="Pampel and Dallmeier-Tiessen 2014">Pampel, H. and
               Dallmeier-Tiessen, S. <title rend="quotes">Open Research Data: From Vision to
                  Practice.</title> In S. Bartling and S. Friesike (eds), <title rend="italic"
                  >Opening Science: The Evolving Guide on How the Internet Is Changing
                  Research</title>, Collaboration and Scholarly Publishing, Cham (2014), pp 213-224,
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-00026-8_14">doi:
                  10.1007/978-3-319-00026-8_14</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pearlman2018" label="Pearlman and Heftberger 2018">Pearlman, K., and
               Heftberger, A. <title rend="quotes">Editorial: Recognising Women’s Work as Creative
                  Work.</title> In A. Heftberger and K. Pearlman (eds) <title rend="italic">Women at
                  the Editing Table: Revising Soviet Film History of the 1920s and
               1930s.</title> Special Issue of <title rend="italic">Apparatus. Film, Media and
                  Digital Cultures in Central and Eastern Europe</title> 6 (2018), <ref
                  target="http://dx.doi.org/10.17892/app.2018.0006.124"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.17892/app.2018.0006.124</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramsay2004" label="Ramsay 2004">Ramsay, S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Databases.</title> In S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and J. Unsworth (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, Malden (2004), pp.
               177-197, doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470999875.ch15"
                  >10.1002/9780470999875.ch15</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schoch2013" label="Schöch 2013">Schöch, C. <title rend="quotes">Big?
                  Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 2.3 (2013), <ref
                  target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/#to-big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities-n-6"
                  >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/#to-big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities-n-6</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sobchack2000" label="Sobchack 2000">Sobchack, V. <title rend="quotes">What
                  is film history?, or, the Riddle of the Sphinxes.</title> In C. Gledhill and L.
               Williams (eds), <title rend="italic">Reinventing film studies</title>, London (2000),
               pp. 300-315.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stallybrass2007" label="Stallybrass 2007">Stallybrass, P. <title
                  rend="quotes">Against Thinking,</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 122.5 (2007): 1580-1587.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zaagsma2013" label="Zaagsma 2013">Zaagsma, G. <title rend="quotes">On
                  Digital History,</title>
               <title rend="italic">BMGN – Low Countries Historical Review</title>, 128.4 (2013):
               3-29.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
