<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research
                    across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities
                    and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Natalie <dhq:family>Philips</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Michigan State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nmp@msu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Natalie Phillips is an associate professor of English and affiliated
                            faculty in Cognitive Science at Michigan State University. As founder
                            and co-director of the Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition lab
                            (DHLC), she is devoted to pioneering interdisciplinary experiments that
                            foreground the humanities as they explore the complex cognitive systems
                            involved in our engagement with literature, music and the arts.
                            Alongside her first book, Distraction (JHUP), her work in
                            eighteenth-century literature, cognitive approaches to fiction, literary
                            neuroscience, and the history of mind has appeared in high-impact
                            volumes from Oxford University Press, MIT Press, Routledge, among
                            others, and has been supported by grants including the American Council
                            of Learned Societies, the Mellon foundation, the Wallenberg foundation,
                            and the National Science Foundation (NSF).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Alexander <dhq:family>Babbitt</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Michigan State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>babbitt6@msu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Alexander Babbitt has his bachelor’s degree in English from Michigan
                            State University. While at Michigan State University, he studied the
                            relationship between cognitive science and the humanities, with an
                            emphasis on interdisciplinary pedagogy. Currently, he is an Elementary
                            School teacher in Brooklyn, NYC. His current interests are centered
                            around creating accessible and interdisciplinary instruction for
                            childhood education.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Soohyun <dhq:family>Cho</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Michigan State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>chosooh1@msu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Soohyun Cho is a Ph.D. candidate in English at Michigan State University,
                            specializing in crime fiction, cognitive approaches to literature,
                            disability studies, and digital humanities. Her current project focuses
                            on the intersection of disability studies and popular culture studies,
                            exploring the tradition of detectives with non-normative minds. Her
                            ongoing digital experiment investigates the reader's experience with
                            Kindle. In her time at MSU, Soohyun has served as a lab lead as well as
                            a Graduate Research Assistant in the DHLC Lab.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jessica <dhq:family>Kane</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Albion College</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kanejess@msu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jessica Kane is the Associate Director of Community-Based Learning at
                            Albion College. Her professional work focuses on supporting authentic,
                            equitable campus-community partnerships to enhance civic engagement and
                            positive social change. Her scholarly work focuses on gender, genre, and
                            narrative authority in eighteenth-century British literature. The link
                            between the two is an emphasis on how the relationships we create and
                            stories we tell can change the world.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Cody <dhq:family>Mejeur</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University at Buffalo</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>cmejeur@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Cody Mejeur is Visiting Assistant Professor of Game Studies at University
                            at Buffalo. Their work uses games to theorize narrative as an embodied
                            and playful process that constructs how we understand ourselves and our
                            realities. They have published on games pedagogy, gender and queerness
                            in games, and the narrative construction of reality. They are currently
                            Associate Director of Palah Light Lab at UB, researcher with the LGBTQ
                            Video Game Archive, editor at One Shot: A Journal of Critical Games
                            &amp; Play, and serve as Diversity Officer for the Digital Games
                            Research Association.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Craig <dhq:family>Pearson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Michigan State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>craigspearson@wustl.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Craig Pearson has bachelor's degrees in Neuroscience and Biochemistry
                            &amp; Molecular Biology from Michigan State University, with an
                            additional major in English and, as a Marshall Scholar, he earned a PhD
                            in clinical neuroscience at the University of Cambridge. He is now a
                            medical student at Washington University School of Medicine. His
                            interests include art, fiction, and narrative medicine, and he has
                            contributed to several collaborative projects that showcase the
                            perspectives of people with different abilities and health status.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000478</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000478/000478.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State
                    University was founded in 2012 with the mission of bringing together scholars
                    from disciplines including literature, neuroscience, education, computer
                    science, and digital humanities to investigate the cognitive processes involved
                    in reading texts of all kinds. The real story is much more complicated: emerging
                    through a combination of institutional risk-taking and serendipitous accident,
                    the lab was — and remains — an example of how conventional definitions of a
                        <soCalled>laboratory,</soCalled> and particularly the rather fraught label
                    of <soCalled>humanities lab,</soCalled> often come short of capturing the true
                    cross-disciplinary nature of this type of work. More than any academic or
                    methodological template, the DHLC lab emerged through the curiosity and
                    enthusiasm of the students who inhabit it. For that reason, this case study — a
                    brief history of the DHLC’s development, cultural practices, and ongoing work —
                    has been written collaboratively with multiple voices, including the lab
                    director (Natalie Phillips) and the student researchers. Together, we describe
                    the challenges and opportunities created by embarking on a radically
                    interdisciplinary research effort. We report the elements that enabled the DHLC
                    lab to find success through a willingness to abandon expectations and adapt to
                    rapidly evolving research practices, while maintaining our core focus on the
                    humanities. We hope this case study proves useful for those who, like us, seek
                    to explore the vast potential of interdisciplinary lab space for DH practice,
                    the pedagogical benefits of collaborative research, and how to prioritize
                    humanities in a STEM-focused world.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This is a case study describing the creation of the Digital Humanities and
                    Literary Cognition lab at Michigan State University and the interdisciplinary
                    research efforts made within the lab.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Prologue</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at
                        Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic
                        planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and
                        serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.<note>We use italics
                            here and throughout to represent the voice of Professor Natalie
                            Philliips, Director of the Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition
                            lab. When we switch into non-italic font, this indicates the collective
                            voice of the article’s six authors. </note> It emerged organically from
                        interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU
                        colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford... and at times, people who
                        just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely
                        what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the
                        development of other humanities labs <ptr target="#breithaupt2017"/>. One
                        common way to approach building such a lab — a trend you might say — is by
                        creating a digital scholarship or digital humanities center, a space devoted
                        to supporting as many different fields, departments, and faculty as
                        possible: building websites, <quote rend="inline">provid[ing] a support
                            mechanism for the growing areas of e-research and digital
                            scholarship,</quote> and facilitating the use of big, expensive pieces
                        of technology (or even better, the analysis of <soCalled>big
                        data</soCalled>) <ptr target="#lippincott2014"/>. We have a version of this
                        at MSU, the <ref target="http://digitalscholarshiplab.msu.edu/">Digital
                            Scholarship Lab</ref>, and it’s amazing. That’s not quite what we do. I
                        can run an MRI and conduct advanced brain imaging, but I can’t build a
                        website to save my life, so I’m glad that others aren’t relying on me or the
                        lab to do this type of DH. Instead, the DHLC began with a specific research
                        question about close reading and literary neuroscience. Now, we design and
                        run a variety of new experiments, opening up the space for ever-growing
                        grassroots engagement with others across campus and with our
                    community.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In 2012, the lab wasn’t what most would call a
                            <soCalled>lab.</soCalled> One day, I was working with three students —
                        one from English, one from education, one from neuroscience — at a table
                        we’d dragged from a supply closet. Clustered over our laptops, we were so
                        focused we scarcely looked up as a team of technicians walked in and began
                        installing computers around us. For a DH lab, the moment when the technology
                        appears is normally a glorious occasion; looking back, I can see why the
                        arrival of these computers wasn’t treated with the usual tech-centric
                        revelry. The actual lab was already there — in full swing, fueled by the
                        energy being brought by everyone around the table. The lab was the students,
                        the people. And with them, we got momentum, a combination of student energy
                        and brilliance that would propel us for the next seven years.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">It’s the energy of the people in the lab that sustains me as I
                        navigate the balance of my own work and these new fields we’re engaging. I’m
                        an eighteenth centuryist who gets excited about Margaret Cavendish’s
                        seventeenth-century jokes about the brain, and I also put (willing!)
                        students in brain scanners to see if we can learn more about the cognitive
                        intricacy and uniqueness of reading literature. Fortunately, I work
                        alongside equally interdisciplinary folks. The computer scientist who helped
                        us code our sonnet study at MSU loves poetry so much he actually memorizes
                        it, down to the punctuation (you should hear him recite Whitman or Keats).
                        My co-lead on our music study was a major in violin before he switched to
                        computer science; only later did he jump to cognitive science, focusing on
                        rhythm and music. This sort of interdisciplinary work is not without its
                        limits. As Urszula Pawlicka points out with Bruno Latour, just the name
                            <soCalled>humanities lab</soCalled> risks assuming an ideologically
                        dangerous <quote rend="inline">scientification of the humanities.</quote> If
                        the laboratory is <quote rend="inline">a place that has been socially
                            constructed so as to project the mythos of science onto the world
                            outside its walls,</quote> she writes, <quote rend="inline">then
                            humanities laboratories may begin by borrowing the foreign glamour of
                            science and end by reproducing its ideological parochialisms</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pawlicka2017" loc="527"/>. Rather than remaining naïve to such
                        challenges, our lab — with over thirty students from across disciplines —
                        tackles them head-on in an ongoing, energetic attempt to demonstrate that
                        one can do work that cuts across both humanities and sciences without caving
                        to reductionism and instead centering our humanist commitments. We have not
                        given in to an <soCalled>interdisciplinary delusion</soCalled> but seek to
                        model the pluralism of true cross-disciplinary work, with all the
                        multiplicity it entails <ptr target="#kramnick2018"/>. This is why we are
                        writing this case study — and why we have chosen to tell it collectively.
                        The only way to tell this story is to have students write as well, as equal
                        collaborators and researchers who have made the lab what it is
                    today.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The sounds of the lab on any given day include the clack of typing, the light
                    squeak of pen against dry-erase board, and music — live streaming everything
                    from classical to indie-rock (one undergrad lab lead’s favorite band is Rainbow
                    Kitten Surprise). Academic conversations about our latest lab project on music
                    and narrative intermix with light cursing over how to change font size in
                    E-Prime (the requisite software for taking our poetry study to fMRI). It’s a
                    space for kvetching about grad school applications. Most importantly, it’s a
                    space for laughter, be it a fierce debate on whether the lab’s next event will
                    be an escape room or laser tag, or an equally fierce argument over whose
                    favorite candy is actually disgusting. Entering the lab means joining a warm,
                    rich, chaotic space full of work, odd debates, and enjoyment. The collegial and
                    even goofy atmosphere of the lab is not a weakness — if anything, it energizes
                    our work and makes it more generative. This is our kind of
                    interdisciplinarity.</p>
                <p>One of the real strengths of an interdisciplinary and comparatively young field
                    like digital humanities is the sheer amount of experimentation and invention
                    that digital humanists engage in on a daily basis. We have to, because the work
                    we do is often the first of its kind. We can’t help but be cutting-edge, unique,
                    and integrative, because we have limited models to draw from in terms of
                    literary neuroscience. Even as digital humanities labs at prestigious
                    universities such as Stanford, MIT, and CUNY have become well established, there
                    remain many interdisciplinary areas (i.e. literary cognition) that are only just
                    starting to be explored. As the field continues to grow and mature, however, we
                    have the opportunity to build on one another’s wisdom, to create new models and
                    best practices for present and future digital humanities scholars to follow.
                    That is part of what this article seeks to do, inviting readers to learn from
                    the <emph>story</emph> of our challenges as well as our successes.</p>
                <p>We cannot, however, give you a template. We do not have a model you can simply
                    copy. There is no formula for how to create your own cutting-edge humanities lab
                    — such a thing does not exist, because the most effective labs and programs
                    build on the specific strengths of a given community. Instead, the following
                    case study it is an exploration of one lab, our Digital Humanities and Literary
                    Cognition (DHLC) lab, with a discussion of some of the approaches and strategies
                    we used to create it. In our current moment when the question is shifting from
                    whether or not to have humanities labs to how those labs should operate in more
                    inclusive, equitable, and sustainable ways, our experiences in the DHLC offer
                    some practices for those working in labs old, new, and yet to be. As you read
                    the specifics of how the DHLC works and why we set it up that way, we invite you
                    to imagine yourself and your own situation — to dream of what your own lab could
                    be.</p>
                <p>The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab was founded in 2012. Its
                    first seven years provide a powerful and unique case study that reveals what
                    interdisciplinary work in DH can be, including points of promise and innovation,
                    points of disciplinary tension and translation, and most importantly, lessons
                    that point to the power of actively involving students in a humanities lab. At
                    its core, the DHLC’s mission is to understand how humans think in and through
                    genres of literary art. In other words, we want to understand the intertwined
                    cognitive, neurological, emotional, and cultural processes by which we engage
                    with art, relate to it, and use it to make sense of ourselves. We call our
                    research in cognitive and digital humanities <soCalled>literary
                        neuroscience,</soCalled> a phrase that captures how such work could never be
                    just one or the other, just humanities or just science.</p>
                <p>In 1959, C.P. Snow famously described the humanities and sciences as <quote
                        rend="inline">two cultures</quote> separated by a <quote rend="inline"
                        >gap</quote> of <quote rend="inline">mutual incomprehension.</quote> It
                    seemed the two were unable to communicate, and the increasingly siloed nature of
                    disciplinary knowledge throughout the twentieth century did little to help. The
                    present situation is a paradox. As many institutions call for interdisciplinary
                    scholarship and teaching, arts and humanities programs continue to be defunded
                        <ptr target="#wythoff2018"/>. In this cultural moment, interdisciplinary
                    labs like the DHLC have a vital role to play by communicating across the
                    humanities and sciences, translating the value of the humanities, and in
                    particular, championing the critical perspective that the humanities
                        <emph>brings</emph> to interdisciplinary research.</p>
                <p>The DHLC works hard to be a truly interdisciplinary space — we actively integrate
                    methodologies, approaches, and scholars from different disciplines on equal
                    footing. As one example, we always insist on capturing both qualitative and
                    quantitative data whenever we design experiments, and we further ensure that our
                    qualitative data includes space for narrative. The stories and reflections of
                    our study participants are as important as the numbers on an aesthetic pleasure
                    scale, and our student researchers specializing in both humanistic and
                    scientific methods work directly with each other in small groups to analyze the
                    data in tandem. In this way we bring together the strengths of both sciences and
                    humanities, which gives us a richer set of data that enables us to talk to
                    people in different fields in their own languages and concepts.</p>
                <p>In pursuing such a significant cultural and academic goal, it can be easy to get
                    lost in the sauce, so we try to keep our day-to-day research practices in
                    perspective. Walking into the DHLC means walking into a space enclosed by the
                    usual four walls, one of which is a window that stretches from floor to ceiling,
                    offering a gorgeous view of trees and the occasional sunset. Double layered,
                    bright green blinds — technologically advanced to move with the changing
                    daylight, yet broken beyond comprehension — seem to have a mind of their own and
                    close and open over the window randomly, making temperature regulation uniquely
                    difficult. To counteract this, we have an ancient box fan, named <title
                        rend="quotes">Fanny</title> after the protagonist of <title rend="italic"
                        >Mansfield Park</title>. Eight state-of-the-art computers for processing MRI
                    data, DH visualizations, and project results line two walls, and tables are
                    littered with brightly colored sticky notes that range from complex mathematical
                    equations to single words like <quote rend="inline">gender?!?</quote> There are
                    four different styles of chairs, ranging from the foldable to the <quote
                        rend="inline">spinny</quote> chairs that allow for a dramatic turn to listen
                    to someone talking. A portrait of Jane Austen looks over the lab, observing the
                    years of inside jokes written around the room. Most importantly, this physical
                    room we call our lab — the DHLC — not only brings together students from
                    English, Psychology, Neuroscience, Computer Science, Rhetoric, Business, and
                    Art; it creates unique points of contact between them. Neuroscience students
                    read poetry, debate Austen’s irony, and listen to excerpts of orchestral music.
                    Scholars of literature and psychology work together on interdisciplinary fMRI
                    experiment design while artists join computer scientists to develop new digital
                    tools for making art accessible across museum spaces, digital platforms, and
                    coffee shops. There are not many places where a freshman undergrad in political
                    science can talk literary cognition theory with a 5th year English PhD, or where
                    you find professors taking careful notes about sophomores and seniors’ latest
                    project insights. But this is what it means to be at the DHLC.</p>
                <p>Our lab has never adhered to traditional hierarchies, and we actively cultivate a
                    lab culture that resists the neoliberal, top-down power structures of the
                    contemporary university <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#mann2019"/>. We have a PI and lab leads, but these roles are more
                    administrative than anything else. Questions, ideas, answers, and new directions
                    can, should, and do come from everyone (including new researchers bringing fresh
                    perspective to our projects), such that it can be easy to forget who is an
                    undergraduate student, who is a graduate student, and who is a faculty member.
                    Our PI specifically goes by <soCalled>Natalie</soCalled> in the lab as one way
                    to emphasize our non-hierarchical structure. No one asks your rank when you walk
                    into a lab meeting, nor offers their own; instead, anyone might suggest where
                    you can jump in on the latest spreadsheet or data sorting. Our
                    interdisciplinarity supports this setup, because we recognize that each of our
                    members brings a different set of skills and experiences to the lab. Strict
                    hierarchies simply do not make sense when a third-year student might be the
                    expert on a piece of software, a first-year student might be trained in fMRI, a
                    graduate student might have a music theory background, a faculty member might
                    have several successful grants under her belt, and a fourth-year student might
                    have actually run participants in a particular study. We help each other
                    communicate across these many fields and experiences by holding workshops during
                    our regular meetings where researchers will introduce each other to particular
                    concepts, theories, methods, or software and discuss how to best incorporate
                    that knowledge in our studies. In essence, we all do the work, we all have
                    different roles to play, and we could not possibly do all that the lab does if
                    we assumed that any of those roles is more prestigious or more important.</p>
                <p>Bringing together science and humanities in the study of cognition and literary
                    art is certainly a tall order. We <soCalled>manage</soCalled> it in the lab —
                    day by day and project by project — by relying on an open system and a
                    question-led approach, rather than an institutionally-designed order. This model
                    brings with it particular affordances and limitations. It requires maintaining
                    an open lab space in collaboration with student researchers and project leads
                    while also ensuring secure storage for study participants’ data. It relies
                    heavily on the energy and guidance of both the PI and the lab leads. It invites
                    students from all kinds of disciplines who never dreamed of being part of a lab
                    to join in the work of creating knowledge. It means that projects are abandoned
                    partway through, or unnecessarily redone, or go in three directions at once; it
                    also leads to astonishing breakthroughs. It loses some portion of institutional
                    knowledge with every student researcher’s graduation. It can also feel
                    overwhelming especially for new lab members, so we introduce new researchers to
                    the lab’s projects one at a time in order to help them learn about the projects,
                    navigate the IRB process, and let them choose where and how they want to
                    participate according to their interests and availability. It means keeping in
                    regular contact with weekly meetings for the different projects, with constant
                    reminders to take breaks and step back from the work in order to take care of
                    ourselves and each other. And, crucially, it must ensure that all researchers
                    (especially students!) are compensated and credited for their work in the forms
                    of hourly pay, presentations at conferences, and authorship on lab publications.
                    All of this continues to successfully sustain the lab after eight years with
                    minimal advertising (mostly by word of mouth in classes) because it draws people
                    in and gives them the space to explore their own research practices.</p>
                <p>At the beginning of each semester, lab leads for each of the three major research
                    projects present broad semester goals. At the same time, if any group members
                    come up with a hypothesis, they are given a semester or two to play around with
                    the new approach. If the research idea seems sustainable, it becomes a long-term
                    project and is incorporated into a future beginning-of-semester goal
                    presentation. If not, we store detailed notes on the process in a <title
                        rend="quotes">research questions</title> document for future reference. For
                    example, one of the undergraduate researchers got so excited about metaphors
                    that he spent a full semester mapping how often participants highlighted
                    metaphors and how tangible, familiar, or cliché the metaphors were. Although
                    this got stored away for a year, it turns out that it will be absolutely pivotal
                    as we start writing a new article (TBA) for a special issue of <title
                        rend="italic">Narrative</title> in 2023 titled <title rend="quotes">When Do
                        We Love Literature?: The Pleasures of Poetry Reading and the Power of
                        Story.</title></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Lab Slack conversation. Image and names shared with permission. Source:
                        DHLC Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>A screenshot of a conversation on Slack including a meme and discussion
                        of meetings.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Our projects range from fMRI studies of novel reading, to experiments on poetry
                    and pleasure, to cultural explorations of the stories we hear in music. Outside
                    the world of interdisciplinary experiments, the DHLC also organizes exhibitions
                    that blend art, medical humanities, and disability studies to create accessible
                    art installations in museums where everyone — including those along the visual
                    disability spectrum — can <emph>touch</emph> the art. This means we have used DH
                    tools that range from computational software for analyzing brain data and
                    patterns in neural activation (FSL), text analysis tools such as Voyant and
                    sentiment analysis, and Guide by Cell, the latest web-based link that we use to
                    provide audio descriptions for Accessible Art visitors with visual disabilities
                    (much better than QR codes). The fact that we use DH tools so much in order to
                        <emph>do</emph> our research makes the lab an equally fascinating case study
                    in how digital tools blend the virtual and physical. Depending on the day and
                    number of computers, we use Skype, Zoom, or Google Hangouts, we write and edit
                    on Google Drive, and we communicate in almost twenty Slack channels for
                    different projects, though most researchers are active primarily in the few
                    related to their chosen projects. In the image above, a lost-in-sauce meme
                    motivated students to focus in the last frantic hours of poster writing before
                    our yearly undergraduate conference (see Figure 1). We use many of these same
                    channels to talk with collaborators around the world: Stanford University, New
                    York University, The University of Arkansas, Princeton University, and the
                    University of Hong Kong. In these ways, our lab is quite expansive, both
                    physically and virtually <ptr target="#perkel2016"/>.</p>
                <p>This highly collaborative nature of our digital humanities research makes our lab
                    a <soCalled>hybrid space,</soCalled> something Steve Harrison and Paul Dourish
                    define as a space that <quote rend="inline">comprises both physical and
                        virtual</quote>
                    <ptr target="#harrison1996" loc="72"/>. We experience this physical–digital
                    interplay in the lab daily, in embodied interactions that are <quote
                        rend="inline">framed simultaneously by the physical space, the virtual space
                        and the relationship between the two</quote>
                    <ptr target="#harrison1996" loc="72"/>. Interdisciplinary work in the lab
                    involves bridging not only disciplines but also places and practices, and how we
                    conduct research is in many ways defined and delimited by both physical and
                    virtual spaces (see Figure 2). For instance, our lab is located at Michigan
                    State University (MSU). Most of our lab members and participants therefore
                    reflect typical university demographics and range in ages from seventeen to
                    thirty-five. Thus, we constantly remind ourselves when analyzing data that we
                    have a particular group of college students who like coffee and poetry, are
                    interested in $5 Starbucks gift cards to participate in our latest study, and
                    have many other time commitments in their studies, work, and social lives. The
                    lab’s physical space comfortably fits only approximately ten of our thirty lab
                    members at a time. Accessibility measures are also ironically difficult in a lab
                    that intentionally organizes accessible art events — Natalie uses a rolling
                    walker when needed but can’t fit it inside our small space.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Members working in the lab. Source: DHLC Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>Seven workers chatting and working in the lab.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The role space plays in defining research becomes even more apparent when that
                    research involves placing people in circular magnetic tubes. As Joshua Mann
                    notes of digital technologies used to represent the past, nothing about this
                    present technology is <quote rend="inline">hermeneutically neutral</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mann2018"/>. The MRI scanner presents a panoply of physical
                    limitations on research almost too numerous to describe. Students cannot bring a
                    paperback inside a scanner, so they read a digital rendition of a
                        <soCalled>page</soCalled> (or sonnet) at the back of the scanner through a
                    mirror above their eyes, pushing a button or scrolling with a mouse to move
                    through the lines and pages.</p>
                <p>Head movement in an MRI machine means the scan will pick up on the wrong brain
                    regions, so we make a participant as comfortable as possible, providing
                    ear-plugs to drown out the noise of pulse sequences, as well as foam pillows
                    under their knees, for their elbows, and alongside their head for comfort. In
                    this case, we accept the unique constraints on physical space inside an MRI
                    scanner (we can’t change Radiology...yet), but we use our humanist background to
                    push to the very edges of what’s traditionally allowed to be seen inside a
                    scanner. In a radical humanist departure from MRI tradition, our participants
                    read long sections of novels and poetry <emph>at their own pace</emph>, rather
                    than being presented with single sentences or phrases flashing rhythmically on
                    the screen. Yes, the physical constraints determine the research that can be
                    done. Yet DH can open new opportunities, as the DHLC’s first project
                    demonstrates.</p>
                <p>The lab’s first project, <title rend="quotes">Jane Austen and the Neuroscience of
                        Reading and Attention,</title> was an fMRI study of the different levels of
                    attention we can bring to a novel and specifically the differences between close
                    and pleasure reading <ptr target="#phillips2010"/>. Eighteen Ph.D. students in
                    English (picked for their literary training) were asked to read the first
                    chapters of Jane Austen’s <title rend="italic">Mansfield Park</title> inside an
                    MRI, switching between close reading and pleasure reading at defined sections.
                    Afterward, outside the scanner, they wrote informal literary essays on the
                    sections they’d close read. To our astonishment, they ended up quoting the text
                    extensively from memory <ptr target="#phillips2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#phillips2018"/>. Sponsored by an ACLS Digital Innovations grant,
                    we also began to map the unique patterns of quoting from Mansfield Park,
                    revealing an attraction to tangible and material words in the text and how these
                    mnemonic anchors grounded sophisticated analysis of class dynamics, stylistics,
                    gender roles, and Austen’s irony. Analysis is still ongoing, but this first
                    experiment exemplifies the spontaneity and delightful accident that marks all
                    our projects. In seeking to study the different levels of attention we bring to
                    books, we ended up being the first study of natural reading. Based on an article
                    gone viral, the study also ended up being an unexpected showcase for the value
                    of literary study, revealing the widespread brain regions activated by close
                    reading, a core skill in the liberal arts <ptr target="#goldman2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#thompson2012"/>.</p>
                <p>Ultimately, this study and the other DHLC projects we describe in the coming
                    pages reveal how digital humanities labs can take an active role in championing
                    the humanities in our communities. We believe that the interdisciplinary,
                    non-hierarchical structure of our lab is valuable philosophically, politically,
                    and practically. We see the different fields represented in the lab as equally
                    important partners in our work, rather than science chasing humanities or
                    humanities chasing science. In the same vein, the members of our lab are equally
                    important partners in our work, regardless of university rank. Together, these
                    approaches shake up the relationships between fields and between people, giving
                    everyone ownership in what the lab does and reminding us that everyone can and
                    should be part of the process of expanding human knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Pleasures of Poetry Reading</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">We could say that the international recognition our first study
                        of Austen received naturally led to a second project, <title rend="quotes"
                            >Neuroaesthetics: Poetry and Aesthetic Pleasure.</title> We moved from
                        novels to poetry, conducting an experiment that emerged organically from a
                        research group centered at NYU on the neural and cognitive dimensions of
                        aesthetic experience. In reality, I was grading papers for a course on the
                        eighteenth-century novel with a friend when an unexpected email arrived from
                        a Dean at NYU declaring she and her colleagues had been following my
                        research and inviting me to join a global collaboration on neuroscience and
                        art. I knew if I wanted to take this on — that is, involve the lab in
                        designing three new experiments on literature, music, and art — I would need
                        to bring the lab with me. I said yes, and boarded a plane to New York… with
                        three students in tow. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">What I didn’t expect was that it was absolutely necessary that
                        the students be there. Sitting at the table in a group of neuroscientific
                        leaders, I watched in awe as they offered insights (and even experimental
                        critiques) again and again, gaining the respect of famous scholars in the
                        neuroscience of music, vision, and art. Yet, as we all know, most of the
                        work — and many of the decisions — happens, not in the conference room, but
                        over dinner. During the wining and dining, the students mixed and mingled
                        with enviable ease, picking up comments that would prove invaluable. Had
                        they been virtually present over Skype, all that would have been lost. On
                        our final night, free from the formality of fine dining, we ordered to-go
                        Indian food and clustered over our laptops in my hotel room. As we pieced
                        together our notes from the weekend, and laughed over the comic tidbits we’d
                        overheard, we dropped all previous expectations and began to design a
                        totally new experiment on poetry — one that would advance Neuroaesthetics
                        and further define the DHLC. As we worked and laughed, I realized the lab
                        had been moved, so to speak, to a small hotel room in New York, with plastic
                        knives and chana masala in styrofoam cups.</hi></p>
                <p>Forging ahead with the energy from that first trip to NYU, and in ongoing
                    collaboration with G. Gabrielle Starr, we designed a study looking at real-time
                    responses to poetry <ptr target="#starr2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#starr2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#belfi2018"/>. We wanted to capture readers’ aesthetic reactions to
                    poems as well as how their pleasure shifted as they read; thus, we asked
                    participants to highlight moments they found aesthetically pleasing and
                    displeasing while reading sonnets. First with pencil and paper, later with red
                    and green highlights on a computer screen, fifty MSU students registered their
                    aesthetic responses when reading a set of sonnets drawn from the early modern
                    period to now. After reading and highlighting, participants were asked to use a
                    provided numerical scale to rate the vividness of imagery, the poem’s positive
                    or negative overall theme, and the intensity of their own emotional response.
                    What we found fascinating is that, while individual tastes clearly differ, there
                    are stunning similarities in moments people collectively find moving. For
                    example, reading <title rend="quotes">Dawn in New York,</title> a sonnet by key
                    Harlem Renaissance writer Claude McKay, 60% of participants single out the
                    description of women and men wandering the streets of Manhattan with <quote
                        rend="inline">wine-weakened</quote> eyes as particularly aesthetically
                    pleasing <ptr target="#mckay2019"/>. At this point pleasure aligned across
                    readers, revealing an unexpected moment of cognitive and emotional unity.</p>
                <p>The data for each sonnet was so rich, with so many things to explore, that
                    students involved in the poetry study decided to pursue two distinct research
                    questions. One group (nicknamed <soCalled><ref
                            target="https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/columnist/2017/03/03/guide-all-those-weird-words-your-teen-uses/98688930/"
                            >LIT</ref></soCalled>) is exploring the question of why so many people
                        <soCalled>like</soCalled> (or positively highlighted) obviously negative
                    words and phrases.<note>A nickname that is simultaneously a combination of team
                        members’ initials, a shortening of the word <soCalled>literature,</soCalled>
                        a reference to the colloquial phrase <soCalled>lit,</soCalled> meaning
                        something fresh and on fire <ptr target="#jolly2017"/>. </note> They
                    observed, with a wry joy, that participants hadn’t only positively highlighted
                    moments of aesthetic pleasure associated with positive themes (i.e. love,
                    sunrises, hope) but also took pleasure in negative themes (i.e. war and
                    sadness). For instance, participants found poetic beauty in McKay’s <quote
                        rend="inline">cheerless domes;</quote> similarly, in Michael Ferris’ <title
                        rend="quotes">The Catskill Eagle,</title> numerous participants loved the
                    moment where the sonnet describes <quote rend="inline">rage and wonder battle
                        cruel, and strange</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ferris2011"/>. The other group became fascinated with the question
                    of the potential differences between how English majors and non-English majors
                    read and enjoy poetry, with a zeal that earned them the group name <title
                        rend="quotes">Oxford Comma.</title> Curious about the influence of a
                    literary education on aesthetic pleasure, they decided to design and run another
                    set of experiments. Fueled by coffee and candy from our famously always-full
                    candy pitcher and recently-donated Keurig machine, they ran another
                    approximately thirty psychology majors as participants (see Figure 3).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Candy Jar. Source: DHLC Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>A jar filled with candy and a list titled <title rend="quotes">What is
                            your favorite candy</title> sit on a desk.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In the new experiments, Psychology majors highlighted what they loved (and
                    didn’t) about poetry, providing key data to match up with the previous data from
                    English majors. Immediately, we noticed radical differences in aesthetic
                    pleasure, with Psychology students generally loving Henry Wadsworth Longfellow
                    and English students delighting instead in the far lesser known poem, Catherine
                    Chandler’s <title rend="quotes">Henslow’s Sparrow.</title> Though Chandler’s
                    poem opens with extensive descriptions of the elusive bird, it turns, mid-poem,
                    to admit the poet has never heard or seen one: <cit><quote rend="block"><l>Or so
                                they say; for I have yet to spy</l>
                            <l>the shy, elusive bird, or hear its song,</l>
                            <l>except in Audubon recordings. I</l>
                            <l>admit to shaky faith, but play along; and though my yard’s a skirl of
                                jays and crows,</l>
                            <l>someday it might show up. One never knows.</l></quote><ptr
                            target="#chandler2019"/></cit> The part English majors love best is the
                    final cryptic phase: <quote rend="inline">One never knows.</quote> In a world
                    where students notoriously complain that they don’t like poetry because they
                    don’t know what it means, the English majors are <emph>drawn</emph> to the
                    uncertain ending that one can <quote rend="inline">never know [sic].</quote></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Compiled highlighting for all participants. The highlighting on the left
                        was our first attempt that highlights specific words, the image on the right
                        is the heatmap method created with ArcGIS. Source: DHLC Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>An overlaid image of highlighting by 30 English majors on a
                        sonnet.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>What students highlighted as particularly pleasing (or not) grew more and more
                    riveting to us as we gathered more responses. Some phrases in poems stood out to
                    a majority of readers, either positively or negatively. But before we could
                    answer that, we had to be able to see it. We tried bolding words that
                    participants had repeatedly highlighted, but this method couldn’t represent the
                    magnitude of students who loved or hated a phrase. Based on the number of likes
                    we tried changing the font size by statistical increments but the rest of the
                    poem was too small to be read. The best answer we could find was to create a
                    statistical highlighting system where words and phrases got darker and darker,
                    in green for pleasure and red for displeasure, which worked well enough until we
                    reached a point where so many people liked or disliked a word that you could no
                    longer see it. Our lab solution was to just turn that word white (see Figure 4).
                    Fortunately, MSU is invested in DH beyond the lab, and had just created a
                    Digital Scholarship Lab in the library. We reached out with a rough idea in mind
                    to solve the visualization problem and they quickly set us up with someone who
                    knew a technology for heat mapping. Together, their GIS specialist and an
                    English undergrad from the lab solved the problem that we had been staring at
                    for a year using ArcGIS, a geographical mapping software. The result was a
                    heatmap that showed where participants collectively found the most pleasure and
                    displeasure in the sonnets they read. Amusingly, we later returned to the
                    Digital Scholarship Lab as invited presenters, with our co-created poetry heat
                    map on display. The presentation received many excited questions for our
                    innovative use of ArcGIS — a testament to how interdisciplinary scholarship can
                    generate new, often unexpected engagements with digital tools that push our
                    questions and how we answer them further.</p>
                <p>The poetry study epitomizes the crucial role physical place and in-person
                    interactions play in advancing the work that goes on in and beyond the lab.
                    Being in the same physical space allows us to rapidly iterate on experiment
                    design, data analysis, and digital tool development in our studies, responding
                    to theoretical concerns and practical considerations as they emerge. However the
                    poetry study also demonstrates how the physical, the virtual, and the digital
                    are increasingly blurred in an interdisciplinary lab. As our most recent study
                    on music and narrative cognition reveals, online collaboration and digital tools
                    for both communication and community research are just as essential for
                    understanding how we encounter literary art in the twenty-first century.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Narrative Perceptions of Music</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Some studies come from concerted effort and invited
                        collaboration, as at NYU. Others emerge by serendipitous accident. This was
                        certainly the case for our study on the stories we hear in music. I had gone
                        to Nashville with my fiancé for one of his (many) music cognition
                        conferences. I’d skipped out of most of the talks and spent much of my time
                        exploring the streets of Nashville, with its eccentric restaurants, huge
                        musical billboards, and fabulous collection of old bookstores. But one
                        poster session caught my eye, so I made my way back to the conference,
                        keeping my badge face-down to stay blissfully incognito. As I read over a
                        poster on <soCalled>close listening</soCalled> to music, I marveled at the
                        structural similarity to our Austen study’s exploration of close and
                        pleasure reading. All of a sudden, the presenter appeared and said: <quote
                            rend="inline">Oh my goodness, it’s you!</quote> I swiftly learned she
                        had designed her study at Stanford intentionally building off our previous
                        work. She had tons of questions and I was happy to help, delving into a
                        conversation that lasted far beyond the poster session and carried us down
                        the stairs toward lunch. I saw my fiancé deeply engaged in a conversation
                        about budget practicalities with the new treasurer for the society, and told
                        her we’d need to meet up later, exchanging cards. When she turned to me on
                        the last step and said, <quote rend="inline">I can’t believe we met. The
                            Brain on Jane!</quote> the acoustics of the space magnified her voice so
                        that (it seemed) the whole room heard. Certainly, my fiance’s conversation
                        about treasury suddenly ended; his companion, Lisa, evidently familiar with
                        our study, promptly turned to me and said, <quote rend="inline">You’re a
                            cognitive narratologist? There’s something I need you to
                        see.</quote></hi></p>
                <p>Lisa Margulis, it turns out, is an interdisciplinary scholar who runs the <ref
                        target="http://www.elizabethmargulis.com/about-music-cognition-lab/">Music
                        Cognition Lab</ref> in the Music department at U. Arkansas (soon to be
                    moving to Princeton). She ran a study where she had participants listen to music
                    without words and asked them to describe any story they heard; a surprising
                    number of people did indeed hear a story <ptr target="#margulis2017"/>. She sat
                    Natalie down and had her read some of the narratives they wrote, many of which
                    were incredibly similar, often sharing the same topics, themes, even specific
                    words. The images she showed Natalie — expanded and extended to represent the
                    full experiment — were to become for us the crucial narrative data to explore
                    convergences (and divergences) in the stories people hear in music. When Natalie
                    got back she called the lab leads together at the DHLC and asked the unaskable
                    question: <quote rend="inline">I know we have a lot going on at the lab — too
                        much already. I’m tired, you’re tired… still, is it interesting enough for
                        us to run with it anyway?</quote> Everyone was fascinated. And, despite the
                    amount of work we had, it was too interesting to <emph>not</emph> work with.</p>
                <p>Supported by a number of fellowships (written together over Skype), an
                    ever-accumulating number of collaborators, and a National Science Foundation
                    (NSF) grant, we began to explore whether — particularly how and when — we use
                    narratives to understand music. In other words, when trying to make sense of a
                    new piece of music, do we begin to <soCalled>hear</soCalled> stories — or,
                    certain types of stories? How much do the tendencies to construct narratives
                    when listening to music, and to have those narratives align, depend on cultural
                    background? The study itself is deceptively simple: participants listen to a
                    piece of orchestral music and are asked if they imagined a story or elements of
                    a story while listening. If they say yes, they are asked to describe the
                    imagined story in as much detail as possible. The similarities in participant
                    answers were often startling. For example, almost 74% of participants listening
                    to an excerpt of Liszt’s music at U. Arkansas described a <quote rend="inline"
                        >cat-and-mouse story</quote> (see Figure 5).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Sample participant descriptions for two pieces of music. Source: DHLC
                        Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>Table presenting five participants' descriptions of Liszt's <title
                            rend="quotes">Faust's Symphony</title>. All describe a typical
                            <soCalled>cat and mouse</soCalled> scene.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>For the excerpt from Telemann’s <title rend="quotes">Suite in E Major,
                        II,</title> a completely different narrative emerged for listeners: 88% of
                    these subjects imagined wealthy — even royal — characters dancing in a fancy
                    ballroom. Unlike the cat-and-mouse stories, participants listening to Telemann
                    were highly focused on setting. According to their descriptions, any narrative
                    activities — dancing, feasting, socializing, etc. — took place, not
                    consecutively (i.e. cat chases mouse, mouse runs, cat chases again, etc...), but
                    recursively, choreographed in social tandem.</p>
                <p>In order to assess how much cultural context affects these narratives, we are
                    partnering with researchers at the U. of Hong Kong to compare results of our
                    narrative listening studies at U. Arkansas and Michigan State with participants
                    from rural China. In this new cross-cultural version of the study, participants
                    from U. Arkansas, MSU, <emph>and</emph> regions of rural China listen to both
                    Chinese and Western music, allowing us to explore if cultural familiarity with a
                    certain musical style affects the likelihood of imagining stories, or the
                    similarity of the stories they tell. Through five iterations of this study, from
                    the original at U. Arkansas to the ongoing research in China, we have data from
                    a total of 1202 participants. After Natalie’s in-person meeting with Lisa, the
                    rest of the NSF <title rend="italic">Narrative Perceptions of Music</title>
                    study unfolded in virtual space. The musical selections are stored online and
                    played for participants on a computer, with participants’ responses stored
                    carefully in coded Excel files. Since our collaboration spans the globe as well
                    as the country, most of our conversations happen online, fitting the trend of
                    increasingly digital scholarly communication <ptr target="#lopez2015"/>.
                    Messages and results wing back and forth between MSU, U. Arkansas, and the U. of
                    Hong Kong. Most often, we use Zoom, Google Hangouts or Skype to create a
                    collaborative, interdisciplinary, and cross-institutional space to allow
                    ethno-musicologists, computational sound-technicians, cognitive musicologists
                    and narrative theorists to connect. Bringing a variety of DH and humanistic
                    tools to the analysis of these narratives, we are beginning to explore how much
                    these music-inspired storylines converge or diverge for each piece — with the
                    goal of testing this across cultures. This means that at any given time, walking
                    into the lab, you might find people dispersed, each working on a different
                    computer and using a different DH tool to explore similarities and points of
                    uniqueness in our now ~1,500 musical stories. At one computer, we have a student
                    (relatively new to the lab) using Voyant to offer a first-round exploration of
                    common themes in the seventy-nine stories from the students at U. Arkansas
                    listening to musical excerpt WA15. With appropriate stop words, we can begin to
                    see what stands out as a through-line for the stories linked to this particular
                    piece. Do people tend to invoke pirates? Dancing squirrels? Star Wars and/or
                    lightsabers? Out of the word-cloud, we can then return relatively quickly to the
                    specific stories and check their context for more nuance and richness, always
                    keeping a humanities eye out for themes that might go unnoticed by sheer word
                    count. Comments jotted down on a sticky note pose questions: 1) Do these
                    commonly-used words actually point us to themes? 2) Does sheer frequency of a
                    phrase reveal focus? 3) How about what’s implied or left unsaid here...which
                    often seems to carry as much meaning as the explicit and stated?!?</p>
                <p>If you look next to her, on the same side of the lab is an English major, who
                    jumped into our poetry study so early and deeply that he taught himself E-Prime,
                    the standard tool for creating computerized experimental design and data
                    collection. Now, having finished designing macros for our lab computers to make
                    certain common lab tasks easier, and having finished developing an algorithm to
                    map word count for our ever-increasing data-set of stories that people heard in
                    music, we find him deep in network analysis, looking to see how often key terms
                    and phrases from the music-inspired storylines intersected for different pieces
                    of music. He’s never lost his English side — you should hear him go on about
                    metaphor theory some day.</p>
                <p>Across the lab, with headphones in and deeply focused, is a tech-savvy grad
                    student in English and DH developing a tool in R to improve sentiment analysis
                    for our narratives, seeking to assess subtle similarities and differences in the
                        <emph>mood</emph> or <emph>tone</emph> of the stories that might otherwise
                    go unnoticed. In a previous effort to do this for ~500 stories with sentiment
                    analysis tools from IBM Watson and Stanford NLP, two dogged undergrads ran into
                    problems so obvious we couldn’t continue without digging into the algorithm. Our
                    funniest example was about ducks. As it turned out both IBM Watson and Stanford
                    NLP rated a student-imagined story about a bunch of ducks swimming in a pond
                    gathering food as <quote rend="inline">strongly negative.</quote> Other less
                    comic cases of this abounded, and, knowing that we must be thinking critically
                    about these tools, we decided, <quote rend="inline">why not just create our
                        own.</quote> Thus, our brilliant grad student developing a tool in R to
                    better analyze the sentiment of our narratives and capture moods that will
                    always slip by word count.</p>
                <p>At the end of the day, no matter how many different tools we’re working with (or
                    how many people are at the lab), someone usually jokingly admits that candy
                    isn’t cutting it. <quote rend="inline">I’m going to need a drink after this…
                        does anyone want to join?</quote> and off we go to a local bar or
                    restaurant. We stay away from work as much as we can at the bar but conversation
                    often includes laughing over the inside jokes and funniest stories we’ve seen.
                    Some of our favorites examples include: <quote rend="inline">I imagined a fight
                        between two squirrels,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline">This music sounded like a mixture of Michael Myers and
                        clowns,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">plz stp playing songs that stress
                        me out.</quote> While all of these last examples happened <emph>in</emph>
                    (or near) the lab, <title rend="italic">Narrative Perceptions of Music</title>
                    is one of the best studies for talking about how extensive a role virtual tools
                    play in DHLC life, especially considering the national and international
                    collaborations. At one point we met with Lisa virtually on Google Hangouts to
                    discuss challenges with the system we were developing for categorizing the
                    narratives. With the help of our new technological tool, OWL, we could have 360
                    degree video conference camera scope that allowed access to the whole room while
                    automatically shifting focus to different people as they spoke. Still better,
                    everyone in the room could hear (and be heard) while simultaneously being seen
                    no matter where they were. This technology helped the conversation stay vibrant
                    and productive, bringing people together over great distance <ptr
                        target="#bly1993"/>. Modeling the spirit of the lab, Lisa and Devin (two
                    full professors) listened intently as students offered critical feedback on how
                    literary scholars would approach narrative categorization. For instance, when
                    they offered the example <quote rend="inline">I imagined animated shadows
                        creeping over the walls</quote> as an abstract narrative without characters
                    or agents, students were able to offer feedback as equals. When our
                    undergraduate lab lead pointed out that shadows (as well as colors, objects,
                    animals, etc.) could be considered agents (i.e. characters), traditional
                    professorial power dynamics went out the window. Lisa simply said <quote
                        rend="inline">I trust your intuition as a literary scholar.</quote></p>
                <p>It is this same spirit of equality and open-access that motivates our development
                    of <ref target="https://adagia.org/">Adagia</ref>, an online app that collects
                    and maps the narratives of users who listen to a short musical excerpt and share
                    any story they heard (see Figure 6). Their response is immediately visible to
                    them (and others) on a GPS-based map, allowing us to explore how local and
                    cultural influences shape the stories. Our long-term goal for Adagia is to allow
                    users to enrich and reshape the project (adding new music samples online,
                    suggesting new questions, or proposing an easier coding platform). Crowdsourcing
                    traditional scientific research, rendering it online, and making it
                    humanities-friendly, this digital work will also yield an ever-expanding set of
                    stories ripe for DH text analytics. We view Adagia as filling a similar role to
                    Amazon’s Mechanical Turk, an online platform often used to scale up psychology
                    research, but without the corporate overlords or problematic labor practices
                        <ptr target="#burhmester2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#bohannon2016"/>. The virtual and digital elements of our work
                    allow us to reimagine our situated research practices and bring our work beyond
                    the DHLC, MSU, and China. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Adagia screenshot. Source: DHLC Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>A screenshot of a map of the United States. Heart shape symbols
                        represent responses by listeners.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Neurodiversity, Medical Humanities, and Accessible Art</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In Lab Girl, Hope Jahren has a beautiful and moving description
                        of her lab space: <quote rend="block">My laboratory is a place where the
                            lights are always on. My laboratory has no windows, but it needs none.
                            It is self-contained. It is its own world. My lab is both private and
                            familiar, populated by a small number of people who know one another
                            well. My lab is the place where I put my brain out on my fingers and I
                            do things….In my lab, whatever I need is greatly outbalanced by what I
                            have. The drawers are packed full with items that might come in handy.
                            Every object in my lab — no matter how small or misshapen — exists for a
                            reason, even if its purpose has not yet been found….The door is locked
                            and I know everyone who has a key. Because the outside world cannot come
                            into the lab, the lab has become the place where I can be the real me.
                            (18-19)</quote>
                    </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">I find this gorgeous because it captures such a strong part of
                        how I feel about the DHLC. Yet there’s a part of the lab that’s different;
                        something central to its beauty. Yes, the lab is its own world and a
                        sanctuary to me. Yes, it’s stocked with objects whose purpose may not have
                        been found (yet). But every time I go into the lab, I see both people who I
                        know well and people I’ve never met before. And it’s just as often the
                        people I’ve never seen before who have suddenly (I learn) solved an
                        experimental problem — or a problem with complex software and coding — I
                        didn’t even know existed. This shows what it means to be an
                            <soCalled>open</soCalled> humanities lab. We have IRB to protect the
                        confidentiality of brain data, but since the IRB training is essential and
                        free, the lab is radically and powerfully open. This means that problems are
                        solved from the ground up, not top-down. And that the students come up with
                        new questions to ask about each and every project we do, with an energy that
                        carries it far beyond the original idea.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The ultimate proof of this came when I had to go down briefly
                        for medical leave. I’ll admit, egocentrically, I worried that the lab would
                        come to a complete and grinding halt without me. Instead, it flourished as
                        much it always has, possibly even more, since the students knew, deeply now,
                        that what I’d been telling them — that they had the leadership, they had to
                        trust their own instincts, and they could take it forward — was true. They’d
                        been trained for it. This is the ultimate proof that the lab is not
                        vertically driven, nor hierarchical by nature; it continued and prospered
                        while the director was down. Two English majors from a class I taught who
                        joined the lab while I was away ended up, in their first semester, designing
                        and running an entire new branch of the poetry study, getting scientists to
                        highlight the aspects of the poems they found most powerful (or not).
                        Another group went out into the dormitories and hallways and gathered
                        everyday students’ definitions of aesthetic pleasure. Perhaps most
                        impressively, an Accessible Art event that I’d been working on, pulled out
                        of my hands by necessity, expanded based on student innovation to include
                        not just students — as had been my original model — but local community
                        artists and a week-long public exhibition. While away, I found myself
                        missing the lab more than I can say; going in to the DHLC had always meant
                        going into a space where things were happening...where students always had
                        new projects and ideas (not that three experiments and an accessible art
                        project weren’t enough to keep us on our toes). Not that I’m back, I realize
                        what I missed most; the vibrance in the atmosphere — and the sanctuary it
                        provided, always showing, rather than telling that humanists and scientists
                        could do things together...at times, brilliantly...and in ways that expand
                        beyond experiments into the community.</hi></p>
                <p>One of the most powerful ways the DHLC breaks the mold of what labs usually do
                    (obscure experiments behind closed doors) is through a series of multisensory
                    and inclusive art exhibits that have come to be known as Accessible Art. In 2015
                    the student editor of <title rend="italic">Exceptions</title>, a journal housed
                    within the DHLC that publishes work by and for people with visual disabilities,
                    approached an English professor and an art professor with the idea for a
                    touchable art exhibit. English students would select or create a sensory-rich
                    passage of text, which students in the art class would use as inspiration for a
                    multisensory piece of art. The Accessible Art exhibit was born with the motto
                        <title rend="quotes">Touch the Art!</title> After that first year, <title
                        rend="italic">Exceptions</title> editors continued to plan different
                    accessible artistic events, including a second Accessible Art exhibit in 2017.
                    In honor of Veteran’s day this exhibit focused on depictions of war, and <ref
                        target="https://www.exceptionsjournal.com/blog/2017/11/sense-of-self">drew
                        over 200 visitors</ref>. One wrote, <quote rend="inline">This changed the
                        paradigm of art for me, before this event I only thought of art as visual
                        and did not consider the fact that art can and should engage all senses and
                        be accessible for all people.</quote> Another put it this way: <quote
                        rend="inline">it was actually accessible to everyone. QR codes were
                        available to have the literary aspects of the art read aloud and then of
                        course we were encouraged to touch the art, which is something unheard of in
                        a museum.</quote> Our events were never only about opening museum spaces to
                    visitors with visual disabilities, important as such work is. Instead, we sought
                    to encourage every visitor to think about engaging with art in a different way.
                    The enjoyment that comes from the multi-sensory indulgence of touching the
                    untouchable opens people’s minds to consider what a more inclusive and
                    accessible world might look like (see Figure 7).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Children at Accessible Art exhibit touching artwork. Source: DHLC
                        Lab</head>
                    <figDesc>Two children touching artwork.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>It was precisely this call for art to engage all senses and all people that
                    guided our vision for the 2019 exhibit. Natalie was on medical leave, but it
                    didn’t occur to us to question whether a group of students could pull off the
                    project ourselves — our collective years with the lab had taught us we could. We
                    began with the pattern of the two previous exhibits, and in August 2018 a few
                    graduate students attended a folk art festival and met a local quiltmaker. Her
                    fidget quilts — lap blankets with tassels, beads, textural patterns, zippers,
                    and ribbons — give people with Alzheimer’s and dementia something to play with
                    that soothes the restlessness than often accompanies those diseases (see Figure
                    8).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Artist’s fidget quilt for people with Alzheimer’s and dementia. Source:
                        Beth Donaldson, used with permission</head>
                    <figDesc>A blue quilt with multiple fabrics and textures.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>We wanted her art as part of the exhibit, and started dreaming of an event that
                    brought together student and community art. The project grew to include almost a
                    dozen undergraduate and graduate students on the planning team as well as nearly
                    fifty undergraduate students and community members creating multi-sensory art,
                    designing the exhibit, documenting the exhibit’s accessibility, writing grants,
                    and organizing tours for local schools. In addition to the fidget quilt, our art
                    pieces included other textiles, like a piece of embroidery that uses both
                    Braille and the Latin alphabet. Another installation was a mirror hung at forty
                    inches from the ground, the proper level for someone in a wheelchair, surrounded
                    by selfies the artist has taken of herself in mirrors around the MSU campus; the
                    pictures are mostly the top of her head and empty space, because the mirrors are
                    too high. Visitors were encouraged to take selfies in this mirror — people who
                    don’t use wheelchairs will mostly get torso shots, demonstrating what it feels
                    like when the world is not set up for you. Numerous sculptures played with
                    texture, like one that is mixed metal and ceramics, another that incorporates
                    moss, and a third that is a window box full of fake flowers created from
                    materials like yarn, tulle, pipe cleaners, and feathers.</p>
                <p>The 2019 Accessible Art exhibit is a testament to the way the DHLC empowers its
                    members not only to take on independent work but also to take it outside the lab
                    itself. Our <soCalled>closed</soCalled> lab is just one node in an open,
                    interconnected web that stretches across the campus, country, and world, similar
                    to other emerging art labs <ptr target="#pormann2015"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>What’s in a Lab? Digital Humanities, Interdisciplinary Futures</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The brief sketches of the DHLC and its projects, students, and
                        possibilities that we’ve included here are only the beginning of where our
                        lab has been, and where it is going. It certainly hasn’t always been easy to
                        organize and run an interdisciplinary DH lab, but thankfully I’ve had the
                        support of many fantastic colleagues — including my students — in doing so.
                        In so many ways, the DHLC is driven by student innovation and research,
                        including students creating their own studies using the skills and tools
                        they learned in the lab. For example, graduate students Cody Mejeur, Soohyun
                        Cho, and Jes Lopez have designed experiments that identify the neural
                        networks involved in narrative comprehension in video games, investigate the
                        cognitive and cultural effects of Kindle Popular Highlights, and analyze the
                        representations of autistic characters in literature and film through
                        embedded sentiment, respectively.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">If I could sum up the most important lessons I’ve learned along
                        the way for those interested in building and running similar labs, these
                        would be my main points: <list type="ordered">
                            <item><hi rend="bold">Involve students as equals.</hi> Not just as
                                students but as lively, active, curious people. Let them explore and
                                grow. Even better, treat them with the respect you give your
                                colleagues and global collaborators. You’ll be astonished. </item>
                            <item><hi rend="bold">Accept that serendipitous accidents will grow into
                                    new things</hi>: a lab, an fMRI, a poetry study, or a series of
                                accessible art exhibits. Embrace it, and embrace the fact that each
                                new project will make you want a new tool.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="bold">Things expand: be ready</hi> (it’s going to be
                                okay). The lab can’t hold it all, so reserve extra rooms.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="bold">Think of interdisciplinary as pluralism</hi>. It’s
                                not DH vs traditional methods, but rather a both/and situation that
                                involves a lot of translation work, over and over again.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="bold">Allow yourself the joy of working with
                                    students</hi>. Running a lab is a lot of work, I won’t lie. But
                                you’ll experience moments of personal fulfillment and pride in a
                                group that are absolutely unrivaled.</item>
                        </list></hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In the <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher
                            Education</title>, Jonathan Kramnick claims we are living in an academic
                        moment governed by <title rend="quotes">The Interdisciplinary
                            Delusion</title>
                        <ptr target="#kramnick2018"/>. And there are days when it does feel like a
                        delusion, but not the one that Kramnick cites. It feels like a delusion when
                        on the morning of a university-wide research competition, I stop by the lab
                        to see students in English, Biology, and Education still adding new data to
                        their posters, and then, hours later, watch them accept the top prize. When
                        I return from medical leave to discover that students have run two new
                        studies despite joining the lab just a month earlier. When I step into the
                        Broad Art Museum for the lab’s Accessible Art exhibition and get to touch my
                        first work of student art and feel how they captured an element of the
                        poetry. It’s the brilliance and energy of the students that are drawn to
                        this work, not the facade of interdisciplinary novelty, that so astonishes
                        and inspires me.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Interdisciplinary work is a shift of view, not a truth claim.
                        No one in the lab and none of my colleagues feel that we will somehow find
                        the absolute truth about poetry and pleasure. Far from it. Instead we are
                        simply using a different set of tools to get a glimpse into what 30 students
                        love, or hate, about sixteen sonnets. Our music and narrative study may
                        extend to China, but it has the same limits. The excitement isn’t all <quote
                            rend="inline">an interdisciplinary fantasy of the moment.</quote> It
                        comes from real students, professors, and colleagues around the world who
                        have their own deep disciplinary training and are contributing it to
                        illuminate a new facet that otherwise would never have been seen about how
                        we engage with literature, music, and art.</hi></p>
                <p>The common fear of digital humanities and other interdisciplinary fields like
                    literary neuroscience is that we are attempting to scientize the humanities,
                    making them more quantifiable, measurable, and profitable <ptr
                        target="#pask2018"/>. Without wading too deeply into a longstanding debate
                    about the validity of these fields, we want to acknowledge that there are
                    reasons to be cautious about a type of interdisciplinary research that just
                    seeks to import scientific knowledge to the humanities in order to attract more
                    institutional support and grant dollars <ptr target="#allington2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#singh2016"/>. In the DHLC, we make it a primary goal to challenge
                    this trend. We believe that truly interdisciplinary work isn’t a one-way street,
                    as though the sciences have the authority on truth and reality and the
                    humanities are here merely to dress it up. Rather, we are proud of having a lab
                    space that humanitizes the sciences, seeing young neuroscientists regularly
                    reading literature and poetry, and introducing scholars in English, Education,
                    Rhetoric, and other areas to neuroscience and digital tools for analyzing
                    artistic media. Interdisciplinary digital humanities labs are uniquely
                    positioned to make these points of contact happen, and to do the critical work of
                    championing the humanities and resisting the institutional privileging of the
                    sciences.</p>
                <p>In an age where human life is increasingly shaped by digital media — indeed,
                    where we seem to be evolving alongside our technology, as N. Katherine Hayles
                    argues — brain imaging technology can give us new insight on how human
                    meaning-making is embodied, and how it operates in different digital contexts
                        <ptr target="#hayles2012"/>. At the same time, our ability to critique the
                    forms, power, and ideologies that shape the sciences we use helps us to
                    encounter the limits of neuroscience — all the many places where existing
                    studies fail to account for the rich diversity of human experience <ptr
                        target="#kim2018"/>. The implications of such understandings are potentially
                    far-reaching. For example, knowing how we close read and pleasure read
                    differently can change how we teach and approach texts, or learning how we
                    perceive music as narrative can affect how we compose and use everything from
                    advertising jingles to symphonies.</p>
                <p>Our work in the digital humanities and literary cognition is just one of many
                    possible sites for interdisciplinary collaboration and research. Imagine, for
                    example, what humanities-based ecocriticism labs might look like, or consider
                    what the humanities could bring to the critical coding and computing centers and
                    networks that have sprung up in recent years <ptr target="#ruiz2017"/>.<note>See
                        FemTechNet, Fembot Collective, Software Studies Initiative, to name only a
                        few.</note> In many ways we have only begun to see the potential
                    combinations and new perspectives that such lab work can generate. And even on
                    the level of individual labs, as the DHLC demonstrates, work is expanding beyond
                    the walls of any one institution into many physical and virtual spaces across
                    the globe <ptr target="#klein2016"/>. Approaches from the DHLC have inspired the
                    structure and process of other digital humanities labs, like Dr. Stephen
                    Grandchamp’s <ref target="https://umfdh.org/">Digital Humanities Lab</ref> at
                    the University of Maine at Farmington, which utilizes the student-led model of
                    the DHLC by having undergraduates work with faculty to integrate DH into
                    curricula and to provide one-on-one instruction for students. Grandchamp also
                    adjusted and adapted this model in ways that are different from how the DHLC
                    run: all his student assistants have been hired as freshmen with the goal of
                    working four complete years in the lab. This creative reconfiguration has led to
                    brilliant work for DH outreach in Maine — the student assistants are taking the
                    lead on a digital archival project by scanning the historical catalogs
                    (including creative writing and visual art) of a local seed cooperative with the
                    goal of creating a fully-searchable online archive.</p>
                <p>Of course there are good reasons to be suspicious of these trends, and thankfully
                    the humanities draw our attention to questions of access, privilege, and power
                    in pursuing them <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#risam2015"/>. Still, if there is anything we have learned that can
                    help others in running, starting, or just considering a lab, it is that
                    embracing a <soCalled>try everything</soCalled> ethos can lead to unexpected and
                    generative opportunities for changing how we think, especially when trying
                    everything is inclusive of different peoples and supportive of their skills,
                    knowledges, and goals. Our research practices are always situated within various
                    types of institutions, traditions, and systems of power, but they also always
                    hold out the possibility for new and revolutionary insights to spontaneously
                    emerge. To be more specific to the digital humanities, if we are to critically
                    engage with digital technologies, then we have to be willing to let those
                    engagements evolve and emerge to address the critical question or situation at
                    hand. We also have to be open to taking risks, and even to failing. After all,
                    we can learn just as much (and sometimes more!) from the experiments that fail
                    as the ones that produce promising results. The great benefit of prioritizing
                    the humanities in this trial and error is that they can guide the process,
                    minimizing the harm and emphasizing the importance of considering the meanings
                    and ethics behind research projects. This interdisciplinary work is not the
                    delusion of one moment in higher education, it is an ongoing project that
                    contributes to answering some of the most pernicious problems of the
                    twenty-first century.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allington2016" label="Allington 2016">Allington, D., S. Brouillette,
                    and D. Golumbia. <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A
                        Political History of Digital Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Los
                        Angeles Review of Books</title>. May 1, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="belfi2018" label="Belfi 2018">Belfi, A. M., E. A. Vessel, and G. G.
                    Starr. <title rend="quotes">Individual ratings of vividness predict aesthetic
                        appeal in poetry</title>. <title rend="italic">Psychology of Aesthetics,
                        Creativity, and the Arts</title> 12 (3): 341–350.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bly1993" label="Bly 1993">Bly, S. A., S. R. Harrison, and S. Irwin.
                        <title rend="quotes">Media spaces: bringing people together in a video,
                        audio, and computing environment</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Communications of the ACM</title> 36 (1): 28–46.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bohannon2016" label="Bohannon 2016">Bohannon, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Mechanical Turk upends social sciences</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Science</title>, 352 (6291): 1263–1264.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burhmester2011" label="Burhmester 2011">Buhrmester, M., T. Kwang, and
                    S. D. Gosling. <title rend="quotes">Amazon’s Mechanical Turk: A New Source of
                        Inexpensive, Yet High-Quality, Data?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>, 6 (1):
                    3–5.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="breithaupt2017" label="Breithaupt 2017">Breithaupt, F. <title
                        rend="quotes">Designing a Lab in the Humanities</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, February 6, 2017,
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.chronicle.com/article/Designing-a-Lab-in-the/239132"
                        >https://www.chronicle.com/article/Designing-a-Lab-in-the/239132</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chandler2019" label="Chandler 2019">Chandler, C. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Henslow’s Sparrow</title>. <ref
                        target="http://poetrymagazines.org.uk/magazine/recorddc4c.html?id=20339"
                        >http://poetrymagazines.org.uk/magazine/recorddc4c.html?id=20339</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ferris2011" label="Ferris 2011">Ferris, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Catskill Eagle</title>. <title rend="italic">14by14</title>, August 23,
                    2011, <ref
                        target="http://www.14by14.com/Sonnets/August2011/TheCatskillEagle.html"
                        >http://www.14by14.com/Sonnets/August2011/TheCatskillEagle.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldman2012" label="Goldman 2012">Goldman, C. <title rend="quotes"
                        >This is your brain on Jane Austen, and Stanford researchers are taking
                        notes</title>. <title rend="italic">Stanford News</title>, September 7,
                    2012, <ref
                        target="https://news.stanford.edu/news/2012/september/austen-reading-fmri-090712.html"
                        >https://news.stanford.edu/news/2012/september/austen-reading-fmri-090712.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harrison1996" label="Harrison 1996">Harrison, S., and P. Dourish.
                        <title rend="quotes">Re-place-ing space: the roles of place and space in
                        collaborative systems</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 1996
                        ACM conference on Computer supported cooperative work - CSCW ’96</title>.
                    Boston: ACM Press, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayles2012" label="Hayles
                2012">Hayles, K. <title
                        rend="italic">How we think: digital media and contemporary
                        technogenesis</title>. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jolly2017" label="Jolly 2017">Jolly, J. <title rend="quotes">A guide
                        to all those weird words your teen uses</title>.<title rend="italic">USA
                        Today</title>, March 3, 2017, <ref
                        target="https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/columnist/2017/03/03/guide-all-those-weird-words-you
                    r-teen-uses/98688930/"
                        >https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/columnist/2017/03/03/guide-all-those-weird-words-you
                        r-teen-uses/98688930/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kim2018" label="Kim 2018">Kim, S. J. <title rend="quotes">Sense and
                        Sensitivity: Cognitive Approaches to Race &amp; Ethnicity</title>. 2018
                    International Conference on Narrative, Montreal, Quebec, CA, April 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2016" label="Kirschenbaum 2016">Kirschenbaum, M. (2016,
                    May 12). <title rend="quotes">Am I a Digital Humanist? Confessions of a
                        Neoliberal Tool</title>. <title rend="italic">Medium</title>, May 12, 2016,
                        <ref
                        target="https://medium.com/@mkirschenbaum/am-i-a-digital-humanist-confessions-of-a-neoliberal-t
                    ool-1bc64caaa984"
                        >https://medium.com/@mkirschenbaum/am-i-a-digital-humanist-confessions-of-a-neoliberal-t
                        ool-1bc64caaa984</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2016" label="Klein 2016">Klein, L. F., and M.K. Gold. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities: The Expanded Field</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>. Edited by L.
                    F. Klein and M. K. Gold, University of Minnesota Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kramnick2018" label="Kramnick
                2018">Kramnick, J.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Interdisciplinary Delusion</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, October 11, 2018,
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.chronicle.com/article/The-Interdisciplinary-Delusion/244772"
                        >https://www.chronicle.com/article/The-Interdisciplinary-Delusion/244772</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lippincott2014" label="Lippincott 2014">Lippincott, J., Hemmasi, H.,
                    and Lewis, V. <title rend="quotes">Trends in Digital Scholarship
                    Centers</title>. <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE</title>, June 16, 2014, <ref
                        target="https://er.educause.edu/articles/2014/6/trends-in-digital-scholarship-centers"
                        >https://er.educause.edu/articles/2014/6/trends-in-digital-scholarship-centers</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lopez2015" label="Lopez 2015">Lopez, A., F. Rowland, and K.
                    Fitzpatrick. <title rend="quotes">On Scholarly Communication and the Digital
                        Humanities: An Interview with Kathleen Fitzpatrick</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">In The Library With The Lead Pipe</title>. 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lothian2013" label="Lothian 2013">Lothian, A., and A. Phillips. <title
                        rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities Mean Transformative Critique?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of E-Media Studies</title>, 3 (1).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mann2018" label="Mann 2018">Mann, J. L. <title rend="quotes">How
                        Technology Means: Texts, History, and Their Associated Technologies</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12 (3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mann2019" label="Mann 2019">Mann, R. <title rend="quotes">Paid to Do
                        but Not to Think: Reevaluating the Role of Graduate Student
                        Collaborators</title>. <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2019</title>. Edited by L. F. Klein and M. K. Gold, University of
                    Minnesota Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="margulis2017" label="Margulis 2017">Margulis, E. H. <title
                        rend="quotes">An Exploratory Study of Narrative Experiences of
                    Music</title>. Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal , 35 (2):
                    235–248.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mckay2019" label="McKay 2019">McKay, C. <title rend="quotes">Dawn In
                        New York</title>. <title rend="italic">Vox Populi</title>, <ref
                        target="https://voxpopulisphere.com/2017/04/27/claude-mckay-dawn-in-new-york/"
                        >https://voxpopulisphere.com/2017/04/27/claude-mckay-dawn-in-new-york/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pask2018" label="Pask 2018">Pask, K. <title rend="quotes">In the
                        Literature Lab</title>. <title rend="italic">Modern Language
                        Quarterly</title>, 79 (1): 1–24.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pawlicka2017" label="Pawlicka 2017">Pawlicka, U. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Data, Collaboration, Laboratory: Bringing Concepts from Science into
                        Humanities Practice</title>. <title rend="italic">English Studies</title>,
                    98 (5): 526–541.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perkel2016" label="Perkel 2016">Perkel, J. M. <title rend="quotes">How
                        scientists use Slack</title>. <title rend="italic">Nature</title>, 541
                    (7635): 123–124.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2010" label="Phillips 2010">Phillips, N. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Distraction as Liveliness of Mind: A Cognitive Approach to Characterization
                        in Jane Austen</title>. <title rend="italic">Theory of Mind and
                        Literature</title>. Edited by P. Leverage, H. Mancing, J. Marston William,
                    and R. Schweickert, Purdue University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2015" label="Phillips 2015">Phillips, N. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Literary Neuroscience and History of Mind: An Interdisciplinary fMRI Study
                        of Attention and Jane Austen</title>. <title rend="italic">The Oxford
                        Handbook of Cognitive Literary Studies</title>. Edited by L. Zunshine,
                    Oxford University Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2018" label="Phillips 2018">Phillips, N., S. Antonucci, L.
                    Grasser, M. Meter, R. Narayan, K. Persenaire, K. Smith, S. Smith, and L.
                    Straley. <title rend="quotes">Patterns of Attention and Memory in Jane Austen:
                        Literary Neuroscience, Intellectual History, and the Importance of
                        Individual Difference</title>.<title rend="italic">Jane Austen and sciences
                        of the mind</title>. Edited by B. Lau, London: Routledge, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pormann2015" label="Pormann 2015">Pormann, P. E. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Interdisciplinarity: Inside Manchester’s <q>arts lab</q></title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Nature</title>, 525: 318–319.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                        the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanitie</title>”. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9 (2).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruiz2017" label="Ruiz 2017">Ruiz, S., M. Areguin, E. Estrada, J.
                    Jimenez, D. Lopez, K. Sanchez, and J. Valenzuela. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Radicalizing the Digital Humanities: Reimagining Environmental Justice
                        Research and Teaching</title>. <title rend="italic">Radical Teacher</title>,
                    109 (1): 29–37.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="singh2016" label="Singh 2016">Singh, A. <title rend="quotes">In
                        Defense of Digital Tools (by a Non-Tool)</title>. Amardeep Singh (blog), May
                    2, 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.electrostani.com/2016/05/in-defense-of-digital-tools-by-non-tool.html"
                        >http://www.electrostani.com/2016/05/in-defense-of-digital-tools-by-non-tool.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="starr2007" label="Starr 2007">Starr, G. G. <title rend="quotes">Poetic
                        Subjects and Grecian Urns: Close Reading and the Tools of Cognitive
                        Science</title>. <title rend="italic">Modern Philology</title>, 105 (1):
                    48–61.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="starr2010" label="Starr 2010">Starr, G. G. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Multisensory Imagery</title>. <title rend="italic">Introduction to
                        Cognitive Cultural Studies</title>. Edited by L. Zunshine, John Hopkins
                    University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thompson2012" label="Thompson 2012">Thompson, H., and S. Vedantam.
                        <title rend="quotes">A Lively Mind: Your Brain on Jane Austen</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">NPR</title>, October 9, 2012, <ref
                        target="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2012/10/09/162401053/a-lively-mind-your-brain-o
                        n-jane-austen"
                        >https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2012/10/09/162401053/a-lively-mind-your-brain-o
                        n-jane-austen</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wythoff2018" label="Wythoff 2018">Wythoff, G. <title rend="quotes">On
                        Method in the Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Configurations</title>, 26 (3): 289–295.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
