<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conference Review: <title rend="italic">Reading Digital Literature</title> at Brown
   University, October 4-7, 2007.</title>
            <author>Patricia Tomaszek</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Patricia <dhq:family>Tomaszek</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Siegen University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>tomaszek at fk615.uni-siegen.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Patricia Tomaszek researches digital literature at the Cultural Studies Research Centre
     <title rend="quotes">Media Upheavals</title> based in Siegen, Germany. Within a project group, Patricia is analyzing the
     ongoing changes of literary communication and aesthetics in programmable and networked media.
     She is also a Research Assistant for the Archive-it Project the Electronic Literature
     Organization maintains in collaboration with the Library Of Congress. In autumn 2008, she will
     become a Phd Candidate at the Department <title rend="quotes">Literature, Art, New Media and Technologies</title> at the
     University of Siegen. She earned her Bachelor of Arts from Siegen University in 2005, studied
     abroad at Brown University in Spring 2007, and is currently completing her M.A. thesis on
     Teaching Digital Literature.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000018</idno>
            <idno type="volume">002</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2008-06-21">21 June 2008</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace" rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2008-04-21" who="Flanders"> Encoded document </change>
         <change when="2008-04-24" who="Ashwini"> Added date, id, issue, vol attributes to root element,
     revised encoding of the change element dated 2008-04-21, removed "#" from target attribute of
     ref element, encoded external links as xref in the text and listBibl, removed top xsl
     declaration </change>
         <change when="2008-06-14" who="jf">Added final metadata, bio and abstract, publication statement</change>
         <change when="2008-06-16" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added details to
     publicationStmt, changed xref to ref for validation with new schema, added "#" to target
     attribute of internal ref</change>
         <change when="2008-06-20" who="jf">Changed email address.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This is a review of the conference, <title rend="italic">Reading Digital Literature</title> at Brown University,
               organized by Roberto Simanowski (Brown University and <title rend="italic">Dichtung
                  Digital</title>) October 4-7, 2007.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Close reading literature that is produced within programmable media implies more than
   close reading.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Close Reading in the Realm of Static and Dynamic Texts</head>
            <p>Review of <title rend="italic">Reading Digital Literature</title> at Brown University,
    organized by Roberto Simanowski (Brown University and <title rend="italic">Dichtung
    Digital</title>) October 4-7, 2007.</p>
            <p> One often approaches paper-based texts as unified, stable with little to no self-generative
    properties. Such texts are objects and characterized by a linear structure, which can be traced
    to a single author. We think of texts that mirror meaning through the stylistic and rhetorical
    devices as well as through all nuances and connotations of language its author uses. We pay
    attention to the vocabulary, construction, grammar, imagery and symbolism the author applies to his
    text, and we carefully read through these texts with the aim of noting all the striking features
    that the text manifests, noting also relationships of textual elements that point at things
    outside of the text. We do this with a physical marker, underlining significant text passages
    and annotating comments <emph>on</emph> the text, namely <emph>on</emph> the page the text is
    written (and therefore tangible). By following an author’s reasoning inductively we conduct
    observations and interpretations which we want to prove in the text, and we can do so by
    pointing directly to the relevant passage. In short, before considering other analytical
    possibilities, we start a close reading by taking into account the stylistic, linguistic,
    semantic, structural and cultural properties of a text.</p>
            <p> What can we refer to in texts that are produced within programmable media that do not
    incorporate a narrated unified property, texts that move and morph, that change by mouse-over or
    are altered randomly by the computer-program itself? How can we conduct a close reading of
    literature that is displayed on intangible screens such as installations, or literature that
    isn’t even symbolized by visible alphabetical characters and that merges different media
    seamlessly? For authors like Daniel Howe, digital literature is meant to augment the
     <q>writing process</q> via digital/procedural processes;<note>This is a comment taken
     from the conference booklet. Roberto Simanowski asked each participant to submit statements to
     the following questions: This aspect of digital literature excites me most; This aspect of
     digital literature bothers me most; My favorite work of digital literature; My favorite work of
     non-digital art. The statements mirror manifold insights and can be read here: <ref target="http://www.interfictions.org/readingdigitalliterature">http://www.interfictions.org/readingdigitalliterature</ref>.</note> for the reader this
    augmentation renders almost palpable the need for new reading strategies. New reading strategies
    require a broadening of the close reading concept that applies to traditional texts. </p>
            <p> Close reading literature that is produced within programmable media implies more than close
    reading. It means to look beyond the surface, beyond the visible written word, it means to
    examine the complex production processes that operate within a work of digital literature
    accompanied, for example, by animated or machine-generated random words that alter
    signification. And since writing itself is technology, the writing technology (software,
    programming) of digital texts needs to be examined; that is, how the code affects a piece of
    digital literature. The code that underlies a work of digital literature is meaning-making and
    therefore not to be underestimated in the critical analysis that goes along with a close
    scholarly reading of digital literature. Tools of literary criticism need to be reconfigured
    towards an elaborated interdisciplinary perspective emphazising media studies and evaluation of
    programming effects in digital literature.<note>See also <ref target="#peterson2006">Peterson
      2006</ref>.</note> Stating this isn’t meant to transform the critic into a critical software
    engineer; I do think, however, that a critic who is writing an elaborated critique of a digital
    work should bring to bear at least simple <q>code grammar</q> knowledge <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1995">and be acquainted with some of the structures and strategies that underlie
     software engineering in any programming language</quote>
                  <ptr target="#murray1995"/>
               </cit>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Reading Digital Literature</head>
            <p> Aiming at bringing ten scholars and practitioners together to undertake close readings of
    digital literature in order to <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">advance the field of digital literature and
     digital humanities</quote>, to entail the <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">understanding of the language of
     digital media</quote> and to develop <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">reading competence</quote> in the
    realm of digital literature, media and art, Roberto Simanowski’s opening words to the conference
     <title rend="italic">Reading Digital Literature</title> might still echo in participants’
    minds, reminding them that <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">[T]his is a special moment in the history of
            digital literature</quote><ptr target="#simanowski2007"/></cit>. N. Katherine Hayles amplified Simanowski's sentiment by calling on
    conference participants <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">to move away from highly generalized accounts into
     detailed and specific readings that account, in media-specific ways, for the practices,
     effects, and interpretations of important works</quote> (quoted in <ptr target="#simanowski2007"/>). </p>
            <p> Simanowski and Hayles’s remarks call to mind earlier discussions between scholars and
    practitioners of digital art and literature who already tried to draw our attention to the
    development of a new digital literacy. In 2002, for example, the Electronic Literature
    Organization’s symposium on the <title rend="italic">State of the Arts</title> discussed
     <q>Multimedia Criticism</q>, exploring the role of multimedia techniques in critical
    writing. Nevertheless, the event this October at Brown University for the first time focused on
    close readings of digital literature presented within a conference format that permitted time
    for immediate discussions and follow-ups. Simanowski had a useful approach: each of the ten
    presentations was followed by a comment provided by another presenter. Through this
    intersection, two perspectives on the same topic were presented. Additionally, the commentary
    served as an opener for each discussion, and participants, presenters and conference guests
    alike engaged in numerous constructive dialogues, exchanging views and arguments in the
    moderated debates that were mostly too short in time (as frequently happens at conferences). </p>
            <p>The three-day conference that opened at Brown’s List Arts Center, exhibiting three
    installations of digital literature (Daniel Howe’s <title rend="italic">Text Curtain</title>,
    Aya Karpinska’s <title rend="italic">For This We Pray</title> and John Cayley’s
     <title>Imposition</title>), had much to offer and mirrored Simanowski’s aim of bringing together
    practitioners and artists shifting between co-events like public screenings, digital writing
    performances of Brown-affiliated authors and the conference itself. The conference ended with a
     <q>brainstorming lunch</q> after a lively discussion among scholars of the
    humanities departments and experts from the electronic writing programs who exchanged ideas on
    how meaning is being generated in works of digital literature by discussing aesthetic effects
    the artist produces with code. </p>
            <p>The conference papers were presented by widely-known researchers, some among them recognized
    for their pioneering studies in the field of digital literature: Chris Funkhouser, Peter
    Gendolla, N. Katherine Hayles, Fotis Jannidis, Rita Raley, Francisco Ricardo, Jörgen Schäfer,
    Thomas Swiss, Karin Wenz and Mark Tribe. Their papers presented close readings of works that
    included the interactive drama Michael Mateas’ and Andrew Stern’s <title rend="italic">Façade</title>, the computer game <title rend="italic">S.T.A.L.K.E.R</title>, <title rend="italic">Slippingglimpse</title> by Stephanie Strickland and Cynthia Jaramillo, the
    installations <title rend="italic">Text Rain</title> (Camille Utterback, Romy Achituv), and
     <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title> (Mark Hansen, Ben Rubin), Thomas Swiss’ three
    versions of his collaborative work <title rend="italic">Blind Side of a Secret</title>, the
    Hypertext <title rend="italic">The Demon Machine</title> (Esther Hunziker, Felix Zbinden), and
    presentations on Poetry Machines like Christopher Strachey's <title rend="italic">Love Letter
     Generator</title> and <title rend="italic">Syntext</title> that refers to the poetry of Text
    Generators. The conference explored a wide range of works of digital literature that were for
    the first time presented and discussed with a close reading. </p>
            <p>Posing the difficult questions over the appropriate reading methods through which digital
    literature should be approached, and asking how to read a digital sign, Simanowski initiated the
    discussion on how to develop a digital literacy that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">develops by exploring
     the semiotics of the technical effects in digital media</quote>
                  <ptr target="#simanowski2007"/>
               </cit>. To my mind, the question of <emph>how</emph> to read digital
    literature forces scholars not only to develop a reading competence for advancing the
    understanding of works but also to evolve substantial and illustrative techniques for an
    adequate criticism in the field of <q>literary digital studies</q>. Taking into
    account what the conference was aiming for, this article addresses problems of close reading
     <emph>digital</emph> literature and reviews an exemplary method of a close reading that Rita
    Raley presented, <q>reading</q>
               <title rend="italic">List(en)ing Post</title>. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Close Reading Techniques</head>
            <p> A good point of departure is to discuss the meaning of <q>close reading</q> in its
    conventional sense when applied to traditional literature.<note>Interesting insights into what
      <q>close reading</q> might mean are given by Jan van Looy and Jan Baetens in their
     introduction to <title rend="quotes">Close Reading New Media: Analyzing Electronic
     Literature</title>, discussing the relationship of <q>close</q> and
      <q>reading</q>
                  <ptr target="#baetens2003"/>.</note> This procedure is justified
    because we are facing a new and rather young form of literature that has not yet developed its
    own theory of reading. Today we find ourselves faced with manipulated texts that reorder the
    structure of reading through the use of programmable media. Digital literature that is
    distributed by computerized media is in need of a reading theory that takes into account the
    changes the digital environment causes with all its consequences, presenting: <quote rend="inline" source="#simanowski2007">eventilized texts</quote> (Hayles, quoted in <ptr target="#simanowski2007"/>), kinetic texts, algorithmic interpolations, machine-based randomly
    recombined and generated texts, plays with legibility, video and animated flash-poems,
    interactive narratives and games, hypertext and hyperfictions, writing in immersive virtual
    reality, and installations. These alter the readers’ reception and also transform aspects of
     <emph>literariness</emph> in the works, as well. It is not far-fetched to claim that we should
    move away from traditional literary studies that focus on static text, broadening our theories
    to encompass <q>digital literary studies</q> and preparing them to address literature
    that is born-digital. This claim, however, does not mean that we should neglect literary studies
    which will always serve as a starting point of any discussion of digital literature — for its
    theories will always serve as a touchstone for further critical studies — but that we should
    allow our bearings to adjust to the medium at hand.<note>Simanowski proposes a shift from
     hermeneutics of linguistic signs to a hermeneutic of intermedial, interactive, and processing
     signs, suggesting to undertake the discussion on digital literature by combining new and old
     criteria of literary theory.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head> Considering Reading Strategies </head>
            <p> The conference <title rend="italic">Reading Digital Literature</title> that brought together
    scholars from different scientific fields also explored diverse reading strategies and
    perspectives that enriched the possible approaches of reading digital literature. What will
    follow before I present a <q>close reading review</q> of Rita Raley’s presentation on
     <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title> is a summary of the approaches that were undertaken
    by the presenters that aims to find common ground and focuses on the main reading methods used. </p>
            <p>There is a diversity of approaches when undertaking a close reading. Jörgen Schäfer drew out
    the Aristotelian theory of drama that underlies the interactive drama <title rend="italic">Façade</title>, exploring the hybridization of the literary genre from the perspective of
    literary and performance studies. Another course of studies followed Fotis Jannidis invoked
    elements of pop culture when analyzing the computer game <title rend="italic">S.T.A.L.K.E.R</title> in relation to the paradigms of the ego-shooter genre. He contributed a
    hermeneutics of this art. Art itself was questioned. Mark Tribe discussed the Flash work of
    Young-Hae Chang <title rend="italic">Heavy Industries</title> one of whose recent works, <title rend="italic">The Art of Sleep</title>, draws out various tendencies in digital art and the
    contemporary art world generally, and takes on central issues concerning the futility of art and
    the difficulty of defining it. Raley commented on Tribe’s presentation, pointing out that taking
    the <soCalled>art question</soCalled> seriously is <soCalled>always
    lethal</soCalled>. She read Tribe’s presentation as highlighting the absence of signature aspects
    of Chang’s work, wondering if this were <q>partly to do with limitations of
     Flash (kinetic text), which introduces a tension between contemplation and distraction</q>.
    Actually, Tribe himself drew our attention to the software that Young-Hae Chang <title rend="italic">Heavy Industries</title> used: Flash. He explained how this software could be
    used creatively but without any reference to what happens to the reader or the viewer of Chang’s
     <title rend="italic">Bust Down the Doors!</title> and <title rend="italic">The Art of
    Sleep</title>. </p>
            <p> The question of what happens to the reader when evaluating the repercussions on her of the
    literary work was barely acknowledged in the close readings of the presenters. Peter Gendolla
    who reminded us of the traditional functions that literature used to provide by examining
    Christopher Strachey's <title rend="italic">Love Letter Generator</title>, contrasting it with
    traditional poetry, and thereby attempting to ascertain whether in this way it is possible
    either to isolate or to retrieve the literary process. </p>
            <p> Literariness is a crucial point to take into account in connection with generated literature.
    Is any literariness remarkable? Chris Funkhouser presented poetry outcomes from <title rend="italic">Syntext</title>, a collection of fifteen computer programs from the 70s, 80s, and
    90s that automatically generate various styles of poetry in DOS. His method and procedure are
    worth noting since he reported on the inner workings of the machine as well as on the outcomes,
    analyzing the generated poetry similarly to the methods applied to close readings in traditional
    literature by commenting on, for example, syntax and structure. Thus, this again was an approach
    that resulted in the confrontation of both the literary- and the machine-generated literature. </p>
            <p> Integrating this perspective with the view on the coding and programming possibilities was a
    skilled approach that applied to Hayles’s call to process <q>media-specific</q> readings. Karin Wenz’s analysis of the hypertextual work, <title rend="italic">The demon machine or 80 ways to face a demon</title>, offered a close reading of
    the interface and its multi-medial dimensions. Wenz's close reading approach was <soCalled>media-specific</soCalled>, but her analysis lacked focus on the literariness that is
    applied to the piece (even though there are more videos and images than text implemented in the
    hypertext). The presentation was perhaps overly centered on the interface following both a
    highly descriptive and detailed explanation of the work’s structure, but it was not a close
    reading of the literature or narrative itself. Another close reading that scratched the surface
    of what <q>close reading</q> might be was Thomas Swiss’s <q>personal
    alphabet</q>. Swiss claimed that he <q>shies away</q> from methods.
    Instead, he wrote in the manner of a piece of digital literature itself: with surprising
    surrealistic turns and remarks on Roland Barthes, Jonathan Culler and responses to proper
    questions of criticism or critique, elaborating a responsive nonlinear paper. </p>
            <p> What was once again missing from this? Attention to the literary work that Swiss was
    addressing, namely a poem that had been transposed into three versions of digital literature.
    What was the poem about?! I close this general overview with N. Katherine Hayles’ and Francisco
    Ricardo’s close reading methods and then give a <q>close reading review</q> of Rita
    Raley’s <title rend="italic">List(en)ing Post</title> presentation. </p>
            <p> Hayles’s close reading was rich in its applied methods, both reading and contextualizing the
    form, content and structure of Strickland and Lawson Jaramillo’s <title rend="italic">Slippingglimpse</title>, and bringing these elements into relation with each other by
    approaching the reading along <q>three major axes of interpretation</q>.
    Hayles offers a way to read this work, taking into account the <q>inner
     workings</q> and the algorithms of the piece, she is spelling out how the machine
     <q>reads</q> the text, the poem that underlies the digital artwork that includes
    video, images and a kinetic text. By detailed explanations of how the intended programming
    interplays with the meaning, Hayles gives a very close reading of the work that serves as an
    example <q>what reading might mean in digital media</q>. </p>
            <p> Similarly concerned with the connection between text, and visual patterns, Ricardo’s
    presentation of the installation <title rend="italic">Text Rain</title> refers to <q>literature as a genre of text wrapped in a mantle of imagery</q>. Here, he
    offers a reading of the <q>discursive spaces</q> of the <q>transmodal</q> work <title rend="italic">Text Rain</title> by drawing a
    distinction over the <q>de-modalization</q> that characterizes <q>pure literature</q> and framing the relation of imagery and literature within
    historic, ontological and philosophical perspectives that mirror the longstanding <q>tension in relating word to image within the literary experience</q>. Thus,
    his close reading manifests through drawing attention to the larger <q>
                  <foreign>écriture</foreign>
               </q> of the works’ literary space. And here, like Swiss and Hayles, he considers aims that
    criticism might and might not bear, approaching the reading of the piece in Sontag’s manner,
    against interpretation. </p>
            <p>Swiss, Hayles and Ricardo exhibit a common ground in methodological approaches: they refer
    back to traditional generic concepts and confront traditional literature with the outcomes of
    the digital (Schäfer, Gendolla, Funkhouser, Raley). Others frame a work within another realm of
    digital art and culture (Jannidis, Wenz, Tribe, Raley). Swiss, Hayles and Ricardo also discuss
    the methodology of a close reading. Additionally, some of the close readings referred to the
    code and algorithm that underlies a work (Funkhouser, Tribe, Raley, Hayles) which is worth
    noting since the code is, in my view, a crucial instrument of meaning making in digital
    literature. Thus, I have chosen Rita Raley’ close reading presentation on <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title>. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Close Reading Raley’s <title rend="italic">List(en)ing Post</title>
            </head>
            <p> It is remarkable that Rita Raley’s presentation at the conference is simply titled with the
    work it refers to: <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title>. And this and nothing else is
    what Raley deals with, offering a close and specific reading of the installation by commenting
    on aesthetic aspects. Listening Post’s literary value, by discussing form, structure and content
    and last but not least by drawing analogies to the realm of digital culture. Even though Raley
    doesn’t present specific insights to the tools of software that were used (written with/in Perl,
    using C, Max/MSP, C++, sh/tcsh, R) she brings up general information on the <q>inner
     workings</q> of the machines that control the output by describing the effects of the
    installation’s algorithm. The analytical insights that she did bring to bear were, however,
    ample, and necessary for the better understanding what <title rend="italic">Listening
    Post</title> is and what happens while the installation is processing. Here, it is probably not
    essential to know more about the specific programming code. In <title rend="italic">Listening
     Post</title> the installation itself and its output bear the meaning — arguably, more so than the
    code. What happens visibly and aurally is essential. The software used and its programming
    serve, in this case, as a means to underpin the meanings Hansen and Rubin intended to generate,
    that is to <title rend="italic">capture the moments of human connection</title>
               <ptr target="#reas2007"/>.<note>Even though it might be clear that another program
     construction/performance could make a difference when keeping the developments of ideas, its
     rejections and realizations in mind: Hansen and Rubin give interesting insights into the
     project’s <q>making of</q> in an interview with Casey Reas and Ben Fry <ptr target="#reas2007"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p> There is a distinction in analysing the interplay of content-intention, form and structure.
    Other works of digital literature might project a meaning into a specific code performance; in
     <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title> it seems like the tools are, as mentioned, aids in
    performing a meaning that does not lie in the code itself. Raley is successful in presenting the
    artist’s transferred meaning, outlining the project’s significance that is derived amongst other
    instances from <q>its virtuoso technique</q> and its literary value that
     <q>allows us to encounter a social totality in all of its complexity
    (…)</q>. Her close reading technique is detailed but differs (of course) from reading
    techniques that refer to print-based texts. However, she proceeds conscientiously, inductively,
    reporting on the seven cycles the installation traverses, describing the applying arrangements
    that refer to visual, aural and musical levels. Raley reflects on the cycles meanings, their
    effects, keeping in mind the <soCalled>viewer</soCalled>, not the <soCalled>reader</soCalled>, who experiences textual upheavals, a-semantics, illegibility, words that are
    sounded out by the Listening Post’s text-to-speech engine that treats abbreviations and acronyms
    as words that <q>one has to move in to isolate a single display to
    read</q>. The experiences Raley evokes from the installation allow her to allude to other
    works of visual and literary art (indicating Gibson’s cyberspace, Pynchon’s circuit card and the
    circuitry in the film 13th Floor, Mark Lombardi and Chris Jordan, as well as media artists that
    deal with surveillance). Raley takes note of another aspect of <title rend="italic">Listening
     Post</title>: the organization of information on PowerPoint slides, lists that allude to <q>the interplay between the individual and the cumulative whole</q>. She points
    out that <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title> brings such lists into some form of
    relation and synthesis with the “long-term tradition of literary lists” that are used to produce
    aesthetic effects. </p>
            <p> On the whole, Raley is successful in her close reading thanks to the interdisciplinary
    approach she has chosen, moving back and forth between related themes, outlining observations
    made in the realm of digital culture and always returning to the reading of the work itself:
     <title rend="italic">Listening Post</title>. </p>
            <p> What one might derive from the whole conference is that there is still a need for an
    elaborated methodology of close reading. The approaches were as different as the works of
    digital literature that were discussed, even though it is possible to categorize them all in a
    summary way. The central problem of theorizing the close reading of digital literature is the
    diversity of digital literature. Each work uses distinct software environments, different
    multi-medial devices, programming methods, and algorithmic strategies, as well as distinct
    varieties of interplay with text. This makes it difficult to maintain <emph>the</emph> theory
    since it would have to combine disciplinary perspectives which should apply to the heterogeneity
    of a work. Criticism of digital literature will always be diverse because the object of its
    focus is, as we have argued, inherently diverse. Having said this, there are three themes that
    should remain consistent in a critical examination: The question of what is literary; a focus on
    its underlying code that affects digital literature; and Hayles's proposed <soCalled>media-specific</soCalled> analysis. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baetens2003" label="Baetens 2003" key="baetens2003">
               <author>Baetens, J.</author> and <author>van Looy, J.</author>
               <title rend="italic">Close Reading New Media: Analyzing Electronic Literature</title>.
    <pubPlace>Leuven</pubPlace>: <publisher>Leuven University Press</publisher>, <date>2003</date>.
    <ref target="http://www.maerlant.be/closereadingnewmedia/introduction.htm">http://www.maerlant.be/closereadingnewmedia/introduction.htm</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murray1995" label="Murray 1995" key="murray1995">
   
               <author>Murray, J. H.</author>
               <title rend="quotes">The Pedagogy of Cyberfiction: Teaching a Course on Reading and Writing
    Interactive Narrative</title>. In <editor>Barrett, E.</editor> and <editor>M. Redmond</editor>
   (eds), <title rend="italic">Contextual Media: Multimedia and Interpretation</title>.
    <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</publisher>,
    <date>1995</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="peterson2006" label="Peterson 2006" key="peterson2006">
   
               <author>Peterson, T.</author>
               <title rend="quotes">New Media Poetry and Poetics. From Concrete to Codework: Praxis in Networked
    and Programmable Media</title>. In <title rend="quotes">New Media Poetry and Poetics</title>
   Special Issue, <title rend="italic">Leonardo Electronic Almanac</title>, Vol. 14, no.
   5-6, <date>2006</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reas2007" label="Reas 2007" key="reas2007">
   
               <author>Reas, C.</author> and <author>Fry, B.</author>
               <title rend="italic">Processing: A Programming Handbook for Visual Designers and Artists</title>.
    <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</publisher>,
    <date>2007</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="simanowski2007" label="Simanowski 2007" key="simanowski2007">
   
               <author>Simanowski, R.</author> Opening Words. <title rend="italic">Reading Digital
   Literature</title> Conference. <pubPlace>Providence, Rhode Island</pubPlace>. <date>4-7 October
    2007</date>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>