<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">What can the digital humanities learn from feminist game
                    studies?</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Elizabeth <dhq:family>Losh</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of California, San Diego</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>lizlosh@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Elizabeth Losh is the author of <title rend="italic">Virtualpolitik: An
                                Electronic History of Government Media-Making in a Time of War,
                                Scandal, Disaster, Miscommunication, and Mistakes</title> (MIT
                            Press, 2009) and <title rend="italic">The War on Learning: Gaining
                                Ground in the Digital University</title> (MIT Press, 2014). She is
                            the co-author of the comic book textbook <title rend="italic"
                                >Understanding Rhetoric: A Graphic Guide to Writing</title>
                            (Bedford/St. Martin's, 2013) with Jonathan Alexander. She is currently
                            working on a new monograph, tentatively entitled <title rend="italic"
                                >Obama Online: Technology, Masculinity, and Democracy</title>.</p>
                        <p> She writes about gender and technology, the digital humanities, distance
                            learning, connected learning, media literacy, and the rhetoric
                            surrounding regulatory attempts to limit everyday digital practices.</p>
                        <p> She has written a number of frequently cited essays about communities
                            that produce, consume, and circulate online video, videogames, digital
                            photographs, text postings, and programming code. The diverse range of
                            subject matter analyzed in her scholarship has included coming out
                            videos on YouTube, videogame fan films created by immigrants, combat
                            footage from soldiers in Iraq shot on mobile devices, video evidence
                            created for social media sites by protesters on the Mavi Marmara, remix
                            videos from the Arab Spring, and the use of Twitter and Facebook by
                            Indian activists working for women’s rights after the Delhi rape case.
                            Much of this body of work concerns the legitimation of political
                            institutions through visual evidence, representations of war and
                            violence in global news, and discourses about human rights. This work
                            has appeared in edited collections from MIT Press, Routledge, University
                            of Chicago, Minnesota, Oxford, Continuum, and many other presses.</p>
                        <p> She is Director of the Culture, Art, and Technology program at Sixth
                            College at U.C. San Diego, where she teaches courses on digital rhetoric
                            and new media. She is also a blogger for Digital Media and Learning
                            Central, and a Steering Committee member of HASTAC and FemTechNet. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000200</idno>
                <idno type="volume">009</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2015-09-02">2 September 2015</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>game studies</item>
                        <item>feminism</item>
                        <item>instrumentalism</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="EH" when="2015-02-05">Encoded article</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>When game studies became an area for scholarly inquiry in the academy, feminist
                    game studies soon followed. The first generation of feminist theory in game
                    studies built on the work of Sherry Turkle, Brenda Laurel, and Janet Murray,
                    although some might argue that the legacy of challenging gender norms in game
                    studies goes back even earlier. Now feminist game scholars organize
                    international conferences, edit journals and scholarly collections, and shape
                    trends in the profession, much as their counterparts in the digital humanities
                    attempt to do, but critics in feminist game studies have been able to take
                    advantage of what is seen as a relatively long trajectory of feminist
                    theoretical inquiry and field development. Articulating a need for a feminist
                    corrective in the digital humanities has come at a much slower pace, perhaps
                    because the instrumentalism of a <soCalled>tool</soCalled> seems much less
                    blatantly anti-feminist than the instrumentalism of a gun. Furthermore, calls to
                    action from more radicalized forms of feminist approaches to science and
                    technology studies have been noticeably absent in the literature around digital
                    information retrieval in the humanities. This issue of <title rend="italic"
                        >DHQ</title> indicates that a sea change may finally be taking place. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p> Feminist game studies within the digital humanities </p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>When game studies became an area for scholarly inquiry in the academy, feminist game
                studies soon followed. After all, when so many videogames so obviously featured
                ejaculatory shooting, sexual conquest, objectified femininity, alienated labor,
                separation of the domestic and commercial spheres, physical domination, zero-sum
                negotiations, and waging mass warfare, the need for feminist responses to the
                aggression and opportunism represented in computer games might have seemed
                self-evident. The first generation of feminist theory in game studies built on the
                work of Sherry Turkle, Brenda Laurel, and Janet Murray, although some might argue
                that the legacy of challenging gender norms in game studies goes back at least to
                the countercultural subversion of the new games movement in the sixties and
                seventies or the work of the Situationists. Perhaps the correspondence between Ada
                Lovelace and Charles Babbage about his mechanized tic-tac-toe game may point to an
                even long history of feminist engagement in algorithmic game culture. Now feminist
                game scholars organize international conferences, edit journals and scholarly
                collections, and shape trends in the profession, much as their counterparts in the
                digital humanities attempt to do, but critics in feminist game studies have been
                able to take advantage of what is seen as a relatively long trajectory of feminist
                theoretical inquiry and field development. </p>
            <p>Articulating a need for a feminist corrective in the digital humanities has come at a
                much slower pace, perhaps because the instrumentalism of a <soCalled>tool</soCalled>
                seems much less blatantly anti-feminist than the instrumentalism of a gun.
                Furthermore, calls to action from more radicalized forms of feminist approaches to
                science and technology studies, epitomized by decades of work spanning from Donna
                Haraway to Kavita Philip, has been noticeably absent in the literature around
                digital information retrieval in the humanities. Tara McPherson has argued that the
                early humanities computing projects were actually characterized by reactionary
                tendencies to shun feminism, queer theory, and multiculturalism in the name of
                preserving great books and memorializing canonical authors in a neutral,
                technocratic archive divorced from the increasingly politicized campuses of the free
                speech era and the subsequent culture wars. Despite the fact that librarians and
                archivists have often been allies of the American cultural left, many early digital
                humanities initiatives seemed to aspire to be apolitical in their orientation. It
                could be argued that the digital humanities was also surprisingly slow to consider
                the implications of what Judy Wajcman calls <soCalled>TechnoFeminism</soCalled> by
                interrogating the masculinist ideologies of technology itself. </p>
            <p>This issue of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> indicates that a sea change may
                finally be taking place. Recent high-profile blog posts by Bethany Nowviskie about
                gendered language at the heart of the NEH’s <title rend="quotes">Digging into Data
                    Challenge</title> and from Miriam Posner about brogrammer code culture that
                privileges literacies that exclude women have finally catalyzed more serious
                discussions about the possibilities of creating a field of feminist digital
                humanities. Amy Earhart and Julia Flanders remind the DH community that collections
                and archives from nascent women’s studies departments often provided impetus for
                many early digital humanities projects. Rising scholars in the #transformDH movement
                are also bringing queer theory, transgender perspectives, and posthumanism into
                public discussions about inclusion and exclusion in DH.</p>
            <p>But where would the field of Feminist DH locate its core values? How can it be more
                than simply anti-masculinist in its orientation? Criticizing the obvious fetishizing
                of tools, code, competition, and <q>massive</q> or <q>big</q> data projects is one
                thing. Doing field-building work is another. Furthermore, how would feminist DH be
                specifically feminist in its theoretical grounding rather than merely oriented
                toward improving access and equity for women in DH? What does it mean to rethink
                rule-based systems and user agency from a feminist perspective and then apply the
                worldview of feminist game studies to the work of the digital humanities? According
                to Carolyn Guertin, subjectivity under feminism <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#guertin2009">becomes a process and a performance that is constantly in
                    a state of redefining its own complexity according to a network of power
                    formations</quote> (2009). What would it mean to move from a paradigm of tool
                development to a paradigm of process and performance in which the network of power
                formations moves from ground to figure? </p>
            <p>Nina B. Huntemann defines feminist game studies as a field that focuses on <quote
                    rend="inline" source="#huntemann2012">how gender, and its intersections with
                    race, class, sexuality, etc., is produced, represented, consumed and practiced
                    in and through digital games</quote> (2012). Huntemann, like many feminist game
                scholars, is also interested in the genealogies of computer games, and their origins
                in a computational media history shaped by military training, surveillance
                technologies, and the exercise of force by the power of the state <ptr
                    target="#huntemann2010"/>. Feminist digital artists who deploy game
                technologies, as Anne-Marie Schleiner does in her <title rend="italic"
                    >Counterstrike</title> intervention <title rend="italic">Velvet-Strike</title>
                or Char Davies does by using 3D graphics with a head-mounted display in her
                immersive installations, may explicitly promote forms of user interaction that defy
                command-and-control tactics and subvert expectations that the user should obliterate
                obstacles and occupy territory. Although some scholars have pointed out how digital
                humanities projects borrow specific technologies of geospatial mapping developed for
                the user interface of flight simulators <ptr target="#presner2008"/>,
                knowledge-sharing between the military and the digital humanities often still takes
                place without comment. </p>
            <p>Feminist approaches to videogames and virtual worlds have included a range of
                approaches that explicitly borrow from feminist methodologies in ethnography,
                human-computer interaction, science and technology studies, media arts practice, and
                textual criticism. It is worth noting that many of these fields are now only
                beginning to be referenced in the scholarly literature of the digital humanities.
                Many current scholars of computer games and virtual worlds – such as Beth Coleman,
                Mary Flanagan, Tracy Fullerton, Celia Pearce, Emily Roxworthy, and Katie Salen –
                also identify as designers and bring their experiences as creative professionals
                with prototyping, workflow management, iteration, and user-testing to the field.
                Even if they don’t identify as designers, many in feminist game studies identify
                strongly as players or power users of videogames. For example, Mia Consalvo, Lisbeth
                Klastrup, Bonnie Nardi, Carol Stabile, T.L. Taylor, and Jill Walker Rettberg have
                pursued advancement within in-game reputation systems, and their scholarly ethos as
                game scholars seems to be enhanced by having progressed from apprenticeship to
                mastery in particular games, as evidenced by their achievements, hours logged, and
                the fame of their avatar names. </p>
            <p>Many debates in the digital humanities recall debates already rehearsed in game
                studies. For example, significant cohorts of digital designers, programmers, and
                architects must collaborate and compete with those who identify exclusively as
                critics and theorists within the research community. Questions about which group can
                speak with the most authority in public fora can be difficult to resolve,
                particularly when plainspoken discourse and highly technical skills prized by
                builders and makers are devalued by the academy. Much as DH purists have called for
                    <q>more hack, less yack</q> or lionized <soCalled>builders,</soCalled> designers
                of classic games are often the keynote speakers at game conferences and serve as
                celebrity attendees. However, it may be reasonable for digital humanities projects
                to also consider how certain power users intent on exploring collections for hours
                at a time can provide specialized input about system design, much as attention to
                    <soCalled>hardcore gamers</soCalled> in game studies may provide insights about
                the co-creation of knowledge.</p>
            <p>There are a number of useful insights to be gained in the digital humanities from
                observing how feminist game studies gained legitimacy in an environment devoted to
                machismo mastery and performance. Feminist game scholars have done important work on
                protocols, market forces, technoculture, datification, instrumentalism, opportunism,
                and online aggression, as well as on appropriation, domesticity, reciprocity,
                collective agency, community building, and empathy. They have also successfully
                built networks, collectives, and collaboratives. However, feminist game studies also
                benefited from the fact that during the past three decades feminist scholarship
                transformed both science and technology studies and film and television studies.
                Feminist scholars of literacy, programming, and cultural studies including Anne
                Balsamo, Wendy Chun, Radhika Gajjala, N. Katherine Hayles, and Lisa Nakamura used
                critical frameworks that reconfigured ideas about bodies, machines, affect, and
                labor and applied analytic methods formerly reserved for art and literary texts to
                technological discourses, such as those around reproductive medicine or computer
                science. At the same time, the contributions of scholars such as Mary Anne Doane,
                Anne Friedberg, Linda Williams, Lisa Parks, Lisa Cartwright, and Teresa de Lauretis
                exerted a major influence on the field of media studies by shifting the focus of
                critical practice from text and discourse to matters of the apparatus, technosocial
                environments, embodied experiences, and the interfaces and platforms of
                mediation.</p>
            <p>Obviously, to take game studies seriously in the digital humanities presents a number
                of disciplinary, methodological, and practical problems. Game studies scholars often
                situate themselves as participant-observers rather than disinterested critics or
                archivists and reject poses of depersonalized neutrality. Game interfaces are
                characterized by the intentional frustration of easy user access by the game’s
                designers. In contrast, interfaces for digital humanities projects – search engine
                portals, hyperlinked pages, timelines, maps, or visualizations are supposed to be
                unambiguously user-friendly. Players are expected to risk failure as they solve
                puzzles and explore dead ends, which is a key part of game play, rather than zip
                through transparent navigation into the assets of core databases. In fact, the
                pleasure of a game play experience can often be attributed to its lack of
                predictability, replicability, and even stability. Furthermore, the attitudes of
                gamers often focus on celebrating acts of individual hacking meant to gain personal
                advantage rather than creating universal standards through deliberative processes
                dictated by professional associations. Feminist games may prove to be doubly
                transgressive in design. For example, in <title rend="italic">The Path</title> by
                the Belgian game collective Tale of Tales, going directly to grandma’s house ends
                the game in failure immediately; you need to go into the woods, develop sexually,
                and risk danger among the wolves in order to have any hope of gaining knowledge of
                the game world.</p>
            <p>To position oneself as a feminist can also be difficult in the context of
                participating in civil discourse in digital culture. In the mid-nineties
                cyberfeminist critics promised that new forms of social relations constituted by
                user-generated content on distributed networks would reshape existing architectures
                that defined gendered power relations, but now many who study social network sites,
                computer games, and virtual worlds contend that it is difficult to mount resistance
                against a neoliberal agenda promoted by the very design of infrastructures and
                interfaces upon which our technologically mediated existence depends <ptr
                    target="#gajjala2012"/>. Furthermore, although identifying as a feminist critic
                can be an act of solidarity with like-minded others, lines of inquiry in game
                studies that challenge the dominant culture can also risk exposure to the rhetorical
                violence of anti-feminist online affinity groups, as Mia Consalvo points out: <quote
                    rend="block" source="#spurr2012">While I was writing this piece, for example, a
                    Canadian blogger created a game where one can punch and bruise the face of Anita
                    Sarkeesian, creator of the popular website <title rend="italic">Feminist
                        Frequency: Conversations with Pop Culture</title>
                    <ptr target="#spurr2012"/>. The game was in response to news of her Kickstarter
                    campaign, where she proposed investigating portrayals of women in videogames
                    over the past few decades. The game was only the latest in a string of attacks
                    on Sarkeesian for her proposed project: she also received death threats, had her
                    Wikipedia page defaced with pornographic imagery, and was repeatedly harassed on
                    the Kickstarter page and elsewhere.</quote></p>
            <p>Much as feminist bloggers have been victimized by Internet harassment for taking a
                stand against particular forms of aggressive online conduct accepted as normative,
                feminist game critics might sometimes find themselves targeted for challenging the
                hypermasculinity of existing user behavior. </p>
            <p>To understand the landscape of feminist game studies it may be helpful to look at the
                prototypical collaboration of Ludica, a group of four feminist game scholars (Janine
                Fron, Tracy Fullerton, Jacquelyn Ford Morie, and Celia Pearce) who took turns
                presenting their collectively authored papers at game conferences throughout the
                world. The group wrote a paper for the Digital Games Research Association that
                generated considerable controversy among that research community by calling
                attention to what they called <quote rend="inline" source="#fron2007">the hegemony
                    of play</quote> that defined the user population of computer games too narrowly
                and ignored large populations of supposed <soCalled>non-gamers</soCalled> who
                actively played online card games or participated in virtual worlds that focused on
                clothing or social interaction. In this call to action Ludica envisioned a
                three-pronged systematic critique of existing scholarship and design research around
                games that would encompass <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#fron2007">1) the production process and
                        environment for the creation of digital games; 2) the technologies of play,
                        including the evolution of games from folk traditions and cultural artifacts
                        to industrial products and intellectual property, and now to digital
                        products and virtual societies; and 3) the cultural positioning of games and
                            <q>gamers</q></quote>
                    <ptr target="#fron2007"/>
                </cit>. They noted biases of age and race as well as biases of gender in how games
                and gamers were counted and defined. </p>
            <p>What currently constitutes the <soCalled>big data</soCalled> digital humanities may
                be similarly charged with ignoring large contingents of archival practitioners by
                virtue of how their labor may be gendered and valued, especially given the long
                pre-digital history of low-status librarianship in schools and communities and the
                tendency for men to occupy managerial positions in more prestigious libraries <ptr
                    target="#golub2010"/>. Certainly, only the largest city libraries, such as the
                New York Public Library, are sufficiently capitalized and connected for
                participation in NEH-scale digital humanities research projects, while local
                librarians must focus on their service as infomediaries who help clients navigate
                the user-interfaces of computer databases and locate and interpret sources that meet
                their needs <ptr target="#ramirez2009"/>. Ironically, city and school libraries are
                also more likely to have the game and social media functions of their computer
                networks curtailed by government regulators intent on users only accessing
                high-status approved sites for purposes of legitimated research labor <ptr
                    target="#losh2012"/>. </p>
            <p>To think about the <q>small</q> data digital humanities for a moment, it might be
                useful to look at the function of niche audience websites like The Library
                Observatory, an open-submission Tumblr blog, where users can <q>post screenshots of
                    quirks in data from the Digital Public Library of America,</q> such as
                cataloging typos or sloppy metadata parameters, which have been made visible by The
                Library Observatory’s main digital humanities visualization site operated by
                Harvard’s metaLAB. Just as <soCalled>mess</soCalled> is an important category for
                feminist HCI researchers <ptr target="#dourish2011"/>, it also might be important in
                the small data digital humanities, where the foibles of manual labor might be made
                manifest by chuckles in the blogosphere over the bejeweled and manicured hand of a
                female digitizer accidentally appearing in the Google Book Search results for <title
                    rend="italic">The Gentleman’s Magazine</title>
                <ptr target="#losh2009"/>.</p>
            <p>Collaborative scholarship has been an important practice among intersecting groups of
                feminist game scholars. For example, Ludica’s Pearce also served as a coauthor of
                    <hi rend="italic">Ethnography and Virtual Worlds: A Handbook of Method</hi>,
                along with Tom Beollstroff, Bonnie Nardi, and T.L. Taylor. This handbook not only
                emphasizes the important contributions of feminist ethnography to our understanding
                of digital culture but also criticizes the instrumentalism, quantification, and
                subsequent myopia of the scientific rationalism that derides subjective, personal,
                or embodied perspectives. Yet collaborative authorship in the digital humanities
                cannot be similarly strongly correlated with feminism. Only one of the ten authors
                of the critical code studies book <title rend="italic">10 PRINT</title> was female,
                and women made up only a fraction of the multiple authors of the
                    <soCalled>crowdsourced</soCalled> book from the University of Michigan Press
                    <title rend="italic">Hacking the Academy</title>. Perhaps this is not surprising
                given the machismo sometimes associated with multiple authorship in other forms of
                digital textual collaboration, such as when hackers generate code or Wikipedia
                editors produce pages or computer scientists rack up publications with the multiple
                authorship that defines their scholarly networks. </p>
            <p>Yet feminists can make distinct contributions by providing opportunities for digital
                humanists to think across disciplines, particularly to consider how the literature
                of the social sciences or of the digital arts can trouble the simple model of coding
                knowledge promulgated by the humanities computing paradigm. After all, to visit a
                digital archive as a remote user still involves accessing, browsing, reading, and
                wayfinding. In particular, contemporary researchers in human-computer interaction
                point to the importance of considering how embodiment or identity is experienced by
                computer users who are engaged in computer mediated practices of telepresence or
                ubiquity, and feminist game scholars have led in their discipline on these issues.
                For example, Taylor asserts that designers should <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#taylor2006">rise to the challenge presented by a
                        sociology of the body</quote>
                    <ptr target="#taylor2006" loc="124"/>
                </cit>. </p>
            <p>In <title rend="italic">Communities of Play</title>, Pearce focuses on how
                inhabitants of virtual worlds understand their own social construction of identity
                and experience intersubjectivity. Pearce uses feminist ethnography to ground her
                research on members of the <q><emph>Uru</emph> diaspora</q> of players who were
                forced to recreate their familiar 3D world in new platforms after the game was
                discontinued, much as participants in many digital humanities initiatives must cope
                with choosing between the options of <soCalled>emulation</soCalled> or
                    <soCalled>migration</soCalled> when hardware or software that supports a beloved
                project becomes obsolete. She observes that <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#pearce2009">feminist ethnography has long
                        challenged boundaries between subjectivity and objectivity, individual and
                        society, researcher and subject, fact and faction, self and other, and art
                        and science</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pearce2009" loc="21"/>
                </cit>. It is worth noting that successful digital humanities projects often
                encourage imaginative identification with other times and places and allow the
                visitor to become a participant in historical narratives. </p>
            <p>Although feminist game studies is still a relatively new area of inquiry, it also
                benefits from opportunities to reflect on its own intellectual history. Looking back
                to the work of Sherry Turkle on the shift in the mid-1980s away from hard mastery
                and toward <soCalled>soft</soCalled> forms of computer use in which <quote
                    rend="inline" source="#turkle1995">the computer is still a tool but less like a
                    hammer and more like a harpsichord</quote> in Turkle’s words (63), Mimi Ito
                argues that gaming is much like other domains of digital mastery in that user
                behavior can’t be reduced to a <soCalled>feminine</soCalled> stance of
                    <soCalled>soft</soCalled> engagement that might only reinforce gender norms
                (147). In contrast, Mary Flanagan feels like she can build on the work of feminist
                pioneer Brenda Laurel in seeing herself as a <soCalled>culture worker</soCalled>
                capable of <q>conscious interventions</q> that foster <q>action styles</q> that
                offer <q>models for other emerging practices</q> and <q>sites of empowerment</q> to
                marginalized groups (256). Of course, the promotion of feminist game studies has to
                do with the agencies of peers as well as the existence of progenitors, so perhaps
                this issue of DHQ will serve as an important early step in field building.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Barnett" xml:id="barnett2013"> Barnett, Fiona. CFP: Feminist Game
                    Studies | HASTAC. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://hastac.org/blogs/fionab/2012/07/06/cfp-feminist-game-studies"
                        >http://hastac.org/blogs/fionab/2012/07/06/cfp-feminist-game-studies</ref>
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013a].</bibl>
                <bibl label="metaLAB Library Observatory" xml:id="metaLAB2013">. metaLAB Library
                    Observatory. Available at: <ref target="http://libobserve.tumblr.com"
                        >http://libobserve.tumblr.com</ref> [Accessed March 26, 2013b].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Dourish and Bell 2011" xml:id="dourish2011"> Dourish, P. &amp; Bell,
                    G., 2011. <title rend="italic">Divining a digital future mess and mythology in
                        ubiquitous computing</title>, Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press. Available at:
                        <ref target="http://site.ebrary.com/id/10476094"
                        >http://site.ebrary.com/id/10476094</ref> [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Flanagan 2009" xml:id="flanagan2009">Flanagan, M., 2009. <title
                        rend="italic">Critical play radical game design</title>, Cambridge, Mass.:
                    MIT Press. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;db=nlabk&amp;AN=291810"
                        >http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;db=nlabk&amp;AN=291810</ref>
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fron et al. 2007" xml:id="fron2007">Fron, J. et al., 2007. <title
                        rend="italic">The Hegemony of Play.</title>
                    <ref target="http://ict.usc.edu/pubs/The%20Hegemony%20of%20Play.pdf"
                        >http://ict.usc.edu/pubs/The%20Hegemony%20of%20Play.pdf</ref>,
                    pp.309–318.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gajjala and Oh 2012" xml:id="gajjala2012">Gajjala, R. &amp; Oh, Y.J.,
                    2012. <title rend="italic">Cyberfeminism 2.0</title>, New York: Peter Lang
                    Pub.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Golub 2010" xml:id="golub2010">Golub, E.M., 2010. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Gender Divide in Librarianship: Past, Present and Future, Gender Divide in
                        Librarianship: Past, Present, and Future</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Library Student Journal, Library Student Journal</title>, 5,(0, 0).
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.librarystudentjournal.org/index.php/lsj/article/view/129"
                        >http://www.librarystudentjournal.org/index.php/lsj/article/view/129</ref>,
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Guertin 2009" xml:id="guertin2009">Guertin, C., 2009. <title
                        rend="quotes">From Complicity to Interactivity: Theories of Feminist Game
                        Play.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Studies / Le champ numérique</title>, 0(0.09).
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/194"
                        >http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/194</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hanson 2003" xml:id="hanson2003">Hanson, A., 2003. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Humanities and School Libraries.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Library3000</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://alidas460portfolio.tumblr.com/post/45639362470/digital-humanities-and-school-libraries"
                        >
                        http://alidas460portfolio.tumblr.com/post/45639362470/digital-humanities-and-school-libraries</ref>
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Huntemann and Payne 2010" xml:id="huntemann2010">Huntemann, N. &amp;
                    Payne, M.T., 2010. <title rend="italic">Joystick soldiers the politics of play
                        in military video games</title>, New York: Routledge. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://public.eblib.com/EBLPublic/PublicView.do?ptiID=448316"
                        >http://public.eblib.com/EBLPublic/PublicView.do?ptiID=448316</ref>
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Huntemann 2012" xml:id="huntemann2012">Huntemann, N.B., 2012. <title
                        rend="quotes">Feminist Game Studies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Antenna</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://blog.commarts.wisc.edu/2012/03/20/feminist-game-studies/"
                        >http://blog.commarts.wisc.edu/2012/03/20/feminist-game-studies/</ref>
                    [Accessed March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ito 2009" xml:id="ito2009">Ito, M., 2009. <title rend="italic"
                        >Engineering play a cultural history of children’s software</title>,
                    Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Losh 2009" xml:id="losh2009">Losh, Elizabeth. <title rend="italic"
                        >Virtualpolitik : An Electronic History of Government Media-Making in a Time
                        of War, Scandal, Disaster, Miscommunication, and Mistakes.</title>
                    Cambridge, MA MIT Press, 2009.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Losh and Jenkins 2012" xml:id="losh2012">Losh, E. &amp; Jenkins, H.,
                    2012. <title rend="quotes">Can Public Education Coexist with Participatory
                        Culture?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Knowledge Quest</title>, 41(1), pp.16–21.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Mandell 2012" xml:id="mandell2012">Mandell, L., 2012. <title
                        rend="quotes">Media X: A Report on the Digital Humanities from MLA
                        2012.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Inquire: Journal of Comparative Literature</title>, 2(1).
                    Available at: <ref target="http://inquire.streetmag.org/articles/62"
                        >http://inquire.streetmag.org/articles/62</ref> [Accessed March 29,
                    2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="McRobert 2007" xml:id="mcrobert2007">McRobert, L., 2007. <title
                        rend="italic">Char Davies’ immersive virtual art and the essence of
                        spatiality</title>, Toronto: University of Toronto Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Montfort 2013" xml:id="montfort2013">Montfort, N., 2013. <title
                        rend="italic">10 PRINT CHR$(205.5+RND(1));:GOTO 10</title>, Cambridge,
                    Mass.: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Nowviskie 2011" xml:id="nowviskie2011">Nowviskie, B., 2011. <title
                        rend="quotes">What do girls dig?</title>
                    <hi rend="italic">Bethany Nowviskie</hi>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://nowviskie.org/2011/what-do-girls-dig/"
                        >http://nowviskie.org/2011/what-do-girls-dig/</ref> [Accessed February 1,
                    2014].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pearce 2009" xml:id="pearce2009">Pearce, C., 2009. <title rend="italic"
                        >Communities of play emergent cultures in multiplayer games and virtual
                        worlds</title>, Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Posner 2010" xml:id="posner2012">Posner, M., 2012. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Some things to think about before you exhort everyone to code.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Miriam Posner’s Blog</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://miriamposner.com/blog/some-things-to-think-about-before-you-exhort-everyone-to-code/"
                        >http://miriamposner.com/blog/some-things-to-think-about-before-you-exhort-everyone-to-code/</ref>
                    [Accessed February 1, 2014].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Presner 2008" xml:id="presner2008">Presner, T., 2008. <title
                        rend="quotes">HyperCities, Google, and the Digital
                    Dialectic.</title>University of California, Irvine, School of Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ramirez, Parthasarathy, and Gordon 2009" xml:id="ramirez2009">Ramirex,
                    R., Parthasarathy, B. &amp; Gordon, A., 2009. <title rend="italic"
                        >Infomediaries: Public access brokers: Final Report.</title> Global Impact
                    Study Research Report Series, Seattle: Technology &amp; Social Change Group,
                    University of Washington Information School, Available at: <ref
                        target="http://tascha.uw.edu/publications/brokers-of-public-access"
                        >http://tascha.uw.edu/publications/brokers-of-public-access</ref> [Accessed
                    March 26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Scheinfeldt 2011" xml:id="scheinfeldt">Scheinfeldt, T., Cohen, D. &amp;
                    George Mason University. Center for History and New Media, 2011. <title
                        rend="italic">Hacking the academy: a book crowdsourced in one week.</title>
                    Available at: <ref target="http://www.digitalculture.org/hacking-the-academy/"
                        >http://www.digitalculture.org/hacking-the-academy/</ref> [Accessed March
                    26, 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Spurr2012" xml:id="spurr2012"> Bendilin. (2012). Eulogy for <title
                        rend="quotes">Beat up Anita Sarkeesian.</title> Newgrounds, available online
                    at <ref target="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/598591"
                        >http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/598591</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Taylor 2006" xml:id="taylor2006">Taylor, T.L., 2006. <title
                        rend="italic">Play between worlds: exploring online game culture</title>,
                    Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Turkle 1995" xml:id="turkle1995">Turkle, S., 1995. <title rend="italic"
                        >Life on the screen: identity in the age of the Internet</title>, New York:
                    Simon &amp; Schuster.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wajcman 2004" xml:id="wajcman2004">Wajcman, J., 2004. <title
                        rend="italic">TechnoFeminism</title>, Cambridge; Malden, MA: Polity.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
