<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
	xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">DH as Data: Establishing Greater Access through
					Sustainability</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Alex <dhq:family>Kinnaman</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8943-8946</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Virginia Tech University</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>alexk93@vt.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Corinne <dhq:family>Guimont</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9364-7708</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Virginia Tech University</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>gcorinne@vt.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000715<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
						target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
						>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref> </bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
						target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
						>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref> </bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language extent="original" ident="en"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<term corresp="#access"/>
					<term corresp="#data_curation"/>
					<term corresp="#project_management"/>
					<term corresp="#project_report"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
				target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000715/000715.xml"
				>GitHub </ref> </change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="original" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>This paper presents methodology and findings from a multi-case study exploring the use of
					preservation and sustainability measures to increase access to digital humanities (DH)
					content. Specifically, we seek to develop a workflow to both prepare DH content for
					preservation while enhancing the accessibility of the project. This work is based on the
					idea of treating DH as traditional data by applying data curation and digital preservation
					methods to DH content. Our outcomes are an evaluation of the process and output using
					qualitative methods, publicly accessible and described project components on two Virginia
					Tech projects, and a potential workflow that can be applied to future work. By breaking
					down individual projects into their respective components of content, code, metadata, and
					documentation and examining each component individually for access and preservation, we
					can begin migrating our digital scholarship to a sustainable, portable, and accessible
					existence.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p>Numerous Digital Humanities (DH) projects are developed in institutions and organizations
					without standards for access and preservation. However, various standards and best
					practices more closely associated with other fields exist for project management, data
					curation, access, and preservation, but have not been exclusively adapted for DH. The goal
					of this paper is to explore the concept of DH as data and the application of data curation
					methods to two DH projects at Virginia Tech (VT) in order to enhance access and
					preservation. By breaking down individual projects into their respective components and
					treating them as data, we can begin preparing digital scholarship for a sustainable,
					portable, and accessible existence.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Challenges in Maintaining DH</head>
				<p>At Virginia Tech University Libraries (VTUL) there are currently eighteen DH projects that
					we currently maintain on a technical level, may potentially maintain, or plan to provide
					preservation services for project content. These projects are currently hosted on local
					library servers, private servers we do not have access to, different departmental servers,
					and two projects that are currently hosted outside of the university. Seven of the
					projects are built on Omeka, four on Wordpress, and many were built using HTML or other
					homegrown tools. These projects were created over a period of time ranging from 1996 to
					2021 with some having been static and unmaintained since the mid-2000’s. A survey of these
					projects revealed that seven had some supplementary content (such as news articles,
					corresponding publications, presentations, and images) in our institutional repository
					VTechWorks, but only one of the projects had deposited raw data or content into that
					repository. Further, only four projects mention or document details regarding preservation
					and sustainability efforts for ongoing access. These projects are fragile with an average
					lifespan of two to five<!--2-5--> years without human intervention, and as the University
					Library we are responsible for the maintenance of the open source resources created by our
					VT community. In a larger effort to support these projects and other future digital work,
					we chose to explore methods to preserve DH projects with a strategy that could be
					reasonably implemented on a larger scale. This strategy is based on preserving components
					of the DH project for reconstruction of the content in the future and documenting methods
					to educate our digital scholars to create and modify their projects with preservation in
					mind.</p>
				<p>The problem with developing a reasonable approach to sustainable DH projects is manifold
					but can be summed up into a single concept. DH is uniquely located in the overlap between
					the humanities, archives, and information technology, but unless a resource is labeled
					DH-related, it may be overlooked. There are best practices, and general technical
					maintenance that are applied in several other fields, but may not cross into DH education
					and infrastructure <ptr target="#barats_etal2020"/>. By identifying these practices and
					testing their application specifically to DH without compromising the culture and purpose,
					we can avoid reinventing new ways to curate digital content.</p>
				<p>For the purposes of this paper, we refer to the Digital Preservation Coalition definition
					of digital preservation as <cit><quote rend="inline">the series of managed activities
					necessary to ensure continued access to digital materials for as long as
					necessary</quote><ptr target="#dpc"/></cit>. This is a widely adopted definition utilized
					by libraries and archives as it allows for varied approaches to preservation based on
					needs. Although this paper is written in the context of an academic library, it is also a
					resource for those creating DH projects and sustaining and preserving the digital
					components of their work. Further, we define a sustainable project as one that can be
					supported financially, including the resources for storage, ongoing maintenance and
					monitoring, unique technology needs, and time and effort from personnel. Finally,
					infrastructure refers to the technical scaffolding and organized governance necessary to
					host, maintain, and preserve digital projects.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Digital Humanities as Data</head>
				<p>Given the infrastructural issues discussed above, VTUL is exploring the idea of DH as data.
					In this case, we describe <q>data</q> as all of the digital content pertaining to a DH
					project or produced in the preservation process. Our approach is to preserve each DH
					project component as an individual entity with corresponding metadata for the purpose of
					reconstruction. Project components are distinguished by their file format or software type
					and enhanced for our purposes with documentation and metadata.</p>
				<p>The concept of treating content as data was explored by the IMLS project <title
					rend="italic">Collections as Data</title> <ptr target="#padilla_etal2020"/>, which sought
					to address the problem that <quote rend="inline">cultural heritage institutions have
					rarely built digital collections or designed access with the aim to support computational
					use.</quote> This signals a cultural shift that treats non-traditional data, such as text,
					images, and audio, as data to be computationally explored. While definitions of DH are
					broad and varied, this concept can be applied to enhance access on small and large scales.
					The <title rend="quotes">Ten Principles</title> <ptr target="#padilla_etal2020"/>
					developed by the <title rend="italic">Collections as Data</title> project are a starting
					point to guide digital collections into a more engaged environment that promotes multiple
					forms of access.</p>
				<p>We applied <title rend="italic">Collections as Data</title> to the idea of DH as data in
					that it widely varies in tools, techniques, file formats, softwares, and hardwares, to
					generate, manipulate, and render information. Where DH lacks a community-supported
					archival best practice for creation and storage, there are definitive database structures
					built to store and maintain data, metadata standards to improve search and context, and
					ways to measure the success and use of the data. Rather than reinventing a new workflow
					for DH as a field, treating components of DH projects as pieces of a dataset serves to
					provide a best practice for development, access, and storage that increases the long-term
					preservation and usability of project material. Treating DH as data also serves to support
					DH as an academic scholarship, which it is not often considered at many institutions, and
					provides a more familiar structure to further legitimize the labor of developing effective
					DH work.</p>
				<p>Similar efforts have been explored at the <ref target="https://www.sds.ox.ac.uk/home"
					>University of Oxford Sustainable Digital Scholarship Program</ref> in their Humanities
					Division that supports sustainable digital scholarship through the data repository
					platform <ref target="https://figshare.com/about"><title rend="none"
					>Figshare</title></ref>. <ref target="https://figshare.sds.ox.ac.uk/">The Oxford instance
					of Figshare</ref> hosts exclusively humanities content supporting digital scholarship and
					adheres to the <title rend="italic">FAIR Data Principles</title>. The <title rend="italic"
					>FAIR Principles for Data</title> <ptr target="#wilkinson_etal2016"/> are guidelines for
					increasing the <term>findability</term>, <term>accessibility</term>,
					<term>interoperability</term>, <term>reusability</term> of data and its metadata, and the
					system’s infrastructure. This method applies a license to the data and increases the
					discoverability of the data through proposed metadata, persistent and unique identifiers,
					and open access. These basic discoverability and preservation parameters apply to all
					digital content and are already used as best practices.</p>
				<p>Instruction on this topic is emerging as well. Outside of courses in formalized university
					programs, organizations like the Digital Humanities Summer Institute Technologies East
					2021 hosted a class in May 2021 on <title rend="quotes">Making Research Data Public:
					Workshopping Data Curation for Digital Humanities
					Projects</title>,<!--<note>DHSITE workshop:
					<ref
					target="https://biblio.uottawa.ca/en/news/making-research-data-public-workshopping-data-curation-digital-humanities-projects?utm_source=Digital+Humanists+at+UOttawa&amp;utm_campaign=4864db65b9-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2020_02_23_03_23_COPY_01&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_0a320e70ea-4864db65b9-63601215"
					>https://biblio.uottawa.ca/en/news/making-research-data-public-workshopping-data-curation-digital-humanities-projects?utm_source=Digital+Humanists+at+UOttawa&amp;utm_campaign=4864db65b9-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2020_02_23_03_23_COPY_01&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_0a320e70ea-4864db65b9-63601215</ref>
					</note>--> citing in its abstract that <quote rend="inline">a lack of formal training
					opportunities for data curation in multi-site DH teams means that the data produced in
					these teams is in danger of being lost.</quote> This is a single example among many DH
					organizations moving towards technology education to enhance projects.</p>
				<p>Many grant funders also require data management plans, sustainability plans, technical
					plans, and other relevant documentation in grant proposals. The National Endowment for the
					Humanities Office of Digital Humanities, for example, provides tips on writing final white
					papers that includes an entire section on outcomes and obstacles in technology,
					documentation, and platforms,<!--<note>Office of Digital Humanities.</note>--> and
					requires a section on Managing and Sustaining the Project Assets in level three DH
					Advancement Grants <ptr target="#serventi2019"/>.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Methodology </head>
				<p>We used a multi-method approach, with a comprehensive literature review on the community’s
					practice in developing sustainable DH projects, as well as two case studies conducted over
					a year-long period.</p>
				<div>
					<head>Literature Review </head>
					<p>Acknowledging that the rapid increase of digital scholarship also requires new methods
						of preservation and sustainability for long-term access has been an ongoing topic of
						discussion since the early days of DH. Discussion on best practices for preserving and
						curating DH scholarship became more common in the mid-2000s with the impending issue
						of preserving complex digital objects. In their article, Hunter and Choudhury <ref
						target="#hunter_etal2003">2003</ref><quote rend="inline" source="#hunter_etal2003"
						>focus on the problem of preserving composite digital objects consisting of multiple
						media types</quote> and introduce the concept of emulation, migration, and metadata as
						it pertains to complex digital objects, which includes DH. They state, <cit><quote
						rend="inline">As scholars in the humanities create increasingly sophisticated
						multimedia research and teaching resources, they need to capture, collect, and create
						the documentation or metadata – descriptive, administrative, and structural –
						necessary to migrate, emulate, or otherwise translate existing resources to future
						hardware and software configurations</quote><ptr target="#hunter_etal2003"/></cit>.
						Cantara (<ref target="#cantara2006">2006</ref>) performed an early literature review
						of digital humanities metadata best practices and tools to automate that metadata,
						which is significantly different from traditional cataloging <ptr
						target="#cantara2006"/>.</p>
					<p>The bulk of individual digital objects being preserved are simple; images, text files,
						audio/visual materials, all of which we have established best practices for ensuring
						continuity. We have the <ref target="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/"
						>Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement</ref> to transform objects into the
						optimal format for long-term access. We use checksums to confirm fixity and ensure
						objects are unchanged and uncorrupted. We use audit logs like the <ref
						target="https://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v3/">PREMIS Data Dictionary for
						Preservation Metadata</ref> to document stages in an object's lifestyle, such as
						ingest, deletion, restoration, fixity change, virus checking, etc., and then use tools
						like the <ref target="https://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/METSOverview.v2.html"
						>Metadata Encoding and Transmission Standard</ref> to encode the metadata for broader
						understandability and interoperability with common systems. We maintain copies, mirror
						the information technology method for redundancy. All of these practices are guided by
						digital preservation auditing metrics, most notably the <ref
						target="https://www.iso.org/standard/56510.html">ISO 16363:2012 Space data and
						information transfer systems — Audit and certification of trustworthy digital
						repositories (TDR)</ref> which also provides guidance on governance, security, and
						financial sustainability. Good and best practices for common digital objects are
						straightforward and have well-established guidelines, but when combined into a complex
						digital object like a website, interactive resource, or software, the basic digital
						preservation principle of ongoing preservation becomes increasingly complicated.</p>
					<p>Another problem at large in hosting digital projects lies within the general
						scalability and sustainability of the services offered. Conway (<ref
						target="#conway2010">2010</ref>) explored the concepts of digitizing for preservation
						and digital preservation and the transition from traditional preservation to digital
						preservations, leading to dilemmas in what objects are treated differently and how
						they are treated in a digital environment. Further, Vinopal and McCormick (<ref
						target="#vinopal_etal2013">2013</ref>) state that <quote rend="inline"
						source="#vinopal_etal2013">these services should promote the development of reusable
						tools, platforms, and methods, and facilitate the creation of preservable, reusable
						scholarly content to ensure the long-term value of and access to the institution's
						research.</quote> Their article provides an overview of various researcher needs and
						the relationship between the services and Libraries of a given institution and
						provides a Proposed Model for Digital Scholarship Services that includes DH
						scholarship and how DH programs fit into other institutional services. Leslie Johnston
						of the National Archives and Records Administration expresses similar thoughts on
						strategies in preserving DH specifically, stating <cit><quote rend="inline"
						>sustainability and preservation depend on active management of a project. Digital
						humanities projects correctly put the highest focus on the content and scholarship
						that they present. But these projects should not let their technologies go
						stale</quote><ref target="#johnston2013">2013</ref></cit> by relying on technologies
						and plugins that no longer receive maintenance or community support.</p>
					<p>Project failure can occur in many ways, from lack of funding to complete, inaccessible
						data, little to no preservation or access storage, and lack of technical training,
						among others. While a project can fail for a number of reasons, we searched for
						examples of DH projects that had failed due to lack of preservation or sustainability
						planning. Surprisingly, there is little record of specific projects that have been
						discontinued or failed as they are no longer accessible. A study conducted by Timothy
						Vines and his team surveyed 516 articles published over the course of ten years and
						found that after the first two years of publication, access to scientific data falls
						by seventeen percent every year <ptr target="#vines_etal2013"/>. Their summary was
						that <cit><quote rend="inline">broken emails and obsolete storage devices were the
						main obstacles to data sharing</quote><ptr target="#vines_etal2013"/></cit>. This
						study examined accessibility and sharing and can be applied to other forms of digital
						content in that broken links and obsolete storage are obstacles to digital
						maintenance. In terms of DH, there are some but few examples of failed projects. James
						Cummings, for example, provided a list of projects he personally supported that had
						ultimately failed, five of six of which included lack of sustainability planning,
						funding, or limited technology in their reasons for failure (<ref
						target="#cummings2020">2020</ref>). Jasmine Kirby also discusses the failure of the
						Sophie 2.0 project at the University of Southern California, an international
						collaboration with over a million dollars in funding, noting <cit><quote rend="inline"
						>the focus was on building the tool with the most features and not something that
						actually could be sustained or even worked</quote><ref target="#kirby2019"
						>2019</ref></cit>. Even a 2013 JISC study surveyed DH Center Directors regarding
						long-term maintenance of hosted projects and found difficulty in keeping these sites
						live <ptr target="#maron_etal2013"/>. The study suggests that centers can turn to
						museums and libraries for long-term hosting and access, but also notes that
						<cit><quote rend="inline">many have yet to develop a formal digital
						strategy</quote><ref target="#maron_etal2013">2013</ref></cit>.</p>
					<p>In contrast to unsuccessful projects, many long-standing DH projects share specific
						aspects that led to success. The accessibility of the raw data as a component of the
						project regardless of the platform and the ability to explore it independently appears
						to be the key to the success of these long-standing projects. These projects all
						ensure the data is platform-agnostic and manipulable in other platforms with multiple
						tools and exists in formats that are interoperable. Many of these projects also
						contain corresponding documentation to describe the data as another component of the
						work. For example, the <ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/">Walt Whitman
						Archive</ref> is built on TEI/XML and simple HTML. The interface has not been updated
						in some time, however, the success of this project is based on the range and depth of
						the content, and the accessibility of the raw data. All of the manuscripts,
						correspondence, and most other content is available for <ref
						target="https://github.com/whitmanarchive">direct download from the Git
						repository</ref> in their original TEI/XML markup. Similarly, the <ref
						target="http://www.blakearchive.org/staticpage/archiveataglance?p=api">William Blake
						Archive</ref> provides a short API code to query the entire archive independently.
						Finally, the <ref target="http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/swinburne/">Charles Algernon
						Swineburne Project</ref> provides basic <ref
						target="http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/swinburne/downloads.jsp">TEI/XML and XSLT
						files</ref> to explore and recreate the archive.</p>
					<p>Comparing these successful and unsuccessful projects prompted us to review other guides
						on sustainable websites in beginning our case studies. There are several guides on
						creating sustainable websites available through the Library of Congress’ <title
						rend="quotes">Creating Preservable Websites</title> page, the blog post <title
						rend="quotes">On Preserving Digital Culture and Digital Projects</title> and <title
						rend="quotes">Digital Humanities for Tomorrow: Opening the Conversation about DH
						Project Preservation</title> (<ref target="#samberg_etal2016">2016</ref>) from Digital
						Humanities at Berkeley, and Stanford Libraries’ <title rend="quotes"
						>Archivability</title> guide (<ref target="#stanford">Stanford Libraries</ref>). This
						guidance provides some foundational best practices and again acknowledges the need for
						sustainable and preservable websites, but does not provide a comprehensive solution.
						Additional guides that are more thorough and include practical information such as the
						<ref target="https://sites.haa.pitt.edu/sustainabilityroadmap/">Socio-Technical
						Sustainability Roadmap</ref> at the University of Pittsburgh and the Digital Project
						Preservation Plan: A Guide for Preserving Digital Humanities <ptr target="#miller2019"
						/> have been recently developed. However, Kilbride (<ref target="#kilbride2015"
						>2015</ref>) notes that while the standards have been created to fill the gaps in
						digital preservation as it pertains to DH, these best practices have not been widely
						adopted.</p>
					<p>The literature review of resources, guides, and projects indicate that increasing
						access to DH scholarship is a mix of infrastructural and developing best practices, as
						well as providing education for scholars to learn to adopt best practices. The review
						also supports the theory of supporting the components of projects for long-term
						preservation and access in regards to common preservation practices and what has
						allowed long-standing DH projects to thrive.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Case Studies at Virginia Tech</head>
					<p>Virginia Tech is home to dozens of DH projects ranging in legacy to recent, hundreds to
						thousands of items, and on a variety of platforms. Recently the Libraries have
						received requests from faculty and administration to develop sustainability plans for
						these programs and to promote greater use through easier access to data, formal
						analytics and branding, and advertising of these projects. The Libraries approached
						this request by experimenting with the concept of DH as data with comprehensive
						exports of project content, the creation of necessary metadata, and the creation of
						project documentation into a single data set.</p>
					<p>There are several possible repositories and storage locations for this content.
						Projects that contain humanities content with additional scholarship and fit the
						criteria for the institutional repository, VTechWorks. While projects that contain
						mapping datasets fit the criteria for the Virginia Tech Data Repository. Additionally,
						any project that is a general product of Virginia Tech research could be ingested into
						our newer platform the Virginia Tech Digital Libraries Platform. For the both of our
						case studies, we found them most suitable for the <ref
						target="https://data.lib.vt.edu/">Virginia Tech Data Repository</ref> as the final
						preservation datasets contained a layered file system with a mix of documentation and
						smaller datasets.</p>
					<p>We explored two case studies in the last year. Social Networks in Georgian Britain
						(SNiGB), a new project branching off of a long-standing project, Lord Byron and His
						Times (LBT), to enhance the exploration of the content containing over 40,000 items.
						And the second project, Redlining Virginia, is an Omeka-based project with
						approximately 110 items that is represented in multiple instances outside of the Omeka
						site.</p>
					<div>
						<head>Social Networks in Georgian Britain</head>
						<p>SNiGB originated in 2008 when it began as the prosopography for LBT, an archive of
							printed letters and diaries by and about Byron’s associates encoded in TEI-XML and
							rendered as the website <ref target="https://lordbyron.org/"
							>https://lordbyron.org/</ref> using XSLT transformations and XPath queries. These
							records, used to generate footnotes, included links to name authority files such
							as the LOC, National Archive (UK), National Portrait Gallery (UK), Oxford
							Dictionary of National Biography (ODNB), and the Virtual International Authority
							File (VIAF). In 2014, the LBT prosopography became an XML relational database with
							the addition of a demographic file containing fields for place of origin and
							professions, with linked information about family members, educational
							institutions, and correspondents. Fields were hand-coded using TEI elements and
							included place of origin, professions, and correspondents.</p>
						<p>From 2008 to 2012, the LBT website was hosted by Performant Software in
							Charlottesville, and sponsored by <ref target="https://nines.org/">Nineteenth
							Century Scholarship Online</ref> (NINES); in 2012 web hosting was transferred to
							VTUL. In 2017, work in LBT shifted from document markup to development of the
							prosopography exclusively, and Professor <name>David Radcliffe</name> began
							discussions with VTUL about data design and publication. With the 20,000 names
							originally collected from the letters and diaries, Dr. Radcliffe has since added
							an additional 25,000+ names collected from membership lists of learned societies,
							social and benevolent clubs, and political organizations.</p>
						<p>In the winter of 2018, as data collection and description continued, four VTUL
							personnel and additional student workers began structuring a work plan to
							transform the TEI-XML into a freely accessible database with a publicly available,
							interactive user interface. In recent years, VTUL has increased support for
							faculty and student digital projects, including website and database hosting,
							consultations, and support for new technologies. However, the transformation and
							migration of a project at this scale has yet to be tested. The final version of
							SNiGB content comprising over 40,000 names has been completed by Dr.
							<name>Radcliffe</name>, and in collaboration with him, this new content has been
							exported into individual XML files by person and organization, bagged, and
							ingested into the Virginia Tech Data Repository as a new access point for the raw
							data which can be accessed at <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7294/14849748"
							>https://doi.org/10.7294/14849748</ref> and have been made available in an HTML
							index at <ref target="https://snigb.vt.domains/persNames_index.html"
							>https://snigb.vt.domains/persNames_index.html</ref>. The development of an
							interactive prosopography site is forthcoming, and this currently serves as the
							exclusive access point to the entire network of names in its final format.</p>
						<p>As a longer-standing DH project, SNiGB is reflective of similar projects mentioned
							in the Literature Review, such as the Walt Whitman Archive, and of the other
							projects VTUL may need to manage in the future. It is built on standard TEI-XML
							with a simple HTML/CSS interface that has maintained existence partially because
							of its simplicity. The maintenance issues that originally prompted the restructure
							of this project stem from all of the records being encoded in a single TEI
							document that could not be validated.</p>
					</div>
					<div>
						<head>Redlining Virginia</head>
						<p>The second case study is a practical application of our initial strategy on the
							<ref target="http://redliningvirginia.org/">Virginia Tech project Redlining
							Virginia</ref> led by history professor LaDale Winling. Redlining Virginia <quote
							rend="inline">explores the actions of Home Owners' Loan Corporation (HOLC) in
							Virginia and its impact on Virginia cities.</quote> It is a child project of the
							larger <ref target="https://dsl.richmond.edu/panorama/redlining/"><title
							rend="quotes">Mapping Inequality: Redlining in New Deal America</title></ref> that
							specifically explores the Virginia and West Virginia eastern regions. This digital
							project consists of images, contextual text, videos, and georectified maps. It was
							also featured as a physical exhibit in Newman Library at Virginia Tech from
							December 7, 2016 - February 17, 2017, which broadened the content to images of the
							exhibit and post-it notes left by visitors to the exhibit.</p>
						<p>This DH project was chosen for several reasons. It is much newer and less
							long-lived than SNiGB and therefore much smaller, approximately 110 items in the
							original website, but also contains a wider variety of file types for
							experimentation. It is hosted on Omeka where items and their metadata could be
							exported. Packages containing the georectified maps were already uploaded to the
							Virginia Tech Data Repository by Professor Winling, but the corresponding text is
							not replicated elsewhere. The digital exhibit hosted at VT contained post-it notes
							with feedback from visitors and were also uploaded to the institutional
							repository, VTechWorks. These factors indicated that it would be reasonable to
							assemble all of the project components into a single package and create additional
							documentation to recreate or reconstruct the website.</p>
						<p>Components for Redlining Virginia spanned several locations between both Virginia
							Tech repositories, Omeka, the parent project Mapping Inequality, and Professor
							Winling’s personal machine. We also created several new pieces of documentation,
							including a preservation profile, a collection-level Metadata Application Profile,
							additional metadata in DublinCore for the images of the physical exhibit, and
							additional metadata in the <ref
							target="https://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm-standard">Content Standard for Digital
							Geospatial Metadata</ref> for the georectified maps. To replicate the website, we
							exported the HTML and CSS, as well as exporting each page of text to a PDF and
							included several screenshots to preserve the original visual style and
							organization. We also prepared a user guide with details on each digital object,
							information on how to read and write content in open access software, and general
							project information. This package can be viewed in the Virginia Tech Data
							Repository at <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7294/14597751.v1"
							>https://doi.org/10.7294/14597751.v1</ref>. The original website is static and
							live, and this additional access point provides all individual project components
							to a user.</p>
						<p>Given that VTUL has at least seven Omeka-based projects from students and faculty
							that may require support, this aligns with our current field of practice. We chose
							this project because we know there are other Omeka based projects we will need to
							preserve; however, we ultimately want to serve other platforms and projects as
							well. Omeka is also a popular tool for DH projects <ptr target="#rath2016"/>, as
							well as a tool used in other digital scholarship projects <ptr
							target="#cobourn2016"/> and therefore relatable to a wide variety of practicing
							digital humanists.</p>
					</div>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Results</head>
				<p>These results include both the impact of the case studies on our work, as well as the key
					themes that arose over the year of research and implementing the case studies.</p>
				<p>In terms of these case studies, we define success as first, preparing the data for
					long-term storage which included migrating formats, documenting workflows for open source
					software needed to open each format, and creating collection-level metadata; and second,
					depositing the resulting package of the original project objects and new documentation
					into a repository as an access point and into a third-party digital preservation service
					for preservation storage.</p>
				<p>While our case studies were successful in practice, they did require a lot of bandwidth
					from us that is difficult to repeat at a larger scale for all DH projects at VT. We found
					two key themes, in our context at VTUL, that are the primary obstacles to increasing the
					access, usability, and preservation of DH scholarship: a lack of education on best
					practices from our DH creators, and a lack of sustainable infrastructure development to
					support DH projects in university libraries.<!-- adjusted wording for clarity --></p>
				<div>
					<head>Case Studies</head>
					<p>We employed data curation methods that resulted in described datasets and content
						packages consolidated to be portable, explorable, and reused. The two case studies we
						have conducted so far have produced another access point for the raw data, content,
						and code, as well as provided another method of tracking impact through the Virginia
						Tech Data Repository (VTDR) when the Libraries do not have the ownership to apply
						analytics to a live project. This accomplishes both goals of providing a permanent
						access location for data regardless of whether the project as a whole was successful
						(an example of Redlining Virginia is in <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>), and
						of providing a preservation environment for DH data. Impact can also be measured
						through the number of views and downloads shown in the VTDR interface.</p>
					<p>VTDR is hosted on Figshare, which is backed up automatically to the digital
						preservation service <ref target="https://libraries.ucsd.edu/chronopolis/"
						>Chronopolis</ref> and VTDR manually deposits all datasets into the <ref
						target="https://aptrust.org/">Academic Preservation Trust</ref> digital preservation
						service of which VTUL are members. We successfully ingested each project’s data into a
						stable storage location with enough context to reconstruct the entire project in its
						integrity and to explore individual components. This was accomplished by organizing
						each individual component into its own folder with associated metadata packaged into a
						single folder with collection-level documentation and guides on where and how to
						locate additional resources (an example of Redlining Virginia file structure is in
						<ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>, <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>, <ref
						target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>, <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>, and <ref
						target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>).</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure01">
						<head>Screenshot of Redlining Virginia data in the Virginia Tech Data Repository
							hosted in Figshare</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
						<figDesc>Figshare interface shown preserving access and data.</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure02">
						<head>Screenshot of the top level folder</head>
						<graphic style="width: 25%;" url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
						<figDesc/>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure03">
						<head>Screenshot of the collection-level documentation</head>
						<graphic style="width: 25%;" url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
						<figDesc/>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure04">
						<head>Screenshot of each map that contains georectified maps and associated
							metadata</head>
						<graphic style="width: 40%;" url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
						<figDesc/>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure05">
						<head>Screenshot of the images from the associated physical exhibit and its
							metadata</head>
						<graphic style="width: 30%;" url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
						<figDesc/>
					</figure>
					<figure xml:id="figure06">
						<head>Screenshot of the collected website components and associated metadata</head>
						<graphic style="width: 40%;" url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
						<figDesc/>
					</figure>
					<p>Metadata development for SNiGB was straightforward as the raw data is a series of small
						XML files stored in zipped folders. Redlining Virginia contained georectified maps
						displaying the evolution of redlining over time. These maps, a combination of JPG,
						TIF, XML, TFW, OVR, and Shapefile bundles, required more research into appropriate
						metadata schemes. The final schema chosen was the <ref
						target="https://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm-standard">Content Standard for Digital
						Geospatial Metadata</ref> modified for our georectified maps. From a technical
						standpoint, researching and developing this metadata was the single most
						time-consuming phase of this case study. We applied a newly developed Digital Exhibits
						Metadata Application Profile designed by the Metadata Coordinator and a Preservation
						Profile designed by the Digital Preservation Coordinator and Digital Preservation
						Technologist that will also be applied to additional DH projects. Applications of both
						of these Profiles can be viewed in the <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.7294/14597751.v1">Virginia Tech Data Repository
						preservation packages for Redlining Virginia</ref>.</p>
					<p>One limitation we did not explore is discoverability. The new documentation developed
						for these case studies is not discoverable in and of itself and is only found through
						the data repository via the associated title, keywords, and descriptions. While we
						established another location for access, we did not have any autonomy in the metadata
						development to be more efficient in search engine capabilities.</p>
					<p>This practice is imperfect. We can only enhance and preserve what we are given or what
						can be found and exported. From these case studies, it is clear that defining a
						minimal standard of what is required from the project and researchers, and what is
						reasonable and possible for the Library to manage, is necessary.</p>
					<p>Time and bandwidth were also challenges in these case studies. Two library faculty
						members dedicated over forty<!--approximately 40+--> hours of time each to develop and
						implement workflows for each project. Given the dozens of projects that will require
						similar efforts in preservation and without considering additional enhancement and
						large-scale migration, this is not a reasonable task. The immediate outcome from these
						two case studies was increased evidence and advocacy in VTUL for a permanent support
						system for digital scholarship in the form of a standing committee . With sponsorship
						from the Associate Dean and Information Technology Executive Director and support from
						Library stakeholders and department heads, the newly established Digital Scholarship
						Technical Review Committee is designed to serve as an advisory and implementation body
						for both legacy and new Digital Scholarship and web-based projects hosted by VTUL.
						This committee is currently developing and will implement workflows, policies, and
						technical infrastructure for hosting digital scholarship, and will also include the
						appraisal and prioritization of migrating and developing projects. The committee will
						determine what qualifies as a digital scholarship project that the library is prepared
						to support, create migration procedures, identify responsible individuals, and
						implement workflows to transfer projects to the Libraries. This committee will also
						develop documentation and guidance for creating new sustainable digital projects.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Education and Best Practices </head>
					<p>The first qualitative result we found is that accessible and sustainable DH suffers
						from a lack of education for researchers and a lack of standards and best practices
						that are usable by novices. Kilbride <ref target="#kilbride2015">2015</ref> suitably
						remarks: <quote rend="inline">Consequently there are two abiding risks for those
						humanities scholars trying to ensure a long-term future for their precious digital
						cargo: that the emerging practices of digital preservation are a poor fit to the
						changing needs of humanities; and that jargon and miscommunication confound thoughtful
						efforts to engage.</quote> The overlap of humanities critical analysis skills and the
						technical skills to implement a successful and usable project is difficult to attain,
						particularly for projects hoping to continue beyond a few years. Foundational DH
						courses in the undergraduate and graduate programs tend to focus on the multiple
						definitions of DH, tools and techniques, and impact of providing unique public access
						to otherwise unavailable information. Sustainability, usability, and project
						management may be introduced, yet the number of DH projects created early in a
						researcher’s profession that eventually break or disappear is high.</p>
					<p>What DH standards and best practices do we introduce to students and new professionals?
						A traditional example is <ref target="https://nines.org/">Nineteenth Century
						Scholarship Online </ref> which provides a formal, peer-reviewed system for evaluating
						projects, but is limited to projects concentrating on 19th century humanities. Other
						similar resources are equally contextual and not universally applicable, such as the
						University of Nebraska-Lincoln’s <title rend="quotes">Best Practices for Digital
						Humanities Projects</title> guide that offers technical best practices, but does not
						necessarily provide information on documentation or preservation infrastructure.</p>
					<p>Within the DH field it is often necessary to learn at least one or multiple
						technologies from digitization, processing and quality control, metadata, website
						development, text mining, and so on to create successful digital scholarship. With our
						two case studies, as well as many other projects at Virginia Tech, researchers are
						largely self-taught and use popular platforms like Omeka to execute their work.
						Sometimes these projects are completed without direction or collaboration with the
						library and are later brought to VTUL for maintenance and preservation. In the case of
						older projects, many of these were built before VTUL had developed a preservation
						program, meaning that even those with the best intentions may have received little
						direction in the area of preservation. Humanists are not trained in information
						technology, digitization standards, metadata standards, content management systems,
						storage management, and digital preservation, because that is not generally required
						in the field. There is a balance between what technology is community-supported, what
						is simple to adopt, and what is sustainable. What are considered foundational DH
						skills may not incorporate IT best practices, digitization guidelines, or project
						management. The problem is paradoxical - what services can a library provide to its
						faculty and students when there are no defined best practices to teach? The lack of
						consistency between institutions and initiatives in their approach to DH is partially
						what makes DH so dynamic, but also causes formalization to be even more difficult than
						in a more established field of study.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Infrastructure </head>
					<p>The second result we found was an inconsistent approach to project building, indicating
						a lack of DH project infrastructure available to DH-ers. Like many other digital
						scholarship projects, website creation, and digital resources, DH projects are
						typically not designed to be sustainable and preservable. DH has grappled with
						insecure and unsupported technology because many creators are drawn to trendy
						technology that may not be sustainable <ptr target="#owens2014"/>. DH is often driven
						by new or easy-to-use technology that may not have a built-in infrastructure yet, when
						the goal of the project should drive the technology choices. Butler et al explored
						this integral infrastructure issue in 2019 in the two-part blog series <title
						rend="quotes">Archiving DH</title>. Taking a new technology and applying it to brand
						new research is a unique benefit for exploring options, but the lack of infrastructure
						leaves these projects unsustainable over time <ptr target="#butler_etal2019"/>. In
						<title rend="quotes">Archiving DH Part II: The problem in detail</title>, Butler et al
						also discuss what defines <quote rend="inline">authentic access and use over time for
						digital scholarship</quote> as websites cannot last forever without human intervention
						and maintenance. The authors discuss what the ideal point in the life cycle of
						scholarship is to introduce <cit><quote rend="inline">preservation, sustainability,
						and portability</quote><ptr target="#butler_etal2019"/></cit>. The piece on
						portability is highly relevant to the existing DH projects at VTUL as the Libraries
						receive many requests to transfer ownership of projects, and in some cases, this can
						mean transferring the platform of the project.</p>
					<p>As a culture, DH is open access in that many of the projects are openly available
						online. Additionally, funding from sources like NEH require grant awardees to produce
						open access projects <ptr target="#brennan2020"/>, while publishers like the
						International Journal for Digital Humanities are exclusively open access, and more
						often than not, DH is designed to highlight new content and research that only benefit
						from open distribution. However, while a project and its corresponding data may be
						openly available, if the code, algorithms, documentation, and metadata are not, how
						impactful and usable is the project in the long-term? Preservation is tricky, you
						cannot just <q>preserve it</q> because the essence of what matters about <q>it</q> is
						something that is contextually dependent on the way of being and seeing in the world
						that you have decided to textual components alone are not enough to accurately
						enhance, reproduce, or preserve a DH project.</p>
					<p>There are also the typical digital object collection problems to consider regarding
						storage, access platform, and responsibility for maintenance. For traditional
						scholarship we have journal databases and institutional repositories, and for data we
						have databases and data repositories, but a best practice for storing and maintaining
						DH projects, which is often a combination of scholarship and data, is still evolving.
						The choice we made to store our DH preservation packages in the Virginia Tech Data
						Repository was based on the best choice from the resources we had available, not
						because it’s a perfect DH storage solution.</p>
					<p>At VTUL we want to provide access to a preservation package that contains the text,
						context, code, metadata, and infrastructure to reproduce and reuse. This preservation
						package is designed to provide all of the components of a project and guidance on how
						to reuse, rebuild, and validate DH projects and data. In terms of digital preservation
						specifically, in the <ref target="http://www.oais.info/">Open Archival Information
						System (OAIS) Reference Model</ref>, the Submission Information Package would be
						created by VTUL, the Archival Information Package is stored in a preservation system
						(Virginia Tech Data Repository), and the Dissemination Information Package is hosted
						in a publicly accessible location (the live website). In many Virginia Tech DH
						projects, and many DH projects in general, the main deliverable is equivalent to the
						Dissemination Information Package with little regard to raw data or preservation and
						sustainability from the lack of technical infrastructure.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Solution and Suggestions </head>
				<p>On a more universal level, these case studies have indicated the need for established,
					straightforward models for researchers to understand and implement. The <ref
					target="http://www.datainfolit.org/">Data Information Literacy Project</ref> from the
					Institute of Libraries and Museums provides a similar framework for a standard training
					package for DH. The project provides a framework for educating graduate students and
					researchers on following best practices in data management with their research. A similar
					approach could be taken for creating sustainable and preservable DH projects. Based on our
					experience attempting to develop a reasonable and scalable workflow for preserving our DH
					projects, we recommend the following priorities to others both creating and curating DH
					projects: documentation development, openness and raw data sharing, and implementing
					sustainable storage and digital preservation practices.</p>
				<p>Our case studies required significant documentation to be created. This included
					specialized metadata, VTUL-established metadata, lists of file formats and open access
					tools and softwares to open them, and some additional content conversion for better
					portability and preservation. Establishing a method of documentation and examples of said
					documentation can increase usability from a wider audience. DH-ers creating new projects
					can begin documenting during project planning and design and develop content that is
					technology-agnostic and providing guidance on how to use and manipulate data and code
					increases the range of users that can access a DH project. Curators can work with DH-ers
					managing existing projects to create this documentation in a way that is most suitable for
					their access and/or preservation platform and for their infrastructure to migrate hosting
					to the Libraries.</p>
				<p>The ultimate goal of preservation is access. DH creators can share raw data and
					documentation to increase transparency and further research validation. By providing
					additional contextual information, raw data, code, and more, other users can fully access
					the many pieces of a DH project. Additionally, while not every project has the ability to
					support data mining, visualization software, or other methods of data exploration,
					providing access to other features such as unique code, exportable metadata, and plaintext
					files can increase usability of a project even if it’s not in its final format. This is
					similar to our approach with SNiGB, for which the preservation package is a series of XML
					files that does not yet have a platform for visualization or mining. Curators can take
					this approach to assist current projects to create more usable files for access.</p>
				<p>Furthermore, we recommend DH researchers focus on project planning and unique or specific
					project needs as early in the process as possible. Deciding what standards to use or best
					practices to follow after the project has begun can muddle progress and force researchers
					to backtrack in order to adopt a different strategy or undergo deduplication. Since there
					are few well-established standards specifically for DH as a field that have also been
					adopted by the community, choosing best practices that support individual project
					components can aid in developing an entire infrastructure of components that are
					supported, sustainable, and documented. As an example, in our case study with the
					Redlining Virginia preservation package, we needed to identify a metadata standard that
					aligned with the content, specifically for the georectified maps and their Shapefile
					bundles. We chose to find and use an existing schema rather than attempting to create a
					brand new metadata schema. While creators should be documenting as they develop, this is
					not a usual experience and the effort may fall largely to the curator for technical
					documentation development.</p>
				<p>Finally, technical infrastructure, storage, and preservation must be prioritized by DH-ers
					creating projects. Identifying a pre-established location for storage, such as an
					institutional repository or an appropriate public repository and ensuring the data fits
					the standard for that repository early on ensures a form of access and direct line to
					preservation copies and activities without the previously mentioned challenge of revising
					content or metadata after development to conform to a repository. Preservation activities
					ensure long term use through migration into preservation file formats that are
					well-supported, non-proprietary, and likely able to be migratable in the future. Digital
					preservation supports records of provenance articulating if data has changed or needs to
					be migrated or updated. It also monitors the lifespan and viability of the technology
					being used. Preservation-centric projects ensure that the project will be accessible over
					time and can be migrated or updated more smoothly. Reaching out to a university library or
					comparable institutional body to see what options are available for hosting and storage
					early in the process will help DH-ers create more sustainable projects and provide
					curators with more information to successfully maintain projects.</p>
				<p>Despite the success of creating a new iteration of the VT case study projects, the task of
					managing dozens of projects with the same methodology is not a sustainable process for two
					people to manage. Successful DH programs require dedicated and intentional infrastructure
					supporting the needs of researchers. Mutual responsibility for the Library to be
					transparent about what tools are supported and for researchers to choose a tool that can
					be supported in a location that can be easily accessed. However, many of our strategies
					can be duplicated at different levels depending on the resources available.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Conclusion </head>
				<p>This paper explored the case studies performed on two Virginia Tech DH projects at varying
					stages of complexity and age for the purposes of access and preservation. These case
					studies aimed to compile project components, develop additional description and
					documentation, and prepare content for long-term access. The findings shaped specific
					interventions utilized by VTUL and will be applied to additional DH projecfts. The result
					was the appraisal of two DH projects for preservation and access needs and the compilation
					of preservation-prepared datasets and corresponding documentation stored and accessible
					through the Virginia Tech Data Repository. The other significant result was the improved
					advocacy and support for our current and legacy DH projects as we work to maintain and
					enhance VT digital scholarship through a newly established Library committee.</p>
				<p>Our current goal is to ensure that our DH projects at VTUL can be reconstructed or
					recreated in the event that access to the original format is lost. In the preservation
					field, emulation is the optimal form of preservation for access. As organizations like SPN
					are already investigating the preservation and future accessibility of software and as we
					are currently employing web archiving through Archive-It, our ideal goal would be to
					ensure the usability of sites that cannot be migrated without losing integrity can be
					emulated and reused. Web archiving can preserve the look and feel of the project but may
					not be able to handle complex data manipulation software in a way that is meaningful to a
					user, thus the need to think of the components of DH projects and what we can do to
					preserve those as well as the look and feel.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl label="Ammon 2019" xml:id="ammon2019">Ammon, S. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Archiving DH
					part 1: The Problem. University of Virginia Scholars Lab</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-one"
					>https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-one</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Barats, Schafer, and Fickers 2020" xml:id="barats_etal2020">Barats, C., Schafer,
					V. and Fickers, A. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Fading Away... The Challenge of
					Sustainability in Digital Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
					Quarterly</title>, 14(3). Available at: <ref
					target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000484/000484.html"
					>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000484/000484.html</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Brennan 2020" xml:id="brennan2020">Brennan, S. (2020) <title rend="italic"
					>Planning Your Next DHAG 1: Idea, Audience, Innovation, Context</title>. Available at:
					<ref
					target="https://www.neh.gov/blog/planning-your-next-dhag-1-idea-audience-innovation-context"
					>https://www.neh.gov/blog/planning-your-next-dhag-1-idea-audience-innovation-context</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Butler, Visconti, and Work 2019" xml:id="butler_etal2019">Butler, B., Visconti,
					A. and Work, L. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Archiving DH Part 2: The Problem in
					Detail</title>, University of Virginia Libraries Scholars Lab. Available at: <ref
					target="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail"
					>https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Cantara 2006" xml:id="cantara2006">Cantara, L. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Long
					Term Preservation of Digital Humanities Scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">OCLC
					Systems &amp; Services: International Digital Library Perspectives</title>, 22(1), pp.
					38–42. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/10650750610640793"
					>https://doi.org/10.1108/10650750610640793</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Cobourn 2016" xml:id="cobourn2016">Cobourn, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
					>Spreading Awareness of Digital Preservation and Copyright Via Omeka-Based
					Projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Interactive Technology and
					Pedagogy</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/spreading-awareness-of-digital-preservation-and-copyright-via-omeka-based-projects/"
					>https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/spreading-awareness-of-digital-preservation-and-copyright-via-omeka-based-projects/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Library of Congress" xml:id="loc">Library of Congress (no date) <title
					rend="quotes">Creating Preservable Websites</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://www.loc.gov/programs/web-archiving/for-site-owners/creating-preservable-websites/"
					>https://www.loc.gov/programs/web-archiving/for-site-owners/creating-preservable-websites/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Conway 2010" xml:id="conway2010">Conway, P. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
					>Preservation in the Age of Google: Digitization, Digital Preservation, and
					Dilemmas</title>, <title rend="italic">The Library Quarterly</title>, 80(1), pp. 61–79.
					Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1086/648463"
					>https://doi.org/10.1086/648463</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Cummings 2020" xml:id="cummings2020">Cummings, J. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
					>Learning how to fail better: Resilience in Digital Humanities projects</title>, in <title
					rend="italic">Proceedings of the Centre for Data, Culture, and Society</title>, University
					of Edinburgh. Available at: <ref target="https://slides.com/jamescummings/cdcs2020/"
					>https://slides.com/jamescummings/cdcs2020/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Digital Preservation Coalition" xml:id="dpc">Digital Preservation Coalition.
					(2023) <title rend="italic">Digital Preservation Handbook, Glossary</title>. Available at:
					<ref target="https://www.dpconline.org/handbook/glossary"
					>https://www.dpconline.org/handbook/glossary</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Hunter and Choudhury 2003" xml:id="hunter_etal2003">Hunter, J. and Choudhury, S.
					(2003) <title rend="quotes">Implementing preservation strategies for complex multimedia
					objects</title>, in T. Koch and I.T. Sølvberg (eds) <title rend="italic">Research and
					Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries</title>, ECDL 2003: Lecture Notes in Computer
					Science, 2769. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer, pp. 473–486. Available at: <ref
					target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-45175-4_43"
					>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-45175-4_43</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Johnston 2013" xml:id="johnston2013">Johnston, L. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
					>Digital Humanities and Digital Preservation</title>, in <title rend="italic">The Signal,
					Library of Congress</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://blogs.loc.gov/thesignal/2013/04/digital-humanities-and-digital-preservation/"
					>https://blogs.loc.gov/thesignal/2013/04/digital-humanities-and-digital-preservation/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Kilbride 2015" xml:id="kilbride2015">Kilbride, W. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
					>Saving the Bits: Digital Humanities Forever?</title>, in S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and
					J. Unsworth (eds) <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. John
					Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, pp. 408–419. Available at: <ref
					target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch28"
					>https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch28</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Kirby 2019" xml:id="kirby2019">Kirby, J.S. (2019) <title rend="quotes">How NOT to
					Create a Digital Media Scholarship Platform: The History of the Sophie 2.0
					Project</title>, <title rend="italic">IASSIST Quarterly</title>, 42(4), pp. 1–16.
					Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.29173/iq926"
					>https://doi.org/10.29173/iq926</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Stanford University Libraries" xml:id="stanford">Stanford University Libraries.
					(no date) <title rend="quotes">Archivability</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://library.stanford.edu/projects/web-archiving/archivability"
					>https://library.stanford.edu/projects/web-archiving/archivability</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Maron and Pickle 2013" xml:id="maron_etal2013">Maron, N. and Pickle, S. (2013)
					<title rend="quotes">Sustaining our Digital Future: Institutional Strategies for Digital
					Content</title>, in <title rend="italic">Ithaka S+R</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="http://sr.ithaka.org?p=22547">http://sr.ithaka.org?p=22547</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Miller 2019" xml:id="miller2019">Miller, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Digital
					Project Preservation Plan: A Guide for Preserving Digital Humanities / Scholarship
					Projects</title>, in <title rend="italic">Middle Tennessee State University Digital
					Scholarship Initiatives Publications</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="http://jewlscholar.mtsu.edu/xmlui/handle/mtsu/5761"
					>http://jewlscholar.mtsu.edu/xmlui/handle/mtsu/5761</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Owens 2014" xml:id="owens2014">Owens, T. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Digital
					preservation’s place in the future of the digital humanities</title>, in <title
					rend="italic">Trevor Owens Personal Blog</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="http://www.trevorowens.org/2014/03/digital-preservations-place-in-the-future-of-the-digital-humanities"
					>http://www.trevorowens.org/2014/03/digital-preservations-place-in-the-future-of-the-digital-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Padilla et al 2020" xml:id="padilla_etal2020">Padilla, T. et al. (2020) <title
					rend="quotes">Always Already Computational: Collections as Data</title>, in <title
					rend="italic">Final report to Institute of Museum and Library Services</title>
					(LG-73-16-0096-16). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/MX6UK"
					>https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/MX6UK</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Rath 2016" xml:id="rath2016">Rath, L. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Omeka.net as a
					Librarian-Led Digital Humanities Meeting Place</title>, <title rend="italic">New Library
					World</title>, 117(3), pp. 158–172. Available at: <ref
					target="https://doi.org/10.1108/NLW-09-2015-0070"
					>https://doi.org/10.1108/NLW-09-2015-0070</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Ross 2012" xml:id="ross2012">Ross, S. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Digital
					Preservation, Archival Science and Methodological Foundations for Digital
					Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">New Review of Information Networking</title>,
					17(1), pp. 43–68. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13614576.2012.679446"
					>https://doi.org/10.1080/13614576.2012.679446</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Samberg and Reardon 2016" xml:id="samberg_etal2016">Samberg, R.G. and Reardon, S.
					(2016) <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities for Tomorrow: Open the Conversation about
					DH Project Preservation</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities at Berkely
					Blog</title>. </bibl>
				<bibl label="Serventi 2019" xml:id="serventi2019">Serventi, J. (2019) <title rend="italic"
					>Planning your next DHAG 3: Managing and Sustaining the Project Assets</title>. Available
					at: <ref
					target="https://www.neh.gov/blog/planning-your-next-dhag-3-managing-and-sustaining-project-assets"
					>https://www.neh.gov/blog/planning-your-next-dhag-3-managing-and-sustaining-project-assets</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Vinopal and McCormick 2013" xml:id="vinopal_etal2013">Vinopal, J. and McCormick,
					M. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Supporting Digital Scholarship in Research Libraries:
					Scalability and Sustainability</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Library
					Administration</title>, 53(1), pp. 27-42.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Vines et al 2013" xml:id="vines_etal2013">Vines, T.H., et al (2013) <title
					rend="quotes">Mandated Data Archiving Greatly Improves Access to Research Data</title>.
					<title rend="quotes">The FASEB Journal</title>, 27, pp.1304–1308.</bibl>
				<bibl label="Wilkinson et al 2016" xml:id="wilkinson_etal2016">Wilkinson, M. et al (2016)
					<title rend="quotes">The FAIR Guiding Principles for Scientific Data Management and
					Stewardship</title>, <title rend="italic">Scientific Data</title>, 3. Available at: <ref
					target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18"
					>https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</ref>.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
