<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and
               Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Franny <dhq:family>Gaede</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4482-8577</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oregon</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mfgaede@uoregon.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Franny Gaede (she/her/hers) is the Director of Digital Scholarship Services at
                     the University of Oregon. She provides leadership and support for digital
                     scholarship in teaching and research, digital collections, digital
                     preservation, scholarly communication, and library-led open access
                     publishing.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ana-Maurine <dhq:family>Lara</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oregon</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>amlara@uoregon.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara is an Associate Professor in the Department of Women’s,
                     Gender and Sexuality Studies at University of Oregon. An award winning
                     novelist, poet, and academic writer, her most recent books are Konjher Woman,
                     Streetwalking: LGBT Lives and Protest in the Dominican Republic and Queer
                     Freedom, Black Sovereignty.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Alaí <dhq:family>Reyes-Santos</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oregon</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alai@uoregon.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Alai Reyes-Santos is an independent scholar currently serving as the
                     Associate Director of the Mellon-funded PNW Just Futures Institute for Racial
                     and Climate Justice; a Professor of Practice at the University of Oregon School
                     of Law; and a consultant on equity, and social and environmental justice.
                     www.alaireyessantos.com</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Kate <dhq:family>Thornhill</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1096-6963</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oregon</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>kmthorn@uoregon.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Kate Thornhill (she/her/hers) is the Digital Scholarship Librarian at the
                     University of Oregon. Since 2013, her focus has been on developing and
                     sustaining digital services as a hybrid librarian, archivist, and web
                     technologist specializing in digital stewardship, digital repositories, and
                     digital humanities research and classroom projects.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000631</idno>
         	<idno type="volume"
         		><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
         	<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-07-22">22 July 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):
                  CC-BY:
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Black digital humanities</item>
                  <item>Caribbean</item>
                  <item>Digital archive</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-08" who="BRG">resolved encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p><title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within
                  Afro-Indigenous Traditions</title>, is a multi-year collaborative research
               co-produced by faculty and digital librarians and technical professionals from the
               University of Oregon Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS). This digital
               humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering
               deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human
               dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship. More
               specifically, <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> highlights how
               Afro-Indigenous (Black and Black-Indigenous) women elders mobilize their
               intergenerational knowledge and roles as healers, teachers, and community leaders
               within Caribbean healing traditions to effect change well beyond the traditional
               centers of those communities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>This interdisciplinary team placed the healers’ community at the center of the
               research project to publicly validate and share aspects of their knowledge with the
               healers, teachers, researchers, and students studying race, indigeneity,
               ethnobotanical medicinal healing, and intersectionality.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within
                  Afro-Indigenous Traditions</title>, is a multi-year collaborative research project
               developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by
               the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical
               professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department
               under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny
               Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.<note> To develop the first and second
                  phase of this project, we received funding and support from the University of
                  Oregon’s Center for the Study of Women and Society, the University of Oregon’s
                  Vice President’s Research Initiative Faculty Research Award, the University of
                  Oregon’s Center for Latin@ and Latin American Studies, and a fellowship from the
                  University of Oregon Libraries Digital Scholarship Center. We have worked under
                  the approval of the University of Oregon Human Subjects review committee since
                  2016.</note> This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital
               Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that
               prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data
               stewardship. More specifically, <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers
               </title>highlights how Afro-Indigenous (Black and Black-Indigenous) women elders
               mobilize their intergenerational knowledge and roles as healers, teachers, and
               community leaders within Caribbean healing traditions to effect change well beyond
               the traditional centers of those communities. </p>
            <p>In 2016, after four years of meeting and spending time with Caribbean women that keep
               their Afro-Indigenous, Indigenous and Afro-descendant healing traditions alive,
               Reyes-Santos and Lara were inspired to conceptualize a project that validates
               healers’ knowledge in a world where Eurocentric notions of health and medicine vilify
               and dismiss them. As healers and ceremonialists, themselves, Reyes-Santos and Lara’s
               journeys within Caribbean communities throughout the Dominican Republic, Cuba, Puerto
               Rico, and the U.S. Pacific Northwest region, seeks to interrogate and to interrupt
               the colonial gaze that historically vilifies and demeans our elders as
                  <q>uneducated,</q> or <q>simple,</q> or <q>primitive,</q> and that deems their
               knowledge simply <q>folklore,</q>
               <q>popular religion,</q> or <q>supersitition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As a space pushing back at these settler mentalities, <title rend="italic">Caribbean
                  Women Healers</title> documents Afro-Indigenous, Afro-descendant, and Indigenous
               healing within a TEK context that includes preserving food and medicine forests and
               gathering grounds, transmitting traditional food and medicine knowledge to others,
               caring for and treating their families, and members of their communities. Healing
               work includes attending to people who seek help with the health of their lands,
               plants, animals and human bodies. Healing entails attending to physical, emotional,
               psychological, social and spiritual dimensions of health and well-being. As such, the
               healers documented for this project also manage encyclopedic, communally-sustained
               knowledge of spiritual traditions kept alive in spite of colonial and nation-states’
               attempts to disappear and vilify them. The healing practices and ethnobotanical
               knowledge disseminated through this digital humanities project are legacies of
               survival strategies in the face of colonization and slavery, anti-Black racism, and
               anti-Indigenous genocidal practices. </p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> is informed by the positionality
               of its researchers, two Black-Indigenous women who are a third generation <term>curandera</term> and tradition keeper from Puerto Rico
               (Reyes-Santos) and a fifth generation <term>curandera</term> and
               tradition keeper from the Dominican Republic (Lara), both living in the Pacific Northwest.<note>
                  <term>Curandera</term> is a traditional healer. This is term used
                  throughout the Spanish-speaking Caribbean and Latin America to name women who heal
                  through traditional intuitive, spiritual, and ethnobotanical practices. It is
                  usually a role passed down across generations. A <term
                     >curandera</term> may be a priestess of <term>regla de
                     ocha</term>, a <term>servidora of la 21 division, </term>a
                     <term>sobadora</term>, or none of the above. <term>Regla de ocha, servidora of la 21 division, </term>and <term>sobadora</term> are ways to describe specific healing
                  traditions, tools, and sacred practices — and <term
                     >curanderas</term> may draw from many more. </note> The researchers’ own
               rootedness in relationships with elders and healers were central to the relationships
               that were developed prior to and will continue to be maintained after the project.
               The healer partnerships cultivated and traditional ecological knowledge documented by
               Reyes-Santos and Lara are represented by digital artifacts captured using sound,
               video, and photography. Taking lead responsibility for website conceptualization,
               writing and digital artifact creation, layout ideation, and conduit between the
               healers, Reyes-Santos’ and Lara’s direction positioned <title rend="italic">Caribbean
                  Women Healers</title> to be one for and about the healers’ traditional ecological
               knowledge. </p>
            <p>Core to the project’s digital development was DSS’ specialization in co-creating open
               digital humanities projects that center cultural awareness through web development
               and design, online privacy, open source and proprietary web application development
               and management, and data stewardship. The library research team included Thornhill as
               digital project manager; Gaede as project administrator; Anna Lepska as graduate
               student digital research assistant; Azle Malinao-Alvarez as the interactive
               technology consultant with support from digital collections and preservation expert
               Julia Simic, as well as Corey Gillen and Ray Henry, members of the UO Libraries’
               Library Technology Services department (now Applications Development and
               Integration). This library team will henceforth be referred to collectively as <q>the
                  builders</q> the authors of this paper <q>the authors,</q> and Reyes-Santos and
               Lara <q>the researchers.</q> This interdisciplinary team placed the healers’
               community at the center of the research project to publicly validate and share
               aspects of their knowledge with the healers, teachers, researchers, and students
               studying race, indigeneity, ethnobotanical medicinal healing, and
               intersectionality.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>History of the Project</head>
            <p>Since 2010, as Afro-Indigenous ceremonialists and scholars working in the fields of
               Black and Indigenous Studies, Reyes-Santos and Lara have collaborated in
               Afro-Indigenous survival and revitalization projects, ethnographic research projects,
               and on another digital project. They have spent the past eleven years travelling to
               Indigenous, Afro-descendant, and Afro-Indigenous ritual, healing, and ceremonial
               spaces in Mexico, the Dominican Republic, Cuba, Puerto Rico, and the United States.
               While participating in and collaborating with these spaces, they have become
               students, apprentices, and allies working with elders to continue disseminating and
               valorizing their traditional knowledge through visits, fundraising, workshops,
               ceremonies, and academic research. For instance, in 2012, Lara and Reyes-Santos
               fundraised and planned a visit of Mexica elders to sacred sites in the Dominican
               Republic, where they met Afro-Indigenous healers and ritual leaders; in 2012, the
               Black Feminist Retreat in the Dominican Republic brought together U.S.-based Black
               scholars and artists, and activists, cultural workers, and traditional ceremonialists
               living in the Dominican Republic; in 2015, they also organized a trip of Mexica and
               Mezcalero Apache elders to meet Cuban <title rend="italic">regla de ocha</title>
               communities in Havana. Both these events are examples of the kind of exchanges they
               have helped bring to fruition as efforts to disseminate and exchange traditional
               healing knowledge across Indigenous, Afro-descendant, and Afro-Indigenous communities
               in the Americas. </p>
            <p>They began to experiment with digital platforms as powerful tools to share
               information early on. In 2011 they interviewed Dominican feminist and queer activists
               on educational justice; Reyes-Santos edited short films documenting their
               experiences, and posted them to a YouTube channel. In 2017, Lara trained students in
               Reyes-Santos’ class in ethnographic methodologies to participate in a storytelling
               documentation trip in the wake of Hurricane Maria and create educational resources
               for the <ref target="https://blogs.uoregon.edu/theuopuertoricoproject/"> University
                  of Oregon Puerto Rico Project</ref>. Some students travelled to Puerto Rico with
               Reyes-Santos, took photos documenting the catastrophe and how people organized
               themselves as communities, and completed interviews with people affected by the
               Hurricane in mostly rural areas. A student team edited content and created a blog to
               educate people in the Pacific Northwest about Puerto Rico’s history and to
               disseminate the stories shared by people in the island.</p>
            <p>In 2018, the UO Libraries launched the DSS Faculty Grants Program. As an internal
               university award, UO faculty were eligible to apply for in-kind and budget support
               offered by DSS, and its sister library departments, for scholars to explore
               non-traditional and creative digital scholarship through either through a humanities,
               social science, or interdisciplinary lens. As a major strategic priority for the
               department, <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> was selected because
               of its innovative approach to raising the voices of historically marginalized and
               colonized voices. It was also selected because DSS wanted to explore the question,
                  <quote rend="inline">How might the sustainability of a digital project be
                  conceptualized from a standpoint that considers humanity as a social construction
                  and subject to change over time and place?</quote> <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>.</p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title>
               <ref target="https://healers.uoregon.edu/">WordPress site </ref>contains over 200
               photographs and interview clips with eight healers, highlighting various research
               sites and depicting biodiversity in botanical plant life in different micro-climates
               and ecological areas. The website gives context for how Reyes-Santos and Lara
               partnered with healers and how the healers’ knowledge and approaches to sharing
               influenced the research’s overall ethnographic practices. Additionally, the site
               includes a digital map highlighting research sites and an extensive bibliography that
               introduces a variety of texts that serve as an introduction to the study of
               Afro-Indigenous communities in the Caribbean, and their spiritual and traditional
               ecological knowledges. And on April 22, 2020, the website celebrated its launch with
               over 70 people in attendance globally virtually attending on Zoom.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Contextualizing <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers </title>in Black
               DH</head>
            <epigraph>
               <cit><quote rend="block">Openness is a concept that has come to characterize knowledge and
                  communication systems, epistemologies, society and politics, institutions or
                  organizations, and individual personalities. In essence, openness in all these
                  dimensions refers to a kind of transparency which is the opposite of secrecy and
                  most often this transparency is seen in terms of access to information especially
                  within organizations, institutions or societies. </quote>
               <ptr target="#peters2015"/></cit>
            </epigraph>
            <p>In order to allow democratic collaboration, co-design, co-creation, co-management,
               and co-evaluation through the Internet, openness emphasizes free, transparent, and
               unrestricted access to knowledge and information. Within the digital humanities,
               openness situates scholars to be self-aware and confront socio-technologic and
               economic frameworks that influence their research and teaching practices. </p>
            <p>As digital cultural heritage materials have become more common online, in large part
               thanks to funding through private and grant funding agencies and foundations (e.g.
               The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, National Endowment for the Humanities, and Institute
               of Library and Information Science), openness has become a norm for those working in
               custodial <ptr target="#sas2021"/> and post-custodial <ptr target="#sas2021b"/>
               digital stewardship <ptr target="#sas2021c"/>. </p>
            <p>The relationships between openness, data, digital technologies, and Black and
               Indigenous studies demonstrate how digital technologies and data privilege white
               Western cultural traditions and power systems that systematically oppress human
               beings, societies, and cultures through violence, genocide, racism, and
                  enslavement.<ptr target="#gallon2016"/>
               <ptr target="#lothian2013"/>
               <ptr target="#risam2016"/>
               <ptr target="#christen2019"/>. The rejection of those oppressive traditions and power
               systems have given rise to a number of Black Digital Humanities archival projects
               that curate and provide public access to documents, maps, and other historical,
               material and textual materials. <ref target="http://carisealand.org/"><title
                     rend="italic">The Caribbean Sea &amp; Land Project</title></ref> demonstrates
               the relevance of mapping and sharing historical and cultural information in
               accessible and interactive formats, specifically when engaging Black and Indigenous
               Caribbean populations. It incorporates a digital map to share geographical and
               historical information about different islands in the Eastern Caribbean. <ref
                  target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/"><title rend="italic">Slave
                  Voyages</title></ref>; <ref
                  target="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/black-history/"><title rend="italic"
                     >Black British History on Record</title></ref>; <title rend="italic"><ref
                     target="http://firstblacks.org/en/">First Blacks in the Americas</ref></title>;
               and the <title rend="italic"><ref target="https://ecda.northeastern.edu/">Early
                     Caribbean Digital Archive</ref></title>, among others, illustrate how
               geographies and public access to historical records play a central role in Black DH
               practices.</p>
            <p>The diasporic and transnational realities of Black communities, and the legacy of
               slavery and the Middle Passage, present those of us in the Black DH with
               opportunities to create platforms that represent transcolonial and transnational
               realities beyond textual representation, while incorporating different communities
               and learning styles. <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> joins in
               the oral digital storytelling practices that characterizes projects such as <title
                  rend="italic"><ref target="https://www.noneonrecord.com/">None on Record;
                  </ref></title> <title rend="italic"><ref
                     target="http://exhibitions.nypl.org/africansindianocean/index2.php">African
                     Diaspora in the Indian Ocean World</ref></title>; and <title rend="italic">
                  <ref target="https://crbb.tcu.edu/">Civil Rights in Black &amp;
                  Brown</ref></title>; and initiatives like the <title rend="italic"><ref
                     target="http://www.caribbeanmemoryproject.com/explore.html#/"> Caribbean Memory
                     Project</ref></title> that foster public participation and co-creation of
               digital archives by Caribbean people.</p>
            <p>Aligned with these Black DH projects, and as scholars who seek to work in the open,
               we seek to apply decolonizing methodologies connected to the ontologies of openness:
               access, transparency, collaboration, sharing, accessibility, and the choice of
               permanence. <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> frames humanity
               within the context of historical colonial violence and the oppression of
               Afro-Indigenous people. It subverts the colonial gaze by giving respect, space, and
               validation for TEK through its imagery, interviews, and bilingual nature. A core
               attribute of this digital project is its approach to the openness of sharing and
               documenting TEK. This project’s knowledge work is rooted in authors’ participatory
               ethnographic documentary, Black Feminist, and open decolonization methodologies for
               working with TEK.</p>
            <p> For the authors, this means centering participant’s dignity and cultural practices,
               and rejecting white, Western settler supremacy ways of being. Ownership and custody
               of digital technologies and digital cultural heritage is a core issue for how the
               authors operated throughout the project as researchers and builders. The work of Kim
               Christen <ptr target="#christen2012"/>
               <ptr target="#christen2019"/>, Christen with Jane Anderson <ptr
                  target="#anderson2019"/>, and Trevor Reed <ptr target="#reed2021"/><ptr
                  target="#reed2021b"/><ptr target="#reed2021c"/> offer directions for open
               engagement within an ethics of care <ptr target="#caswell2016"/><ptr
                  target="#archer2017"/> and participatory cultural heritage collecting frameworks
                  <ptr target="#gilliland2014"/><ptr target="#allard2015"/>
               <ptr target="#mccracken2015"/>
               <ptr target="#earhart2016"/>
               <ptr target="#becerralicha2017"/><ptr target="#benoit2019"/> foregrounding the
               cultural underpinnings and politics regarding indigenous knowledge and sovereignty.
               Centering the healer community's individual choice, cultural access protocols, and
               applying their own deep listening practices was the highest priority.</p>
            <p>Reyes-Santos and Lara’s emphasis on Afro-Indigenous narratives honors the historical
               reality of <emph>palenques</emph> and <emph
                  >manieles</emph>, sovereign communities where Indigenous and African peoples came
               together in freedom; where Indigenous peoples shared herbal, medicinal knowledge with
               recently arrived Africans; where African communities shared their ancestral healing
               and ceremonial knowledges, and found ways to retain their traditions far away from
               home; where Indigenous and African peoples came together in kin relations and treaty
               building. Their methodology honors the Afro-Indigenous paths of resistance that have
               enabled the maintenance and dissemination of traditional healing practices and
               ecological knowledge for 528 years. The healers featured in <title rend="italic"
                  >Caribbean Women Healers </title>are steeped in these histories and the traditions
               born out of them. The methodologies used for this project enabled this to come into
               being, and how, specifically, these methodologies and website contribute to breaking
               down the marginalization of Black Digital Humanities. <ptr target="#gallon2016"/></p>
            <p>As Afro-Indigenous communities gain visibility, this project initiates what must be a
               broader dialogue in Black DH about what it means to bridge the concerns of Black and
               Indigenous methodologies and community needs in the U.S. and internationally for the
               successful implementation of open scholarship projects. It foregrounds Black Feminist
               DH practice deeply informed by Indigenous decolonial methodologies for
               community-based research applied to the digital sphere. The methodological approach
               to the stories and ethnobotanical resources shared on the site and digital
               stewardship techniques draw from the norms for social interactions and information
               sharing exemplified by the healers themselves, as well as healers’ intentions.</p>
            <p>The project was always meant to be open, shared beyond the healer and scholarly
               communities from whence it came. It has been motivated by the needs and desires of
               the healers themselves. All community participants were excited and saw a need to
               make traditional knowledge available through new technologies. Rather than see the
               Internet as a hindrance to their world and belief systems, they articulated an
               understanding that presenting their work and knowledge to the world was a way to
               safeguard them and their knowledge. Healers, like the Cuban-American <title
                  rend="italic">Iyalocha</title> Jannes Martínez, were specific in their critique of
               what they saw as decontextualized traditional knowledge permeating the Internet.
               Technological access acts as a supplement to relationship and practice. As Jannes
               stated in her interview with Reyes-Santos and Lara, <quote rend="inline">Reading something on the
               internet doesn’t mean you know it and understand it.</quote></p>
            <p>Many of those who participated, in particular those from Puerto Rico and those living
               in rural areas in the Dominican Republic, stated there has been a rupture to
               traditional forms of knowledge transmission and production. They theorize that these
               ruptures are produced by three primary factors: </p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>social violence that produces early death, expressed in the saying, “la muerte
                  es parte de la vida” (death is a part of life); </item>
               <item>rapid emigration from their communities to urban centers and to other countries
                  expressed in the statement “el campo se está vaciando” (the countryside is being
                  emptied); </item>
               <item>fundamentalist Christian religious social values and norms that demonize
                  Afro-Indigenous/Black traditions and practices. </item>
            </list>
            <p>Their theories speak to scholarly findings in the field of Black Studies and
               Reyes-Santos and Lara’s engagement with the field. Reyes-Santos and Lara understand
               that the social violences discussed by healers as the reason behind “early death” are
               an extension of colonial-modern state policies that fail to produce the conditions
               for sustaining Black life, as well as colonial-modern ideas about race, gender and
               sexuality that foster the punishment of gender and sexual difference, and the
               devaluation of Blackness. (Wynter 2003) Neoliberal economic policies and state
               participation in globalized capitalism have contributed to rapid urban migration and
               emigration to Latin America, Europe and North America that have left rural areas
               depopulated and/or disenfranchised, and elders caring for land and knowledge on their
               own <ptr target="#reyessantos2015"/> <ptr target="#thomas2013"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Ethnographic and historical research by Lara documents that Christian colonial
               violence leads to the ongoing ostracization of traditional healers, the demonization
               of Afro-Indigenous practices and traditions, the dismantling of altars and the
               destruction of sacred sites <ptr target="#lara2020"/>. Even with all of these
               obstacles, and perhaps because of them, healers expressed the need to continue
               transmitting knowledge to their families, communities and future generations. That
               impulse has shaped this project from beginning to end. Moreover, the fact that both
               Reyes-Santos and Lara are themselves Afro-Indigenous Caribbean healers and keepers of
               traditional ceremonies opened up spaces for connection with elders, for sharing and
               meeting healers in ceremony, and understanding the worldviews articulated by the
               healers in multiple Caribbean traditions. Often, once Reyes-Santos and Lara were
               recognized as healers and ceremonialists, a deeper conversation ensued with
               interviewees.</p>
            <p>As stated by Winona LaDuke, <quote rend="inline">Traditional ecological knowledge is
                  the culturally and spiritually based way in which Indigenous peoples relate to
                  their ecosystems.</quote> Here we highlight how Afro-descendant and
               Afro-Indigenous communities have a wealth of resources to contribute to TEK in the
               Americas. Our Black Feminist DH approach required that the authors be willing to be
               transformed by the people Reyes-Santos and Lara were honoring in the documentation
               process; Reyes-Santos and Lara had to be open to transform how they imagined the
               work, how at times they were trained to undertake this kind of endeavor. The
               researchers centered Black/Afro-descendant women and queer healers’ voices and ways
               of knowing, while destabilizing colonial distinctions between researchers and
               research subjects <ptr target="#mclaurin2001"/>.
               <ptr target="#simmons2001"/> The authors had to become research subjects as well; all
               of us from our specific social and academic location observing how we responded to
               systems of knowledge that have historically been rendered invalid in academic
               setting: Black, Indigenous, female, queer, healer, oral, collective. </p>
            <p>Healers, researchers, and builders were engaged in a collaborative process of
               knowledge production to together imagine what would be the best ways of representing
               the information on the website. We privileged oral transmission of knowledge over
               archives while still providing access to relevant archival projects, scholarship,
               creative work, and educational tools. We recognized the orality that characterizes
               interactions with healers and the relevance of sustaining oral traditions in the
               contemporary moment; specifically, honoring how women and queer people have
               maintained traditional ecological and medicinal knowledge alive while facing high
               levels of social vulnerability and violence whether in the Caribbean or the U.S.</p>
            <p>As articulated by Moya Bailey, <quote rend="inline">The ways in which identities
                  inform both theory and practice in digital humanities have been largely
                  overlooked. Those already marginalized in society and the academy can also find
                  themselves in the liminal spaces of this field. By centering the lives of women,
                  people of color, and disabled folks, the types of possible conversations
                  in digital humanities shift. The move “<ref
                     target="http://www.charisbooksandmore.com/book/9780896086135">from margin to
                     center</ref>” offers the opportunity to engage new sets of theoretical
                  questions that expose implicit assumptions about what and who counts in digital
                  humanities as well as exposes structural limitations that are the inevitable
                  result of an unexamined identity politics of whiteness, masculinity, and
                  ablebodiness</quote> <ptr target="#bailey2011"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Participatory Methodology &amp; Decolonizing the Digital</head>
            <div>
               <head>Healer Community-Centric Methodology and Their Impact on the Project</head>
               <p>This research project provides a powerful counterpoint to the context in which
                  Afro-Indigenous traditions are being maintained and practiced. The aforementioned
                  dynamics not only generate interruptions in inter-generational transmission of
                  traditional ecological and spiritual knowledges. They are also reflective of a
                  socio-political context in which Afro-Indigenous traditions and ways of knowing
                  are marginalized. As the <term>campos</term>, the countryside,
                  <q>empty out,</q> traditional land bases and community spaces are increasingly
                  threatened. As economic marginalization increases, Black people, Afro-Indigenous
                  healers have to become even more creative in figuring out ways to gather the
                  medicines that they need, collect the materials for their offerings, and develop
                  paths to find each other.</p>
               <p>Very much aligned with Reyes-Santos and Lara’s approaches to working with the
                  healers, the authors’ awareness of socio-political sensitivities heavily
                  influenced the digital treatments of spoken word, portraits, plant location data,
                  Internet access, and website design worked to not reinforce the harms brought upon
                  Afro-Indigenous communities. Together, healer, researcher, and builder
                  methodologies sought to subvert the western-centric approach to using digital
                  tools for tools and innovations and putting something on the Internet for the sake
                  of making information publicly available. It was important for the authors to
                  always ask questions of the community regarding access, transparency,
                  collaboration, sharing, accessibility, and the choice of permanence. Ultimately,
                  the authors’ approach first foregrounded permission and consent knowing that not
                  all information should be free and open. Centering the healer community's
                  individual choice and cultural access protocols was their first priority.</p>
               <p>Beginning in 2016, Reyes-Santos and Lara conducted interviews with women healers
                  in rural and urban communities in the Dominican Republic, the Pacific Northwest,
                  Cuba and Puerto Rico. In these interviews, they focused on the world views of
                  their elders. Their research approaches were (and continue to be) grounded in a
                  critical Indigenous approach <ptr target="#smith2011"/>
                  <ptr target="#cole2001"/> whereby the elders determined the parameters of shared
                  knowledge, and in conjunction with us, determined the kinds of questions and
                  methods by which those questions would be answered. This approach was not only
                  critical, it was absolutely required. As younger women engaged in respectful
                  relation with elders, Reyes-Santos and Lara could open the possibility of
                  conversation, but the elders were the ones who would determine what it was that
                  Reyes-Santos and Lara should, could and needed to know. </p>
               <p>Critically engaged methods include the collection of oral histories,<ptr
                     target="#smith2011"/> observant participation, <ptr target="#campbell2014"/> and
                  transparent data collection <ptr target="#smith2011"/>
                  <ptr target="#simpson2014"/> in ways that prioritized the locations and points of
                  views of their elders. Gathering this knowledge took place in the midst of healing
                  sessions, at family gatherings, hanging out in peoples’ patios, at the dinner
                  table, at dance parties, hiking, resting, and just spending time together, <term>compartiendo</term>. They spoke with <term>regla
                     de ocha</term> priestesses, <term>servidoras of la 21
                     división</term>, <term>sobadoras</term>, and other healers
                  drawing from their Indigenous and Afro-descendant ancestral knowledge; women they
                  have met while dancing at the rhythm of Caribbean batá or atabales drums, or just
                  walking down the street in a place that was new to them. Reyes-Santos and Lara
                  were also attentive to including queer/two-spirit healers living in the Diaspora,
                  whose own geographies include healing communities in the U.S. and the Caribbean. </p>
               <p>These initial methods soon transformed into a practice of deep listening. The
                  first thing Reyes-Santos and Lara were taught was deep listening. Over the last
                  decade, they have learned to understand deep listening as a practice that is
                  central to the pedagogical methods of Caribbean religious traditions. It involves
                  listening with the whole body, to what is articulated and unarticulated, and
                  paying attention to what is seen and not seen. Deep listening is about observing
                  collective ritual behaviors and the utterances that take place between people. To
                  listen deeply is to be a part of, extending beyond ethnographic participant
                  observation and into the realm of being in loving community. To listen deeply is
                  to listen to dreams, to listen to <quote rend="inline">the counsel of spirits and
                     ancestors,</quote> to dance to music, and to be present to the ups and downs of
                  their elders’ (and their families’) lives. </p>
               <p>Deep listening changed Reyes-Santos and Lara as researchers because it changed
                  their orientations to <q>being,</q> to space-time, and to their own relations. It
                  required prioritizing recording the conversation in the format most comfortable to
                  the healers; to undertake interviews healers with husbands, children, neighbors,
                  or patients around us or while on a hike through a forest in the middle of a hot
                  tropical morning. Deep listening is about being embedded in everyday living, to
                  listen to the cacophony of voices, noises, landscapes where healing takes place.
                  Beyond the initial interview, Reyes-Santos and Lara were kept accountable to this
                  practice by continued check-ins and visits with healers. Their relationships
                  transcend the timeline of the project.</p>
               <p>By engaging in a practice of deep listening, Reyes-Santos and Lara first learned
                  that all of the elders have unique and powerful understandings of the divine,
                  known variously as Bondieu, Papa Dios, Olofi, Ometeotl and Gran Espíritu. They
                  learned about the unspoken understandings of elders’ relationships to ancestors
                  and to all living beings, which are the primary sites for healing. They learned
                  about the parameters of what is considered <q>alive</q> and <q>dead</q> (e.g. all of
                  existence is alive, but plastic is dead). They learned about the context in which
                  life is prolonged and death is accepted — or not. They learned about how current
                  economic, political and social conditions are understood in relationship to the
                  prolongation and/or decimation of the lives of elders, their families, their
                  communities, and the land itself. They learned that in different traditions
                  healing is directed either towards the prolongation of life or toward the aversion
                  of death. These distinct orientations translate into relationships with the plant
                  world, relationships with the spirit and ancestral worlds, and relationships to
                  living, breathing human beings.</p>
               <p>In addition to deeply listening, Reyes-Santos and Lara also walked. Miriam Ricourt
                  describes walking as a practice of disruption and meaning-making that was and
                  continues to be a central praxis of maroon peoples (<term
                     >cimarrones</term>). Walking was critical to their understanding of elders’
                  worlds. They walked with them through their communities, as seen in Figure 1,
                  through their forests, within their churches, homes, and ceremonial grounds.
                  Walking together, and being together in walking, allowed all present to assert our
                  mutual humanity (everyone was hot) and limitations (when one person got tired —
                  usually Reyes-Santos or Lara, much to the amusement of those who could keep
                  going). Walking together allowed Reyes-Santos and Lara to understand how elders
                  move through space and why. Walking enabled Reyes-Santos and Lara to understand
                  the elders’ specific geographies — the trees, plants, and places where they make
                  meaning on an on-going basis, the ways they tended these spaces, and the sense of
                  loss that is an increasing part of the human experience in the face of rapid
                  climate change. In walking together, Reyes-Santos photographed plants, groups of
                  plants, and Lara asked questions that prompted stories about specific places. </p>
              
               <figure>
                  <head>Walking together through town. Ana and Eugenia on their way to visit
                     with women elders from Eugenia’s community.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/Figure01.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Picture of two people walking down a sidewalk with trees on the left side</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>There were stories of disappeared species, of disappeared peoples, of new
                  constructions and new economic forces. There were stories of successful healings
                  and of challenging circumstances. There were stories of plants transplanted and of
                  the spirits who lived among them. All of this was possible to learn when they
                  walked together. </p>
               <p>Deep listening and walking required Reyes-Santos and Lara to shift their emphasis
                  from video clips in the original prospectus to audio clips that are not clear of
                  contextual noise. The microphone often created an uncomfortable situation in
                  spaces where knowledge is mostly produced through communal conversation,
                  questions, and interactions with the human world and plants. Most of the women
                  interviewed did not feel comfortable being recorded on video and shared their most
                  insightful stories while receiving patients or taking a stroll to show specific
                  plants. </p>
               <p>To produce a website with equal representation, Reyes-Santos and Lara decided to
                  privilege audio over video to share information. Audio clips are short and speak
                  to specific, relevant themes. They worked with an editor who was asked to leave
                  contextual noise in the recordings to enable the listener to understand what it
                  was like to be in conversation with the healer in their everyday practice and
                  subtly convey the context. Reyes-Santos and Lara are not documentary filmmakers
                  and were aware they were not seeking to produce documentary-quality material. They
                  were documenting some of the wealth of knowledge they have received over the years
                  from elders and share that knowledge respectfully with others seeking to value it,
                  research it, and connect with it. The material on the website allows us all to
                  reflect on how we have come to construe knowledge in the Americas and what our
                  elders have to offer as humanity approaches a variety of social and environmental
                  challenges.</p>
               <p>Working with elders in a transparent way that honors the sacrifices they continue
                  to make to sustain their knowledge means that everything presented on the website
                  has been discussed with them. Reyes-Santos and Lara printed photographs, shared
                  audio clips and received the authorization to continue not just from the elders,
                  but also from the guardian spirits that guide them. This multi-layered process of
                  knowledge ratification extends beyond the ethical boundaries of university human
                  subjects committees and is directly and permanently rooted in the ethical
                  parameters of Afro-Indigenous traditions themselves. </p>
               <p>Researching within and with traditional ceremonial and healing communities carries
                  with it the ethical obligation to not only cause no harm, but the additional
                  ethical obligation of honoring the self-determination and affective and spiritual
                  priorities of Afro-Indigenous communities. Reyes-Santos and Lara presented these
                  values in a slide show format in the website. Together, these values articulate a
                  different set of ethical values underlying community engaged digital humanities
                  scholarship. These values place Black voices, ways of knowing, ways of being and
                  ways of teaching front and center within the digital sphere, rupturing <quote
                     rend="inline"> implicit assumptions about what and who counts in digital
                     humanities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bailey2011"/>. The values that undergird an ethical code of conduct
                  among the healers included in the project are: </p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item><q>Antes que todo, Dios. (Gracias a la Misericordia)</q>: Humility
                     before Creation, and all beings – human, plant and animal – are a manifestation
                     of Creation </item>
                  <item><q>Todo Vive.</q>: All of Earth is alive; All of Earth is
                     life.</item>
                  <item><q>Moyumba/Ancestros</q>: To honor ancestors and elders and all
                     those who have come before us. </item>
                  <item><q>Obedi ka ka, obedi le le.</q>: Knowldege was shared throughout
                     the world.</item>
                  <item><q>Convivir.</q>: To be in relation with each other across a long
                     span of time.</item>
                  <item><q>Compartir.</q>: To generate intimacy and authenticity in our
                     relations through storytelling, laughter, sitting together, eating together,
                     etc.</item>
                  <item><q>Cara a Cara.</q>: To see each other’s faces, to know the truth of
                     our experiences in each other’s gazes/eyes/faces</item>
                  <item><q>Ser generosa.</q>: To never arrive empty handed, to never let
                     someone leave empty handed, either.</item>
                  <item><q>Ser recíproca.</q>: Enabling balance in the universe between all
                     living beings, material and immaterial, even in the creation of
                     knowledge.</item>
                  <item><q>Hay que fluir.</q>: To be flexible and easy-going in the rhythms
                     of life’s chaos and unexpected events. </item>
               </list>
               <p>From the beginning Reyes-Santos and Lara knew that they wanted <title
                     rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers </title>to be primarily used as a site of
                  knowledge production and transfer for practitioners, students, and the general
                  public. They wanted it to be a place for the provision of resources and to
                  function as a teaching tool. Construction of the digital project formally started
                  at the beginning of the 2019-2020 academic year with the goal of launch on Earth
                  Day 2020. Collaboratively the project builders helped address digital technology
                  platforms and we began conversations about web design and digital assets
                  management and its representation, with an emphasis on the protection of community
                  as part of open digital practice. Because the researchers wanted to create a
                  multimodal digital research project, the builders listened to the researchers
                  speak about their ideas and aspirations, interviewing them on questions of visual
                  design, ownership, and digital content representation. This gave the builders a
                  sense of what types of website user interactions and reader experiences were to be
                  anticipated while navigating the website. Throughout the conversations, the
                  builders were able to help prioritize target audiences while also learning about
                  what types of digital assets were being created with and for healer stories, and
                  how Reyes and Lara wanted users to experience text, audio, images, and geographic
                  space. </p>
               <p>The questions asked by the builders (Appendix A) helped to inform approaches to
                  the overall digital stewardship and web development approach to the project. By
                  applying these questions that were inspired by National Endowment for the
                  Humanities recommendations for data management plan <ptr target="#neh2018"/>, user
                  interactions and collections management for ethnographic archives, <ptr
                     target="#punzalan2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#christen2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#christen2019"/>, and web accessibility standards to support people
                  with disabilities and cultural awareness <ptr target="#wwwc2020"/> <ptr
                     target="#williams2012"/>, the answers helped determine what would be the best
                  socio-technical infrastructure for the digital project’s future sustainability.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Understanding the Technology in Use</head>
               <p>The technologies used to build <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers
                  </title>were selected based on the builders’ collective professional experiences
                  developing and managing digital library and archival services and public
                  humanities projects within higher education and expertise in cultural heritage
                  digital stewardship. Throughout the project, the builders approached construction
                  to prioritize cultural needs, web accessibility, and long-term social-technologic
                  sustainability framed within a digital assets and software preservation context, a
                  framing that requires constant digital curation and software monitoring. They
                  needed to balance technology selection and choices in methodologies that would
                  align with the values of the project as well as ones that allowed a small build
                  team to manage the project without fear of losing platform technical support
                  beyond their capabilities. Another requirement was robust user support
                  documentation for all digital tools so researchers could continue maintenance if
                  the builders were no longer available.</p>
               <p>At the University of Oregon, WordPress and the premium theme Divi are available as
                  a Software as a Service enterprise technology solution through the vendor
                  CampusPress. The project’s digital assets and written content representation,
                  usability, and arrangement, flexibility for responsive web design and visual
                  design, and the ability to have interactive media embedded in the site were
                  foundational technical requirements. The batch upload and extraction of embedded
                  descriptive metadata from digital images were important for digital project
                  workflows and possible in WordPress. The platform also needed to allow for embed
                  streaming audio-visual assets hosted on a third-party streaming media service, and
                  store at least 1 GB of data. The UO’s campus agreement with CampusPress meant the
                  digital technologies were vetted by the university for ADA-compliance (WCAG 2.0
                  Level AA) and other campus privacy and security records requirements. WordPress is
                  commonly used by the DH community <ptr target="#digitalhumanitiesintiative2020"
                     /> <ptr target="#coble2021"/> <ptr target="#dirt2018"/>, and the research team
                  had experience using it. Divi has a number of accessibility tools built-in and
                  this set-up is compatible with the toolkit we use to build and evaluate projects,
                  including the Accessible Color Palette Builder, the WAVE web accessibility
                  evaluation tool, and Toltap Colorblind Web Page Filter. </p>
               <p>Interviews for <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers </title>are hosted on
                  the streaming media service Panopto. Like WordPress, this tool was vetted by the
                  University for ADA-compliance and other privacy and security requirements. For the
                  project, we required robust sharing and permission access controls, as well as the
                  ability to make transcripts and captions available. Using Panopto, the builders
                  created embed codes so the interviews could be embedded in iframes on the website.
                  The builders also added ADA-compliant PDF transcriptions and translations, as well
                  as closed captions in .srt files. In Figure 2, you can see a screenshot of a
                  healer interview playing in Panopto with translated closed captions, a
                  transcription, and interactive timestamps.</p>
      

               <figure>
                  <head>Screenshot of a healer interview playing through Panopto with closed
                     captions, a transcription, and interactive timestamps.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/Figure02.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of Panopto with transcriptions on the left side and on the right side a document that says "Caribbean Women Healers"</figDesc>
               </figure>

               <p>The map requirements for this project included the ability to embed it within the
                  project site and have the ability to operate like a tour and simulation of moving
                  from one country, as seen in Figure 3, Cuba, to another – a rupture to the borders
                  produced through our modern nation-states. The tool also allowed builders to make
                  web accessibility modifications for universal user experience using the HTML tags.
                  At the time of the build, StoryMapsJS hosted by the Northwestern University Knight
                  Lab met this requirement.</p>

               
               <figure>
                  <head>Screenshot of the StoryMapJS digital map representing Cuba</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/Figure03.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of a map of Cuba. On the right side is an image of Cuba with writing describing Cuba</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
               
               <p>The digital assets created for this research project included audio files, digital
                  images, and textual documents. All digital files and metadata associated with them
                  required specific tools for creation, manipulation, file interoperability, and
                  ability to meet digital preservation standards supported by the United States
                  National Archives and Records Administration.<ptr target="#nationalarchives2019"/>
                  Beginning with the audio files, Audacity was used for editing the healers’
                  full-length interviews and conversion into .mp3 files. Adobe Photoshop and Bridge
                  were used for resizing and reformatting of JPGs. They were also used to embed
                  photographic descriptive metadata aligned with IPTC and DublinCore standards.
                  Additionally for digital images, EXIF Tool was used to analyze and extract
                  embedded technical metadata before making them web ready and available on the
                  project site. Microsoft Word and Adobe Acrobat Pro were used to create
                  ADA-compliance PDFs of interview transcriptions and translations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Open Digital Stewardship as Methodology Supporting Decolonization</head>
               <p>Digital stewardship, also called data stewardship, is framed within a research
                  data management and archival context it is the creation and management of digital
                  objects over a lifecycle involving the creation, appraisal and selection, ingest,
                  preservation actions, digital storage, access and reuse, and transformation
                  (Digital Curation Centre 2021). Rooted in library and archival information science
                  practice, digital stewardship calls for digital practitioners to curate and
                  preserve digital files, and the metadata or information that gives said files
                  context and meaning, with the goal of long-term access and on-going preservation
                  planning that avoids technological obsolescence. Traditionally applied only to
                  digital asset management or research data management spaces, digital stewardship
                  can extend to the software access and preservation with the goal of supporting
                  organizational decision practices associated with the development, maintenance,
                  and preservation of technological infrastructures <ptr target="#spn2021"/>. Digital
                  stewardship at its core works to avoid and prevent information loss while making
                  sure digital assets and software are FAIR (findable, accessible, interoperable,
                  and reusable) <ptr target="#gofair2021"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers </title>is an example of applying
                     decolonizing methodologies to approaches in digital stewardship. The
                     documentary of cultural heritage and spiritual practices situated the research
                     team to be self-aware and confront western centric socio-technologic and
                     economic frameworks that influenced how they applied digital methodologies to
                     the project’s digital design, construction, and the treatment of traditional
                     ecological knowledge and indigenous healers' voices. Calling back to the
                     ontologies of openness; access, transparency, collaboration, sharing,
                     accessibility, and the choice of permanence all have place within the
                     decolonization of traditional digital stewardship practices rooted in
                     traditional archival custodial practices. </p>
                  <p>The central frame for the research team’s work is to center the dignity and
                     respect the cultural practices of the people with whom they are working. Toward
                     that goal, the team worked to maintain transparency with each other and asked
                     what can be difficult questions regarding access, collaboration, sharing,
                     accessibility, and the choice of permanence. </p>
                  <p>Speaking first to transparency, it was important to acknowledge the white
                     hegemony of academia, libraries, and the digital space, and the potential for
                     intellectual violence when white researchers enter the Black research space.
                     Within the team, we sought to forestall this by centering the healers, the
                     researchers, their voices, methodologies, and the values shared. We also
                     maintained a regular meeting schedule to continue to discuss all aspects of
                     site design and implementation as wireframes and interactive prototypes were
                     created. Throughout this collaborative process, issues regarding the site’s
                     overall layout, navigation, and missed pages and content were remediated
                     together.</p>
                  <p>Access connects to intellectual property ownership and custody, readability and
                     interpretations within cultural contexts, and public access to the project.
                     Designing <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers </title>to be freely
                     available for anyone to access over the Internet meant critically thinking
                     about the impact access to TEK would have on the healers and website visitors.
                     As a research team, it was always the goal to make the website available for
                     educational use and give space for sharing healer knowledge. Creative Commons
                     was discussed, but determined not to be appropriate because the researchers and
                     community only wanted information to be permitted in an educational environment
                     all the while retaining their copyright to the digital assets and project as a
                     whole. Together the team selected RightsStatements.org “In Copyright -
                     Educational Use Permitted”. It is not intended for licensing, but captures the
                     researchers’ intention and the agreement with the healers, as well as being
                     reader-friendly as opposed to intense legal-ese or complicated rights holder
                     statements.</p>
                  <p>These examples associated with access are also ones of collaboration, another
                     tenant of openness. The project team worked by respecting each other's
                     expertise and centering collaboration with the community, asking many questions
                     and prioritizing culturally aware and accessible design that could only be
                     planned, built, and maintained with the support and expertise of the full
                     interdisciplinary team. In supporting the web design for cultural awareness,
                     Reyes-Santos and Lara discussed with the building team what colors, symbols,
                     and visual characteristics were appropriate and which could not be used, such
                     as the color red. Using these guidelines, Malinao-Alvarez and Thornhill worked
                     together to create an accessibility-compliant color palette and style guide, as
                     seen in Figure 4, to shape the feel of the site. </p>

               
               <figure>
                  <head>Caribbean Women Healers Project style guide</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/Figure04.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of the project's style guide. The image is an example of the style guide with headers and paragraphs outlined </figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
               
                  <p>Ensuring Spanish access to the website was critical because the majority of
                     healers are monolingual Spanish speakers, and similarly, a major audience for
                     the website was the English-speaking student body of the University of Oregon
                     for whom we would need to transcribe and translate the healers’ Spanish
                     language knowledge and interviews. </p>
                  <p>For both groups, it is important for them to hear the words used by the
                     communities themselves to name the plants they use for healing; to have their
                     plant knowledge validated throughout the site and for others to learn such
                     names. This was a major reason why the research team declined to use the Latin
                     scientific or English terms for the plants. The sixteen interview clips on the
                     website were selected and edited from full-length interviews, first by
                     undergraduate research assistant Miguel Perez and then by Thornhill after Perez
                     needed to leave the project. When artificial intelligence captioning services
                     from Panopto and Zoom proved unable to provide Spanish transcriptions for the
                     edited clips, first Perez, then Thornhill created transcriptions, which we
                     contracted with Rev.com for English translations. After having graduate
                     assistant Lepska, Reyes-Santos, and Lara review these translations for quality
                     assurance, future transcriptions and translations were performed by
                     Transcription Outsourcing LLC. Reyes-Santos and Lara continued to review
                     translations for accuracy before anything was made available on the site.</p>
                  <p>The careful curation of shared knowledge was a major task for the research
                     team, selecting what was appropriate to be shared openly and online and what
                     was for the healer community alone. The choice of open or closed access remains
                     with the community; these collections did not become part of the Libraries’
                     collections, nor are the healer interviews available to be downloaded through
                     Panopto. One area that this was particularly acute was in the creation of the
                     digital map and the latitude and longitude associated with the photographs of
                     plants taken in association with a planned ethnobotanical dictionary. That
                     metadata was removed using EXIF Tool and Adobe Bridge and for the map,
                     abstracted to a more general location, with the story shared on the map talking
                     about history and methodology, rather than the specificity of the location or
                     the research site where the photograph was taken. This honored some of the
                     healers’ requests to protect them from ongoing ostracization in their
                     communities. </p>
                  <p>What is shared, though, is meant to be shared with the largest possible
                     audience. A running thread throughout the process was the emphasis on
                     accessibility, navigation, content display and ability to view the content
                     through multiple kinds of devices and networks. Given that the majority of
                     healers in the project live in rural communities outside the U.S., and that
                     they access the internet through phones on 3G networks, we wanted to ensure
                     that the website is equitable, flexible, and intuitive for user and
                     interactivity; have information be perceived in multiple ways regardless of
                     sensory ability; and have the site be responsive to different screen sizes
                     dependent on the types of technical devices used to access it. By applying
                     accessibility concepts throughout the digital technology selection and digital
                     content process, the builders understood requirements for a sitemap,
                     inspirations for look and feel, and different ways to represent and engage with
                     interviews. For example, transcriptions and translations were made separately
                     available to download on healer pages. These PDFs, which are speech-to-text
                     reader-friendly, are read aloud by the computer. </p> </div>
            <div>
                  <head>Open Source and Sustainability</head>
                  <p>Given the principles of openness informing <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women
                        Healers</title> and many (if not most) digital humanities projects, it might
                     be expected that open-source software solutions were selected for philosophical
                     reasons rather than for desirable design or special features. This is not to
                     say that open source cannot be beautiful, usable, or functional (or all three)
                     — that would be absurd. However, in many years of development experience, the
                     staff of DSS discovered the custom open-source digital projects they co-created
                     with faculty at the University of Oregon typically had a limited lifespan as
                     teaching or research tools. Whether an individual left the university, or a
                     major database system or programming language was deprecated, after a few
                     years, the project was frequently in dire straits, with security and
                     accessibility issues requiring significant intervention.</p>
                  <p>We can and should approach digital projects with a clear understanding of their
                     limited lifespan, engaging in appropriate digital stewardship activities to
                     ensure the underlying digital collections are maintained. Beyond those
                     collections, however, the builders sought a greater level of sustainability for
                        <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> by using platforms with
                     broad institutional support. Not only is WordPress the most-used web content
                     management system in the world, but the University of Oregon has a multi-site
                     license agreement with the educational technology company, CampusPress to
                     provide access to WordPress to all faculty, staff, and students. There is a
                     depth of WordPress expertise in the Libraries and in central campus Information
                     Services, as well as access to vendor support should more extensive
                     troubleshooting be required. Through CampusPress, we have access to the premium
                     WordPress theme Divi, which we used for <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women
                        Healers</title> and enabled the builders to closely implement the culturally
                     responsive design vision developed by the research team. </p>
                  <p>In selecting a digital mapping tool, we opted for the familiar open-source
                     option, Northwestern University’s Knight Lab-sponsored StoryMapJS, rather than
                     ESRI’s recently updated Story Map product. Either would have worked for our
                     needs, abstracting from a specific location to protect healers’ privacy and
                     showcasing Reyes-Santos' and Lara’s images and writings from their research
                     sites. Each story on the map focuses on the spiritual histories of enslaved and
                     colonized Indigenous communities of that location. Given the builders’
                     collective experience with StoryMapJS, we were disinclined to add a new
                     platform to our oeuvre for the sake of it or because it was new. In the time
                     since <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title>’ launch, Thornhill
                     and Gaede have gained a great deal of experience with ESRI Story Maps and the
                     same institutional support factors that has encouraged our use of WordPress may
                     yet see us switching platforms for digital mapping. </p>
                  <p>Ultimately, the lifespan of <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women
                        Healers</title> is a combination of technical and methodological choice. We
                     selected platforms based on institutional environments and what we thought
                     would give the project the most longevity. UO Libraries’ Special Collections
                     and University Archives will not taking custody of the digital collections
                     created as part of this project; everything remains with the researchers as
                     surrogates and members of the communities from which they were collected,
                     settling questions of post-custodial disposition. If any healer wishes their
                     interviews or materials to be removed, both the formal research protocol and
                     their personal agreements with the researchers dictate prompt removal. That
                     right to be forgotten is absolute <ptr target="#christen2015"/>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <div>
               <head>Successes</head>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> enables the dissemination and
                  continuity of Afro-Indigenous healers’ knowledge and values in a format that is
                  open access and built to last. Together, a diverse and collaborative team of
                  healers, faculty, librarians, students, and technology specialists produced a DH
                  project that centers the decolonial values of the research throughout the digital
                  scholarship process. This project disrupts the use of unsustainable technical
                  infrastructures and information dissemination, has a research output beyond the
                  boundaries of academia, breaks down disciplinary silos, and redefines
                  relationships between teaching and research <ptr target="#moritz2017"/>. As a
                  project informed by Black feminist praxis, it pays particular attention to the
                  locations of knowledge production, while aiming to maintain multiplicity and
                  plurality. As stated by Nicole M. Brown et al., <quote rend="inline">black feminism
                     offers interventions that serve to dismantle embedded privilege and reification
                     and (digitally) center the experiences of Black women within digital humanities
                     research.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Challenges</head>
               <p>Team communication can be challenging across disciplines. The disciplinary
                  vocabulary and jargon, particularly that associated with the digital work, could
                  create barriers between researchers and builders. Similarly, researchers had to
                  find language to explain project stages to healers. Ongoing communication and
                  mutual openness to questions was key and created opportunities to learn and share
                  new words, meanings, and theories that are part of expertise in ethnography, black
                  feminist praxis, decolonial methodologies, ethnobotany, web development, and
                  information science. An example of this communication challenge are definitions
                  and applications of metadata that are required for images, interviews, and other
                  materials cataloging.</p>
               <p><title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers</title> was first presented in
                  English, requiring additional resources for future development and presentation in
                  Spanish – the primary language of those centered by the project. We kept all
                  interviews in their original languages so healers could hear themselves and share
                  with others their interviews as they were done. And yet we could not escape the
                  demands of the imperial academy to produce knowledge in English as the only
                  legitimate knowledge <ptr target="#curtisboles2012"/> <ptr target="#mohanty2006"
                  />. The resources are in the U.S. and finding digital teams with the kinds of
                  resources and capacity that the UO Libraries provided within the Caribbean is
                  difficult at best. These dynamics replicate some of the inherent issues of the
                  digital humanities, whereby the United States continues to predominate as a site
                  for the production of digital scholarship <ptr target="#risam2016"/>. It is a
                  dynamic that feels inescapable given that both researchers live and work within
                  the U.S. academy. In the meantime, we are aware that academic systems of
                  evaluation for tenure and promotion may implicitly erase the labor that healers
                  engaged in giving input, feedback, and changing and transforming knowledge within
                  the overall process.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Just Futures</head>
               <p>The Pacific Northwest Just Futures Institute for Racial and Climate Justice was
                  founded in early 2021 with a generous grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
                  and is sponsoring the next stage of <title rend="italic">Caribbean Women Healers,
                     Sustaining Climate Justice and Health through Afro-Indigenous Healing</title>.
                  With Mellon funding, Reyes-Santos and Lara will continue their work to incorporate
                  storytelling and healing practices in conversations about TEK with support from
                  the UO Libraries team, including Thornhill, Gaede, and Malinao-Alvarez. Thornhill,
                  Gaede, and Malinao-Alvarez team will initially work on building the Spanish mirror
                  site, with content created by Lara. </p>
               <p>Reyes-Santos and Lara will work with Indigenous, Afro-Indigenous, and Black
                  communities in the Pacific Northwest to document and disseminate how these healers
                  deploy TEK to support communities disproportionately impacted by climate change,
                  its attendant environmental disasters, and the pandemic; foster and document TEK
                  exchanges between growing migrant Afro-Indigenous communities and local Native and
                  African American communities; train students to engage in related climate and
                  racial-justice research; and recruit students of color and working-class students
                  as research interns. Work will include edited audio/video interviews,
                  ethnobotanical surveys, and pedagogical resources, in collaboration with students
                  of color, migrant students, and first-generation students.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Future Work</head>
               <p>Reyes and Lara, both Black-Indigenous women, placed the desires, visions and
                  values of their communities at the center of their collaboration with the UO
                  Libraries. With or without technology, Afro-Indigenous healers in the Caribbean
                  continue to live their lives, working for a present and future in which Black life
                  can be sustained across the generations. And, as the healers told us, this project
                  enables the transmission of knowledge in ways that circumvent the impacts of
                  social violence, rapid emigration and ongoing social stigma. </p>
               <p>We do expect that while facing these challenges and lessons, <title rend="italic"
                     >Caribbean Women Healers</title> will intervene in the future of Black Studies,
                  a future that engages the heterogeneity and inter-ethnic realities of the Black
                  Diaspora; continues to forge transcolonial, transnational, multilingual
                  connections between Black peoples and histories; engages Afro-Indigeneity, women
                  and queer people seriously; bravely interweaves histories of genocide and slavery,
                  and of Indigenous and Black resistance; centers decolonial knowledge production
                  and orality; fosters collaborative, interdisciplinary, self-transformative
                  scholarship that destabilize the assumptions of both Black Studies and DH; and
                  employs Black DH tools to create sound open-access scholarship, teaching tools,
                  and creative possibilities for academia to engage general audiences.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allard2015" label="Allard and Ferris 2015"> Allard, D. and Ferris, S.
               (2015) <title rend="quotes">‘Antiviolence and marginalized communities: Knowledge
                  creation, community mobilization, and social justice through a participatory
                  archiving approach</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title>, 64.2
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/lib.2015.0043"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1353/lib.2015.0043</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="anderson2019" label="Anderson and Christen 2019"> Anderson, J. and
               Christen, K. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Decolonizing attribution: Traditions of
                  exclusion</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Radical Librarianship</title>,5 <ref
                  target="https://journal.radicallibrarianship.org/index.php/journal/article/view/38"
                  >https://journal.radicallibrarianship.org/index.php/journal/article/view/38</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="archer2017" label="Archer and Prinsloo 2017"> Archer, E. and Prinsloo, P.
               (2017) <title rend="quotes">Some exploratory thoughts on Openness and an ethics of
                  care</title>, in Singh, D. and Stückelberger, C. (eds.) <title rend="italic"
                  >Ethics in higher education: Values-driven leaders for the future</title>.<ref
                  target="https://uir.unisa.ac.za/handle/10500/21903"
                  >https://uir.unisa.ac.za/handle/10500/21903</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bailey2011" label="Bailey 2011">Bailey, M. Z. (2011) <title rend="quotes"
                  >All the Digital Humanists are white, all the nerds are men, but some of us are
                  brave</title>,in <title rend="italic">Journal of the Digital Humanities</title>, :
                  <ref
                  target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/all-the-digital-humanists-are-white-all-the-nerds-are-men-but-some-of-us-are-brave-by-moya-z-bailey/"
                  >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/all-the-digital-humanists-are-white-all-the-nerds-are-men-but-some-of-us-are-brave-by-moya-z-bailey/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="becerralicha2017" label="Becerra-Licha 2017">Becerra-Licha, S. (2017)
                  <title rend="quotes"> Participatory and post-custodial archives as community
                  practice</title>, <title rend="italic">EDUCAUSE Review </title>52.6 <ref
                  target="https://er.educause.edu/articles/2017/10/participatory-and-post-custodial-archives-as-community-practice"
                  >https://er.educause.edu/articles/2017/10/participatory-and-post-custodial-archives-as-community-practice</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="benoit2019" label="Benoit and Eveleigh 2019"> Benoit, E. and Eveleigh, A.
               (2019) <title rend="italic">Participatory archives: Theory and practice. </title>
               London, England: Facet Publishing.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="campbell2014" label="Campbell and Lassiter 2014"> Campbell, E. and
               Lassiter, L. E. (2014) <title rend="italic">Doing ethnography today: Theories,
                  methods, exercises</title>. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="caswell2016" label="Caswell and Cifor 2016">Caswell, M. and Cifor, M.
               (2016). <title rend="quotes">From human rights to Feminist ethics: Radical empathy in
                  the archives,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title> 81 <ref
                  target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/687705"
                  >https://muse.jhu.edu/article/687705</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="christen2012" label="Christen 2012"> Christen, K. (2012) <title
                  rend="quotes">Does information really want to be free? Indigenous knowledge
                  systems and the question of openness</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Communication</title>, 6 <ref
                  target="https://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/view/1618"
                  >https://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/view/1618</ref> .</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="christen2015" label="Christen 2015"> Christen, K. (2015) <title
                  rend="quotes">Tribal archives, Traditional Knowledge, and local contexts: Why the
                  “s” matters</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Western Archives </title>6.1
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.26077/78d5-47cf"
                  >https://doi.org/10.26077/78d5-47cf</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="christen2018" label="Christen 2018"> Christen, K. (2018) <title
                  rend="quotes">Relationships, not records: Digital heritage and the ethics of
                  sharing indigenous knowledge online</title> in Sayers, J. (ed) <title
                  rend="italic">Routledge companion to Media Studies and Digital Humanities</title>.
               New York, New York: Routledge, pp. 403-412.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="christen2019" label="Christen 2019"> Christen, K. (2019). <title
                  rend="quotes"><q>The songline is alive in Mukurtu</q>: Return, reuse, and
                  respect</title>, in Barwick, L., Green, J. and Vaarzon-Morel, P. (eds.) <title
                  rend="italic">Archival returns: Central Australia and beyond</title>. Honolulu,
               HI: University of Hawai’i Press and Sydney University Press. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="coble2021" label="Coble 2021"> Coble, Z. (2021) <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital Humanities: Tools &amp; Software </title>NYU Libraries Research Guides.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://guides.nyu.edu/digital-humanities/tools-and-software"
                  >https://guides.nyu.edu/digital-humanities/tools-and-software</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="cole2001" label="Cole 2001"> Cole, J. B. (2001) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Foreward</title> in McClaurin, I. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Black Feminist
                  anthropology: Theory, politics, praxis, and poetics</title>. New Brunswick, NJ:
               Rutgers University Press. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="curtisboles2012" label="Curtis-Boles 2012"> Curtis-Boles, H. (2012) <title
                  rend="quotes">An African American woman’s experience in the academy: Negotiating
                  cultures</title> in Curtis-Boles, H., Adams, D. M., and Jenkins-Monroe V. (eds.)
                  <title rend="italic">Making our voices heard: Women of Color in academia</title>.
               Hauppage, NY: Nova Science Publishers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="digitalcuration2021" label="Digital Curation Center 2021"> Digital
               Curation Centre. (2021) <title rend="italic">Curation Lifecycle Model </title>
               Available at: <ref target="https://www.dcc.ac.uk/guidance/curation-lifecycle-model"
                  >https://www.dcc.ac.uk/guidance/curation-lifecycle-model</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="digitalhumanitiesintiative2020" label="Digital Humanities Intiative 2020">
               Digital Humanities Initiative. (2020) <title rend="italic"> WordPress</title> Duke
               Digital Humanities. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://digitalhumanities.duke.edu/tools/wordpress"
                  >https://digitalhumanities.duke.edu/tools/wordpress</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dirt2018" label="DiRT: Digital Research Tools 2018"> DiRT: Digital
               Research Tools. (2018) <title rend="italic">Publishing </title>DiRT Directory.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://web.archive.org/web/20180903093406/http://dirtdirectory.org/tadirah/publishing"
                  >https://web.archive.org/web/20180903093406/http://dirtdirectory.org/tadirah/publishing</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="earhart2016" label="Earhart and Taylor 2016"> Earhart, A. E. and Taylor,
               T. L. <title rend="quotes">Pedagogies of race: Digital Humanities in the age of
                  Ferguson</title> in Gold, M. K. and Klein, L. F. (eds.) <title rend="italic"
                  >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: Minnesota
               University Press.<ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/58ca5d2e-da4b-41cf-abd2-d8f2a68d2914"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/58ca5d2e-da4b-41cf-abd2-d8f2a68d2914</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Making a case for the Black Digital Humanities</title> in Gold, M. K. and Klein,
               L. F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>.
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gilliland2014" label="Gilliland and McKemmish 2014">Gilliland, A. J. and
               McKemmish, S. (2014) <title rend="quotes">The role of participatory archives in
                  furthering human rights, reconciliation and recovery</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Atlanti: Review for Modern Archival Theory and Practice</title> 24.<ref
                  target="https://escholarship.org/uc/item/346521tf"
                  >https://escholarship.org/uc/item/346521tf</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gofair2021" label="GO FAIR"> GO FAIR. (2021) <title rend="italic">FAIR
                  Principles</title> [Online].<ref target="https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/"
                  >https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lara2020" label="Lara 2020"> Lara, A. (2020) <title rend="italic">Queer
                  freedom: Black sovereignty </title>. Albany, NY: SUNY Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lothian2013" label="Lothian and Phillips 2013"> Lothian, A. and Phillips,
               A. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities mean transformative
                  critique?</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of E-Media Studies</title> 3.1
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1349/PS1.1938-6060.A.425"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1349/PS1.1938-6060.A.425</ref> </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mclaurin2001" label="McClaurin 2001"> McClaurin, I. (2001) <title
                  rend="quotes">Theorizing a Black Feminist self in anthropology: Toward an
                  autoethnographic approach</title> in McClaurin, I. (ed.) <title rend="italic"
                  >Black Feminist anthropology: Theory, politics, praxis, and poetics</title>pp.
               49-76 New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccracken2015" label="McCracken 2015"> McCracken, K. (2015) <title
                  rend="quotes">Community archival practice: Indigenous grassroutes collaboration at
                  the Shingwauk Residential Schools Centre</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                  American Archivist</title> 78.1 <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.17723/0360-9081.78.1.181"
                  >https://doi.org/10.17723/0360-9081.78.1.181</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mohanty2006" label="Mohanty 2006"> Mohanty, C. T. (2006) <title
                  rend="quotes">US empire and the project of Women’s Studies: Stories of
                  citizenship, complicity and dissent</title>, <title rend="italic">Gender, Place
                  &amp; Culture </title>13.1 <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09663690600571209"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/09663690600571209</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="moritz2017" label="Moritz et al. 2017"> Moritz, C., Smart, R., Retteen,
               A., Hunter, M. Stanely, S., Soper, D., and Vandegrift, M. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >De-centering and recentering Digital Scholarship: A manifesto</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">LIS Scholarship Archive Preprints</title>
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.31229/osf.io/t7hfu"
                  >https://doi.org/10.31229/osf.io/t7hfu</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="nationalarchives2019" label="National Archives 2019"> National Archives
               (2019) <title rend="italic">Digital Preservation Strategy</title>
               <ref
                  target="https://www.archives.gov/preservation/electronic-records/digital-preservation-strategy"
                  >https://www.archives.gov/preservation/electronic-records/digital-preservation-strategy
               </ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="neh2018" label="National Endowment for the Humanities 2018"> National
               Endowment for the Humanities. (2018) <title rend="italic">Data Management Plans for
                  NEH Office of Digital Humanities Proposals and Awards</title>
               <ref
                  target="https://www.neh.gov/sites/default/files/2018-06/data_management_plans_2018.pdf"
                  >https://www.neh.gov/sites/default/files/2018-06/data_management_plans_2018.pdf</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="peters2015" label="Peters 2015"> Peters, M. A. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Open education and education for openness</title> in Peters, M. (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Encyclopedia of educational philosophy and theory</title>.
               Singapore: Springer.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-287-532-7_411-1"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-287-532-7_411-1</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="punzalan2017" label="Punzalan et al. 2017"> Punzalan, R. L., Marsh, D. E.,
               and Cools, K. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Beyond clicks, likes, and downloads:
                  Identifying meaningful impacts for digitized ethnographic archives.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title> 84 <ref
                  target="https://archivaria.ca/index.php/archivaria/article/view/13614"
                  >https://archivaria.ca/index.php/archivaria/article/view/13614</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="risam2016" label="Risam 2016"> Risam, R. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Navigating the global Digital Humanities: Insights from Black Feminism</title>,
               in Gold, M. K. and Klein, L. F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                  Humanities 2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="reed2021" label="Reed 2021"> Reed, T. (2021) <title rend="quotes">
                  Creative sovereignties: Should copyright apply on tribal lands?</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Journal for the Copyright Society USA</title><ref
                  target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3736137"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3736137</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="reed2021b" label="Reed 2021b"> Reed, T. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Fair
                  use as cultural appropriation</title>, <title rend="italic"> California Law
                  Review</title> 109.4 <ref target="https://doi.org/10.15779/Z38V97ZS35">
                  https://doi.org/10.15779/Z38V97ZS35</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="reed2021c" label="Reed 2021c"> Reed, T. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Indigenous dignity and the right to be forgotten</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Brigham Young University Law Review</title> 46.4 <ref
                  target="https://digitalcommons.law.byu.edu/lawreview/vol46/iss4/9/"
                  >https://digitalcommons.law.byu.edu/lawreview/vol46/iss4/9/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="reyessantos2015" label="Reyes-Santos 2015"> Reyes-Santos, A. (2015) <title
                  rend="italic">Our Caribbean kin: Race and nation in the Neoliberal
                  Antilles</title>. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="simmons2001" label="Simmons 2001">Simmons, K. E. (2001) <title
                  rend="quotes">A passion for sameness: Encountering a Black Feminist self in
                  fieldwork in the Dominican Republic</title> in McClaurin, I. (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Black Feminist anthropology: Theory, politics, praxis, and
                  poetics</title>pp. 77-101. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="simpson2014" label="Simpson 2015"> Simpson, A. (2014) <title rend="italic"
                  >Mohawk interruptus: Political life across the borders of settler states</title>.
               Durham, NC: Duke University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="smith2011" label="Smith 2011">Smith, L. T. (2011) <title rend="italic"
                  >Decolonizing methodologies: Research and indigenous peoples</title>. London,
               England: Zed Books Ltd. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sas2021" label="Society of American Archivists 2021"> Society of American
               Archivists. (2021). <title rend="italic">Custodial</title> Dictionary of Archives
               Terminology <ref target="https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/custodial.html"
                  >https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/custodial.html</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sas2021b" label="Society of American Archivists 2021b"> Society of
               American Archivists. (2021). <title rend="italic"> Digital stewardship </title>
               Dictionary of Archives Terminology. <ref
                  target="https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/digitalstewardship.html"
                  >https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/digitalstewardship.html</ref> .</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sas2021c" label="Society of American Archivists 2021c"> Society of
               American Archivists. (2021). <title rend="italic">Postcustodial</title> Dictionary of
               Archives Terminology. <ref
                  target="https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/postcustodial.html"
                  >https://dictionary.archivists.org/entry/postcustodial.html</ref> . </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="spn2021" label="Software Preservation Network 2021"> Software Preservation
               Network. (2021). <title rend="italic"> Technological Infrastructure</title><ref
                  target="https://www.softwarepreservationnetwork.org/core-activities/technological-infrastructure/"
                  >https://www.softwarepreservationnetwork.org/core-activities/technological-infrastructure/</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="thomas2013" label="Thomas and Clarke 2013"> Thomas, D. A. and Clarke, M.
               K. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Globalization and race: Structures of inequality, new
                  sovereignties, and citizenship in a neoliberal era </title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Annual Review of Anthropology</title> 42 <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-anthro-092412-155515"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-anthro-092412-155515</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="thornton2016" label="Thornton 2016">Thornton, B. J. (2016) <title
                  rend="italic"> Negotiating respect: Pentecostalism, masculinity, and the politics
                  of spiritual authority in the Dominican Republic</title>. Gainesville, FL:
               University Press of Florida. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="williams2012" label="Williams 2012"> Williams, G. H. (2012) <title
                  rend="quotes">Disability, universal design, and the Digital Humanities </title> in
               Gold, M. K. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
               2012</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wwwc2020" label="World Wide Web Consortium 2020"> World Wide Web
               Consortium. (2020) <title rend="italic">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)
                  2.0</title> Web Accessibility Initiative. <ref
                  target="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wynter2003" label="Wynter 2003"> Wynter, S. (2003)<title rend="quotes"
                  >Unsettling the coloniality of being/power/truth/freedom: Towards the human, after
                  man, its overrepresentation — An argument</title>, <title rend="italic">CR: The
                  New Centennial Review</title> 3.3 <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1353/ncr.2004.0015"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1353/ncr.2004.0015</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
