<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument:
                    Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values
                    expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jo <dhq:family>Guldi</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Southern Methodist University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jguldi@mail.smu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jo Guldi is co-author, with David Armitage, of <title rend="italic">The
                                History Manifesto</title> (Cambridge 2014), and author of <title
                                rend="italic">Roads to Power: Britain Invents the Infrastructure
                                State</title> (2010). In 2015 she left Brown University without
                            going up for tenure to join the History Department at Southern Methodist
                            University, where she is now Associate Professor of History. With Cora
                            Johnson-Roberson, she designed <title rend="italic">Paper
                                Machines</title>, an early DH plugin for word count and topic
                            modeling. With various leaders of the interdisciplinary community around
                            the digital humanities and social sciences, she founded and directed the
                            Think-Play-Hack conference and hackathon in 2018 and 2019. She is PI of
                            a $1 million NSF grant to investigate the changing meanings of property
                            over the past 200 years. She has authored many technical articles on
                            aspects of text mining applied to the historical study of technology,
                            property, and infrastructure over time.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000463</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-01">01 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
                <dhq:revisionNote previous="000463_01" when="2021-01-29">This article has been
                    revised since its original publication. The language describing Zotero has been
                    updated. The updated portion is <ref target="#p116"
                    >here</ref>.</dhq:revisionNote>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
            <change when="2020-04-23" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
                <p>What values does infrastructure-building represent?  This article begins by
                    situating scholarly practices around infrastructure within a broader
                    transformation of twenty-first century life and indeed scholarship and learning
                    by infrastructures, and distinguishing <soCalled>scholarly</soCalled>
                    infrastructure from other kinds of infrastructure designed to share information
                    that nevertheless lack scholarly engagement with analysis.  This article
                    compares the role of scholar-builders in crystallizing a set of theoretical
                    concerns, data, and analyses to that of the architects of opera houses during
                    the golden age of European opera, who structured, illuminated, and constrained
                    possible future creations of art.  The article next attempts to excavate a set
                    of implicit values, while making room for the possibility that the list of
                    values put forward here is only incomplete, and that the list of values itself
                    is the subject of potential debate, critique, or dissent, some of which may take
                    the form of building infrastructures differently than the patterns laid out
                    here.  A first section outlines a set of <emph>bibliographic</emph> values;
                    while the article’s second half turns to the power dynamics of infrastructure
                    and a set of <emph>critical</emph> values encompassed by particular projects,
                    before turning to the issue of why understanding these values is so essential to
                    understanding infrastructure projects as a form of scholarly production that
                    merit support and recognition by the community at large.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                <p>This article discusses infrastructure within the transformation of twenty-first
                    centuty life and scholarship.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
            	<head/>
                <p> We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by
                    infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in
                    today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as
                    well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of
                    practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that
                    scholars tend to create for their traditional work. The reasons for this are
                    seldom explicitly articulated in the existing literature that documents their
                    use and purpose. The creation of public tools for visualizing data is
                    increasingly important to many scholars, and it represents a non-negligible
                    commitment in terms of time and grant money. </p>
                <p> This article argues that that choice and commitment are best understood as a
                    kind of work deeply informed by an engagement with certain <emph>values</emph>,
                    including scholarly transparency and political participation, which often align
                    with scholars’ moral commitments, intellectual heritage, and disciplinary
                    traditions. Indeed, that alignment has been so powerful for many builders of
                    scholarly data that they have chosen to pursue the building of infrastructure
                    projects even when that choice was otherwise out of alignment with recognizable
                    promotion incentives in their professional communities. </p>
                <p> In many cases, the infrastructure project advances an argument: but if web
                    portals existed merely to convey arguments to a broader audience, they could
                    just as easily take the form of an open-access article or monography. Why, then,
                    would a scholar or a scholarly team choose to invest their energy in designing
                    and constructing a web project? </p>
                <p> The pages that follow then attempt to answer the question: what values does
                    infrastructure-building represent? This article begins by situating scholarly
                    practices around infrastructure within a broader transformation of twenty-first
                    century life and indeed scholarship and learning by infrastructures, and
                    distinguishing <q>scholarly</q> infrastructure from other kinds of
                    infrastructure designed to share information that nevertheless lack scholarly
                    engagement with analysis. The article next attempts to excavate a set of
                    implicit values, while making room for the possibility that the list of values
                    put forward here is only incomplete, and that the list of values itself is the
                    subject of potential debate, critique, or dissent, some of which may take the
                    form of building infrastructures differently than the patterns laid out here. A
                    first section outlines a set of <q>bibliographic</q> values; while the article’s
                    second half turns to the power dynamics of infrastructure and a set of
                        <q>critical </q> values encompassed by particular projects, before turning
                    to the issue of why understanding these values is so essential to understanding
                    infrastructure projects as a form of scholarly production that merit support and
                    recognition by the community at large. </p>
                <p> The principles and case-studies here suggest that infrastructure represents a
                    conscientious choice about the format for disseminating that argument that
                    reflects critical thinking about the value of scholarship. In designing
                    infrastructure, many scholars today are amplifying the values embedded in their
                    scholarship – whether values of accessibility, of replicability, or even of the
                    political critique of institutions – and that for this reason, infrastructure
                    needs to be looked on as a particular kind of gesture, one that not merely
                    critiques the world but attempts to actively remake it. The author’s personal
                    history as a theorist/historian of infrastructure and sometime builder of
                    infrastructure are offered by way of laying out the importance of the scholarly
                    community engaging with the critical issues represented by a choice to build –
                    and the hazards to professional careers that can occur when activities of this
                    kind are undertheorized, underengaged, or otherwise underappreciated.
                    Infrastructure thereby deserves to be elevated within a humanistic discourse
                    that privileges action as well as contemplation. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Of Infrastructure</head>

                <p> Web portals that visualize data may strike many scholars as a strange place to
                    begin a discussion of infrastructure. Visualizing data, of course, is but part
                    from the whole, even as a physical mailbox is invisibly connected to a network
                    of roads and trains, law and labor, standards and trust — so familiar that it
                    too disappears into the background of landscape taken everywhere for granted —
                    which allows letters posted in one continent to be delivered promptly to another
                    quarter of the world within days. The colossus of infrastructure that has
                    developed in university libraries and digital humanities centers to make
                    possible the scraping, cleaning, and serving of data is the subject of a great
                    deal of documentation, much of which takes the role of making visible otherwise
                    invisible commitments of expense, labor, maintenance, and ideation. </p>
                <p> As understood in its broadest form, infrastructure encompasses any use of
                    technology or information which connects communities. Science and technology
                    scholars such as Janet Vertesi have defined infrastructure in terms of a
                    technology or management structure distinguished by its deliberate design, its
                    scale, its capacity to deliver information, and, frequently, its invisibility
                        <ptr target="#vertesi2019" loc="263–4"/>. In the digital age, new
                    infrastructures have rapidly transformed how ordinary citizens as well as
                    scholars access information. Individuals read e-books, consult maps, and digest
                    newspapers whose delivery depends upon a vast infrastructure system ranging from
                    transoceanic cables to smart phones <ptr target="#starosielski2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#sawyer2019"/>. </p>
                <p>Meanwhile, scholarship too has grown to depend increasingly on a world of
                    invisible technologies. Already in 2010, Geoffrey Rockwell described an <quote
                        rend="inline">infrastructure turn</quote> that was shaping how a majority of
                    scholars accessed data <ptr target="#rockwell2010"/>, which entailed new worlds
                    of labor, storage, and expense for universities, much of which required new
                    skills at managing digital data. Tara McPherson, founder and editor of a journal
                    that provided one infrastructure for delivering digital projects to readers,
                    described the creation of a <quote rend="inline">broader culture of
                        experimentation and change</quote> among faculty, particularly those with a
                    specialty in visual analysis, as requiring new developments in infrastructure
                    that would service, validate, and share faculty experiments – from accessible to
                    journals tenure and review processes <ptr target="#mcpherson2010"/>.</p>
                <p> Indeed, a broad range of institutional players came into being at most
                    universities and within many disciplines, including digital humanities centers,
                    digital humanities majors, institutional repositories, and new guidelines for
                    dissertation-writing and for the tenure and promotion of faculty <ptr
                        target="#gold2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#clement2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#flanders2013"/>. Libraries began to engage data storage, standards
                    that define the data, the data itself, metadata, and applications that retrieve
                    and serve the data, as well as hardware, software, and structures for the
                    management of labor <ptr target="#mattern2014"/>. </p>
                <p> Researchers can turn to an emerging field of similarly interoperable tools that
                    put quantitative analysis of texts within the grasp of textual scholars from any
                    tradition in the humanities or social sciences. Among those tools are <ref
                        target="https://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/philologic/">
                        <title rend="italic">PhiloLogic</title>
                    </ref>,UChicago’s browser for topic-modeling text, analyzing word co-occurrence
                    and re-use; <ref target="https://www.hypershelf.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">InPho Topic Explorer</title>
                    </ref>, which allows users to apply topic modeling to their own body of text;
                        <ref target="https://voyant-tools.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">Voyant</title>
                    </ref>, a simple web-interface which allows the user to pipe a selection of text
                    through a variety of visualizations; <ref
                        target="https://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio/">
                        <title rend="italic">Palladio</title>
                    </ref>, Stanford’s application for visualizing correspondence such as letters
                    within a social network; <ref target="https://www.cortext.net/">
                        <title rend="italic">CorTexT</title>
                    </ref>, Jean-Philippe Cointet’s extremely flexible and strong tool for
                    language-based analysis on a body of text with temporal metadata; and <ref
                        target="https://archivesunleashed.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">Archives Unleashed</title>
                    </ref>, Ian Milligan’s toolbox for digital humanities and social sciences
                    analysis of archives. </p>
                <p> There are also, of course, individual repositories of texts that offer
                    particular tools for a unique set of documents, especially JSTOR’s data for
                    research portal, the online instance of the <ref
                        target="http://oldbaileyonline.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">Old Bailey</title>
                    </ref>, as well as an expanding range of online portals for individual moments
                    in time; those covered in this article include <ref
                        target="http://slavevoyages.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">Slave Voyages</title>
                    </ref>, the <ref target="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/">
                        <title rend="italic">Legacies of the British Slave-Ownership</title>
                    </ref> project, and <ref
                        target="http://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/volume/2/index">
                        <title rend="italic">Torn Apart/Separados</title>
                    </ref>, a project that documents the contemporary incarceration of immigrants
                    and their families in the U.S. Effort will be made in this discussion to
                    foreground the author’s personal experience of the successes and failures of the
                        <ref target="http://papermachines.org/">
                        <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title>
                    </ref> experiment, and the strengths of the infrastructure that supplanted it,
                    towards a genealogy of the design principles appropriate to infrastructure in
                    the humanities and social sciences. </p>
                <p>Even more recently, Roopika Risam has argued for the existence of a postcolonial
                    DH, marked by an <quote rend="inline">ethos of building,</quote> where scholars
                    create infrastructure to reconfigure access to suppressed voices that document
                    the experience of colonization. She points to several examples of projects where
                    scholars used infrastructure to reinterpret and challenge colonial world-making
                    projects implicit in archives, by assembling alternative archives of information
                    that supported research on the experience of colonized persons. Risam gives
                    numerous examples that document the variety and importance of this work,
                    including The Early Caribbean Digital Archive and the Online Tagore Variorum,
                    which reassemble scattered texts documenting the experience of colonized
                    persons, as well as Chicana por mi Raza, an archive of oral histories, ephemera,
                    out-of-print publications that provide resources for Latina/o experience, and
                    The Indigenous Digital Archive in New Mexico, which made available the records
                    of Hope and Diné experience with boarding schools. Infrastructure in this case
                    is at work reassembling the scattered voices of colonized persons, constructing
                    alternative archives that challenge and actively provide alternatives to
                    libraries whose holdings predominantly reflect the information matrix of the
                    colonizer. In Risam’s eloquent phrase, <quote rend="inline">The archive uses
                        technology to push back against dominant cultural representations of
                        indigenous communities</quote>
                    <ptr target="#risam2019" loc="36"/>.</p>
                <p>Scholarly creation of infrastructure has become a primary realm of critical
                    encounter with public narratives about culture, identity, and the past. Scholars
                    who have engaged this space have forged an entirely new modality of scholarly
                    publishing, one with tremendous power to shape public discourse. It is not
                    clear, however, that all forms of infrastructure constitute a critical
                    intervention in scholarship. The <ref target="http://archive.org/">Internet
                        Archive</ref> is a stalwart repository for preserving the historical
                    artifacts, the creation of which surely constituted a political act in its time.
                    Many of its sub-collections – for instance, troves of anthropological films
                    collected by universities over decades — represent some work of critical
                    scholarship. Nevertheless, it would be hard to argue that the Internet Archive’s
                    little-curated collection of historical objects represents a scholarly
                    intervention in any particular field. While not a scholarly piece of
                    infrastructure by design, the Internet Archive’s voluminous collections of
                    scanned books, archival videos, and recordings nevertheless consists of a
                        <q>potential </q>site of future critical interventions such as OCR,
                    metadata, preservation, and collection analysis. Thus the distinction between
                    scholarly and non-scholarly infrastructure is not hard and fast. </p>
                <p> In a critical review of existing digital humanities and social sciences
                    projects, I have attempted to derive an overview of the values that motivated
                    those projects via their expression in public-facing websites. The idea that a
                    piece of infrastructure may encapsulate scholarly values is premised, in the
                    first place, upon the implicit understanding that the designers of
                    infrastructure have already made critical argumentation, embedded within the
                    larger culture of critical thinking about technology and culture, and inspired
                    by its insights. In other words, this article advances the proposition that the
                    design of infrastructure, when it engages critically with existing thought about
                    power, represents a form of scholarly argumentation. </p>
                <p> In the following sections, this article will take the first step towards
                    articulating some principles that define the culture of infrastructure. These
                    principles are divided in two parts, reflecting the distance between the
                    concepts of <q>scholarship</q> and <q>criticality</q> that I have teased apart
                    in the introduction. A set of <q>bibliographic</q> principles of infrastructure
                    describe the principles that bring data into alignment with traditional
                    bibliophilic concerns about verifiability and fact in the liberal arts,
                    including web tools that link directly back to particular manuscripts in
                    particular archives. A set of <q>critical</q> principles of infrastructure
                    describe the kind of interventions that render the invisible visible, and which
                    otherwise mirror the kind of critical thinking called upon by Arendt and others
                    as a liberatory intervention in the public sphere. </p>
                <p>The principles advanced in this essay are merely a starting point – a review of
                    possible sources, both from the traditional humanities and social sciences and
                    from critical politics, which begins with an autobiographical narrative of the
                    author’s own participation in the design and building of a piece of
                    infrastructure. It is hoped that this starter list of principles will be amended
                    and argued with, towards the creation of a more critical discourse about what
                    humanistic infrastructure looks like and where critical thinking takes place,
                    with the expected outcome of generating a scholarly discourse about the choices
                    made in designing infrastructures for the public. An essay of this kind affords
                    an opportunity to reflect on the public purposes and intellectual orientation
                    intended in the building of infrastructure, and the extent to which humanities
                    and social science critiques of the flow of information and power in society
                    have resulted in the creation of alternative or transformative flows. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Infrastructure as Proto-Argumentation</head>

                <p>In enabling the researcher to efficiently identify the patterns that characterize
                    a vast scale of documents, infrastructure can seed dozens or hundreds of
                    scholarly arguments. The infrastructure thus represents a
                        <term>proto-argument</term>, if not an argument or analysis itself. </p>
                <p>What do I mean by <term>proto-argument</term>? An infrastructure contains
                    constraints that structure and direct the format of the argument eventually
                    produced over them, even as the shape of opera houses in London and Turin framed
                    civic ambitions, structuring how later compositions, libretti, and performances
                    would be received; those opera houses hosted hundreds or thousands of later
                    productions. </p>
                <p>In relationships of this kind, the architect’s work was often to envision and
                    crystallize a set of intellectual values and ideological ambitions latent in
                    opera. As historians of the opera have reasoned, the work of the architect was
                    to offer a framework of imagination that included <quote rend="inline">civic
                        ambition,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline">unabashed commercialism,</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                        >international cosmopolitanism,</quote> which ran in parallel to textual
                    forms of argument-making about history, civic identity, and teleology <ptr
                        target="#aspden2019" loc="6"/>. Indeed, the opera house structured the
                    reception of operas within a <quote rend="inline">penumbra of
                        exclusivity</quote> that mirrored the social structuring of other forms of
                    enlightenment knowledge <ptr target="#aspden2019"/>. </p>
                <p>Hence the <q>proto</q> in <term>proto-argument</term>. The architect’s work
                    codified enlightenment values into a structure that would both enhance later
                    performances, extend the potential of the. The creation of the vessel represents
                    the moment in time when an ideology is crystallized into a form where it can be
                    replicated. Much of the work of conceptualizing what <title rend="italic"
                        >Aida</title> — as an epic about the tragedy of gender, race, and empire —
                    might be was thus the work of a generation of architects and opera-designers who
                    worked previous to Verdi’s masterpiece. Similarly, the infrastructure allows the
                    application of one <emph>theory</emph> of text or temporality to a million data
                    sets. </p>
                <p>Architecture and infrastructure both function simultaneously as creation, vessel,
                    and constraint. They are proto-arguments in the sense that they structure the
                    natural course of use, exchange, and argumentation that follows from an original
                    design. One cannot stage a Brechtian play in an opera house. In a state of
                    disaffection, one might <emph>imagine</emph> dissolving the fourth wall from the
                    opera house at Turin, but one would have to build a totally different kind of
                    theater in order to realize it. </p>
                <p>Similarly, scholarly infrastructures that curate particular choices of word
                    analysis – grammar, topic, bag-of-words; transparent or not, open to
                    interpretation or not – package an entire system of understanding about what a
                    text is, what components of grammatical and semiotic structure or historical
                    context matter, and who is allowed to participate in the interpretation of text.
                    Scholarly infrastructure can be designed in such a way as to elucidate the
                    critical function of scholarship or to diminish it; and to expand public access
                    to polysemous interpretations or battles over the historical record or to
                    channel them. All of those choices have enormous downstream implications for
                    what scholarship can be executed, published, or received. </p>
                <p>Builder-scholars, over the last decade, have made legion critical decisions that
                    open up corpora to possible kinds of engagement. <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/ngrams">Google Ngrams</ref> does not allow
                    the scholar to inquire about word co-location as PhiloLogic does; Cortext allows
                    the user to highlight discontinuities in time in a way that few other resources
                    do; each innovation in analysis represents an opening to a critical question,
                    informed by concerns in linguistics or history, bringing the theories of
                    disciplines into alignment with algorithms and corpus in such a way as to
                        <emph>scale </emph> theory into an analysis with new documents. </p>
                <p>Builder-scholars are also, as I shall argue below, responsible for making choices
                    that govern who has the opportunity to inspect, to use, or to interpret data,
                    thus structuring entire communities of knowledge. The builder’s decisions – to
                    model gender or not, to open the structure, to an enormous degree, whether and
                    how fluidly later scholars who use the infrastructure will be able to compare
                    the use of gender, race, or class in the text; whether hours, days, years, or
                    decades of change over time are susceptible to analysis; and who is allowed to
                    make that analysis – whether a scholarly elite or anyone at all. </p>
                <p>To embrace this perspective made atop a web portal is to highlight the hybridity
                    of labor in discoveries, where both the design of infrastructure and the
                    scholarly analysis built upon those discoveries are crucial. When an
                    award-winning paper is published that relies on the metrics of gender difference
                    encoded in historical data made available by a public-facing portal, is the
                    award properly given to the paper’s author, or to the website’s designer, who
                    identified gender difference as a key component of that data, fit the data with
                    the correct algorithm for analysis, and made the results available? Arguably,
                    the award would properly be given to both: not only because the paper would be
                    impossible without the labor of the data, but also because a large portion of
                    the critical perspective implicit in the paper was given in advance by the
                    infrastructure. </p>
                <p>Above all, this line of reasoning underscores that the design and building of
                    portals is itself an act of imagination, and possible critique. In the following
                    section, I will propose some general lines of reasoning about what kinds of
                    imagination and critique the present generations of portals embody.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Bibliographic Principles of Scholarly Infrastructure </head>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of Transparency with Respect to a Document Base.</head>
                    <p>One challenge of interoperability is making sure that the origin and nature
                        of artifacts is preserved, even as information is exchanged. A variety of
                        tools – including <ref target="https://omeka.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Omeka</title>
                        </ref> and <ref target="https://duraspace.org/fedora/">
                            <title rend="italic">Fedora Commons</title>
                        </ref> — make possible the tracking of metadata about archival objects <ptr
                            target="#gourley2010"/>. A user in the humanities needs always to know
                        on what documents and particular words a visualization is based. Only in
                        this way can the user defend herself against the critical challenges of
                        readers who will want to know if a homonym has been used in different sense,
                        if a single word example counted by a computer is based on an OCR error, or
                        if the statement counted as an earnest example of nationalism was made in
                        jest. </p>
                    <p> For this reason, it is crucial that humanities infrastructure be designed so
                        that every visualization is transparent. Each visualization based on data in
                        an archive should be clickable; each word or point on a chart should link to
                        another page that cites the documents and passages represented by that
                        analysis. Ideally, each list of citations should link back to the snippet of
                        original text that was counted to create the analysis. Where copyright
                        allows, that snippet of original text would link back to the original scan
                        of the document itself. </p>
                    <p> The University of Chicago’s <ref
                            target="http://guides.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/philologic">
                            <title rend="italic">PhiloLogic</title>
                        </ref> platform is a paragon of this value: visualizations of keyword
                        prevalence over time can be linked to original passages in the text, which
                        link back to chapter and edition, with the result that the scholar is always
                        clear about upon which original texts a visualization is based, and how
                        those individual parts of the text relate to a larger text and cycle of
                        publication. </p>
                    <p>
                        <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> singularly failed with regard to
                        this principle of clickability, but other infrastructures are more
                        satisfying. In <title rend="italic">PhiloLogic</title>, each visualization
                        of word counts over time links to a list of documents and passages that
                        links to the original text in its context. In the <ref
                            target="https://www.oldbaileyonline.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Old Bailey</title>
                        </ref>, keyword searches and crime searches link back to passages that link
                        to the original scans of the document. The user is never deluded with
                        respect to the evidence and where it comes from. Adherence to the Principle
                        of Transparency with Respect to a Document Base ensures that users, both
                        scholarly and vernacular, can link abstract word counts to original text,
                        whether by looking up the citation given or through a link to a verbatim
                        copy of an original text. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of Interoperability with Existing Documents.</head>
                    <p>A basic orientation of Paper Machines that the prosthesis must be
                        interoperable with the material that scholars already had on their
                        computers. Despite the range of national and temporal orientations, every
                        research scholar I knew worked with pdfs, which had recently become the
                        standard digitized format for journal articles and scanned books. A single
                        application would accept pdf’s and churn out a text version of the article
                        (presumably with the noise of headers, footers, and page numbers intact).
                        Despite the noise, the information encoded in the text would be sufficient
                        for us to design the application so that it could generalize about
                        collections of pdf’s, for instance creating word clouds that suggested the
                        transition of pdf’s in a single field from one decade to the next.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="http://papermachines.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title>
                        </ref> was thus designed to operate within existing infrastructure –
                        depending on the folders of pdf’s that users already had on their machines.
                        I originally imagined it as a kind of box, into which a user would drag
                        folders of documents, with the result of producing visualizations about the
                        contents of those folders. Eventually, my co-designer, Christopher
                        Johnson-Roberson, proposed a tool that would scrape text and generate
                        visualizations from inside another existing piece of humanities
                        infrastructure: <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Zotero</title>
                        </ref>, the application that many humanists use to organize their citations
                        for books, articles, and archival materials. Inside <title rend="italic"
                            >Zotero</title>, <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> operated as
                        a right-click menu that offered a set of commands by which a researcher
                        could extract text from a file, or order that text to be generalized into
                        topic models, word clouds, or networks of phrases. </p>
                    <p> Today, a variety of humanities applications, including <ref
                            target="https://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio/">
                            <title rend="italic">Palladio</title>
                        </ref> and <ref target="https://www.cortext.net/">
                            <title rend="italic">Cortext</title>
                        </ref> allow users to upload their own data, typically accepting files in
                        the form of text or Excel document. Tools like <ref
                            target="https://voyant-tools.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Voyant</title>
                        </ref> and <ref target="https://www.hypershelf.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">InPho Topic Explorer</title>
                        </ref> allow scholars to cut-and-paste raw text from any source. PhiloLogic
                        works with any TEI-encoded text sent directly to its editors for uploading.
                        Portals of this kind offer an invaluable resource for scholars with little
                        technical background who wish to take advantage of existing digital tools to
                        analyze text in a given form.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of Neutrality with Respect to Technical Literacy.</head>
                    <p>Consider sociologist Matthew Desmond’s website, <ref
                            target="http://evictionlab.org/">Eviction Lab</ref>, which currently
                        serves data on local eviction rates to members of the public, directly
                        feeding local housing campaigns, but also providing a solid stream of data
                        to journalists and legislators via the site’s API. Desmond’s web portal is
                            <q>friendly</q>, we might say, in the sense of serving data within a
                        sparsely-designed interface, set to a map of the United States; users can
                        zoom into any locality, and explore rates of eviction and demographics for
                        that site, as well as comparing one site to others. The portal delivers
                        information; the cleaner the interface, the easier to use, and the more
                        attention the portal attracts. </p>
                    <p>
                        <q>Friendliness</q> is thus a function of obscurity, in a sense: more
                        accessible than a monograph or scholarly journal, the portal obscures
                        expertise; there are no footnotes or citations and few allusions to other
                        organizations. One dimension of this friendliness is the obscuring of other
                        forms of infrastructure – the many organizations whose work contributed to
                        the gathering of the data; the many organizations at work, some of which
                        initially complained at a lack of acknowledgement from Eviction Lab <ptr
                            target="#aiello2018"/>. Indeed, as we have seen, one function of
                        infrastructure is frequently its invisibility: the cables that carry data
                        across the ocean are submerged; users of libraries rarely consider the labor
                        and investments that created those institutions. Yet obscurity is not the
                        only function of friendly design; rather, a clean and legible design also
                        serves the function of inviting participation.</p>
                    <p> Friendly design tempts users to investigate a dataset or tool according to
                        their own peculiar motivations, which have only been anticipated by the
                        interface’s designer in a general way. Indeed, one aspect of the
                        accessibility of web portals is to obscure many of the acts of accreditation
                        and comparison that are typical of journal footnotes and published
                        monographs, explaining the conclusions that a scholar came to on the basis
                        of data. Instead, in Eviction Lab, the user is invited to make their own
                        comparisons between any two geographical entities, examining rates of
                        eviction, poverty and race between a given city and the rest of the state
                        where it is located. </p>
                    <p> Another dimension of the seeming accessibility of the data is thus that the
                        uses presented to the public are potentially open-ended: the scholar who
                        shares data about rent, city-by-city, cannot know the political ends to
                        which arguments about that data will be put. Data about rents is interpreted
                        in one way by advocates of the free market and another way by advocates of
                        welfare services; but without facts to argue about, the discussion is won
                        merely by the fact of identification with an ideology, and thus by
                        authority, rather than discourse, debate, and reason. </p>
                    <p> Faith in the <emph>process</emph> of such a discourse to produce
                        understanding, particularly when all players have access to original texts,
                        is part of the legacy of the enlightenment. Indeed, encouraging contemporary
                        people to engage the shared reality of the past – to interpret it and come
                        to understanding on their own, to begin to understand the present in
                        relationship to shared historical experience, however naively at first – is
                        surely part of the core duty of scholars and universities. Builders can
                        limit the extent to which users of topic models or other abstractions can
                        away from historical truth by linking visualizations back to the original
                        text – a strategy we discussed in the Principle of Transparency – such that
                        a debate on social media might occur that took the form of a series of
                        refutations grounded in precise arguments about what to make of particular
                        passages of texts. </p>
                    <p> In the humanities, it is possible that certain scholars experience an
                        aversion to the principle of sharing learned documents beyond the sacrosanct
                        borders of those initiated into the elite habits of hermeneutics and
                        historiography. An anecdote shared by one scholar/builder suggests that a
                        grant to release a public topic model of Jefferson’s correspondence was
                        crushed, at one point, by a reviewer who feared that political forces in the
                        public would demonize Jefferson on account of topics that referred to
                        slaves. </p>
                    <p> Sharing the tools of abstracting and contextualizing arguments in their
                        original context is surely part of the process of helping the public to
                        perceive the past as accessible and a source of reason or rational debate to
                        begin with: it is tools that can be argued about, linked to original
                        passages of text, that can prove to naïve readers that the past is something
                        about which rational arguments can be had, where arguments about the past
                        have to be backed up by reasonable citations of an authoritative text
                        stream. Engaging the tools doesn’t relinquish the battle over
                        interpretation; rather, it moves the battle of interpretation out of the
                        arcane world of footnotes, into a world of (preferably transparent) graphs
                        and passages of text that any literate person can begin to understand. I
                        shall return to this question of how tools help contemporary societies to
                        establish a shared understanding of their past and present in the discussion
                        of a later section, the Principle of Creating Knowledge About the Social
                        World. </p>
                    <p> Today, portals such as <title rend="italic">Philologic</title>, <title
                            rend="italic">Topic Explorer</title>, <title rend="italic"
                            >Voyant</title> and <title rend="italic">Palladio</title> make readily
                        available a graphic user interface for documents brought in by the user,
                        wrought out of precious seasons of user-testing the redesign, with the
                        purpose of delivering a tool easy to use to those with no training.
                        Single-archive portals such as the <title rend="italic">Old Bailey</title>
                        offer multiple transformations so that a user can explore the history of
                        court cases by gender, crime, name, and other archive-supplied variables.
                        All of these tools aim on bringing the facility and nimbleness of code to a
                        base of users whose priority is research, rather than mastery of the
                        architecture of coding.</p>
                    <p> In 2010-2, I worked on a similar piece of infrastructure – <title
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> – which could be embedded within
                        the existing Zotero portal for storing documents, allowing users to generate
                        word clouds and other visualizations for the pdf’s organized on their
                        computer. Our starting assumptions with <title rend="italic">Paper
                            Machines</title> departed from a moment when most scholars in the
                        humanities lacked the technical expertise to convert files from pdf to clean
                        text. We anticipated that scholars would want to harness the tools of
                        aggregating information across thousands of the pdf’s that each of us
                        already had on our desktops, and that Google Books had just made available
                        in enormous numbers. In order to accomplish this, scholars would need access
                        to highly interoperable tools. By the nature of the community in which I was
                        embedded, any tool I worked on necessarily needed to bring insights to a
                        plurality of scholars who worked on a range of topics, periods, languages
                        and nations, who possessed a range of technical proficiencies from ample to
                        extremely limited. Such an imagined user base underscored the importance of
                        working with existing infrastructure, of transparency and usability as
                        values. The idea is to present a low bar of technical literacy with the end
                        of enabling all users – regardless of their background – to replicate a
                        scholarly analysis, or to run their own. </p>
                    <p> In the case of our work, it was vital that <title rend="italic">Paper
                            Machines</title> serve the largest number of users with the smallest
                        technological interventions to produce an easy transformation of the data
                        into visual form, organized so as to be as convenient as possible to
                        novices. It was intended to be facile and transparent, easily installed and
                        easily opened. </p>
                    <p> Extended beyond <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title>, this principle
                        raises questions about the design of library and museum catalogues, national
                        newspaper collections and archives of political debates, and indeed any
                        collection of archives whose user base includes a general public which may
                        not be literate. If the institution wishes to justify itself to a public
                        taxpayer-base, to create transparency about national history or the nature
                        of its political system, then builders of humanities infrastructure must
                        follow the precepts of user interface design to enable the movement from
                        question to analysis through a transparent, largely visual interface. </p>
                    <p> Indeed, the barriers to technological literacy may be more vast than the
                        infrastructure itself. As Miriam Posner has argued, barriers may be
                        institutional and cultural rather than defined by software. Successful
                        digital humanities centers typically require a great deal of independence
                        from university administration — as well as support — in order to provision
                        researchers with the tools of committed research <ptr target="#posner2013"
                        />.</p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of the Primacy of Pattern Recognition. </head>
                    <p>Today, the designers of algorithms can borrow from an immense assortment of
                        possible clustering algorithms from Machine Learning and statistics. It is
                        not clear, in all cases, how the transformation of language encoded in these
                        processes are applicable to humanities concerns. Put simply, pattern
                        recognition is the coin of the realm of the humanities and social sciences,
                        structuring insights from linguistics, history, archaeology, sociology, and
                        political science, since at least the age of Ernst Cassirer. </p>
                    <p> In the design of Paper Machines, algorithms were chosen that would
                        foreground pattern recognition and make available insights to which scholars
                        could give their assent – on the basis of relatively easy-to-explain
                        insights from computer science. My graduate school education coincided with
                        the linguistic turn in British history, and my first point of orientation to
                        the digital humanities was the possibility of measuring language as an index
                        of political change. Another basic orientation was that we would foreground
                        forms of analysis that already replicated, insofar as possible, the sorting
                        and pattern-recognition functions of ordinary scholars of cultural, social,
                        or political language. </p>
                    <p> Establishing and foregrounding the patterns being measured in a text has a
                        clear benefit: it underscores examples of human behavior that other
                        observers can easily recognize, grounded in facts that can be shown to
                        correlate with the analysis. For this reason, pattern recognition is the
                        gold standard of analysis in the humanities and social sciences. </p>
                    <p> For this reason, likewise, drawing attention to cultural patterns has
                        transformative potential because it directly relates analysis to fact.
                        Inspired by the overwhelming power of cultural criticism based in patterns,
                        digital humanities students at Berkeley addressed the #blacklivesmatter
                        movement by creating an Online Hate Index (OHI) that would recognize
                        patterns in twitter and social media <ptr target="#vacano2017"/>. Such a
                        tool, in theory, has transformative political potential as much as any
                        Frankfurt School analysis of culture, on the same principle: that
                        enlightenment can be tagged to self-conscious reflexivity about cultural
                        phenomena, and that awakening, therefore, can be harnessed to the
                        recognition and analysis of patterns. </p>
                    <p> Not every online archive necessarily helps readers to navigate by using
                        visualizations that foreground repeated patterns in the text. Earlier
                        schools of infrastructure design – for example, many hyperlinked scholarly
                        editions, web-born exhibits of art history, and keyword-searchable web
                        repositories too numerous to mention – simply delivered text or
                        visualizations to the user, one list or item at a time.</p>
                    <p> The skills of rendering insights from repeated patterns are associated with
                        the school of Cultural Analytics, especially publications in the <title
                            rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>, which has begun, in
                        recent years, to harvest the most successful examples of pattern-recognition
                        aided by advances in statistics and machine learning <ptr
                            target="#bamman2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#kraicer2019"/>
                        <ptr target="#lansdall-welfare2017"/>
                        <ptr target="#so2019"/>
                        <ptr target="#underwood2018"/>. The natural next expression of the methods
                        laid out in these journal articles – which count, for example, named
                        subjects by gender and race, or identify words associated with gender and
                        race, or cluster documents temporally – is for those toolsets to be made
                        usable by the public through the design of portals that would harness the
                        full capability of our present knowledge of pattern-recognition. </p>
                    <p> To foreground the tools that draw attention to patterns based on repeated
                        use of words – from basic keyword-counting to named entity extraction to
                        topic modeling – reduces the technological intervention to something
                        grounded in theories familiar to scholars of language such as Wittgenstein,
                        Cassirer, Laswell, Austin, Skinner, Koselleck, and their heirs. A
                        pattern-recognition toolkit is relatively transparent to users with respect
                        to its possible uses and implications. At the same time, insisting on the
                        primacy of pattern recognition must not come into conflict with the reality
                        of the plural desires of humanists. </p>
                    <p> For those insights to be useable, and to garner consent, it is not enough
                        that the types of analysis used be composed of concepts familiar to
                        humanists and social scientists; they must also be replicable.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of Replicability.</head>
                    <p>A concept introduced in another article in this issue, the <q>pipeline</q>
                        promise that the results of working with any given text base can be
                        generalized. A term borrowed from computer science, the pipeline suggests a
                        structure that enables the transformation of data through particular
                        modules, each of which is completed before the next takes over.
                        Conceptually, describing the way that a particular data visualization was
                        produced through a pipeline underscores the need to transparently document
                        the choices that comprise any particular approach to data. Sharing a
                        pipeline, in the form of open data or open-source code, means being fully
                        transparent about how a scholar arrived at a particular conclusion. Sharing
                        pipelines also opens the gates to constructive scholarly critique, for
                        instance, inviting other scholars to run the same code on the same data, but
                        with a different cleaning algorithm or clustering equation, to see how
                        different the results might be.</p>
                    <p> Scholarly journals in the humanities have begun to make this kind of sharing
                        possible by adopting relationships with existing infrastructure that
                        supports the sharing of code and data alongside shared ideas and
                        visualizations. For instance, the <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural
                            Analytics</title> asks authors to contribute their data and code to the
                        Harvard Dataverse, an existing open-source infrastructure that allows a user
                        to share and label datasets and code so that they are transparent and
                        findable. The <title rend="italic">Hansard Topic Relevance
                            Identifier</title>, <title rend="italic">HaToRI</title>, discussed in
                        another essay in the same issue of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                            Quarterly</title> – aspires to the <q>pipeline</q> concept documented
                        here, where every choice in the production of an analysis is documented, and
                        any choice can be questioned, with the result of producing different
                        material. </p>
                    <p> Sharing pipelines encourages inter-disciplinary, inter-temporal, and
                        inter-national replication of results, comparison, and extrapolation. A
                        pipeline designed around the Hansard debates for Great Britain can be
                        plugged into the EU debates, the debates of the American congress or NYC
                        council, with the same transformations executed on the same infrastructure. </p>
                    <p> Building infrastructure in this way makes good on the promise typically
                        ascribed to <term>critical theory</term> in the humanities and social
                        sciences since the era of Hegel and Marx, where comparisons of social
                        phenomena from diverse places and times can be rendered understandable and
                        compared in aggregate. Infrastructure designed to work only with a single
                        group of texts does not do this, but infrastructure that is interoperable
                        with a great range of material in theory allows vast comparisons and
                        contrasts that will enable the next generation of social theorists,
                        theorists of literature, and theorists of society to draw the
                        generalizations that will structure our knowledge of the world. </p>
                    <p>Eve Kraicer, Andrew Piper and other scholars are pursuing an intellectual
                        agenda in the design of code pipelines that make possible the critical
                        reading of gender, class, and race in large-scale bodies of texts <ptr
                            target="#kraicer2019"/>. Their work differs from traditional endeavors,
                        of course, in that it is replicable – that is, the body of code that Kraicer
                        and Piper apply to American best-selling novels since the 1970s can, with
                        the adjustment of perhaps five lines of code, be applied to Victorian novels
                        or Renaissance broadsides, assuming clean data has already been prepared. </p>
                    <p>Potential replicability is underscored where scholars share actual code – or
                        create a web portal that allows a body of code to be applied texts supplied
                        by the scholar. A scholarly body of code, such as historian Lincoln Mullen’s
                            <q>textreuse</q>, a toolset for comparing large bodies of text, opens
                        doors for further scholarship, thus matching in significance works of
                        critical theory, potentially rendering Mullen a contemporary Bourdieu. In
                            <title rend="italic">InPho Topic Explorer</title>, philosopher Colin
                        Allen provides an interface where scholars can submit any body of text to
                        topic modeling, thus allowing humanists and social scientists access to a
                        preferred tool for the machine-enabled clustering of documents.</p>
                    <p>Drawing attention to the wealth of postcolonial projects in the space of the
                        digital humanities, Roopika Risam has underscored the way that digital
                        technology allows scholars not merely to assert, but to replicate a critique
                        of empire through the assemblage of alternative archives. Reviewing numerous
                        examples, she shows how scholars have created and share alternative archives
                        that run in parallel to the maps, laws, censuses, and other documentation of
                        empire. Only through building — not merely through scholarship — she
                        reasons, can scholars truly challenge the dominance of the colonized voice
                            <ptr target="#risam2019"/>. Unlike a one-time publication, which might
                        critique the official archive without enabling other scholars the tools of
                        directly accessing more voices, infrastructure projects of this sort
                        actively provide the work for a hundred or a thousand new research projects
                        and student papers.</p>
                    <p>This potential replicability of a theory across data-sets represents the
                        fulfillment of the universalizing principles of the humanities since Vico,
                        that is, the desire to make sense of multiple times and places. At the same
                        time, the critical theory impulses of Piper and his cohort also have crafted
                        forms of code (such as vector analysis of gender-index words) that enable
                        scholars to lift nuanced semantic differences from very diverse bodies of
                        text. In other words, the skilled reader, addressing this material, should
                        be able, with the help of critical infrastructure, to preserve and describe
                        cultural nuances that differentiate one moment from another, peering with
                        ever finer attention into the characteristics and tensions within a
                        corpus.</p>
                    <p>I am not saying, of course, that different cultures will not require
                        different infrastructures or different kinds of code. Scholars of Chinese
                        history, for example, reaffirm that many forms of digital humanities
                        pipelines developed for western texts – which, for instance, depend upon
                        word order for grammatical understanding – would be misapplied to their
                        field, even while forms of analysis that jettison word order – including
                        semantic network analysis and topic modeling – appear to work fine. The
                        promise of infrastructure to extend and replicate scholarly inquiry is
                        clear; the limits of that promise need still to be worked out through many
                        case studies and much experimentation. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of Creating Knowledge About the Social World. </head>
                    <p>An implied extension of a transparent document base is that documents are a
                        reflection of a shared historical context that has a reality and permanence,
                        even within opposing interpretations: Jefferson’s contemporaries might have
                        argued about the tolerability of human slavery, but none would have
                        contested that slavery was a contemporary reality of deep and persistent
                        concern, structuring their economic and social world to a deep degree. A
                        piece of infrastructure can be – in certain circumstances – a tool for
                        generating assent. Through encouraging consensus around some insight into
                        social or economic reality, pattern recognition can offer the basis for
                        collective action. More than simply advising a critical point of view,
                        infrastructure can provision citizens and movements with data that actually
                        then becomes part of their work. </p>
                    <p> It is clear that the humanities and social sciences have a great deal to
                        offer, on an interpretive level, to the public, beyond merely being
                        purveyors of data. Philosophers and feminists from Hannah Arendt to Seyla
                        Benhabib have long valorized the role of the humanities and social sciences
                        in the public sphere, in particular citing its capacity to enliven critical
                        thinking about contemporary discourses of politics and identity. Working in
                        this tradition, many scholars are used to understanding <q>critique</q> and
                            <q>complication</q> as aligned with a political critique of empire,
                        politics, and exclusion. More recently, Rita Felski has argued that critique
                        reaches its limit when the hermeneutics of suspicion is turned everywhere
                            <ptr target="#felski2015"/>, and has urged scholars to remember their
                        value as curators of memory, critics of politics, and composers of
                        stories.</p>
                    <p>Inviting the public to inspect data for itself is an action that implies
                        political consequences. Consider the political context that motivated
                        historians David Eltis and Catherine Hall – both historians of slavery —
                        have turned into builders of infrastructure, in the midst of British debates
                        about remunerations for slavery. Such projects as these represent broadly
                        the fact that scholars are using infrastructures for serving cultural and
                        political artifacts to the public as a way of engaging, instructing, and
                        facilitating further cycles of engagement by the public. </p>
                    <p>Their projects have granted the public access not only to a curated debates
                        about the history of slavery, but also directly to massive troves of
                        quantitative, spatial and economic data about the British slave trade (<ref
                            target="https://www.slavevoyages.org/">Slave Voyages</ref>, <ref
                            target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs">The Legacies of British
                        Slavery</ref>). Of the two projects, it is Hall’s – the <title rend="quotes"
                            >Legacies of British Slavery</title> – that has perhaps most directly
                        sought to create an epistemic bridge to contemporary discourse, insofar as
                        they profile the continuing profits that Europeans have reaped as a result
                        of legacies of the past. </p>
                    <p>Both portals did three things that critical essays cannot do: (1) They
                        reduced the arguments over Britain’s involvement in the slave trade down to
                        a single visualization. (2) Indirectly, they invited the public to view the
                        data upon which the visualization was based for themselves, offering it in
                        the agnostic guise of <q>raw data</q> rather than as a series of footnotes
                        compiled by an expert in the service of a project. We might, of course, take
                        issue with <q>raw data</q> in principle, agreeing with Johanna Drucker that
                        all data is already cooked: but the public fascination with raw data
                        remains. And both scholars implicitly took advantage of the public
                        fascination with raw data to demonstrate, in their portals, the extent of
                        data upon which their visualizations rest. (3) They made the data
                        interoperable, allowing the public to test conclusions for themselves. </p>
                    <p>At the same time, other scholars reviewing those projects might raise
                        questions about whether all examples are equally <q>critical</q> in the
                        sense of how profound is the new perspective it offers on the past. A
                        scholarly edition represents a critical intervention in Literary Studies and
                        is celebrated when evidence is mustered to persuade readers of a
                        dramatically new interpretation of a canonical text. Digital editions, like
                            <ref target="https://www.frankenbook.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Frankenbook</title>
                        </ref>, the most recent digital edition of <title rend="italic"
                            >Frankenstein</title> – an exemplars of the genre, built on several
                        generations of digital edition work — would have to pass this test of
                            <q>critical</q> interventions in order to attract the notice of some
                        departments. Clearer examples of critical interventions where humanities and
                        social sciences knowledge is used to create a radical break with present-day
                        narratives of politics and identity include <ref
                            target="http://xpmethod.plaintext.in/torn-apart/volume/2/index">
                            <title rend="italic">Torn Apart/Separados</title>
                        </ref>, which documents child separations at detainment centers along the
                        national border, providing users with data, visualizations, and a critical
                        narrative. At the same time, <title rend="italic">Torn Apart</title> ejects
                        a critical humanistic perspective into materials in the public sphere. </p>
                    <p> In sociologist Matthew Desmond’s ethnography, <title rend="italic">Evicted
                        </title>, Desmond provides accounts of families in Milwaukee who faced
                        eviction, and the resulting stress to savings, education, children, health,
                        and jobs that resulted from their experience. In Desmond’s companion
                        website, <title rend="italic">Eviction Lab</title>, he provides users across
                        the United States with information about the rate of homelessness and
                        eviction in their neighborhoods. The infrastructure offers insight into the
                        local realities of neighborhoods outside the Rust Belt. Another companion
                        website, <ref target="https://justshelter.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">JustShelter</title>
                        </ref>, offers corridors to action by connecting users with organizations
                        that advocate for housing rights. </p>
                    <p>Like Desmond’s <title rend="italic">Eviction Lab</title>, <title
                            rend="italic">Torn Apart</title> offers the public an open-source
                        databank that renders visible previously invisible patterns of expenditure
                        and violence. <title rend="italic">Torn Apart</title> thus creates a
                        scholarly intervention in a realm that was previously little addressed by
                        scholars, or if addressed, in such a partial way as to make less of an
                        intervention than <title rend="italic">Torn Apart’s</title> open-source
                        databank. Rendering visible the invisible, and making accessible the
                        previously inaccessible data of knowledge, such infrastructures as these
                        attempt interventions that differ in content, scale, and power from other
                        scholarly productions, and they are therefore deserving of special attention
                        as models of criticality and engagement with the public sphere.</p>
                    <p>The social power of documents to create an informed consensus becomes evident
                        in digital humanities portals that illuminate politically contested episodes
                        of national history. In portals such as <title rend="italic">Slave
                            Voyages</title> and the <title rend="italic">Legacies of British Slavery
                        </title>site, historians of Britain have published, for the benefit of a
                        wide public, the primary records and quantitative distillation of the
                        history of persons enslaved by the modern west. The portals, by their
                        design, offer members of the public, as well as other scholars, access to
                        primary-source artifacts, original numbers, visualizations and maps, as well
                        as critical interpretations that, for instance in the case of the Legacies
                        project, link the historical record to present-day companies and families
                        whose wealth was bound up with the trade. </p>
                    <p>In such a circumstance, where the material governed by a site is potentially
                        political, the designers of infrastructure have an opportunity to thwart the
                        logic of naysayerdom in the era of fake news by firmly circulating
                        primary-source evidence to users. By providing direct links to the primary
                        source material on which the analysis is based, the <title rend="italic"
                            >Legacies</title> site all the more firmly asserts the possibility of a
                        new consensus around the history of British slavery and its
                        repercussions.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps a more important aspect of scholarly infrastructure as argument
                        functions in the realm of a critical understanding of the potential
                        audiences and points of access to scholarly data. In the age of peer-to-peer
                        networking with humanities and social science data, new collaborations are
                        possible that never could have been accomplished in the age of individual
                        research in the archive, and many journalistic theories have sought to
                        characterize the generative potential of <q>hive mind</q> or many-to-many
                        learning (Shirky). More recent research, however, has emphasized that
                        many-to-many discursive spaces online create echo chambers that can be
                        deleterious to learning, feedback, or critical thinking (Nguyen).</p>
                    <p>Information flows of any kind may generate echo chambers. Social theory
                        foregrounds the potential of any flow of information to either intensify
                        power or undercut it. It suggests that the choices made in the construction
                        of institutions and infrastructure determine whether the experience of
                        information will create a cult-like experience of information – where
                        outside information is met with suspicion – or whether new information,
                        data, and expertise will be experienced as the essence of liberation. </p>
                    <p> It might appear, of course, that a principle that demands consensus about
                        reality is one of top-down power exerted over the user base by the
                        designers. Indeed, the principle of creating knowledge about the social
                        world operates in tension with another principle: that of a plurality of
                        humanistic desires. </p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>The Principle of a Plurality of Humanistic Desires. </head>
                    <p>Yet another orientation was to imagine our potential users as a plural
                        community with a diversity of desires and perspectives with regard to
                        electronic archives. In designing <title rend="italic">Paper
                            Machines</title> for an imagined diverse public of my fellow
                        researchers, I had no ambition of creating a specific tool that would
                            <q>understand</q> documents; rather I would leave it to users to
                        organize their documents into relevant categories – for example, comparing
                        decades, authors, subject-matter, or genres of writing. Instead, the tool
                        would only implement algorithms that would prosthetically <q>extend</q> the
                        ordinary capabilities of scholars: generalizing about large bodies of text,
                        enabling the researcher to develop new insights into the material. By
                        designing an infrastructure with fairly humble goals, we would offer the
                        services of these algorithms to researchers who had little time away from
                        the archive to code. </p>
                    <p> This principle holds more instruction for institutions such as libraries,
                        museums, and national archives that have a particular responsibility to a
                        non-scholarly user base. If the infrastructure is supposed to serve the
                        general public, it must be accessible and transparent to a general public,
                        whose desires from the archive may be genealogical or political in a narrow
                        sense, rather than a reflection of current scholarship. The tools at hand
                        should enable the finding of more documents according to a plurality of
                        desires. </p>
                    <p> Indeed, Joris van Zundert has lately underscored the limits of humanities
                        infrastructure projects tailored to a single archive – and the need of tools
                        to help scholars who deal with heterogenous data <ptr
                            target="#vanzundert2012"/>. The desire principle, in theory, would
                        facilitate not only collective research programs but also individual
                        trajectories of research within those archives – and across multiple
                        archives. Zotero allows a user to collect documents from multiple databases,
                        for instance gathering trials from the Old Bailey and books from Hathi Trust
                        alongside pamphlets help on JSTOR. By working within Zotero, <title
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines </title> made room for such erratic
                        document-gathering habits, and attempted to offer tools that would allow the
                        researcher to generalize about the collection as a whole. </p>
                    <p> Once a scholar who used Zotero had collected her own archive, <title
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> was designed to facilitate
                        individual exploration and experimentation with as broad an array of tools
                        as possible. By trying on different categories, researchers could summon
                        algorithms to quantitatively interpret texts, in much the same way as
                        researchers’ own imagination typically sorts texts into different categories
                        by decade, genre, and theme. The researcher would thus be able to
                            <emph>test</emph> her subjective assessment of different categories
                        using the quantitative power of a tool. Quantitative testing, we assumed,
                        might reveal the user’s subjective categories to be grounded in fact.
                        Alternatively, it might destabilize the user’s categories and suggest other
                        patterns, established by regular word order, that might complement or
                        challenge the user’s assessments. </p>
                    <p> Through these operations, researchers could iteratively model sub-portions
                        of a corpus. They could view a body of texts as if through different lenses,
                        reorganizing the corpus into different subcategories, and comparing the
                        perspective raised by these subcategories, for instance rapidly glancing at
                        the perspective of the corpus organized by decades and that of the corpus
                        organized by genres or themes. Similar design principles governed the
                        University of Virginia’s <title rend="italic">Collex </title>, designed to
                        facilitate the collection and exhibition of a suite of documents gathered by
                        a researcher according to his or her own research program; they continue to
                        inform the design principles behind <title rend="italic">Omeka</title>, the
                        go-to resource for narrating a public story grounded in well-annotated
                        archival artifacts. Both tools allowed scholars to extrapolate their own
                        language for analyzing cultural documents, providing basic annotations like
                        maps or timelines to enhance the user’s capabilities of storytelling.</p>
                    <p>
                        <title rend="italic">Paper Machines </title>and other analogues like <title
                            rend="italic">Voyant</title> and <title rend="italic">Cortext</title>
                        enhanced individual story-telling with the possibility of data analysis.
                        They provide researchers with a to test different quantitative perspectives
                        on the corpus, rapidly switching between the perspective enabled by two
                        different mathematical models, for example word count and topic model. </p>
                    <p> Yet <title rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> added one facet that the
                        others lacked: because it was built in Zotero – a platform that allowed
                        scholars to share collections of documents with each other – <title
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines </title> facilitated research on shared
                        archives, where a group of scholars might agree about a subset of documents
                        of interest, and then embark on different algorithmic approaches to
                        understanding those documents. This zone of inquiry would take place between
                        individual research on mass shared collections and individual research on
                        individual collections, occupying what Paul Edwards might dub the
                            <q>intermediary scale</q> of research infrastructure. It would make room
                        for shared, sociable research desires to emerge – not merely on an
                        individual or collective scale – but also within the space of
                        micro-communities. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Critical Principles of Scholarly Infrastructure </head>
                    <p> Thus far, the principles have focused on the relationship between a
                        non-technical user base and a technical process of transformation, although
                        embracing the principles has, as has been shown, implications for the power
                        of the digital humanities to redound onto critical theory and seed
                        interventions across the disciplines. Another set of principles govern the
                        relationship between users and the erudite nature of archives themselves;
                        these principles are best understood within a review of writings about power
                        dynamics and infrastructure. </p>
                    <p> The implicit power dynamics involved with supporting digital infrastructure
                        within the university itself have been subject to inspection and critique
                        for at least two decades. After all, as critics of modern technologies of
                        communication have long understood, power is at work at each scale in an
                        infrastructure system. As many scholars in what is now called <quote
                            rend="inline">critical infrastructure studies</quote> have shown, at
                        each scale and within each part of the pipeline, choices in values can
                        change what is implemented <ptr target="#cicollective"/>). On a national
                        scale, highway systems, water systems, and other infrastructure are designed
                        with the desire with potential interest groups in mind: for example, water
                        policy in early twentieth-century California shored up the advantages of
                        large landholders by giving them privileged access to irrigation (Worster),
                        while the design of eighteenth-century road networks in Britain and
                        nineteenth-century land redistribution programs in America was designed to
                        give economic access to small farmers and workers (Worster, Guldi, Foner). A
                        choice of values – which either reinforce existing power dynamics or
                        counteract them — is thus at work in the design of infrastructure at every
                        level of scale. </p>
                    <p>Digital infrastructures play into the same dynamics: they redound power
                        dynamics of rich and poor nations and rich and poor communities, experts and
                        non-experts, by reinforcing existing differentials of access. On a global
                        scale, internet infrastructure is effected by choices about internet
                        providers, such as networks of physical cables that connect rich countries
                        to the exclusion of the poor translate realpolitik into technology <ptr
                            target="#starosielski2015"/>. On the geographical scale of each
                        community, smart phones and GPS usage require some levels of literacy and
                        other forms of expertise in order to be useful <ptr target="#sawyer2019"/>.
                        What’s more, the choice to maintain or not to maintain structures the
                        accessibility of infrastructure and its benefits <ptr target="#mattern2018"/>
                        <ptr target="#graham2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#henke1999"/>: as when local maintenance of water facilities,
                        delayed in Michigan, results in working-class populations being poisoned, or
                        when differential maintenance across Parisian neighborhoods results in a
                        seamless experience for an elite minority and a degraded experience for the
                        rest <ptr target="#denis2014"/>. </p>
                    <p>In creating digital infrastructures, the builders of web portals have
                        opportunities to counteract these power differentials. Builders who favor
                        the strategies of <quote rend="inline">minimal computing</quote> put their
                        websites within reach of citizens in the global south or poor neighborhoods
                        who frequently must access the internet through second-rate connections <ptr
                            target="#godh2018"/>.</p>
                    <p>Other builders of infrastructure have primarily conceived of themselves as
                        designing the tools for the coming of another community beyond the
                        imagination of the designers. For example, the activists who designed
                        toolkits for participatory mapping in the 1970s and 1980s imagined that the
                        toolsets they wove together would be used by communities for purposes beyond
                        what the original activists could imagine: and indeed, put into action, the
                        participatory maps came to be used for the purposes of monitoring pollution,
                        redistributing land, and protecting indigenous property rights (Guldi). Just
                        so, the historical function of Britain’s nineteenth-century road network
                        cannot be entirely understood through the work of engineers, but only
                        through the use of the network made by the road’s users – including
                        Methodists, journeymen, and radicals – who used the roads to create
                        communities sometimes antithetical to the capitalist and nation-building
                        purposes imagined by the network’s designers <ptr target="#guldi2012"/>. The
                        power of relinquishing control over infrastructure often makes the
                        infrastructure of comparatively long use and greater effectiveness overall. </p>
                    <p>Some scholars will resist a form of scholarly practice marked by the
                        relinquishing of control. They may argue that the value of traditional
                        scholarship reflects the scholar’s command of language, citation, and
                        transparency of sources to elucidate what facts have been used and what
                        argument is being made. Indeed, many scholarly infrastructure project
                        support direct control over the transmission of bibliographic information.
                        While a web-born scholarly edition of Mary Shelley’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Frankenstein</title>, for example, may offer a useful resource to the
                        teachers of Victorian literature grounded in printed and manuscript
                        archives, the web-born format almost entirely replicates the form of
                        traditional scholarly editions – something entirely useful for the purposes
                        of tenure and promotion. Similarly, carefully-annotated digital collections
                        of historical documents such as <title rend="italic">Vistas: Visual Culture
                            in Spanish America, 1520–1820</title> (<ref
                            target="https://vistas.ace.fordham.edu/"
                            >https://vistas.ace.fordham.edu/</ref>) represent the equivalent labor
                        of an art history exhibition or heavily-researched book. In format, these
                        tools differ very little from traditional scholarly publications in books,
                        excepting the use of hyperlinks and the scale of their accessibility.
                        Scholarly infrastructure with a traditional form may nevertheless be radical
                        in terms of its content; both the edition of <title rend="italic"
                            >Frankenstein</title> and <title rend="italic">Vistas</title> open up
                        important questions about gender and race. Not all authors of scholarly
                        infrastructure make the relinquishing of control over their sources or the
                        sources’ interpretation a feature of their design. </p>
                    <p>Projects that emphasize the <q>critical</q> use of infrastructure make at
                        least some gesture towards the relinquishing of control, pointing towards
                        the wider uses of the community. As such, they overlap with the final
                        instance of the humanistic principles, the <quote rend="inline">principle of
                            a multiplicity of humanistic desires.</quote> Infrastructure of this
                        kind resonates with participatory traditions in urban planning, where
                        planners consult the local community about the best course of development in
                        a particular neighborhood <ptr target="#friedmann1973"/>
                        <ptr target="#guldi2017"/>. There are, moreover, traditions of literature
                        and philosophy where the relinquishing of control is the hallmark of
                        utility. For Roland Barthes, one of the hallmarks <quote rend="inline"
                            >writerly literature</quote> is that it can inspire multiple readings
                        and uses in cultures far from its point of origin, and so <quote
                            rend="inline">make the reader no longer a consumer but a producer of the
                            text</quote>
                        <ptr target="#barthes1974" loc="4"/>. The creation of a meaningful
                        infrastructure project is marked by the project’s ability to support the
                        user’s active production of knowledge. </p>
                    <p>The principles outlined below investigate how scale of exposure is
                        deliberately used by certain websites to place texts of data in the public
                        realm, often marked by the relinquishing of control over the ends to which
                        the later products are put. Frequently, infrastructure projects of this sort
                        work towards the multiplication of projects well beyond those imagined or
                        intended by the designers. This article’s conclusion will strive to
                        understand what this multiplication implies for the work of scholarly
                        infrastructure.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Principle that Democratization of Access to Information Breeds Better
                        Democracy.</head>
                    <p>The experiments with infrastructure that press the principle of neutrality
                        with respect to technical literacy to its furthest extent are those that
                        underscore mass participation, and they come to us typically from science
                        and technology studies – a discipline familiar with theories of how
                        technologies define the limits of their own participation or exclusion. In
                        Science and Technology Studies, researchers have experimented with radical
                        infrastructures that extend the principle of technical accessibility past
                        the archive and web application, into a physical infrastructure accessible
                        even to individuals whose computer and internet access is limited. In his
                        dissertation on formaldehyde in FEMA trailers, anthropologist Nicholas
                        Shapiro worked with chemists to commission post cards that would test the
                        formaldehyde content in the trailers’ walls, if occupants mailed the
                        postcard to a testing facility <ptr target="#zhang2019"/>. The paper
                        infrastructure of chemical-sensitive postcards thus made chemical testing of
                        pollution in the environment radically available to ordinary citizens,
                        allowing occupants of the trailers to test their environment for noxious
                        chemicals by themselves. Infrastructure projects such as these have pressed
                        the bar of what it means to offer information directly to the public. </p>
                    <p>Early in the scholarly infrastructure turn, many designers of infrastructure
                        believed that delivering data and stories via the web offered an opportunity
                        to democratize access to both scholarship and primary sources. In 2008,
                        Harvard historian Robert Darnton was already making the case for open access
                        to the digitized books scanned by Google, Howard Rheingold’s article, <title
                            rend="quotes">Participative Pedagogy: For a Literacy of
                            Literacies</title>, for example, argued for digital practices that
                        broadened access to <quote rend="inline">literacy</quote>, broadly defined,
                        with the end of teaching <quote rend="inline">the ways people use knowledge
                            and technology to create wealth, secure freedom, resist tyranny</quote>.
                        For Rheingold, this <quote rend="inline">literacy of literacy</quote> was
                        more important than teaching the how-to of particular kinds of code or
                        technology; in essence, Rheingold was arguing that the age of the internet
                        made more necessary the proliferation of engaged and critical readings of
                        culture <ptr target="#rheingold2008"/>.</p>
                    <p> It is hard to imagine a humanities infrastructure that mirrors’ Shapiro’s
                        postcards in bringing the knowledge of the university radically to bear for
                        communities in need, but some archivists have begun to theorize the shape of
                        such a project. At the Columbia University Library, Alex Gil’s <ref
                            target="https://nimbletents.github.io/"><title rend="italic">Nimble
                                Tents</title></ref> creates digitization kits to help communities
                        rebuilding after a natural disaster to map their resources. Gil has also
                        created <title rend="quotes">The Translation Toolkit</title>, another kit
                        with which communities in impoverished neighborhoods and the developing
                        world can record their own stories and send a copy to Columbia for
                        preservation and translation – with the idea that recordings belong
                        ultimately to the community, and that Columbia can aid communities in their
                        analysis and documentation <ptr target="#gil2018"/>.</p>
                    <p>The elaborate series of scholarly articles introducing students to the Old
                        Bailey archive (<ref target="http://www.oldbailey.org"
                            >http://www.oldbailey.org</ref>) expose students to themes of poverty,
                        violence, gender, and race in Britain’s past. The website obviously holds
                        the same merit as (at least one) traditional textbook, if not many more, by
                        virtue of its carefully prepared archive and the many visualizations
                        thereof: the main use of this part of the website is to expand the scale of
                        potential readers who can potentially access these essays. </p>
                    <p> Consider <title rend="italic">EvictionLab</title>, which shares social
                        science data about the demographic effects of eviction policies around the
                        nation. <title rend="italic">EvictionaLab</title> can be seen as
                        complementary response to the social and economic critique of the harm
                        served by eviction against families of color offered by Matt Desmond’s
                        traditional scholarship, ethnographies published in the form of scholarly
                        articles. The scale of harm that Desmond uncovered in eviction was a form of
                        harm <term>at scale</term>. A critique – even a powerful one – barely
                        approximates the scale of the harm that he discovered. </p>
                    <p> Becoming a builder of infrastructure allowed Desmond to deploy his research
                            <term>at scale</term>. By creating a public portal that could answer to
                        a multiplicity of local demands for information about the local face of
                        eviction, Desmond was able to offer a level of detail that would be hard to
                        rival in a traditional book or article. In a sense, the act of building
                        allowed Desmond to enact a remedy of an appropriate scale for facing the
                        trouble that he had elsewhere critiqued. Thus while critique illuminates our
                        knowledge of harm, the limited effectiveness of critique hampers it:
                        infrastructure-building, by contrast, in the form of data portal’s like
                        Desmond’s, is a form of scholarly activity that activates a critique at
                        scale, demonstrating the relevance of an economic critique to geographical
                        locales. </p>
                    <p> The era of scholarly infrastructure has thus begun to forge a fundamentally
                        new idiom of scholarly communication, one where the intellectual labor of
                        critique can be married to the possibility of broad application at scale.
                        The proposed equivalence is ethical in nature: a deep harm, which scales to
                        the level of billions of families, requires a remedy that can travel further
                        than a single well-cited journal article. Deep harm requires a remedy at
                        scale: potentially, a remedy at scale also therefore requires not critique
                        alone but also data infrastructure. </p>
                    <p>In many cases, by using scale and relinquishing control over the uses of
                        data, infrastructure invites broadcast participation in arguments over
                        social facts and public documents. In so doing, infrastructure does the work
                        that many scholarly essays, for reasons of their small audience, often
                        simply cannot do: elevating a political critique into the public sphere.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> The Principle of Community Ownership.</head>
                    <p>In an article elsewhere, I have argued for the relevance to social science
                        and the humanities of citizen science and other movements that collect and
                        analyze data. For scholars pursuing the history of rent and eviction, for
                        instance, the labor of an individual scholar is dwarfed by the scale of
                        research imaginable if members of the public took up a scholarly charge to
                        begin collecting data about the history of rent prices, rent laws, and
                        eviction rates in every city around the world. To be sure, scholarly
                        acceptance of such a crowdsourced database would depend upon adhering to the
                        foundational principle of transparency, as well as existing standards for
                        the documentation of the <term>provenance</term> of a document <ptr
                            target="#cheney2012"/>. The payoff of building avenues towards
                        crowdsourced knowledge, however, would be an undertaking of research that
                        would dwarf contemporary undertakings in its scale and potential for
                        insight. A truly global program of insight would result. </p>
                    <p>Critical theory has long recognized the existence of principles of democratic
                        participation against which initiatives and organizations can be measured.
                        In 1968, Sheri Arnstein’s <quote rend="inline">ladder of citizen
                            participation</quote> arranged different forms of information sharing in
                        the public sphere on a hierarchy of democracy, ranging from
                            <q>manipulation</q> and <q>therapy</q> on one extreme to the devolution
                        of power at the most democratic. Arstein’s theory underscored the power
                        dynamics in information flows from government experts to the people, and
                        raised the possibility of new kinds of citizen-governed institutions, a move
                        that reflected current concerns of African-American populations in American
                        cities, but mirrored radical ideas about governance going back at least to
                        the era of the Paris Commune <ptr target="#guldi2017"/>. This early theory
                        of power and democracy in political information offers a pattern for
                        understanding the radical potential of scholarly information on the
                        internet. </p>
                    <p>Today, examples of citizen science abound, where users contribute
                        observations, insights or desires, which are exchanged over a community-run
                        infrastructure. Science and technology theorists have often critiqued the
                        first generation of citizen science for the lack of discursive engagement
                        with a program of observation laid out by experts: citizens were mobilized
                        to count birds, to cite one famous example, but not to raise critical
                        questions about how or why existing climate science had failed to be taken
                        up in American public discourse. </p>
                    <p>There is enormous variation in whom different portals allow to play and how.
                        The <title rend="italic">Legacies of British Slavery</title> project makes
                        data available to users, but stops short of allowing users to shape their
                        own inquiries, holding tight to the overall interpretation of the moment in
                        what may be informed by a concern for preserving the sacrosanct authority of
                        interpretation at a time of rising ethnic nationalism. <ref
                            target="http://evictionlab.org/">
                            <title rend="italic">Eviction Lab</title>
                        </ref> gives away the data, allowing users to make what they will of
                        demographics and instances of families ejected from their homes. The <ref
                            target="https://github.com/dbamman/book-nlp">
                            <title rend="italic">BookNLP</title>
                        </ref> software package allows users to isolate variations in the handling
                        of gender, but lacks a public portal (as of now) that would allow a
                        tech-illiterate user to engage such an analysis. Each of these decisions
                        results from a complex of ideas about the scholar’s role, the expertise of
                        their intended audience, whether scholarly production serves purposes
                        outside the academy, and what the scholar’s relationship to that public is
                        or ought to be. Those decisions are, by nature, philosophical, political,
                        and professional; they are also subject to critical debate.</p>
                    <p>Outside the academy, communities are transforming science into the practice
                        of citizen science by realizing Arnstein’s principle of participation and
                        community ownership. For example, the organization Public Lab hosts <title
                            rend="quotes">Research Notes</title> where community members like social
                        scientist Nicholas Shapiro post requests for technical expertise – in
                        Shapiro’s case, requesting help with the technical end of formaldehyde
                        testing. In another online community, a community of small farmers called
                            <title rend="italic">FarmHack</title> shares blueprints for appropriate
                        technology to make small-scale farming more economically viable. But
                        experiments of this kind are less common in the digital humanities.</p>
                    <p>Humanists who share the values of democracy would be well-advised to consider
                        whether the practice of citizen science has its place in the interpretation
                        of text: for example, whether ordinary citizens require the tools of
                        inspecting, via distant reading, the congressional or parliamentary debates
                        of their own government. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Labor of Infrastructure Building</head>

                <p>In the foregoing sections, I have surveyed a range of possible values expressed
                    by the builders of scholarly infrastructure. A proposition of this kind is
                    important because the intellectual engagement of infrastructure-builders with
                    critical thought has not always been self-evident to outsiders.</p>
                <p> Understanding value as a factor in the kind of work embodied by scholarly
                    infrastructure projects – including the bibliographic, critical, political
                    values represented by engaging in project-building as opposed to traditional
                    scholarly documentation in the form of books and articles – is crucial to having
                    those projects accepted and interpreted as interventions in the realm of
                    scholarship, where critical commentary routinely engages the kind of
                    intellectual values represented by a project and the way that data,
                    visualizations, and other forms of labor support those values. Understanding the
                    range of possible values underlying those commitments is therefore crucial, as
                    communities and scholars come to terms with the stake of committing energy to
                    infrastructure-building rather than to traditional scholarship products such as
                    grants and articles. </p>
                <p>The metaphors that I have offered above – comparing scholarly infrastructure to
                    an opera house – are also productive in a number of directions that cannot be
                    exhausted in the course of this article, especially involving the question of
                    where labor or ideological contributions occur. Panning out from the opera and
                    opera-house itself, one can see any given production of <title rend="italic"
                        >Aida</title> is itself the product of architect, composer and librettist,
                    conductor, and cast. A reader-centric interpretation even pushes this list to
                    include the audience in the theater on any given night, and their manifold
                    interpretations of the opera <ptr target="#locke2006"/>.</p>
                <p>Just so, the work of digital production and interpretation includes all of those
                    forms of invisible infrastructure that include scanning and cleaning texts,
                    storing and serving them, before the design of the infrastructure; the
                    infrastructure itself, any scholarly articles whose interpretive approach
                    depends on the infrastructure in question, and any individual users of the
                    infrastructure, whether or not they later become authors of analyses published
                    in traditional academic venues. </p>
                <p> The multiple locations of labor and interpretation in such a process constellate
                    a broader transition to a hermeneutic regime of information at scale. Elsewhere,
                    I have argued that shifts of this kind are marked by a deferment of <quote
                        rend="inline">critical thinking</quote>, where insight is produced at a
                    single point of interpretation and argumentation with the text, into a processes
                    of <quote rend="inline">critical search</quote>, where critical engagement is
                    required over the entire length of an information pipeline <ptr
                        target="#guldi2018a"/>. </p>
                <p>Appreciation for the values implicit in scholarly infrastructure has not always
                    been the tone by which digital scholarship is received by larger communities in
                    the university. In one inflammatory editorial in the <title rend="italic"
                        >Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, a scholar characterized the digital
                    humanities as being the tool of the neoliberal takeover of the university and an
                    ally in the adjunctification of the professoriate <ptr target="#brennan2017"/>.
                    In at least one tenure process with which the author is familiar, a department
                    threatened to stage a kind of inquisitorial panel to monitor a digital humanist
                    already published in traditional books and articles, because engagement with
                    digital humanities and social sciences question – including building
                    infrastructure – was understood as somehow sullying the life of the mind with
                    the dirty matter of service.<note>The scholar in question left the university in
                        protest, prior to the activation of the inquisitor panel or the tenure
                        review board. The review panel was proposed alongside a series of
                        requirements that would have allowed the department to dictate the scholar’s
                        future research projects, demands that, in the context of the scholar’s
                        publication history, appeared designed explicitly to punish new research
                        agendas. </note>
                </p>
                <p>The remedy for this failure is debate and conversation that theorizes what it is
                    that people do when they build infrastructure, and at what stages scholarly
                    discourse, humanistic discourse, technological acumen, dissent, and political
                    thought enter the process. Scholars who think critically about infrastructure
                    must advertise their critical engagement in the form of a scholarly essay that
                    reflects on the format of the infrastructure adopted and its implications. </p>
                <p> In teasing apart the range of values represented by modern infrastructure, I
                    have argued that infrastructure building implies, at minimum, a commitment on
                    the part of the scholar to <term>scale</term> and a relinquishing of
                        <emph>control</emph>, which imply a choice of values, including a set of
                        <q>traditional</q> values, such as transparency with regards to document
                    base and the knowledge of society, which are aligned with long-standing
                    commitments in the humanities and social sciences, and <q>critical</q> values,
                    such as participation and the critique of power, which are aligned with radical
                    traditions in the academy and beyond.</p>
                <p> Recognizing the choice values at stake in building infrastructure is essential,
                    I believe, to understanding much of the work in the digital humanities and
                    social sciences as well as other parts of the university today: there is
                    something on offer that has not been illuminated in the voluminous literature on
                    infrastructure, digital humanities, or the crisis of the humanities, which
                    deserves to be recognized, praised, critiqued, and pressed, because it presents
                    a challenge to contemporary practices of scholarship, and scholarly communities
                    must decide whether that challenge is worth embracing.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> What is this offering, and why has it been so submerged? </head>
                <p>On the surface, infrastructure represents a different species of animal from the
                    scholarly article, whether single-authored or authored by many individuals. In
                    some cases, like Andrew Goldstone’s <ref
                        target="https://agoldst.github.io/dfr-browser/demo/">
                        <title rend="italic">Topic Viewer</title>
                    </ref>, they are the creation of a single individual, but the individual’s
                    responsibilities include using code to who cobble together existing packages for
                    data cleaning, analysis, and visualization, as well as scholarly insight about
                    the kinds of cleaning, analysis, and visualization likely to produce insight
                    from texts of a particular type. These designs thus resemble scholarly articles
                    or narratives in that they provide users with an orientation to the data, based
                    on wide experience; but they also resemble cartography or traditional kinds of
                    data analysis in that they entail working with vast amounts of evidence to
                    produce visualizations useful to different parties for different reasons. As a
                    monument of scholarly labor and insight, the building of infrastructure
                    typically represents a major scholarly intervention – entailing more labor than
                    that included in the typical journal article in the humanities or social
                    sciences. It bears the weight of a book. </p>
                <p>In many cases, the committees that assign credit to academics for publishing
                    books and articles resist crediting the development of software with the same
                    power on the basis of the <emph>plurality</emph> of labor represented by the
                    creation of an infrastructural project. Infrastructure often represents the
                    product of collaborations, where <q>labs</q> of scholars and students, or
                    hybrids of scholars working with university staff and/or private contractors,
                    produce the design for the project and its execution. It can, after all, be
                    difficult to isolate the contribution of a single party working on a project
                        <ptr target="#edmond2015"/>. Typically, in these collaborative labs, coders
                    and scholars collaborate to design a visual and interpretive strategy that
                    governs how users interact with the data. The end product reflects ongoing
                    collaborations, much as an edited book may be conceived of and rallied by a
                    single scholar but may represent the work of many hands. </p>
                <p>In some of the most highly-developed web portals that serve humanists, the
                    infrastructure requires ongoing updates managed by graduate students, salaried
                    coders, full-time staff, and administrators, whose tasks may range from insuring
                    interoperability with users’ machines to managing lawsuits (for instance in the
                    famous case in which Thomson-Reuters sued Zotero. In any case, the range of
                    labor provided – from coding and design to data collection, cleaning, analysis,
                    and more – is more diverse than the traditional scholarly processes of archival
                    research, analysis, and writing, even where facaulty act mainly in an
                    administrative or visionary role rather than producing code themselves.
                    Overseeing the development of infrastructurerequires the scholars involved to
                    conceive of their arguments in visual terms, and to produce multiple
                    visualizations that align with different perspectives on the data in
                    question.</p>
                <p> Yet the plurality of labor necessary to realize infrastructure is only part of
                    the story of why the university community is sometimes hostile towards
                    infrastructure projects. A turn towards personal autobiography will be useful
                    here. As a scholar of the history of infrastructure who researched
                    eighteenth-century road building and wayfinding through traditional archival
                    means, I came to the digital humanities primarily as a researcher interested in
                    how keyword search was changing my own techniques of research. Initially, I
                    resisted the idea of building infrastructure, preferring to think of myself
                    exclusively as an author of books and articles and a consumer of tools developed
                    by others. </p>
                <p> The flowering of new tools in the digital humanities – the <quote rend="inline"
                        >infrastructure turn</quote> identified by Geoffrey Rockwell (2010) —
                    persuaded me that scholars with active the gap between existing tools for
                    annotation, curation, and story-telling – such as <title rend="italic"
                        >Zotero</title> and <title rend="italic">Omeka</title> – and the array of
                    text-mining and visualization practices coming into being from computer science.
                    Some of those projects were created by affiliates of research universities such
                    as George Mason, which had a firm commitment to building infrastructure, and
                    whose graduates were distinguished by their knowledge of servers and code.
                    Others were the work of senior faculty, who had already built a career composed
                    of multiple books, who turned to building infrastructure at an advanced stage in
                    their career when they could command a multi-year research project to build an
                    infrastructure around an infrastructure of particular interest to themselves and
                    their students. Admiration for those accomplishments made me question archival
                    research as the sole expression of scholarly research and argumentation, and
                    opened the door for my curiosity about infrastructure-building. </p>
                <p> In 2010, I began writing grants and talking to colleagues about the possibility
                    of building an infrastructure for the digital humanities and social sciences. I
                    imagined that building a tool that would distill scholarly knowledge into
                    frequently-repeated patterns, extending the scholar’s power of recognizing
                    patterns over tens of thousands or millions of documents, and thus acting as a
                    kind of scholarly prosthesis. Working in research-focused departments
                    nevertheless forced me to reconcile my admiration for scholarly infrastructure
                    with my own needs, as well as the needs of my students and colleagues – all of
                    us, of course, being researchers at first-tier research programs, who were
                    incentivized above all to discover new outlooks on the past, whether from
                    archivally-new materials or from a new perspective on events already known but
                    insufficiently understood. It was hard to imagine a single tool that would serve
                    this purpose. The graduate students who I worked with at Chicago had extremely
                    diverse research backgrounds and interests – ranging from early-modern Germany,
                    to modern Latin America and nineteenth-century Chicago. The tool that would
                    serve my research-focused students would necessarily need to work with documents
                    of concern to them all, using existing language-processing algorithms and
                    visualizations to offer insight into documents of different kinds. Thus it was
                    important to build a tool that would allow researchers invested in text from a
                    range of backgrounds to profit from the tools of word-count analysis and topic
                    modeling then being used by a handful of scholars in the digital humanities.</p>
                <p>Many examples mark how senior scholars skeptical of digital methods have held up
                    the career of junior scholars — even those who have otherwise fulfilled
                    traditional requirements for tenure — and this certainly seems to be the case
                    for builders of infrastructure. Such affairs undermine the progress of the
                    field, as one anecdote will illustrate. Consider the case of a scholar, known to
                    me, whose interest in digital methods had led her — after finishing a
                    traditional monograph in her field — to build a piece of digital infrastructure
                    also publish a treatise investigating the future of her field with respect to
                    the digital humanities When she did so, she was punished by her department.</p>
                <p>The grounds for tenure laid out at her hiring were reversed; she was ordered to
                    write a third book on a traditional, archival topic that was ordained by her
                    committee, and it was conveyed to her that the department was outright hostile
                    to her continued use of digital methods. Far from recognizing the value of a
                    piece of infrastructure developed by a junior scholar, her department counted
                    infrastructure as an albatross for her career.</p>
                <p>In the vita that she had submitted to her committee for tenure, this scholar
                    could count several accomplishments unusual for historians, including the
                    aforementioned infrastructure, as well as a significant grant. Following the
                    advice of colleagues in other departments, this scholar circulated a draft in
                    which the infrastructure and grant-related projects were classified under a
                    heading of <quote rend="inline">book weight projects</quote>. Her committee
                    recommended that she remove the infrastructure project to a section on <quote
                        rend="inline">miscellaneous projects</quote>. The message to her was clear:
                    infrastructure would not be valued alongside books and articles as a marker of
                    scholarly labor, intellectual value, or theory-driven critique. The double-binds
                    that this individual faced – resistance to the digital humanities, resistance to
                    infrastructure-building, and few incentives to document the critical thinking
                    behind existing infrastructure experimentation — amounted to an incentive for
                    delay. She delayed writing further about infrastructure, in part, because the
                    culture of resistance she faced meant that even this kind of scholarly
                    commentary on experimentation would itself be rendered suspect by tenure review
                    committees by the same hostility that the article needed to challenge.</p>
                <p> Things might have gone otherwise for the individual and infrastructure in
                    question, of course, had there been intellectual apparatus that considered the
                    development of infrastructure as a form of scholarship, infused with the values
                    of critique: her investments of time might have been viewed as a viable form of
                    scholarship and a valuable investment in future forms of scholarly community,
                    rather than a dangerous action inappropriate for junior faculty. The problem was
                    essentially that investments in scholarly infrastructure were obscure from the
                    point-of-view of existing scholarly institutions; they could be seen neither as
                    a form of scholarly argumentation, nor as a critical reflection on contemporary
                    scholarly practice. In order for that resistance to give way, scholars would
                    need to document the history, debate, and values out of which new experiments
                    with infrastructure were emerging.</p>
                <p> Institutional resistance to a culture of experimentation, however, is a wicked
                    problem, in that no one solution is sufficient to overcome it: a single major
                    publication is rarely sufficient to shift a culture. In my own career, I began
                    to develop such a justification for scholarly infrastructure projects in my
                    second book, <title rend="italic">The History Manifesto</title>, which set
                    forward the promise of tools like topic modeling for opening up longue-durée
                    analysis of problems to historical analysis.</p>
                <p>Failure to recognize or support infrastructure as a scholarly achievement has
                    consequences. Today, the infrastructure in the story is no longer maintained — a
                    fact that highlights the differentials of commitment between senior faculty and
                    junior faculty. As with the train system in the Parisian suburbs, junior faculty
                    projects unprotected by senior administrators are liable to be refused
                    maintenance and so degrade. I delayed writing explicitly about infrastructure as
                    scholarly production and intellectual critique. Very few articles reflect on the
                    process of building or state a case for the role of argumentation and thought in
                    infrastructure design; there was very little, in 2013 and 2014, to point to by
                    way of a firmly-established <soCalled>infrastructure turn</soCalled> that would
                    be acceptable to senior historians. Indeed, at 2019, this essay offers a
                    much-delayed assessment of the role of critical thinking in the design of <title
                        rend="italic">Paper Machines</title> in 2009-13.</p>
                <p> The double-binds that I faced in 2014 — resistance to the digital humanities,
                    resistance to infrastructure-building, and few incentives to document the
                    critical thinking behind existing infrastructure experimentation — amounted to
                    an incentive for delay. After initial hostility to the broad-brushstrokes with
                    which we praised the potential of the digital humanities in the <title
                        rend="italic">Manifesto</title>, I delayed writing further about
                    infrastructure, in part, because the culture of resistance I faced meant that
                    even this kind of scholarly commentary on experimentation would itself be
                    rendered suspect in tenure review committees by the same hostility that the
                    article needed to challenge.</p>
                <p>We might refer to a culture that resists innovation, because the terms that
                    inspire innovation are obscure and hostility is rife, as a <q>culture of
                        delay</q>.</p>
                <p> My own partial and much-delayed engagement with these problems may be
                    symptomatic of larger failures of acknowledgement for the builders of scholarly
                    infrastructure, as well as our own hesitance to explain our values. Scholars who
                    have come to make major investments of time and energy in building
                    infrastructure rarely justify those projects in scholarly or public venues,
                    perhaps because the intellectual labor behind the work or the time dedicated to
                    infrastructure projects is likely to be dismissed, and the labor judged with
                    hostility. The failure of institutions to recognize or reward scholarly
                    infrastructure compounds almost certainly compounds scholars’ slowness to
                    highlight the intellectual values or merit expressed by their infrastructure
                    building projects. </p>
                <p> I therefore propose that the remedy for culture of delay is, ironically, more
                    theory: theory in the service of illuminating the alignments that compel some
                    scholars to experiment with building and sharing infrastructure at scale. The
                    builders of infrastructure need to theorize openly about the choices they have
                    made and the values that those choices represent. The foregoing principles have
                    been offered for the sake of waymarking out some broad and familiar territory,
                    but future theorists of scholarly infrastructure will necessarily have to take
                    up the challenge of setting up their own waymarkers, or arguing with and thus
                    refining the extremely preliminary terms in which I have framed values such as
                        <q>community ownership</q> or <q>transparency</q>. In that process of
                    scholarly debate, a trail of references will be created that will familiarize
                    critical thinking about infrastructure for mainstream communities of scholars.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion: The Work of Scholarly Infrastructure Projects </head>
                <p> What sort of work, then, is the labor that goes into a humanistic web site? This
                    article has already suggested that the principles governing that academic labor
                    reflect not only bibliographic and scholarly traditions, but also discourse from
                    critical theory about the liberatory potential of knowledge and participatory
                    research. A strong argument has thus just been made for infrastructure-building,
                    in the humanities, as a site of intellectual argumentation, so long as the
                    process of designing and building the infrastructure entails some moment of
                    reflection upon the principles that governed its design and their inspiration
                    (which need not, of course, replicate the principles outlined here).</p>
                <p>Clear though the argument may be for critical reflections on infrastructure as a
                    form of scholarly argument, some account must be given of why so little critical
                    discourse exists on the building of digital humanities projects of this kind. </p>
                <p>This article has proposed nine criteria of critical thinking about infrastructure
                    demonstrated in mainstream projects which demonstrate an engagement by the
                    designers with ideas about the humanities. Two of those criteria – those I have
                    labeled <q>critical principles</q> – demonstrate that scholarly infrastructure
                    embodies political and argumentative work prized by some scholars, for example,
                    those concerned with the defense of democracy, or the radicalization of
                    community access to knowledge. Projects that demonstrate these criteria show
                    that the designers have actively prepared the infrastructure so as to engage
                    with the concerns of their discipline, and building, under these concerns,
                    represents an act of engaged criticism and argument. Many of what I have called
                    the <q>bibliographic principles</q> also demonstrate an engagement with critical
                    thinking, and also with the political insights of social theory, in the form of
                    an engagement with infrastructure as a tool of power. Infrastructure projects
                    that demonstrate these both criteria suggest that practitioners have not only
                    engaged with the concerns of their discipline, but with the critical theory of
                    the last half-century as well, particularly as translated through the
                    social/historical infrastructure turn and its critique of the infrastructure of
                    knowledge-making. </p>
                <p>In other words, the realization of the critical principles in acts of scholarly
                    development demonstrate that a wide variety of infrastructure-builders are
                    actively engaging a wide-ranging critique of the institutions of knowledge and
                    their political power. Here, scholarly engagement and argumentation are taken to
                    an extreme largely unknown in the traditional disciplines. A double
                    infrastructure turn – combining social insight and technological building – is
                    at work, which merits the inspection of scholars across the academy.
                    Infrastructure building is the present-day site of engagement with the insights
                    about power and governmentality that defined the scholarly infrastructure turn.
                </p>
            </div>
        	<div type="appendix" xml:id="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>The author wishes to thank Colin Allen and the anonymous reviewer from <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ</title> for their insightful engagement and generous
                    reactions, as well as the editors and other contributors to the special
                    issue.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aiello2018" label="Aiello et al. 2018">Aiello, Daniella, et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Eviction Lab Misses the Mark</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Shelterforce</title> (August 22, 2018), accessed Apr. 8, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://shelterforce.org/2018/08/22/eviction-lab-misses-the-mark/"
                        >https://shelterforce.org/2018/08/22/eviction-lab-misses-the-mark/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aspden2019" label="Aspden 2019">Aspden, Suzanne. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction</title>. In Suzanne Aspden, ed., <title rend="italic">Operatic
                        Geographies: The Place of Opera and the Opera House</title>. University of
                    Chicago Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arnstein1969" label="Arnstein 1969">Arnstein, Sherry R. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Ladder Of Citizen Participation</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of the American Institute of Planners</title> 35, no.
                    4 (1969): 216–24. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01944366908977225"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/01944366908977225</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bamman2014" label="Bamman et al. 2014">Bamman, David, Ted Underwood
                    and Noah Smith. <title rend="quotes">A Bayesian Mixed Effects Model of Literary
                        Character</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 52nd Annual
                        Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>, 2014:
                    370-379.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barthes1974" label="Barthes 1974">Barthes, Roland. <title
                        rend="italic">S/Z: An Essay</title>. Trans. Richard Miller. New York: Hill
                    and Wang, 1974.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brennan2017" label="Brennan 2017">Brennan, Timothy. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital-Humanities Bust.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title> (October 15,
                    2017). <ref
                        target="https://www.chronicle.com/article/the-digital-humanities-bust/"
                        >https://www.chronicle.com/article/the-digital-humanities-bust/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cheney2012" label="Cheney et al. 2012">Cheney, James, Anthony
                    Finkelstein, Bertram Ludaescher, and Stijn Vansummeren. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Principles of Provenance (Dagstuhl Seminar 12091)</title>. Edited by James
                    Cheney, Anthony Finkelstein, Bertram Ludaescher, and Stijn Vansummeren. <title
                        rend="italic">Dagstuhl Reports</title> 2, no. 2 (2012): 84–113. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4230/DagRep.2.2.84"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4230/DagRep.2.2.84</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cicollective" label="CI Collective">CI Collective. <title
                        rend="quotes">CI Studies Bibliography</title>. <ref
                        target="https://cistudies.org/critical-infrastructures-bibliography/"
                        >https://cistudies.org/critical-infrastructures-bibliography/</ref>, no
                    date.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clement2017" label="Clement et al. 2017">Clement, Tanya E., et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">Challenges for New Infrastructures and Paradigms in DH
                        Curricular Program Development</title>. <title rend="italic">DH</title>,
                    2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="denis2014" label="Denis and Pontille 2014">Denis, Jérôme, and David
                    Pontille. <title rend="quotes">Material Ordering and the Care of
                        Things</title>. <title rend="italic">Science, Technology, &amp; Human
                        Values</title> 40, no. 3 (2014): 338–67. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243914553129"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243914553129</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edmond2015" label="Edmond 2015">Edmond, Jennifer. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collaboration and Infrastructure</title>. In <title rend="italic">A New
                        Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, 54–65. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd,
                    2015. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch4"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch4</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="felski2015" label="Felski 2015">Felski, Rita. <title rend="italic">The
                        Limits of Critique</title>. University of Chicago Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders2013" label="Flanders and Hamlin 2013">Flanders, Julia, and
                    Scott Hamlin. <title rend="quotes">TAPAS: Building a TEI Publishing and
                        Repository Service</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text
                        Encoding Initiative</title>, no. Issue 5, Issue 5, Text Encoding Initiative
                    Consortium, Apr. 2013. <title rend="italic">journals.openedition.org</title>,
                        doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.788"
                    >10.4000/jtei.788</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="friedmann1973" label="Friedmann 1973">Friedmann, John. <title
                        rend="italic">Retracking America: A Theory of Transactive Planning</title>.
                    Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1973. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gil2018" label="Gil 2018">Gil, Alex. <title rend="quotes">Nimble
                        Tents</title>. College Park, Maryland: University of Maryland (Tuesday,
                    November 6, 2018). <ref
                        target="https://mith.umd.edu/dialogues/dd-fall-2018-alex-gil/"
                        >https://mith.umd.edu/dialogues/dd-fall-2018-alex-gil/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="godh2018" label="GO::DH 2018">GO::DH. <title rend="quotes">Minimal
                        Computing (GO::DH Site)</title>. <title rend="italic">Minimal
                        Computing</title>, 2018. <ref target="http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/"
                        >http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2018" label="Gold 2018">Gold, Matthew K. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Response to Critical Infrastructure Studies Panel</title>, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:17831/"
                        >https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:17831/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gourley2010" label="Gourley and Battino Viterbo">Gourley, Donald and
                    Paolo Battino Viterbo. <title rend="quotes">A Sustainable Repository
                        Infrastructure for Digital Humanities: The DHO Experience.</title> Digital
                    Heritage, Euro-Mediterranean Conference. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2010,
                    473–81, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-16873-4_38"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-16873-4_38</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="graham2007" label="Graham and Thrift 2007">Graham, Stephen, and Nigel
                    Thrift. <title rend="quotes">Out of Order: Understanding Repair and
                        Maintenance</title>. <title rend="italic">Theory, Culture, and
                        Society</title> 24, no. 3 (2007): 10–11. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407075954"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407075954</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gpp2017" label="GPP 2017">Grassroots Policy Project. <title
                        rend="quotes">Building Social Movement Infrastructure</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Racial Equity Tools</title>, 2017. <ref
                        target="http://www.racialequitytools.org/resourcefiles/socialmovement_infrastructure.pdf"
                        >http://www.racialequitytools.org/resourcefiles/socialmovement_infrastructure.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guldi2012" label="Guldi 2012">Guldi, Jo. <title rend="italic">Roads to
                        Power: Britain Invents the Infrastructure State</title>. Cambridge, Mass.:
                    Harvard University Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guldi2017" label="Guldi 2017">Guldi, Jo. <title rend="quotes">A
                        History of the Participatory Map.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Public Culture</title> 29, no. 1 81 (January 1, 2017):
                    79–112. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/08992363-3644409"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1215/08992363-3644409</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guldi2018a" label="Guldi 2018a">Guldi, Jo. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Critical Search: A Procedure for Guided Reading in Large-Scale Textual
                        Corpora</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title>
                    (2018), <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22148/16.030"
                        >https://doi.org/10.22148/16.030</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guldi2018b" label="Guldi 2018b">Guldi, Jo. <title rend="quotes">Global
                        Questions About Rent and the Longue Durée of Urban Power, 1848 to the
                        Present</title>. <title rend="italic">New Global Studies</title> 12, no. 1
                    (2018): 37–63. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/ngs-2018-0012"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1515/ngs-2018-0012</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henke1999" label="Henke 1999">Henke, Christopher R. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Mechanics of Workplace Order: Toward a Sociology of
                        Repair</title>. <title rend="italic">Berkeley Journal of
                    Sociology</title> 44, no. 1999–2000 (1999): 55–81. <ref
                        target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41035546"
                        >http://www.jstor.org/stable/41035546</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jyoti1992" label="Jyoti 1992">Jyoti, Hosagrahar. <title rend="quotes"
                        >City as Durbar: Theater and Power in Imperial Delhi</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Forms of Dominance: On the Architecture and Urbanism of the
                        Colonial Enterprise</title>, 1992, 83–105.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kraicer2019" label="Kraicer and Piper 2019">Kraicer, Eve and Andrew
                    Piper. <title rend="quotes">Social Characters: The Hierarchy of Gender in
                        Contemporary English-Language Fiction.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title> (2019), <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.22148/16.032"
                        >https://doi.org/10.22148/16.032</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lansdall-welfare2017" label="Lansdall-Welfare et al. 2017"
                    >Lansdall-Welfare,Thomas, Saatviga Sudhahar, et al. <title rend="quotes">Content
                        Analysis of 150 Years of British Periodicals</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >PNAS (Proceedings of the National Academy of the Sciences)</title>, vol.
                    114, no. 4, Jan. 2017, pp. E457–E465, doi:<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1606380114"
                        >10.1073/pnas.1606380114</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu 2012">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes">Where Is
                        Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>, in Matthew Gold and
                    Lauren Klein, eds, <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012),
                    accessed January 29, 2019, <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/20"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/20</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2016" label="Liu 2016">Liu, Alan. <title rend="italic">Drafts
                        for Against the Cultural Singularity</title> (book in progress). 2 May
                        2016. <ref
                        target="https://liu.english.ucsb.edu/drafts-for-against-the-cultural-singularity"
                        >http://liu.english.ucsb.edu/drafts-for-against-the-cultural-singularity</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="locke2006" label="Locke 2006">Locke, Ralph P. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><title rend="italic">Aida</title> and Nine Readings of Empire</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Nineteenth-Century Music Review</title>, vol. 3, no. 1,
                    June 2006, pp. 45–72. <title rend="italic">Crossref</title>, doi:<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1479409800000343"
                        >10.1017/S1479409800000343</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lothian2013" label="Lothian and Phillips 2013">Lothian, Alexis and
                    Amanda Phillips, <title rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities Mean Transformative
                        Critique?</title> E-Media Studies 3.1 (2013): DOI: <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1349/PS1.1938-6060.A.425"
                        >10.1349/PS1.1938-6060.A.425</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mattern2014" label="Mattern 2014">Mattern, Shannon. <title
                        rend="quotes">Library as Infrastructure</title>. <title rend="italic">Places
                        Journal</title>, June 2014. <title rend="italic">placesjournal.org</title>,
                        doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.22269/140609"
                    >10.22269/140609</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mattern2018" label="Mattern 2018">Mattern, Shannon. <title
                        rend="quotes">Maintenance and Care</title>. <title rend="italic">Places
                        Journal</title>, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://placesjournal.org/article/maintenance-and-care/"
                        >https://placesjournal.org/article/maintenance-and-care/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2010" label="McPherson 2010">McPherson, Tara. <title
                        rend="quotes">Scaling Vectors: Thoughts on the Future of Scholarly
                        Communication</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic
                        Publishing</title>, vol. 13, no. 2, Fall 2010, doi:<ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0013.208"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0013.208</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nimbletents" label="Nimble Tents"><title rend="quotes">What is the
                        Nimble Tents Toolkit?</title><ref target="https://nimbletents.github.io/"
                        >https://nimbletents.github.io/</ref>, no date.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2013" label="Posner 2013">Posner, Miriam. <title rend="quotes"
                        >No Half Measures: Overcoming Common Challenges to Doing Digital Humanities
                        in the Library</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Library
                        Administration</title> 53, no. 1 (January 1, 2013): 43–52. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756694"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756694</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rheingold2008" label="Rheingold 2008">Rheingold, Howard. <title
                        rend="quotes">Participative Pedagogy: For a Literacy of Literacies</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Freesouls</title>, ed. Joi Ito. Taiwan: Adams, 2008.
                        <ref
                        target="http://freesouls.cc/essays/03-howard-rheingold-participative-pedagogy-for-a-literacy-of-literacies.html"
                        >http://freesouls.cc/essays/03-howard-rheingold-participative-pedagogy-for-a-literacy-of-literacies.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2019" label="Risam 2019">Risam, Roopika. New Digital Worlds :
                    Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy. Evanston,
                    Illinois: Northwestern University Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2010" label="Rockwell 2010">Rockwell, Geoffrey. <title
                        rend="quotes">As Transparent as Infrastructure: On the research of
                        cyberinfrastructure in the humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Online
                        Humanities Scholarship: The Shape of Things to Come</title>. Edited by
                    Jerome McGann. Rice University Press, 2010. <ref
                        target="https://cnx.org/contents/PVdH0-lD@1.3:_USvuzFn@2/As-Transparent-as-Infrastructure-On-the-research-of-cyberinfrastructure-in-the-humanities"
                        >https://cnx.org/contents/PVdH0-lD@1.3:_USvuzFn@2/As-Transparent-as-Infrastructure-On-the-research-of-cyberinfrastructure-in-the-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sawyer2019" label="Sawyer et al. 2019">Sawyer, S., Erickson, I., &amp;
                    Jarrahi, M. <title rend="quotes">Infrastructural competence.</title> In J.
                    Vertesi &amp; D. Ribes (eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital STS: A field
                        guide</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2019,
                    235-252.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="so2019" label="So et al. 2019">So, Richard, et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Race, Writing, and Computation: Racial Difference and the US
                        Novel, 1880-2000</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural
                        Analytics</title>, 2019. <title rend="italic">Crossref</title>, doi:<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.22148/16.031">10.22148/16.031</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="starosielski2015" label="Starosielski 2015">Starosielski, Nicole.
                        <title rend="italic">The Undersea Network</title>. Raleigh: Duke University
                    Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2018" label="Underwood et al. 2018">Underwood, Ted, et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Transformation of Gender in English-Language
                        Fiction</title>. Cultural Analytics. February 12, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11035"
                        >https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11035</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanzundert2012" label="Van Zundert 2012">Van Zundert, Joris.<title
                        rend="quotes">If You Build It, Will We Come? Large Scale Digital
                        Infrastructures as a Dead End for Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Historical Social Research / Historische
                        Sozialforschung</title> 37, no. 3 (141) (2012): 165–86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vacano2017" label="Vacano et al. 2017">Vacano, Claudia von, Abigail T.
                    De Kosnik, and Stephen Best. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities at Berkeley
                        and the Digital Life Project</title>. In <title rend="italic">DH</title>,
                    2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vertesi2019" label="Vertesi and Ribers 2019">Vertesi, Janet, and David
                    Ribes. <title rend="italic">DigitalSTS: A Field Guide for Science &amp;
                        Technology Studies</title>. Princeton University Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vismann2008" label="Vismann and Winthrop-Young 2008">Vismann,
                    Cornelia, and Geoffrey Winthrop-Young. <title rend="italic">Files: Law and Media
                        Technology</title>. Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wagner2015" label="Wagner et al. 2015">Wagner, Claudia, et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">It's a Man's Wikipedia? Asssessing Gender Inequality in an
                        Online Enyclopedia</title>. The International AAAI Conference on Web and
                    Social Media (ICWSM 2015), <ref target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.06307v2"
                        >https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.06307v2</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weil2006" label="Weil 2006">Weil, Benjamin. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Rivers Come: Colonial Flood Control and Knowledge Systems in the Indus
                        Basin, 1840s-1930s</title>. <title rend="italic">Environment and
                        History</title>, 2006, 3–29.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="williams2008" label="Williams 2008">Williams, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cultural Origins and Environmental Implications of Large Technological
                        Systems</title>. <title rend="italic">Science in Context</title> 6, no. 02
                    (2008): 377–403. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zhang2019" label="Zhang et al. 2019">Zhang, Siyang, Nicholas Shapiro,
                    Gretchen Gehrke, Jessica Castner, Zhenlei Liu, Beverly Guo, Romesh Prasad, et
                    al. <title rend="quotes">Smartphone App for Residential Testing of Formaldehyde
                        (SmART-Form)</title>. <title rend="italic">Building and Environment</title>
                    148 (January 15, 2019): 567–78. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2018.11.029"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2018.11.029</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
