<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive
                    Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language
                    Acquisition, and New Literacies</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Melinda A. <dhq:family>Cro</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Kansas State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>macro@ksu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Melinda A. Cro is Associate Professor of French at Kansas State
                            University. Her research areas are early modern French and Italian
                            literature, the pastoral mode, and methods for teaching literature and
                            culture in second language acquisition settings. She has published in a
                            variety of journals, including <title rend="italic">The French
                                Review</title>, <title rend="italic">French Studies</title>, and
                                <title rend="italic">Romance Notes</title>, and is the founder of
                            the Early Modern Humanities Lab, an initiative for working one-on-one
                            with student researchers on projects that combine digital humanities,
                            pedagogy, and early modern literature. Her most recent monograph, <title
                                rend="italic">Integrating the Digital Humanities in the Second
                                Language Classroom</title> (Georgetown UP, 2020), offers a practical
                            guide to implementing DH in the L2 context. She currently serves as
                            Contributing Editor for Seventeenth-Century French Studies in <title
                                rend="italic">The Year’s Work in Modern Languages</title>
                            (Brill).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sara K. <dhq:family>Kearns</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Kansas State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>skearns@ksu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sara K. Kearns is a Professor in the Libraries at Kansas State University
                            and currently serves as the Academic Services Librarian for the
                            Humanities. Her research areas are diverse while remaining rooted in
                            information literacy and new literacies. She is co-founder of the New
                            Literacies Alliance, a multi-institutional project that creates online,
                            interactive, open education lessons related to information literacy. She
                            is also co-author of the book, <title rend="italic">Creating and Sharing Online Library
                            Instruction</title> (Neal-Schuman, 2017), which offers guidance on
                            interinstitutional collaborations.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000443</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-11-26" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article describes a collaboration between two tenured faculty members (one
                    in the library and one in a department of modern languages) at a large,
                    land-grant institution who sought to introduce a mixed undergraduate and
                    graduate seminar in French literature to DH methods in the second-language
                    classroom culminating in a digital mapping project. Lacking explicit previous
                    training in DH, faculty drew on second language (L2) pedagogy, new literacies,
                    and DH pedagogy to develop an inclusive approach to course design and
                    implementation. The approach focused on students’ development of agency and
                    authority as rising scholars while underscoring conceptions of labor and
                    professional development in the humanities. There is limited scholarship
                    addressing implementing DH in a L2 classroom. However, implementing a combined
                    approach where one pedagogy influenced the other afforded the opportunity to
                    critically consider the role of multilingualism and multiculturalism in a
                    global, open DH context. We adopted this approach in concert with lessons drawn
                    from theories of information literacy and new literacies. This transdisciplinary
                    method encouraged careful consideration of design and implementation given that
                    how information is processed, acquired, and communicated are key concerns in
                    both L2 classrooms and new literacies.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Analyzes the implementation of DH theories and methods in designing and teaching
                    a university-level second-language course</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages
                    and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a
                    digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century
                    French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in
                    digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are
                    disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern
                    Languages department is inherently different from English and history
                    in an anglophone context like the United States in that
                    all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic
                    proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal. Whether it be a language skills
                    course focused on composition and grammar, a culture course, or a literature
                    course, communicative language teaching necessitates a carefully scaffolded
                    approach to maximize individual learners’ linguistic development and achieve
                    programmatic learning outcomes. In Modern Language courses, there is a double
                    concern, first on the course content itself and evaluating texts from thematic,
                    theoretical, or cultural perspectives, and secondly on finding the means to do
                    so linguistically in a language that is not one’s own. For example, reading a
                    novel in the second language is a balancing act between developing an
                    understanding of what is being said in the target language and how it is
                    communicated. Additionally, the L2 classroom builds an immersive community of
                    language users where the focus is on how information (language, concepts, texts)
                    is processed, skills are acquired, and understanding is communicated amongst
                    users of the target language. The inherently collaborative and cooperative
                    nature of the L2 classroom, where meaning is built and evaluated in a community
                    setting, parallels the skills and methods valued in the DH classroom. This focus
                    on meaning making is consonant with approaches explored by new literacies in
                    examining technology as a nexus through which community and meaning converge.
                    While there are inherent parallels between these approaches, pedagogical texts
                    that focus on integrating the digital humanities in, for example, the
                    second-language context are few and far between <ptr target="#pitman2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#cro2020"/>. It is problematic that DH in the US has focused
                    primarily and nearly exclusively on implementation in English-only environments
                    given both the diversity of languages and experiences in the country itself, of
                    the student populations targeted by DH in American higher ed institutions, and
                    the purported global, public, open perspective indicative of work in DH <ptr
                        target="#gil2016"/>.</p>
                <p>Steeped in a methodology that values collaboration, creativity, and digital
                    literacy, DH is perhaps most successful in helping students to consider
                    critically the potential for interdisciplinary, cooperative, and generative
                    approaches to cultural and literary studies. This approach seems particularly
                    apt for the L2 classroom. Indeed, both DH and Modern Languages may be
                    characterized as inter- or transdisciplinary in nature with practitioners who
                    draw from the realms of various subject areas like history, literature, art,
                    philosophy, technology, design, etc. <ptr target="#pitman2017"/>. This echoes
                    the often-interdisciplinary nature of work in an academic library. Academic
                    librarians balance an expertise in information-seeking behaviors with the
                    discipline-specific research methods of the teaching departments with which they
                    liaise. They work with researchers to weave together information resources and
                    methods from multiple disciplines, such as when guiding a historian through
                    economic datasets. Additionally, academic librarians emphasize the critical
                    evaluation and use of information and, increasingly, work with students and
                    faculty as content creators as well as consumers <ptr target="#kuglitsch2015"/>.
                    L2 educators and academic librarians share a common mission in educating
                    students to the degree that the students can exert their agency over research
                    decisions. Students in an upper-level L2 class who are transitioning into
                    careers or graduate degree programs need to be explicitly aware of themselves as
                    creators of new scholarship. New literacies studies provides context for
                    engagement with literature in an online environment. This multifaceted theory is
                    used to study, among other things, reading online. Most important for an L2 and
                    DH classroom, new literacies explores the ways in which reading, writing, and
                    communicating using technologies reflect the communities that engage in those
                    practices <ptr target="#coiro2008"/>. Knobel and Lankshear particularly focus on
                    the <quote rend="inline" source="#knobel2014">participatory, collaborative, and
                        distributed, and less <q>published,</q> less <q>author‐centric,</q> and less
                            <q>individual</q></quote> nature of new literacies <ptr
                        target="#knobel2014" loc="98"/>, which strongly echoes DH practices. Given
                    the similarities between the practitioners’ disciplines and the course goals, a
                    DH-inflected class seemed a productive opportunity for engagement.</p>
                <p>We introduced students to DH methods and tools that informed their ability to
                    design and create a digital research project. The project, however, presented
                    challenges for the professors. Firstly, at the time of the course, neither of us
                    had any formal training in DH and, given the lack of institutional resources for
                    the same, we undertook a <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#harris2013">plucky</quote> <ptr target="#harris2013"/></cit> DIY approach to learning the tools and
                    designing assignments. We both brought some prior experience with DH to the
                    course, and our pedagogy reflected our understanding that DH was not magical
                        <ptr target="#gianetti2017"/> but a practical means of engaging various
                    approaches to literary analysis. In a previous course drawing on DH offered in
                    fall 2016, the professor co-designed and taught a translation and archival
                    project examining WWII correspondence wherein students developed a <ref
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/french-freedom-papers/index">Scalar
                        site</ref> to share information regarding the archive with interested
                    members of the academy and the public.<note><title rend="italic">French Freedom
                            Papers</title> by KSU French 720: <ref
                            target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/french-freedom-papers/index"
                            >http://scalar.usc.edu/works/french-freedom-papers/index</ref>.</note>
                    During that course, the librarian guided students in the research process <ptr
                        target="#antonioli2018"/>. The digital publishing project revealed the
                    compounding complexities of introducing and completing a DH-project in a second
                    language within the constraints of a sixteen-week class. While creating a
                    tangible product was satisfying, our continued exploration of DH led us to
                    reconsider DH as a series of experiences. The focus in <emph>this</emph> course,
                    rather than digital publishing as in the previous experience, was to explore
                    tabular data and visualization as a means of enhancing student approaches to
                    textual and data analysis in the literature classroom. Rather than prioritizing
                    the research essay or the final project as the ultimate expression of knowledge,
                    we drew out the research process into an array of smaller, low-stakes
                    assignments and encouraged students to experiment and propose means of analyzing
                    the texts from a perspective informed by both digital and traditional approaches
                    to the material. We were inspired by digital scholars like Katherine Harris
                    (2013), who proposes a practical, hands-on, collaborative approach to
                    implementing digital humanities in the classroom, and Jentery Sayers (2011)
                    whose <quote rend="inline">tinker-centric</quote> approach also calls for
                    experimentation and freedom to play in the digital classroom. The challenge that
                    had to be considered in design was that students had varying degrees of digital
                    readiness. While technically in the generation commonly called <q>digital
                        natives</q>, students were not, in fact, fluent in all technologies, as has
                    been noted by others <ptr target="#locke2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#prensky2001"/>. This meant that any DH activity had to engage and
                    challenge students across the IT skill spectrum.</p>
                <p>Despite these challenges, the course was successful in that students not only
                    participated in and reflected upon processes for textual analysis and
                    experimentation but examined ways for designing future projects. This
                    necessitated also considering what their status as students at an institution of
                    higher education afforded them in terms of access, and how they might continue
                    and modify their approaches upon graduation in a professional context. The
                    result was an inclusive and productive experience that underscored collaboration
                    and equitable teamwork in the confines of the classroom to model future work in
                    the field. It should be noted, however, that the output did not necessarily
                    succeed in a traditional sense. Students designed a project that ultimately did
                    not correspond to their expectations, but that moment of flux allowed for
                    productive reflection on project design. Our approach mimicked what Croxall and
                    Warnick have identified as <quote rend="inline">Failure as Epistemology</quote>
                    <ptr target="#croxall2016"/>, a pedagogical approach that recognizes and
                    encourages what might be construed as failure in order to offer students an
                    opportunity to reflect on the task, the process, and on questions related to
                    design, user interface, and implementation. Leaving space for failure, for
                    imperfections, for evaluating results that do not correspond to the perceived
                    goals afforded learners the opportunity to develop resiliency and a growth
                    mindset. In this case study, we analyze the productive spaces generated by a
                    DHL2 pedagogy. Below we offer an overview of the pertinent DH and second
                    language acquisition theories and pedagogical best practices that informed our
                    course design; describe the course objectives and projects; and outline the
                    impact that the convergence of DH, L2 pedagogy, and new literacies had on our
                    approach.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Toward an Inclusive, Interdisciplinary Pedagogy</head>
                <p>While there has been an increase in the attention given to DH pedagogy, termed
                        <q>digital pedagogy</q> by many practitioners, the number of resources
                    dealing specifically with DH in the L2 context are scarce.<note>See the
                        forthcoming volume, <title rend="italic">Integrating the Digital Humanities
                            into the Second Language Classroom</title>, by Melinda A. Cro
                        (Georgetown UP, 2020) for a proposed theoretical frame and approach to
                        combining DH and L2 pedagogy. Cro maintains the distinction between <q>DH
                        pedagogy</q> and <q>digital pedagogy</q> as the latter tends to elide with
                        technological approaches to teaching that recall significant work already
                        completed in the field of L2 pedagogy (González-Lloret 2016, Blake
                        2008).</note> Several books offer varying approaches and practical advice
                    with an overview of tools <ptr target="#battershill2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#gardiner2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#hirsch2012"/> and a recent issue of <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title> (11.3, 2017) focused on DH undergraduate
                    education. Even so, none of these sources explicitly describe how to implement a
                    DH approach in the L2 classroom. This is particularly troubling given that DH is
                    most effective from a pedagogical perspective when integrated and localized in a
                    humanities course <ptr target="#cordell2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#antonioli2018"/>. Pitman and Taylor (2017) note a similar lack of
                    examples of DH in the Modern Languages and argue cogently for a <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#pitman2017">critical DHML approach</quote>; that is,
                    a <quote rend="inline" source="#pitman2017">hybrid Modern Languages and Digital
                        Humanities framework</quote> (para. 33) that capitalizes on the shared
                    transdisciplinary nature of the two disciplines to examine how DH practices are
                    inflected linguistically and culturally in a global context.<note>The Modern
                        Language Association’s Annual Convention 2019 featured a panel addressing
                        Digital Humanities and Modern Languages, presided by Élika Ortega.</note>
                    Global DH focuses on understanding the
                    heterogeneous nature of digital practices across languages and cultures <ptr
                        target="#priego2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#gil2016"/> rather than assuming all digital experiences and
                    encounters parallel those of anglophone cultures, a critical consideration for
                    an increasingly globalized world. This perspective parallels second language
                    student training. Examining cultural artifacts from a critical distance and
                    comparing personal experiences with those described in the L2 cultural landscape
                    are core aspects of the World Readiness Standards developed by the American
                    Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages (ACTFL) <ptr target="#actfl"/>.
                    This is a practical skill that serves L2 students well as they encounter digital
                    artifacts and consider how the digital is designed and utilized both in L1
                    (first language) and L2 contexts.</p>
                <p>In addition to the lack of scholarship addressing combined approaches to DH and
                    L2 pedagogy, many practitioners come to DH without the training and support
                    offered in large DH centers in R1 academic institutions. DIY and individual
                    ingenuity often guide approaches to integrating DH in the humanities <ptr
                        target="#harris2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#roued-cunlife2016"/>. Others note that DH is built upon <quote
                        rend="inline">kludges</quote>, workarounds, and the potential for failure;
                    it is rarely an orderly process <ptr target="#presner2009"/>. This reality
                    conditioned our design, both in terms of the course as a whole and the project
                    in particular. While conceptualizing the course, we were cognizant of the
                    emphasis by some in the DH community that unless someone is building, or
                    designing so that others can build, that person is not actually participating in
                    DH <ptr target="#burdick2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#ramsay2013a"/>
                    <ptr target="#ramsay2013b"/>
                    <ptr target="#ramsay2012"/>. We disagree. While building is an important aspect
                    of DH, much can be gained through experimenting with existing tools,
                    particularly for learners who may not have extensive backgrounds in coding.
                    Additionally, the definition of building could be more widely and inclusively
                    construed to reflect an attention to design and experimentation. This was the
                    focus of our own intervention. A student in their first French class will not
                    begin by reading a text as complex as, for example, the travel diaries of Jean
                        Chardin.<note>Jean Chardin (1643-1715) was a French merchant who traveled
                        extensively throughout Persia and the Near East during the seventeenth
                        century, recording detailed entries describing his interactions with and
                        observations about the cultures he encountered in his <title xml:lang="fr"
                            rend="italic">Journal du voyage du Chevalier Chardin en Perse</title>.
                        He was one of the figures whose work we studied in the course.</note>
                    Similarly, a student participating in their first DH experience will not reach
                    the heights of a finalized DH project stemming from their own coding and design.
                    We knew that students were not ready to code their own programs, so we adopted
                    an intermediate approach, capitalizing on extant DH tools as Harris suggests
                        <ptr target="#harris2013"/>.</p>
                <p>We asked students to map an aspect of seventeenth-century Francophone literature,
                    using existing tools like spreadsheets and programs with mapping capabilities.
                    Thus, they worked towards <emph>building</emph> a map. We demonstrated ways to
                    discover and assess DH tools, drawing our pedagogical approach from our own
                    experimental and self-taught backgrounds in DH. To that end, all DH work was
                    situated in a computer lab. The computer lab ensured that all students had
                    comparable computers and programs. Based on our work with college students,
                    their access to technology is not equal and we did not want there to be a
                    technology gap. While students were asked to do some brainstorming and
                    exploration of DH outside the classroom, all design decisions and actual DH work
                    on the project were undertaken in the classroom. In-class activities ensured
                    that students had ample opportunities to share in ownership and ask questions,
                    reducing the affective filter.<note>Students in second language acquisition
                        settings may experience either high or low affective filters. This is the
                        emotional reaction to environmental and social factors such as
                        teacher-student interaction or the physical environment. A low affective
                        filter means that factors are ideal for language acquisition whereas a high
                        filter means that students may be subject to stress that could prohibit
                        successful acquisition <ptr target="#krashen1982"/>
                        <ptr target="#krashen2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#nance2010"/></note> Moreover, we emphasized process-focused
                    implementation in our instruction and design. Rather than presenting a completed
                    framework for mapping, we broke down each aspect and walked through the
                    decision-making process with the students. There was not one single way of
                    achieving or defining success; rather, we recognized many such pathways and
                    encouraged students to evaluate tools and research questions with open minds.
                    Through this process, students explored the discrete aspects of a DH project.
                    This resulted in their ability to apply the process of evaluating and
                    questioning to their own future projects.</p>
                <p>New literacies and academic literacies formed an important theoretical frame as
                    we navigated the pedagogical and social implications of introducing students to
                    DH within the context of literary analysis. Both theories emphasize the social
                    aspect of literacy practices: the ways in which communities develop particular
                    ways of reading, writing, and communicating, and the ways in which power,
                    authority, and identity impact how individuals encounter and engage with those
                    practices <ptr target="#hui2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#lea2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#street2008"/>. New literacies examines how technology,
                    particularly online environments and their participatory features, impact
                    literacy practices <ptr target="#lankshear2011"/>. Academic literacies
                    challenges educators to make explicit the literacy practices of a discipline, in
                    particular how students will engage in those literacy practices within the
                    specific context of an institution or a course <ptr target="#lea2006"/>, a
                    particularly productive perspective given the emphasis on the utility of
                    explicit discussion of acquisition in L2 contexts <ptr
                        target="#bueno-alastuey2015"/> <ptr
                        target="#cohen2007"/> <ptr target="#graham2011"/>. We wanted students to not just learn to use a
                    technology, but to understand how that technology could be applied to their
                    literary analyses as scholars of French literature as well as the impact of
                    these mediums on their engagement with texts and artefacts.</p>
                <p>In drawing out the social implications of DH, we emphasized the collaborative
                    nature of the discipline through project design. We were influenced by movements
                    such as the UVA Scholars Lab Charter (2016) and UCLA’s Student Collaborators
                    Bill of Rights <ptr target="#dipressi2015"/> that exhort creators to think
                    carefully in terms of power structures and time constraints on students. To that
                    end, we approached the material from an inclusive perspective, intending for the
                    students to become fellow scholars, not laborers. We selected a joint mapping
                    project which resonated with the course topic, <title rend="quotes">The
                        Francophone World in the Seventeenth-Century</title>. All students in the
                    class contributed to the same project and thus needed to agree upon a research
                    question and an appropriate method to study, or map, that question. As
                    educators, we forefronted discussions of applicable academic practices and how
                    we were hewing to or deviating from those practices within the confines of our
                    class. For instance, we knew the DH project would not be finished during this
                    course. Rather than treat this as a research failure, we discussed the reality
                    of research outside a course: it often takes much longer than the few weeks
                    allotted a research assignment within a class and involves experimentation,
                    failure, and reassessment. Engaging in a collaborative DH project afforded
                    students the opportunity to practice their discipline’s literacies, including
                    testing and challenging each other’s assumptions about what are important
                    research questions and what methods to employ in order to investigate those
                    questions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Course Design and Institutional Overview</head>
                <p>This was a hybrid course designed for two populations: advanced undergraduate
                    French majors and graduate students at the master’s level who needed a general,
                    survey-like overview of the literary production of the seventeenth-century in
                    the French-speaking context. The course, <title rend="quotes">The Francophone
                        World in the Seventeenth Century</title>, examined the literary and cultural
                    production of the period as well as the first phase of colonial expansion, its
                    historical and cultural implications, and the way in which French national
                    identity was constructed and represented in art and literature. Given the need
                    to serve as a survey, the course material was organized chronologically. All
                    materials were distributed through Canvas, the university’s course management
                    system, using freely-available texts in the public domain, drawing from either
                    the Bibliothèque Nationale Française’s online catalog, <ref
                        target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/accueil/fr/content/accueil-fr/?mode=desktop"
                        >Gallica</ref>, or <ref target="http://wikipedia.fr/index.php?projet=source"
                        >Wikisource.fr</ref>. In order to tease out implications of French identity,
                    we read several works that dealt with the representations of other nations (ex:
                    Spain in Corneille’s <title rend="italic">Le Cid</title>) and explored the
                    significance of the same. Themes explored included travel and cartographic
                    representations of space and emotion (for example, the <title rend="italic"
                        >Carte de Tendre</title> of Madeleine de Scudéry) as well as the
                    construction of both national and individual identity. Student work was
                    carefully divided. In class we focused on both reflective activities and
                    discussions of the literary texts (and various theoretical approaches thereto)
                    as well as all DH work, presented as lab work that necessitated class time due
                    to its inherently collaborative nature. Outside of class students completed
                    readings, conducted research (bringing results to class), and reflected on work
                    done in class. The rubric for the DH project (<ref target="#appendix"
                        >Appendix</ref>), comprising 15% of the total final grade, emphasized
                    teamwork, professionalism, collaboration and the non-finite nature of the
                    project itself, characteristics endemic to the best practices of productive
                    members of the scholarly community and society as a whole.</p>
                <p>Important in the course design was the institutional reality in which we teach.
                    Ours is a large, land-grant university that plays a crucial role in extension
                    activities across the state, related primarily to agriculture. The public nature
                    of DH work is particularly beneficial as it coincides well with the primacy of
                    public accessibility to research in our institution. Both of us believe strongly
                    in the need to prepare students as engaged scholars and citizens who are ready
                    to participate in a range of contexts upon graduation. With this in mind, an
                    important aspect of this course was to explicate not only the ways in which
                    public, digital databases facilitate access to early modern materials, but how
                    digital archival methods are imperative to maintaining the same, and the
                    professional opportunities that exist for those with this type of skill set. We
                    wanted our students to see the type of research they started in this class as
                    feasible outside the academy. Many students in the humanities will find jobs in
                    K-12 schools, museums, libraries, small companies, and other organizations
                    without access to the databases and software made available to them at a large
                    public university. Digital humanities projects that leverage free or publicly
                    accessible tools provide students with resources and skills that they can apply
                    in a range of professional contexts. Additionally, many free or basic tools
                    (like spreadsheets) serve as the foundation for more advanced digital tools that
                    they may choose to explore at a later date.</p>
                <p>The learning goals for the course reflected at once the subject matter objectives
                    as well as the desired linguistic proficiency outcomes for this level of
                    language learner. They were: (1) describe the works examined, their historical
                    context and the importance of said works in relation to the themes, principle
                    figures and events of the seventeenth century; (2) conduct literary analysis of
                    and research into the works studied across a variety of genres (novel, drama,
                    poetry, letter-writing, travel literature, etc.); (3) identify what are the
                    digital humanities, describe the criteria of a DH project and create a digital
                    map of one aspect of the course as designed and selected by the students; (4)
                    demonstrate advanced spoken and written French skills (ex: compose a research
                    paper, present one’s research findings professionally, contribute to course
                    discussions in a professional and respectful manner, etc.). These goals parallel
                    the student learning outcomes of our Modern Languages department and of the field as a whole,
                    reflecting characteristics of advanced- and superior-level proficiency in all
                    skill areas (reading, writing, speaking, listening) as defined by ACTFL
                    (American Council for the Teaching of Foreign Languages) as well as enhanced
                    cultural analysis and awareness. Through carefully scaffolded assignments,
                    students achieved these outcomes. Each reading and project was organized along
                    process-oriented lines; that is, the focus was to learn how to go about
                    participating in the educo-professional goals of the course. Daily work included
                    brief interactive presentations and sharing preliminary research on readings
                    assigned, addressing questions raised by students regarding the texts, analysis
                    of primary and secondary sources, drawing parallels between texts, and
                    performative/creative activities (including imitating the writing style of
                    authors, performing dramatic readings, or role-playing scenarios inspired by the
                    readings). Given the lab setting of the course, we often made use of the Google
                    office suite to share analyses, data collection, or creative endeavors.</p>
                <p>One of the primary challenges we faced was the question of language. As an
                    advanced French seminar, it was imperative that students work on developing
                    proficiency in the target language. However, we had trouble identifying
                    readily-available DH tools in the target language (Voyant Tools being a notable
                    exception) because many DH tools are natively developed in English and the
                    library sessions needed to be in English.<note>The Programming Historian has
                        developed multilingual learning modules for various tools. See <ref
                            target="https://programminghistorian.org/"
                            >https://programminghistorian.org/</ref>.</note> Additionally, we found
                    it challenging to locate examples of DH projects that were French-language at a
                    level that was accessible to students and illustrated concepts of mapping and
                    literary analysis. Therefore, we had to think carefully about how to
                    productively promote and facilitate linguistic development and acquisition in a
                    range of contexts, including those sessions focused on DH. This was a rewarding
                    aspect of the course design as it led to a practical skill-set focused on using
                    the L2 in technology discussions that do not frequently present themselves in a
                    French-language or literature course. Students learned to discuss
                    literary/cultural topics and the use and applicability of digital tools in the
                    target language. They negotiated with one another on questions of design and
                    implementation, learning to discuss digital humanities both in the L1 in
                    sessions with both faculty members present and in the L2 in discussions
                    facilitated by the professor.</p>
                <p>Throughout the course we walked through strategies for collecting data as well as
                    designing and conducting research, focusing on scaffolding these complex
                    processes and explaining the rationale for each of these steps. Students
                    experience technology on a spectrum; what is inconsequential to one student can
                    become an impassable barrier to other students, but some barriers can be reduced
                    if instructors explicitly discuss them with students <ptr target="#kearns2013"
                    />. We broke down digital humanities projects in smaller steps so that they
                    could be completed in-class in a communal and supportive setting, approaching
                    all steps of the project as acts of co-authoring between the faculty and
                    students. Such an approach embraces the tenets of the UCLA Student
                    Collaborator’s Bill of Rights <ptr target="#dipressi2015"/> and the UVA
                    Scholars’ Lab Charter (2016) which recognize the potential for power
                    differentials and the attendant labor issues that may arise in pedagogical
                    settings.</p>
                <p> Building on our discussion of labor and accessibility, we considered whether our
                    students would have access to selected tools and resources after they completed
                    their degrees and left the university setting. Rather than selecting software or
                    programs that required subscriptions, we chose tools that were free, but did not
                    have all of the features available from purchased software. This decision
                    allowed us to focus on fundamentals that could be transferred across fields,
                    rather than teaching the specific features of a particular application. We
                    decided to focus on open access to tools and readings early in the course
                    design. This foresight proved opportune as we found ourselves balancing the
                    benefits of free and open access against hidden or unanticipated trade-offs. The
                    course readings and all software were free and open access, with the exception
                    of some databases and books available through the university library (e.g. MLA
                    International Bibliography). Our commitment to public scholarship and open
                    access often meant an increased labor burden for the faculty, either in
                    preparing for the course or supporting the DH tools during the semester. Had we
                    not begun planning the course months in advance, the reality of the time
                    investment necessitated could have derailed our course goals. We discussed in class the
                    ability to access materials regularly throughout the semester, a reality that
                    surprised students as they had not considered the ramifications of researching
                    outside an institutional context.</p>
                <p>Despite a university subscription to the citation management system <ref
                        target="https://refworks.proquest.com/">RefWorks</ref>, we decided to use
                        <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ref> which offers a free,
                    basic account and supports multiple users collaborating in shared group
                    libraries. These features supported our goal of introducing students to tools
                    for public scholarship. A RefWorks subscription includes technical support, but
                    Zotero does not. Our library only supported RefWorks at that time due to budget
                    constraints. This meant that we assumed all troubleshooting for Zotero and
                    students contacted us directly, without the option of using our library support
                    services; this ad hoc support is common to DH endeavors <ptr
                        target="#posner2013"/>. We also hit an unexpected cost in regards to the
                    group library we created in Zotero because it exceeded storage limits and
                    requiring the group library owner to purchase additional storage. This proved a
                    lesson in the limits of <q>free</q>. In the classroom, while the introductory
                    day highlighted a range of reactions, from highly confident to somewhat
                    tentative, students began using Zotero for this and other classes within days
                    and reported finding the program both useful and easy to use.</p>
                <p>Another risk of using free or open access tools is that they are reliant upon a
                    person or institution providing continued access to and support of the tool. The
                    stability of a tool is affected by continued grant funding or institutional
                    support <ptr target="#boyles2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#dhberkeley2019"/>
                    <ptr target="#zhang2015" loc="370–1"/>. For instance, Google offered the program
                    Fusion Tables as a data visualization app with mapping features. This relatively
                    simple tool allowed us to use spreadsheets and metadata to map locations from
                    the course readings. Multiple users could add and edit data simultaneously in a
                    spreadsheet created in Google Sheets, allowing students to quickly build a
                    shared dataset during a class session. The data was then connected to Fusion
                    Tables and we determined what points to map and display. However, in late 2018,
                    Google announced that Fusion Tables would be <quote rend="inline">turned
                        down</quote> as of December 2019 and that maps and other programs using it
                    would no longer function <ptr target="#google2018"/>. Fortunately, most mapping
                    tools we identified work with common csv files, which can be easily backed up
                    and saved, even if Google <q>turns down</q> Sheets in the future. Creation and
                    maintenance of a DH project necessitates ongoing access to appropriate tools.
                    Whether that means paying an annual subscription or identifying, as we did, the
                    most portable and common file type as your baseline for data sharing, depends on
                    the resources available to the individual project managers.</p>
                <p>The fact that many of the primary texts for the course were old enough to be out
                    of copyright and in the public domain allowed us to assign free digital texts
                    available through sites like Gallica, limiting expenses for students. One
                    challenge to using texts in the public domain is the orthographic differences
                    between early modern and contemporary printing practices. Where a critical
                    edition will standardize spelling and grammar, there may be more variability in
                    an earlier edition, adding complexity to the act of reading. This led to a
                    consideration of the benefit of accessibility and cost-effectiveness for public
                    domain texts against losing the critical apparatus, such as biographies,
                    cultural contexts, and annotations, available in scholarly editions. Opting for
                    the free texts inspired a productive discussion with students regarding the
                    nature of the edition — the benefits and limitations of freely-accessible
                    materials, the question of copyright, and the ways in which scholars put
                    together a critical, annotated edition. However, this also meant that
                    significant time was spent preparing introductions, designing activities that
                    asked students to complete preliminary research prior to reading, and discussing
                    strategies for interacting with texts (including identifying the types of things
                    one might look for while reading that would be annotated in a critical edition).
                    Counter to DH conversations of new ways digital texts can inform our
                    understanding of a primary source <ptr target="#latham2004"/>
                    <ptr target="#webb2007"/>, we noted that digital texts, particularly the texts
                    available in the public domain, were often editions that did not include the
                    rich apparatus available in modern editions. By placing the French texts in a
                    new, digital context instead of the accustomed print edition, we created an
                    environment in which students had to think about the practice of literary
                    criticism more consciously. Because these texts were not accompanied by a
                    critical apparatus or annotated for readers, students had to take on the work of
                    deciphering the text and clarifying textual references without the aid of a
                    critical edition.</p>
                <p> Flexibility was key in our conception of the DH project in order to facilitate a
                    low-barrier of entry to students and reduce the affective filter. This practice
                    ensured that there was always room for student ownership over the project.
                    Because it was treated as a lab experience, students could call upon the group
                    and the instructor to facilitate work and respond to questions. The value of
                    this type of experiential, hands-on, skills-oriented approach was that it
                    capitalized on active, engaged and reflective practices to promote careful
                    consideration of DH implementation. For example, rather than front-loading the
                    DH activities, creating a DH module, or otherwise focusing only on technologies,
                    we paced the introduction of technologies to coincide with specific points in
                    the research process. We introduced the concept of metadata early in the
                    semester while learning to use Zotero, particularly the tag function, in
                    preparation for creating annotated bibliographies. We revisited metadata when
                    studying digitized maps and saving the maps’ details to Zotero, this time
                    focusing on the unique data points needed to cite across media and generate a
                    database. Later in the semester, we focused more fully on metadata in order to
                    create maps using Google Fusion Tables and for our final project of mapping
                    relationships in the targeted corpus.</p>
                <p>Moreover, while copyright in relation to the primary materials used in class was
                    not in question, significant time was devoted to the discussion of copyright and
                    ownership of critical and individual scholarship as part of the library lessons
                    and class discussions. Students, through DH, came to identify themselves as both
                    content users who needed to acknowledge and cite sources and content creators
                    contributing to scholarship. We explored copyright and authorship in a variety
                    of ways, starting with a series of online lessons from the New Literacies
                    Alliance (NLA)
                    <note>The New Literacies Alliance (NLA) lessons are not directly
                        named for the new literacies theory. In the case of the NLA lessons, the
                        term <term>new literacies</term> functions as an umbrella term to describe
                        the emerging literacies, including information literacy, digital literacies,
                        and multiliteracies, needed to navigate and evaluate information found in
                        print and online formats.</note> project: <title rend="italic">Question Authority</title><note>The <title rend="italic">Question
                            Authority</title> lesson covers evaluating sources for credibility, and
                            introduces questions about whose voices are privileged authoritative, whose
                            voices might be overlooked, and what differing perspectives can add.</note>, <title rend="italic"
                                >Citations</title>, and <title rend="italic">Scholarly Conversations</title><note>These lessons contribute to
                                    ideas about how new voices join a research conversation and how to trace and
                                    follow an idea as new research elaborates on, refutes, or refines it.</note>
                    (see these and all lessons
                    at <ref target="http://www.newliteracieslliance.org"
                        >www.newliteracieslliance.org</ref>). The lessons are grounded in the
                    Association of College and Research Libraries' (ACRL) Framework for Information
                    Literacy for Higher Education (Framework). The Framework establishes knowledge
                    practices and dispositions indicative of the critical evaluation of and
                    engagement with information. The practices are organized into six core concepts,
                    or frames, and each frame identifies how researchers, from novices to experts,
                    navigate those practices. Most relevant to our work was the <title rend="italic"
                        >Scholarship as Conversation</title> frame, as it includes concepts ranging
                    from crediting others’ work to recognizing that any given avenue of research is
                    part of a larger, evolving conversation. After these introductory lessons, we
                    returned to the question of authority regularly during the course, recycling
                    insights into authorship and discursive practices both thematically in terms of
                    the texts studied and practically in relation to students' own work.</p>
                <p>Throughout the semester, we focused on the nature of authority and authorship.
                    Because the NLA lessons could be embedded in a course management system, we
                    assigned them as homework to be completed prior to specific class periods when
                    we would be introducing either related technology or research practices.
                    Requiring the lessons as homework established a leveling platform whereby all
                    students in the class were exposed to the same concepts and activities. They
                    also had time to reflect on these concepts prior to in-class discussions about
                    research as an ongoing process in which they could participate. Throughout the
                    course, students were identified as content creators with the authority to
                    participate in a larger conversation due to their adherence to scholarly
                    practices in literature. Students gained familiarity with the research process
                    and increased their confidence in their own voice. Because this course was
                    designed to prepare students to conduct original research and analysis in
                    seventeenth-century French studies while learning about diverse professional
                    opportunities in the field, the NLA lessons were particularly effective in
                    exploring how authority was constructed in various discourses. They offered an
                    opportunity to bridge classroom activities with professional practices. We
                    underscored a range of post-graduate experiences, from teaching to editorial to
                    archival work in diverse cultural institutions. Additionally, we pointed to the
                    transferability of the skills students acquired in the course to a variety of
                    professional contexts across a range of disciplines.</p>
                <p>External to the course planning was the serendipity of the community that
                    developed among the students over the semester. Many of the students in the
                    course had worked with us in prior courses. At least two students were in the
                    prior DH-infused course referenced above. However, in this course, the students
                    developed a back-channel communication method using an app where they could
                    privately discuss the course itself. This turned out to be an immensely positive
                    outcome as it afforded them a private space to discuss questions related to the
                    course and express concern, frustration, or excitement and enthusiasm regarding
                    the course content without the faculty involved. This was an organic development
                    stemming from student initiative with the positive effect of creating and
                    supporting the developing community. It also enhanced teamwork because the
                    students became accustomed to discussing the class itself and the content in a
                    less-formal setting and advocating for each other. For example, if a student had
                    a concern but was nervous about emailing the professor, another student would
                    volunteer and reach out to clarify the question and then report back. Another
                    unexpected effect was increased enthusiasm regarding the materials studied;
                    students were so keen on the material, particularly Corneille’s <title
                        rend="italic">Le Cid</title>, that they asked the professor to work with
                    them to put together an abbreviated performance of the play in French for the
                    campus community.<note>A portion of the class took part (five of the thirteen
                        students enrolled, two MA students and three undergraduate majors) and
                        participated in the selection of scenes as well as the blocking and design
                        of the performance.</note> These student-led initiatives further enhanced
                    the course environment. There is not necessarily a way to implement or replicate
                    this type of organic extracurricular contribution, but we believe that the model
                    of collaborative engagement in the classroom did facilitate and favor these
                    developments. In particular, the professor and the librarian modelled
                    collaborative approaches in teaching the DH content and in exploring concepts
                    such as new literacies, research strategies, and the history of the critical
                    edition. This cooperative approach to instruction illustrated the collaborative
                    nature of DH projects and of the research process and was reflective of the
                    community building inherent in the L2 classroom. The students were developing
                    linguistic proficiency and content mastery (both literary and digital) along
                    parallel lines; while negotiating meaning, they negotiated alternative means of
                    communication and engaged in critical and supportive ways with the material. The
                    emphasis on collaboration in DH enhanced community building while the L2 focus
                    on second-language production underscored opportunities for civic engagement,
                    peer mentoring and advocacy, and developing empathetic, reflective
                    practitioners. Students advocated for their peers, sought to ensure equal access
                    to material and interrogated their own processes and the tools selected in a way
                    that reflected the true potential of a global, linguistically diverse, DHML.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Mapping Collaboratively</head>
                <p> Given the focus on cartography and its potential for encouraging considerations
                    of space, authority, and representation, mapping was explored as both a form of
                    visualization and a theme of study in the course. As the class read through the
                    works, we made constant reference to maps, both contemporary and of the period,
                    to render concrete the geography in play in the literary works. We also
                    discussed the act of mapmaking and how modern advances in technology have deeply
                    changed generative practices in the field of cartography. We curated and
                    presented several DH mapping projects that the students explored in-class and we
                    explored how to read different types of maps across varying mediums. As with the
                    primary source texts discussed above, cartographic techniques in the seventeenth
                    century compared to contemporary maps required learning new textual and visual
                    cues. By focusing on digital maps and visualization techniques, students
                    encountered not just new artefacts (maps) but artefacts that they could
                    manipulate to change how they understood a culture or a primary text. Digital
                    maps, such as ones we explored through the <ref
                        target="https://www.davidrumsey.com/">David Rumsey Map Collection</ref>,
                    allowed zooming and panning which in turn facilitated <q>close</q> readings in
                    geospatial contexts. The DH maps we explored contained features like timelines,
                    connections between individuals, or notes imparting cultural context, and
                    examined how these transform our interpretation of a text or map.<note>Projects
                        included: (1) Jenstad, Janelle. <title rend="quotes">The Agas Map</title>.
                            <title rend="italic">The Map of Early Modern London</title>. Ed. Janelle
                        Jenstad. Victoria: University of Victoria. Accessed November 11, 2019. <ref
                            target="http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/map.htm"
                            >http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/map.htm</ref>; (2) <title rend="quotes">Map
                            of Witchcraft Accusations, 1692</title>. n.d. <title rend="italic">Salem
                            Witch Trials: Documentary Archive and Transcription Project</title>.
                        Accessed November 11, 2019. <ref
                            target="http://salem.lib.virginia.edu/maps/accusationMaps/index.html"
                            >http://salem.lib.virginia.edu/maps/accusationMaps/index.html</ref>; (3)
                        Melendez (map), Richard Kreitner (writer), Steven. 2015. <title
                            rend="quotes">The Obsessively Detailed Map of American Literature’s Most
                            Epic Road Trips</title>. <title rend="italic">Atlas Obscura</title>.
                        July 20, 2015. <ref
                            target="http://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/the-obsessively-detailed-map-of-american-literatures-most-epic-road-trips"
                            >http://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/the-obsessively-detailed-map-of-american-literatures-most-epic-road-trips</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>In order to provide a sample of the potential for mapmaking, the professor and
                    the librarian prepared a tabular datasheet of Jean Chardin’s voyages to and from
                    Persia as the students were reading selections from his travel memoirs, <title
                        rend="italic">Voyages de Monsieur le chevalier Chardin en Perse et autre
                        lieux de l’Orient</title> (ed. Philip Stewart, 2018). We then designed and
                    presented a map using Google Fusion Tables as illustrated in figure 1, described
                    our workflow, and discussed our project goals to students to illustrate method,
                    collaboration, and design. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Fusion Table capture of Chardin data</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The map, depicted in figure 2, included several data points, including locations
                    where Chardin visited and his arrival and departure dates. Students noted that
                    the map allowed them to conceptualize the expanse traveled by Chardin in a way
                    they did not experience when reading the text.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Google map of Chardin data generated from Fusion Table</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    <figDesc>A close up of a Google map of Chardin data generated from Fusion
                        Table.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>While we designed the class around mapping, we purposely stepped back from
                    dictating what would be mapped and how. Cartography, and acts of mapping in
                    particular, are potent opportunities to consider questions of authority and the
                    influence that said authority can have. Maps have long served as defining
                    documents that determine sociopolitical boundaries and impose the same on
                    populations in a commanding fashion and without always permitting a plurality of
                    perspectives on the question. Such concerns parallel those surrounding global DH
                    practices. If one presents and practices solely in an Anglocentric vein, one is
                    ignoring the import and the richness of a multilingual, multicultural approach
                    to DH. With this reality in mind and paired with our own personal pedagogies
                    related to student agency, we sought to avoid imposing an interpretation and
                    instead encouraged students to assert their own perspective. New literacies
                    affirms that new members to a community transform that community’s practices,
                    sometimes with a nudge, sometimes with a shove <ptr target="#lankshear2011"/>.
                    Students had to feel free to experiment with voice, design, and scope, knowing
                    that they had control over the project without feeling that they were going to
                    be left alone without any instructional support. We reminded them that failure
                    was an option, as it always is, but worked to reframe the concept of failure as
                    a possible outcome in the natural workflow of any research project. In
                    particular, we underscored that learning was the ultimate goal: learning how to
                    use the tools, how to work collaboratively, how to design a DH project, and how
                    to seek out support or answers when working in DH and research. Any
                        <q>failure</q> was just the first in a number of iterations that would be
                    important for developing and strengthening their project and, ultimately, their
                    research and project management skills. Striking this balance between scaffolded
                    support and freedom of creation was imperative because we both believed that
                    this course and the DH project served as a steppingstone into careers. We
                    explicitly discussed their agency in the DH project and how that could relate to
                    future endeavors. As professionals and scholars, the students would be expected
                    to demonstrate initiative and problem-solving.</p>
                <p>Interestingly, when it came to designing their own mapping project, students
                    conceived of mapping in a far more abstract way than the rather concrete
                    examples we had illustrated and catalogued. Our conception of mapping was highly
                    geographic whereas the students’ was ultimately more a visualization of the
                    text. In a subsequent class period, we asked students to break into small groups
                    and propose their own ideas for a mapping project, largely construed. They had
                    three questions to discuss: (1) What is the scope and objectives for the
                    project? (2) What texts should be included and why? (3) What information will we
                    need to begin the project? Students were encouraged to think widely and each of
                    the three small groups proposed vastly different conceptions: one group proposed
                    creating a map that connected both the tangible (physical locations) with the
                    intangible (themes, concepts) in a range of works studied; another group
                    proposed elaborating the Chardin map we had begun; another proposed exploring
                    the writing of Marie de Rabutin-Chantal, marquise de Sévigné, a writer known for
                    her extensive correspondence. These projects referenced tenets implicit in
                    global DH by exploring multiplicity of perspective and voice, ranging from
                    intimate women’s accounts to public conceptualizations of nation and identity in
                    a broader Francophone context. These ideas were outlined on a shared Google Doc.
                    Students then presented their ideas to the class and were asked to think about
                    it overnight. In the following class period, students shared their views on pros
                    and cons for each project proposal and ultimately decided on a more “intimate”
                    project — rather than attempting to map the texts from the course as a whole,
                    they wanted to explore the epistolary network of Madame de Sévigné and tease out
                    whether there was a connection between place and theme reflected in the social
                    networks.</p>
                <p>The students made an independent and practical design decision conditioned by
                    their own interests. Additionally, where we had conceived of geography in terms
                    of demonstrating a larger physical reality, students were intrigued by what
                    could be termed the <term>geography of the individual</term>, more abstract
                    constructions of the same in the vein of the <title rend="italic">Carte de
                        Tendre.</title><note>The <ref
                            target="http://expositions.bnf.fr/globes/bornes/it/46/23.htm"><title
                                rend="italic">Carte de Tendre</title></ref> is a seventeenth-century
                        allegorical map found in Madeleine de Scudéry’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Clélie</title> describing the route to true love and the possible
                        pitfalls along the way for the beloved. The link will take you to the BNF’s
                        exposition on maps and copy of the map in question.</note> We anticipated
                    students would plot texts onto a map to visualize the Francophone world in the
                    first phase of colonial expansion, perhaps conceptualizing the overarching
                    course theme through mapping. The student’s approach was a tapestry focused on
                    relationships around a single author. Perhaps our project example focused on
                    Chardin served as an impetus for them, but students chose to explore on a
                    micro-level Sévigné’s social circle rather than on the macro-level of course
                    readings across time and space. This led to particularly productive reflections
                    on the nature of social and epistolary networks: who were the recipients? what
                    were the relationships between Sévigné and her correspondents? where were they
                    when they wrote or received the correspondence? what was the nature of the
                    correspondence and how were epistolary and social practices inscribed in the
                    texts? That is, it was common practice to read these letters aloud--what
                    stylistic choices hinted at these practices? Finally, what was the import of
                    geography and how could mapping help to visualize this polyphonic network and
                    set of relationships?</p>
                <p>Students raised these and more questions as they grappled with the reality of
                    transforming these observations into more precise data points that could
                    ultimately be mapped and visualized digitally. We discussed <q>translating</q>
                    their questions and answers into tabular form. This was a particularly
                    productive moment because it touched on design and project scope while helping
                    students to clarify and isolate data that was truly necessary for their primary
                    objectives from information which might serve as secondary considerations later
                    in the project. It should be noted that this was the culmination of our
                    introduction to digital tools and methods and occurred in the latter third of
                    the semester. Because we purposely scaffolded pieces of this process into
                    earlier assignments (i.e. methods for data collection, the importance of
                    metadata and appropriate categorizing of information, etc.) students were able
                    to draw upon and then recycle those methods independently. Students quickly
                    recognized that the initial scope of their project, given Sévigné’s prolific
                    letter-writing habit, was imposing and pondered how they could efficiently
                    extract the data points from the thousands of pages of letters. This opened the
                    window to return to the question of editions raised earlier in the semester
                    during discussions of manuscripts and printing practices. We brought in the
                    critical edition of Sévigné’s correspondence by the Bibliothèque de la Pléiade
                    to discuss the paratextual material made available through the preparation of
                    the critical edition itself. Importantly, this included an appendix that indexed
                    the letters by correspondent, date, and location. With this appendix, students
                    discovered many of the data points that they had previously discussed and
                    encountered additional data points that arise in letter writing that they had
                    not considered.</p>
                <p>Students then embarked on the final DH activity, entering the data points into a
                    spreadsheet and mapping the data. We created the columns and headings in advance
                    to maximize in-class time, using categories discussed in the prior class, and
                    during the class we reviewed the role of metadata (in this case the column
                    headings) in the mapping process as well as modified the spreadsheet as
                    necessary. Due to the collaborative features of Google Sheet, each small group
                    entered unique data points while observing how their colleagues entered the
                    material (see figure 3 below).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Google Sheet populated with Sévigné correspondence data</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>At one point, work came to a halt when one student raised the issue of how data
                    points like correspondents’ names and days of the week were being entered. The
                    class briefly discussed abbreviations and entering French terms rather than
                    English, or vice versa, because they realized common data points would not be
                    mapped appropriately if they were not uniformly entered. We did not participate
                    in this conversation, making space for the students to independently resolve the
                    issue, which they did, admirably. This moment encapsulated many of our learning
                    goals, particularly in observing the students interact as professional
                    colleagues interrogating their methods for meaningful data collection and the
                    implications of collaborative research design.</p>
                <p>Once students established their controlled vocabulary and entered a few dozen
                    data points, we shifted to Google Fusion Tables and selected the locations from
                    the letters for mapping. At this point, the whole room deflated when everyone
                    realized that the only locations on many of the letters compiled into the
                    spreadsheet were Sévigné’s two residences. We loaded the csv file into
                    Stanford’s <ref target="http://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio/">Palladio</ref> and
                    explored how the relationships could alternatively be mapped (see figure 4
                    below), reinforcing the importance of identifying tools and methods that support
                    the research question.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Screenshot of Sévigné data graphed using Stanford’s Palladio</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>While the class did not culminate with a glorious map, we nonetheless observed
                    the students’ transition from a class of, well, students, to a community of
                    scholars. This started as early as the first month of classes, when students
                    could see each other’s Zotero folders and began recommending sources to each
                    other. Their back-channel communication resembled the ways colleagues manage
                    workplace issues, including advocating for each other. The DH aspect of the
                    course opened the whole class to a greater breadth of research in modern
                    languages. While independent research projects can result in one student
                    learning the value of critical editions or using a visual medium to interrogate
                    a text, this often occurs within a bubble comprised of the student and the
                    professor. There is little opportunity to delve into nuances or to test the
                    implications from several perspectives. The DH project shifted students from
                    solo practitioners experimenting in discipline-specific practices into a
                    community of scholars debating, critiquing, and building upon those practices in
                    collaborative and engaged ways. This communal model of research in the DH
                    classroom echoes the <term>laboratory model</term> wherein researchers test
                    ideas within a shared space before public release. Humanities faculty seeking
                    models to mentor student research may find this idea of the classroom as a
                    micro-DH an attractive approach, with the potential to develop over time as a
                    humanities laboratory that cumulates research from class to class and eventually
                    support individual student research. DH did not present an easier route, but a
                    different route to critically analyzing literature in the L2 context.</p>
                <p>Through our interactions with the students during and after the course as well as
                    through student evaluations and feedback, we noted a range of outcomes that
                    paralleled our own goals for the course: (1) the skills students learned were
                    highly transferable, not only to future professional contexts (which are
                    intangible to many students) but immediately, to other class projects (i.e. the
                    final research essay, research they were conducting in other disciplines from
                    the social to the hard sciences); (2) students became comfortable with and
                    conversant about the critical apparatus surrounding course topics; (3) several
                    students chose to continue and pursue more advanced research topics in the
                    discipline (for example, one student worked with the ML professor on a more
                    advanced topic the following semester, resulting in a published paper); (4)
                    students developed a more profound understanding of what labor and work in the
                    humanities encompass (i.e. teaching, research, and service; research across
                    humanities disciplines, particularly in literary criticism; and what work looks
                    like in various settings, be they institutions of higher learning, museums or
                    public archives, or academic or commercial presses); (5) students in the class
                    formed an engaged community of scholars who assumed roles as active project
                    designers and researchers. These outcomes underscore the vast potential a
                    global, multilingual DH-inflected approach informed by new literacies
                    represents.</p>
                <p>Creating flexibility for student-driven decisions and troubleshooting capitalizes
                    on characteristics of digital pedagogy that correlate nicely with L2 pedagogy,
                    but we did not fully embrace one aspect of digital pedagogy: the exhortation to
                    reach a larger public. While in a previous course the focus was to share results
                    publicly and openly, a key component to DH <ptr target="#sample2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#sample2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#antonioli2018"/>, in this course we sought to extend the
                    traditional definitions of <q>public</q>. We propose that, particularly within a
                    pedagogical context, DH project work might be conceived as <term>communal</term>
                    in addition to or in contrast with <term>public-facing</term>. That is to say,
                    we encouraged students to present results within their own scholarly community,
                    recognizing that while it would not result immediately in public-facing, open
                    scholarship it would represent an important step towards that ultimate goal.
                    Moreover, we pointed out that the initial work done here would be shared with
                    future courses in the field, thereby building a wider community beyond their own
                    class that would share in the findings. At each step we laid the foundation for
                    students to engage in public scholarship in the future by emphasizing open
                    source, open access technologies and discussing implications of authority and
                    access in the public sphere, outside the confines of an academic
                    institution.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion: Expanding Notions of Community, Success, and Labor in a Global
                    DHML</head>
                <p>We believe that exploring DH in the L2 classroom allows a productive space to
                    examine notions related to linguistic and cultural power-dynamics. The more
                    diverse the approaches to DH, the more diverse DH itself becomes. Moreover,
                    exploring digital tools as cultural products with their attending sociocultural
                    contexts in terms of language, costs, and access, challenges the inherent
                    monolingualism of the field and diversifies approaches to and perspectives on
                    DH, DH tools, and DH methodologies. In the L2 classroom, even students for whom
                    English is their first language, the language of technology can be as new and
                    unfamiliar as a second language. Exploring the digital humanities from a
                    scaffolded perspective that calls attention to the nature of cultural power
                    dynamics and the ways in which information is transmitted and interpreted
                    enriches the field immeasurably. For example, students in this course engaged in
                    the participatory nature of new literacies, DH, and L2 practices that emphasized
                    taking advantage of interactive tools to reconsider primary source texts while
                    elaborating that work within a global context. Taking a micro approach to
                    community capitalizing on the iterative, reflective, project-oriented practices
                    inherent in L2 pedagogy and new literacies theories resulted in a course design
                    that drew attention to larger theoretical concerns within DH such as definitions
                    of public and open-access in various contexts, the import of productive failure,
                    and the potential and importance of collaborative practices with shared
                    authorship among all participants.</p>
                <p>In terms of community building, students formed their own scholarly community
                    through both in-class interactions and private social messaging apps, creating
                    forums to discuss the academic literacies they encountered within the context of
                    a specific class. These interactions promoted students’ agency and
                    reconceptualized their roles in scholarly endeavors, enabling students to
                    recognize their own potential as authoritative voices. This student-to-student
                    tutelage reflected the <q>triangular</q> learning and social constructivism
                    observed in other DH projects in L2 environments <ptr target="#mahony2014"/>. We
                    consciously worked to encourage students to feel comfortable engaging in
                    disciplinary discursive practices from which they often feel excluded because
                    they lack a perceived authority and agency therein. We were particularly
                    gratified when students chose a research path distinct from what we had
                    anticipated, illustrating how new participants to an academic literacy transform
                    the conversation and practices, and solidifying that they felt invited to the
                    table to participate. The true value of informing DH and L2 pedagogy with a new
                    literacies perspective is to focus on inclusive discursive practices.</p>
                <p>In addition to students developing their own authority and confidence, we worked
                    to broaden their notions of success. We sought to help students understand more
                    fully the “nuts and bolts” of research design and project management,
                    particularly in terms of defining scope and setting realistic timelines. The
                    average semester-long course can promote false notions that research projects
                    can be begun and completed within three to four months. Additionally, not every
                    research endeavor ends in a neatly packaged product. The reality, as researchers
                    in the humanities know, is vastly different. This project helped to promote
                    patience, in terms of design and results, and with themselves as researchers.
                    Students began to understand that they could (1) participate in multiple
                    projects, such as traditional papers and DH explorations, simultaneously and (2)
                    that not all projects may be defined and designed in the same way. Throughout,
                    we emphasized the importance of process over product, giving the students space
                    to design and conceptualize without the pressure of needing to have a predefined
                    deliverable ready by end of term. This approach diverged from facile notions of
                    success in terms of completion, focusing instead on the potential for failure as
                    a productive practice <ptr target="#croxall2016"/> that may be just as important
                    to the ultimate research process as success and would lead to successful
                    completion. This perfectly encapsulated and modeled a scholarly conversation —
                    students shifted roles from readers to researchers, claiming an active part in
                    the work.</p>
                <p> Furthermore, re-defining success permitted constructive discussions regarding
                    labor and the division of the same, both in DH research initiatives and in terms
                    of designing such a course. Boyles, et. al. (2018) note the precarity of digital
                    humanities in academia, both in terms of those who support DH initiatives (often
                    contingent labor from across various departments in the institution or
                    faculty/staff whose work flow differs substantially from the teaching faculty)
                    as well as the students who are participating therein <ptr target="#boyles2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#anderson2016"/>. While the <q>utopist</q> ideals of collaborative
                    teamwork and inclusive practices have been variously espoused and critiqued in
                    DH scholarship <ptr target="#price2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#presner2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#burdick2012"/>, as Anderson et. al. have noted, <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#anderson2016">very little deals with students as
                            collaborators or active participants in the projects whose success
                            depends, to a great degree, on their labor</quote>
                        <ptr target="#anderson2016" loc="para 4"/></cit>. It was imperative, in our
                    course conception and project design, that students be fully engaged and
                    understand the potential and ramifications of work in the digital humanities.
                    This, in large part, was why we ensured that all DH project work took place in
                    the confines of the classroom where we could work alongside students.
                    Additionally, students were invited to participate in this sphere as fully
                    contributing members, involved in design and work equally. While the impetus for
                    creating the DH project was faculty-led (and noted in the syllabus as part of
                    the course goals), the project itself was a cooperative effort that attempted to
                    correspond to the best practices, including clearly formalizing group structure
                    and work, treating project management and training as part of the course
                    content, encouraging student-led design in the project, and recognizing that
                    projects need not have the same finite deadlines as other coursework <ptr
                        target="#anderson2016"/>. Underscoring the process as product itself greatly
                    facilitated this work.</p>
                <p>Alongside varying expectations for success, we also promoted building a community
                    that recognized at once the multiplicity of voices in the room and reflected on
                    the impact of discipline-specific practices in a global, multicultural context.
                    In our approach to instruction, we capitalized on the benefits of zones of
                    proximal development <ptr target="#vygotsky1978"/> through extensive group work,
                    characteristic of L2 pedagogy to promote language acquisition. This focus on
                    collaborative practices necessitated students prioritize listening to and
                    learning from their peers. Such an approach valorized diverse perspectives and
                    experiences that may diverge from a student’s own worldview. Students’ prior
                    experience with this type of group work in the L2 classroom facilitated
                    transitions to the intensely collaborative work that characterized our classroom
                    and are imperative to a global DH. Working with a global DH in mind contributes
                    towards developing a nuanced, egalitarian, and collaborative work ethic that is
                    particularly apropos to multicultural and multilingual interactions that are
                    increasingly common in the workplace. Not only did we encouraged all
                    participants to practice agency and advocacy through their shared scholarship,
                    these competencies reflect our institutional land grant values. This evokes the
                    core mission of the Modern Languages department, namely to <quote rend="inline"
                        >prepare a linguistically competent and culturally aware citizenry poised to
                        live and work in an increasingly global and diverse society, in accordance
                        with Kansas State University's land grant mission</quote> (Dept. of Modern
                    Languages n.d.). These values, namely the ability to advocate and participate
                    equally in a multicultural and multilingual environment, are at the base of
                    global DH. Adopting this type of approach, however, is not without consequences;
                    namely, that of the time involved. We worked to ensure that integrating a
                    global DH approach into the seminar would not overwhelm students and that the
                    project itself would not exceed the limits of obligation for any one member of
                    the team. This ensured a balanced approach to student labor that ultimately
                    corresponded to our course goals and expectations.</p>
                <p>One aspect of labor that must also be considered is that of the faculty members
                    involved. Designing and implementing this scaffolded approach was a
                    time-consuming process. We met and corresponded regularly outside of class both
                    prior to and during the semester to consult on design, reflect on student
                    progress, and modify where necessary. A nimble approach to DH projects demands
                    that faculty prepare for multiple research scenarios depending on student
                    interest and design. This involved investigating more tools and resources than
                    were ever introduced or used in class. Our own level of collaboration increased
                    over the course of the project as we progressed from initial conversations about
                    a specific DH project and became more invested in a DH-inflected course. As
                    others have noted <ptr target="#harris2013"/>, the inherent time and labor
                    necessitated by the faculty embarking on such an approach is at times
                    staggering. While it may be true that future collaborations will be less
                    time-intensive because we designed all the materials and assignments for this
                    course and the approach from scratch, a significant portion of time was spent in
                    meetings to reflect on progress in the course and consider how best to address
                    questions raised and desired outcomes. This type of reflective practice would be
                    necessary whenever implementing this approach.</p>
                <p>It is true that this approach requires time and patience, two commodities that
                    are not easy to come by, particularly as one reflects on one’s institutional
                    profile and the inherent requirements of faculty therein. However, there are
                    concrete benefits to a DH approach informed by L2 practices and new literacies,
                    both in terms of student learning and faculty development. We found that the
                    student learning theories and practices that already informed our
                    discipline-specific work with students (such as best practices in second
                    language acquisition and new literacies perspectives) remained highly relevant
                    to our implementation of DH pedagogy. Rather than supplanting or overshadowing
                    disciplinary-specific discursive practices, we found that DH methodologies put
                    those practices into greater relief, forcing students and faculty to more
                    consciously explore processes that can become unconscious or habitual. Moreover,
                    this type of experimentation and collaboration is immensely beneficial,
                    particularly if made part of faculty’s research, teaching, and service agendas.
                    While larger institutional attitudes regarding expectations for tenure remain
                    challenging to modify, we who are tenured faculty can shape our scholarship
                    practices to record our own work in collaborative pedagogical endeavors, thereby
                    lending credence to initiatives to widen what counts as <q>scholarship</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix">
                <head>DH Project Rubric (15% of final grade)</head>
                <p>This project, conceived as an introduction to research methodologies in the
                    digital humanities, is a collaborative work among participants in the course.
                    The objectives are the following:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Conceive visually the impact of the Francophone world in the 17th
                        century;</item>
                    <item>Insert into a map selected work(s) in order to develop a cartographic
                        organization of the selected subject;</item>
                    <item>Establish criteria to determine which work(s) will be included in the
                        project as well as what information will be included in standard citations,
                        related to the scope chosen by the team;</item>
                    <item>Prepare appropriate citations for each data point;</item>
                    <item>Present the information in a clear and compelling manner for the general
                        public.</item>
                </list>
                <p>For this project, we will use Google Maps and Fusion Tables.</p>
                <p>In order to prepare this project, we will need to:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Establish the number of citations/works we will include, identify
                        applicable data points</item>
                    <item>Establish the criteria for inclusion</item>
                    <item>Decide what data we would like to analyze and include in each
                        citation</item>
                    <item>Prepare all citations (including images, resources, etc.) for the
                        project</item>
                    <item>Revise in order to ensure that the information is presented clearly and
                        compellingly with our target audience in mind</item>
                </list>
                <p>We will work in class each day over the next month. At the end of that period, we
                    will analyse what we can learn from our visual conceptualization and determine
                    whether this work has helped us to conceive of the texts and/or period
                    differently than before. </p>
                <p>You will be evaluated according to the following criteria:</p>
                <p>1. Collaborative Work in Class (25 points)</p>
                <p>You work in a productive and positive manner, contributing fully to the shared
                    work. You respect your classmates and propose ideas in order to enrich and
                    improve the work and project as a whole. You share the group work
                    proportionately with your peers and contribute concretely to the success of the
                    project. You help the team to achieve their goals. You add information to the
                    spreadsheet, observing the criteria established by the team and your
                    contributions conform to team expectations.</p>
                <p>2. Conception of the project (25 points, shared grade)</p>
                <p>The team works together to (1) establish criteria and project goals; (2) select
                    the form and data to include in each citation/entry; (3) decide on the form of
                    the project. The conception is realistic according to the time we have to work
                    on it and conforms to the expectations of a research project at this level.</p>
                <p>3. Result: Final Project (30 points, shared grade)</p>
                <p>This project will not necessarily be completed during this class. However, you
                    will prepare a database that could be elaborated by students in a future class
                    in order to map a conception the team has chosen. The final project is usable
                    and useful, conforms to the conception and criteria established by the team, and
                    will be accessible to a larger public beyond the classroom. The project is
                    well-organized and clearly presented, compelling, and convincing in design.
                    There are no grammar or spelling errors. You will share the results of your work
                    during the final class period for this course.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="actfl"
                    label="American Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages. n.d.">American
                    Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages. n.d. <title rend="quotes"
                        >World-Readiness Standards for Learning Languages</title>. American Council
                    on the Teaching of Foreign Languages. Accessed June 15, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.actfl.org/publications/all/world-readiness-standards-learning-languages?id=33"
                        >https://www.actfl.org/publications/all/world-readiness-standards-learning-languages?id=33</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="anderson2016" label="Anderson et al. 2016">Anderson, Katrina, Lindsey
                    Bannister, Janey Dodd, Deanna Fong, Michelle Levy, and Lindsey Seatter. 2016.
                        <title rend="quotes">Student Labour and Training in Digital
                        Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 10 (1).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="antonioli2018" label="Antonioli and Cro 2018">Antonioli, Kathleen and
                    Melinda A. Cro. 2018. <title rend="quotes">Collaborative Perspectives on
                        Translation and the Digital Humanities in the Advanced French
                        Classroom</title>, <title rend="italic">French Review</title> 91 (4):
                    130–45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="battershill2017" label="Battershill and Ross 2017">Battershill, Claire
                    and Shawna Ross. 2017. <title rend="italic">Using Digital Humanities in the
                        Classroom: A Practical Introduction for Teachers, Lecturers, and
                        Students</title>. Bloomsbury Academic.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blake2008" label="Blake 2008">Blake, Robert J. 2008. <title
                        rend="italic">Brave New Digital Classroom: Technology and Foreign Language
                        Learning</title>. Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press.<ref
                        target="http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/ksu/detail.action?docID=547784"
                        >http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/ksu/detail.action?docID=547784</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boyles2018" label="Boyles et al. 2018">Boyles, Christina, Anne
                    Cong-Huyen, Carrie Johnston, Jim McGrath, and Amanda Phillips. 2018. <title
                        rend="quotes">Precarious Labor and the Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">American Quarterly</title> 70 (3): 693–700.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0054"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0054</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bueno-alastuey2015" label="Bueno-Alastuey and Agulló">Bueno-Alastuey,
                    M. Camino, and Gloria Luque Agulló. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Explicit
                        Instruction and Implicit Use of L2 Learning Strategies in Higher Secondary
                        EFL Course Books</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                        English Studies</title> 15 (2): 17–39.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012">Burdick, Anne, Johanna
                    Drucker, Peter Lunenfeld, Todd Presner, and Jeffrey Schnapp. 2012. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2007" label="Cohen and Macaro 2007">Cohen, Andrew and Ernesto
                    Macaro. 2007. <title rend="italic">Language Learner Strategies: 30 Years of
                        Research and Practice</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="coiro2008" label="Coiro et al. 2008">Coiro, Julie, Michele Knobel,
                    Colin Lankshear, and Donald J. Leu, eds. 2008. <title rend="italic">Handbook of
                        Research on New Literacies</title>. New York: Lawrence Erlbaum
                    Associates.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cordell2016" label="Cordell 2016">Cordell, Ryan. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">How Not to Teach Digital Humanities</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew
                    K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein. Debates in the Digital Humanities. University of
                    Minnesota Press. <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/87"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/87</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dhberkeley2019" label="DH Berkeley 2019"><title rend="quotes">The Cost
                        of Customization: Building, Maintaining, and Sustaining DH
                        Projects..</title> n.d. Digital Humanities at Berkeley Blog (blog). Accessed
                    November 1, 2019. <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.berkeley.edu/blog/15/04/23/cost-customization-building-maintaining-and-sustaining-dh-projects"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.berkeley.edu/blog/15/04/23/cost-customization-building-maintaining-and-sustaining-dh-projects</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cro2020" label="Cro 2020">Cro, Melinda A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Integrating the Digital Humanities into the Second Language Classroom</title>.
                    Washington, DC: Georgetown UP, 2020. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="croxall2016" label="Croxall and Warnick 2016">Croxall, Brian and Quinn
                    Warnick. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Failure</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities: Concepts, Models, and
                        Experiments</title>, edited by Rebecca Frost Davis, Matthew K. Gold,
                    Katherine D. Harris, and Jentery Sayers. MLA Commons. <ref
                        target="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/keywords/failure/"
                        >https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/keywords/failure/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dept. of Modern Languages. n.d. <title rend="quotes">About Us</title>. Kansas
                    State University. Accessed November 11, 2019. <ref
                        target="https://www.ksu.edu/mlangs/about/index.html"
                        >https://www.ksu.edu/mlangs/about/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dipressi2015" label="Di Pressi 2015">Di Pressi, Haley, Stephanie
                    Gorman, Miriam Posner, Raphael Sasayama, and Tori Schmitt. 2015. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</title>. Center for
                    Digital Humanities - UCLA. June 8, 2015. <ref
                        target="http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/"
                        >http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gardiner2015" label="Gardiner and Musto 2015">Gardiner, Eileen and
                    Ronald G. Musto. 2015. <title rend="italic">The Digital Humanities: A Primer for
                        Students and Scholars</title>. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gianetti2017" label="Gianetti 2017">Giannetti, Francesca. 2017. <title
                        rend="quotes">Against the grain: Reading for the challenges of collaborative
                        digital humanities pedagogy</title>. <title rend="italic">College &amp;
                        Undergraduate Libraries</title>, 24 (2–4), 257–269. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1340217">
                        https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1340217</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gil2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016">Gil, Alex and Élika Ortega. 2016.
                        <title rend="quotes">Multilingual Practices and Minimal Computing</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Doing Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Constance
                    Crompton, Richard J. Lane, and Ray Siemens, 22–34. London and New York:
                    Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gonzález-lloret2016" label="González-Lloret 2016">González-Lloret,
                    Marta. 2016. <title rend="italic">A Practical Guide to Integrating Technology
                        into Task-Based Language Teaching</title>. Digital Shorts. Georgetown
                    University Press.<ref
                        target="http://press.georgetown.edu/book/languages/practical-guide-integrating-technology-task-based-language-teaching"
                        >http://press.georgetown.edu/book/languages/practical-guide-integrating-technology-task-based-language-teaching</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="google2018" label="Google 2018">Google. 2018. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Notice: Google Fusion Tables Turndown - Fusion Tables Help</title>. Fusion
                    Tables Help. December 11, 2018.<ref
                        target="https://support.google.com/fusiontables/answer/9185417?hl=en"
                        >https://support.google.com/fusiontables/answer/9185417?hl=en</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="graham2011" label="Graham et al. 2011">Graham, Suzanne, Denise Santos,
                    and Robert Vanderplank. 2011. <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Relationship
                        between Listening Development and Strategy Use</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Language Teaching Research</title> 15 (4): 435–56. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362168811412026"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/1362168811412026</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harris2013" label="Harris 2013">Harris, Katherine D. 2013. <title
                        rend="quotes">Play, Collaborate, Break, Build, Share: ‘Screwing Around’ in
                        Digital Pedagogy</title>. <title rend="italic">Polymath: An
                        Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences Journal</title> 3 (3). <ref
                        target="https://ojcs.siue.edu/ojs/index.php/polymath/article/view/2853"
                        >https://ojcs.siue.edu/ojs/index.php/polymath/article/view/2853</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hirsch2012" label="Hirsch 2012">Hirsch, Brett D., ed. 2012. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and
                        Politics</title>. Open Book Publishers. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0024"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0024</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hui2018" label="Hui 2018">Hui, Diane. 2018. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Learning from New Literacies: Effects on the Academic Achievements of
                        English Major Undergraduate Language Learners</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Australian Journal of Language &amp; Literacy</title> 41 (2):
                    117–33.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kearns2013" label="Kearns 2013">Kearns, Sara K. 2013. <title
                        rend="italic">First-Year College Students’ Perceptions of Their Experiences
                        Using Information and Communication Technologies in Higher
                    Education</title>. PhD diss., Kansas State University.<ref
                        target="http://hdl.handle.net/2097/15787"
                        >http://hdl.handle.net/2097/15787</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knobel2014" label="Knobel and Lankshear 2014">Knobel, Michele, and
                    Colin Lankshear. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Studying New Literacies</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Adolescent &amp; Adult Literacy</title> 58
                    (2): 97–101. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/jaal.314"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1002/jaal.314</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="krashen1982" label="Krashen 1982">Krashen, Stephen D. 1982. <title
                        rend="italic">Principles and Practice in Second Language
                    Acquisition</title>. 1st ed. Language Teaching Methodology Series. Oxford ; New
                    York: Pergamon.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="krashen2009" label="Krashen 2009">—. 2009. <title rend="italic"
                        >Principles and Practice in Second Language Acquisition</title>. <ref
                        target="https://web.archive.org/web/20110716023230/http:/www.sdkrashen.com/Principles_and_Practice/index.html"
                        >http://www.sdkrashen.com/Principles_and_Practice/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuglitsch2015" label="Kuglitsch 2015">Kuglitsch, Rebecca Z. 2015.
                        <title rend="quotes">Teaching for Transfer: Reconciling the Framework with
                        Disciplinary Information Literacy</title>. <title rend="italic">Portal:
                        Libraries and the Academy</title> 15 (3): 457–70. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1353/pla.2015.0040"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/pla.2015.0040</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lankshear2011" label="Lankshear 2011">Lankshear, Colin and Michele
                    Knobel. 2011. <title rend="italic">New Literacies: Everyday Practices and Social
                        Learning</title>. Maidenhead: McGraw-Hill Education. ProQuest Ebrary.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latham2004" label="Latham 2004">Latham, Sean. 2004. <title
                        rend="quotes"><q>New Age</q> Scholarship: The Work of Criticism in the Age
                        of Digital Reproduction</title>. <title rend="italic">New Literary
                        History</title> 35 (3): 411–426.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lea2006" label="Lea and Street 2006">Lea, Mary R. and Brian V. Street.
                    2006. <title rend="quotes">The <q>Academic Literacies</q> Model: Theory and
                        Applications</title>. <title rend="italic">Theory into Practice</title> 45
                    (4): 368–77.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1207/s15430421tip4504_11"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1207/s15430421tip4504_11</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="locke2017" label="Locke 2017">Locke, Brandon T. 2017. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Pedagogy as Essential Liberal Education: A
                        Framework for Curriculum Development</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title> 11 (3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mahony2014" label="Mahony et al. 2014">Mahony, Simon, Julianne Nyhan,
                    Melissa Terras, and Ulrich Tiedau. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities
                        Pedagogy: Integrative Learning and New Ways of Thinking About Studying the
                        Humanities</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Digital
                        Humanities Congress</title> 2014, edited by Clare Mills, Michael Pidd, and
                    Jessica Williams, 20. Sheffield: HRI Online Publications.<ref
                        target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/openbook/pdf/dhc2014-mahony"
                        >https://www.dhi.ac.uk/openbook/pdf/dhc2014-mahony</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nance2010" label="Nance 2010">Nance, Kimberly A. 2010. <title
                        rend="italic">Teaching Literature in the Languages</title>. Boston: Prentice
                    Hall.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitman2017" label="Pitman and Taylor 2017">Pitman, Thea, and Claire
                    Taylor. 2017. <title rend="quotes">Where’s the ML in DH? And Where’s the DH in
                        ML? The Relationship between Modern Languages and Digital Humanities, and an
                        Argument for a Critical DHML</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title> 11 (1). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000287/000287.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000287/000287.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2013" label="Posner 2013">Posner, Miriam. 2013. <title
                        rend="quotes">No Half Measures: Overcoming Common Challenges to Doing
                        Digital Humanities in the Library</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Library Administration</title> 53 (1): 43–52.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756694"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756694</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prensky2001" label="Prensky 2001">Prensky, Marc. 2001. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Natives, Digital Immigrants Part 1</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">On the Horizon</title> 9 (5): 1–6.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1108/10748120110424816"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1108/10748120110424816</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="presner2009" label="Presner et al. 2009">Presner, Todd, Jeffrey
                    Schnapp, and Peter Lunenfeld. 2009. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities
                        Manifesto 2.0</title>. UCLA Mellon Seminar on the Digital Humanities.<ref
                        target="http://jeffreyschnapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/Manifesto_V2.pdf."
                        >http://jeffreyschnapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/Manifesto_V2.pdf.</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="price2013" label="Price and Siemens 2013">Price, Kenneth M., and Ray
                    Siemens. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Literary Studies in the Digital Age: An Evolving
                        Anthology</title>. MLA Commons.<ref
                        target="https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/introduction/"
                        >https://dlsanthology.mla.hcommons.org/introduction/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="priego2015" label="Priego 2015">Priego, Ernesto. 2015. <title
                        rend="quotes">Geopolitical Diversity in Digital Humanities: An Interview
                        with Isabel Galina Russell</title>. <ref
                        target="http://4humanities.org/2015/10/geopolitical-diversity-in-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-isabel-galina-russell/"
                        >http://4humanities.org/2015/10/geopolitical-diversity-in-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-isabel-galina-russell/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2010" label="Ramsay 2010">Ramsay, Stephen. 2010. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Hermeneutics of Screwing Around; or What You Do with a
                        Million Books</title>. April 17. <ref
                        target="https://libraries.uh.edu/wp-content/uploads/Ramsay-The-Hermeneutics-of-Screwing-Around.pdf"
                        >
                        https://libraries.uh.edu/wp-content/uploads/Ramsay-The-Hermeneutics-of-Screwing-Around.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2013a" label="Ramsay 2013a">―. 2013a. <title rend="quotes">On
                        Building</title>. In <title rend="italic">Defining Digital Humanities: A
                        Reader</title>, edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward
                    Vanhoutte, 243–45. Ashgate Publishing Limited.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2013b" label="Ramsay 2013b">―. 2013b. <title rend="quotes">Who’s
                        In and Who’s Out</title>. In <title rend="italic">Defining Digital
                        Humanities: A Reader</title>, 239–41. Ashgate Publishing Limited.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2012" label="Ramsay and Rockwell 2012">Ramsay, Stephen, and
                    Geoffrey Rockwell. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Developing Things: Notes toward an
                        Epistemology of Building in the Digital Humanities</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew
                    K. Gold. University of Minnesota Press. <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/part/3"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/part/3</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roued-cunlife2016" label="Roued-Cunlife 2016">Roued-Cunlife,
                    Henriette. 2016. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Future of Humanities through
                        the Lens of DIY Culture</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 10 (4).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sample2011" label="Sample 2011">Sample, Mark. 2011. <title
                        rend="quotes">Building and Sharing (When You’re Supposed to Be
                        Teaching)</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title> 1 (1). <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/building-and-sharing-when-youre-supposed-to-be-teaching-by-mark-sample/"
                        >
                        http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/building-and-sharing-when-youre-supposed-to-be-teaching-by-mark-sample/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sample2013" label="Sample 2013">―. 2013. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Digital Humanities Is Not about Building, It’s about Sharing</title>. In
                        <title rend="italic">Defining the Digital Humanities: A Reader</title>,
                    edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, 255–57. Ashgate
                    Publishing Limited.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2011" label="Sayers 2011">Sayers, Jentery. 2011. <title
                        rend="quotes">Tinker-Centric Pedagogy</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Collaborative Approaches to the Digital in English Studies</title>, edited
                    by Laura McGrath, 279–300. Logan, UT: Computers and Composition Digital Press.
                        <ref target="http://ccdigitalpress.org/cad/index2.html"
                        >http://ccdigitalpress.org/cad/index2.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scholar2016" label="Scholar's Lab 2016">Scholar’s Lab. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">Charter</title>. Academic. <title rend="italic">Scholar’s Lab
                        at UVA</title> (blog). June 2016. <ref
                        target="http://scholarslab.org/about/charter/"
                        >http://scholarslab.org/about/charter/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spiro2012" label="Spiro 2012">Spiro, Lisa. 2012. <title rend="quotes"
                            ><q>This Is Why We Fight</q>: Defining the Values of the Digital
                        Humanities</title>. In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew K. Gold. <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="street2008" label="Street 2008">Street, Brian V. 2008. <title
                        rend="quotes">New Literacies, New Times: Developments in Literacy
                        Studies</title>. In <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Language and
                        Education</title>, edited by Brian V. Street and Nancy H Hornberger, 2nd
                    ed., 2:418–431. Springer, Boston, MA. <ref
                        target="doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-30424"
                        >doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-30424</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vygotsky1978" label="Vygotsky 1978">Vygotsky, Lev. 1978. <title
                        rend="italic">Mind in Society: The Development of Higher Psychological
                        Processes</title>. Cambridge: Harvard UP.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webb2007" label="Webb 2007">Webb, Allen. 2007. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Texts and the New Literacies</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                        English Journal</title> 97 (1): 83–88.<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/30047213"
                        >https://doi.org/10.2307/30047213</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zhang2015" label="Zhang et al. 2015">Zhang, Ying, Shu Liu, and Emilee
                    Mathews. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Convergence of Digital Humanities and
                        Digital Libraries</title>. <title rend="italic">Library Management</title>
                    36 (4/5): 362–77.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/LM-09-2014-0116"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1108/LM-09-2014-0116</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
