<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data
               Visualization</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Viktoria <dhq:family>Brüggemann</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>viktoria.brueggemann@fh-potsdam.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Viktoria Brüggemann is a research associate at the UCLAB at the University of
                     Applied Sciences Potsdam. As a cultural scientist, her research emphasis is on
                     cultural history and museums, with a focus on different ways of knowledge
                     sharing in the (digital) present. ORCID: <ref
                        target="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3858-0269"
                        >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3858-0269</ref></p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mark-Jan <dhq:family>Bludau</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mark-jan.bludau@fh-potsdam.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mark-Jan Bludau is research associate at the UCLAB at the University of Applied
                     Sciences Potsdam. His main field of interest lies in information visualization
                     with focus on interaction techniques and the visualization of cultural heritage
                     data. ORCID: <ref target="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6300-8833"
                        >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6300-8833</ref>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Marian <dhq:family>Dörk</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Applied Sciences Potsdam</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>marian.doerk@fh-potsdam.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Marian Dörk is a research professor for information visualization at the
                     Institute for Urban Futures of the University of Applied Sciences Potsdam. He
                     co-directs the UCLAB, a transdisciplinary research space at the intersection
                     between interface design, computer science, and the humanities. ORCID: <ref
                        target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3469-7841"
                        >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3469-7841</ref></p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000487</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-07-31" who="jmurel">Ready for author copyediting</change>
         <change when="2020-07-24" who="jmurel">Created and began encoding file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>We propose the philosophical notion of the fold as an evocative vocabulary for the
               design and critique of interactive data visualizations. An expanding range of
               application areas, such as digital art history and literary studies, illustrates the
               potential of data visualization for research and education in the humanities.
               Coinciding with the increasing currency of data as evidence in the humanities, this
               research addresses a growing interest in data visualization for visual analysis and
               argumentation. For example, cultural collection visualizations promise a range of
               possibilities for visual and interactive representations of digital cultural
               heritage, used both for free exploration and focused research. Based on the concept
               of the fold, prominently advanced by Gilles Deleuze, this paper outlines a critical
               framework that draws attention towards the complexity of the underlying data. The
               fold offers a way to analyze and conceptualize visualizations through the lens of
               three integrated operations: explication, implication, and complication. It is an
               opportunity to think of interactive visualizations as portals into coherent, elastic,
               and ultimately infinite information spaces. Accordingly, it rejects the separation
               between interactivity and visual encoding and draws attention to the transitions
               between multiple states of a visualization. We identify design patterns of the fold
               in data visualizations, devise a framework for the critical interpretation of
               interactivity in data visualization, and demonstrate the implications for the digital
               humanities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Outlines how the Deleuzian concept of the Fold offers a novel means of analyzing and
               conceptualizing data visualizations</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <cit><quote rend="block">... its envelopments and developments, its implications and
                  explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a
                  universal Unity ...</quote>
               <ptr target="#deleuze2006" loc="25"/></cit>
            <p>While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position,
               size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information
               visualizations <ptr target="#bertin1983"/> – have always been central to
               visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role
               of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension <ptr
                  target="#shneiderman1983"/>
               <ptr target="#woods1984"/>
               <ptr target="#elmqvist2011"/>. However, when taken up in the humanities, there is
               arguably less attention devoted to the interactive capabilities of data visualization
               in contrast to the visual encoding that is employed. This may be due to the fact that
               there is limited guidance for designing or analyzing interactivity, especially for
               visualizations of complex information spaces. A lower prioritization of interactivity
               in visualization goes back to the, now quaint, visualization pipeline, that positions
               user input at the very last step <ptr target="#card1999"/>. We argue that the main
               issue is the gap in the design process between devising visual encodings and
               integrating interactive capabilities. While this gap is often bridged through
               animated transitions, the resulting animations can be visually jarring <ptr
                  target="#chevalier2014"/> and could serve a range of possibly competing roles <ptr
                  target="#chevalier2016"/>. </p>
            <p>This is especially problematic when considering complex and multidimensional
               datasets, as of cultural collections <ptr target="#windhager2018"/> and other cases
               from the field of the digital humanities. Although such collections are
               unquestionably suitable for digital methods, an implementation, both theoretically as
               well as practically, of the attributed qualities into rich and coherent data
               visualizations often falls short. It can be challenging to arrive at interactive
               visual representations that are meaningful and insightful, and enable a diverse set
               of user tasks from explorative engagement to focused analysis. Furthermore, visual
               information tends to be perceived as <q>true,</q> which has sparked a debate over the
               role of the humanities in the design and interpretation of visualizations,
               understanding data as interpretive and calling for more ambiguity in their graphical
               expression <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>.</p>
            <p>We propose the notion of the fold, advanced by French philosopher Gilles Deleuze <ptr
                  target="#deleuze2006"/>, as a new way of interpreting and creating interactive
               visualizations of complex information spaces. The fold sheds light on the complexity
               of the underlying data and offers a new perspective on knowledge systems and their
               representation. While written in dense philosophical prose, the concept of the fold
               and the associated operations explication, implication, and complication can serve as
               an illuminating lens on visual interfaces and their interactive capabilities. More
               specifically, we believe that the fold offers an evocative design and research
               vocabulary for the digital humanities that considers encoding and interaction aspects
               in unison. We specifically want to bridge the theoretical and practical threads of
               the digital humanities, which have been criticized for falling short in offering
               inclusive, critical, and research-driven concepts that can serve as a guideline for
               their practice <ptr target="#risam2015"/>.</p>
            <p>With this research, we transfer Deleuze’s notion of the fold to data visualization
               and derive three concrete qualities for visualization design and critique in the
               humanities: coherence, elasticity, and infinity. In a next step, we characterize the
               manifestation of the fold’s operations and qualities in a range of exemplary
               visualizations with the help of interpretive illustrations and concrete examples from
               digital humanities projects. Lastly, we formulate a critical framework consisting of
               principles and questions for the design and interpretation of interactive
               visualizations and discuss open questions for future work at the intersection of data
               visualization design and humanistic inquiry. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Related Work</head>
            <p>This research is largely motivated by a recent surge of work on the visualization of
               cultural heritage data, for which numerous visualization approaches have already been
               proposed, yielding an abundance of visual interfaces and representation techniques
                  <ptr target="#windhager2018"/>. Shneiderman’s widely cited visual information
               seeking mantra <quote rend="inline">Overview first, zoom and filter, then details on
                  demand</quote>
               <ptr target="#shneiderman1996"/> may still hold, to a certain extent, but it has
               already been challenged by alternative approaches that aim for serendipitous
               discovery, generous views, open exploration, and bottom-up analysis <ptr
                  target="#dork2011"/>
               <ptr target="#whitelaw2015"/>
               <ptr target="#thudt2012"/>
               <ptr target="#vanham2009"/>. However, a departure from the primacy of the overview
               requires a careful reconsideration of the place for interactivity in data
               visualization. For instance, while a lot of effort is put into the design of online
               collections of museums, navigation oftentimes ends in impasses and the focus is set
               too much on single objects instead of relations and references <ptr
                  target="#kreiseler2017"/>. While casual users might benefit from such a reduced
               visual complexity, the enabling and integration of humanist inquiry through and into
               visualizations still proves to be challenging <ptr target="#windhager2019"/>. We aim
               to continue this line of research and focus more closely on the role of interactivity
               in visualization of cultural heritage data.</p>
            <p>To this end, a range of techniques and methods have been proposed. The visualization
               of complex datasets, among other, calls for the careful choice of visual variables
               and encodings <ptr target="#bertin1983"/>
               <ptr target="#carpendale2003"/>, the dynamic arrangement of elements between display
               states <ptr target="#woods1984"/>, and the interpretive comparison of data elements
               and properties to reveal relationships and differences <ptr target="#gleicher2018"/>.
               However, when working with high-dimensional data, the identification and
               interpretation of meaningful patterns and relationships can be a daunting enterprise.
               For this, dimensionality reduction has become an important method for the visual
               analysis of datasets containing multiple data dimensions and elements <ptr
                  target="#sacha2017"/>. Nevertheless, the resulting low-dimensional layouts can be
               difficult to interpret and imply a range of projection errors <ptr
                  target="#stahnke2016"/>
               <ptr target="#wattenberg2016"/>. For dimensionality reduction to become more useful,
               novel interaction techniques need to be devised that support iterative and
               exploratory data analysis <ptr target="#sacha2017"/>.</p>
            <p>The iterative analysis of data can be thought of as an ongoing information practice
               that exhibits the characteristics of <quote rend="inline">flow</quote>, i.e., high
               levels of concentration, immersion, and motivation <ptr
                  target="#csikszentmihalyi1990"/>
               <ptr target="#pace2004"/>. Relating this and other theories <ptr
                  target="#shneiderman1983"/>
               <ptr target="#woods1984"/> to data visualization, the concept of fluid interaction
               puts forward a user experience during which people smoothly navigate through a visual
               interface, which supports an efficient and enjoyable sensemaking process <ptr
                  target="#elmqvist2011"/>. So far, an operationalization of such aspirational
               concepts in visualization design proves to be difficult, especially in the sense of
               making the animated display changes comprehensible <ptr target="#chevalier2014"/>.
               While graphical animations which represent temporal change in data can be challenging
               to comprehend <ptr target="#tversky2002"/>, several studies show that animated
               transitions can support the perception of data visualizations and comprehend display
               changes <ptr target="#bederson2003"/>
               <ptr target="#heer2007"/>. However, the often used staggered animations are not
               generally beneficial for visually tracking the elements during display changes <ptr
                  target="#chevalier2014"/>. We are especially interested in not only making display
               changes perceptible but also how meaning can be encoded into the viewer-driven
               animations resulting from interactive use of a visualization.</p>
            <p>In all this, we are guided by a growing critical awareness about graphical interfaces
                  <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>, data visualization <ptr target="#dignazio2016"/>
               <ptr target="#dork2013"/>, and data themselves <ptr target="#dignazio2020"/>
               <ptr target="#loukissas2016"/>. Questions of how to include critical approaches and
               diverse voices into their projects <ptr target="#risam2015"/>, as well as how to take
               an ethical approach to the creation and use of data visualizations <ptr
                  target="#hepworth2018"/> have concerned the digital humanities particularly. From
               a study of digital humanities visualizations, Parry found that most project
               descriptions and media coverage underlined the picturing and illustrating
               characteristic of visualizations <ptr target="#parry2019"/>, while the interpretive
               analysis and critique of their performative materiality has largely remained an
               aspiration <ptr target="#drucker2013"/>. Instead, Parry calls for the use of
               enactment practices in data visualization, both in their conception and production as
               well as analysis and critique <ptr target="#parry2019"/>. With this work, we want to
               join these authors in their aspirations by conceptualizing the fold for data
               visualization, providing both a theoretical framework for critique as well as a
               metaphor for practical implementation. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Fold</head>
            <p>In the following, we briefly introduce Gilles Deleuze’s concept of the fold, in which
               he links Leibniz’ baroque idea of monadology to postmodernism <ptr
                  target="#deleuze2006"/>. Specifically, we focus on transferring some of Deleuze’s
               thoughts on perception and information accumulation to the case of data
               visualization, drawing mainly from the first part of <q>The Fold</q> and abstracting
               vocabulary and concrete functional illustrations. Philosophy, in Deleuze’s sense,
               creates concepts, and concepts produce an orientation or direction for thinking <ptr
                  target="#colebrook2002" loc="15"/>. In this spirit, we examine the fold’s
               operations, as proposed by Deleuze, to speculatively extend them into the realm of
               digital information spaces and devise tentative principles for interactivity in data
               visualization. The connection of Leibniz’ philosophical ideas to the fine arts and
               postmodernist thinking has already been pointed out by Deleuze himself, as well as
               others <ptr target="#bredekamp1988"/>. We aim to show how Deleuze’s ideas about the
               baroque concept of monadology, and his postmodern take on the fold, open up promising
               avenues for the design and interpretation of interactive visualizations.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Thinking through the Manifold</head>
               <p>In <title rend="quotes">The Fold. Leibniz and the Baroque</title> (1988), Deleuze
                  (1925-1995) refers back to Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz’ (1646-1716) concept of
                  monadology, which rejected a dualist ontology (i.e., separation of body and soul)
                  and instead established the monad as the basic building block of the material
                  world <ptr target="#leibniz1898"/>. Leibniz had also briefly introduced the
                  metaphor of the fold as <quote rend="inline">a way to differentiate matter without
                     introducing discontinuity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#laerke2010" loc="27"/>. Deleuze now reconstructs Leibniz’ philosophy
                  as baroque metaphysics, an <quote rend="inline">allegory of the world</quote>
                  which in his sense contains the fold as an element of infinite iteration <ptr
                     target="#laerke2010"/> to which postmodernism is deeply attached and from which
                  it can benefit in terms of thinking the complex, or, with Deleuze’s metaphor, the
                  manifold <ptr target="#wagner1995"/>. Deleuze proposes a new empiricism that is
                  based on a theory of difference and multiplicity as fundamental forces <ptr
                     target="#freitas2016" loc="225"/>, stating that monadologic systems are
                  composed of infinite folds, which consequently form the smallest unit of matter
                     <ptr target="#deleuze2006" loc="6"/>. The monad is filled with folds on two
                  levels: the <quote rend="inline">pleats of matter</quote> and the <quote
                     rend="inline">folds in the soul,</quote> which are distinct and still
                  continuously interwoven. This metaphor also refers to the human body and soul,
                  making the distinction important for the understanding of the processes of
                  information interpretation and accumulation: following Deleuze, the monad (or
                  human) already holds all information, twisted into many folds. If it was
                  confronted with a new question or information on the level of the pleats of
                  matter, through the senses, the folds in the soul would automatically begin to
                  twist and turn, after which the resulting answer or links to other information
                  would suddenly become visible. The answer was already there, it was only hidden in
                  the manifold twists of the soul.</p>
               <p>While Deleuze’s treatment of the fold is rather extensive and, in parts, elusive,
                  his description of the unfolding of information offers a useful vocabulary for the
                  conceptualization of (digital) information spaces. The related notion of the monad
                  has already been proposed as a unique perspective on social systems by Bruno
                  Latour and colleagues <ptr target="#latour2012"/>. For them, the monad usefully
                  complicates the distinction between whole and part, a perspective that has been
                  put forward as an iterative mode of making sense of relational information spaces
                     <ptr target="#dork2014"/>. For Deleuze, this complication is concretely
                  manifested in the fold. He proposes a division of the world into the <quote
                     rend="inline">actual</quote> and the <quote rend="inline">virtual,</quote>
                  which are mutually dependent and connected through folds, just as the monad is
                  divided into pleats of matter and soul, but still continuously interwoven.
                  Although Deleuze may not have meant <q>virtual</q> in the sense of <q>digital,</q>
                  the concept of the fold holds a powerful metaphor for the structure and
                  understanding of digital information spaces, in which only certain parts of the
                  available information are perceptible at a time, while the whole information space
                  remains invisibly present. Following Deleuze, the folds of information exist in
                  the virtual world mostly, because they are potentially infinite and offer an
                  unlimited range of capabilities. Still, everything within the monadologic system
                  is connected, although not always ascertainable <ptr target="#freitas2016"/>.
                  Furthermore, the processes of information accumulation and analysis are to some
                  extent characterized by unpredictability, as the reasons for thought processes and
                  actions stay hidden from the monad: <cit><quote rend="block">Because the world is
                        in the monad, each monad includes every series of the states of the world;
                        but, because the monad is for the world, no one clearly contains the
                        ‘reason’ of the series of which they are all a result, and which remains
                        outside of them, just like the principle of their accord.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#deleuze2006" loc="28"/></cit></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Operations of the Fold</head>
               <p>For Deleuze, the three operations <quote rend="inline"
                     >Explication–implication–complication</quote> form the essential triad of the
                  fold <ptr target="#deleuze2006" loc="25"/>. The first two, explication and
                  implication, need to be understood as a pair of which one is reversing the other.
                  Deleuze describes them as processes of envelopment and development, focusing
                  subsequently on the monad as an inflection of the world. To make this process of
                  folding and flexing more vivid, we have abstracted illustrations inspired by
                  Deleuze’s own use of black-and-white drawings in <q>The Fold</q> (see <ref
                     target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). Explication describes the process of
                  unfolding, e.g., opening a book, dividing something into its subsections, or
                  fanning out its multiple facets (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>,
                  left). On the opposite, implication refers to the commonly known process of
                  folding that reduces something in size and detail, e.g., closing an open book or
                  folding a paper. Deleuze draws our attention closely to these processes within
                  monadic systems: If something inside the monad is hidden through the process of
                  implication, what is folded still comprises everything else, though this is not
                  always perceivable with the human senses. Through the process of explication,
                  hidden connections become visible again, but the (un)folded entity nevertheless
                  possesses connections to all others. Unpredictable outcomes and new connections
                  can occur during folding and unfolding, as a fold can generate the sudden
                  juxtaposition of formerly opposite (and also opposing) points.</p>

               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>The operations of the fold illustrated: Explication &amp; implication
                     (left), and complication (right).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               </figure>

               <p>At the intersection of the fold and monadologic theory, Deleuze introduces
                  complication as the third operation of the fold (see <ref target="#figure01"
                     >Figure 1</ref>, right). Here, he draws from medieval philosopher Nicholas of
                  Cusa (1401-1464) to explain the all-embracing function of folds for the mind and
                  the matter. For Cusa, everything that was outside the perceivable was divine
                  simplicity, which he defined as a <quote rend="inline">true folding</quote> of the
                  opposite and contradictory, and named it <quote rend="inline">complicatio</quote>
                  <ptr target="#gandillac1953"/>. In this thought system, whenever something was
                  inexplicable to humans, it was the <q>complicated</q> god that was able to explain
                  things outside of causal connections and rational thought. Deleuze shifts the
                  process of complication from the divine sphere as outside to the inside of human
                  information processing via his theory of the fold. The operation of complication
                  thus explains the process of information accumulation and connectedness of
                  everything perceivable, while also addressing its arbitrariness. Because
                  everything inside the monad is folded to infinity, every possibility already lies
                  inside of it, yet, it cannot expose itself in its entirety at any moment.
                  Surprising occurrences are thus not more than a <q>complicated</q> folding
                  process, in which connections are rearranged and only a part of the connected
                  universe becomes visible at a time.</p>
               <p>The perpetual incompleteness of any knowledge is what makes this theory so
                  relevant for information representation, which aims to communicate complex
                  matters, but needs to make its omissions and reductions transparent. Folding
                  processes can disclose and even simplify ‘complicated’ occurrences: the moment of
                  collapsing an angle from 1 degree to 0 degree, when the eye can visually follow
                  the angle turning into a line, describes this process best. After having observed
                  the transition, the resulting line is not only a line but consists of two layers
                  and could still be seen as an angle; it comprises multiple folds of information
                  that we can only capture if we are able to follow and understand the operation of
                  the fold.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Qualities of the Fold</head>
               <cit><quote rend="inline">... an elastic body still has cohering parts that form a
                     fold, such that they are not separated into parts of parts but are rather
                     divided to infinity in smaller and smaller folds that always retain a certain
                     cohesion.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#deleuze2006" loc="6"/></cit>
               <p>In addition to the concrete operations of the fold, Deleuze’s opus constitutes a
                  unique and global proposition about the form and function of information spaces.
                  To relate the fold theory with visualization practice, we have abstracted three
                  overarching qualities – coherence, elasticity, and infinity – that align the fold
                  with interactive data visualizations in the context of humanistic inquiry.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Coherence </head>
                  <p>Instead of considering information ‘points’ as discrete objects, the fold
                     expresses the coherent quality of monadologic systems that are defined by
                     context and relations. Accordingly, the single data point in a visualization
                     stands for more than one expression, it is part of a system and defined through
                     its connections to other points of the network. As stated by Deleuze in the
                     opening quote of this section, this quality multiplies itself infinitely: No
                     matter how far the information space is passed through, each finding, output,
                     or information point possesses a relation to the beginning of the journey and
                     the whole universe. The quality of coherence thus includes outcomes and object
                     pairings which might seem opposed, since every connection forms an everlasting
                     part of the fold.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Elasticity </head>
                  <p>This quality captures the ongoing change in an information space, the twisting
                     and turning of information and connections, with one impulse following another.
                     With regard to thought processes, elasticity becomes apparent: Thoughts
                     sometimes stretch and flow unconsciously and casually, sometimes quickly and
                     targeted, but they are continuously changing their form and direction. The same
                     principle should be applied to visualization elements: Through their ability to
                     fold, individual elements and entire arrangements can assume multiple possible
                     manifestations, are flexible in their position and appearance, but never lose
                     the first principle of coherence. Elasticity thus describes a material quality
                     that is situated between fluidity and hardness, i.e., neither lacking coherence
                     nor being fully rigid.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Infinity </head>
                  <p>The fold surprises with its infinite possibilities; the outcomes of folding
                     operations appear to be unlimited. Smaller and smaller threads can be unfolded
                     in a visualization, or connections between elements can be found and followed
                     in a multitude of possible combinations. This does not imply that the actions
                     and events in information spaces are not also repeatable or retraceable, but
                     rather that folding operations are never final or completed. The same holds
                     true for the underlying datasets that may never be sufficiently comprehensive
                     to represent an artefact or collection. There are always further data
                     perspectives that could, in theory, be invoked for interpretation. The quality
                     of infinity is especially connected with the operation of complication and
                     reminds us that comprehensive information spaces might seem structured and
                     transparent at first glance, but are highly dependent on the perspective of the
                     viewer and a multitude of data dimensions. Because the fold offers
                     (potentially) infinite possibilities of twisting and turning, folding processes
                     remain unpredictable and serendipitous <ptr target="#leong2011"/>
                     <ptr target="#thudt2012"/>. If we accept the (partly) unpredictable folds of
                     large information spaces by learning to follow their implication, explication,
                     or complication, we can come to a deeper understanding of our own thought
                     processes and actions, and see the connectedness of every single point that
                     came before and comes after.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Fold in Interactive Visualizations</head>
            <p>In the context of information visualization, interactivity has been largely viewed
               through the lens of users tasks and intents <ptr target="#yi2007"/>, distinctly
               separate from the visual representation of data and animated transitions between
               views. In Deleuze’s description of information processing lies an opportunity to
               conceptualize visualizations in a novel framework that rejects the separation between
               interactivity and visual encoding, just as the monad rejects the dualistic
               distinction between body and soul. We aim at highlighting an encompassing practice of
               visualization for the digital humanities, which have to find visual representations
               for their collections and datasets, while on the other hand conceptualizing
               interactivity with tasks as casual exploration or deep analysis in mind. While
               various visualization techniques already refer to <q>folds</q> or <q>folding</q> in
               their project descriptions or prototypes [e.g., <ref target="#bach2016">Bach et al.
                  2016</ref>, <ref target="#dork2014">Dörk et al. 2014</ref>, <ref
                  target="#riehmann2018">Riehmann et al. 2018</ref>, <ref target="#zhao2014">Zhao et
                  al. 2014</ref>], we will demonstrate that current visualization practice actually
               provides a variety of interaction patterns that align with the principles of the fold
               and can serve as an inspiration for digital humanities scholars. Accordingly, with
               this research, we do not present new visualization techniques, but explore a new way
               to conceptualize interactivity in data visualization.</p>
            <p>Designing visualizations along the fold means to understand information spaces as
               elastic, coherent, and potentially infinite systems. Instead of focusing on static
               snapshots of visualizations, which would favor their visual encoding, the fold sheds
               more light on the <q>in-between</q> states of folding processes, emphasizing the
               transitions between visualization states as meaningful views that need to be
               considered throughout the entire design process. In a design study, we have already
               described this process by means of a book collection from the 19th century, focusing
               on a set of functions which enable what we call <quote rend="inline">scalable
                  exploration</quote>
               <ptr target="#bludau2020"/>. With this work, we want to widen the focus of the design
               framework to questions of perception, interpretation, and critique with the help of
               Deleuze’s philosophy. Data and the resulting representations in data visualization
               can be seen as folds, reminding us that any perspective can only represent one
               possible version of reality, while containing infinite other possibilities to
               perceive a phenomenon. This is especially relevant for visualization practices in the
               digital humanities, which aim at implementing inherently humanist research questions
               into their visual interfaces and have spiked discussions on the problem that data are
               never neutral <ptr target="#dignazio2020"/>
               <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>
               <ptr target="#loukissas2016"/>.</p>
            <p>This section presents examples of folding operations in data visualizations through
               abstracted illustrations and will subsequently demonstrate how the fold’s qualities
               can form the basis of a critical framework for their design and analysis. We
               reference existing visualization examples, which have inspired us in the creation of
               the illustrations and encourage readers to visit them to gain a deeper understanding
               of the various mechanisms of the fold.</p>

            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>Examples of explication (top to bottom) and implication (in reverse): a)
                  Exposing nested nodes in a network graph increases the detailed neighborhood of
                  the selected node. b) Stretching a selected area of a streamgraph in order to
                  increase detail leads to compression of the unselected areas. c) Selection of an
                  item in a tree graph unveils additional subbranches by providing new room through
                  compression of the remaining branches.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
            </figure>

            <div>
               <head>Studying Visualizations through Fold Operations</head>
               <p>Arguably, explication and implication as the first two operations of the fold are
                  common mechanisms in data visualizations, implementing the fold in the sense of
                  increasing or decreasing detail, aggregating or separating, clustering or
                  dispersing, etc. In particular, semantic zoom <ptr target="#perlin1993"/> already
                  supports the operations of the fold by allowing different degrees of granularity
                  while preserving the overall context. <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>
                  illustrates explication and implication for three typical visualization
                  techniques:</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item><hi rend="bold">a)</hi> An interactive mechanism common in network
                     visualizations is selecting a node in a graph to trigger an explication, which
                        <q>unfolds</q> into multiple sub-items and thus provides a more granular
                     view on a selection [e.g., <ref target="#morris2018">Morris 2018</ref>].
                     Network graphs like this are popular in the digital humanities, for instance
                     when visualizing relationships between authors as in this visualization of
                     Johann Wolfgang von Goethe’s social network: <ref
                        target="https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/graph?id=sfz53095"
                        >https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/graph?id=sfz53095</ref>
                     <ptr target="#historische2010"/>. On the other side, implication describes the
                     process of reducing a set of items into a collapsed item leading to the
                     reduction of the overall visual complexity.</item>
                  <item><hi rend="bold">b)</hi> The explication in a temporal streamgraph stretches
                     an area of interest to display more detail, while compressing the rest of the
                     visualization, similar to the mechanics of an accordion. Focus+Context like
                     accordion drawing or a fish-eye technique is oftentimes used to provide a
                     detailed view on a specific area of interest within a visualization while
                     preserving its context [e.g., <ref target="#baur2012">Baur et al. 2012</ref>,
                        <ref target="#cuenca2018">Cuenca et al. 2018</ref>, <ref
                        target="#morawa2014">Morawa et al. 2014</ref>, <ref target="#riehmann2018"
                        >Riehmann et al. 2018</ref>, <ref target="#slack2005">Slack et al.
                        2005</ref>]. As one of the main focus of interest, timeline visualizations
                     have been put into practice with this kind of compression technique, as in the
                        <title rend="quotes">Touch the Time</title> project (<ref
                        target="https://www.uni-weimar.de/projekte/vr-scratch/videos/TTT.mp4"
                        >https://www.uni-weimar.de/projekte/vr-scratch/videos/TTT.mp4</ref>) <ptr
                        target="#riehmann2018"/>. </item>
                  <item><hi rend="bold">c)</hi> The visualization of hierarchical data demonstrates
                     a combination of the two previous mechanisms: Through selection of a tree
                     branch, both the number of elements and the level of detail can be increased,
                     while at the same time the branches that are not selected get compressed to
                     provide sufficient space for the newly unfolded subbranches [e.g., <ref
                        target="#slack2005">Slack et al. 2005</ref>]. Relating to humanistic data,
                     one case study is an expandable word tree that enables new ways of text
                     exploration by giving the possibility to move along sequences of words through
                     expansion and reduction of following or preceding words <ptr
                        target="#wattenberg2008"/>. Using such a word tree, it is, for instance,
                     possible to gradually unfold all possible sentences that start with the name
                        <q>Alice</q> in an interactive word tree version of the book <title
                        rend="italic">Alice in Wonderland</title>: <ref
                        target="https://www.jasondavies.com/wordtree/?source=alice-in-wonderland.txt%20"
                        >https://www.jasondavies.com/wordtree/?source=alice-in-wonderland.txt</ref>
                     <ptr target="#davies"/></item>
               </list>

               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Examples of complication: a) Folding of a timeline based on similarity
                     between data points. b) Use of multidimensional reduction techniques in
                     combination with encoded glyphs for gradual addition of more dimensions in
                     two-dimensional displays. c) Switching between egocentric and noncentric total
                     states of a node-link network graph.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>In contrast to explication and implication, which correspond to established
                  interaction techniques, the operation of complication introduces a conceptual
                  approach to high-dimensional data visualization that is relatively seldom
                  considered. Dimensionality reductions and force-directed layouts can be
                  misleading, error-prone, or difficult to grasp, yet, the gradual build-up of a
                  multidimensional visualization can be viewed as a continuous complication (see
                     <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>):</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item><hi rend="bold">a)</hi> A linear timeline arranges events solely on the
                     basis of their temporal succession (top). The gradual inclusion of additional
                     event data constitutes a complication, in that further aspects are introduced
                     that differentiate and relate the items (from middle to bottom): The straight
                     line is folded into a curve that positions similar events closer together,
                     using, for example, multidimensional scaling, as in the Time Curves technique
                        (<ref target="https://aviz.fr/~bbach/timecurves"
                        >https://aviz.fr/~bbach/timecurves</ref>) <ptr target="#bach2016"/>.</item>
                  <item><hi rend="bold">b)</hi> The two-dimensional visualization of a dataset as a
                     scatterplot (top) can be gradually complicated by the introduction of
                     flower-like glyphs encoding multiple dimensions per element [e.g., <ref
                        target="#kammer2018">Kammer et al. 2018</ref>, <ref target="#stefaner2014"
                        >Stefaner et al. 2014</ref>] and by similarity-based positioning. With
                     sliders on the left, each dimension’s influence on the layout can be adjusted
                     [e.g., <ref target="#goldenberg2017">Goldenberg 2017</ref>, <ref
                        target="#stefaner2014">Stefaner et al. 2014</ref>] (middle and bottom). As
                     an example, such a similarity-based visualization of a country map, calculated
                     through the t-SNE algorithm, lets the user choose between the various factors
                     influencing the layout: <ref
                        target="https://projects.interacta.io/country-tsne"
                        >https://projects.interacta.io/country-tsne</ref>
                     <ptr target="#rokotyan2019"/>]. Furthermore, this project offers a great
                     example of disclosing its mechanisms through a narrative layer which leads
                     visitors through the process under the title <title rend="quotes">Understanding
                        the data</title>. </item>
                  <item><hi rend="bold">c)</hi> An egocentric network centered around one node (top)
                     can be a starting point <ptr target="#vanham2009"/> to gradually expand the
                     analysis from a partial to a comprehensive perspective. The complication
                     dissolves the egocentric perspective towards a full view of the network in
                     which the layout is influenced by all nodes and all links become visible
                     (bottom). Similarly, another common approach is the reversed switch from global
                     to egocentric views [e.g., <ref target="#ortiz2013">Ortiz 2013</ref>]. In the
                     project <title rend="quotes">Six degrees of Francis Bacon</title> (<ref
                        target="http://www.sixdegreesoffrancisbacon.com/"
                        >http://www.sixdegreesoffrancisbacon.com</ref>) <ptr target="#warren"/>, it
                     is possible to change the view from a global, forced-directed network graph
                     that is useful to see general patterns and the general network structure, to an
                     egocentric view. Here, the related nodes are arranged on two rings around a
                     selection, based on their degree of separation, making it easier to
                     differentiate between direct and indirect relations.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Contrary to visualization techniques that separate dimensions into multiple
                  coordinated views or enforce an abrupt display change, complication suggests
                  traceable transitions between successive visualization states, which gradually
                  integrate additional data aspects into the same visualization. To think of
                  multidimensional data visualizations as dynamic processes of data complications
                  instead of a static image of reality can help identify the various factors
                  influencing the visual representation and make interactive functions more
                  comprehensible. For instance, a <q>complicated</q> timeline which positions
                  similar data points next to each other, forming a curve while allowing users to
                  follow the process of bending, sparks questions about the linearity of timelines
                  per se and the underlying structure and dimensions of the dataset. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Towards a Critical Framework</head>
               <p>Considering the examples above, the fold’s operations help to identify the
                  interactive mechanisms of a visualization and examine their role in transforming
                  the appearance and arrangement of visual elements. Furthermore, the three
                  operations can be used to spot the lack of interactive capabilities or conceive
                  dynamic behaviors for visualizations being created. Here the fold does not only
                  offer principles for the design of and interactions with visualizations, but also
                  enables us to think about the potential and challenges of humanistic data.
                  Building on Deleuze’s writing and related visualization research [e.g., <ref
                     target="#elmqvist2011">Elmqvist et al. 2011</ref>], we now formulate tentative
                  design principles and questions, thereby following the operations of the fold but
                  especially relating its newly defined qualities to the critical enquiry of data
                  visualizations.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Consistent Coupling</head>
                  <p>The fold’s coherence manifests itself in the deep contextualization and
                     connectedness of all elements. In order to realize this high degree of
                     coherence in interactive visualizations, the visual encoding and interactive
                     features need to be consistently coupled across all views. Coherence means, for
                     example, that one information point stands in relation to every other point
                     within the visualization, and the context of those relations is both visually
                     and interactively represented. For example, in cultural heritage collections,
                     artifacts might be related to each other through many different explicit (e.g.,
                     same author) or implicit (e.g., sharing a subject) relations over a multitude
                     of possible data dimensions (e.g., attributes, visual similarity, temporal
                     sequences). Integration of coherence in visualization is not only dependent on
                     abstract relations but mainly visible in the form of visual cues and linkages
                     that reveal how elements are connected and invite the viewer to follow
                     them.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 1: How are the connections between data elements,
                        visual encodings, and interactive features exposed?</hi></p>
                  <p>Furthermore, the quality of coherence is particularly promoted by consistent
                     design decisions across the entire visualization, regardless of its dynamic
                     state. As a person interacts with the visualization, the coupling of visual
                     representation and interactivity consistently holds. Similarly, the behaviors
                     of interaction techniques function consistently across all views. Visual
                     variables, such as color, shape or position, that are added to encode
                     additional dimensions should not stand in conflict with existing encodings.
                     Humanities scholars conceptualizing visualizations should therefore pay
                     attention to different states of the visualization (e.g., overview – detail),
                     which interactive functions can be used at which states, and watch out for the
                     application of them throughout a visitor’s journey – for instance when applying
                     filters to a dataset and changing to a different zoom position afterwards.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 2: How consistent are visual encodings and
                        interactive techniques across all views, throughout multiple continuous
                        states?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When reducing many points into a single point, elements should not be removed,
                     but be folded while preserving the respective relation to the remaining
                     elements. The implication or explication does not only influence a discrete
                     element but also has an effect on the whole visualization, indicating the
                     overall coherence of the information space. When visual features are reduced or
                     when elements are collapsed, the design of the respective transitions should be
                     meaningful and consistent. Similarly, elements being added should appear from
                     logical positions in the interface.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 3: Do the arrival and departure of elements in the
                        display convey the concept of object permanence?</hi></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Constrained Fluidity</head>
                  <p>A high degree of elasticity means that elements are flexibly embedded into a
                     complex visual appearance and arrangement and that they are able to change
                     their shape and leave their position to appear elsewhere. They are not static
                     and can show themselves anew repeatedly – and, also in unforeseen
                     representations. For example, objects in visualizations of cultural collections
                     can have multiple relations to each other but are often assigned a static
                     position in web-based interfaces. Instead, it could be helpful to include
                     flexible positions and to consider a range of visual representations, moving
                     between abstract shapes to more concrete images of an object. However, the fold
                     is neither erratic nor random. The changes carried out through folding
                     operations should be comprehensible and meaningful.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 4: To which degree are fluidity and rigidness
                        balanced so that the elements and arrangements accommodate all possible
                        values and relations in a dataset?</hi></p>
                  <p>The spectrum of dynamic changes to individual elements and entire arrangements
                     needs to be carefully considered. To do this it is paramount to view visual
                     encodings not as static mappings between data dimensions and visual variables,
                     but as complex sequences modulated by the fold’s operations. Accordingly, like
                     a blooming flower, the additional data dimensions in <ref target="#figure03"
                        >Figure 3</ref> b) are already comprised in the data points and their
                     revelation demonstrates their elasticity. </p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 5: Are the elements and arrangements designed with
                        regard to their dynamic behaviors, i.e., their intermediate states?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Humanistic data is oftentimes shaped by various forms of uncertainty,
                     subjectivity, and ambiguity <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>. Nevertheless, since
                     such data properties are difficult to address in visualizations <ptr
                        target="#hullman2019"/> and might significantly increase complexity, they
                     are oftentimes omitted completely in visualizations. The elasticity of elements
                     might help to reveal such data properties through folding operations on demand
                     for specific elements. Thus it is possible to critically analyze the datasets
                     beforehand, but even more so during the visualization process. It should be
                     tested whether a visualization shows what researchers expected to see from the
                     dataset or whether it can reveal new qualities in the data through new views
                     and interactive functions.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 6: Does the representation of the data through the
                        visualization constrain interpretive qualities of the data, such as
                        uncertainty or ambiguity, that could be dissolved through interactivity and
                        elasticity of the encoding?</hi></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Linked Perspectives</head>
                  <p>The quality of infinity relates to a multitude of possible representations of
                     data, the insights they may evoke, and circular or open-ended navigation
                     mechanisms. Specific combinations of visual form and interactive functionality
                     in a visualization can evoke new, surprising, and inspiring expressions of a
                     dataset and a variety of possibly unexpected insights, surprises, and
                     serendipitous discoveries. The quality of infinity can be observed, for
                     example, in <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> b) through the seemingly
                     infinite combination possibilities within the weightings of the multiple
                     dimensions.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 7: Do all visual elements in the interface afford
                        interactivity to transform the view and generate new insights?</hi></p>
                  <p>An interactive visualization is never complete, but always in progress. If a
                     data visualization could be thought of as a densely connected network of linked
                     perspectives, at any given point in the network of possible visualization
                     states, users ideally should never be led to dead-ends. For instance, unfolding
                     detail in <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref> b) and c) will always lead to
                     an impression of other information while preserving the context and therefore
                     allowing for open-ended interactions without the need to resort to the
                     browser’s back-button.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Question 8: How is the incompleteness of views embraced and
                        endless traversal of the data encouraged?</hi></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>Arguably, a lot of thought during the design process goes into the visual
               representation of a visualization, i.e., the mapping from various data dimensions to
               a limited number of visual variables, whereas interaction techniques and animated
               transitions are oftentimes only an afterthought, sometimes even used as a last fix to
               solve issues of a visual encoding. Similarly, the interpretation of data
               visualizations is almost exclusively focused on the visual representation – the rules
               of turning data qualities into graphical elements – often disregarding the dynamic
               interplay between display parameters and interactive capabilities. With the fold we
               put forward an approach that emphasizes a need for simultaneous and coordinated
               consideration of interaction and representation in data visualization. In the
               process, we identified the connections between visual encoding and interactivity as
               crucial for the implementation of the folding operations and emphasized them in the
               critical framework, arguing for a close consideration of visual appearance and its
               dynamic behavior. </p>
            <p>However, prototyping interfaces may in parts still be restricted by static forms of
               prototyping techniques, a lack of suitable tools, or a massive amount of data.
               Additionally, thinking of representation and interaction in all states of a
               visualization in unison with the intention to achieve meaningful transitions may turn
               out to demand significant conceptual, technical, and intellectual effort. While
               realistically seeing the complexity that the fold brings to visualization practice in
               the digital humanities, we believe that its notion can have a profound effect on the
               way we think about data, and even in its smallest implementation can contribute to
               more profound and purposeful visualizations.</p>
            <p>Proposing the use of the fold and its operations to approach a gap in the development
               of data visualization, we recommend the consideration of the qualities coherence,
               elasticity, and infinity as fruitful starting points for both creation and critique.
               Nevertheless, these qualities only describe an ideal environment for the fold. In
               practice, their degree of implementation might always be partially limited. While we
               have provided a first framework for their implementation in digital humanities
               projects and research, we are aware that the applied methods are highly dependent on
               the actual data and project setting. Furthermore, the interpretation of data
               visualization remains deeply subjective. Especially machine-generated arrangements,
               for instance, based on similarity, might need a high amount of testing and editing,
               or even a narrative layer, to arrive at comprehensible, yet “complicated”
               visualizations in the sense of the fold. Additionally, we would like to see more
               research into the perception and necessities of different user groups in digital
               humanities visualizations.</p>
            <p>Although this research mainly focused on the implementation of the fold through a new
               perspective on the design and interpretation of visualizations, we also see the
               potential of the fold when it comes to their very foundation: data. Thinking of
               Deleuze’s infinite folds, the common approach to data as <q>given</q>
               <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>, implicitly perceived as objective and fixed, could also
               be understood as one folded impression of reality. We believe that the fold offers a
               unique perspective for digital humanities scholars to translate their datasets into
               interactive visualizations along various meaningful views, which can generate new
               insights for their research and help them in conveying it to the public. This
               perspective becomes especially relevant if we take a look at more recent developments
               concerning critical perspectives on the power and rhetoric of data and their
               visualization <ptr target="#dignazio2020"/>
               <ptr target="#dork2013"/>
               <ptr target="#hullman2011"/>. Here, we are specifically calling for a close
               consideration of theoretical concepts and a practical collaboration between data
               visualization research and the digital humanities to rethink the relationship between
               representation and interactivity in data visualization.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>As data visualization continues to expand its relevance in the digital humanities,
               there is a growing need to come to terms with interactivity as one of its most
               fundamental aspects. While the challenges of cultural heritage data and the
               complexity of their implementation into dynamic visualizations has gained critical
               attention, the prospects of interaction techniques to this end are not discussed as
               intensely. With this research, we proposed the notion of the fold as a productive way
               to jointly consider interaction and encoding in data visualization. While generally
               understood as an essential component of data visualization, interactivity is often
               treated in separation from the visual encoding and as a second step in the design
               process, when all decisions about the visual variables have already been made. This
               relegation of interactivity is perpetuated in the critical interpretation of data
               visualization that is similarly focused on the visual encoding and lacks the
               vocabulary to make sense of the provided interactive capabilities. Drawing from
               Deleuze’s writing on the fold, we formulated a critical framework for interactive
               data visualization consisting of operations, qualities, and questions for their
               design and interpretation. In this context, we do not only hope to encourage
               consideration of folding operations for the visualization of data, but especially see
               the importance of understanding information spaces and the data themselves as a
               manifold space. In order to treat interfaces as subject to critique and
               interpretation <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>
               <ptr target="#sengers2006"/>, the lens of the fold provides a useful thinking tool
               for a humanistic approach to data visualization.</p>
            <p>To investigate the viability of the fold for the critical consideration of existing
               visualizations, we abstracted new, explanatory illustrations from various
               visualization examples. It was our aim to examine in which functions the fold was
               already manifested in data visualization practice. During this process, we noticed
               that a considerable number of the visualization techniques exhibited the
               characteristics of the fold, while certain aspects are still underdeveloped and could
               be explored in future research and design. While the pair of implication and
               explication can be seen in numerous visualization examples, we see a necessity and,
               through the notion of the fold, an opportunity for designing visualizations that
               offer insightful complications, more specifically through meaningful transitions.
               This is particularly important when visualizing digital cultural heritage data, where
               multidimensional and multifaceted collections or datasets offer intriguing
               opportunities for the joint design of interactive exploration and visual
               representation. Based on the operations and qualities of the fold, we have formulated
               a critical framework as an invitation to jointly consider the interactive
               capabilities and visual representations of data in visualization techniques in the
               digital humanities. Coherence, elasticity, and infinity are valuable qualities for
               the design of interactive visualizations that can trigger unexpected and surprising
               insights – the raison d’être of data visualization.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix" xml:id="acknowledgements">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>We would like to thank Linda Freyberg, Sascha Freyberg, Rabea Kleymann, Francesca
               Morini, Arran Ridley, Jonas Rogge, and Fidel Thomet for their comments, advice, and
               feedback along the way. Furthermore, many thanks to the reviewers of <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> for their valuable feedback and
               thoughtful suggestions. Special thanks to Bruno Latour for the personal encouragement
               to peruse Deleuze's writing on monads and folds.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bach2016" label="Bach et al. 2016">Bach, Benjamin, Conglei Shi, Nicolas
               Heulot, Tara Madhyastha, Tom Grabowski, and Pierre Dragicevic. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Time Curves: Folding Time to Visualize Patterns of Temporal Evolution in
                  Data</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                  Graphics, </title>vol. 22, no. 1, 2016, pp. 559–68.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baur2012" label="Baur et al. 2012">Baur, Dominikus, Bongshin Lee, and
               Sheelagh Carpendale. <title rend="quotes">TouchWave: Kinetic Multi-touch Manipulation
                  for Hierarchical Stacked Graphs</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  2012 ACM International Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces</title>,
               ACM, 2012, pp. 255–64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bederson2003" label="Bederson and Boltman 2003">Bederson, Benjamin B., and
               Angela Boltman. <title rend="quotes">Does Animation Help Users Build Mental Maps of
                  Spatial Information?</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Craft of Information Visualization: Readings and
                  Reflections, </title>edited by Benjamin B. Bederson and Ben Shneiderman, Morgan
               Kaufmann, 2003, pp. 87–94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bertin1983" label="Bertin 1983">Bertin, Jacques. <title rend="italic"
                  >Semiology of Graphics: Diagrams, Networks, Maps</title>, University of Wisconsin
               Press, 1983.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bludau2020" label="Bludau et al. 2020">Bludau, Mark-Jan, Viktoria
               Brüggemann, Anna Busch, and Marian Dörk. <title rend="quotes">Reading Traces:
                  Scalable Exploration in Elastic Visualizations of Cultural Heritage Data</title>.
               Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 39, no.3, 2020, pp. 77–87. <ref
                  target="https://diglib.eg.org/bitstream/handle/10.1111/cgf13964/v39i3pp077-087.pdf"
                  >https://diglib.eg.org/bitstream/handle/10.1111/cgf13964/v39i3pp077-087.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bredekamp1988" label="Bredekamp 1988">Bredekamp, Horst. <title
                  rend="quotes">Leibniz’ Gewebe: Strumpfband, Falte, Leinwand</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Die Logik der Bilder</title>, edited by Michael Töteberg and Wim
               Wenders, Verl. d. Autoren, 1988, pp. 233–38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="card1999" label="Card et al. 1999">Card, Stuart K., Jock D. Mackinlay, and
               Ben Shneiderman. <title rend="italic">Using Vision to Think</title>, Kaufmann
               Publishers Inc., 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carpendale2003" label="Carpendale 2003">Carpendale, Sheelagh. <title
                  rend="italic">Considering Visual Variables as a Basis for Information
                  Visualisation</title>, Department of Computer science, University of Calgary,
               2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chevalier2014" label="Chevalier et al. 2014">Chevalier, Fanny, Pierre
               Dragicevic, and Steven Franconeri. <title rend="quotes">The Not-so-Staggering Effect
                  of Staggered Animations on Visual Tracking</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 20, no. 12,
               2014, pp. 2241–50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chevalier2016" label="Chevalier et al. 2016">Chevalier, Fanny, Nathalie
               Henry Riche, Catherine Plaisant, Amira Chalbi, and Christophe Hurter. <title
                  rend="quotes">Animations 25 Years Later: New Roles and Opportunities</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Working Conference on
                  Advanced Visual Interfaces</title>. ACM, 2016, pp. 280–87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="colebrook2002" label="Colebrook 2002">Colebrook, Claire. <title
                  rend="italic">Gilles Deleuze</title>, Routledge Critical Thinkers, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="csikszentmihalyi1990" label="Csikszentmihalyi 1990">Csikszentmihalyi,
               Mihaly. <title rend="italic">Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience</title>,
               HarperPerennial, 1990.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cuenca2018" label="Cuenca et al. 2018">Cuenca, Erick, Arnaud Sallaberry,
               Florence Y. Wang, and Pascal Poncelet. <title rend="quotes">Multistream: A
                  Multiresolution Streamgraph Approach to Explore Hierarchical Time Series</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer
                  Graphics</title>, vol. 24, no. 12, 2018, pp. 3160–3173.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="davies" label="Davies n.d.">Davies, Jason. <title rend="quotes">Word
                  Tree</title>, [online], n.d. Accessed 12 Jun. 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.jasondavies.com/wordtree/"
                  >https://www.jasondavies.com/wordtree/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dignazio2016" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2016">D’Ignazio, Catherine, and
               Lauren F. Klein. <title rend="quotes">Feminist Data Visualization</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">VIS4DH: Workshop on Visualization for the Digital
               Humanities</title>, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dignazio2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020">D’Ignazio, Catherine, and
               Lauren F. Klein. <title rend="italic">Data Feminism</title>, MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deleuze2006" label="Deleuze 2006">Deleuze, Gilles. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Fold: Leibniz and the Baroque</title>, translated by Tom Conley, Continuum,
               2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="historische2010"
               label="Historische Kommission and Bayerische Staatsbibliothek 2010">Historische
               Kommission and Bayerische Staatsbibliothek. <title rend="quotes">Deutsche
                  Biographie</title>, [online], 2010, accessed 22 May 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/"
                  >https://www.deutsche-biographie.de</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dork2011" label="Dörk et al. 2011">Dörk, Marian, Sheelagh Carpendale, and
               Carey Williamson. <title rend="quotes">The Information Flaneur: A Fresh Look at
                  Information Seeking</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the SIGCHI
                  Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>. ACM, 2011, pp.
               1215–24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dork2013" label="Dörk et al. 2013">Dörk, Marian, Patrick Feng, Christopher
               Collins, and Sheelagh Carpendale. <title rend="quotes">Critical InfoVis: Exploring
                  the Politics of Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">alt.chi 2013: Extended
                  Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>.
               ACM, 2013, pp. 2189–98.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dork2014" label="Dörk et al. 2014">Dörk, Marian, Rob Comber, and Martyn
               Dade-Robertson. <title rend="quotes">Monadic Exploration: Seeing the Whole Through
                  Its Parts</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM
                  Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>. ACM, 2014, pp.
               1535–44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</title>. Digital Humanities Quarterly,
               vol. 5, no. 1, 2011. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Performative Materiality and Theoretical Approaches to Interface</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, vol. 7, no. 1, 2013. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000143/000143.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000143/000143.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elmqvist2011" label="Elmqvist et al. 2011">Elmqvist, Niklas, Andrew Vande
               Moere, Hans-Christian Jetter, Daniel Cernea, Harald Reiterer, and T. J. Jankun-Kelly.
                  <title rend="quotes">Fluid Interaction for Information Visualization</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Information Visualization</title>, vol. 10, no. 4, 2011, pp.
               327–40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freitas2016" label="Freitas 2016">Freitas, Elizabeth de. <title
                  rend="quotes">The New Empiricism of the Fractal Fold</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Cultural Studies ↔ Critical Methodologies</title>, vol. 16, no. 2, 2016, pp.
               224–34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gandillac1953" label="Gandillac 1953">Gandillac, Maurice de. <title
                  rend="italic">Nikolaus von Cues: Studien zu seiner Philosophie und philosophischen
                  Weltanschauung</title>, Schwann, 1953.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gleicher2018" label="Gleicher 2018">Gleicher, Michael. <title
                  rend="quotes">Considerations for Visualizing Comparison</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>,
               vol. 24, no. 1, 2018, pp. 413–23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goldenberg2017" label="Goldenberg 2017">Goldenberg, Russell. <title
                  rend="quotes">Craft Beer – So Hot Right now. But what City is the Microbrew
                  Capital of the US?</title>, [online], 2017, accessed 10 Jun. 2020. <ref
                  target="https://pudding.cool/2017/04/beer/"
                  >https://pudding.cool/2017/04/beer/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heer2007" label="Heer and Robertson 2007">Heer, Jeffrey, and George G.
               Robertson. <title rend="quotes">Animated Transitions in Statistical Data
                  Graphics</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and
                  Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 13, no. 6, 2007, pp. 1240–47.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hepworth2018" label="Hepworth and Church 2018">Hepworth, Katherine, and
               Christopher Church. <title rend="quotes">Racism in the Machine: Visualization Ethics
                  in Digital Humanities Projects</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, vol. 12, no. 4, 2018. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hullman2011" label="Hullman and Diakopoulos 2011">Hullman, Jessica, and
               Nick Diakopoulos. <title rend="quotes">Visualization Rhetoric: Framing Effects in
                  Narrative Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on
                  Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 17, no. 12, 2011, pp.
               2231–40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hullman2019" label="Hullman 2019">Hullman, Jessica. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Why Authors Don't Visualize Uncertainty</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 26, no. 1, 2019,
               pp.133–39.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kammer2018" label="Kammer et al. 2018">Kammer, Dietrich, Mandy Keck,
               Thomas Gründer, and Rainer Groh. <title rend="quotes">Big Data Landscapes: Improving
                  the Visualization of Machine Learning-based Clustering Algorithms</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2018 International Conference on Advanced Visual
                  Interfaces</title>. ACM, 2018, p. 66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kreiseler2017" label="Kreiseler et al. 2017">Kreiseler, Sarah, Viktoria
               Brüggemann, and Marian Dörk. <title rend="quotes">Tracing Exploratory Modes in
                  Digital Collections of Museum Web Sites Using Reverse Information
                  Architecture</title>. First Monday, vol. 22, no. 4, 2017. <ref
                  target="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/6984/6090"
                  >https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/6984/6090</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="laerke2010" label="Laerke 2010">Laerke, Mogens. <title rend="quotes">Four
                  Things Deleuze Learned from Leibniz</title>. <title rend="italic">Deleuze and the
                  Fold</title>, edited by Sjoerd van Tuinen and Niamh McDonnell, Palgrave Macmillan,
               2010, pp. 25–45.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour2012" label="Latour et al. 2012">Latour, Bruno, Pablo Jensen,
               Tommaso Venturini, Sébastian Grauwin, and Dominique Bouiller. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Whole is Always Smaller than its Parts ‐ a Digital Test of Gabriel Tardes'
                  Monads</title>. <title rend="italic">British Journal of Sociology</title>, vol.
               63, no. 4, 2012, pp. 590–615.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leibniz1898" label="Leibniz 1898">Leibniz, Gottfried. <title rend="italic"
                  >Monadology</title>, translated by Robert Latta, Clarendon Press, 1898.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leong2011" label="Leong et al. 2011">Leong, Tuck Wah, Richard Harper, and
               Tim Regan. <title rend="quotes">Nudging towards Serendipity: A Case with Personal
                  Digital Photos</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 25th BCS
                  Conference on Human-Computer Interaction</title>. British Computer Society, 2011,
               pp. 385–94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loukissas2016" label="Loukissas 2016">Loukissas, Yanni Alexander. <title
                  rend="quotes">Taking Big Data apart: Local Readings of Composite Media
                  Collections</title>. <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp;
                  Society,</title> vol. 20, no. 5, 2016, pp. 651–664.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="morawa2014" label="Morawa et al. 2014">Morawa, Robert, Tom Horak, Ulrike
               Kister, Annett Mitschick, and Raimund Dachselt. <title rend="quotes">Combining
                  Timeline and Graph Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  Ninth ACM International Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces</title>,
               ACM, 2014, pp. 345–50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="morris2018" label="Morris 2018">Morris, Jeff. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Introducing Neo4j Bloom: Graph Data Visualization for Everyone</title>, [online],
               2018, accessed 12 Jun. 2020. <ref
                  target="https://neo4j.com/blog/introducing-neo4j-bloom-graph-data-visualization-for-everyone/"
                  >https://neo4j.com/blog/introducing-neo4j-bloom-graph-data-visualization-for-everyone/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ortiz2013" label="Ortiz 2013">Ortiz, Santiago. <title rend="quotes">Newk -
                  Twitter Conversations</title>, [online], 2013, accessed 22 May 2020. <ref
                  target="http://moebio.com/newk/twitter">http://moebio.com/newk/twitter</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pace2004" label="Pace 2004">Pace, Steven. <title rend="quotes">A Grounded
                  Theory of the Flow Experiences of Web Users</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title>, vol. 60, no. 3, 2004,
               pp. 327–63. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parry2019" label="Parry 2019">Parry, Kyle. <title rend="quotes">Reading
                  for Enactment: A Performative Approach to Digital Scholarship and Data
                  Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                  Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein, University of
               Minnesota Press, 2019. <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/bd5a43c1-bbfe-4c5c-8c0d-c3db1776eb99#ch13"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/bd5a43c1-bbfe-4c5c-8c0d-c3db1776eb99#ch13</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perlin1993" label="Perlin and Fox 1993">Perlin, Ken, and David Fox. <title
                  rend="quotes">Pad: An Alternative Approach to the Computer Interface</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">SIGGRAPH '93: Proceedings of the 20th annual conference on
                  Computer graphics and interactive techniques</title>. ACM, 1993, pp. 57–64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="riehmann2018" label="Riehmann et al. 2018">Riehmann, Patrick, Joshua
               Reibert, Jens Opolka, and Bernd Froehlich. <title rend="quotes">Touch the Time:
                  Touch-Centered Interaction Paradigms for Time-Oriented Data</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">EuroVis 2018 - Short Papers</title>, edited by Jimmy Johansson et
               al., The Eurographics Association, 2018, pp. 113–17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, Roopika. <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                  the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, vol. 9, no. 2, 2015. <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rokotyan2019" label="Rokotyan et al. 2019">Rokotyan, Nikita, Olya Stukova,
               and Dasha Kolmakova. <title rend="quotes">An Alternative Data-Driven Country
                  Map</title>, [online], 2019, accessed 22 May 2020. <ref
                  target="https://projects.interacta.io/country-tsne"
                  >https://projects.interacta.io/country-tsne</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sacha2017" label="Sacha et al. 2017">Sacha, Dominik, Leishi Zhang, Michael
               Sedlmair, John A. Lee, Jaakko Peltonen, Daniel Weiskopf, Stephen C. North, and Daniel
               A. Keim. <title rend="quotes">Visual Interaction with Dimensionality Reduction: A
                  Structured Literature Analysis</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on
                  Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 23, no. 1, 2017, pp.
               241–50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sengers2006" label="Sengers and Gaver 2006">Sengers, Phoebe, and Bill
               Gaver. <title rend="quotes">Staying Open to Interpretation: Engaging Multiple
                  Meanings in Design and Evaluation</title>. <title rend="italic">DIS '06:
                  Proceedings of the Conference on Designing Interactive Systems</title>. ACM, 2006,
               pp. 99–108.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shneiderman1983" label="Shneiderman 1983">Shneiderman, Ben. <title
                  rend="quotes">Direct Manipulation. A Step Beyond Programming Languages</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>, vol. 16, no. 8, 1983,
               pp. 57–69.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shneiderman1996" label="Shneiderman 1996">Shneiderman, Ben. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information
                  Visualizations</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings / IEEE Symposium on
                  Visual Languages, Sep. 3 - 6, 1996, Boulder, Colorado</title>. IEEE Computer
               Society Press, 1996, pp. 336–43.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="slack2005" label="Slack et al. 2005">Slack, James, Kristian Hildebrand,
               and Tamara Munzner. <title rend="quotes">PRISAD: A Partitioned Rendering
                  Infrastructure for Scalable Accordion Drawing</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Symposium on Information Visualization</title>, 2005, pp. 41–48.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stahnke2016" label="Stahnke et al. 2016">Stahnke, Julian, Marian Dörk,
               Boris Müller, and Andreas Thom. <title rend="quotes">Probing Projections: Interaction
                  Techniques for Interpreting Arrangements and Errors of Dimensionality
                  Reductions</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and
                  Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 22, no. 1, 2016, pp. 629–38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stefaner2014" label="Stefaner et al. 2014">Stefaner, Moritz, Frank Rausch,
               Jonas Leist, Marcus Paeschke, Dominikus Baur, Timm Kekeritz. <title rend="quotes"
                  >OECDBetterLifeIndex.org</title>, [online], 2014, accessed 12 Jun. 2020. <ref
                  target="http://www.oecdbetterlifeindex.org/"
                  >http://www.oecdbetterlifeindex.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thudt2012" label="Thudt et al. 2012">Thudt, Alice, Uta Hinrichs, and
               Sheelagh Carpendale. <title rend="quotes">The Bohemian Bookshelf</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing
                  Systems</title>, edited by Joseph A. Konstan. ACM, 2012, p. 1461.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tversky2002" label="Tversky et al. 2002">Tversky, Barbara, Julie B.
               Morrison, and Mireille Betrancourt. <title rend="quotes">Animation: Can it
                  Facilitate?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Human Computer Studies</title>, vol. 57, no. 4, 2002, pp.
               247–62.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanham2009" label="van Ham and Perer 2009">van Ham, Frank, and Adam Perer.
                  <title rend="quotes"><q>Search, Show Context, Expand on Demand</q>: Supporting
                  Large Graph Exploration with Degree-of-Interest</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 15, no. 6, 2009,
               pp. 953–60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wagner1995" label="Wagner 1995">Wagner, Thomas. <title rend="quotes">Die
                  Falten des Geistes: Barock werden mit Gilles Deleuze</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</title>, vol. 1995, Nr. 283, 5 Dec. 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="warren" label="Warren et al. n.d.">Warren, Christopher, Daniel Shore,
               Jessica Otis, Scott Weingart, and John Ladd. <title rend="quotes">Six Degrees of
                  Francis Bacon</title>, [online], n.d, accessed 22 May 2020. <ref
                  target="http://www.sixdegreesoffrancisbacon.com/"
                  >http://www.sixdegreesoffrancisbacon.com</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wattenberg2008" label="Wattenberg and Viégas 2008">Wattenberg, Martin, and
               Fernanda Viégas. <title rend="quotes">The Word Tree, an Interactive Visual
                  Concordance</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and
                  Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 14, no. 6, 2008, pp. 1221–1228.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wattenberg2016" label="Wattenberg et al. 2016">Wattenberg, Martin,
               Fernanda Viégas, and Ian Johnson. <title rend="quotes">How to Use t-SNE
                  Effectively</title>. Distill, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://distill.pub/2016/misread-tsne/"
                  >https://distill.pub/2016/misread-tsne/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitelaw2015" label="Whitelaw 2015">Whitelaw, Mitchell. <title
                  rend="quotes">Generous Interfaces for Digital Cultural Collections</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, vol. 9, no. 1, 2015. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/1/000205/000205.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="windhager2018" label="Windhager et al. 2018">Windhager, Florian, Paolo
               Federico, Günther Schreder, Katrin Glinka, Marian Dörk, Silvia Miksch, and Eva Mayr.
                  <title rend="quotes">Visualization of Cultural Heritage Collection Data: State of
                  the Art and Future Challenges</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on
                  Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, 2018, pp. 2311–2330.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="windhager2019" label="Windhager et al. 2019">Windhager, Florian, Saminu
               Salisu, Günther Schreder, and Eva Mayr. <title rend="quotes">Uncertainty of What and
                  for Whom - And Does Anyone Care? Propositions for Cultural Collection
                  Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">4th IEEE Workshop on Visualization for
                  the Digital Humanities (VIS4DH)</title>, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="woods1984" label="Woods 1984">Woods, Daniel D. <title rend="quotes">Visual
                  Momentum: A Concept to Improve the Cognitive Coupling of Person and
                  Computer</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of Man-Machine
                  Studies</title>, vol. 21, no. 3, 1984, pp. 229–44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="yi2007" label="Yi et al. 2007">Yi, Ji Soo, Youn ah Kang, John T. Stasko,
               and Julie A. Jacko. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Deeper Understanding of the Role of
                  Interaction in Information Visualization</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, vol. 13, no. 6, pp.
               1224–1231.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhao2014" label="Zhao et al. 2014">Zhao, Jian, Nan Cao, Zhen Wen, Yale
               Song, Yu-ru Lin, and Christopher Collins. <title rend="quotes">#FluxFlow: Visual
                  Analysis of Anomalous Information Spreading on Social Media</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>,
               vol. 20, no. 12, 2014, pp. 1773–82.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
